<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SLO Error Budget Policy Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules so the error-budget policy is a usable decision artefact, not a doc nobody reads.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The policy MUST define exactly four budget states — healthy (≥50% remaining), yellow (50%→25%), red (25%→0%), exhausted (≤0%) — and assign one concrete action per state.</statement>
      <rationale>The artefact mapping budget state to action (ship / freeze / focus) is missing in current corpus. A four-state ladder is the empirically-converged form (Google SRE, Microsoft, Atlassian) and removes the most common failure: teams paralysed at 12% remaining because no one wrote down what 12% means.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[| State    | Budget remaining | Action |
|----------|------------------|--------|
| Healthy  | ≥ 50%            | Ship freely, normal cadence |
| Yellow   | 50% → 25%        | Reduce risky changes, prioritise reliability tickets |
| Red      | 25% → 0%         | Release freeze (only customer-facing fixes + reliability) |
| Exhausted| ≤ 0%             | Escalate to <named-leader>, post-mortem within 5 days |]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The policy MUST be signed (name + date) by a product representative AND an engineering representative; un-signed policies are treated as drafts and cannot trigger freezes.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams keep re-litigating freeze vs ship because the policy was written by SRE alone and product never agreed. The dual signature converts the policy into a binding pre-commit, which is the whole reason it works.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every state MUST name a single decision-maker (handle) authorised to invoke or override the action; "the team decides" is forbidden as decision-maker.</statement>
      <rationale>Plural decision-making at 02:00 → no decision. Naming one human per state means there is always someone to call when the budget is at 24% and a hotfix is queued.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The freeze / yellow states MUST have an explicit exit criterion (e.g. "freeze ends when budget ≥ 30% for 7 consecutive days"); "freeze until next sprint" or undefined exits are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Freezes without exit criteria either lift too early (budget re-burns immediately) or persist past usefulness (delivery resentment). A measurable exit aligns engineering and product on a shared signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The policy MUST be reviewed every quarter and re-signed; policies with last_reviewed &gt;120 days are flagged stale and lose binding authority until reviewed.</statement>
      <rationale>The policy is decision-grade only as long as the signers still agree. Quarterly review catches the case where the product strategy changed (e.g. trading reliability for speed-to-market) but the policy did not.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
