<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Parking Lot Protocol — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that keep the parking lot from collapsing into either silent acceptance or live confrontation.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-verbatim-capture" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every client ask raised during the session is captured verbatim (or as close as possible) into the parking-lot canvas. Paraphrasing in the moment is forbidden because it distorts the ask.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK requirements elicitation; field experience with mis-paraphrasing">A paraphrase is a judgement; the client sees it and feels the BA already decided. Verbatim capture preserves the ask exactly as the requester intended it; clarification happens post-meeting where the BA has time to think.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-visible-canvas" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The parking-lot canvas is visible to the client throughout the meeting (shared screen, physical flipchart, Miro frame). Hidden capture (BA's private notes) is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian Team Playbook; meeting-facilitation literature">Visibility signals respect. The client sees the ask is captured and will not be lost; the BA gets implicit permission to move on without litigating it. A hidden lot creates the same trust failure as no lot.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-no-live-judgement" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The BA MUST NOT classify a parking-lot item as in-scope, change, or creep during the session. The only allowed in-meeting response is: "Captured. We will triage and respond within 48 hours."</statement>
      <rationale source="customer-relationship management; cognitive load of live judgement">Live judgement triggers debate. Even an accurate "that is out of scope" answer in the moment costs more goodwill than it saves. The 48h promise buys the BA thinking time AND keeps the demo on track.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-24h-triage-sla" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every parking-lot item is triaged within 24h of the meeting via the scope-change-vs-scope-creep-detection classifier (or manual equivalent). Items older than 24h trigger an alert to the PM.</statement>
      <rationale source="ITIL incident SLA; field experience with stale parking lots">A stale parking lot becomes the requester's grievance file. Each ageing item is a small trust withdrawal. The 24h SLA is the difference between "they took us seriously" and "they ignored us".</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-48h-response-sla" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each parking-lot item receives a per-item written response to the requester within 48h. Bulk "thanks for your feedback" responses are forbidden; the response cites the triage verdict and the next step.</statement>
      <rationale source="customer-experience research; B2B-services standard">A single bulk response treats the asks as interchangeable; the requester sees that and stops raising asks. Per-item responses signal each ask was considered individually, even when the verdict is "out of scope".</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="In-meeting capture and post-meeting response">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
DEMO 2026-05-14 — parking-lot row added during minute 23:
  Quote: "Could we also export to Excel from the report screen?"
  Requester: Maria, Head of Finance
  Context: shown during the report-drilldown demo
  BA response in meeting: "Captured. We will triage and respond by Thursday EOD."

POST-MEETING (within 24h):
  Triage verdict: legitimate_change (export-to-Excel not in baseline; standard ask)
  Routing: change-control board, low-impact estimate attached.

WITHIN 48H:
  Email to Maria: "Hi Maria, thank you for raising the Excel-export ask in
  Tuesday's demo. We have classified it as a legitimate change-request and
  filed it with the change-control board with a 4-hour effort estimate. You
  will hear back from the sponsor by next Tuesday's steering call. Best, Anna."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 (verbatim quote), r2 (captured visibly), r3 (no live verdict), r4 (24h triage), r5 (per-item written response).</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="The "we will note that" trap">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Demo. Client asks: "Can we add Excel export?"
BA: "We'll note that, thanks."
[BA writes nothing visible; nothing in CRM.]
Three weeks later, client: "Why hasn't anyone come back about Excel?"
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1, r2, r4, r5 all violated. The ask was absorbed but the trust was burnt.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
