<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Nomad Low-Energy Mode Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every nomad-mode trip must follow. These rules exist to prevent the two top failure modes: shipping broken work from a cafe wifi and burning out by pretending the normal cadence still applies.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-declare-mode-before-departure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post a one-page Trip Mode Declaration to the team channel before flight departure. It states: start date, end date, expected timezone(s), response-window widened to 24-48h, list of paused ops (deploys, payments-changes, customer-call hours), and a single emergency contact channel.</statement>
      <rationale source="async-team operating norms; observed nomad-burnout interviews">An undeclared mode means partners, customers, and collaborators continue to expect the normal cadence. The declaration is the load-bearing artifact: it sets expectations and gives the founder permission to defer work without guilt. Founders who skip this step almost always end up working harder on trips than at home.</rationale>
      <example type="good" title="Trip mode declaration">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Trip Mode: 2026-06-03 → 2026-06-17 (Lisbon → Faro → Madeira)

Timezone: UTC+1 (no shift)
Response window: 24-48h, async only
Paused: production deploys, Stripe price changes, customer onboarding calls
Pre-existing customer SLA: maintained (emergency channel: signal +1-555-...)
Daily window: 2h focused, 14:00-16:00 local
Back to normal: 2026-06-18
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-two-hour-window-max" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Daily productive window is 2 hours per day, with a strict ceiling of 4 hours on any single day. Work outside this window is recovery, exploration, or sightseeing — never deferred work that should have been in the window.</statement>
      <rationale source="cognitive-load research; energy management for ultra-low-overhead schedules">Founders consistently overestimate their available focus capacity in unfamiliar environments. A 2-hour window per day produces more usable output across a 2-week trip than ad-hoc 30-minute bursts spread over 10 hours — the latter actively prevents recovery, which is the trip's ostensible purpose.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-deferred-deploy-queue-no-prod-pushes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production deploys, database migrations, and any change requiring 30-minute-or-longer rollback window are deferred to post-trip. All commits to main during nomad mode are tagged with the `defer-deploy` label and queued; staging deploys are permitted, production deploys are blocked at the CI gate by a nomad-mode flag.</statement>
      <rationale source="incident postmortems where rollback was attempted on hotel wifi or 4G">A failed deploy that needs an emergency rollback on a 4G connection has dramatically higher MTTR than on a fixed line. The cost of a 1-week deferral is small; the cost of a 4-hour outage initiated by a cafe-wifi deploy can be revenue-shaped.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-async-only-comms" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No real-time meetings, no video calls, no live customer calls during nomad mode. All comms are written, with explicit "I will reply within 24-48h" framing. Exception: a single 30-minute weekly check-in window per multi-person team if the team explicitly requested it before departure.</statement>
      <rationale source="async-first team operating manuals (Doist, GitLab, Buffer)">Synchronous comms break the 2-hour window rule by forcing the founder to be available outside it. They also expose the founder to high-cost meeting-attendance failures (timezone mistakes, hotel-wifi crashes). Async by default protects both the founder's recovery and the customer's expectations.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-daily-recharge-buffer" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mark at least one calendar day in every 5 as a hard zero-work day. The founder confirms this day in the Trip Mode Declaration. Zero-work means no laptop, no email peeking, no "just one thing" — full disconnect.</statement>
      <rationale source="recovery-cycle research; nomad-burnout case studies">Without forced recovery days, founders default to ambient low-grade work across the whole trip, which produces neither real recovery nor real output. The pre-committed zero-day prevents the slide.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Exiting the mode">
    <list>
      <item>Post end-of-trip update to team channel with: deferred items still pending, deploy queue to clear in week 1, customer threads to triage</item>
      <item>Hold the deferred-deploy queue to a one-by-one rollout in week 1; do NOT batch-deploy on day 1</item>
      <item>Schedule a half-day catch-up block within 72h of return to clear async backlog</item>
      <item>Update the methodology with one lesson learned for the next trip</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
