<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Nomad Mode Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six failure modes that recur across nomad-mode trips. Each has a detector and a repair the founder applies in the moment.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="high">
      <description>Cafe-wifi production deploy — the founder pushes a "small fix" from a cafe, the deploy fails midway, rollback requires a stable connection that the cafe does not provide, outage lasts hours.</description>
      <detector>deploy initiated AND uplink_bandwidth_kbps &lt; 2000 OR network_type in (cafe-wifi, mobile-hotspot, hotel-wifi)</detector>
      <repair>CI gate blocks deploys when the founder's connection is flagged nomad-mode. Override requires a typed override-token. Even with override, the founder is required to confirm a known-stable connection AND a rollback path that does not require sustained bandwidth.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="high">
      <description>Timezone-overlap meeting mistake — the founder accepts a "quick call" from a partner who is in a different timezone, leading to an early-morning or late-night call that wrecks the day's recovery.</description>
      <detector>calendar event accepted AND event_local_time falls outside 10:00-18:00 local AND mode = nomad</detector>
      <repair>Calendar tool blocks event-accept outside the declared window. Override requires an explicit reason in the calendar invite. Founder posts a deferred-call list in the trip channel; partners learn to expect it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="high">
      <description>Payment-related auth flow triggered at the wrong hour — Stripe price change, banking 2FA, or domain renewal initiated during the trip ends up timing out because the founder is asleep when the SMS arrives.</description>
      <detector>Stripe / banking / registrar action queued AND completion-window crosses founder's sleep hours in the trip timezone</detector>
      <repair>Pre-trip checklist forces founder to schedule no payment-related auth flows during the trip. If unavoidable, schedule them in the declared daily window with at least 4h buffer before sleep.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>"Just one thing" creep — founder opens laptop on a declared zero-work day to "check just one thing", which becomes 2 hours of work and defeats the recovery purpose of the day.</description>
      <detector>laptop usage logged on a zero_work_day AND duration &gt; 15 minutes</detector>
      <repair>Founder pre-commits to laptop-physical-distance on zero-work days (locked in hotel safe, left in the car). Self-honour-system based; the detector is a self-check the founder runs the next morning to capture the slip and recalibrate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Async backlog explosion — founder ignores the inbox for 5 days, returns to 200 unread threads, spends week-1 of post-trip clearing them instead of shipping.</description>
      <detector>post_trip.async_backlog_thread_count &gt; 100 OR week-1 post-trip ship count is zero</detector>
      <repair>Founder runs a daily 15-minute triage pass within the 2h window: archive notifications, flag the 5 most important threads for the post-trip block, set auto-responders on all other channels. Backlog stays bounded.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="low">
      <description>Hardware single point of failure — only one device, no backup, no offline-recovery plan if the laptop is stolen or breaks.</description>
      <detector>founder has no backup device on the trip AND repo clone is not present on a secondary device (phone, tablet with git client, cloud workspace)</detector>
      <repair>Pre-departure checklist requires (a) a cloud-recovery workspace ready (Codespaces, Gitpod, or equivalent) AND (b) 2FA backup codes printed AND stored separately AND (c) hardware-loss recovery plan documented (where to buy a replacement laptop in the destination city).</repair>
    </failure-mode>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>
      Customer or partner messages that include urgent framing ("can you just deploy this today, it is critical") must be evaluated against the Trip Mode Declaration. The declaration is the contract. Founder may override for genuine emergencies but the override is logged and treated as an exception, not a precedent.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>
      Post-trip review (week 2 of return): founder reads back through the daily logs, identifies one rule that was hardest to keep, updates the methodology for the next trip. Trips are the data; the methodology is the artifact that compounds.
    </p>
  </section>
</text>
