<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-writing-rules" title="Condensed Spec Writing Rules">
  <summary>Concrete rules for writing FR language, traceability, AC format, and Out of Scope in a condensed spec; antipatterns that indicate the feature has outgrown the condensed format.</summary>

  <section title="FR Language Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every Functional Requirement must use "System SHALL [specific, testable action]" language. Exclude ambiguous verbs: support, handle, manage, validate (when the validation rule is not specified).</statement>
      <rationale>Ambiguous FRs produce ambiguous ACs. "System SHALL validate email" is testable only if the validation rule is stated — "System SHALL validate email format (RFC 5322)" is testable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[System SHALL allow registration with email + password]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[The system shall provide users with the ability to create a new account using their email address and a secure password that meets our security requirements]]></code>
      <note>Verbose, ambiguous "security requirements". Rewrite as a short SHALL statement with explicit criteria.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Traceability Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every FR must trace to exactly one User Story. Every AC must validate at least one FR. Orphaned FRs and orphaned ACs are quality gate failures.</statement>
      <rationale>Traceability lets the executor agent verify coverage mechanically: every Must-priority FR has an AC that passes, therefore the feature satisfies its user stories.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Condense spec traceability to the FR table (Traces To column) and the US Acceptance Criteria field. No separate traceability matrix needed at condensed scale.</statement>
      <rationale>A separate matrix adds overhead that the condensed format is designed to avoid. The table columns carry sufficient traceability for 3-5 FRs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="AC Format Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>All ACs must use Given-When-Then format with specific values (not "valid email" but "test@example.com"). A condensed spec needs exactly one happy path AC and one error case AC.</statement>
      <rationale>ACs without specific values cannot be mechanically verified. "User enters valid email" passes any input; "User enters test@example.com" passes only the correct input.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>AC items that read as requirements: "User can register with email and password."</description>
      <reason>Not a scenario — has no Given, When, Then. Cannot be verified as pass or fail. Rewrite as a Given-When-Then scenario.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Scale Escape Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>If the agent produces more than 3 User Stories or more than 6 Functional Requirements, the feature is not "basic". Escalate to full spec-structure v2.0.</statement>
      <rationale>A condensed spec with 8 FRs is not condensed — it is a full spec with missing sections. The missing sections (NFRs, detailed personas, Open Questions) will cause problems in later phases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents adding "Technical Notes" or "Architecture" sections to a condensed spec.</description>
      <reason>These belong in design.md. The spec answers WHAT and WHY only. Reject these sections at review.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Omitting the Out of Scope section entirely.</description>
      <reason>Without explicit scope boundaries, any omitted feature becomes an implicit requirement. Out of Scope prevents implementation debates.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
