<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<decisions>
  <decision date="2026-05-02" topic="phase-0-always-first">
    <chose>Phase 0 (session review) runs on every invocation, before any optional extension phase, even when the user only asked for a commit or a skill.</chose>
    <rejected>Make Phase 0 optional and gate it on user phrasing like every other phase.</rejected>
    <rationale>Session capture is the cheapest, highest-ROI step in the workflow — re-reading the current conversation costs nothing beyond what the orchestrator already has in context, and the resulting append-only entries compound across sessions. Making it optional means most invocations skip it and the project-local `.aidocs/memory/` files atrophy. The cost of running Phase 0 unconditionally is bounded; the cost of skipping it is unbounded knowledge loss at compaction.</rationale>
  </decision>

  <decision date="2026-05-02" topic="mandatory-user-approval">
    <chose>Phase 3.5 is a hard prerequisite for every Phase 4 apply path, including CRITICAL-priority findings and the "fix the issues" shortcut.</chose>
    <rejected>Allow CRITICAL findings to bypass Phase 3.5 because their priority already implies urgency.</rejected>
    <rationale>The user is the security boundary; the orchestrator is not. CRITICAL describes the impact of inaction, not the consent state for action. Past runs that auto-applied CRITICAL findings caused unintended config rollback and unrequested service restarts. Folding consent into priority confuses two orthogonal axes. The blanket rule "no Phase 4 without Phase 3.5" is enforceable, auditable, and matches the project's broader "never push without confirmation" posture.</rationale>
  </decision>

  <decision date="2026-05-02" topic="system-vs-project-scope-split">
    <chose>Phase 2 routes findings into two scopes — System (config edits, applied directly via Phase 4) and Project (code or architecture changes, routed through Phase 4b SDD planning).</chose>
    <rejected>Single Phase 4 path for all findings, with code changes applied inline like config edits.</rejected>
    <rationale>System and Project changes have different risk profiles, review needs, and reversibility. Config edits are localized, easy to revert, and benefit from same-session apply. Code changes need spec, design, and test plan before implementation — applying them inline bypasses SDD and creates undocumented architectural drift. Splitting at Phase 2 keeps each path's tooling and gate appropriate to its risk class.</rationale>
  </decision>

  <decision date="2026-05-02" topic="memory-files-append-only">
    <chose>`.aidocs/memory/{patterns,mistakes,decisions}.md` are append-only with monotonic `PAT-NNN` / `ERR-NNN` / `DEC-NNN` identifiers; `session.md` is overwritten each run.</chose>
    <rejected>Allow rewrites of past entries when newer information makes them stale, to keep the files concise.</rejected>
    <rationale>External callers (commit messages, SDD tickets, code-review comments) cite specific identifiers. Rewriting past entries breaks those citations and erases the learning trail. Append-only plus monotonic identifiers makes the memory files a reliable citation target across sessions. Conciseness is recovered by appending corrections that reference older identifiers — the trail stays intact and the most recent entry wins on read.</rationale>
  </decision>

  <decision date="2026-05-02" topic="phase-7-reusable-knowledge-bar">
    <chose>Phase 7 (skill creation) requires the captured knowledge to be reusable across at least two future contexts before a methodology folder is created.</chose>
    <rejected>Allow any session-level pattern to become a skill, treating Phase 7 as automatic graduation of any `PAT-NNN` entry.</rejected>
    <rationale>The skills directory is a curated knowledge surface read by future agents and humans. Adding one-off entries dilutes its signal-to-noise and forces every later reader to filter past noise. Most session patterns belong in `patterns.md` only. Phase 7's two-context bar is the entry gate that keeps the skills directory a high-signal index instead of an unfiltered append log.</rationale>
  </decision>
</decisions>
