<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Stakeholder Management: Identification and Mapping Framework">
  <summary>Stakeholder types, Power/Interest grid with mandatory attitude dimension, engagement levels, and the four-step identification-to-execution process.</summary>

  <section title="Stakeholder Types">
    <list>
      <item>End Users: customers, employees — need value from product</item>
      <item>Decision Makers: executives, sponsors — need business outcomes</item>
      <item>Influencers: advisors, thought leaders — need credibility and early access</item>
      <item>Builders: developers, designers — need clear requirements</item>
      <item>Support: customer success, sales — need product knowledge</item>
      <item>External: partners, regulators — need compliance and compatibility</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Power/Interest Grid">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always add an explicit attitude column (Supporter / Neutral / Resistor) to the Power/Interest grid. Mark Unknown when attitude cannot be inferred from a cited source. Never leave attitude blank.</statement>
      <rationale>A Power/Interest grid without the attitude dimension is a 2D map of a 3D problem. A high-power stakeholder coded as "Manage Closely" but secretly a Resistor is the silent killer of cross-functional product launches.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>High Power, High Interest → Manage Closely: engage deeply, regular bidirectional updates, co-creation where possible</item>
      <item>High Power, Low Interest → Keep Satisfied: periodic updates, frame in terms of business outcomes, not details</item>
      <item>Low Power, High Interest → Keep Informed: involve in feedback sessions, one-way updates are sufficient for most</item>
      <item>Low Power, Low Interest → Monitor: minimal effort, periodic check-ins only</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Engagement Levels">
    <list>
      <item>Partner: active collaboration, co-creation, regular meetings, bidirectional input loops</item>
      <item>Involved: regular input, reviews, feedback sessions</item>
      <item>Informed: one-way updates, newsletters, demos</item>
      <item>Monitor: minimal contact, periodic check-ins</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every stakeholder must have a named engagement cadence (weekly 1:1, biweekly email, monthly review). "Ad-hoc" is code for "nothing happens".</statement>
      <rationale>A communication plan without a concrete cadence produces the same outcome as no plan — stakeholders feel ignored, resistors go undetected, and late-stage blockers emerge at critical milestones.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Four-Step Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Identify: who uses, pays, approves, builds, supports, or could block this product</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Analyze: what they want, what they fear, power level, interest level, attitude</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Plan engagement: cadence, format, information they need, relationship owner</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Execute and adapt: regular touchpoints, track attitude shifts, handle conflicts proactively</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
