<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-templates-and-examples" title="Stakeholder Management: Register, Communication Plan, and Examples">
  <summary>Stakeholder register column schema, communication plan matrix, meeting template structure, and worked examples for both SaaS feature launch and solo product contexts.</summary>

  <section title="Stakeholder Register Schema">
    <rule>
      <statement>The register must include these columns: name, role, interest (H/M/L), power (H/M/L), attitude (Supporter/Neutral/Resistor/Unknown), engagement level (Partner/Involved/Informed/Monitor), owner. The owner column is non-optional — "whole team manages this exec" means nobody does.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a named owner per stakeholder relationship, escalations have no clear path and engagement drifts to whoever is most available rather than most informed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cite the source for every Power and Attitude classification (meeting notes, org chart, repo CODEOWNERS). Mark Unknown if no source exists, not a guess.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM-generated stakeholder analyses hallucinate stakeholders from project-type templates. Requiring a source for each classification catches fabricated rows before they drive engagement decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Communication Plan Matrix">
    <list>
      <item>Executive sponsor: status + decisions, weekly, 1:1 meeting, PM owns</item>
      <item>Dev team: requirements + changes, daily, stand-up, PM owns</item>
      <item>Sales team: features + timeline, bi-weekly, email update, PM owns</item>
      <item>Customers: releases + feedback, monthly, newsletter, Marketing owns</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the escalation path with real names and backups: Issue → PM → (24h unresolved) → Director → (48h unresolved) → Executive sponsor. "Escalate to Director" with no name is unactionable at 11pm.</statement>
      <rationale>Escalation paths with role names instead of person names fail when roles turn over or when multiple people hold the role. Named individuals with backup contacts are actionable; role labels are not.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Worked Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS feature launch (5+ stakeholders): CEO (High/Medium → Keep Satisfied, quarterly), Head of Sales (High/High → Partner, weekly sync), Engineering Lead (Medium/High → Involved, daily standups), Key Customer (Low/High → Informed, beta access), Support Team (Low/High → Involved, training sessions). Explicit owner assigned to each row.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Solo product stakeholder register: Early customers (need working product + support → Discord and email), Payment processor (need compliance → documentation), Hosting provider (need technical requirements → support tickets), Advisor/mentor (need progress → monthly call), Family (need time boundaries → clear schedule). Even solopreneurs have stakeholders requiring explicit engagement plans.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Register with attitude column left blank for all rows, owner column filled with "team", and cadence listed as "ad-hoc". This register produces no value — attitude Unknown rows never get escalated, no one owns relationships, and "ad-hoc" means nothing happens.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/stakeholder-register.md">Register with all required columns and detailed profile section</reference>
  <reference path="templates/communication-plan.md">Communication matrix, key messages by audience, escalation path</reference>
  <reference path="templates/meeting-template.md">Stakeholder update meeting agenda: progress, decisions needed, risks, action items</reference>
</text>
