<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Scope-Creep Park List Template Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Scope-Creep Park List Template. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-park-do-not-debate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Off-scope ideas during a walkthrough are PARKED, not debated. Facilitator says one acknowledgement line and writes the row; debate happens at sprint planning.</statement>
      <rationale source="Facilitation-discipline practice">Mid-meeting debate destroys the decision-ask; parking keeps the meeting on track and respects the stakeholder.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-name-owner-per-row" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each parked row carries a named owner (typically the stakeholder who raised the idea) and the facilitator&apos;s handle.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI / single-throat-to-choke">Plural ownership produces orphan ideas; the stakeholder must be re-engageable at revisit time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-revisit-gate-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each row carries an explicit revisit_gate: &apos;next sprint planning&apos;, &apos;after launch&apos;, &apos;never (out of scope)&apos;; vague &apos;later&apos; is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-rule stability">Vague gates produce backlog rot; explicit gates trigger calendar reminders.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-acknowledgement-line" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each row carries the verbatim acknowledgement line the facilitator used in the meeting (e.g. &apos;Good point — parking for sprint planning&apos;); silent parking is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stakeholder-trust practice">Silently parked ideas feel dismissed; the acknowledgement line builds trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-review-at-sprint-planning" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Park list is reviewed at the next sprint planning; rows graduate to (a) backlog row, (b) design-decision-log row, or (c) explicit &apos;closed — out of scope&apos;. Rows untouched 2 sprints surface a warning.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay convention">Without review, parked rows fester; the review keeps the bank honest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-scope-creep-park-list-template.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
