<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Client Visibility Vs Velocity Tradeoff Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Client Visibility Vs Velocity Tradeoff application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-bound-scope" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply Client Visibility Vs Velocity Tradeoff only to a single instance of 'role-project-manager/Async cross-timezone delivery cadence (P4 outsource)'. Never batch multiple unrelated decisions through one pass.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-conflation pattern">Batching turns a 1-decision artefact into a debate club. Each instance gets its own record so the rationale is traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-typed-input" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every input field has a declared type and source. Free-form prose without a source citation is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-first artefacts">Untyped inputs let LLMs hallucinate plausible-but-wrong values. Typed + sourced inputs make the output falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The output names a single accountable owner (handle, email, or org role). No 'team' or 'we' as owner.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI / single-throat-to-choke">Plural ownership = no ownership. Future readers need a named human to chase when the artefact is stale.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-versioned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output carries semver-style version and last_reviewed date. Stale records (&gt;90 days, no review) must be flagged on read.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice">Methodology outputs decay; treating them as immutable is a defect. Versioning + review-by-date forces refresh cadence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-traceable-decision" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every decision in the output cites the input artefact(s) that justified it. Untraceable decisions are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-trail discipline">Without traceability, the artefact becomes opinion. Citations make the output reviewable by a future operator with no context.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
