<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Chunking Basics — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules for chunking: tiktoken measurement, default 500/50 band, content-type routing, metadata at creation, content-based IDs, version on strategy change.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-tiktoken-measure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Token counts MUST be measured with the same tiktoken encoding as the target embedding model (e.g. cl100k_base for OpenAI text-embedding-3-*). Word counts MUST NOT be used as a token proxy.</statement>
      <rationale source="Pinecone chunking guide + OpenAI tokenizer docs">Word counts diverge from token counts by ~30% for English and far more for non-Latin scripts. Chunk_size enforced in words can produce chunks that exceed the embedding model's input cap.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-default-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start with chunk_size=500 tokens, overlap=50 tokens. Use 1000–1500 for legal/technical, 200–400 for QA. Tune only after the first retrieval benchmark on ≥5 queries.</statement>
      <rationale source="LangChain/LlamaIndex defaults + retrieval benchmarks">500 tokens is the empirical middle ground that preserves context while keeping chunks focused. Tuning without a benchmark is guesswork.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-content-type-routing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Different content types MUST route to different splitters: code goes to AST splitter, markdown goes to header splitter, html goes to tag splitter, prose goes to recursive/sentence splitter. The pipeline MUST detect type before applying the splitter.</statement>
      <rationale source="LangChain text_splitters module design">A prose splitter on code destroys function boundaries; a code splitter on prose creates incoherent chunks. Strategy must match structure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-overlap-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Overlap MUST be 10–20% of chunk_size. For QA corpora where questions span chunk boundaries use the upper 20% bound.</statement>
      <rationale source="Retrieval recall studies on overlapping windows">Zero overlap causes boundary-spanning queries to retrieve no relevant chunk. Overlap above 20% inflates index size with diminishing recall gain.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-metadata-at-creation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each chunk MUST carry source, page, chunk_index, strategy, version, token_count at creation. Retrofitting metadata after indexing requires a full re-index.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion-network ingestion incident log">Missing source/page makes hits unattributable; missing strategy/version makes A/B comparisons impossible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-content-based-ids" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Chunk IDs MUST be content-based: md5(source_path + chunk_index + strategy_version). Sequential integers MUST NOT be used.</statement>
      <rationale source="Idempotent re-ingest pattern">Sequential IDs collide on update or re-chunk. Content-based IDs keep re-ingest idempotent and allow incremental delete/replace.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
