<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Change Control Lifecycle">
  <summary>The six-step change control process: receive, log, analyze impact, decide with tiered authority, implement, and close with documentation.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Receive and Log">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture every change request in writing with a unique ID before any analysis or work begins; verbal requests are not change requests.</statement>
      <rationale>Undocumented changes become disputed scope — the requester remembers agreement, the team remembers refusal, and neither has evidence. A CR ID creates a paper trail from the moment of request.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Required fields at receipt: requester name and role, date submitted, plain-language description of the change, business justification, and urgency.</p>
    <p>CR status lifecycle: Submitted → Under Review → Approved / Rejected / Deferred → Implemented (if approved) → Closed.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Impact Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every impact analysis must include a "do nothing" option; omitting it prevents the explicit cost-of-inaction reasoning that justifies or rejects the change.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a baseline option, decision makers compare change variants against each other rather than against the status quo, which inflates the perceived value of every change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Impact areas to assess for every CR:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Scope — which features or WBS elements are affected.</item>
      <item>Schedule — additional days; which milestones move.</item>
      <item>Cost — additional budget; which line items are affected.</item>
      <item>Quality — impact on standards, testing, technical debt.</item>
      <item>Risk — new risks introduced; existing risks affected.</item>
      <item>Resources — who must work on it; opportunity cost to other work.</item>
      <item>Test impact — regression and integration testing required (explicitly, not bundled into "Quality").</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/change-request-form.md">Change request form with impact analysis</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Decision with Tiered Authority">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define decision-authority thresholds in writing at kickoff, post them publicly, and do not revise them without sponsor agreement; thresholds that drift upward make every change a "minor" change.</statement>
      <rationale>Without written thresholds, PMs informally expand their own authority over time ("it's only 2 days, I'll approve it myself"), which bypasses the sponsor and sponsor approval stops being meaningful.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Minor (e.g., less than 1 day, less than $500) — PM approves.</item>
      <item>Medium (e.g., 1-5 days, $500-$5,000) — Sponsor approves.</item>
      <item>Major (e.g., more than 5 days, more than $5,000) — CCB approves.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Bundle minor CRs into a weekly "minor changes" approval batch to maintain cadence without per-request ceremony; present the aggregate schedule and cost impact, not individual items.</statement>
      <rationale>Per-item approval for minor changes produces either rubber-stamping (no real bar) or approval fatigue; aggregate presentation makes the cumulative cost visible and triggers escalation when it crosses a threshold.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Implement and Close">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tie every approved CR to a baseline-update commit (WBS, schedule, budget) in the same PR; scope changes without corresponding document updates create drift between the plan and the baseline.</statement>
      <rationale>A CR logged as "approved" but not reflected in the scope baseline and schedule produces a team working to the new scope while reporting against the old baseline — a measurement error masquerading as performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/change-register.md">Change register for tracking all CRs</reference>
    <reference path="scripts/cr_drift.sh">Script to sum cumulative schedule/cost impact of approved CRs</reference>
  </section>
</text>
