<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ads-meta-campaign-setup">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>ppc-manager</domain>
    <summary>Meta campaign setup: install Pixel, select objective, configure three-tier structure (Campaign → Ad Set → Ad), set targeting and placements, upload 3+ creatives, avoid learning phase edits.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>meta</tag>
      <tag>facebook</tag>
      <tag>instagram</tag>
      <tag>campaign-setup</tag>
      <tag>pixel</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Meta Campaign Setup</title>

    <summary>End-to-end checklist for launching a Facebook/Instagram campaign via Meta Ads Manager: install and verify the Meta Pixel, choose the correct campaign objective, configure the three-tier structure (Campaign → Ad Set → Ad), set targeting and placements, upload at least 3 creative variations per ad set, and avoid editing during the learning phase. The core rule is: select the objective that matches the actual business action — choosing Traffic when the goal is leads optimizes for clicks, not conversions, and wastes budget.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Meta's delivery system optimizes for the event you specify as your objective. Wrong objective = wrong optimization signal. The learning phase requires ~50 conversions per ad set per week; editing during learning resets the counter and extends unstable performance. Campaign Budget Optimization (CBO) distributes spend across ad sets dynamically, outperforming fixed ad-set budgets once the algorithm has enough signal. These mechanics make correct initial setup critical — retrofitting an objective after launch requires a new campaign.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Launching a new Meta campaign from scratch</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing campaign's structure for mis-aligned objectives or missing Pixel setup</item>
        <item>Setting up the naming conventions and UTM parameters for a new product line</item>
        <item>Configuring CBO vs. ad-set budget for a new test</item>
        <item>Onboarding a new account that has never run Meta ads</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Audience construction (custom, lookalike, interest targeting) — use meta-audience-targeting</item>
        <item>Creative copy and image/video spec decisions for Instagram placements — use instagram-ads</item>
        <item>Budget reallocation across live campaigns — use ads-budget-optimization</item>
        <item>Reporting and analysis of a running campaign — use the Meta reporting methodology</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="meta-pixel-installation-and-verification">
      <p>The Meta Pixel is the foundation of all data-driven Meta advertising. Without it, campaigns cannot optimize on conversions.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Install and verify the Meta Pixel before creating any campaign — do not run ads without confirmed event tracking.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a firing pixel, campaign objectives requiring conversions (Sales, Leads) have no optimization signal; the algorithm delivers to random audiences at high CPMs with no learning.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not launch until conversion events show "Active" status in Events Manager for at least 24 hours with real traffic, not just test events.</statement>
        <rationale>Test events confirm code fires but do not confirm production reliability — a deployment issue or CSP block may prevent firing in production under normal traffic.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>PageView — automatic on all pages (base code required)</item>
        <item>ViewContent — product/service page views</item>
        <item>AddToCart — e-commerce cart additions</item>
        <item>InitiateCheckout — checkout start</item>
        <item>Purchase — completed transaction with value</item>
        <item>Lead — form submission, sign-up</item>
        <item>CompleteRegistration — account creation</item>
      </list>
      <list>
        <item>Install Meta Pixel Helper Chrome extension</item>
        <item>Visit the website and confirm PageView fires (green indicator)</item>
        <item>Trigger each conversion event manually (add to cart, submit form)</item>
        <item>Check Events Manager → Test Events tab for real-time confirmation</item>
        <item>Verify event values are passing correctly (purchase amount, currency)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="campaign-structure-and-objective-selection">
      <p>Meta campaigns follow a strict three-tier hierarchy, and objective selection determines the optimization signal throughout.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never mix objectives within a campaign — each campaign optimizes for exactly one objective signal.</statement>
        <rationale>Meta's delivery system is objective-aware at the campaign level; splitting objectives forces the algorithm to optimize for incompatible signals simultaneously.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>For revenue-driven campaigns, always choose Sales or Leads objective — never Traffic, even if conversion volume is low initially.</statement>
        <rationale>Traffic objective optimizes for the cheapest click, not the most likely buyer; this fills the funnel with high-bounce, low-intent visits that look good in CPCs but produce zero conversions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Three-tier structure: Campaign defines objective. Ad Set defines audience, placements, schedule, budget. Ad defines creative and copy.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Awareness → reach and impressions (brand, new markets)</item>
        <item>Traffic → link clicks or landing page views (content promotion)</item>
        <item>Engagement → post interactions (social proof building)</item>
        <item>Leads → Lead Instant Forms or website lead events</item>
        <item>App Installs → mobile install events</item>
        <item>Sales → Purchase pixel event or catalog sales</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cbo-vs-ad-set-budget">
      <p>Budget optimization strategy significantly impacts campaign performance and learning speed.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Start with CBO at $20-50/day minimum and let Meta distribute; switch to ad-set budget only if a specific ad set is being chronically under-funded by CBO after 7+ days.</statement>
        <rationale>CBO with sufficient total budget finds efficient delivery faster than manual allocation; premature manual allocation forces sub-optimal fixed splits.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>CBO (Campaign Budget Optimization) — Meta distributes across ad sets dynamically; best when testing multiple audiences with equal starting budgets</item>
        <item>Ad-Set Budget — fixed per ad set; use when one ad set must never be starved by others (e.g. retargeting)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ad-set-configuration">
      <p>Audience size, placement selection, and optimization goal must align with campaign objectives.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Target 500K-5M audience size for interest-based cold targeting — smaller audiences constrain delivery and prevent the learning phase from completing.</statement>
        <rationale>Meta needs approximately 50 conversions per ad set per week to exit learning. Audiences under 100K often cannot generate enough unique impressions to achieve this, keeping the campaign in the unstable learning phase indefinitely.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Under 100K — too narrow; high CPMs, limited learning</item>
        <item>100K-500K — acceptable for high-value niche B2B</item>
        <item>500K-5M — optimal for most consumer and SMB targeting</item>
        <item>Over 10M — consider narrowing with one behavioral qualifier</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Start new campaigns with Advantage+ Placements (automatic); manually select placements only after placement-level performance data shows a clear winner after 7+ days.</statement>
        <rationale>Manual placement selection at launch removes inventory Meta's algorithm would have tested; automatic placement gives the widest pool for the learning phase, reducing time-to-stable-CPA.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Sales objective → optimize for Purchase event</item>
        <item>Leads objective → optimize for Lead or CompleteRegistration event</item>
        <item>Traffic objective → optimize for Landing Page Views (not Link Clicks)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ad-creation-and-launch">
      <p>Creative requirements, minimum variation, and launch-phase rules determine early campaign performance.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Primary text: 125 characters shown without truncation; additional text behind "See more"</item>
        <item>Headline: 40 characters ideal</item>
        <item>Description: optional, appears below headline</item>
        <item>CTA button: required — Learn More, Sign Up, Shop Now, Get Quote, etc.</item>
        <item>Image or video: must match placement spec (see instagram-ads for specs)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Upload at least 3 ad variations per ad set covering different formats (image, video, carousel) — never launch with a single creative.</statement>
        <rationale>Single-creative ad sets cannot be optimized; Meta needs variation to identify which creative, format, or angle resonates with a given audience segment.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Add UTM parameters to all ad destination URLs before launch — never rely on Meta's internal attribution alone.</statement>
        <rationale>Meta attribution and GA4 attribution diverge by 20-50% due to view-through vs click-through differences; UTMs provide the GA4 ground truth needed for cross-platform comparison.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="UTM parameter format">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
?utm_source=facebook&utm_medium=paid-social&utm_campaign={{campaign.name}}&utm_content={{ad.name}}
        ]]></code>
        <note>Meta supports dynamic UTM parameters using {{campaign.name}}, {{adset.name}}, {{ad.name}} placeholders.</note>
      </example>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not edit ad sets, targeting, bids, or budgets during the first 3-7 days — any significant edit resets the learning phase counter.</statement>
        <rationale>The learning phase requires ~50 conversions to complete; editing forces a restart, extending the period of unstable, high-CPA delivery.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <p>Common setup mistakes that prevent campaigns from achieving stable, profitable performance.</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running campaigns without a verified Meta Pixel.</description>
        <reason>No conversion data means the delivery system cannot optimize — ads serve to random segments at maximum CPM with zero feedback loop.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Choosing Traffic objective when the actual goal is leads or purchases.</description>
        <reason>Traffic optimizes for cheap clicks; it finds audiences that click but don't convert, inflating CTR while producing zero revenue.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using an audience under 100K for interest-based prospecting.</description>
        <reason>Audience exhaustion occurs within days; high frequency causes CPM inflation and ad fatigue before the algorithm can learn anything meaningful.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Launching with one ad per ad set.</description>
        <reason>No creative variation means no optimization path — Meta cannot identify a winner and the campaign performance is limited to whatever the single creative happens to achieve.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Editing budgets, targeting, or bids during the first 3-7 days.</description>
        <reason>Resets the learning phase counter; the campaign re-enters unstable high-CPA delivery, negating any potential improvement from the edit.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Omitting UTM parameters from destination URLs.</description>
        <reason>Without UTMs, GA4 attributes Meta-driven sessions as direct traffic, making cross-channel ROAS comparison impossible.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/campaign-naming.txt" purpose="Naming convention for campaigns, ad sets, and ads"/>
      <template path="templates/launch-checklist.md" purpose="Pre-launch checklist: pixel, objective, budget, targeting, creatives, tracking"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/marketing-apis/overview"/>
      <link href="https://www.facebook.com/business/help/1438417719786103"/>
      <link href="https://www.facebook.com/business/help/1619591734742116"/>
      <link href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/marketing-api/conversions-api"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/pipeboard-co/meta-ads-mcp"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
