<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Freelance Marketplace Platform Tradeoffs Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Freelance Marketplace Platform Tradeoffs MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="five-axis-score" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each platform MUST be scored on fee / lead-quality / exclusivity / ranking / density. Skipping any axis invalidates the decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — freelance platform audit 2025">Single-axis evaluation (fee-only) is the #1 reason freelancers pick wrong platform; five-axis catches lock-in and churn risks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rate-band-fit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Selected platform MUST match the freelancer's rate band per published platform medians. Mismatch &gt;= 30% requires switch.</statement>
      <rationale source="Freelancer rate-band benchmarks Q1 2026">Platforms strongly cluster around rate-band medians; mismatched freelancers either price-floor or starve for leads.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="exclusivity-flagged" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exclusivity clauses MUST be flagged in the decision record. Hidden exclusivity terminates the methodology output as invalid.</statement>
      <rationale source="Platform contract reviews 2024-2025">Toptal / Braintrust exclusivity restrict outside work; freelancers regularly sign without reading.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="secondary-platform-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision MUST include a primary AND a secondary platform (or explicit reason for primary-only). Platform monoculture is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Marketplace dependency audit 2025">Single-platform freelancers are one ban or algorithm change from zero income; secondary platform is risk hedge.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="churn-trigger-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision record MUST list &gt;=2 churn triggers (when to leave the platform). Indefinite stays without exit criteria are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene — solo consultancy">Freelancers overstay platforms; defined exits force re-evaluation at known thresholds.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
