<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-artifact-templates" title="SDD Artifact Templates">
  <summary>Template bodies for Constitution, Spec, Design, Task, and Implementation Plan — the five core SDD artifacts an agent must produce with consistent structure.</summary>

  <section title="Constitution Template">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the Constitution template for every new project before any feature work begins. It is the only artifact that does not change per-feature.</statement>
      <rationale>Constitution captures tech stack, standards, and quality gates in one place. Agents reference it in every spec and task to avoid reinventing decisions already made.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/constitution.md">Fillable Constitution skeleton with vision, tech stack table, architecture patterns, code standards, git workflow, project structure, quality gates, principles.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Specification Template">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide the spec template as part of the system prompt when generating a spec. Instruct the agent to fill each section and output only the filled template — do not add sections not in the template.</statement>
      <rationale>Constrains output structure; prevents agents from inventing non-standard sections like "Technical Notes" or "Architecture" that belong in design.md.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Spec template key fields: Version, Status (Draft/Review/Approved), Problem Statement (Who/Problem/Impact/Solution/Success Metric), User Personas, User Stories (As a / I want / So that / Priority), FR table (ID, Requirement, Traces To, Priority), NFR table (ID, Category, Requirement, Target), AC in Given-When-Then, Out of Scope table, Assumptions, Dependencies, Related Features.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Implementation Plan Template">
    <rule>
      <statement>The Implementation Plan template wave/checkpoint structure must be preserved intact — the executor agent relies on it to process tasks in dependency order without re-reading the entire plan.</statement>
      <rationale>If wave boundaries are removed or merged, the executor cannot determine which tasks are safe to run in parallel and which must wait.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/implementation-plan.md">Fillable Implementation Plan skeleton with overview, task summary table (Task/Name/Complexity/Est.Tokens/Depends On/Enables), dependency graph, execution waves with checkpoints, task detail blocks, quality gates, FR/AD coverage matrix, risks.</reference>
    <p>Token estimation guide for common components:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Django model (simple): 5-10k tokens</item>
      <item>Django model (complex): 15-25k tokens</item>
      <item>Service class: 20-40k tokens</item>
      <item>ViewSet: 15-30k tokens</item>
      <item>Serializer: 5-15k tokens</item>
      <item>Test file: 20-40k tokens</item>
      <item>React component (simple): 5-10k tokens</item>
      <item>React component (complex): 15-30k tokens</item>
      <item>API endpoint: 10-20k tokens</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>When uncertain about a token estimate, estimate higher and split the task.</statement>
      <rationale>Underestimates cause mid-execution context overflow; the executor produces incomplete output and marks the task done without detecting failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Task File Template">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every TASK_*.md file must include Metadata (Complexity, Est. Tokens, Priority), SDD References (spec, design, plan links), Task Dependency Tree, Objective, Dependencies (with reasons), Acceptance Criteria, Technical Approach (steps), Files to change, and token budget.</statement>
      <rationale>The executor agent stops at BLOCKED status. Missing fields mean the executor cannot proceed; it will either produce wrong output or halt without logging the reason.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Leaving {placeholder} text in non-obvious fields after template fill (e.g., "Project: {project-name}").</description>
      <reason>Agents filling templates miss placeholder fields in metadata; run grep for '{' in generated docs before committing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
