<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-planning-templates" title="Planning and Memory Templates">
  <summary>Templates for Roadmap, Backlog Item, Grooming Session, Confidence Check, Pattern Record, and Mistake Record — the artifacts that support planning, triage, and cross-session learning.</summary>

  <section title="Roadmap Template">
    <rule>
      <statement>Roadmap items in the "Now" bucket must have a target milestone and a status (On Track / At Risk / Delayed). "Later" items carry no target — only thematic groupings.</statement>
      <rationale>Concrete targets in "Now" create accountability; absent targets in "Later" prevent false precision for work that will change as earlier work lands.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/roadmap.md">Roadmap skeleton: Vision, Now (current quarter with milestone + feature status), Next (next quarter with confidence level), Later (themes only), Not Planned list, Dependencies table, Change Log.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Backlog Item Template">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every backlog item must include a RICE score section before it is promoted from ideas/ to validated/. Agent-generated RICE numbers must be flagged as "estimate-needed" when Reach or Impact inputs are not grounded in real data.</statement>
      <rationale>RICE scores generated without real data are illustrative only. Flagging them prevents false ranking precision that leads to executing low-value work first.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/backlog-item.md">Backlog item skeleton with ID, Status lifecycle, Priority P0-P3, Summary, Problem, Proposed Solution, User Stories, RICE table, MoSCoW checkboxes, Dependencies, Risks, Next Steps.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Confidence Check Template">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the Confidence Check template at four explicit gates: Pre-Spec, Pre-Design, Pre-Task, Pre-Implementation. Skip none. The "Open Questions" section blocks Approved status — unresolved questions are blockers, not optional notes.</statement>
      <rationale>Advancing with unresolved questions causes rework in later phases. The Confidence Check makes ambiguities visible before the cost of fixing them rises.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/confidence-check.md">Confidence Check skeleton: Phase, Score table (Check/Weight/Status/Evidence), Verdict (Proceed/Clarify/Stop), Questions to Answer First, Recommended Actions.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Pattern and Mistake Records">
    <rule>
      <statement>After each task execution, the executor agent appends a Pattern Record or Mistake Record to .aidocs/memory/. These must be indexed so future agents can find and apply prior learnings without repeating mistakes.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents that cannot find prior patterns repeat mistakes. The structured JSON format enables programmatic search and aggregation across sessions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/pattern-record.json">JSON schema: id (PAT-NNN), timestamp, project, task_type, pattern_name, description, context (when to use), code_example, success_count, tags.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/mistake-record.json">JSON schema: id (ERR-NNN), timestamp, project, task_type, error_type, description, root_cause, solution, prevention, occurrence_count, tags.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
