<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-usage-rules" title="Template Usage Rules">
  <summary>Rules for correct template usage: no extra sections, four confidence-check gates, token estimation discipline, and agent self-logging pattern.</summary>

  <section title="Do Not Add Sections">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always use the template as-is for the first version. Resist adding custom sections until the standard ones are proven insufficient.</statement>
      <rationale>Custom sections added by agents are invisible to other agents and tools that parse the standard structure. They also indicate that the template boundary was wrong, which should be fixed in the template itself, not patched per-feature.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent adds "Technical Notes" section to spec.md or "Architecture" section to a task file.</description>
      <reason>These belong in design.md. Spec = WHAT/WHY. Task = atomic unit with observable AC. Architecture = design.md AD-X.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Four Confidence Check Gates">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the Confidence Check template at Pre-Spec, Pre-Design, Pre-Task, and Pre-Implementation. Do not skip any gate, even under time pressure.</statement>
      <rationale>Each gate checks that the previous phase's output is sufficient to begin the next. Skipping a gate means advancing with gaps that will cause rework at a higher cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Token Estimation Discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a 20% buffer to test file estimates. Generated code (GraphQL schema, Prisma client, migration snapshots) can be 5-10x larger than hand-written equivalents — account for them explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale>Token estimates that omit generated files cause context overflow mid-execution. The executor does not abort; it produces incomplete output and marks the task done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using "Est. tokens: ~Xk" without a breakdown showing which files contribute to that total.</description>
      <reason>Unitemized estimates cannot be audited and are consistently optimistic by 30-50% in practice.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Self-Logging Pattern">
    <rule>
      <statement>After each task execution, the executor agent must append either a Pattern Record or Mistake Record to .aidocs/memory/. Pattern records log what worked; mistake records log errors with root cause and prevention.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents without cross-session memory repeat the same mistakes. Structured JSON records enable programmatic aggregation and future agent retrieval without loading the full history in context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pattern and Mistake Records must be indexed. Agents that cannot find prior patterns via index will re-discover them at cost.</statement>
      <rationale>An unindexed memory is effectively no memory. The index must list ID, task_type, and summary for each record so agents can selectively load relevant ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
