<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agency Acquisition Prep Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Agency Acquisition Prep plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="founder-dependency-reduction" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The acquisition-prep cycle MUST measure founder-dependency: the share of revenue, decisions, and client relationships that pass through the founder alone, with a target ≤30%.</statement>
      <rationale source="Built to Sell — John Warrillow (2010)">Acquirers price down agencies where the founder is the product; reducing dependency is the highest-leverage prep work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="deal-lane-choice-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each cycle MUST pick one of three lanes (strategic acquirer / financial buyer / aqui-hire) and reject mixed-lane prep activities for the cycle.</statement>
      <rationale source="Quiet Light Brokerage — agency exits">Strategic and financial buyers value entirely different metrics; trying to optimise for both produces a deck that signals neither well.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="loi-hygiene-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any inbound LOI MUST be reviewed under the standard hygiene checklist (exclusivity window, earnout cap, IP carve-outs, non-compete radius) before any verbal commitment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Walker Deibel — Buy Then Build (2018)">Verbal commitments to a single LOI eliminate competitive tension and tank valuation; LOI hygiene is the founder's primary leverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="data-room-rolling" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The data room MUST be maintained on a rolling weekly basis with the latest P&amp;L, payroll roster, top-10 client retainer status, and IP inventory — not assembled reactively when an LOI arrives.</statement>
      <rationale source="Quiet Light Brokerage diligence playbook">Reactive data rooms are 30% incomplete and cost 6+ weeks; rolling data rooms close in 2-3 weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="items-need-owner-or-defer" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any checklist item without a named owner this cycle MUST be deferred with a written reason and aging counter — never silently skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atul Gawande — The Checklist Manifesto">Unowned items create the illusion of work; deferring + aging surfaces structural gaps (missing capability, wrong person) instead of hiding them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
