<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-structure" title="OKR Structure: Objectives, Key Results, and Scoring">
  <summary>Defines what makes a valid Objective and Key Result, the scoring scale, and the structural rules (3-5 O, 3-5 KR each).</summary>

  <section title="Objective Characteristics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Objectives must be qualitative, inspiring, time-bound, and memorable. They must not contain numbers. Any Objective that contains a percentage or count is a Key Result in disguise.</statement>
      <rationale>Objectives set direction; Key Results measure progress toward it. Mixing them destroys the separation that makes OKRs useful — if the Objective already contains the number, the KR adds nothing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit to 3-5 Objectives per quarter. More than 5 is a strategic failure — everything is important means nothing is. Solo creators should limit to 1 Objective with 3 KRs.</statement>
      <rationale>Focus is the primary value OKRs provide. An OKR set with 8 Objectives tells the team to work on everything, which is indistinguishable from having no OKRs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Objective: "Delight early adopters and earn their advocacy." Qualitative, inspiring, does not contain a number, clearly time-bound to the quarter.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Objective: "Increase NPS to 50." This is a Key Result. The Objective should be "Build a product users love and recommend."</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Result Characteristics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Key Results must be outcomes, not outputs. Ban the verbs ship/launch/build/release/create/design/implement/deploy at the start of any KR. KRs starting with these verbs are tasks, not outcomes.</statement>
      <rationale>KRs measure whether the Objective was achieved, not whether work was done. "Ship feature X" can be 100% complete while the Objective fails entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every KR requires a baseline number stated on the day the OKRs are committed. No baseline equals no commitment. If the metric is not yet instrumented, write "TO BE INSTRUMENTED by [owner] by [date]" — never invent a baseline number.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a baseline, "improve from X to Y" is undefined. Teams with no baseline cannot track progress and will report subjective completion at quarter end.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Target confidence at 70% (stretch but achievable). KRs with 100% confidence are sandbagged. KRs with 30% confidence are fantasy. Score 0.7 as ideal; 0.0-0.3 = failed, 0.4-0.6 = progress, 0.7-1.0 = success.</statement>
      <rationale>The 70% target creates psychological safety for ambitious KRs. If hitting 100% is expected, teams anchor to safe targets. If 70% is the norm, teams stretch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never couple OKRs to compensation. Any KR linked to individual bonuses will be sandbagged within one quarter. OKRs are learning tools, not performance ratings.</statement>
      <rationale>Compensation coupling converts stretch goals into low-risk targets and destroys the candor required for honest quarterly retrospectives.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
