<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="OKR 6-Step Process">
  <summary>Sequential steps from strategy alignment through weekly tracking cadence.</summary>

  <section title="Setting OKRs">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — Align to strategy. Inputs: company mission/vision, annual goals, previous quarter's learnings and scores, current market conditions. The anchoring question: "What must we accomplish this quarter to move toward our vision?"</statement>
      <rationale>OKRs disconnected from strategy are vanity. The "why this matters" sentence per Objective is more important than the Objective wording itself. Lose the why and OKRs become prose.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Draft Objectives by brainstorming. Ask: "What is most important right now?", "If we could only achieve one thing, what would it be?", "What would make this quarter a success?" Limit to 3-5 Objectives maximum.</statement>
      <rationale>Brainstorming before constraining prevents anchoring to last quarter's OKRs. The single-thing question forces prioritization before KRs are written.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Define Key Results for each Objective. For each KR: how will we know we achieved the Objective? What metric matters? What is the specific target? What is today's baseline? Can it be measured without building new instrumentation?</statement>
      <rationale>The instrumentation question prevents phantom KRs — KRs that sound measurable but require 6 weeks of data pipeline work before they can be tracked at all.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Validate. Check: Objectives are qualitative, KRs are measurable outcomes (not tasks), 70% confidence per KR, connected to higher-level goals, total count is focused.</statement>
      <rationale>Validation before commitment catches KR-as-task and missing baselines when they are cheapest to fix — before the quarter starts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5 — Communicate and commit. Share with stakeholders, get explicit buy-in, make visible on a shared dashboard or wiki. Add a kill condition per Objective: "We drop this Objective if [leading indicator] does not move by week 6."</statement>
      <rationale>Kill conditions prevent OKR theatre — beautiful OKRs that no one acts on. A kill condition forces a mid-quarter honest assessment rather than waiting for the retrospective.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 6 — Track weekly with confidence (High/Med/Low), not progress percent. Confidence is forward-looking; percent is backward-looking. Score KRs at end of quarter on 0.0-1.0 scale. Append to the record; do not replace it.</statement>
      <rationale>Confidence tracking surfaces risk earlier. A KR at 80% progress with Low confidence is a bigger problem than a KR at 30% progress with High confidence. Weekly appends preserve the trend history that the retrospective depends on.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/okr-template.md">Quarterly OKR document with baseline/target/current/score table</reference>
  <reference path="templates/kr-lint.py">Python linter to catch task-shaped and unbaselined KRs before commitment</reference>
</text>
