<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-antipatterns" title="OKR Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Common failure modes that produce OKR theatre or sandbagging, with root causes.</summary>

  <antipattern>
    <description>KR-as-task: "Launch feature X by Q2", "Ship the mobile redesign", "Build the reporting dashboard." The KR is a task disguised as an outcome.</description>
    <reason>Tasks can be 100% complete while the Objective fails entirely. "Launch feature X" is done when the deploy button is pressed; "Increase feature adoption from 10% to 30%" is done when users actually use it. Apply the banned-verb list: ship/launch/build/release/create/design/implement/deploy.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Missing baseline: "Improve NPS" or "Increase conversion rate to 8%" with no starting number. Teams cannot determine whether progress is being made.</description>
    <reason>Without a baseline, 0.7 KR scoring is subjective. Teams will always report "significant improvement" regardless of actual movement. Every KR committed without a baseline becomes a vehicle for post-hoc rationalization.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Sandbagging: KRs set at 100% confidence that the team knows it will achieve. End-of-quarter scores cluster at 0.95-1.0.</description>
    <reason>Results from coupling OKRs to compensation or from cultures that punish misses. Safe KRs produce zero strategic information. The 70% confidence target is designed to produce ~70% scores at quarter end — teams that consistently score above 0.85 are not stretching.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>OKR theatre: OKR documents are created, weekly check-ins are performed as ritual, no real behavior change occurs. Everyone "achieved" their OKRs.</description>
    <reason>OKRs without a kill condition and without genuine leadership accountability are performative. The kill condition per Objective ("drop this if leading indicator does not move by week 6") is the mechanism that converts OKRs from documentation into decision tools.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Cascading dilution: by the time a company-level Objective cascades to an IC, it has been restated at every level and is now either unrecognizable or trivially achievable.</description>
    <reason>Each level of cascade should add resolution, not copy the level above. A team OKR should decompose the company Objective into the specific contribution the team makes, not paraphrase it.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Too many OKRs: 8 Objectives with 4 KRs each. The team works on all of them equally, which is equivalent to having no priorities.</description>
    <reason>The purpose of OKRs is to declare what is NOT being worked on, not to document everything that will be worked on. More than 5 Objectives means everything is important, which means nothing is.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
