<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="okr-setting Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for okr-setting as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>KR-as-task: "Launch feature X by Q2", "Ship the mobile redesign", "Build the reporting dashboard." The KR is a task disguised as an outcome.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tasks can be 100% complete while the Objective fails entirely. "Launch feature X" is done when the deploy button is pressed; "Increase feature adoption from 10% to 30%" is done when users actually use it. Apply the banned-verb list: ship/launch/build/release/create/design/implement/deploy.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Missing baseline: "Improve NPS" or "Increase conversion rate to 8%" with no starting number. Teams cannot determine whether progress is being made.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a baseline, 0.7 KR scoring is subjective. Teams will always report "significant improvement" regardless of actual movement. Every KR committed without a baseline becomes a vehicle for post-hoc rationalization.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Sandbagging: KRs set at 100% confidence that the team knows it will achieve. End-of-quarter scores cluster at 0.95-1.0.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Results from coupling OKRs to compensation or from cultures that punish misses. Safe KRs produce zero strategic information. The 70% confidence target is designed to produce ~70% scores at quarter end — teams that consistently score above 0.85 are not stretching.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>OKR theatre: OKR documents are created, weekly check-ins are performed as ritual, no real behavior change occurs. Everyone "achieved" their OKRs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>OKRs without a kill condition and without genuine leadership accountability are performative. The kill condition per Objective ("drop this if leading indicator does not move by week 6") is the mechanism that converts OKRs from documentation into decision tools.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Cascading dilution: by the time a company-level Objective cascades to an IC, it has been restated at every level and is now either unrecognizable or trivially achievable.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each level of cascade should add resolution, not copy the level above. A team OKR should decompose the company Objective into the specific contribution the team makes, not paraphrase it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Too many OKRs: 8 Objectives with 4 KRs each. The team works on all of them equally, which is equivalent to having no priorities.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The purpose of OKRs is to declare what is NOT being worked on, not to document everything that will be worked on. More than 5 Objectives means everything is important, which means nothing is.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs produce gorgeous Objective prose ("delight users with magical experiences") that has zero strategic content. Force "why this matters" tied to a specific business reality.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Language models optimize for inspirational tone, not strategic clarity. Without grounding, they produce pleasant-sounding non-statements.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Models default to KRs-as-tasks because shipping is concrete. Apply a hard banned-verb list: ship/launch/build/release/create/design/implement/deploy.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Task-oriented language is more natural to language models than outcome-oriented language.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Baselines get hallucinated. Require explicit baseline citation (dashboard URL, query, or "TO BE INSTRUMENTED" with owner).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models will invent plausible numbers without grounding.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Cascade agents flatten everything — team OKRs become a restatement of company OKRs. Force decomposition: each level adds resolution, not a copy.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Restatement is easier and more coherent than genuine decomposition.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Weekly tracker agents over-write the narrative every week, hiding trend. Append, do not replace.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models optimize for each-week coherence, not trend history.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Human-in-loop checkpoint: final OKR set requires explicit human sign-off; agents are too eager to ship the draft.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models prioritize output generation over quality gates.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Human-in-loop checkpoint: end-of-quarter scoring is sensitive — agents will over-credit progress to look successful. Require human review of final 0.0-1.0 scoring.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models have bias toward positive narratives.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Coupling OKRs to AI-driven performance reviews is a category error. Do not let agents auto-translate KR scores into individual performance ratings.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>This conflates learning metrics with evaluation metrics, destroying both.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
