<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-star-method" title="STAR Method: Components, Flow, and Follow-Up Probes">
  <summary>STAR component definitions, the four-step interview flow, follow-up probe questions, and patterns for distinguishing complete from incomplete responses.</summary>

  <section title="STAR Components">
    <rule>
      <statement>A complete STAR response requires all four components; accept nothing as evidence until the Action and Result are specific and attributable to the candidate personally.</statement>
      <rationale>Candidates default to team-credit framing ("we delivered...") and omit results because they are uncertain what to share. Probing for personal contribution and quantified outcomes converts vague stories into scorable evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Component Definitions">
      <p>Situation: the context or background — who, what, when, what was at stake. The interviewer prompt: "Tell me about a time when..."</p>
      <p>Task: the candidate's specific responsibility in the situation — not the team's goal, the candidate's goal. Probe: "What was your role specifically?"</p>
      <p>Action: what the candidate specifically did — concrete steps in first-person singular. Probe: "Walk me through exactly what YOU did, not what the team did."</p>
      <p>Result: the outcome and its scope — quantified where possible, time-bounded, learning noted. Probe: "What was the outcome? What changed as a result? What would you do differently?"</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Interview Flow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow the four-step flow for every behavioral question: ask, listen for the Situation, probe for missing Task and Action specificity, confirm the Result.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping probes when the story sounds good is the primary source of false positives. Compelling narratives often lack the candidate's personal contribution — probing exposes whether the role was central or peripheral.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Ask the behavioral question. Let the candidate answer without interruption.</item>
      <item>Step 2: Listen for Situation. Note: is the context specific? Is there a timeframe? Who was involved?</item>
      <item>Step 3: Probe for Task and Action. Ask: "What was your specific responsibility?" and "Walk me through exactly what you did." Distinguish personal action from team action.</item>
      <item>Step 4: Confirm the Result. Ask: "What was the outcome?" and "What metrics can you share?" and "What did you learn?" If the result is vague, ask: "What would have happened if you hadn't done that?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Follow-Up Probe Catalog">
    <section title="Clarification Probes">
      <p>"Can you be more specific about [the situation / the decision / the outcome]?"</p>
      <p>"When did this happen? How long did it take?"</p>
    </section>
    <section title="Personal-Contribution Probes">
      <p>"What was YOUR contribution versus the team's?"</p>
      <p>"If you hadn't been involved, what would have happened?"</p>
      <p>"Who else was involved? What did they do specifically?"</p>
    </section>
    <section title="Quantification Probes">
      <p>"What were the specific numbers or metrics?"</p>
      <p>"How did you measure success?"</p>
      <p>"How does that compare to before you made the change?"</p>
    </section>
    <section title="Learning Probes">
      <p>"What would you do differently if you faced this again?"</p>
      <p>"What did you learn from this experience?"</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Complete vs. Incomplete Response Patterns">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Complete STAR: "When the migration project fell 3 weeks behind (S), I was responsible for unblocking the backend team's dependency on the data model changes (T). I held daily standups with the data team, reprioritized 4 schema changes to unblock the critical path, and shipped a compatibility shim that let both teams work in parallel (A). We recovered 2 of the 3 weeks and launched within 1 week of the original date; the shim became a pattern two other teams adopted (R)."</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <note>Missing Action: "The project was falling behind, so our team fixed the dependency issues and we hit the deadline." No personal contribution visible; probe required: "What specifically did you do to fix the dependency issues?"</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <note>Missing Result: "I led a cross-functional team and we worked really hard on the migration." No outcome; probe required: "What was the result of the migration? Did you hit the deadline? What changed for the users?"</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <note>Hypothetical answer: "I would approach a situation like that by first aligning stakeholders, then setting up a project plan..." The question asked for a past example. Probe: "Can you give me a specific situation where you actually did this?"</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
