<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-question-bank" title="STAR Question Bank by Competency">
  <summary>Behavioral interview questions organized by five core competencies: leadership, problem-solving, communication, collaboration, and adaptability.</summary>

  <section title="Leadership">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use leadership questions for any role where the candidate will influence, direct, or develop others; do not assume leadership only applies to management titles.</statement>
      <rationale>Individual contributors lead without authority (technical decisions, driving standards, unblocking teammates). Leadership questions reveal influence mechanisms, not just direct-report management.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you led a team through a significant change."</item>
      <item>"Describe a situation where you had to motivate an underperforming team member."</item>
      <item>"Give an example of when you made an unpopular decision and how you handled the pushback."</item>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you delegated an important task. What did you delegate and why?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Problem-Solving">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer problem-solving questions where the candidate had incomplete information or time pressure; easy problems with clear solutions produce undifferentiated responses.</statement>
      <rationale>Problem-solving under ambiguity is the most differentiating signal for IC and manager roles. Questions about "a complex problem" without constraints invite retrospective polishing; adding "with incomplete information" or "under pressure" reduces the ability to construct a generic answer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>"Describe a complex problem you solved at work."</item>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you had to make an important decision with incomplete information."</item>
      <item>"Give an example of when you identified a problem before others on the team noticed it."</item>
      <item>"Describe a time you had to troubleshoot a critical issue under time pressure."</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Communication">
    <list>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you had to deliver difficult feedback or news to someone."</item>
      <item>"Describe a situation where you had to persuade someone to change their position."</item>
      <item>"Give an example of when you had to explain something complex to a non-technical audience."</item>
      <item>"Tell me about a miscommunication that caused a problem. How did you resolve it?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Collaboration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include at least one conflict or disagreement question in every behavioral loop; candidates who only describe smooth collaboration have not been stress-tested on the most predictive dimension.</statement>
      <rationale>How candidates describe conflict reveals their conflict resolution style, attribution tendencies (self-blame vs. other-blame), and ability to sustain relationships under stress — all strong predictors of team performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>"Describe a successful cross-functional project you worked on. What made it succeed?"</item>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you had a conflict with a colleague or stakeholder. How did you handle it?"</item>
      <item>"Give an example of when you had to work with someone whose working style differed significantly from yours."</item>
      <item>"Describe how you built a working relationship with a key stakeholder who was initially skeptical."</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Adaptability">
    <list>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you had to adapt to a major change in your role, team, or company direction."</item>
      <item>"Describe a situation where priorities suddenly shifted and you had to pivot your work."</item>
      <item>"Give an example of when you had to learn something new quickly under pressure."</item>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you failed at something important. What did you do, and what did you learn?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
