<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-venn-model" title="Venn Model: Overlapping Roles in AI-Era Product Teams">
  <summary>Describes the shift from relay-race handoffs to overlapping Venn diagram teams, the new PM skillset required in 2026, and cross-functional expectations per role.</summary>

  <section title="Traditional vs. AI-Era PM Skillset">
    <p>Traditional PM skills: write specs, own roadmap, manage stakeholders, prioritize features. AI-era PM additionally requires: speak design fluently, understand data deeply (write SQL), know how models work, have a credible view on distribution and pricing strategy.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Write every PM job description as "primary lens (product strategy) + 3 fluencies (data, design, AI) + 1 specialist depth + explicit non-goals" rather than a flat skill list.</statement>
      <rationale>A flat skill list produces shallow generalism and fails to encode where the PM does NOT own depth; the T-shape with explicit non-goals prevents PM burnout from absorbing every discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Team Ratio Evolution">
    <p>Traditional ratio: 1 PM to 4-8 engineers. AI-era ratio: 2 PMs to 1 engineer (Andrew Ng observation). This holds only when the engineer is heavily AI-augmented — track agent-assisted velocity separately before changing the ratio. The bottleneck shifts to discovery, evals, and prioritization — all PM work.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the 2:1 PM:Engineer ratio as a hypothesis per team, not an industry benchmark; validate against actual agent-assisted engineering throughput before any hiring decision.</statement>
      <rationale>The ratio was one observation from one operator; applying it without measuring current agent-assisted velocity risks over-hiring PMs and under-building the product.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cross-Functional Expectations">
    <p>Role expectations in AI-era teams: PM — speak design, understand data, know AI basics; Designer — understand constraints, track activation metrics, own one funnel; Engineer — join discovery, talk to customers; Data — participate in product decisions, not just supply numbers.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every "PM speaks design" expectation with a designer-side blurring expectation; one-sided blurring breeds resentment and burns out the PM.</statement>
      <rationale>The Venn model describes mutual overlap, not PM absorption of all disciplines; unilateral blurring turns the PM into a permanent integrator with no leverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Specialist Retention">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Full blurring expectations on deep domains (security, accessibility, ML eval, monetization) with no specialist backstop.</description>
      <reason>Full blurring is an anti-pattern in deep domains; keep one depth specialist PM per critical surface as the audit backstop — the Venn model does not mean every PM must be equally broad in every area.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using the Venn model as a hiring filter that shuts out specialists (deep researcher, deep platform PM, deep growth PM).</description>
      <reason>Skill-blurring expectations in JDs covertly reject candidates the team actually needs; label specialist roles explicitly rather than requiring generalism that doesn't exist in the market.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
