<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-overlap-governance" title="Overlap Zone Governance and Agent Constraints">
  <summary>Defines DRI assignment rules for PM-vs-X overlap zones, agent role constraints, the quarterly audit cadence, and human-in-the-loop checkpoints.</summary>

  <section title="DRI Assignment Per Overlap Zone">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name exactly one human PM DRI for each overlap zone (PM/design, PM/growth, PM/engineer, PM/data, PM/eval); agents fill the zone but only the PM closes decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>A zone without a DRI becomes a place where decisions stall instead of accelerate — the Venn overlap is only productive when the convergence point is a named human with decision authority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Document the DRI assignment in the PM job description, not in tribal knowledge; it must survive PM turnover.</statement>
      <rationale>Undocumented DRI assignments disappear when the PM leaves; the next PM inherits ambiguity and re-creates the handoff gaps the Venn model was designed to eliminate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Role Constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Constrain agent personas via tool allow-lists: faion-mvp-scope-analyzer-agent must not have Edit permissions on source files; PM-vs-engineer overlap must not collapse at the file level.</statement>
      <rationale>An agent given the PM JD plus repo access will silently rewrite code in the PM-vs-engineer overlap zone; tool allow-lists are the only reliable constraint, not prompt instructions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use faion-brainstorm to fan out persona-flavored agents (PM-agent, designer-agent, growth-agent, eng-agent) on the same problem in parallel, then converge in a PM-DRI session.</statement>
      <rationale>Parallel role-persona agents produce contradictions; without a human PM-DRI to converge, the PRD ships the loudest agent's recommendation — the diverge-converge structure forces explicit resolution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent-driven PM evaluations rating PM data fluency from PRDs used as performance inputs.</description>
      <reason>LLMs are biased toward verbose writers and score calibration against PRD length, not insight; use as a discussion seed only, never as a performance or leveling input.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Quarterly Scope Audit">
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-audit PM scope quarterly with faion-improver; blurred PM roles drift back to delivery-brokering under deadline pressure.</statement>
      <rationale>Scope drift is invisible without measurement; the quarterly audit forces the conversation about where the PM actually spent time vs. the Venn target, using commit-author and ticket-assignee data as ground truth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use commit-author and Linear/Jira-assignee distribution as the truth signal for current PM scope; self-reported scope in surveys is systematically wrong by approximately 30%.</statement>
      <rationale>PMs systematically under-report time spent on delivery brokering and over-report time on discovery; objective data from git and trackers corrects this bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/pm-scope-audit.sh">Emit PM ticket-type distribution from Linear (discovery vs. delivery vs. handoff)</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-the-Loop Checkpoints">
    <list>
      <item>PM-DRI assignment per overlap zone — before any agent pair runs on a shared problem.</item>
      <item>Approval of any PM JD rewrite generated by an agent.</item>
      <item>Explicit sign-off on PM:Engineer ratio change before any hiring action.</item>
      <item>PM review of every eval set drafted by an agent before it enters a test suite.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
