<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="flexibility-efficiency">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Design must serve both novice and expert users. Accelerators (keyboard shortcuts, batch operations, command palettes, customization) speed up expert workflows while remaining invisible to novices. A command palette is the single best surface for making accelerators discoverable.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>keyboard-shortcuts</tag>
      <tag>accelerators</tag>
      <tag>usability</tag>
      <tag>heuristic-7</tag>
      <tag>power-users</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Flexibility and Efficiency of Use</title>

    <summary>Nielsen's Usability Heuristic #7: design must serve both novice and expert users. Accelerators (keyboard shortcuts, batch operations, command palettes, customization) speed up expert workflows while remaining invisible to novices. A command palette (Ctrl+K / Cmd+K) is the single best surface for making accelerators discoverable to both user types.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Interfaces designed only for novices frustrate power users who repeat the same actions daily. Interfaces designed only for experts overwhelm newcomers. The novice/expert spectrum is the most consistent source of usability complaints in productivity software; serving both requires layered affordances.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Auditing a feature spec or UI for missing keyboard shortcuts, batch operations, and power-user accelerators.</item>
        <item>Reviewing shortcut schemes for consistency with platform conventions (Mac/Windows/web).</item>
        <item>Identifying progressive disclosure opportunities: hiding advanced options without affecting novice users.</item>
        <item>Code review: checking that CLI/API operations match UI operations (agent-accessibility parity).</item>
        <item>Generating a Flexibility Audit report from an action inventory.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Product serves a single narrow use case with one user type — novice/expert design is unnecessary overhead.</item>
        <item>Very early wireframing — flexibility patterns are implementation-level concerns, not concept-level.</item>
        <item>Consumer mobile apps with infrequent use — most mobile users are perpetual novices; keyboard shortcuts do not apply.</item>
        <item>When the bottleneck is latency, not interaction speed — shortcuts do not help if actions are slow.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="user-spectrum">
      <p>The interface must serve: novice (occasional users, need guided paths), intermediate (regular users, learning accelerators), power users (daily use, need shortcuts and automation). Design layers for all three simultaneously.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Implement a command palette (Ctrl+K / Cmd+K) as the single discoverability surface for all shortcuts.</statement>
        <rationale>A command palette serves novice (can search for actions) and expert (can type known shortcut) users from the same UI surface; it is the most efficient single investment in flexibility.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="keyboard-shortcuts">
      <rule>
        <statement>Show keyboard shortcuts in menu items and tooltips; shortcuts that are not discoverable do not exist for most users.</statement>
        <rationale>Undiscoverable shortcuts are used only by users who read documentation; visible shortcuts in context menus teach users passively during normal use.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never override Ctrl+W, Ctrl+N, Ctrl+T, or Ctrl+F in a web application.</statement>
        <rationale>These browser-native shortcuts (close tab, new window, new tab, find) are deeply ingrained; overriding them creates severe friction and breaks platform expectations.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Layered accessibility: Level 1 = menu item (visible to all); Level 2 = keyboard shortcut shown in menu; Level 3 = expert knows by heart. All three levels from the same menu item.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Figma: Cmd+/ opens quick actions (command palette), showing all shortcuts with labels">
        <note>New users discover shortcuts passively; experts use them daily.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Complex dashboard with no keyboard shortcuts, requiring mouse navigation for every action">
        <note>Power users forced into slow click-only workflows daily.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="progressive-disclosure">
      <rule>
        <statement>Expose the 3-5 most-used settings immediately; place the remaining 80% behind an "Advanced" toggle.</statement>
        <rationale>Showing all settings at once overwhelms novice users; hiding primary settings frustrates experts. The 80/20 split satisfies both.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="batch-operations">
      <rule>
        <statement>For each action that affects a single item, design a batch variant as an accelerator layer.</statement>
        <rationale>Single-item actions work for novices; batch operations unlock expert-level efficiency for high-volume workflows without adding complexity to the basic flow.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="platform-convention-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Follow platform shortcut conventions; validate agent shortcut recommendations against the specific framework and browser environment.</statement>
        <rationale>Shortcut conflicts with browser/OS defaults (Ctrl+W, Ctrl+F) create severe friction; agent recommendations must be verified against target platform before implementation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Compute segment results only for pre-specified segments — post-hoc shortcut adoption analysis inflates false positives.</statement>
        <rationale>Shortcut usage varies by user type; analyzing only segments that look good post-hoc misrepresents adoption.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="measuring-efficiency">
      <p>Metrics to track: task completion time by user experience level, shortcut usage vs. mouse-click ratio per action, customization adoption rate (% who change defaults), error rate by user experience level, time on task over multiple sessions (learning curve slope).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Track keyboard vs. mouse event source per action before investing in additional shortcuts.</statement>
        <rationale>If 95% of users use mouse for an action, keyboard shortcut investment has low ROI; data-driven shortcut prioritization is more effective than comprehensive coverage.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Expert-only interface — all options always visible, no progressive disclosure.</description>
        <reason>Overwhelming novice users causes abandonment before they reach the point of becoming regular users; progressive disclosure is not optional for complex tools.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Novice-only interface — no accelerators, every action requires full guided flow.</description>
        <reason>Power users who repeat the same guided flow dozens of times daily experience significant productivity loss and frustration.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Over-customization — too many configuration options confuse users.</description>
        <reason>Customization beyond the 20% of settings users actually change adds cognitive load without benefit; limit customization to high-frequency actions and layout.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-usage-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>PM or lead must approve power-user feature recommendations before implementation; agent does not account for build complexity or support burden.</statement>
        <rationale>Custom shortcuts, saved layouts, and command palettes have significant implementation cost; agent recommendations are feature ideas, not implementation decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Filter agent-generated command palette action lists for internal or admin-only actions before exposing to end users.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent may include operations from the full action inventory without distinguishing between user-facing and admin actions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/flexibility-audit.md" purpose="Audit table: action × shortcut/multi-path/batch/customization + recommendations"/>
      <template path="templates/find-shortcuts.sh" purpose="Bash script to extract all keyboard event listeners from a JS/TS codebase"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/keyboard-accessibility/"/>
      <link href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2015/05/keyboard-accessibility/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
