<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-dashboard-rules" title="Reporting Dashboard Rules">
  <summary>Rules for dashboard setup, data quality validation, report schema design, and Slack delivery constraints.</summary>

  <section title="Data Quality">
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate data before sending any report. If committed issues = 0, the sprint query likely failed — send an error alert, not a 0% completion report. If velocity data is unavailable, state "data unavailable" explicitly rather than showing 0.</statement>
      <rationale>Technically correct but contextually misleading reports (0% because of a query failure) erode trust in automated reporting. Recipients will stop reading the reports within weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Dashboard data is only as clean as the underlying PM data. Before automating reports, audit PM data quality: are all sprint issues estimated? Are statuses current? Are done issues actually marked Done? Fix data quality issues before building dashboards — automation amplifies existing problems.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated reports surface data quality problems to stakeholders at scale. A dashboard reporting inflated velocity because of uncleared "Done" issues does more harm than no dashboard.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not infer project health from a single metric. A sprint with 90% completion but 10 scope-added issues mid-sprint is not actually healthy. Combine completion rate, scope creep (issues added after Day 2), and blocked item count as minimum health indicators.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-metric thresholds create false positive health reports that undermine the value of dashboards over time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Report Schema">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define a fixed report schema before automating. Every automated report must include: status (On Track/At Risk/Off Track), the metric thresholds that determine status (On Track = completion &gt;= 85%, At Risk = 70-84%, Off Track = &lt;70%), a link to the live dashboard, and archival path for the generated report.</statement>
      <rationale>Ad-hoc report formats generate "what does this number mean?" questions from recipients. Fixed thresholds make status classifications auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Archive every generated report as a file (Notion page, S3 object, GitHub issue comment, or local file) before delivery. Slack message history is ephemeral — archived reports enable trend analysis and dispute resolution.</statement>
      <rationale>Reports that exist only in Slack are inaccessible after 30 days (free plan) or when searching for specific historical data. Archival creates a queryable record.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Slack Delivery">
    <rule>
      <statement>Slack Block Kit messages have a 3001-character limit per block. Reports with large tables must be chunked into multiple blocks or truncated with a "see full report" link to the archived version.</statement>
      <rationale>Messages exceeding the block limit are silently truncated by the Slack API without error. Recipients receive incomplete data without knowing it was truncated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Scheduled reports sent to Slack lose readership within 2-4 weeks if signal-to-noise is poor. Start with weekly cadence, not daily. Include a link to the live dashboard in every automated message. Remove or simplify reports that get zero interaction after 4 consecutive sends.</statement>
      <rationale>Slack notification fatigue is the most common cause of automated report abandonment. High signal-to-noise requires pruning metrics that recipients do not act on.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/weekly-status-report.md">Weekly status report template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/sprint-report.md">Sprint report template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/jira-metrics-fetcher.py">Python script for Jira metrics and Slack delivery</reference>
</text>
