<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-writing-rules" title="Email Writing Rules and Metrics">
  <summary>Per-email structural rules, subject line constraints, CTA policy, and performance targets per email.</summary>

  <section title="Email Structure Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each onboarding email must contain exactly one CTA — one button or one link, never both.</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple CTAs split attention and reduce completion. The single-action constraint forces clarity about the email's purpose.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Write body copy at 3-5 sentences maximum in short paragraphs (1-2 sentences each).</statement>
      <rationale>Onboarding emails compete with product notifications; walls of text get skipped. Short paragraphs signal respect for user time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Write from a named person (founder or CS rep), not from a company account, during the onboarding phase.</statement>
      <rationale>Personal tone outperforms branded templates in onboarding; plain text often outperforms HTML for the first 14 days.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Subject: 4-7 words, get opened</item>
      <item>Preview text: 40-60 chars, enhances open rate</item>
      <item>Opening: 1-2 sentences, personal connection</item>
      <item>Body: 3-5 sentences, single message</item>
      <item>CTA: one action, button or link (not both)</item>
      <item>PS: optional secondary info (reply invitation works well here)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Performance Targets">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track email-received-to-action-completed conversion per email, not just open or click rate.</statement>
      <rationale>Open and click metrics measure email quality; the activation conversion metric measures whether the email achieves its actual goal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Open rate target: 50%+ (below → fix subject line)</item>
      <item>Click rate target: 10%+ (below → fix CTA or copy)</item>
      <item>Conversion target: 5%+ (below → reduce friction in product)</item>
      <item>Unsubscribe cap: &lt;0.5% (above → check frequency)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="A/B Testing Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>A/B test subject lines in the first 4 hours post-send; do not run subject line tests on emails older than 24 hours.</statement>
      <rationale>Onboarding email recency is critical — stale tests are not representative of how current subscribers respond to the trigger context.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="ESP Integration Notes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Specify the ESP (Customer.io, ConvertKit, ActiveCampaign) in every agent prompt producing email copy — personalization token syntax varies by platform.</statement>
      <rationale>Customer.io uses {{customer.first_name}}; ConvertKit uses {{subscriber.first_name}}. Wrong tokens produce broken personalization silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <note>Trigger conditions described in natural language must be translated into ESP-specific automation logic by a human — never deploy agent-described conditions directly to an ESP without human configuration.</note>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/email-welcome.txt">Welcome email template — first action, reply-friendly</reference>
  <reference path="templates/email-nudge.txt">Stuck-user nudge — blocker removal, Day 2</reference>
  <reference path="templates/email-celebration.txt">Completion celebration — milestone + next step</reference>
  <reference path="templates/email-personal-outreach.txt">High-value signup outreach — Day 10</reference>
  <reference path="templates/email-trial-end.txt">Trial ending — activated user conversion</reference>
</text>
