<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="growth-onboarding-emails Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for growth-onboarding-emails as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Sending more than one email per day during onboarding.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Frequency above 1/day causes unsubscribe spikes that hurt overall deliverability, not just the onboarding sequence. Deliverability damage is disproportionate to the marginal activation gain.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Including multiple CTAs in a single onboarding email (e.g., "Complete setup" AND "Explore features" AND "Invite a teammate").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multiple CTAs split user attention. The user chooses nothing or the wrong thing. One email, one action.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Using only time-based triggers (Day 1, Day 3, Day 7) with no behavioral conditions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Time-based emails reach activated and inactive users identically. An activated user receives a "still getting started?" email after completing setup — undermining trust.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Using generic copy not tied to segment or trigger context (e.g., "Here are some tips!" to all users regardless of their activity).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generic copy signals the email was not written for the recipient. Personalization based on actual behavior (even "I see you created a project") doubles reply rate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping the escalation path — no emails for users who take no action after Day 2.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Users who get stuck silently churn. Without escalation, the sequence abandons users at the exact moment they need help most.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Using personalization tokens without verifying the ESP's event tracking is reliably firing them (e.g., "You created your first project!" when the event is not reliably tracked).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Broken personalization is worse than no personalization — it signals a broken product or broken communication system.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Automating the Day 10 personal outreach email at full scale without a human review step.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Personal outreach emails feel authentic only if they can be followed up. A fully automated "book a call" email with no human behind it damages trust when the user tries to reply.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
