<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Evaluation Process, TCO, and Decision Framework">
  <summary>PoC protocol, TCO calculation structure, decision matrix weights, and agent gotchas for PM tool selection.</summary>

  <section title="Proof of Concept Protocol">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score from team-measured PoC data, not vendor marketing; require a vendor-docs URL for every claimed integration.</statement>
      <rationale>Vendor claims systematically overstate usability; agents hallucinate integrations that do not exist. Only measured data is decision-grade.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>Duration: 2 weeks minimum (scaling pain only surfaces at >10k issues; note this limitation)</item>
      <item>Participants: 1 PM representative, 2 developer representatives, 1 manager representative</item>
      <item>Test scenarios: create project structure, import sample data, setup sprint, configure automations, test integrations, generate reports</item>
      <item>Measured outputs: setup time (hours), daily workflow time (minutes), feature coverage (%), team satisfaction (1-10), performance (1-10)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="TCO Structure">
    <p>Total cost of ownership must include three categories; migration and custom-reporting costs almost always exceed projections.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Direct costs: license per user × user count × 12 months, add-ons, support tier</item>
      <item>Indirect costs: implementation (setup hours × hourly rate), migration (consultant days × day rate), training (sessions × cost), ongoing admin (hours/month × rate × 12)</item>
      <item>Hidden costs: productivity loss during transition, integration development, custom reporting, abandoned workflows</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture migration cost at item-count granularity (#issues, #automations, #integrations) before signing; line-item estimation prevents systematic undercount.</statement>
      <rationale>High-level "migration cost" estimates routinely miss custom automation conversion and historical data queries; item-count forces the evaluator to enumerate what must move.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Decision Matrix">
    <p>Five weighted categories for final tool selection. Weights below are defaults; adjust per team before evaluation begins.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Technical fit (30%): feature coverage, integration capabilities, API quality, performance</item>
      <item>Usability (25%): learning curve, daily efficiency, mobile experience, documentation quality</item>
      <item>Strategic fit (20%): vendor stability, roadmap alignment, community ecosystem, scalability</item>
      <item>Cost (15%): license cost, implementation cost, ongoing admin, 3-year TCO</item>
      <item>Risk (10%): migration complexity, vendor lock-in, data portability, support quality</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent favors newer or more frequently mentioned online tools.</description>
      <reason>Recency bias from training data; require PoC measurements from the actual team, not sentiment from internet discussions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent runs comparison and recommendation in one prompt.</description>
      <reason>Produces anchored outputs; separate steps: (1) fill matrix, (2) forced rank, (3) draft recommendation, (4) human review.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Pricing data scraped from vendor sites without checking recency.</description>
      <reason>Pricing changes frequently; require explicit date-checked URLs and mark cells older than 12 months as STALE.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/tco.yaml">TCO calculation template with direct, indirect, and hidden cost categories</reference>
  <reference path="templates/weighted_score.py">Computes weighted totals from a YAML scorecard</reference>
</text>
