<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Fixed-Price vs T&amp;M CR Pricing Playbook Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules cross the BA / procurement boundary and produce a defensible CR pricing decision in either contract regime.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every CR is classified at intake by contract type before any sizing: fixed-price (FP) → "margin event, mechanism = addendum or absorb", T&amp;M → "velocity event, mechanism = re-baseline burn-down". The classification is stamped at the top of the CR memo; sizing must not start until the classification is recorded.</statement>
      <rationale source="Change requests behave radically differently under fixed-price vs T&amp;M">Skipping the regime check leads to BAs accidentally treating an FP change as a velocity update, which means the margin is silently eaten until the project goes red weeks later. Stamping the regime first prevents the category error.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Under fixed-price, CRs are bucketed by size against the remaining undrawn contingency: ≤ 25% of contingency → candidate for absorb; 25-75% → candidate for scope-swap (drop equivalent-value scope to make room); &gt; 75% or contingency exhausted → mandatory paid addendum. The bucket determines the default action; the BA may override only with a written reason approved by the vendor sponsor.</statement>
      <rationale source="When to absorb, when to negotiate addendum, how to price risk">Absorb-or-addendum cannot be vibes-based; tying it to remaining contingency keeps the vendor solvent and the client relationship intact. The override clause acknowledges that exceptional cases exist but forces them to be written down.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Under T&amp;M, no CR is "absorbed" — every CR triggers a re-baseline of the burn-down and a written impact memo to the client showing forecasted hours delta, revised end date, and whether the new total exceeds any cap (not-to-exceed clause). The BA explicitly flags any CR that pushes the engagement above 90% of NTE within the next two sprints.</statement>
      <rationale source="T&amp;M change behaviour: every CR is a velocity event">Under T&amp;M the client pays for the change automatically, so the failure mode is not margin loss but invisible cap-creep. The 90%-of-NTE alarm is what stops a polite series of small CRs from arriving at the contract ceiling without warning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Residual risk is priced explicitly, not folded into the headline number. The CR memo carries a "risk addendum" line that names the uncertainty (e.g. third-party API completeness, regulator interpretation, data-volume guess) and applies a percentage uplift bounded by category: low-risk integration 5%, medium-risk regulatory or third-party 10-20%, high-risk data-quality or scope-fuzzy 20-40%. The buyer sees the uplift line by line.</statement>
      <rationale source="How to price risk on a CR at the BA/procurement boundary">Hidden risk loading destroys trust when delivery comes in under estimate (vendor looks padded) or over (client refuses to pay). Disclosed loading converts CR negotiation from theatre to grown-up conversation about who carries what risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The handoff to procurement is a single artefact (the CR options matrix) that contains: classification (FP vs T&amp;M), bucket (absorb / swap / addendum / defer), three options with priced uplift and residual risk, and the recommended option with a one-paragraph rationale. The BA never sends procurement a chat log or a meeting recap as a substitute; the artefact is the contract surface.</statement>
      <rationale source="Crosses BA / procurement boundary which currently has no bridge content">Procurement people work from documents, not from BA narrative. A single artefact lets them sign or push back inside their own workflow; anything less stalls the addendum cycle and inflates the implementation lag.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical example">
    <example type="good" title="A scope-fuzzy fixed-price CR midway through delivery">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Intake stamp:
  CR-019  contract_type: fixed-price  remaining_contingency: €12k

Sizing:
  Option A (absorb):   estimated cost €7k = 58% of contingency
  Option B (swap):     drop "admin export to CSV" feature, gain €6k room, then absorb
  Option C (addendum): full paid CR €11k + 15% risk addendum = €12.65k

Bucket decision:
  Size at 58% of contingency → in the 25-75% band → scope-swap candidate.
  BA recommends Option B (swap) with override rationale: "client already uses
   manual CSV; loss is acceptable, preserves contingency for two upcoming
   regulator-driven CRs identified in last week's discovery."

Handoff to procurement:
  artefact = CR-019-options-matrix.pdf
  attachments: revised SOW with feature swap, signed by client sponsor

Result:
  Margin protected, contingency preserved, no addendum needed,
  buyer sees the exact trade and approves in 2 days instead of 2 weeks.
]]></code>
      <note>The regime check forced the right framing; the bucket forced the right default; the artefact handed procurement a signable document instead of a meeting summary.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
