<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-platform-observability" title="Platform Engineering and Observability Trends">
  <summary>Platform engineering growth trajectory, portal vs platform distinction, golden paths; OpenTelemetry dominance, three pillars plus profiling, and shift-left observability.</summary>

  <section title="Platform Engineering">
    <p>Platform team adoption: 45% of large orgs in 2022 → 80% projected by 2026 (Gartner). The driver is developer experience — platform teams reduce cognitive load by providing "golden paths" that make the right thing easy.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Distinguish platform (backend system) from portal (frontend UI); investing in portal without platform produces expensive dashboards with no underlying capability.</statement>
      <rationale>A common mistake: teams build Backstage (portal) without the underlying platform (Kubernetes, Terraform, CI/CD pipelines). The portal can only surface what the platform provides.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Platform: Kubernetes, Terraform — provisions, deploys, orchestrates</item>
      <item>Portal: Backstage, Port — discovers, accesses, visualizes</item>
    </list>
    <p>Golden paths map directly to SDD constitution.md: define the paved road once, enforce it in quality gates. Metrics that matter: time to first commit, deployment frequency, lead time for changes, mean time to recovery.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="OpenTelemetry and Observability">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with OTel traces on agent task boundaries (start/end/error) before adding metrics and logs — traces provide the most value for debugging agent failures.</statement>
      <rationale>Traces show the execution path through a system; for debugging agent failures, seeing which steps ran, in what order, and where they failed is more valuable than aggregate metrics or unstructured log lines.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>OpenTelemetry is the #2 CNCF project (after Kubernetes) and the de-facto standard for vendor-neutral telemetry as of 2025.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Logs: event records</item>
      <item>Metrics: measurements over time</item>
      <item>Traces: request flow across services</item>
      <item>Profiles: resource consumption (added 2025)</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <item>OTel collector patterns:</item>
      <item>Agent: per-instance, low latency</item>
      <item>Gateway: centralized, easier ops</item>
      <item>Hierarchical: agent + gateway combined (recommended for agent pipelines)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply shift-left observability: instrument at every stage (dev → test → stage → prod), not only in production.</statement>
      <rationale>Observability gaps in dev and test environments mean failures are first detected in production. Shift-left observability catches performance regressions and error patterns in earlier, cheaper-to-fix stages.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
