<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Core VUI Design Principles Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules anchoring the core-vui-design-principles methodology, each grounded in a source.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="single-idea-per-response" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A spoken response MUST convey a single primary idea; multi-idea responses MUST be split or offered as branching follow-ups.</statement>
      <rationale source="NN/g voice interaction research">Working memory in spoken-mode is shorter than visual; multi-idea responses lose listeners after ~15 seconds.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="fifteen-second-ceiling" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A single uninterrupted spoken response MUST NOT exceed ~15 seconds; longer content MUST be chunked with `Would you like to hear more?` style branches.</statement>
      <rationale source="Voice design literature">User attention drops sharply past 15 sec; chunking with consent preserves engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="barge-in-supported" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Runtime MUST honour barge-in (user can interrupt mid-prompt); silent forced-listen prompts are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Alexa + Google HIG">Forced listen breaks turn-taking convention and frustrates frequent users.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="explicit-context-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Multi-turn dialogs MUST declare an explicit context window (turns remembered + duration); silent reset is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Conversational UX best practices">Users build mental models around remembered context; silent reset breaks them.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="no-verbatim-repeat-on-retry" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>On error retry, the prompt MUST vary (rephrase + add example) — verbatim repeat is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Error handling in VUI literature">Verbatim repeat sounds robotic and rarely fixes the underlying confusion.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Skip-If preconditions hold, the methodology MUST be skipped and the caller routed to the linked alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="self">Applying this machinery to the wrong workflow burns tokens without producing a usable artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
