<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Three Core VUI Design Principles with Examples">
  <summary>The three foundational VUI principles — simplicity, natural conversation, and context awareness — with good/bad dialogue examples.</summary>

  <section title="Principle 1: Simplicity and Clarity">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every agent turn must convey one piece of information or request one piece of input; split compound responses across turns.</statement>
      <rationale>Listening comprehension is harder than reading; users cannot re-read a voice response, so each turn must be immediately parseable in working memory.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[System: "Your order is confirmed for delivery tomorrow."]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[System: "Your order has been successfully processed and scheduled for
delivery on January 20th at a time between 9 AM and 5 PM in your
local timezone. You will receive a confirmation email shortly."]]></code>
      <note>Too much information in a single turn; the user cannot retain all of it and cannot re-listen.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Principle 2: Natural Conversation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design agent turns to follow natural conversational turn-taking: acknowledge the user's input briefly, then provide the response or request, without robotic enumerations.</statement>
      <rationale>Users calibrate their interaction style to the agent's tone; robotic responses trigger a robotic, stilted interaction from the user, increasing ASR errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[User: "What's the weather?"
VUI:  "It's 72 and sunny. Want to know about tomorrow?"]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[User: "What's the weather?"
VUI:  "The current temperature is 72 degrees Fahrenheit with sunny
conditions. Humidity is 45 percent. Wind speed is 8 miles per hour."]]></code>
      <note>Reciting all available data fields is a database-readout pattern, not a conversation.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM over-acknowledgment: "Sure! I can absolutely do that for you! Let me check that right away!"</description>
      <reason>Filler acknowledgment inflates latency — every word adds ~50ms TTS overhead — and feels sycophantic. One-word acknowledgment ("Got it.") or no acknowledgment before the answer is preferred.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Principle 3: Context Awareness">
    <rule>
      <statement>The agent must correctly resolve pronoun references from the immediately preceding user turn without asking for clarification more than once per session.</statement>
      <rationale>Users expect the agent to understand "it", "that", "the one I mentioned" — repeated clarification requests signal that the agent forgot context and are perceived as system failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Remember previous conversation turns within the session to resolve follow-up questions.</item>
      <item>Understand ellipsis and pronoun references ("And tomorrow?" after a weather query).</item>
      <item>Adapt to stated user preferences within the session (e.g., user said "I prefer Celsius" → use Celsius for all subsequent queries).</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Context window exhaustion causes the agent to ask the user to repeat information already provided earlier in the session.</description>
      <reason>Context limits (~30k tokens for Realtime API) are a design constraint; the session structure must proactively summarize and compress prior context before limits are hit.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
