<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="VUI Principle Rules and Known Failure Modes">
  <summary>Testable rules derived from the three VUI principles, with LLM-specific failure modes and latency constraints.</summary>

  <section title="Testable Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>No agent turn may exceed 25 words unless the content is a required legal disclosure; flag any turn over 25 words for simplification review.</statement>
      <rationale>25 words is approximately the working memory capacity for spoken information; longer turns cause information loss and user re-prompting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not include more than one proactive offer per turn (e.g., "Want to know about tomorrow?" is one offer; adding "Shall I also check traffic?" in the same turn is too many choices).</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple simultaneous offers force the user to hold all options in working memory; one clear offer per turn keeps the conversation linear.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Write acceptance criteria for voice flows that include a latency gate: total round-trip must be under 1.5 seconds; streams must produce first audio within 0.8 seconds.</statement>
      <rationale>Users interpret gaps beyond 1.5 s as system failure; without a latency gate in acceptance criteria the constraint is never tested.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM-Specific Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM over-acknowledges every user input with affirmations ("Great!", "Of course!", "Sure thing!").</description>
      <reason>Each filler word adds TTS latency and signals non-human origin; instruct the model explicitly to omit acknowledgment before answering.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Simplicity principle applied to chat or visual copy, producing text that is too terse for reading contexts.</description>
      <reason>VUI simplicity rules are calibrated for audio processing, not reading; a 10-word sentence that is ideal for voice can be insufficient for a UI label.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent applies these principles to a mandatory regulatory disclosure script (banking, healthcare).</description>
      <reason>Regulatory disclosures must be verbatim; "natural conversation" and "simplicity" cannot override legal text requirements.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Cultural and Linguistic Scope">
    <p>These principles are derived from US English voice UX research. Conversational norms, turn-taking conventions, and acceptable response lengths vary significantly across languages and cultures. Apply only after localization review for non-English deployments.</p>
  </section>
</text>
