<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Scope Drift Metrics — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every scope-drift dashboard must satisfy. The rules guarantee the metrics catch real drift instead of producing alarm fatigue or false comfort.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-five-metric-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The dashboard MUST compute all five named metrics nightly. Cherry-picking a subset is forbidden because each metric catches a different drift pattern.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI scope-performance research; field experience with single-metric dashboards">CR-volume catches explicit changes. AC-rewrite catches sneaky changes inside accepted tickets. Story-split catches estimation drift. Churn ratio catches add-and-delete cycles. Parking-lot age catches the demo-creep backlog. A dashboard missing any one has a blind spot the project will eventually fall into.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-baseline-relative-thresholds" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Thresholds (green / amber / red) MUST be expressed relative to the signed baseline (e.g. "AC-rewrite rate exceeds 15% of baseline AC count per sprint"), not absolute. Absolute thresholds bias the dashboard toward project size.</statement>
      <rationale source="ratio-based performance measurement; PMBOK earned-value practice">Absolute thresholds (e.g. "≥20 CRs is red") under-warn a large project (which can absorb 20) and over-warn a small one (where 5 is catastrophic). Baseline-relative thresholds work across project sizes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-daily-refresh" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dashboard refresh cadence MUST be ≤24h. Weekly refresh is insufficient because drift accumulates within a single sprint.</statement>
      <rationale source="control-chart theory; agile reporting cadence">By the time a weekly-refresh dashboard shows red, the team has already done a week of work on uncontested-but-creep tickets. Daily refresh detects the inflection within the sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-trigger-actions-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each amber and red threshold has a named trigger action with owner and SLA. "Increase awareness" is not an action. Red triggers always route through `risk-threshold-policy`.</statement>
      <rationale source="incident-management practice; field experience with dashboards-without-actions">A dashboard without actions is decoration. The named action turns each threshold breach into a calendar event with an owner; the SLA prevents the action from being indefinitely deferred.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-dashboard-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The dashboard has exactly one named owner who reviews it daily and acknowledges amber/red signals. Unowned dashboards are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI clarity; "every dashboard needs a parent" principle">The owner converts data into decisions. Without an owner, a red signal sits visible but unacted-upon for days. The acknowledgement event also produces the audit trail for later disputes.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Metric definitions and thresholds (defaults)">
    <list>
      <item><b>CR-volume velocity</b>: count of tickets classified as CR (per `scope-change-vs-scope-creep-detection`) divided by baseline-requirement count, per sprint. Green ≤3%, amber 3-8%, red &gt;8%.</item>
      <item><b>AC-rewrite rate</b>: count of acceptance-criteria edits AFTER sprint start, divided by AC count for the sprint's tickets. Green ≤5%, amber 5-15%, red &gt;15%.</item>
      <item><b>Story-split count</b>: number of stories split mid-sprint divided by sprint story count. Green ≤5%, amber 5-15%, red &gt;15%.</item>
      <item><b>Requirement-churn ratio</b>: (added + deleted requirements over 14 days) ÷ total baseline requirements. Green ≤2%, amber 2-8%, red &gt;8%.</item>
      <item><b>Parking-lot age</b>: median age (hours) of OPEN parking-lot items. Green ≤24h, amber 24-72h, red &gt;72h.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Amber on AC-rewrite rate triggers an early conversation">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Sprint 5, day 6: AC-rewrite rate = 11% (amber threshold).
Trigger action: BA pulls the affected tickets; finds 3 stories with rewritten AC
all related to the same module (reporting). Conversation with PM:
"reporting module has unclear spec, not creep". Re-baseline conversation
scheduled within 5 days, change-control input drafted. No surprise at sprint
review.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 (metric measured), r3 (caught mid-sprint), r4 (named trigger), r5 (BA owned).</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="The dashboard nobody reads">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Dashboard exists; AC-rewrite at 22% (red) for 3 weeks; nobody acknowledged.
Sprint 8 review: 40% of stories not actually meeting AC; client refuses to
sign off; full re-baseline triggered with steering committee involvement.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r4 (no trigger action followed) and r5 (no owner) violated. The dashboard saw the drift; the project did not.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
