<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="error-prevention">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Apply six prevention strategies in order of preference — constraints, suggestions, defaults, confirmation, real-time validation, and affordances. Eliminate error-prone conditions before they occur instead of recovering afterward.</summary>
    <category>error-handling</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>error-prevention</tag>
      <tag>form-design</tag>
      <tag>input-validation</tag>
      <tag>user-experience</tag>
      <tag>heuristic-5</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Error Prevention — Nielsen Heuristic #5</title>

    <summary>Design to eliminate error-prone conditions before they occur. Apply six strategies in order of preference — constraints, suggestions, defaults, confirmation, real-time validation, and affordances. Use confirmation dialogs only for irreversible or high-consequence actions; avoid them for routine or easily reversible ones. Prevention is always cheaper than recovery: the user wastes less effort, support costs are lower, and data quality is better.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Error recovery is always more expensive than prevention: the user wastes effort, support costs rise, and data quality degrades. Prevention strategies — particularly input constraints and inline validation — interrupt errors at the point of entry rather than after form submission, reducing abandonment and the cognitive load of parsing a list of errors at the end of a long form.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing or auditing any form with consequential data (payments, account changes, orders).</item>
        <item>When form abandonment or submission error rates are high in analytics.</item>
        <item>When reviewing any destructive action (delete, cancel subscription, bulk operation) for whether it needs a confirmation step.</item>
        <item>When validating that input fields constrain or guide input to valid values only.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Do not add confirmation dialogs to routine or easily reversible actions — over-confirming trains users to dismiss dialogs without reading, defeating the purpose.</item>
        <item>Do not apply real-time validation to every field indiscriminately — aggressive inline errors before the user has finished typing increase frustration; validate on blur for most fields, on keypress only for password strength indicators.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="the-heuristic">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply Nielsen Heuristic #5: eliminate error-prone conditions or present a confirmation option before users commit to a consequential action.</statement>
        <rationale>Recovery is always more expensive than prevention — it costs user effort, time, and trust. Prevention eliminates the error path entirely; recovery only mitigates its impact.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="error-type-classification">
      <rule>
        <statement>Distinguish slips (right intention, wrong action) from mistakes (wrong intention) — they require different prevention strategies.</statement>
        <rationale>Slips are prevented by constraints and confirmation; mistakes are prevented by providing better information and guidance. Applying confirmation dialogs to slip-prone actions without addressing the underlying ambiguity only slows users down.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-1-constraints">
      <rule>
        <statement>Constrain input to valid values only — use pickers, dropdowns, and bounded fields instead of free-text fields wherever the valid value set is finite.</statement>
        <rationale>A constrained input cannot produce an invalid value; a free-text field always can. Constraints eliminate the error before it is possible to make it.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Date: use a date picker that only allows valid dates, not a text field where users type dates. Quantity: min 1, max 99 with +/- buttons, not a free numeric field. Country: dropdown of countries, not "enter country name".</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-2-smart-defaults">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pre-populate fields with the most likely correct value whenever context (location, history, profile) makes it determinable.</statement>
        <rationale>Smart defaults reduce the number of fields users must fill in and simultaneously prevent errors on those fields by providing a correct starting value that requires no change for the majority of users.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Detect user location and pre-fill country. Pre-fill today's date for current events. Remember previous selections from the user's history.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-3-inline-validation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Validate on blur for most fields; validate on keypress only for password strength and character counters. Never validate on keypress for format errors — wait until the user has finished typing.</statement>
        <rationale>Validating format errors on every keystroke (showing "invalid email" when the user has typed "us") creates false error states that frustrate before any error has actually been made.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Password field: show requirements checklist, check each as user types (8+ characters, one uppercase, one number). Email field: validate format on blur — not while typing.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-4-confirmation-dialogs">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use confirmation dialogs only for irreversible actions with significant consequences. Do not use them for routine, frequent, or easily reversible operations.</statement>
        <rationale>Overuse of confirmations trains users to dismiss them without reading. This is worse than no confirmation — users click through the dialog reflexively and still trigger the unwanted action.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Use: permanent delete, cancel subscription, bulk destructive operations.</item>
        <item>Do not use: save file, move to trash, log out, send message with undo available.</item>
      </list>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Good confirmation: "Delete 47 items permanently? This action cannot be undone. All selected files will be permanently removed." Buttons: [Cancel] [Delete 47 Items]. The button label repeats the count — users see the magnitude of what they are confirming.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-5-format-guidance">
      <rule>
        <statement>Show expected format inside or below the field before the user starts typing; auto-format as the user types for structured data like phone numbers and credit cards.</statement>
        <rationale>Users should not have to guess the format. Format shown after an error is too late — it should be visible before input begins.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prevention-by-field-type">
      <p>Text: character limits with counter, format hints, auto-complete suggestions, real-time validation on blur.</p>
      <p>Numeric: numeric keyboard on mobile, min/max constraints, increment buttons, format guidance for currency.</p>
      <p>Date: date picker (never text input), disable invalid dates, clear format display, relative dates (Today, Tomorrow).</p>
      <p>Selection: default selection when appropriate, logical ordering, search for lists over 10 items.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/error-prevention-audit.md" purpose="Audit table: field, input type, constraints, validation timing, defaults, recommendations"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/slips/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/user-errors/"/>
      <link href="https://formsthatwork.com/"/>
      <link href="https://zod.dev"/>
      <link href="https://react-hook-form.com"/>
      <ref slug="error-recovery"/>
      <ref slug="heuristic-evaluation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>