<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Requirements Documentation Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the requirements-documentation methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 1 (compose br): Draft BR (the why); reject solution-shaped phrasing.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the compose br gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 2 (derive sh): Per stakeholder group, derive SH records.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the derive sh gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 3 (decompose sr): Decompose into SR (FR + NFR); add acceptance criteria.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the decompose sr gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 4 (lint): Frontmatter, glossary links, AC presence, source citation count.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the lint gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 5 (commit): Commit to version control; tag baseline.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the commit gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for requirements-documentation do not hold, do not apply this methodology; route to an alternative as the decision tree suggests.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Methodologies misapplied to wrong contexts create overhead without value; explicit skip preserves the agent's budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
