<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="WBS Creation Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six testable rules grounding WBS Creation. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced by the decision tree.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="deliverable-orientation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every WBS node name MUST be a noun phrase (an output) — never a verb phrase (an activity). Reject names matching `^(Build|Design|Implement|Test|Code|Develop|Create) `.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI Practice Standard for Work Breakdown Structures (3rd ed.); PMBOK 7 Planning Performance Domain">Deliverable names remain stable when implementation changes; activity names do not. "User Authentication Module" survives a rewrite; "Build user authentication" does not.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="hundred-percent-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every parent MUST represent exactly 100% of its children's scope — no gaps, no overlaps. Verified by `weight_pct` summing to 100 (+/- 1%) per parent.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI WBS Practice Standard; DoD MIL-STD-881F">Gaps create forgotten work that surfaces late. Overlaps create double-counted effort and budget conflicts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="eight-eighty-sizing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Leaf work packages MUST have an effort estimate in [8, 80] hours. Outliers MUST be split (&gt; 80) or merged (&lt; 8). Tracking unit may shift the bounds, but a calibrated range must exist.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI WBS Practice Standard; PRINCE2 product-based planning">Below 8 hours, tracking overhead exceeds value. Above 80 hours, the estimate is a guess and dependencies are invisible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="mandatory-overhead-branches" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The WBS MUST include all six overhead branches: Project Management, Quality Assurance, Deployment, Documentation, Training, Transition. Missing branches are flagged as a defect, NOT silently omitted.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI cost-management knowledge area; agency P&amp;L cohort data">Overhead is 15-25% of real project effort. Agents and manual drafters systematically omit it, creating a structural budget gap.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="append-only-ids" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>WBS numeric IDs (1, 1.1, 1.1.1) are append-only. Once assigned, an ID MUST NEVER change or be reused, even after node deletion. Renumbering is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI WBS Practice Standard ID-stability guidance">Change requests, risk entries, and tasks reference WBS IDs. Renumbering breaks traceability across the entire project record.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="dictionary-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every leaf MUST have a Dictionary entry with all required fields: id, name, description (included AND excluded scope), deliverable, acceptance_criteria (observable + testable), owner (one accountable person or named team), effort_hours (8-80), dependencies (predecessor IDs).</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI WBS Practice Standard Dictionary chapter; PMBOK Scope Management knowledge area">Missing acceptance criteria make sign-off subjective. Missing exclusions cause scope creep. Missing ownership causes handoff gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
