<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="WBS Core Principles">
  <summary>The four rules that make a WBS valid: deliverable orientation, 100% rule, 8/80 leaf sizing, and mandatory overhead packages.</summary>

  <section title="Deliverable Orientation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name every WBS node as a noun (the output produced), never as a verb (the activity performed).</statement>
      <rationale>Deliverable names remain stable when implementation changes; activity names do not. "User Authentication Module" survives a rewrite; "Build user authentication" does not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Verb-based decomposition — breaks when approach changes.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1.1 Design authentication
1.2 Code authentication
1.3 Test authentication
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Deliverable-based — stable regardless of method.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1.1 Authentication Module
    1.1.1 Registration System
    1.1.2 Login / Logout
    1.1.3 Password Reset
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="100% Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every level must capture 100% of the work in its parent — no gaps, no overlaps.</statement>
      <rationale>Gaps create forgotten work that surfaces late. Overlaps create double-counted effort and budget conflicts. The rule is verified by asking: "If all children are complete, is the parent complete?"</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include the following overhead branches or flag their absence as a defect: Project Management, QA, Deployment, Documentation, Training, Transition.</statement>
      <rationale>Overhead is 15-25% of real project effort. Agents and manual drafters systematically omit it, creating a budget gap from day one.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Work Package Sizing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Leaf nodes (work packages) must have an effort estimate between 8 and 80 hours. Nodes outside this range must be split or merged.</statement>
      <rationale>Below 8 hours the tracking overhead exceeds the tracking value. Above 80 hours the estimate is a guess and dependencies are invisible. The 8/80 rule is a calibration heuristic, not a law — adjust the bounds to match your tracking unit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stop decomposing when the 8/80 rule is satisfied; more than 4 levels rarely adds estimate accuracy.</statement>
      <rationale>Deep trees create maintenance overhead and give a false sense of precision without improving schedule or cost predictability.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="ID Stability">
    <rule>
      <statement>WBS IDs are append-only: once assigned, a numeric ID (1.2.3) never changes or gets reused, even if the node is deleted.</statement>
      <rationale>Change requests, risk entries, and tasks reference WBS IDs. Renumbering breaks traceability across the whole project record.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-wbs-dictionary.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/wbs-validate.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
