<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="wbs-creation Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for wbs-creation as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>WBS without a Dictionary — just a numbered outline.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Numbers without definitions leave acceptance criteria, ownership, and scope boundaries undefined. The tree looks complete but is not actionable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Mixing WBS with schedule — adding start/end dates to nodes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The WBS answers "what"; the schedule answers "when". Mixing them creates churn when either changes independently.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Decomposing unevenly — 4 levels for development, 1 level for deployment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Uneven depth signals that some branches are under-estimated; both depth and estimate accuracy should be consistent across siblings.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs default to activity verbs; explicitly instruct "use noun phrases for deliverables".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without explicit instruction, agents generate activity-based WBS that breaks on implementation changes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents skip overhead packages (PM, QA, deploy, train) — hard-code them in the prompt as required.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents default to product deliverables; overhead must be explicitly mandated.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Decomposition often has uneven depth: backend gets 4 levels, "Marketing" stays at level 2. Force the agent to balance.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Uneven depth hides estimate errors in under-decomposed branches.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Dictionary entries get hallucinated owners and dates; force them to come from a stakeholder register and schedule input.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Made-up owners and dates destroy traceability and accountability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents inflate estimates symmetrically (everything is 40h); inject a few known-good estimates as anchors.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Anchoring prevents uniform inflation and calibrates agent estimates to real data.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Do not let agents "consolidate" leaves to fit a target count — that breaks 8/80; reject and re-prompt.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Consolidation violates 8/80 rule; agents use it to artificially meet targets.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>When converting WBS to tasks, beware ID drift: keep wbs_id field in every generated task for round-tripping.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Lost traceability between WBS and tasks makes re-planning impossible.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
