<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-enterprise-xr-rules" title="Enterprise XR — Design Rules and Use Cases">
  <summary>Core design rules for enterprise XR applications: validated use case patterns, session comfort requirements, enterprise integration and security constraints, and training interaction design.</summary>

  <section title="Enterprise Use Case Patterns">
    <list>
      <item>Training and simulation: step-by-step safety procedures, equipment operation, emergency response</item>
      <item>Remote assistance: expert guidance overlaid on worker's view via AR</item>
      <item>Digital twins: real-time 3D representation of manufacturing lines or facilities for monitoring</item>
      <item>3D data visualization: spatial analytics dashboards for complex datasets</item>
      <item>Collaboration: virtual design reviews, remote co-presence for distributed teams</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate that the chosen use case has a measurable ROI metric before committing to XR development. Common metrics: training completion rate, error rate reduction, travel cost saved, support call duration.</statement>
      <rationale>Enterprise XR projects without a defined ROI metric rarely survive past pilot; stakeholders cannot justify hardware and development costs without evidence of return.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Session Comfort for Long Use">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design for sessions of 30-90 minutes maximum without mandatory break. Incorporate in-session rest states (lower-intensity tasks, seated interactions, gaze-based fallbacks) rather than requiring headset removal.</statement>
      <rationale>Enterprise XR is used in multi-hour work contexts; headset fatigue — physical weight, eye strain, heat — is the primary reason for abandonment of otherwise successful pilots.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Avoid UI elements that require sustained arm extension above shoulder height (gorilla arm). Place interactive zones within comfortable reach: arms slightly bent, in front of the body.</statement>
      <rationale>Sustained arm elevation causes rapid muscle fatigue; interactions placed at comfortable reach extend tolerable session duration significantly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Enterprise Integration and Security">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define integration requirements for existing enterprise tools (ERP, LMS, CMMS) at the design stage. Voice or gaze-based input must accommodate workers wearing gloves or PPE.</statement>
      <rationale>XR systems that cannot integrate with existing workflows are rejected by IT departments and require parallel data entry — eliminating efficiency gains.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Specify data classification for all content displayed in XR (e.g., proprietary schematics, patient records). Apply appropriate encryption, access controls, and audit logging from the architecture phase.</statement>
      <rationale>Enterprise data displayed in XR is visible in the physical environment and may be screen-captured by the headset; data security is a procurement blocker if not addressed early.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Design for MDM (Mobile Device Management) compatibility: device enrollment, remote wipe, app distribution, and usage logging must be supported.</statement>
      <rationale>Corporate IT will not deploy XR hardware without MDM control; lack of MDM support blocks enterprise rollout.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Training Interaction Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every training step must: highlight the current action target, show the next step contextually, provide immediate pass/fail feedback, track completion, and allow retry without restart.</statement>
      <rationale>Step-by-step guidance reduces cognitive load and training time; retry-without-restart prevents frustration from procedural errors that would require restarting a long simulation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include a performance dashboard accessible outside the headset (web/mobile) for managers and trainers to track completion rates and error patterns across the workforce.</statement>
      <rationale>Enterprise XR training ROI is measured at the organizational level, not just individual sessions; external reporting is required for management adoption.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
