<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-sizing-methods" title="TAM/SAM/SOM Calculation Methods">
  <summary>Three calculation methods for market sizing with validation checks and the triangulation requirement.</summary>

  <section title="Definitions">
    <list>
      <item>TAM (Total Addressable Market): total revenue if you captured 100% of potential buyers — formula: total potential customers × average revenue per customer per year</item>
      <item>SAM (Serviceable Available Market): portion of TAM actually reachable given geography, language, industry, company size, and tech constraints — formula: TAM × segment percentage</item>
      <item>SOM (Serviceable Obtainable Market): realistic market share in 3-5 years — formula: SAM × realistic market share percentage (Year 1: 0.1-0.5%, Year 3: 1-3%, Year 5: 3-10%)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Method 1 — Top-Down">
    <p>Start with an industry report, narrow down through segmentation filters (geography, industry, company size, tech stack). Use case: shows opportunity ceiling; establishes TAM for investor communication.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cite source, publication year, and page number for every top-down number. Reject any row with a dollar figure but no URL.</statement>
      <rationale>Top-down numbers from Gartner/Statista are routinely inflated 3-10x. LLMs confidently parrot fabricated CAGRs with two decimal places. Citation discipline is the only defense.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Method 2 — Bottom-Up">
    <p>Start from countable potential customers, multiply by conversion rate and price. Use case: grounds the SOM in operational reality; more credible to investors than top-down alone.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[15M freelancers in target geography
× 0.5% reachable with current marketing budget
= 75,000 addressable prospects
× 1% Year 1 trial conversion
= 750 customers
× $20/mo × 12
= $180K Year 1 SOM]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Method 3 — Competitor-Based">
    <p>Estimate total market from visible competitor revenues, then derive realistic share. Use case: cross-check for top-down and bottom-up; anchors SOM to actual market capacity.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Find competitor ARR estimates: Crunchbase funding data, SimilarWeb traffic × revenue per visit, LinkedIn employee count × $200K revenue per employee rule of thumb, or pricing × estimated customer count</item>
      <item>Sum visible competitor revenues to estimate total market</item>
      <item>Apply realistic share (1% of $500M market = $5M SOM at Year 3)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Validation Checks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always triangulate with both top-down and bottom-up. If the two results diverge more than 2x, flag it as a research gap — do not average the numbers or pick the more favorable one.</statement>
      <rationale>Divergence above 2x signals a definitional mismatch, a data quality problem, or an unconsidered constraint. Averaging hides the problem; flagging it forces investigation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Does the TAM feel real? Compare against public market research data</item>
      <item>Is the SAM specific enough? Can you name 100 target customers right now?</item>
      <item>Is the SOM achievable? Can you explain the operational path to get there?</item>
      <item>Does bottom-up match top-down within 2x? If not, document the gap</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
