<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-three-cuts" title="Three Audience Cuts from the Canonical Base">
  <summary>Investor cut, GTM cut, and pricing-tier cut: how each derives from the canonical market-research.md base.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>All three cuts must derive from the same canonical base at .aidocs/product_docs/market-research.md. If the investor cut and GTM cut disagree on the SAM number, something is wrong.</statement>
    <rationale>Divergent numbers across deck, GTM plan, and pricing model undermine credibility with partners, GTM team, and product managers simultaneously. One canonical source of truth prevents drift.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Investor Cut">
    <list>
      <item>One slide, three numbers (TAM / SAM / SOM), three sources, one chart, 40 words maximum</item>
      <item>TAM labeled explicitly as "if-100% scenario" in a footnote — partners reward honesty</item>
      <item>SOM growth arrow must match the Y5 ARR in the financial model exactly</item>
      <item>Include 2 public-comp equivalents at the same stage for instant credibility</item>
      <item>Round aggressively for the slide ($8B), preserve precision in the appendix ($8.27B) — never reverse</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>The investor cut must fit on one slide. If it does not, the agent has not finished the work.</statement>
      <rationale>An overloaded market slide signals that the founder cannot explain the opportunity succinctly. Partners use this as a signal about pitch clarity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="GTM Cut">
    <list>
      <item>Split SAM into mutually exclusive acquisition channels: PLG (low CAC, low ACV), outbound (high CAC, high ACV), partner (medium), content/SEO (decaying low CAC)</item>
      <item>Each bucket has a SAM ceiling — total reachable accounts via that channel only</item>
      <item>CAC envelope per bucket comes from pricing-research.md; any tier where bucket-CAC exceeds 0.33 × tier-LTV is GTM-blocked</item>
      <item>Geography splits must align with the pricing cut — no GTM motion in regions without localized pricing</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>GTM channel buckets must be mutually exclusive. Double-counting a customer between PLG and outbound is the most common GTM-cut audit failure.</statement>
      <rationale>Overlapping channel buckets inflate the reachable market and produce GTM plans that exceed the actual addressable population.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pricing-Tier Cut">
    <list>
      <item>For each pricing tier: tier-SAM = SAM × tier-mix percentage, tier-SOM = tier-SAM × realistic-share-for-tier</item>
      <item>Tier-mix reality: most SaaS land 60-70% Starter, 25-30% Pro, 5-10% Enterprise — a deck claiming 40% Enterprise requires evidence</item>
      <item>LTV uses tier-specific churn, not blended rate — Starter churn is often 3-5x Enterprise churn</item>
      <item>Any tier whose Y3 SOM is below 6 months of one engineer's salary should be cut from the deck — distraction</item>
      <item>Express tier-SOM in customer count first ("12,000 Pro seats"), dollars second — investors trust counts more</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/tier-som.sh">Script decomposing SAM/SOM per tier with LTV/CAC sanity check</reference>
  </section>
</text>
