<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="market-research-tam-sam-som Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for market-research-tam-sam-som as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Presenting only TAM without a bottom-up SOM calculation</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>TAM is the ceiling; SOM is what determines whether the business is worth building. Investors require both; a TAM-only deck signals the founder has not done the work.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Trusting a single industry report source</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Single-source TAMs are the number-one reason investor memos fall apart. Triangulate from at least 3 independent sources and publish the range, not a point estimate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring competitor share in the SOM calculation</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>SOM without subtracting established competitor share overestimates the realistically capturable market in a competitive category.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Static SOM in a fast-moving category</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>SOM must be redrawn every 6 months in high-CAGR categories; a stale curve presented as current breaks credibility in investor Q&amp;A.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent conflates TAM (gross addressable revenue) with ARR projection (net revenue)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Both numbers must appear with explicit labels every time; they are not interchangeable and differ by assumptions about market share, pricing, and churn.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Tier-mix defaulting to even splits (33/33/33 across Starter/Pro/Enterprise)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Even splits never match reality; force the agent to read category benchmarks (OpenView, ChartMogul) before assigning tier-mix percentages.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent puts the same customer account in both PLG and outbound channel buckets</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each customer appears in exactly one channel bucket; require a uniqueness key per row in the GTM cut model.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates 200 words for the investor slide</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Investor cut is capped at 40 words on the slide; all additional detail goes in the appendix where partners can read it if challenged.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent cites a hallucinated comparable ("Stripe is at 12% of TAM") without a source URL</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require a URL for every comparable cited on the investor cut; strike any row without one.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent uses headline list price as tier ARPU rather than effective ARPU</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Effective ARPU = list × (1 - discount) × annual-billing-mix; require an explicit effective-ARPU column, not list price.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
