<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="wireframing">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Low-fidelity UI structure representations to validate hierarchy and interactions before high-fidelity design.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>wireframing</tag>
      <tag>ux-design</tag>
      <tag>layout</tag>
      <tag>prototyping</tag>
      <tag>low-fidelity</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Wireframing</title>

    <summary>Low-fidelity representations of UI structure, layout, and functionality without visual design details. Use to validate information hierarchy and interaction patterns before committing to high-fidelity design. Produce layout descriptions, annotation tables, and state checklists — then hand off to a Figma session, not as the final deliverable.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Jumping to high-fidelity design conflates structural problems with aesthetic ones. Wireframes make layout and functionality cheap to debate and change. Stakeholders focus on usability instead of color choices. Structural problems caught in wireframes cost a fraction of what they cost in implemented code.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Exploring multiple layout concepts before committing to one direction.</item>
        <item>Generating a wireframe document (ASCII layout + annotation table + states) from a feature spec.</item>
        <item>Reviewing a wireframe against acceptance criteria to flag missing states or interactions.</item>
        <item>Creating component wireframe templates (card, form, modal) from a design system definition.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Generating visual design — wireframes are intentionally lo-fi; skipping to polished mockups bypasses structural validation.</item>
        <item>When stakeholders need pixel-precise layouts for developer handoff — wireframes are for alignment, not spec.</item>
        <item>Replacing collaborative sketching sessions where team buy-in is the goal, not an artifact.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="fidelity-levels">
      <list>
        <item>Low fidelity: boxes and lines only — use for early concept exploration, cheap to discard.</item>
        <item>Medium fidelity: basic content structure, placeholder text — use for design iteration and stakeholder review.</item>
        <item>High fidelity: detailed layout, realistic content — use to finalize structure before visual design begins.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Start at low fidelity; increase fidelity only after layout direction is agreed.</statement>
        <rationale>High-fidelity wireframes invite aesthetic feedback before structural decisions are made, conflating two distinct design decisions and slowing both.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="content-rules">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Wireframes must show: layout structure, content hierarchy, navigation, functionality, interaction patterns. Must exclude: colors (except grayscale), typography styles, real images, branding, final copy.</statement>
        <rationale>Including visual design elements in wireframes causes stakeholder feedback to focus on aesthetics instead of usability. Grayscale boxes enforce structural thinking.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Adding color to indicate priority or state in wireframes.</description>
        <reason>Introduces visual design decisions before structural ones are validated, conflating two separate design phases and creating premature commitment to color choices.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="state-coverage">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every wireframe must cover all states: default, empty, loading, error, success, and any permission-gated view.</statement>
        <rationale>Empty states and error states are always missed in first-pass wireframes and always noticed by users. Missing states in wireframes produce missing states in implementation, which ship to production and surprise users.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Default: the populated, normal-operation view.</item>
        <item>Empty: first use or no-data state ("no results found", "no orders yet").</item>
        <item>Loading: while data is being fetched.</item>
        <item>Error: when an operation fails (form validation, network error, permission denied).</item>
        <item>Success: confirmation after completing an action.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Explicitly wireframe empty states before launch — these are always missed and always noticed by users on first use.</statement>
        <rationale>Empty states are what new users see first. A blank screen with no guidance is the worst possible first impression. Wireframing empty states forces the team to design a productive first-use experience.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="responsive-requirements">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Include mobile breakpoint notes in every wireframe, even for desktop-first products.</statement>
        <rationale>Retrofitting responsive behavior after desktop wireframes are approved costs significantly more than adding responsive notes during the wireframing phase.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="annotation-requirements">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Annotation tables must include an "Open Questions" section that surfaces design assumptions needing resolution before engineering begins.</statement>
        <rationale>Unstated assumptions in wireframes become incorrect implementations. Forcing designers to state open questions creates explicit decision points rather than hidden ones.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="wireframing-process">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Read user needs, business requirements, technical constraints, and content inventory before sketching anything.</statement>
        <rationale>Wireframes that do not reflect requirements must be redone. Reading requirements first prevents the most expensive type of wireframe rework.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Produce at least 3 layout variants for key screens before committing to one direction.</statement>
        <rationale>The first layout is rarely the best. Convergence too early eliminates valid alternatives without evaluation. Sketching three variants takes minutes; reworking a committed Figma file takes hours.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every wireframe must include an annotation table documenting behavior, conditional states, and technical requirements for each element.</statement>
        <rationale>Undocumented behavior assumptions cause expensive rework in implementation when engineers make different assumptions. The annotation table is the contract between design and engineering.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="low-fidelity-example">
      <example type="good" title="Simple page layout wireframe">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
+----------------------------------+
|  Logo        [Nav] [Nav] [Nav]  |
+----------------------------------+
|                                  |
|  [     Hero Headline      ]     |
|  [     Subtext            ]     |
|       [  CTA Button  ]          |
|                                  |
+----------------------------------+
|  [Card]    [Card]    [Card]     |
+----------------------------------+
|  Footer links | Social | Legal  |
+----------------------------------+
        ]]></code>
        <note>Layout direction only, no colors, no content. Can be sketched in 2 minutes. Enough for stakeholders to validate page structure.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-element-patterns">
      <example type="good" title="Standard UI component patterns">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
## Navigation bar
[Logo]    [Home]  [Products]  [About]  [Get Started]

## Hero section
[     Headline H1 — clear and concise              ]
[     Subtext — 1-2 lines max                      ]
[ Primary CTA ]    [ Secondary CTA ]

## Card (3-column grid)
+----------+  +----------+  +----------+
| [Image]  |  | [Image]  |  | [Image]  |
| Title    |  | Title    |  | Title    |
| Body     |  | Body     |  | Body     |
| [Action] |  | [Action] |  | [Action] |
+----------+  +----------+  +----------+

## Form field
Label *
[Input field                         ]
Helper text: format guidance here

## Footer
[Link group] [Link group] [Link group] [Social icons]
Copyright notice | Privacy | Terms
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agent reads a feature spec or user story set. Produces for each screen: ASCII layout diagram (boxes and labels, no colors), annotation table (Element, Description, Behavior/Notes), states checklist (default, empty, loading, error, success), responsive notes (what changes at mobile breakpoint), open questions (ambiguous decisions needing resolution before engineering). This document is the input to a Figma session, not the output.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent generates happy-path wireframes only, missing all error and empty states.</description>
        <reason>Explicitly add to every wireframe prompt: "include all error, empty, loading, and permission-denied states." Agents do not include these unless explicitly instructed.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>ASCII wireframes look correct in raw text but break in rendered markdown due to character width differences.</description>
        <reason>ASCII box-drawing in monospace looks correct in editors but breaks when rendered in GitHub, Notion, or Slack which use proportional fonts. Validate rendering environment before sharing.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Annotation tables generated without access to the actual spec contain invented behavior descriptions.</description>
        <reason>Always provide the feature spec or acceptance criteria as context when generating annotation tables. Without it, agents invent plausible-sounding behavior that may contradict requirements.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents omit "open questions" unless explicitly instructed to flag ambiguity.</description>
        <reason>This is the most valuable part of a wireframe document for early-stage design. Force agents to include open questions with explicit prompt instructions.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Human review of wireframes skipped because the agent produced something plausible.</description>
        <reason>Agents surface structure but cannot judge whether it matches user mental models or business intent. Human review is mandatory before engineering starts.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Produce at minimum 3 layout variants for key screens before settling on one — convergence too early eliminates valid alternatives.</item>
        <item>Every wireframe must include the annotation table — undocumented behavior assumptions cause expensive rework in implementation.</item>
        <item>Explicitly wireframe empty states before launch: "no results", "no data yet", "permission denied" — these are always missed and always noticed by users.</item>
        <item>Include mobile breakpoint notes in every wireframe, even for desktop-first products — retrofitting responsive is always more expensive.</item>
        <item>Use a persistent header in the annotation table: "Open Questions" section forces designers to surface assumptions before engineering starts.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="anti-patterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Presenting one layout option to stakeholders for approval.</description>
        <reason>Single-option reviews produce either acceptance without exploration or rejection without alternatives, both of which slow design progress. Minimum three variants before converging.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping sketching and opening a Figma file directly.</description>
        <reason>Digital wireframing tools have friction that suppresses exploration. Paper sketching is 10x faster for generating and discarding layout ideas. Open Figma after you know the layout direction.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/wireframe-doc.md" purpose="Screen wireframe document: purpose, layout, annotation table, states, interactions, responsive notes."/>
      <template path="templates/component-wireframe.md" purpose="Component wireframe: variants, states, content guidelines, usage notes."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-wireframe.txt" purpose="LLM prompt for generating a wireframe spec from a user story."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.figma.com/resource-library/wireframing/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/wireframe-tools/"/>
      <link href="https://sensible.com/dont-make-me-think/"/>
      <link href="https://balsamiq.com/learn/"/>
      <link href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2023/wireframing-guide/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
