<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-positioning-framework" title="Competitive Positioning Framework">
  <summary>Covers April Dunford's six-component positioning model, four positioning strategies with trade-offs, and the 6-step development process.</summary>

  <section title="Six-Component Model">
    <p>April Dunford's model: (1) Competitive alternatives — what would customers do if this product didn't exist? (2) Unique attributes — what does the product have that others don't? (3) Value — what does that attribute enable for the customer? (4) Target customer — who cares most about that value? (5) Market category — what type of product is this? (6) Positioning statement — the synthesized claim.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap the canvas at 3 unique attributes, then map every roadmap initiative to exactly one; initiatives that reinforce zero attributes must be killed or reframed before entering the sprint.</statement>
      <rationale>More than 3 unique attributes means the product is trying to win on too many dimensions; the resulting roadmap becomes unfocused and the positioning is unmemorizable by sales.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Four Positioning Strategies">
    <p>Head-to-Head: when you are better on established criteria (risk: feature wars). Differentiation: when you serve a specific need others ignore (risk: niche too small). Niche Dominance: when you own a specific segment (risk: growth ceiling). Category Creation: when you are truly new (risk: market education required, hardest to execute).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use win/loss reasons as ground truth for the "competitive alternatives" cell; what you actually competed against in customers' words trumps any agent-generated competitor list.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent-generated competitor lists reflect market knowledge from training data, not the actual alternatives customers considered before choosing or rejecting your product.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="6-Step Development Process">
    <p>Step 1: List all competitive alternatives including indirect competitors and status quo. Step 2: Identify unique attributes — test each with "Can competitors truthfully claim this too?" Step 3: Translate attributes to customer value with three "So what?" levels. Step 4: Identify best-fit customers who value this most. Step 5: Define market category (existing/subcategory/new). Step 6: Craft the positioning statement using the template.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Translate every unique attribute through three "So what?" levels to reach the ultimate customer outcome, not just the feature benefit.</statement>
      <rationale>Feature-level positioning ("we have real-time sync") triggers feature-war comparisons; outcome-level positioning ("ship faster with fewer mistakes") connects to business value and is harder to commoditize.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Attribute: Real-time sync. So what: team always sees the latest version. So what: no version confusion. So what: ship faster with fewer mistakes. The third level is the positioning anchor.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"We're like Asana but better" — no differentiation, no targeting, triggers feature war comparison against a larger, better-resourced competitor.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Positioning Statement Template">
    <p>Template structure: "For [target customer] who [need/situation], [Product name] is [market category] that [key benefit]. Unlike [alternatives], we [unique differentiator]."</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Bind each unique attribute claim to a telemetry signal showing at least 10% of MAU exercises it, or tag it explicitly as "future bet" on the canvas.</statement>
      <rationale>Positioning claims backed only by marketing copy and not by usage data are fiction; when sales uses them and the customer asks for proof, trust collapses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/positioning-canvas.md">Full canvas template with all six components and proof points section</reference>
  </section>
</text>
