<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-positioning-gate-loop" title="Positioning Gate Loop and Canvas Maintenance">
  <summary>Defines the PM's positioning-fit gate for every backlog item, quarterly canvas refresh triggers, drift detection across quarters, and agent-specific failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Positioning-Fit Gate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score every backlog item 0-3 on positioning-fit before it enters a sprint: 0 = orthogonal or dilutes, 1 = neutral table-stakes, 2 = reinforces one unique attribute, 3 = reinforces two or more. Veto items scoring 0 regardless of RICE score.</statement>
      <rationale>RICE scoring inflates Reach and ignores positioning-fit; a positioning-diluting feature can rank high on RICE while eroding the product's differentiation quarter by quarter.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require a citation (canvas section + telemetry signal) for any positioning-fit score of 2 or higher; reject uncited scores.</statement>
      <rationale>Backlog authors learn the gate's heuristics and stuff PRDs with positioning keywords; requiring a citation from the actual canvas prevents score gaming.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include a "positioning fit" column alongside RICE in roadmap reviews; add an "off-positioning shipped" anti-metric (trend-down target) to the product health dashboard.</statement>
      <rationale>What gets measured gets managed; tracking off-positioning features shipped creates organizational pressure to maintain the positioning discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/roadmap-positioning-drift.sh">Flag backlog items that dilute positioning — non-zero exit on dilution detected</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Quarterly Canvas Refresh">
    <rule>
      <statement>Refresh the positioning canvas at the start of each planning quarter; diff it against the prior quarter and run a backlog-impact report for in-flight initiatives.</statement>
      <rationale>Incremental drift is invisible in any single quarter; a diff across four quarters shows the trajectory of the positioning — and whether the wedge is being maintained or lost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not change the canvas if the diff would invalidate more than 50% of the in-flight roadmap without PM sign-off; output a "breaking-change" report instead.</statement>
      <rationale>A canvas change that invalidates most of the in-flight work is a strategic pivot, not a positioning refresh; the PM must explicitly acknowledge it before any downstream doc updates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the outbound-loop propagator when the canvas changes: update roadmap.md, OKR docs, pricing-page copy, and sales enablement skeletons atomically in a single PR.</statement>
      <rationale>A canvas updated without propagating to OKRs and roadmap creates the classic misalignment: quarterly OKRs still reference last quarter's positioning while the product has moved on.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent regenerating the canvas without checking whether the in-flight backlog can deliver the new positioning.</description>
      <reason>Canvas-first, backlog-second sequencing creates a positioning that the current development capacity cannot deliver; every regen prompt must include the in-flight roadmap.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent widening the canvas to absorb every lost-deal feature request (sales-laundered positioning).</description>
      <reason>Feature-list widening destroys differentiation; pre-process win/loss notes to extract the category of competitor, not feature checklists, and reject feature-list dilution at the prompt level.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent generating positioning sections with "customer-centric approach," "best-in-class," or "innovative" as unique attributes.</description>
      <reason>These terms are claims every competitor makes; require a specific named attribute from the canvas and a citation that differentiates it from direct competitors.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>PRD positioning section auto-filled with generic text like "this reinforces our customer-centric approach" without naming a specific canvas attribute.</description>
      <reason>Generic positioning answers are worse than no answer; they pass the gate-loop check superficially while adding no information, and they train reviewers to stop reading the positioning section.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-the-Loop Checkpoints">
    <list>
      <item>PM approves the regenerated canvas before any downstream doc updates.</item>
      <item>PM signs off on each ship/defer/reject recommendation from the gate-loop agent — agents must not auto-close issues.</item>
      <item>PM personally walks marketing, sales, and support through canvas changes once per quarter.</item>
      <item>PM owns the call on category-creation vs. subcategory positioning — agents flag the question, never decide it.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
