<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="competitive-positioning Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for competitive-positioning as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent regenerating the canvas without checking whether the in-flight backlog can deliver the new positioning.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Canvas-first, backlog-second sequencing creates a positioning that the current development capacity cannot deliver; every regen prompt must include the in-flight roadmap.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent widening the canvas to absorb every lost-deal feature request (sales-laundered positioning).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feature-list widening destroys differentiation; pre-process win/loss notes to extract the category of competitor, not feature checklists, and reject feature-list dilution at the prompt level.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generating positioning sections with "customer-centric approach," "best-in-class," or "innovative" as unique attributes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>These terms are claims every competitor makes; require a specific named attribute from the canvas and a citation that differentiates it from direct competitors.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>PRD positioning section auto-filled with generic text like "this reinforces our customer-centric approach" without naming a specific canvas attribute.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generic positioning answers are worse than no answer; they pass the gate-loop check superficially while adding no information, and they train reviewers to stop reading the positioning section.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
