<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-geo-principles" title="GEO: Generative Engine Optimization Principles">
  <summary>Multi-platform search landscape, GEO vs traditional SEO distinction, and core citation optimization principles.</summary>

  <section title="Search Landscape 2026">
    <rule>
      <statement>Optimize for AI engine citation in addition to Google rank — treat them as separate but complementary signals.</statement>
      <rationale>ChatGPT and Perplexity handle 400M+ weekly queries combined. Semrush projects LLM traffic to overtake traditional Google search by end of 2027. Content invisible to AI engines loses share regardless of Google rank.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Google: 90% market share, 30% of queries now trigger AI Overviews</item>
      <item>ChatGPT/Perplexity: 400M+ weekly users, citation-based results</item>
      <item>YouTube: second-largest search engine, video SEO rules apply</item>
      <item>TikTok: primary search for Gen Z, short-form video format</item>
      <item>Amazon: product search, A9 algorithm, voice commerce ($80B by 2026)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="GEO vs Traditional SEO">
    <rule>
      <statement>GEO targets being the source AI engines cite, not just the link at position 1-10 in results.</statement>
      <rationale>Traditional SEO optimizes for ranked links. GEO optimizes for inclusion in AI-generated answers. These are different mechanisms: citations are based on authority, entity clarity, and content extractability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Traditional SEO: rank in positions 1-10 for a keyword</item>
      <item>GEO: get cited, referenced, or recommended in AI-generated answers</item>
      <item>Topic targeting over keyword targeting (broader subject authority)</item>
      <item>Brand visibility and mentions over position rankings</item>
      <item>Structured, extractable content over flowing prose</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Core GEO Citation Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Update content within 30 days — fresh content receives 3.2x more AI citations than stale content (Semrush research).</statement>
      <rationale>AI engines weight recency as an authority signal. Content that has not been updated signals potential staleness, reducing citation probability regardless of original quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Become an authoritative source: earn citations, backlinks, and earned media</item>
      <item>Provide clear, structured information with direct answers</item>
      <item>Use schema markup for machine readability</item>
      <item>Create comprehensive, well-researched original content</item>
      <item>Build consensus across owned and earned media</item>
      <item>Focus on original insights, frameworks, and proprietary data</item>
      <item>Build entity consistency: same brand name, product names, author names everywhere</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="GEO Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>AI Visibility Score: frequency of brand appearance in AI responses</item>
      <item>Source Citations: times AI models reference or link to content</item>
      <item>AI Share of Voice: % of relevant AI answers mentioning the brand</item>
      <item>Time-to-Citation: days from publishing to first AI citation</item>
    </list>
    <note>AI citation tracking requires paid tools (Otterly.AI, Profound, Semrush AI Visibility Toolkit). No free API tier exists for monitoring. Set up Google Alerts for brand mentions as a low-cost proxy.</note>
  </section>
</text>
