<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-aeo-practices" title="AEO: Answer Engine Optimization Best Practices">
  <summary>Content structure, schema types, and platform-specific practices for AI engine answer inclusion.</summary>

  <section title="Content Structure Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure every content page so each H2/H3 heading is a question and the first paragraph directly answers it within 2 sentences.</statement>
      <rationale>This is the highest-impact single change for AEO. AI engines extract the question-answer pair as a unit. Content that buries answers in the third paragraph is rarely cited even when technically correct.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>H2: "What is GEO?" followed immediately by: "GEO (Generative Engine Optimization) is the practice of optimizing content to be cited by AI-powered search engines. It differs from traditional SEO by targeting inclusion in AI-generated answers rather than ranked link positions."</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>H2: "Understanding GEO" followed by three paragraphs of background context before a definition appears. AI engines skip this content for cleaner sources.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="AEO Content Rules">
    <list>
      <item>Short paragraphs (2-4 lines), bullet points, and tables for key data</item>
      <item>Proper heading hierarchy (H1, H2, H3) — no skipped levels</item>
      <item>Target featured snippets and AI Overviews on Google</item>
      <item>Match "People Also Ask" query formats in subheadings</item>
      <item>Provide direct, concise answers immediately after headings</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Schema Types for AEO">
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement FAQPage schema on all Q&amp;A content and HowTo schema on all tutorial content — these are explicitly consumed by voice search and AI engines.</statement>
      <rationale>FAQPage and HowTo schema are in the Speakable category that Google explicitly uses for voice search and AI Overview sourcing. They create a machine-readable signal that the content is answer-structured.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>FAQPage: Q&amp;A sections, "People Also Ask" content</item>
      <item>HowTo: step-by-step tutorials, instructions</item>
      <item>Article/BlogPosting: all editorial content with author and date</item>
      <item>Organization + Person: brand and author entity definitions</item>
      <item>BreadcrumbList: topic relationship signals</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/faq-schema.json">JSON-LD FAQPage schema template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Platform-Specific Priorities">
    <list>
      <item>Google: SEO readiness + Helpful Content signals + schema markup</item>
      <item>Perplexity: clarity, recency (within 30 days), external citations in content</item>
      <item>ChatGPT: authority signals (backlinks, brand mentions) — behavior varies by model</item>
    </list>
    <note>AI citation behavior is non-deterministic and changes with model updates. Optimizations made today may not hold in 3-6 months. Focus on durable signals: content quality, entity consistency, schema markup.</note>
  </section>
</text>
