<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-implementation" title="GEO/AEO Implementation and Agent Workflow">
  <summary>GEO audit criteria, schema deployment workflow, monitoring approach, and agent-specific gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="GEO Audit Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Audit each content page on five criteria before publishing or updating. Fail on any criterion triggers a specific fix, not a general "improve content" note.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague audit feedback ("make it better") produces no action. Specific fail criteria produce specific fixes that can be verified and retested.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>1. Does each heading have a direct answer within 2 sentences? (Pass/Fail)</item>
      <item>2. Are there FAQ sections with question-format headings? (Pass/Fail)</item>
      <item>3. Is entity language consistent (brand name, product names, author name)? (Pass/Fail)</item>
      <item>4. Are there tables, bullet points, or numbered lists for key data? (Pass/Fail)</item>
      <item>5. Is there original data, framework, or insight an AI would cite? (Pass/Fail)</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-geo-audit.txt">LLM prompt to run GEO/AEO audit on a content page</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Schema Deployment Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate all JSON-LD schema with Google Rich Results Test before deployment — never deploy agent-generated schema without validation.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents produce syntactically plausible but semantically incorrect schema: wrong @type values, missing required fields, incorrect nesting. Invalid schema produces no rich results and may trigger Search Console errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Generate schema from template or agent</item>
      <item>Validate JSON syntax (jsonlint.com or IDE)</item>
      <item>Test with Google Rich Results Test</item>
      <item>Verify no conflicting schema definitions on the page</item>
      <item>Deploy and monitor Search Console for errors</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Monitoring Setup">
    <list>
      <item>Otterly.AI or Profound: monthly AI citation check (paid)</item>
      <item>Google Alerts for brand name: free proxy for citation monitoring</item>
      <item>Google Search Console: AI Overviews impression data (limited)</item>
      <item>Semrush AI Visibility Toolkit: AI share of voice tracking (paid)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent recommends "publish more content" without specifying content gaps as article titles and target queries.</description>
      <reason>Vague content volume recommendations are not actionable. Require the agent to output specific gaps as: article title, target query, and format (FAQ, HowTo, comparison).</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent updates publication dates in metadata without updating the actual content.</description>
      <reason>AI engines and Google both detect content freshness via substantive changes, not metadata timestamps. A date update without content change provides no citation benefit.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent suggests entity relationships (brand associated with specific concepts or people) without verifying what AI engines currently associate with the brand.</description>
      <reason>Suggested entity relationships may not match the brand's current knowledge graph representation. Incorrect associations can confuse AI engine entity resolution.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
