<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Doc Examples Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Design Doc Examples. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-four-archetypes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain exactly four worked examples: single-service feature, cross-service refactor, data migration, hot-path performance.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — design-doc patterns audit">Four archetypes cover ~85% of design problems without overwhelming the writer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-fully-realistic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every example is fully filled in with realistic content — no placeholders, no placeholders inside the example body.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — half-filled examples">Placeholders signal &apos;optional&apos; and writers skip the sections; full content sets the expected depth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-version-coupled" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Examples carry the same version as design-doc-structure; updates to structure trigger re-syncing examples in the same PR.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — sync hygiene">Drift between structure and examples confuses writers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-named-archetype" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Writer states which archetype they picked in the final doc&apos;s front-matter; &apos;none&apos; is a valid value but must be intentional.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — doc lineage">Stating the archetype lets reviewers calibrate expectations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-adapt-not-copy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Writer adapts: every example field is either replaced with real content or explicitly marked &apos;kept from example&apos;.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — copy-paste audit">Verbatim copies signal lack of engagement; the archetype tag tracks adapted vs kept.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-examples-reviewed-quarterly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Examples are reviewed quarterly to keep them aligned with current architecture and tooling.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — stale-example audit">Stale examples mislead writers; quarterly review keeps them fresh.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md &quot;Applies If&quot; do not all hold, OR any &quot;Skip If&quot; disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-design-doc-examples.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
