<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="hr" count="15">
  <methodology slug="30-60-90-day-plan" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/30-60-90-day-plan">
    <summary>A three-phase new-hire ramp framework based on Michael Watkins's Learn / Contribute / Execute cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-contractor-jd-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/agency-contractor-jd-template">
    <summary>Reusable template for agency contractor jd template that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="employee-value-proposition" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/employee-value-proposition">
    <summary>A methodology for defining and communicating the unique value employees receive in exchange for their skills and commitment, structured around five pillars: Compensation, Benefits, Career, Work Environment, and Culture/Purpose.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="employer-branding" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/employer-branding">
    <summary>Strategy and execution methodology for building and maintaining an employer brand across Glassdoor, LinkedIn, careers page, employee testimonials, and content calendars.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="interview-methods" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/interview-methods">
    <summary>Bundle of structured-interview methodologies covering competency definition, STAR behavioral questions, scorecards, technical assessments, culture-fit assessment, reference checks, and hiring-committee debrief.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="onboarding" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/onboarding">
    <summary>An end-to-end framework for designing and operating a repeatable new-hire onboarding program: preboarding, Day 1 orientation, buddy pairing, 30-60-90 day progression, feedback loops, manager guides, and remote adaptations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="onboarding-30-day" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/onboarding-30-day">
    <summary>Structured first-30-day onboarding framework covering orientation (Week 1), foundation building (Week 2), and deep-dive with first deliverable (Weeks 3-4).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="onboarding-60-90-day" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/onboarding-60-90-day">
    <summary>A two-phase framework for structured new-hire progression after the initial 30-day learning phase: Contribute (days 31-60, first owned project, active collaboration) and Execute (days 61-90, independent delivery, measurable results).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="recruiting-process" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/recruiting-process">
    <summary>A full-cycle talent acquisition framework covering ten methodologies from multi-channel sourcing through offer management.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="recruitment-funnel-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/recruitment-funnel-optimization">
    <summary>A stage-by-stage framework for measuring and improving candidate conversion across six hiring phases: Awareness, Application, Screening, Interview, Offer, and Onboarding.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="retention-compliance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/retention-compliance">
    <summary>A paired framework covering two related HR domains: employee retention (stay interviews, exit analysis, 9-box talent reviews, internal mobility) and hiring compliance (legal requirements per funnel stage, DEI practices, process audits).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="star-interview-examples" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/star-interview-examples">
    <summary>Worked examples of strong, weak, and red-flag STAR responses paired with probing scripts for each failure mode, plus an interviewer training module and quality assurance checklist.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="star-interview-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/star-interview-framework">
    <summary>The STAR framework (Situation-Task-Action-Result) is a structured behavioral interviewing technique that elicits four-part responses from candidates, forcing specificity and comparability across candidates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="star-interview-method" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/star-interview-method">
    <summary>The STAR framework (Situation-Task-Action-Result) is a behavioral-interview method for extracting evidence of past performance and structuring post-interview analysis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="structured-interview-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/structured-interview-design">
    <summary>A six-step process for building a consistent, predictive interview process: define 4-6 competencies, write standardized behavioral and situational questions, build a scored rubric with behavioral anchors, train interviewers, execute identically for every candidate, and debrief with independent scores before discussion.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
