<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="vui-conversation-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for vui-conversation-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs over-confirm. Every "Just to confirm…" turn is a tax; force the agent to justify each one.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Confirmation turns delay goal completion and increase abandonment. Only confirm high-consequence actions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Generated paraphrase corpora cluster around the LLM's own register, missing dialect and code-switching.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLM paraphrases are over-formal and lack regional variation. Augment with real voice logs or crowdsourced examples.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs generate the wake word or branded voice persona unsupervised.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>TTS pronunciation lands wrong on syllable stress and prosody. Human voice talent and TTS tuning are non-negotiable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Dialog state is implicit ("in the prompt"). Long-context models fake competence and then drop entities at turn 5.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Only explicit slot-filling frames are reliable. Never use context-window depth as a substitute for state management.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy ignored: raw user audio piped into a cloud LLM without redaction.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Regulatory exposure (GDPR, HIPAA, CCPA). Strip names, account numbers, and PHI before logging.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Streaming ASR partial results trigger premature LLM responses.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Partial results cause early action and jarring UX. Gate on `is_final` flag and pin a stability threshold (e.g., 500ms silence).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
