<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules">
  <rule testable="true">A story is READY only when all 8 items pass: clear outcome, named acceptance criteria, design or wireframe linked, dependencies resolved, env access granted, test data identified, security/legal sign-off (if applicable), client PM accountable; ≤7/8 = NOT READY, send back to refinement.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Client-side dependency check (5 items) is mandatory and runs BEFORE engineering check: (a) client PM confirmed in writing, (b) env credentials or VPN tested by a team member, (c) realistic test dataset accessible, (d) regulator/legal/security ticket exists or is N/A in writing, (e) any required client-side IT change is ticketed with an SLA.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Stories carrying compliance impact (HIPAA, GDPR, SOC2, PCI) require a named compliance contact and a written N/A or sign-off attached; without it, ready=false regardless of other items.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">DoR check is timeboxed to 5 minutes per story in grooming; if the story cannot be evaluated in 5 minutes, mark NOT READY for "insufficient definition" and route to a discovery session.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Failure to meet DoR is logged with the failing item; track which item fails most often per client — the top failing item is the discovery focus for the next iteration.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Re-estimation of the same story is forbidden until DoR is met; this enforces upstream work and removes the false comfort of "we estimated it again" without unblocking it.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">The checklist is co-owned by BA + PM and reviewed quarterly with the client; clients who consistently produce DoR failures get a written escalation in the QBR — DoR is the client-side accountability artifact.</rule>
  <example>Backlog grooming, outsource team for a HealthTech client: Story "Add PHI export endpoint". Outcome: yes. AC: yes. Design: linked. Deps: data model PR open (BLOCKED). Env: VPN works, prod-like DB seeded. Test data: 100 PHI rows available behind BAA. Compliance: HIPAA contact named, written sign-off pending (BLOCKED). Client PM: named. Score 6/8 — NOT READY, two items returned to client PM with deadlines, story stays out of sprint.</example>
</text>
