<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-domains" title="Eight PMBoK 7 Performance Domains">
  <summary>Eight interconnected domains that together define where project managers must achieve results, not just follow processes.</summary>

  <section title="1. Stakeholder">
    <p>Purpose: effectively engage stakeholders throughout the project. Outcomes: stakeholders identified and understood, engagement strategies developed, stakeholders actively involved, satisfaction achieved. Related methodologies: stakeholder-register, stakeholder-engagement.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="2. Team">
    <p>Purpose: establish and maintain a high-performing project team. Outcomes: shared ownership, collaborative environment, continuous development, distributed leadership. Related methodologies: raci-matrix, team-development, communications-management.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="3. Development Approach">
    <p>Purpose: select and maintain the optimal delivery approach. Outcomes: approach aligned with project needs, continuous improvement incorporated. Approach options: Predictive (clear requirements, low uncertainty), Iterative (need to refine solution), Incremental (deliver partial value early), Agile (high uncertainty, need flexibility), Hybrid (mixed characteristics). Related methodologies: agile-hybrid-approaches.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="4. Planning">
    <p>Purpose: plan how project work will be done. Outcomes: organised scope, realistic schedule and budget, resource plans. Related methodologies: work-breakdown-structure, schedule-development, cost-estimation, scope-management.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="5. Project Work">
    <p>Purpose: establish processes and perform work efficiently. Outcomes: efficient processes, appropriate communication, resources managed, procurements handled. Related methodologies: change-control, procurement-management.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="6. Delivery">
    <p>Purpose: deliver value and outcomes that stakeholders accept. Outcomes: scope completed, quality met, benefits realised. Related methodologies: quality-management, benefits-realization, project-closure.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="7. Measurement">
    <p>Purpose: assess project performance and take action. Outcomes: reliable decision information, timely data, performance forecasts. Related methodologies: earned-value-management, lessons-learned.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="8. Uncertainty">
    <p>Purpose: address uncertainty and risk proactively. Outcomes: threats reduced, opportunities captured, reserves appropriate. Related methodologies: risk-register, risk-management.</p>
  </section>
</text>
