<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-interactions" title="Domain Interactions and Assessment Rules">
  <summary>Domain interaction matrix showing upstream failure cascades, routing rules, and antipatterns for domain-based assessment.</summary>

  <section title="Domain Interaction Matrix">
    <p>When a domain struggles, these others are typically affected:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Stakeholder weak → Team, Delivery, Measurement suffer (misaligned expectations propagate)</item>
      <item>Team weak → Project Work, Delivery suffer (execution degrades)</item>
      <item>Development Approach wrong → Planning, Project Work, Delivery suffer (wrong tools for the work)</item>
      <item>Planning weak → Project Work, Delivery, Measurement suffer (no baseline to measure against)</item>
      <item>Project Work weak → Delivery, Measurement suffer (output quality degrades)</item>
      <item>Delivery weak → Stakeholder, Measurement suffer (value not visible)</item>
      <item>Measurement weak → all domains suffer (no visibility into what is wrong)</item>
      <item>Uncertainty weak → all domains suffer (unmanaged risks materialise unpredictably)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <rule>
    <statement>Re-assess domains at every project gate (kickoff, mid-point, pre-launch, close), not weekly; weekly drives status theatre.</statement>
    <rationale>Domain assessment is a strategic tool; overuse dilutes its signal and creates reporting overhead without changing PM decisions.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Start every status report with the two weakest domains; do not rotate through all 8.</statement>
    <rationale>Focus on the weakest domains drives action; rotating through all eight creates the illusion of coverage without improving anything.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>The Uncertainty domain requires an active risk register to score green; absence of a register means automatic red.</statement>
    <rationale>Uncertainty is most often under-resourced; requiring a concrete artefact prevents superficial compliance.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Domains are NOT phases; never write "Stakeholder phase complete" or "Team phase done".</statement>
    <rationale>Domains are ongoing concurrent concerns that persist for the entire project; "complete" misrepresents the nature of domain management.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>When dropping a domain for a low-stakes project, drop the entire domain, not partial methodologies; "light EVM" is usually fake EVM.</statement>
    <rationale>Half-applied methodologies consume overhead without delivering the discipline benefits; commit or skip explicitly.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Collapsing the 8 domains back into the old 5 process groups (Initiate/Plan/Execute/M&amp;C/Close).</description>
    <reason>This is a PMBoK 6 regression; domains are outcome-based auditing primitives, not sequential phases.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Asking an LLM "is this domain healthy?" without providing evidence artefacts or metrics.</description>
    <reason>Without inputs, the agent produces generic prose that does not reflect actual project health; always feed evidence and require citations.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <reference path="templates/domain-assessment.md">Eight-row domain health assessment template</reference>
</text>
