<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ada-title-ii-compliance-2026">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>US state/local government compliance: WCAG 2.1 AA by April 2026 (50K+ pop) or 2027. Full scope, remediation roadmap, VPAT documentation, training, procurement standards.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>ada</tag>
      <tag>title-ii</tag>
      <tag>compliance</tag>
      <tag>wcag</tag>
      <tag>government</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>ADA Title II Compliance 2026</title>
    <summary>Compliance methodology for US state and local government entities required to meet WCAG 2.1 Level AA under the DOJ ADA Title II final rule: large entities (50K+ population) by April 24, 2026; smaller entities by April 24, 2027. Covers full scope (web, mobile apps, multimedia, PDFs, third-party content), the six-step remediation roadmap, accessibility statement requirements, VPAT/ACR documentation, training, and procurement standards.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Non-compliance risks DOJ investigation, private lawsuits, loss of federal funding, and multi-year consent decrees. The scope is broader than HTML: mobile apps, PDFs, video captions, interactive forms, and third-party social embeds are all in scope. Overlay tools (accessibility.widget) do not constitute compliance — the DOJ has explicitly warned against them. VPAT 2.5 INT alone is not proof of conformance; courts require real test evidence.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>US state/local government entity or federal-funded program building or auditing public-facing digital services.</item>
        <item>Vendor responding to government RFP requiring VPAT/ACR and remediation plan.</item>
        <item>Procurement officer evaluating third-party SaaS for accessibility risk before contract award.</item>
        <item>Pre-litigation triage after a DOJ complaint or Title II demand letter.</item>
        <item>Drafting or reviewing accessibility statements, procurement clauses, or staff training plans.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Private commercial sites unrelated to government funding — ADA Title III and WCAG 2.2 AA apply; different case law.</item>
        <item>EU-only products — use regulatory-compliance-2026 for EAA + EN 301 549.</item>
        <item>Internal-only tools not used by the public — Section 504/508 may apply instead of the Title II web rule.</item>
        <item>Greenfield design — apply accessibility-first-design from day one to avoid remediation cost.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="compliance-deadlines-and-scope">
      <p>The DOJ ADA Title II final rule sets specific deadlines and defines scope broadly beyond just websites.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Large state/local government entities (serving 50,000+ population) must comply by April 24, 2026; smaller entities by April 24, 2027. Standard: WCAG 2.1 Level AA.</statement>
        <rationale>DOJ Final Rule published April 2024. ADA Title II applies to all state and local government entities that receive federal assistance — not just websites, but all digital services used by the public.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Public-facing websites and web applications.</item>
        <item>Mobile applications (iOS and Android) — requires platform-specific AT testing, not just web axe scans.</item>
        <item>Multimedia content: all pre-recorded video requires captions; all live video requires real-time captions or equivalent alternative.</item>
        <item>PDF documents and interactive forms.</item>
        <item>Third-party content embedded on government sites (social media embeds, widgets, chat).</item>
        <item>Online services and citizen portals.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="wcag-21-aa-requirements-by-principle">
      <p>WCAG 2.1 is organized into four principles. Here are the key requirements for each:</p>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Principle       | Key Requirements
Perceivable     | Alt text (1.1.1), captions (1.2.x), contrast 4.5:1 normal / 3:1 large (1.4.3), responsive (1.4.4)
Operable        | Keyboard access (2.1.1), no keyboard traps (2.1.2), no time limits or adjustable (2.2.1), skip links (2.4.1), focus visible (2.4.7)
Understandable  | Language attribute (3.1.1), predictable navigation (3.2), error identification (3.3.1), error suggestion (3.3.3)
Robust          | Valid HTML with name/role/value (4.1.2), status messages (4.1.3), compatible with AT
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="video-and-document-requirements">
      <p>Video and PDF accessibility are the most-litigated gaps in government compliance. These requirements are non-negotiable.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>All pre-recorded government video must have accurate, synchronized captions and audio descriptions before publication — not retroactively after a complaint.</statement>
        <rationale>Courts define "accurate" as >= 99% accuracy; auto-generated captions from Whisper or YouTube are ~92-96% accurate and require human QA before claiming compliance.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Captions: accurate, synchronized, complete; include speaker identification and non-speech sounds.</item>
        <item>Audio descriptions: visual information not available in the soundtrack must be described (extended audio descriptions if pauses are insufficient).</item>
        <item>PDFs: tagged PDF structure, defined reading order, alt text for images, labeled form fields, bookmarks for documents over 10 pages.</item>
        <item>Media player: keyboard accessible controls; screen reader compatible; caption and audio description toggle.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="exemptions">
      <p>Exemptions are narrow, individually documented, and must be accompanied by accessible alternatives.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Exemptions are narrow and individually documented; each must be accompanied by an accessible alternative access method.</statement>
        <rationale>DOJ has rejected broad exemptions ("everything before the deadline"). Once an exemption applies, the organization must still provide alternative access to the information or service.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-effective-date content: content published before the compliance date and NOT subsequently altered. Altering old content revokes the exemption.</item>
        <item>Archived content: clearly labeled as archived, not updated, not actively relied on by the public.</item>
        <item>Third-party content not under government control: must still provide an accessible alternative.</item>
        <item>Undue burden: requires documented cost analysis specific to the entity — not a general "too expensive" claim.</item>
        <item>Fundamental alteration: changes the essential nature of the service; very rarely applies to digital accessibility.</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Deploying an accessibility overlay widget as the primary compliance strategy.</description>
        <reason>The DOJ has explicitly warned that overlays do not substitute for underlying code fixes. They remain legally exposed to Title II complaints. Fix the source, not the surface.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="six-step-remediation-roadmap">
      <p>A structured approach from audit through ongoing monitoring is required for government compliance.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track conformance per page per WCAG criterion in a matrix; do not report a single global score — DOJ guidance asks for criterion-level evidence.</statement>
        <rationale>A single percentage score cannot demonstrate that specific legal requirements are met. Criterion-level tracking is required for VPAT 2.5 and for responding to DOJ data requests.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Step 1: Audit
  - Automated scan (axe, WAVE, Lighthouse) on all public pages
  - Manual keyboard and screen reader testing on key user flows
  - PDF and video accessibility audit
  - Mobile app testing (XCUITest + Accessibility Inspector, Espresso AccessibilityChecks)

Step 2: Gap Analysis
  - Map findings to WCAG 2.1 AA criteria
  - Identify pages/flows with highest traffic and severity
  - Inventory pre-effective-date vs. post-effective-date content

Step 3: Remediation Roadmap
  - Critical (blocks access): immediate / hotfix
  - High (high-traffic pages): 0-3 months
  - Medium: 3-6 months
  - Low: 6-12 months

Step 4: Implementation
  - Fix in priority order; test fixes before deploying
  - Caption all new video before publication
  - Remediate PDFs with CommonLook or Adobe Acrobat Pro

Step 5: Ongoing Monitoring
  - Automated axe scan in CI/CD on every PR
  - Quarterly manual audits
  - Annual comprehensive audit with AT testing
  - Accessibility statement updated within 12 months

Step 6: Conformance Documentation
  - VPAT 2.5 INT (covers Section 508 + WCAG 2.1 + EN 301 549)
  - Accessibility Conformance Report (ACR) from test evidence
  - Public accessibility statement published
  - Feedback mechanism live and monitored
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="accessibility-statement-requirements">
      <p>A public-facing accessibility statement is effectively required under the DOJ Title II rule.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Publish an accessibility statement on every government website; it must include conformance level, known limitations, a feedback contact, and a date of last review.</statement>
        <rationale>The DOJ Title II rule effectively requires an accessibility statement. A statement without a current review date (within 12 months) or a working contact address is itself a compliance gap.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Organizational commitment to accessibility.</item>
        <item>Conformance status: "Partially conformant with WCAG 2.1 Level AA" if any known issues exist.</item>
        <item>Known limitations listed individually — vague "ongoing effort" is not sufficient.</item>
        <item>Contact: email and phone for accessibility issues; response within 2 business days.</item>
        <item>Date of last review — must be within 12 months.</item>
        <item>Escalation path (e.g., DOJ ADA Information Line) for unresolved complaints.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="training-and-procurement">
      <p>Building accessibility into the organization requires training and procurement policies.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Training required for: content creators/editors, web developers, procurement officers, customer service, leadership.</item>
        <item>Training topics: WCAG 2.1 AA requirements, accessible document creation, screen reader testing basics, accessible form design, video captioning and audio descriptions.</item>
        <item>Procurement: require VPAT 2.5 INT from all software/SaaS vendors; include remediation timeline and reaudit-on-major-version clauses in contracts.</item>
        <item>Caption all videos before posting to social media; provide alt text for all images; choose accessible social platforms.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agents excel at several compliance tasks but do not replace legal review or human testing.</p>
      <p>Agents excel at: WCAG-criterion mapping of axe/Pa11y findings, drafting accessibility statements, generating VPAT/ACR boilerplate, building remediation roadmap from issue tracker, monitoring CI for regressions. Agents do NOT replace: legal review, real screen-reader user testing, complex video audio description writing, undue-burden analysis. Two-track pipeline: technical agent (audit + fix) + compliance agent (VPAT, statements, contract clauses).</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — model each WCAG criterion gap as an SDD task with criterion ID and conformance evidence requirement.</item>
        <item>Compliance-doc subagent — converts audit JSON into VPAT 2.5 INT (Revised Section 508 + WCAG 2.1) markdown.</item>
        <item>Procurement subagent — extracts a11y clauses from a vendor's VPAT, flags non-conformant criteria.</item>
        <item>See also: a11y-testing (technical scan side) and wcag-22-compliance (criterion details).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <p>These prompt patterns guide agents in government compliance tasks:</p>
      <example type="good" title="ADA Title II conformance audit">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are an ADA Title II compliance agent. Given the audit JSON
(axe + Pa11y + manual screen-reader notes), produce:
  1) WCAG 2.1 AA conformance table (Supports / Partially / Does Not / N/A) per criterion.
  2) Remediation roadmap: Critical (immediate) / High (3mo) / Med (6mo) / Low (12mo).
  3) Draft accessibility statement using DOJ-aligned template.
Cite the WCAG criterion number for every entry. Never assert "Supports" for
a criterion not directly tested.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Vendor VPAT procurement review">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Review this vendor VPAT 2.5 for procurement. List criteria marked "Does Not
Support" or "Partially Supports", their user impact, and required contract
clauses (remediation timeline, escrow, periodic reaudit).
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>@axe-core/cli — WCAG 2.1/2.2 AA scanner. Install: npm i -g @axe-core/cli</item>
        <item>pa11y-ci — Sitemap-driven scan with thresholds. Install: npm i -g pa11y-ci</item>
        <item>lighthouse — Auditing per page. Install: npm i -g lighthouse</item>
        <item>pdfix-pdf-accessibility — PDF/UA validation, remediation. https://pdfix.net</item>
        <item>pac-2024 (PAC) — Free PDF accessibility checker. https://pdfua.foundation</item>
        <item>andi (bookmarklet) — Manual ANDI tool from SSA. https://www.ssa.gov/accessibility/andi/</item>
        <item>ffmpeg + whisper — Auto-caption pipeline (still requires human QA). https://github.com/openai/whisper</item>
        <item>accessibility-insights-cli — MS automated tab-stop and guided checks. https://accessibilityinsights.io</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <p>Various SaaS platforms and services support government compliance at scale:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Siteimprove (SaaS) — REST API. Used widely by US gov; tracks compliance posture, exports gov-style reports.</item>
        <item>Level Access / AudioEye (SaaS) — API + manual audit. Combine automated + human; AudioEye's overlay alone is NOT compliance — DOJ has stated overlays don't substitute for fixes.</item>
        <item>Deque axe Auditor + axe Monitor (SaaS) — API. Continuous monitoring, IGT, regression tracking.</item>
        <item>3PlayMedia (SaaS) — API. Captioning + audio description for video.</item>
        <item>Rev (SaaS) — API. Captions/transcripts; cheaper than 3PlayMedia for English.</item>
        <item>CommonLook (SaaS) — Desktop only. PDF remediation gold standard.</item>
        <item>Allyant (PDF/document remediation) (SaaS / service) — Manual. For long-form docs and forms.</item>
        <item>Section508.gov ICT testing baseline (OSS docs) — Use as procurement baseline.</item>
        <item>GSA Section508.gov VPAT templates (OSS) — Always start from VPAT 2.5 INT.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="vpat-cell-generator-template">
      <p>Shell script generating VPAT conformance table cells from axe JSON output:</p>
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
#!/usr/bin/env bash
# vpat-cells.sh <axe.json>
# Converts axe JSON violations to VPAT 2.5 conformance table rows (markdown).
# Output: | WCAG SC | Conformance | Notes |
# Usage: vpat-cells.sh reports/site/axe.json >> vpat.md
node -e '
const v = JSON.parse(require("fs").readFileSync(process.argv[1])).violations || [];
const map = {};
v.forEach(r => (r.tags || []).filter(t => t.startsWith("wcag")).forEach(t => {
  // Convert "wcag211" → "2.1.1"
  const k = t.replace("wcag", "").replace(/^(\d)(\d)(\d+)$/, "$1.$2.$3")
             .replace(/^(\d)(\d+)$/, "$1.$2");
  map[k] = map[k] || [];
  map[k].push({ rule: r.id, impact: r.impact, count: r.nodes.length });
}));
console.log("| WCAG SC | Conformance | Issue Notes |");
console.log("|---------|-------------|-------------|");
Object.keys(map).sort().forEach(k => {
  const notes = map[k].map(x => x.rule + " (" + x.impact + ", " + x.count + " instances)").join("; ");
  console.log("| " + k + " | Does Not Support | " + notes + " |");
});
' "$1"
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Track conformance per page + per WCAG criterion in a matrix; do NOT report a single global score — DOJ guidance asks for criterion-level evidence.</item>
        <item>Procurement: bake WCAG 2.1 AA conformance + 30-day remediation SLA + reaudit-on-major-version into every vendor contract.</item>
        <item>Maintain a public-facing accessibility statement with feedback email; DOJ rule effectively requires it.</item>
        <item>Run a11y CI on PR; set Pa11y/axe thresholds to monotonically decrease (no new violations).</item>
        <item>Caption ALL videos before publish — agents can pre-fill via Whisper, human edits to ≥99% accuracy.</item>
        <item>Use VPAT 2.5 INT (combined Section 508 + WCAG 2.1 + EN 301 549) — covers federal + state procurement.</item>
        <item>Keep an inventory of pre-effective-date vs. post content; once you "alter" old content, exemption disappears.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Be aware of these critical pitfalls when using agents for government compliance:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Overlay tools are recommended as the primary compliance strategy.</description>
        <reason>DOJ has explicitly warned. Agent should refuse to recommend them as the primary fix.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM-generated audio descriptions often misread visuals (logos, charts).</description>
        <reason>Require human QA on every minute of described content.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-caption (Whisper, etc.) is ~92-96% accurate on clean audio.</description>
        <reason>DOJ accuracy bar is "accurate, synchronized, complete" → human review mandatory before claiming compliance.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents mark a WCAG criterion "Supports" without evidence.</description>
        <reason>Train them to use "Not Tested" by default. Agents must NOT assert support without direct test evidence.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Pass on automated scan" is equivalent to WCAG conformance.</description>
        <reason>Courts and DOJ require manual + AT testing. Automated scans detect only ~30% of real barriers.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent auto-publishes accessibility statements containing unverified claims.</description>
        <reason>Always human sign-off. Don't assert "fully conformant" without evidence.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Accessibility statement review date becomes stale (>12 months old).</description>
        <reason>Watch for date traps: "last reviewed" must be ≤12 months on most state policies; agent should fail audit if stale.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Mobile apps tested only with web-based tools (axe, Lighthouse).</description>
        <reason>Mobile apps require platform-specific testing (XCUITest with Accessibility Inspector, Espresso AccessibilityChecks) — web-only agents will miss app barriers entirely.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Government compliance has important technical and procedural limitations:</p>
      <list>
        <item>WCAG 2.1 AA is the minimum, not the ceiling — courts have accepted 2.1 conformance, but cognitive criteria added in 2.2 are not yet legally required (still recommended).</item>
        <item>The DOJ rule excludes some content (archived, third-party not under control, pre-effective-date unaltered) — these exceptions are commonly misapplied. Document carefully.</item>
        <item>"Undue burden" defense rarely succeeds at scale — must show specific resources analysis, not just "expensive".</item>
        <item>VPAT 2.5 ≠ proof of conformance — auditors require evidence (test reports, code samples).</item>
        <item>Mobile apps + PDFs are the most-litigated gaps; many entities only audit web HTML and miss them.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.ada.gov/resources/2024-03-08-web-rule/"/>
      <link href="https://www.ada.gov/resources/web-guidance/"/>
      <link href="https://www.section508.gov"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/quickref/"/>
      <link href="https://www.itic.org/policy/accessibility/vpat"/>
      <link href="https://webaim.org/articles/laws/"/>
      <ref slug="accessibility-first-design"/>
      <ref slug="a11y-testing"/>
      <ref slug="wcag-22-compliance"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
