<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-domains" title="PMBOK 7 Eight Performance Domains">
  <summary>All eight PMBOK 7 performance domains with purpose, outcomes, key activities, and related methodologies.</summary>

  <section title="Domain Framework">
    <p>Performance domains are concurrent and interconnected — all eight are active throughout the project lifecycle. No domain is sequential to another. Neglecting any one domain produces measurable degradation in others through documented interaction chains.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Assess all eight domains in a single sitting; partial assessments are misleading because domain health is interdependent.</statement>
      <rationale>A green Planning domain masks a red Uncertainty domain until a risk materializes; partial snapshots create false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="1 — Stakeholder">
    <p>Effectively engage all stakeholders throughout the project.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Outcomes: stakeholders identified, engagement strategies active, satisfaction achieved</item>
      <item>Key activities: stakeholder register, engagement level assessment, communications planning</item>
      <item>Related: stakeholder-register, stakeholder-engagement methodologies</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="2 — Team">
    <p>Establish a high-performing project team with shared ownership and continuous development.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Outcomes: collaborative environment, distributed leadership, continuous development</item>
      <item>Key activities: team culture, role clarity (RACI), resource management</item>
      <item>Related: team-development, raci-matrix methodologies</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="3 — Development Approach">
    <p>Select and adapt the optimal delivery approach — Predictive, Iterative, Incremental, Agile, or Hybrid.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Outcomes: approach aligned with project characteristics, continuous improvement incorporated</item>
      <item>Key activities: approach selection, cadence definition, delivery model tailoring</item>
      <item>Related: agile-hybrid-approaches methodology</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="4 — Planning">
    <p>Organize project work with realistic scope, schedule, budget, and resource plans.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Outcomes: articulated scope, achievable schedule, resource plans in place</item>
      <item>Key activities: scope definition, WBS, schedule development, cost estimation, communications planning</item>
      <item>Related: work-breakdown-structure, schedule-development, cost-estimation methodologies</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="5 — Project Work">
    <p>Establish processes and perform work efficiently with appropriate communication and resource management.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Outcomes: efficient work processes, knowledge sharing, procurements handled</item>
      <item>Key activities: plan execution, change management, procurement management</item>
      <item>Related: change-control, procurement-management methodologies</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="6 — Delivery">
    <p>Deliver value and outcomes: scope completed, quality met, stakeholders accept deliverables, benefits realized.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Outcomes: requirements delivered, quality validated, benefits realized</item>
      <item>Key activities: quality management, scope validation, benefits realization, project closure</item>
      <item>Related: quality-management, benefits-realization, project-closure methodologies</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="7 — Measurement">
    <p>Assess project performance with reliable, timely data and generate accurate forecasts.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Outcomes: reliable decision data, clear performance picture, accurate forecasts</item>
      <item>Key activities: metrics definition, progress tracking (EVM), forecasting, lessons learned</item>
      <item>Related: earned-value-management, lessons-learned methodologies</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="8 — Uncertainty">
    <p>Address uncertainty and risk: threats reduced, opportunities captured, project outcomes protected.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Outcomes: threats minimized, opportunities captured, reserves appropriate</item>
      <item>Key activities: risk identification, analysis, response planning, monitoring</item>
      <item>Related: risk-management methodology</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
