<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-interactions" title="Domain Interactions, Assessment Procedure, and Gotchas">
  <summary>Domain interaction chains, health assessment procedure, common mistakes, and agent-specific gotchas for PMBOK 7 performance domain audits.</summary>

  <section title="Domain Interaction Chains">
    <p>When one domain degrades, specific other domains are predictably affected. Use these chains to identify root causes and prioritize remediation.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Stakeholder struggles → Team (morale), Delivery (unclear acceptance), Measurement (disputed metrics)</item>
      <item>Team struggles → Project Work (slower execution), Delivery (quality drops)</item>
      <item>Development Approach struggles → Planning (wrong artifacts), Project Work (wrong cadence), Delivery (wrong increments)</item>
      <item>Planning struggles → Project Work (unclear priorities), Delivery (missed scope), Measurement (no baseline)</item>
      <item>Measurement struggles → all domains (blind decisions without data)</item>
      <item>Uncertainty struggles → all domains (risk materializes everywhere simultaneously)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>When multiple domains are red, identify the single domain whose improvement unblocks the most others; fix that domain first before attempting parallel remediation.</statement>
      <rationale>Parallel remediation across multiple Red domains spreads PM attention too thin; sequenced priority produces completed fixes faster than simultaneous partial progress.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Assessment Procedure">
    <list>
      <item>Gather artifacts: retros, status reports, risk register, sprint logs, issue tracker exports</item>
      <item>Declare the evidence time window (e.g., "last 30 days"); assessments without a declared window are not reproducible</item>
      <item>Score each domain with one quoted evidence item per RAG color</item>
      <item>Identify the weakest domain and explain its cross-domain impact</item>
      <item>Publish no more than 3 priority actions; more than 3 cannot be worked in parallel</item>
      <item>Track domain health as a trend (direction matters more than absolute level)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the assessment on a fixed monthly cadence AND on triggers: incident, scope change, leadership change, team-composition change.</statement>
      <rationale>Monthly cadence catches gradual drift; trigger-based re-scoring catches sudden regressions that monthly timing misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating domains as sequential rather than concurrent.</description>
      <reason>All eight domains require attention simultaneously; skipping one because "we're in planning now" leaves it unmonitored until a late-stage crisis surfaces.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Process over outcomes — tracking activities within a domain rather than domain outcomes.</description>
      <reason>A team can run all the right activities (risk workshops, stakeholder meetings) while domain outcomes (threats mitigated, stakeholders engaged) deteriorate.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>One-time assessment without repeat on a fixed cadence.</description>
      <reason>Domain health changes; a one-time Green assessment gives false confidence for months while conditions drift to Red.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent over-rates Team and Stakeholder domains Green because retros are polite.</description>
      <reason>Counterweight with attrition data and NPS/satisfaction scores; retro politeness is not a valid evidence source for health.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent scores AND prescribes actions in one pass.</description>
      <reason>Bias compounds; split into two prompts: first scoring with evidence, then separate prescriptions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent produces assessments without declaring the evidence time window.</description>
      <reason>Undated assessments cannot be reproduced or audited; require explicit time window in every assessment output.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/pd-assessment.sh">Emits a fresh eight-row assessment skeleton with weakest-domain section</reference>
</text>
