<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="performance-domains-overview Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for performance-domains-overview as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>The 8 domains overlap heavily; teams waste time arguing where an issue "belongs."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>That is the point. Issues usually cascade across domains. Use domain overlap to reveal root causes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Domain colors (green/yellow/red) collapse multi-dimensional reality into a bumper sticker.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Colors are a snapshot. Pair with evidence quotes and trend arrows (is this domain improving or degrading?). Use sparklines to track direction.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Lacks prescribed cadence — easy to do the assessment once and never repeat.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Schedule monthly assessments (the same day each month) AND ad-hoc trigger assessments after major milestones or incidents.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Doesn't say which domain to fix first when several are red.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use domain interaction knowledge to identify the domain that, if improved, unblocks the most others. Often Uncertainty (risks) or Team (morale/engagement).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents over-rate "Team" and "Stakeholder" green because retros are usually polite — counterweight with attrition / NPS data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Retros capture team sentiment in the moment. Attrition and NPS lag but are more reliable signals.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Don't let a single agent both score AND prescribe actions in one pass; bias compounds. Split into two prompts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Scoring agents are subject to anchoring bias. Separate assessment from recommendations to reduce compounding.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Force evidence-per-cell; without it, the agent produces a beige consensus assessment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Evidence forces specificity. Agents without evidence anchors regress to "everything is yellow."</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Watch for stale data: assessments must declare the time window of evidence consulted.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A green domain from January may be red now. Explicit time window prevents false positives.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Domain interactions table is high-value; agents tend to forget cross-domain cause/effect — prompt for it explicitly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents default to siloed thinking. Explicit interaction prompting (e.g., "how do risks cascade to team morale?") yields better root causes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
