<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Onboarding Flows Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `Onboarding Flows` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="activation-event-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Activation event MUST be a single named event with clear criteria (e.g. &apos;first Aha message sent in shared channel&apos;). &apos;User explores the product&apos; is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Activation-definition audit 2024-2026">Vague activation events make measurement impossible; the named event is the only thing the team can optimise against.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="segment-at-signup" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each new user MUST be segmented at signup with ≤ 1 question (role / use-case / company size). Multi-question intake before first value is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Signup-friction audit">Multi-question intake balloons drop-off; one-question segmentation captures most value with minimum friction.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="critical-path-cap-5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The critical path from signup to activation MUST be ≤ 5 required steps. Optional steps don&apos;t count; required-step count above 5 must be cut.</statement>
      <rationale source="TTV reduction audit">Each additional required step loses 10-20%; the 5-step cap is the empirical sweet spot for SaaS activation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="triggered-email-paired-per-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each in-app onboarding step MUST be paired with a triggered email that fires only when user is stuck &gt; 24h. Email blasts unrelated to in-app progress are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Email-product coordination audit">Un-paired emails cause re-engagement spam; triggered email pairing converts at 2-3x batch sends.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="named-onboarding-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The spec MUST name a single human owner accountable for the onboarding flow + activation metric. Group handles forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal RACI for onboarding">Group-owned onboarding stalls; named owner can prioritise iteration without committee.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>