<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-patterns" title="Onboarding Patterns, Segmentation, and Optimization">
  <summary>Five onboarding patterns matched to product types, per-segment routing, critical-path definition, and step-reduction tactics.</summary>

  <section title="Five Onboarding Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select one onboarding pattern per user segment based on product surface and user intent; never apply the same pattern to all segments.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic patterns for all segments compound drop-off — individual users get team setup screens, evaluators get power-user prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>Template-first: start with pre-built example, let users customize. Best for configurable workflow tools (Notion, Trello, Canva). Fastest path to Aha for new users with no prior context.</item>
      <item>Wizard onboarding: step-by-step guided setup with 2-4 personalization questions. Best for products requiring integration/configuration (Slack, Asana, Zapier).</item>
      <item>Interactive tutorial: learn by doing inside a sandboxed demo environment. Best for spatial UIs or complex interactions (Figma, Duolingo). Requires engineering investment.</item>
      <item>Self-serve exploration: minimal guidance with optional help. Best for simple, intuitive products (Instagram, Pinterest). Avoid for products with configurable state.</item>
      <item>Concierge onboarding: high-touch 1:1 setup call. Best for enterprise B2B or products with high switching cost. Does not scale; gates growth on CS headcount.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Segmentation at Signup">
    <rule>
      <statement>Ask exactly one segmentation question at signup to route users to per-segment onboarding flows. Choices should map directly to product use cases, not demographic personas.</statement>
      <rationale>A single routing question + segment-specific flow outperforms perfectly generic flow. More than one routing question increases drop-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>One question, three routes mapping to different onboarding patterns.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
What brings you here?
[ ] Personal use       → Quick-start template flow
[ ] Team collaboration → Team setup wizard
[ ] Just exploring     → Interactive demo
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Critical Path">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the critical path as the minimum steps required to reach the activation event — typically 3-5 steps. Everything else is optional and triggered contextually after activation.</statement>
      <rationale>Every additional required step loses users. Moving optional steps (profile photo, preferences, integrations) to contextual triggers preserves path completion without losing feature depth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Activation event: "created 1 project with 3+ tasks". Critical path has 3 required steps.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
REQUIRED (critical path):
1. Email signup
2. Create first project (with sample task pre-loaded)
3. Add 2 more tasks → activates

OPTIONAL (contextual triggers post-activation):
- Profile photo (trigger: first share action)
- Timezone preference (trigger: first calendar integration)
- Team invite (trigger: user creates 5th task)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Optimization Tactics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-fill all inferable defaults (timezone, language, plan tier) and stop asking for information the product can detect or defer.</statement>
      <rationale>Every required field that can be auto-detected or collected later reduces drop-off without data loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Show a progress checklist with 3-7 items and a completion percentage. Celebrate each completion. Never show an empty product state without a concrete single primary action.</statement>
      <rationale>Progress indicators increase checklist completion rate by 15%. Empty states with no action ("create your first project" with no template) force users to think before they have context.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
