<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Onboarding Hard Rules and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete, testable rules for email sequencing, microcopy, and step gating, plus antipatterns that silently kill activation.</summary>

  <section title="Email Sequence Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Kill the triggered email sequence the moment the user fires the activation event. No exceptions. Every campaign must subscribe to the activation event and exit immediately on fire.</statement>
      <rationale>Email sequences that fire after activation produce embarrassing "still need help?" messages to already-engaged users, which damages trust and increases unsubscribes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure the email sequence as: Email 1 (immediate) = welcome + one action; Email 2 (Day 1) = quick-win tutorial; Email 3 (Day 3) = feature highlight; Email 4 (Day 7) = success story. Stop sending when the user activates.</statement>
      <rationale>Mid-trial check-in on day 7 of a 14-day trial outperforms higher-frequency early emails; users need quiet space to explore before being nudged.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Microcopy Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap all tooltip and in-app guidance copy at 80 characters. Use neutral/direct voice — no exclamations, no emojis, no "Welcome aboard!" filler.</statement>
      <rationale>Appcues and Pendo enforce character limits. Exclamatory copy trends toward corporate-speak that users dismiss without reading.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit tooltip tours to a maximum of 5 items in a single session. More than 8 tooltips trigger dismiss-and-forget behavior.</statement>
      <rationale>Users stop reading tooltip sequences above ~5; every additional tooltip reduces completion of all subsequent tooltips.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step Gating Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never gate the activation event behind profile completion, payment info, or optional preferences. Make those steps available but not required before the user reaches first value.</statement>
      <rationale>Required profile completion blocks the activation event and tanks Day-0 retention — the single strongest predictor of eventual conversion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a no-onboarding control cell (5% of new signups) to measure the true incremental lift of the onboarding flow. Check this quarterly.</statement>
      <rationale>Onboarding sometimes adds zero net activation lift; the answer can only be found by measuring against no-onboarding. Teams that skip this sometimes discover they are adding friction, not removing it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Tooltip tour with 8+ stops shown in the first session.</description>
      <reason>Users dismiss the entire sequence after the third tooltip; critical guidance for later steps is never seen.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>A/B testing onboarding without segmenting by user type.</description>
      <reason>Segment X gains and segment Y losses cancel out; the test appears flat even when one group benefits significantly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Empty state with multiple "create / import / use template" calls to action of equal weight.</description>
      <reason>Users who face a choice with no hierarchy think instead of act. One primary action + two secondary fallbacks is the correct pattern.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/flow-spec.md">Per-segment onboarding flow specification template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/validate-flow.sh">Bash validator — fails if any step lacks a defined analytics event</reference>
</text>
