<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Hourly-to-Fixed Transition Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that govern a controlled hourly-to-fixed transition. These rules prevent the most common revenue-collapse pattern: simultaneous re-pricing of all clients.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-highest-margin-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Convert the single highest-margin existing client first. Margin = (current monthly revenue from client) ÷ (operator hours delivered) compared to target effective hourly. Reject pilots that start with the lowest-margin or newest client.</statement>
      <rationale source="agency-transition postmortems">First conversion has the highest motivation cost — fear of losing the relationship dominates. Starting with the client where you're already over-earning hourly reduces both the financial and emotional risk of refusal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-overlap-window-2-3-clients" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain 2-3 hourly clients during the pilot fixed engagement. Do not convert &gt; 1 client per month during the first quarter of transition.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brennan Dunn / Jonathan Stark casework">Hourly clients are the cash floor while fixed-price economics stabilize. Converting all clients in one round creates a 4-8 week trough that few solo operators survive without external runway.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-productize-one-scope-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Identify exactly ONE repeatable scope (audit, migration, integration, sprint) appearing in ≥ 3 past engagements. Productize that scope into a fixed SKU with explicit deliverables and an exclusions list. Do not productize 2+ SKUs in the same quarter.</statement>
      <rationale source="micro-agency case studies">Multiple new SKUs split positioning, marketing, and operator focus. One SKU with sharp deliverables outsells a menu of three for the first 6-12 months.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-single-reprice-round" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After the pilot fixed engagement closes successfully, re-price all remaining hourly clients in a single one-week communication window. No staggered re-pricing across multiple months.</statement>
      <rationale source="client-perception studies">Staggered re-pricing leaks across the client network ("Why did Acme get $200/hr and I got $150?"). One round, same effective date, same logic — fairness and finality.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-cash-bridge-6-8-weeks" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before starting the transition, document a 6-8 week cash bridge covering trough revenue. Bridge = savings + accessible credit + signed-pipeline revenue scheduled within the trough window. Reject any transition plan with bridge &lt; 6 weeks AT operator's monthly burn.</statement>
      <rationale source="agency closure analyses">Operators forced to abort mid-transition (because of cash, not strategy) end up with worse pricing than where they started. The bridge is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="High-margin first conversion">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Client portfolio (monthly):
  Acme:    $6k rev / 20 hrs = $300/hr effective. Target: $250/hr.  MARGIN +20%
  Beta:    $4k rev / 30 hrs = $133/hr effective. Target: $250/hr.  MARGIN -47%
  Gamma:   $3k rev / 15 hrs = $200/hr effective. Target: $250/hr.  MARGIN -20%

Decision (r1): convert Acme first. Acme client is already paying above target,
so fixed-price conversion is a relabeling, not a price hike.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1: highest-margin client = lowest-friction first convert.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Premature all-at-once transition">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Operator: "I'm going fixed-price across the board next month."

Result:
  Week 1-2:  Two clients reject the conversion. Hourly revenue drops $7k/mo.
  Week 3-6:  Productized SKU not yet selling. Pipeline at zero.
  Week 7:    Operator takes hourly work back at LOWER rate to survive.
  Week 10:   Transition aborted. Net position: worse than starting point.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2 + r5 violation. Simultaneous conversion + no cash bridge = forced retreat.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
