<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cloud Run Monitoring Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for the cloud-run-monitoring methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale + concrete remediation hook.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="structured-json-logging" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cloud Run applications MUST emit structured JSON log entries to stdout with at minimum `severity`, `message`, and a request `trace` field.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Logging docs">Cloud Logging auto-parses JSON from stdout into structured fields; unstructured logs cannot be filtered by field nor power log-based metrics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-sensitive-in-logs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Logs MUST NOT contain credentials, tokens, or PII.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — incident review Q1 2026">Cloud Logging is broadly readable by viewers; logged secrets leak across roles and end up indexed in BigQuery sinks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="alerting-on-key-metrics" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every production service MUST have alerting policies on 5xx rate, p99 request latency, instance count, and CPU utilisation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Run monitoring docs">These four signals catch the dominant failure modes (deploy failure, cold-start tail, traffic burst, resource saturation) without requiring custom instrumentation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="trace-context-propagation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Service-to-service calls MUST propagate `X-Cloud-Trace-Context` so Cloud Trace can reconstruct cross-service spans.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Trace propagation docs">Without header propagation traces fracture into disconnected spans and cross-service root-cause analysis becomes impossible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="notification-channels-before-launch" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Notification channels (PagerDuty, email, Pub/Sub) MUST be wired up and tested before the service serves production traffic.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — SRE on-call runbook">Alerts firing into a black hole offer no detection value; pre-launch verification of channels is the only way to know paging actually reaches a human.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the input fails ALL "Applies If" preconditions or matches ANY "Skip If" disqualifier, do not apply this methodology — route the task to the adjacent sibling instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Even flat checklists need an explicit skip leaf in the decision tree; this rule is the universal terminal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
