<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Incident Triage Checklist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Solo Incident Triage Checklist methodology. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-named-on-call" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every incident has a named operator owning it from detection to closure. &apos;team&apos; / &apos;we&apos; / &apos;&apos; are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — outage postmortems + RACI">Plural ownership during an incident = action paralysis.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-comms-within-15min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>First customer-facing comms (status page or email) MUST go out within 15 minutes of detection. Even &apos;we are investigating&apos; counts.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian incident comms playbook">Silence amplifies anger more than the bug. Acknowledgement buys patience.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-contain-before-fix" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CONTAIN (rollback / feature-flag off) MUST be attempted BEFORE forward-fix on prod. Forward-fix without containment is forbidden unless containment is impossible.</statement>
      <rationale source="SRE practice">Forward-fix on a flaming prod is how 1-hour incidents become 6-hour incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-blameless-postmortem" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Postmortem MUST happen within 72h of resolution, MUST list root cause + ≥1 corrective action, MUST avoid naming individuals (system flaws, not human flaws).</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE book + Etsy blameless">Blameful postmortems suppress reporting; suppressed incidents recur.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-untested-forward-fix" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any forward-fix deployed during an incident MUST be tested in a local repro OR previously-prepared staging clone — NEVER &apos;I think this will work&apos;.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — postmortems">Untested forward-fixes during incidents are the textbook cause of compound outages.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md &quot;Applies If&quot; do not all hold, OR any &quot;Skip If&quot; disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent&apos;s context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-solo-incident-triage-checklist.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
