<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="On-Call Rotation Bootstrap Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the On-Call Rotation Bootstrap methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-explicit-charter-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Publish a one-page On-Call Charter to the team wiki before the first shift. It states: shift length, shift boundaries, participating engineers, acknowledgement SLA, escalation tree (primary + secondary + manager), comp policy, swap policy, named rotation owner.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Book Chapter 11; PagerDuty Operations Maturity Model">An undocumented rotation defaults to whatever the loudest engineer remembers from their last job. The charter is the contract that prevents loudest-engineer drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-ack-sla-per-severity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define an acknowledgement SLA per severity (sev-1=5min, sev-2=15min, sev-3=no SLA). Escalation to secondary fires automatically when primary misses the ack window. The SLA is enforced in the paging tool, not by social pressure.</statement>
      <rationale source="SRE workbook chapter on escalation">Tool-enforced escalation removes cognitive load on the primary ('am I OK to go to sleep?') and protects customer MTTR.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-two-tier-rotation-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default to a two-tier rotation: primary + secondary per shift. The secondary covers primary unavailability, takes over after 4 consecutive pages, and is the second pair of eyes on sev-1. Single-engineer rotation is allowed ONLY for teams of 5-7 with an external SRE retainer.</statement>
      <rationale source="SRE workbook on cognitive load; common burnout postmortems">Single-engineer rotation under unbounded page load is the single highest-correlation cause of on-call resignations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-comp-time-policy-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Off-hours work during on-call accrues compensation: typically 1 hour of time-off-in-lieu per off-hours page-and-respond, capped per shift, with cash payout above the cap. Policy documented in the HR handbook with signatures from engineering leader and HR.</statement>
      <rationale source="research on burnout in on-call rotations; EU/UK/Brazil labour-law on after-hours work">Unpaid 3 AM pages are the single most-cited driver of on-call resignations. Comp must be automatic, defaulted-on, and explicit in the handbook.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-on-call-load-red-line" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define red-line thresholds: &gt;2 off-hours pages/shift OR &gt;3 weekend pages/quarter triggers a load-reduction action (alert tuning, runbook automation, headcount, temporary external SRE). The red-line is checked weekly and reported monthly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Book on on-call sustainability; toil-budget concept">Without a red-line, on-call load drifts upward as alerts proliferate. The red-line forces action when load crosses a quantitative threshold.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-shadow-period-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every new rotation member completes 2 shadow shifts (silent observer on secondary) + 2 supervised solo shifts (primary with the previous primary as named safety-net) before a true solo shift. The paging tool blocks solo primary assignment without a completed shadow record.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — on-call onboarding postmortems">Throwing new joiners into solo primary on day one spikes MTTR; the shadow period internalizes runbook conventions and the paging tool muscle memory.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
