<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="structured-interview-design">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>hr-recruiter</domain>
    <summary>Six-step interview design: define competencies, write questions, build anchors, train interviewers, execute identically, debrief independently. Twice as predictive as unstructured.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>interview-design</tag>
      <tag>hiring-process</tag>
      <tag>structured-hiring</tag>
      <tag>interview-rubric</tag>
      <tag>competency-assessment</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>interview</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Structured Interview Design</title>
    <summary>A six-step process for building a consistent, predictive interview process: define 4-6 competencies, write standardized behavioral and situational questions, build a scored rubric with behavioral anchors, train interviewers, execute identically for every candidate, and debrief with independent scores before discussion. Studies show structured interviews are 2x more predictive of job performance than unstructured ones.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>When interviewers ask different questions and score subjectively, hiring decisions reflect interviewer bias more than candidate ability. Identical questions plus behavioral anchors (1-5 scale) enable cross-candidate comparison and audit trails. Independent scoring before debrief prevents groupthink from collapsing a diverse panel into one person's opinion.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing interview processes for any role with two or more interview rounds.</item>
        <item>Calibrating a new hiring team on a role for the first time.</item>
        <item>Reducing offer-to-hire variance caused by inconsistent interviewer standards.</item>
        <item>Post-mortem after a bad hire traced back to subjective evaluation.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Highly exploratory or research roles where competencies are not yet defined — define them first.</item>
        <item>One-off contract roles where a single screen is sufficient.</item>
        <item>Roles where the assessment is a pure technical test (take-home, live coding) with no behavioral component.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="design-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use the same questions in the same order for every candidate; deviation breaks comparability and introduces interviewer-specific bias.</statement>
        <rationale>Meta-analyses (Schmidt and Hunter, 1998; Structured Interviewing meta-analysis, 2016) show structured interviews have validity twice that of unstructured ones for predicting job performance. Consistency is the mechanism: without it, you are comparing different data points, not different candidates.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="step-1-define-competencies">
        <rule>
          <statement>Identify 4-6 competencies per role; more than 6 cannot be evaluated in a standard interview loop without diluting each assessment.</statement>
          <rationale>Each competency requires 2-3 questions and meaningful scoring time. With 4-6 competencies across 4-5 interview rounds, each round can own 1-2 competencies without overlap.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <section name="competency-profiles-by-level">
          <p>Individual contributor: technical skills, problem-solving, communication, collaboration.</p>
          <p>Manager: leadership, delegation, developing others, strategic thinking.</p>
          <p>Executive: vision, influence, business acumen, change management.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section name="step-2-create-questions">
        <rule>
          <statement>Write 2-3 behavioral questions per competency; pair with 1 situational question for roles where candidates may lack direct experience.</statement>
          <rationale>Behavioral questions ("Tell me about a time...") require real past examples. Situational questions ("What would you do if...") are weaker but necessary when the candidate pool includes career-changers or new graduates.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <section name="question-type-selection">
          <p>Behavioral: past performance; preferred for any competency where the candidate should have prior experience. Situational: hypothetical; use for competencies new-to-role candidates cannot yet demonstrate. Technical: skill assessment; architecture, code, or domain-specific knowledge. Motivational: fit and values; use sparingly, not as a substitute for behavioral evidence.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section name="step-3-build-scoring-rubric">
        <rule>
          <statement>Define behavioral anchors for each score on the rating scale before the interview loop begins; anchors must describe observable behaviors, not impressions.</statement>
          <rationale>Without anchors, a "4" means different things to different interviewers. Behavioral anchors ("Identified root cause; implemented a lasting solution visible to the team") produce cross-interviewer score correlation above 0.8 when calibrated.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <p>Rating scale: 5 = exceptional (far exceeds expectations), 4 = strong (exceeds), 3 = meets, 2 = developing (below), 1 = insufficient (does not meet).</p>
      </section>
      <section name="steps-4-6-train-execute-debrief">
        <rule>
          <statement>Run a calibration session with all interviewers before the first candidate; score a sample response together and discuss divergence.</statement>
          <rationale>Interviewers who have never calibrated together will diverge by 1-2 points on the same evidence. A 30-minute calibration session closes most of that gap before it affects real candidates.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Collect all interviewer scores independently before the debrief meeting; discussing scores first collapses independent signals into one opinion.</statement>
          <rationale>When the first voice in a debrief is strong (hiring manager, senior engineer), subsequent scorers anchor to it regardless of their own evidence. Independent scoring is the primary mechanism for maintaining panel diversity value.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="scoring-and-anchors">
      <section name="rating-scale">
        <rule>
          <statement>Use a 1-5 rating scale; avoid 7- or 10-point scales that introduce false precision without additional behavioral anchor resolution.</statement>
          <rationale>A 1-5 scale maps cleanly to behavioral anchors (exceptional / strong / meets / developing / insufficient). Wider scales force interviewers to make distinctions the anchors cannot support, producing noise rather than signal.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <section name="scale-definitions">
          <p>5 — Exceptional: far exceeds expectations; demonstrates this competency at a level above the role requirements; would be an outlier contributor on the team.</p>
          <p>4 — Strong: exceeds expectations; demonstrates this competency beyond what is minimally required; likely to perform well in the first year without significant ramp.</p>
          <p>3 — Meets: meets expectations; demonstrates this competency at the level the role requires; standard hire.</p>
          <p>2 — Developing: below expectations; demonstrates partial evidence of this competency; would require significant coaching or favorable conditions.</p>
          <p>1 — Insufficient: does not meet requirements; cannot demonstrate this competency; not suitable for this role at this time.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section name="behavioral-anchors">
        <rule>
          <statement>Write behavioral anchors before the interview loop begins, not after scoring; post-hoc anchors are written to justify scores already given.</statement>
          <rationale>Anchors written after scoring rationalize the gut impression rather than defining the evidence standard. Pre-written anchors force the interviewer to look for specific behaviors during the interview, not after.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <example type="good">
          <note>Problem-Solving anchor example. Score 5: "Solved an ambiguous, cross-functional problem; created a framework or approach now used by others on the team." Score 4: "Identified root cause through systematic analysis; implemented a solution that persisted beyond the immediate situation." Score 3: "Solved a standard problem using a known approach; logical reasoning but did not go beyond the expected path." Score 2: "Needed significant guidance; could describe the problem but struggled to identify a path forward independently." Score 1: "Could not demonstrate problem-solving ability; responses were hypothetical or described team effort without personal contribution."</note>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section name="antipatterns">
        <antipattern>
          <description>Scoring "culture fit" as an unanchored gut impression.</description>
          <reason>Unanchored "culture fit" is the most common vector for affinity bias. Replace with a specific competency ("alignment with operating principles", "collaboration style") that has behavioral anchors like any other.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Asking different questions to different candidates and still using a shared scorecard.</description>
          <reason>A scorecard built for Question A cannot validly assess a candidate who answered Question B. The scores are not comparable, and the process will not withstand an audit.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Discussing candidate impressions in Slack or over lunch before the formal debrief.</description>
          <reason>Informal pre-debrief discussion anchors subsequent scorers to the first opinion shared; it functions as an unstructured debrief with no documentation. Written scores before any discussion is the only protection against anchoring.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Panel of more than 5 interviewers per candidate.</description>
          <reason>Beyond 5 interviewers, candidate fatigue produces declining response quality in later rounds, and scorecard aggregation yields diminishing returns. Incremental signal from round 6+ is noise, not information.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
      <section name="process-quality-metrics">
        <p>Interview-to-offer rate: target 15-25%; significantly below may indicate over-filtering, above may indicate insufficient rigor. Quality of hire: percentage of hires meeting or exceeding expectations at 1-year review; target above 80%. Interviewer calibration: score correlation across interviewers on the same candidate; target above 80% agreement within 1 point. Candidate experience: post-interview survey score; target above 4.0/5. Time in interview process: total calendar days from first interview to offer; predictable, not necessarily short, is the target.</p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations-and-gotchas">
      <p>Predictive validity assumes the rubric measures the right competencies; structured interviewing of the wrong things is precise garbage.</p>
      <p>Behavioral anchors written by an LLM read as adjective lists; they need observable verbs to be scoreable.</p>
      <p>Calibration drifts silently as interviewers absorb each other's anchoring during loops.</p>
      <p>Panels of more than 5 interviewers introduce candidate fatigue without raising signal — the marginal interviewer adds noise.</p>
      <p>Independent scoring "before discussion" is a policy, not a control; without technical lockout, in practice scores leak via Slack.</p>
      <p>Cross-cultural pragmatics: Western-style structured interviews under-rate candidates from cultures that downplay personal credit ("we did" vs "I did").</p>
      <p>Assessment center-style structured interviews require trained assessors; agent-trained-only interviewers will skip the calibration practice and rate raw.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive structured-interview design as a six-stage pipeline owned by faion-recruiter-agent. Stage 1 (competency definition, opus) — interrogates the JD + leveling rubric and emits a 4-6 row competency table with weights summing to 100. Stage 2 (question generation, sonnet) — 2-3 behavioral + 1 situational + 1 technical-or-motivational per competency, parameterized by role level. Stage 3 (rubric authoring, sonnet) — 1-5 scale per competency with observable behavioral anchors at each level. Stage 4 (round design, opus) — assigns competencies to rounds with no double-coverage and minimum 2 panel members per critical competency. Stage 5 (calibration pack, sonnet) — strong / borderline / weak mock answers per question with the "right" rubric scores. Stage 6 (debrief synthesis, opus) — only post-independent-submission; surfaces variance ≥2, evidence-vs-impression language, ranked candidate comparison.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>4-6 competencies, integer weights summing to 100. Any deviation is a smell.</item>
        <item>One competency per question, one question per competency primary (others can re-probe).</item>
        <item>Behavioral anchors: observable verb + measurable outcome. "Re-architected payment retry, dropping failures from 12% to 3%" not "strong systems thinker".</item>
        <item>Cap loop at 4-5 interviewers; more than 5 raises fatigue, not signal.</item>
        <item>Run a 60-min calibration session per new role family; rerun whenever a new interviewer joins.</item>
        <item>Every interviewer scores independently before the debrief — enforce technically (ATS lock), not by policy.</item>
        <item>Track inter-rater agreement (Cohen's kappa per competency); if less than 0.4 sustained, recalibrate before any more hires.</item>
        <item>Every quarter, audit hire vs no-hire decisions against actual 12-month performance. Recalibrate anchors if predictive validity drifts.</item>
        <item>Behavioral + situational + technical, in that order of weight, for most knowledge work.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Agents conflate "competency" with "trait" and produce non-scoreable rubrics ("emotionally intelligent", "growth-minded"). Force observable verbs.</item>
        <item>LLMs default to 5-point scales for everything; force a justification per competency.</item>
        <item>Generated questions cluster in leadership/communication; weight the prompt to enforce technical/execution coverage.</item>
        <item>Agents will write "exceeds expectations" anchors that are tautological — push for outcomes, not levels.</item>
        <item>Independent-scoring violations are invisible to LLMs; they read submitted scorecards and assume independence. Add a timestamp / Slack-traffic check.</item>
        <item>Calibration packs auto-generated by an LLM are too on-the-nose — borderline cases need real ambiguity, not surface-level mid-cases. Pull real anonymized historical answers when possible.</item>
        <item>Panel composition: agents will assign the same competency to all panelists "for safety", destroying coverage. Constrain at the prompt level.</item>
        <item>Mandatory human-in-loop: (1) competency table approval (HRBP), (2) legal-risk pass on questions, (3) every score, (4) every hire decision, (5) any anchor change after launch.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/interview-design-doc.md" purpose="Interview design document: role overview, competencies with weights, round structure, questions per round."/>
      <template path="templates/scorecard.md" purpose="Per-interviewer scorecard: competency scores, STAR notes per question, hire recommendation."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="star-interview-method"/>
      <ref slug="star-interview-framework"/>
      <ref slug="interview-methods"/>
      <link href="https://rework.withgoogle.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.shrm.org/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
