<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="stakeholder-analysis Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for stakeholder-analysis. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>List every party who is affected by, has influence over, must approve, will implement, or will use the solution.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Missing a stakeholder early guarantees conflicting or incomplete requirements arriving late.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document influence, impact, attitude, knowledge, needs, and communication style for each identified stakeholder.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without per-stakeholder attributes, engagement is generic and misses resistance early.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Place stakeholders on a 2x2 power-interest grid: Manage Closely (high/high), Keep Satisfied (high/low), Keep Informed (low/high), Monitor (low/low).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Grid quadrant determines engagement cadence and channel; without this, effort is spread evenly across unequal stakeholders.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For each key stakeholder, record specific needs, concerns, success criteria, and current pain points.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stated needs alone are insufficient; unstated concerns drive resistance if not surfaced early.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign an engagement approach (Active/Consult/Inform), frequency, and method to each stakeholder based on their grid quadrant.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A single plan for all stakeholders wastes sponsor time and under-invests in high-impact resistors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat stakeholder analysis as a living activity: re-run the salience classifier after org events (reorg, leadership change, regulatory letter).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">BAKOK 3 explicitly calls stakeholder analysis a continuous activity; static artifacts go stale in 2-6 weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Mendelow for engagement cadence (which quadrant maps to which channel), not for prioritization.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mendelow flattens politics to two axes and is silent on legitimacy and urgency; it is a channel selector, not a prioritization model.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply Mitchell-Agle-Wood (power x legitimacy x urgency) to classify each stakeholder into one of 8 types: dormant, discretionary, demanding, dominant, dangerous, dependent, definitive, non-stakeholder.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Salience tells you who matters and in what order; Mendelow tells you which channel to use. They are complementary, not substitutes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require cited evidence (quote, transcript line, org-chart entry) for every salience axis; return "unknown" if evidence is absent — never infer urgency from tone alone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLM urgency inference from tone is a known failure mode; a regulatory deadline or contractual SLA is the only valid urgency signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick ONE responsibility model per program before any artifact is produced; document the choice and its rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">RACI, RASCI, DACI, and RAPID use some of the same letters with different meanings; mixing models within a program makes every role assignment ambiguous.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enforce RACI integrity mechanically: exactly one Accountable per row, at least one Responsible, no R+A collapse to a single person. Lint in CI.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Human-edited RACI tables drift toward multiple A entries and R-spam; a linter is cheaper than an audit finding.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep stakeholder, persona, and actor artifacts strictly separate: a stakeholder row never becomes a persona; an actor (UML) is a system-interaction role with no political weight; a persona has no decision authority.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Conflating them breaks requirements traceability; a persona that inherits engagement cadence from a stakeholder produces meaningless engagement plans.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain an explicit non-stakeholders list. Documenting exclusions prevents repeated re-litigation of who belongs on the register.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a declared exclusion list, every new team member re-opens the same boundary debates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before classifying any stakeholder, persist a glossary.md and model-choice.md in the program BA folder declaring: stakeholder definition (verbatim from BABOK 3 §3.2 or ISO 21502 §4.4), responsibility model chosen, salience model chosen, and rationale for rejecting alternatives.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs treat "stakeholder" as a synonym for "user" or "persona" by default; injecting the frozen definition verbatim into the system prompt is the only reliable mitigation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sponsor signs the register baseline; subsequent diffs require sponsor acknowledgment only for attitude or accountability changes, not for contact info updates.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Keeps sign-off lightweight while protecting the high-stakes fields that affect engagement strategy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
