<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Stakeholder Analysis — 6-Step Framework">
  <summary>Identifies, characterizes, maps, and engages all parties who affect or are affected by a change initiative.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Identify Stakeholders">
    <rule>
      <statement>List every party who is affected by, has influence over, must approve, will implement, or will use the solution.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing a stakeholder early guarantees conflicting or incomplete requirements arriving late.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Stakeholder categories:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Customer — external beneficiary (end users, buyers)</item>
      <item>End User — direct solution users (employees, customers)</item>
      <item>Sponsor — provides resources or authority (executive, budget owner)</item>
      <item>Domain SME — subject matter expert (process owners, specialists)</item>
      <item>Implementation SME — technical expert (developers, architects)</item>
      <item>Tester — validates solution (QA team, UAT participants)</item>
      <item>Regulator — compliance authority (legal, audit, government)</item>
      <item>Supplier — external provider (vendors, partners)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Characterize Each Stakeholder">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document influence, impact, attitude, knowledge, needs, and communication style for each identified stakeholder.</statement>
      <rationale>Without per-stakeholder attributes, engagement is generic and misses resistance early.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Map Influence and Impact">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place stakeholders on a 2x2 power-interest grid: Manage Closely (high/high), Keep Satisfied (high/low), Keep Informed (low/high), Monitor (low/low).</statement>
      <rationale>Grid quadrant determines engagement cadence and channel; without this, effort is spread evenly across unequal stakeholders.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Identify Needs and Concerns">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each key stakeholder, record specific needs, concerns, success criteria, and current pain points.</statement>
      <rationale>Stated needs alone are insufficient; unstated concerns drive resistance if not surfaced early.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Plan Engagement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign an engagement approach (Active/Consult/Inform), frequency, and method to each stakeholder based on their grid quadrant.</statement>
      <rationale>A single plan for all stakeholders wastes sponsor time and under-invests in high-impact resistors.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Manage Relationships Continuously">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat stakeholder analysis as a living activity: re-run the salience classifier after org events (reorg, leadership change, regulatory letter).</statement>
      <rationale>BABOK 3 explicitly calls stakeholder analysis a continuous activity; static artifacts go stale in 2-6 weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Conflict resolution sequence: understand each position, find common ground, identify trade-offs, escalate to sponsor if needed, document decision with rationale.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="RACI for BA Activities">
    <example type="good">
      <note>BA activity responsibility assignments using RACI (R=Responsible, A=Accountable, C=Consulted, I=Informed).</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Activity                | Sponsor | SME | User | BA |
|-------------------------|---------|-----|------|----|
| Define requirements     | A       | C   | R    | R  |
| Approve requirements    | A       | C   | I    | R  |
| Validate solution       | A       | C   | R    | R  |
| Accept delivery         | A       | C   | R    | I  |
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/stakeholder-register.md">Register table for tracking all stakeholders with classifications</reference>
  <reference path="templates/stakeholder-profile.md">Per-stakeholder profile template with needs, concerns, and engagement history</reference>
</text>
