<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-models" title="Stakeholder Models — Salience and Responsibility">
  <summary>Covers the Mendelow and Mitchell-Agle-Wood models for stakeholder classification and RACI/RASCI/DACI/RAPID for responsibility assignment.</summary>

  <section title="Mendelow Power-Interest Grid (1991)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Mendelow for engagement cadence (which quadrant maps to which channel), not for prioritization.</statement>
      <rationale>Mendelow flattens politics to two axes and is silent on legitimacy and urgency; it is a channel selector, not a prioritization model.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating Mendelow as the only classification model.</description>
      <reason>It does not capture urgency or legitimacy; a high-power actor without legitimacy is a bully, not a stakeholder — the correct response is escalation, not accommodation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Mitchell-Agle-Wood Salience Model (1997)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply Mitchell-Agle-Wood (power x legitimacy x urgency) to classify each stakeholder into one of 8 types: dormant, discretionary, demanding, dominant, dangerous, dependent, definitive, non-stakeholder.</statement>
      <rationale>Salience tells you who matters and in what order; Mendelow tells you which channel to use. They are complementary, not substitutes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require cited evidence (quote, transcript line, org-chart entry) for every salience axis; return "unknown" if evidence is absent — never infer urgency from tone alone.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM urgency inference from tone is a known failure mode; a regulatory deadline or contractual SLA is the only valid urgency signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Classifying legitimacy using Anglo-American corporate norms only.</description>
      <reason>In high-context cultures (JP, KR, parts of EU) and in jurisdictions with statutory bodies (e.g., DE Betriebsrat), legitimacy flows through indirect networks the standard model does not capture.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Responsibility Models">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick ONE responsibility model per program before any artifact is produced; document the choice and its rationale.</statement>
      <rationale>RACI, RASCI, DACI, and RAPID use some of the same letters with different meanings; mixing models within a program makes every role assignment ambiguous.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>RACI — steady-state operations: exactly one A per row, one or more R</item>
      <item>RASCI — adds S (Support); use when "support" roles are common (data ops, infra)</item>
      <item>DACI — time-boxed decisions with a single Driver and an Approver</item>
      <item>RAPID — cross-functional decisions with split Input and Agreement roles</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce RACI integrity mechanically: exactly one Accountable per row, at least one Responsible, no R+A collapse to a single person. Lint in CI.</statement>
      <rationale>Human-edited RACI tables drift toward multiple A entries and R-spam; a linter is cheaper than an audit finding.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/raci-lint.sh">Bash script that fails if any RACI row has != 1 A or 0 R</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Stakeholder vs. Adjacent Concepts">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep stakeholder, persona, and actor artifacts strictly separate: a stakeholder row never becomes a persona; an actor (UML) is a system-interaction role with no political weight; a persona has no decision authority.</statement>
      <rationale>Conflating them breaks requirements traceability; a persona that inherits engagement cadence from a stakeholder produces meaningless engagement plans.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain an explicit non-stakeholders list. Documenting exclusions prevents repeated re-litigation of who belongs on the register.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a declared exclusion list, every new team member re-opens the same boundary debates.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
