<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="stakeholder-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for stakeholder-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating Mendelow as the only classification model.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>It does not capture urgency or legitimacy; a high-power actor without legitimacy is a bully, not a stakeholder — the correct response is escalation, not accommodation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Classifying legitimacy using Anglo-American corporate norms only.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>In high-context cultures (JP, KR, parts of EU) and in jurisdictions with statutory bodies (e.g., DE Betriebsrat), legitimacy flows through indirect networks the standard model does not capture.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent silently merges "stakeholder" with "user" or "persona".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Default LLM training conflates these; fix by forcing the chosen stakeholder_definition into the system prompt verbatim every call.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent over-assigns R and C in RACI — every role gets something.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Constrain output: max 1 A, max 3 R, require one-line rationale per C; validate with the lint script.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent infers urgency from message tone rather than from a cited deadline or SLA.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tone-based urgency is statistically biased; require "urgency_source: deadline/SLA/contractual" and reject entries without it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>BABOK section citations hallucinate plausible-sounding clause numbers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Maintain a curated bakok-toc.md and constrain the agent to cite only from it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent auto-publishes the register.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Names, attitudes, and salience scores are confidential; one accidental share ends stakeholder trust.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
