<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="cognitive-inclusion-design">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Design for cognitive diversity: ADHD, autism, dyslexia, anxiety. Reduce cognitive load with chunking, progress indicators, and customizable settings.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
      <tag>cognitive</tag>
      <tag>inclusion</tag>
      <tag>adhd</tag>
      <tag>autism</tag>
      <tag>dyslexia</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Cognitive Inclusion Design</title>
    <summary>A design methodology that reduces cognitive load and adapts interfaces for users with ADHD, autism spectrum, dyslexia, dyscalculia, anxiety, low literacy, and aging cognition through structural patterns (chunking, predictability, progress indicators) and optional settings (focus mode, dyslexia font, reduced motion, extended time limits).</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Traditional accessibility focuses on visual and motor impairments; cognitive disabilities are larger in population but underserved by WCAG 2.2. Forms, tax workflows, healthcare portals, and government services lose significant user populations to cognitive friction that automated tools cannot detect. W3C COGA Task Force and WCAG 3.0 working draft add specific cognitive guidelines that will become compliance targets; designing for them now prevents retrofitting.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing for users with ADHD, autism, dyslexia, dyscalculia, anxiety, low-literacy, or aging cognition.</item>
        <item>Adding plain-language, focus mode, reduced-motion, customizable text/layout, time-extension features.</item>
        <item>Reviewing flows where cognitive load is the dominant friction (forms, taxes, healthcare, legal, government).</item>
        <item>Aligning with WCAG 3.0 working draft cognitive guidelines and W3C COGA Task Force gap analysis.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure visual / motor accessibility—handle via WCAG 2.2 AA + assistive-tech testing first.</item>
        <item>Marketing surfaces with single-action goals (CTA + form)—usually does not need cognitive customization.</item>
        <item>Highly regulated technical interfaces (industrial control) where literal labeling is already required.</item>
        <item>As a substitute for plain-language editing—cognitive design assumes content is already plain.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="design-patterns-by-profile">
      <p>Concrete design patterns for four cognitive profiles: general cognitive load reduction, ADHD, autism spectrum, and dyslexia.</p>

      <section name="general-cognitive-load-reduction">
        <p>These patterns benefit all users and provide the highest inclusion return when combined:</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Structure all content with a clear visual hierarchy, chunk information into groups of 5 or fewer items, and make navigation predictable and consistent across screens.</statement>
          <rationale>Working memory limits apply to all users; cognitive disabilities lower the threshold, so patterns that reduce load universally provide the highest inclusion return.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Clear heading hierarchy—users scan by heading, not by reading paragraph by paragraph.</item>
          <item>Non-intrusive notifications—user-controllable timing and position.</item>
          <item>Error messages—plain language, non-blaming ("The email address looks incomplete" not "Invalid input"), with a clear corrective action.</item>
          <item>Time limits—extend or eliminate where possible; always warn before expiry and offer extension without loss of progress.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="adhd-friendly-patterns">
        <p>ADHD impairs working memory and sustained attention. Design for interruption recovery:</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Provide progress indicators for all multi-step tasks, auto-save on every input, and a bookmark/resume capability for long flows.</statement>
          <rationale>ADHD impairs working memory and sustained attention; losing progress on interruption causes abandonment and distrust.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Progress indicators: step N of M, percentage complete, or visual stepper.</item>
          <item>Auto-save: triggered on every field blur or every 30 seconds—never on page close only.</item>
          <item>Reduced-motion option: provided as a settings toggle, not assumed system-wide via prefers-reduced-motion alone.</item>
          <item>Focus mode: hides non-essential navigation and ambient content during task completion.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="autism-friendly-patterns">
        <p>Autistic users benefit from literal language, predictability, and clear warnings about state changes:</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Use literal, unambiguous language throughout—no idioms, metaphors, or sarcasm—and warn users before any screen transition or state change.</statement>
          <rationale>Ambiguous language and unexpected transitions are common sources of anxiety and disorientation for autistic users.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Predictable interactions: same action always produces same result across the product.</item>
          <item>Clear visual boundaries between content regions.</item>
          <item>Sensory-friendly color palettes: avoid high saturation or flashing content; offer a low-stimulation theme.</item>
          <item>Transition warnings: modal or inline notice before navigating away from a partially-completed task.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="dyslexia-friendly-patterns">
        <p>Dyslexic readers benefit from specific typography and spacing settings:</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Set default line height to at least 1.5, left-align all body text (never justify), and offer a dyslexia-friendly font as an opt-in setting rather than a global default.</statement>
          <rationale>Justified text creates uneven word spacing that disrupts reading flow for dyslexic readers; left-aligned text preserves consistent spacing. Dyslexia fonts (e.g., OpenDyslexic) have weak empirical support as universal defaults but are valued by individual users.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Letter spacing: offer a setting to increase spacing to at least 0.12em.</item>
          <item>High contrast modes: multiple options beyond system dark mode.</item>
          <item>Text-to-speech integration: accessible via keyboard, not hidden in menus.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="implementation-rules">
      <p>Rules for translating patterns into working interfaces:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Make all cognitive customization settings (font, spacing, motion, focus mode) discoverable, persistent across sessions, and accessible without navigating into deep settings menus.</statement>
        <rationale>A customization option that users cannot find or that resets on each visit provides zero benefit; discoverability and persistence are the minimum viability bar.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not remove motion globally based on prefers-reduced-motion alone; audit which animations are critical (focus indicators, progress feedback) before suppressing them.</statement>
        <rationale>Indiscriminate motion removal breaks critical feedback signals that sighted users rely on for orientation; targeted suppression preserves function.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Review time-limit removal with the security team; session-timeout limits may be non-negotiable security requirements that need a joint UX + security solution.</statement>
        <rationale>Time limits often exist for security reasons; unilateral removal creates vulnerabilities that require a coordinated design rather than a UX-only decision.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="evidence-caveats">
      <p>Known limitations of cognitive inclusion techniques:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Dyslexia-friendly fonts" (e.g., OpenDyslexic) have weak empirical support—provide as option, not default.</description>
        <reason>Empirical evidence for dyslexia fonts as universal defaults is weak; offer as a user-controlled option rather than imposing on users who may find it harder to read.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Customization (font, color, spacing) only helps if discoverable and persistent across sessions.</description>
        <reason>A hidden or session-reset setting provides zero benefit; implementation is as critical as the design pattern itself.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Plain-language and "literal language" can clash with branded voice; product needs a tone-of-voice exception list.</description>
        <reason>Cognitive design patterns assume content is already written in plain language; restructuring a screen cannot fix fundamentally complex or jargon-heavy source text.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Reducing motion globally can break critical animations (focus indicators, progress feedback).</description>
        <reason>Indiscriminate motion removal breaks critical feedback signals; scope carefully and test with users relying on animation for navigation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Time-limit removal can collide with security session timeouts—needs UX + security joint review.</description>
        <reason>Some time limits exist for security reasons; unilateral removal creates vulnerabilities that require coordinated design.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Most automated tools cannot detect cognitive issues; requires structured manual review + user research.</description>
        <reason>Cognitive accessibility requires human evaluation. Automated tools cover only syntactic checks (headings, labels); they cannot evaluate reading level, mental model alignment, or interaction flow clarity.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A multi-agent workflow for cognitive inclusion assessment and implementation:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use a subagent to run a Cognitive Accessibility Checklist (W3C COGA + Hassell Inclusion + Microsoft Inclusive Design) against each screen using DOM + content snapshots. A second agent rewrites flagged copy at a target reading level (Hemingway grade ≤6, Flesch-Kincaid ≥70) and produces alternative shorter versions. A third proposes settings (focus mode, font, motion) and persistence design. Recruitment of cognitive-disabled users for validation is a human responsibility.</statement>
        <rationale>Cognitive inclusion is multidisciplinary: pattern detection requires templates, copy rewriting requires readability tooling, settings design requires persistence architecture, and validation requires user research. Subagents excel at the template and tooling phases; humans handle the strategic and research phases.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <rule>
        <statement>faion-usability-agent runs cognitive checklist, rewrites copy, proposes setting matrix. faion-ux-researcher-agent recruits and runs sessions with cognitively diverse users. faion-sdd-executor-agent implements settings UI, persists preferences, applies font/spacing tokens.</statement>
        <rationale>Each subagent specializes in a phase: pattern detection and copy rewriting (usability), user research and validation (research), and implementation and persistence (SDD).</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <p>Effective prompts for cognitive inclusion subagents:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>For readability analysis: "For page [url], output: (1) Flesch-Kincaid grade level of body copy, (2) sentences over 20 words, (3) idioms, metaphors, irony, sarcasm—list each with literal rewrite, (4) jargon—list each with definition. Output as a fix-list, not narrative."</statement>
        <rationale>Specific readability metrics and structured output make the analysis actionable for both agents and humans. Literal rewrites reduce back-and-forth.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>For focus mode design: "Propose a 'Focus Mode' for this page: items to hide (decoration, secondary nav, animations), items to keep (primary task, save button, exit). Provide CSS class strategy that does not break keyboard order or screen-reader traversal."</statement>
        <rationale>Specifying the output format (CSS classes, keyboard order) ensures the agent considers implementation constraints and accessibility.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>Tools for measuring and enforcing cognitive accessibility:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>textlint + textlint-rule-write-good: Plain-language linting in CI. Install: npm i -D textlint textlint-rule-write-good.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated plain-language enforcement catches common jargon and complex-sentence patterns in CI.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>proselint: Style + clarity linter. Install: pip install proselint.</statement>
        <rationale>Prose-specific linting for readability and clarity.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>readability (pip install readability): Flesch-Kincaid, SMOG, Coleman-Liau scores. Docs: github.com/andreasvc/readability.</statement>
        <rationale>Quantify reading level; Flesch-Kincaid ≥70 and grade level ≤6 are common cognitive inclusion targets.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>vale: Configurable prose linter with plain-language style guides. Docs: vale.sh.</statement>
        <rationale>Build custom prose rules aligned with brand voice and cognitive accessibility targets.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>axe-core cognitive rule extension: Limited cognitive checks (focus, blinking, time). Docs: deque.com/axe.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated but limited; combine with manual review.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>motion-prefers-checker (custom): Lints CSS for prefers-reduced-motion coverage.</statement>
        <rationale>Ensure motion overrides are comprehensive and avoid blanket disabling.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-platforms">
      <p>External services for cognitive accessibility:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Hemingway Editor: SaaS. Partial agent support (no API; emulate with readability). Useful as design reference.</statement>
        <rationale>Visual readability feedback. No API but results can be replicated via readability tooling.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Acrolinx: SaaS. REST API. Enterprise plain-language enforcement.</statement>
        <rationale>Scalable API-driven plain-language enforcement for large teams.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Readable.com: SaaS. REST API. Bulk readability scoring.</statement>
        <rationale>API-driven bulk analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Userway / accessiBe: SaaS overlay. Avoid; not a substitute for fixes.</statement>
        <rationale>Overlay widgets cannot fix structural cognitive issues and may worsen accessibility if misconfigured.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Recite Me: SaaS. Partial agent support via widget embed. User-side customization toolbar.</statement>
        <rationale>User-side customization as an alternative to source-code changes, but limited to overlay widget capabilities.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Texthelp Read &amp; Write: SaaS. Extension. Validate compatibility, not a fix.</statement>
        <rationale>A user's assistive tool; ensure compatibility, but not a replacement for accessible design.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Microsoft Immersive Reader: SaaS. Embed API. Strong reference for reading customization patterns.</statement>
        <rationale>Exemplary implementation of customizable reading settings; use as design reference for focus mode and font/spacing options.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Offer an explicit "Reading preferences" panel (font, size, line-height, contrast, motion). Persist to user account.</statement>
        <rationale>User control and persistence are non-negotiable for inclusion.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Default to system settings: prefers-reduced-motion, prefers-color-scheme, forced-colors, prefers-contrast.</statement>
        <rationale>Respect OS-level accessibility preferences by default, then allow override.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Show progress for any task >2 steps—both numeric ("3 of 5") and visual.</statement>
        <rationale>Multiple progress representations accommodate different cognitive strengths.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Auto-save every form field on blur; never lose user input on session expiry.</statement>
        <rationale>Interruptions are common for cognitively disabled users; data loss breaks trust and causes abandonment.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use literal language for instructions; reserve metaphor for marketing copy with literal alt.</statement>
        <rationale>Literal language is unambiguous; metaphor requires inference and can be misunderstood by some cognitive profiles.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>For time limits, offer extend / disable. If security forces a limit, warn at 80% with clear extend control.</statement>
        <rationale>Some cognitive profiles cannot work under time pressure; extend/disable is essential. If security requires a limit, joint UX + security design is required.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Avoid all-caps for emphasis (some screen readers spell letter-by-letter and dyslexic readers struggle).</statement>
        <rationale>Use bold or color instead of all-caps for emphasis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Provide a non-blaming error message format: "Phone needs 10 digits—you entered 9."</statement>
        <rationale>Non-blaming error messages reduce anxiety and help users self-correct.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Common mistakes agents make when implementing cognitive inclusion:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents add jargon to "sound professional"—enforce a banned-word list (utilize → use, leverage → use, etc.).</description>
        <reason>LLM default tone is formal and jargon-heavy. Provide a banned-word list and require ≤20 words/sentence + ≤2 ideas per sentence.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs default to long sentences; require max 20 words/sentence and ≤2 ideas per sentence.</description>
        <reason>Cognitive inclusion requires short, simple sentences. Explicit constraints prevent complex sentence structures.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents apply OpenDyslexic globally—keep it opt-in; default font choice is contested.</description>
        <reason>OpenDyslexic empirical support is weak. Treat as user-optional, not default.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Reduce motion" agent adds * { animation: none } blanket rule, breaking focus indicators—scope carefully.</description>
        <reason>Indiscriminate motion removal breaks critical UX. Audit which animations are essential (focus, progress) before suppressing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Time-limit removal vs. security session: agent must surface this as a trade-off, not silently extend.</description>
        <reason>Some time limits are security-critical. Agent must alert humans to this conflict instead of unilaterally removing the limit.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents recommend overlay widgets—refuse; document fix at source.</description>
        <reason>Overlay widgets cannot fix structural issues and may worsen accessibility.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Cognitive needs are heterogeneous; avoid grouping users by diagnosis. Design for needs (focus, time, structure), not labels.</description>
        <reason>Two autistic users may have completely different needs. Design for underlying needs (structure, literal language) rather than diagnostic labels.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="references">
      <p>External references and standards for cognitive inclusion:</p>
      <list>
        <item>W3C Cognitive and Learning Disabilities (COGA) Task Force—w3.org/WAI/cognitive/</item>
        <item>W3C "Making Content Usable for People with Cognitive and Learning Disabilities"—w3.org/TR/coga-usable/</item>
        <item>WCAG 3.0 Working Draft—w3.org/TR/wcag-3.0/</item>
        <item>Microsoft Inclusive Design Toolkit—inclusive.microsoft.design</item>
        <item>"Cognitive Accessibility Roadmap and Gap Analysis" (W3C)—w3.org/TR/coga-gap-analysis/</item>
        <item>Hassell Inclusion, "Cognitive Accessibility Patterns"—hassellinclusion.com</item>
        <item>Plain Language Action Network (PLAIN)—plainlanguage.gov</item>
        <item>Centre for Inclusive Design, "The Benefit of Designing for Everyone"—centreforinclusivedesign.org.au</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/cognitive/"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/coga-usable/"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/wcag-3.0/"/>
      <link href="https://inclusive.microsoft.design"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/coga-gap-analysis/"/>
      <link href="https://plainlanguage.gov"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
