<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="blurred-roles-team-evolution">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-operations</domain>
    <summary>Modern AI-era product teams operate as overlapping Venn diagrams with cross-functional fluency, replacing relay-race handoffs. Every role holds secondary competencies in adjacent disciplines.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>team-structure</tag>
      <tag>product-operations</tag>
      <tag>ai-augmented-teams</tag>
      <tag>organizational-design</tag>
      <tag>cross-functional</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Blurred Roles and Team Evolution</title>
    <summary>Modern AI-era product teams operate as overlapping Venn diagrams rather than relay-race handoffs. Each role (PM, designer, engineer, data) is expected to hold fluency in adjacent disciplines. The ratio shifts toward more PMs relative to engineers as discovery, evals, and prioritization become the bottleneck — not coding. Every overlap zone must have one human DRI; agents fill the zone but do not own the decision.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Handoff-based structures slow AI-era development. When models can code at scale, the bottleneck moves upstream to discovery, evaluation, and judgment calls. Cross-functional fluency — not specialization in isolation — is what allows a small team to out-learn a large one. Andrew Ng's "2 PMs : 1 Engineer" inversion captures the ratio shift; the Venn metaphor captures the operating model shift.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing or auditing role splits for an AI-augmented product team</item>
        <item>Migrating a relay-race workflow (spec → design → eng → QA) into overlapping ownership</item>
        <item>Framing solopreneur staffing: which roles to absorb, delegate to agents, or keep as a human hire</item>
        <item>Calibrating PM:Engineer ratios when agent throughput shifts the bottleneck to discovery</item>
        <item>Writing role descriptions or hiring scorecards that assume cross-disciplinary fluency</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Heavily regulated environments (medical devices, aerospace, SOX, IEC 62304) where role separation is a compliance requirement — blurring violates the audit trail</item>
        <item>Large-scale orgs (>50 engineers) with established RACI — this is a future-state model, not a refactor playbook</item>
        <item>Performance-management decisions — this is an operating-model lens, not a competency framework</item>
        <item>Day-to-day task assignment within a single sprint — use a normal queue/board</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="core-shift">
      <p>Traditional product teams pass work in sequence: PM writes spec, designer designs, engineer builds, QA tests. AI-era teams operate as overlapping Venn diagrams. Each discipline participates earlier and across more phases. The overlap is intentional — it is the operating model.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every Venn-overlap zone must have exactly one human DRI. Agents fill the zone but never own the decision.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a DRI, parallel role-persona agents on the same problem produce contradictions and the team ships the loudest recommendation rather than the right one.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="new-pm-skillset">
      <p>As engineering throughput scales with AI, the bottleneck shifts to discovery, evaluation, and judgment. PMs without adjacent fluency become the constraint.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Require PMs to hold fluency in design, data, model behavior, distribution, and pricing — not just spec writing and roadmap ownership.</statement>
        <rationale>As engineering throughput scales with AI, the bottleneck shifts to discovery, evaluation, and judgment. PMs without adjacent fluency become the constraint.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>PM who can write SQL to validate a hypothesis, read a confusion matrix, and articulate a pricing model trade-off participates in all three overlap zones without creating handoffs.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>PM who writes a spec and hands it to design, then waits for a handoff from engineering to review, is operating as a relay runner — creating latency at every baton pass.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="cross-functional-expectations">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pair every "PM speaks design" expectation with a symmetric expectation on the other side. One-sided blurring breeds resentment.</statement>
        <rationale>If PMs are expected to give design feedback but designers are not expected to track metrics, the blurring is extractive, not collaborative.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep one depth specialist per critical discipline (security, ML eval, accessibility). Full-blurring is an anti-pattern in deep domains.</statement>
        <rationale>T-shaped fluency scales well; eliminating specialization entirely creates a team that is mediocre at everything and expert at nothing.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="pm-engineer-ratio">
      <p>Andrew Ng observed at Sequoia AI Ascent 2024 that AI-augmented teams invert the traditional ratio: 2 PMs per 1 Engineer replaces the traditional 1 PM per 4–8 Engineers. This holds when engineering throughput is heavily agent-assisted and the real bottleneck is discovery, evals, and prioritization — not coding.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat the 2:1 PM:Engineer ratio as a hypothesis per team, not a universal target. Measure agent-assisted velocity separately from baseline engineering throughput.</statement>
        <rationale>The inversion only holds when the engineer is heavily AI-augmented. Measuring on baseline throughput leads to over-hiring PMs and under-building.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="audit-and-evolution">
      <p>Blurred roles defined in a document drift back to silos under deadline pressure. The quarterly audit is the forcing function that prevents reversion.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-audit role overlap quarterly using commit/PR-author distribution as the truth signal, not self-reported role descriptions.</statement>
        <rationale>Self-reported role splits in surveys are systematically wrong by ~30%. Git shortlog surfaces who actually touches which areas of the codebase.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Blurred roles defined in a Notion page but not reflected in actual work assignment or code ownership.</description>
        <reason>Blurred roles drift back to silos under deadline pressure. The quarterly audit is the forcing function that prevents reversion.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Methodology is a single conceptual page (Andrew Ng quote + Venn metaphor + skill table). Zero implementation detail, no checklist content, no examples — overstating it as a "process" leads to cargo-culting.</p>
      <p>The 2:1 PM:Engineer ratio is one observation, not a benchmark; treat as a hypothesis per team, not a target.</p>
      <p>Blurred ownership creates accountability gaps. Without a "decision DRI" convention, decisions stall in the overlap zone.</p>
      <p>Cross-functional fluency expectations can become unspoken hiring filters that discriminate against specialists; keep an explicit "depth role" alongside the T-shape.</p>
      <p>Agents amplify the failure mode: if four subagents all "join discovery", you get four contradictory PRDs and no owner.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="role-persona-subagent-pattern">
      <rule>
        <statement>Assign each Venn-overlap zone (PM/design, eng/discovery, data/product) to one agent role with a single human DRI. Agents run parallel disciplinary lenses; the human DRI converges.</statement>
        <rationale>Parallel agents without convergence produce contradictory PRDs, evals, and GTM briefs with no owner. The converge step is mandatory, not optional.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Use brainstorm to spin a diverge phase across PM-agent, designer-agent, data-agent, and eng-agent on the same problem. Each agent produces only its disciplinary lens. The human DRI reads all four and makes the call.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Four subagents all given write access to the same PRD produce four contradictory PRDs and no decision. Always attach a converge step with a named human DRI.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="role-audit-workflow">
      <rule>
        <statement>For role-evolution audits, run a researcher-style agent that maps current responsibilities to target Venn zones and emits a gap list, then file SDD tasks per gap.</statement>
        <rationale>Manual role mapping is biased toward self-perception. Agent-driven mapping from git, Linear, and CODEOWNERS produces evidence-based gaps rather than aspirational ones.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Audit current team T against the blurred-roles model. For each member,
list (a) primary discipline, (b) secondary fluencies, (c) overlap zones
they participate in, (d) gaps. Output a CSV plus 3 prioritized SDD tasks
to close the largest gap. Do not propose firing or restructuring.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Treat each Venn-overlap zone (PM/design, eng/discovery, data/product) as an agent role with a single human DRI. The human owns the decision; agents run the parallel disciplinary lenses and converge on a shared artifact (PRD, eval set, GTM brief). Use `brainstorm` to spin a diverge phase across role-flavored personas (PM-agent, designer-agent, data-agent, eng-agent) on the same problem, then converge. For role-evolution audits, run a one-shot `researcher`-style agent that maps current responsibilities → target Venn zones → gap list, then file SDD tasks for each gap.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>`brainstorm` — diverge/converge across role personas on a single problem (PM, designer, eng, data) to surface overlap and conflict before a human DRI decides.</item>
        <item>`improver` — session-based audit of current role split vs. blurred-role target; emits gap list and SDD tasks.</item>
        <item>`faion-sdd-executor-agent` — execute the resulting role-restructuring tasks (job-spec rewrites, RACI updates, skill-plan docs) under quality gates.</item>
        <item>`researcher` (knowledge skill) — pull external benchmarks (PM:Eng ratios, AI-era job descriptions) when calibrating targets.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <prompt purpose="role-persona-diverge">
        <![CDATA[You are <role>-agent for product P. Other agents are running in parallel
for the other roles. Read the shared brief at <path>. Produce only your
discipline's lens (risks, opportunities, constraints) — do not synthesize
across roles. The human DRI converges. Output: <schema>.]]>
      </prompt>
      <prompt purpose="role-audit">
        <![CDATA[Audit current team T against the blurred-roles model. For each member,
list (a) primary discipline, (b) secondary fluencies, (c) overlap zones
they participate in, (d) gaps. Output a CSV plus 3 prioritized SDD tasks
to close the largest gap. Do not propose firing or restructuring.]]>
      </prompt>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Parallel role-persona agents on the same problem produce contradictions; without a human DRI to converge, the team ships the loudest agent's recommendation.</description>
        <reason>Always attach a converge step with a named human DRI.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents inherit the prompt's role boundary, so a PM-agent given an engineering codebase will silently write code.</description>
        <reason>Constrain via tool allow-lists per persona, not via prose instructions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent-driven skill assessments (e.g., "rate this PM on data fluency from their PRDs") are noisy and biased toward verbose writers.</description>
        <reason>Use as a discussion seed, never as a performance input.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>The "2 PMs : 1 Engineer" inversion only holds when the engineer is heavily AI-augmented; if you measure on baseline engineering throughput, you'll over-hire PMs and under-build.</description>
        <reason>Track agent-assisted velocity separately.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Cross-role knowledge transfer between agents leaks proprietary context (e.g., the data-agent surfaces customer PII in a design-agent prompt).</description>
        <reason>Run a `password-scrubber-agent` style filter on inter-agent handoffs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="human-in-the-loop-checkpoints">
      <list>
        <item>DRI assignment per overlap zone — documented in the role doc, not tribal knowledge</item>
        <item>Approval of any role-restructure SDD task generated by the audit agent</item>
        <item>Final sign-off on hiring scorecards produced by agents</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>gh — Pull team membership, code-review patterns, who-touches-what to infer current role overlap — `gh auth login`; https://cli.github.com</p>
      <p>git shortlog -sne --since=90.days — Surface contribution distribution per person → input to overlap analysis — built-in</p>
      <p>linear-cli / linear MCP — Read assignee history per ticket type to map current role split — https://github.com/evangelion-ui/linear-cli</p>
      <p>notion-cli / Notion MCP — Sync role docs, RACI, skill matrices into the team wiki — https://github.com/makenotion/notion-mcp-server</p>
      <p>op (1Password CLI) — Pull access matrices (who has prod, who has analytics) — a real proxy for current role boundaries — `op-unlock`; https://developer.1password.com/docs/cli</p>
      <p>claude (Claude Code CLI) — Drive the role-persona subagents non-interactively (`claude -p "..."`) for batch audits — https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/claude-code</p>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <p>Linear (SaaS) — Best signal for who-owns-what; query assignees+labels to derive current role split — Yes (REST + MCP)</p>
      <p>Notion (SaaS) — Host the role-Venn doc, RACI, skill-growth plan — Yes (MCP, REST)</p>
      <p>GitHub Projects (SaaS) — Cheaper Linear substitute; CODEOWNERS file is the most concrete role boundary — Yes (`gh` + GraphQL)</p>
      <p>Lattice / 15Five (SaaS) — Skill-growth tracking; agents can read goals but writes usually need human approval — Partial (REST, gated)</p>
      <p>Pavilion / Reforge (SaaS) — Curriculum source for the new PM skillset; manual reading only — No</p>
      <p>Maven cohorts ("AI for PMs") (SaaS) — External upskilling; agent role is to summarize and map to internal gaps — No</p>
      <p>HoneyDew / Productboard (SaaS) — Useful when PM owns data — single source for product+metric overlap — Partial (REST)</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Make every Venn-overlap zone have exactly one human DRI; agents fill the zone but never own the decision. Document this in the role doc, not in tribal knowledge.</p>
      <p>When inverting the PM:Eng ratio, hire/grow PMs who can run evals and write SQL — otherwise the ratio just creates more meetings.</p>
      <p>Write the new role description as "primary lens + 3 fluencies + 1 overlap zone owned" rather than a flat skill list. Forces explicit T-shape.</p>
      <p>Use commit/PR-author distribution as the truth signal for current role boundaries; self-reported role splits in surveys are systematically wrong by ~30%.</p>
      <p>Pair every "PM speaks design" expectation with a designer-side expectation ("understands constraints, tracks metrics"). One-sided blurring breeds resentment.</p>
      <p>Re-audit role overlap quarterly. Blurred roles drift back to silos under pressure; the audit is the forcing function.</p>
      <p>Keep one "depth specialist" per critical discipline (security, ML eval, accessibility). Full-blurring is an anti-pattern in deep domains.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="references">
      <p>Andrew Ng, "AI is changing the role of the PM" (Sequoia AI Ascent 2024 talk).</p>
      <p>Marty Cagan, "Transformed: Moving to the Product Operating Model" (2024) — chapter on cross-functional teams.</p>
      <p>Lenny Rachitsky newsletter, "The new PM skillset for the AI era" (2024–2025 issues).</p>
      <p>Reforge, "Product Strategy in the Age of AI" course outline.</p>
      <p>"The Product Operating Model" — Silicon Valley Product Group, https://www.svpg.com/</p>
      <p>Anthropic, Claude Code subagents docs — https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/claude-code/sub-agents</p>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/role-overlap.sh" purpose="Emit per-author file-area distribution from git history to surface actual role boundaries"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
