<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="star-interview-examples Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for star-interview-examples. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a candidate rambles without structure, interrupt politely and anchor to the Situation component. Never let a rambling answer consume the full time slot without capturing S/T/A/R.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Structured probing gives every candidate the same opportunity to demonstrate competence regardless of communication style, reducing bias from interview performance vs. job performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a candidate consistently says "we" without specifying personal contribution, probe explicitly for individual action before scoring the Action component.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Team re-attribution is the most common STAR inflation path. Agents must flag answers with "we" dominance and no first-person Action statements as incomplete.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a candidate describes actions without an outcome, always probe for the Result before closing the question. A STAR answer without R is incomplete and cannot be scored on outcome quality.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Result quantification is the primary defense against rehearsed inflation; specific numbers are harder to fabricate and easier to verify in reference checks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agents must never assign numeric scores to STAR responses. Agents extract S/T/A/R component spans, flag missing components, and summarize evidence. Scoring is always human.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLM scoring is biased toward fluent, polished delivery — disadvantaging non-native speakers and neurodiverse candidates whose answers may have weaker structure but stronger substance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reject any candidate response beginning with "I would..." or "I generally..." as not qualifying as a STAR response. Trigger the prescribed probe: "Can you give me a specific past example?"</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hypothetical answers have near-zero predictive validity. Accepting them as STAR responses produces scores that predict interview performance, not job performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Redact any transcript utterance referencing protected-class information (pregnancy, age, religion, disability, nationality) with [REDACTED] before storage. Never feed protected-class data into scoring prompts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Using protected-class information in hiring decisions is illegal in most jurisdictions and creates substantial EEOC/GDPR liability. The redaction must happen before any LLM scoring pass.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
