<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules-and-gotchas" title="STAR Examples Agent Rules">
  <summary>Fluency bias, protected-class leakage, legal compliance, and agent scoring prohibition for STAR examples.</summary>

  <section title="Scoring prohibition">
    <rule>
      <statement>Agents must never assign numeric scores to STAR responses. Agents extract S/T/A/R component spans, flag missing components, and summarize evidence. Scoring is always human.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM scoring is biased toward fluent, polished delivery — disadvantaging non-native speakers and neurodiverse candidates whose answers may have weaker structure but stronger substance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Hypothetical acceptance block">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reject any candidate response beginning with "I would..." or "I generally..." as not qualifying as a STAR response. Trigger the prescribed probe: "Can you give me a specific past example?"</statement>
      <rationale>Hypothetical answers have near-zero predictive validity. Accepting them as STAR responses produces scores that predict interview performance, not job performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Protected-class leakage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Redact any transcript utterance referencing protected-class information (pregnancy, age, religion, disability, nationality) with [REDACTED] before storage. Never feed protected-class data into scoring prompts.</statement>
      <rationale>Using protected-class information in hiring decisions is illegal in most jurisdictions and creates substantial EEOC/GDPR liability. The redaction must happen before any LLM scoring pass.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Legal compliance">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running live fully-automated candidate screening (accept/reject) without a human interviewer present.</description>
      <reason>NYC AEDT law, Illinois AIVIA, and EU AI Act classify automated hiring decisions as high-risk and require bias audits, candidate disclosure, and consent. Fully automated screening without these controls is illegal in those jurisdictions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Processing interview recordings without documented candidate consent.</description>
      <reason>Recording without consent is illegal in California, EU member states, and Illinois. The consent flag must be verified before any audio processing begins.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/interviewer-training-agenda.md">2-hour calibration training with role-play scenarios and scoring exercise.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/scorecard-qa-checklist.md">Pre-submit review: evidence completeness, no impressions without quotes.</reference>
</text>
