<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-input-modalities" title="Spatial Interaction — Input Modalities and Interaction Patterns">
  <summary>Five input modalities for XR interfaces compared by use case and accessibility, and three primary interaction patterns with their respective tradeoffs.</summary>

  <section title="Input Modalities">
    <list>
      <item>Hand tracking: direct manipulation of virtual objects; most natural feel; requires clear camera view of hands; best for close-range interactions</item>
      <item>Controllers: precise 6DOF input with physical haptic feedback; best for gaming, creative work, and precision tasks; less natural than hand tracking</item>
      <item>Gaze: selection and navigation via eye direction; best for accessibility, passive browsing, and cursor replacement; requires dwell confirmation to avoid Midas touch</item>
      <item>Voice: text entry, commands, navigation; best for hands-free contexts and when hands are gloved or occupied; sensitive to noise and recognition errors</item>
      <item>Gesture: defined hand poses for shortcuts (thumbs up, peace sign); best for frequent quick actions; requires user training; recognition less reliable than explicit input</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Design at minimum two input modalities for every interaction: a primary modality and a fallback. Gaze+dwell serves as the universal accessibility fallback for users with motor impairments who cannot perform hand gestures.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-modality XR interfaces exclude users whose primary modality is unavailable (gloved hands, controller battery, arm fatigue); a fallback is a functional accessibility requirement.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Direct Manipulation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use direct manipulation (grab, pinch-resize, two-hand rotate, throw) for objects within arm's reach in the interaction zone. Provide physics-based feedback — resistance, snap-to-grid, collision — to make virtual objects feel real.</statement>
      <rationale>Direct manipulation maps to existing physical world intuitions and requires no learned grammar; it is the most learnable interaction pattern for new XR users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Requiring sustained arm extension above shoulder height for direct manipulation of frequently accessed objects.</description>
      <reason>Sustained arm elevation (gorilla arm) causes rapid muscle fatigue and is the primary cause of session abandonment in training and productivity XR applications.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Ray-Casting">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use ray-casting (laser pointer from hand or controller) for selecting objects at distance, activating menus, and interacting with wall-mounted or ceiling-mounted content. Require an explicit confirmation action (click, pinch) to prevent accidental activation.</statement>
      <rationale>Ray-casting extends the interaction range beyond arm's reach without requiring physical movement; it is the standard far-field interaction pattern across platforms.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Pattern: Gaze highlights target → Ray confirms pointing → Pinch activates
Use for: menu items, far panels, ceiling-mounted status displays
Avoid for: precise 3D manipulation where direct touch is more accurate
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Gaze and Dwell">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use gaze+dwell (look at target for 1-2 seconds to activate) as the accessibility fallback for any interaction that normally uses hand or controller input. Display a visible countdown indicator during the dwell period.</statement>
      <rationale>Gaze+dwell enables full XR interaction for users with motor impairments who cannot perform hand gestures or hold controllers; the countdown indicator confirms intent and prevents surprise activations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set dwell time to a minimum of 1 second for destructive actions and 0.5 seconds for safe, reversible selections. Make dwell time configurable in accessibility settings.</statement>
      <rationale>Fixed dwell times that are too short cause accidental activations (Midas touch); too long causes fatigue; individual variability requires a configurable range.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
