<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Post Launch Conversion Drip Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5+ testable rules every Post Launch Conversion Drip application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-tag-every-launch" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tag every launch-week signup with source=launch-&lt;channel&gt;-&lt;date&gt; at capture time; without the tag the drip cannot be isolated from steady-state onboarding and you cannot measure its lift.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-send-t-within" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send T+0 (within 2 hours of signup) with one job: confirm + set the next-step expectation; include the single quickstart link, no feature dump; &gt;1 link reduces click-through by ~30% on this email per typical SaaS data.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-send-t-h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send T+2 (≈48h) with one job: deliver an aha-moment — a 60-second video, a sample report, or a templated "try this with your data" prompt; this is the highest-lift email of the drip, do not skip it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-send-t-with" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send T+7 with one job: social proof — one named case study with concrete numbers and a quote from a real user; generic testimonials reduce reply rate vs a named user with a logo.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-send-t-with" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send T+14 with one job: ask for a decision — book a call, start trial, or one-question reply ("what's stopping you?"); the open-ended reply email out-performs hard CTAs for unactivated signups on this drip stage.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-suppress-the-drip" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Suppress the drip if the user has already converted to paid or completed activation; running the drip on already-activated users dilutes engagement signal and risks unsubscribes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-measure-four-kpis" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Measure four KPIs per send (open, click, primary CTA conversion, unsubscribe) and one funnel KPI (signup → activated → paid by T+30 for this cohort); compare to your non-launch baseline cohort — if the drip does not beat baseline by ≥1.5× on conversion, rewrite, do not just retry.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-28 chunk-02 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
