<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules">
  <rule testable="true">Tag every launch-week signup with source=launch-&lt;channel&gt;-&lt;date&gt; at capture time; without the tag the drip cannot be isolated from steady-state onboarding and you cannot measure its lift.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Send T+0 (within 2 hours of signup) with one job: confirm + set the next-step expectation; include the single quickstart link, no feature dump; &gt;1 link reduces click-through by ~30% on this email per typical SaaS data.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Send T+2 (≈48h) with one job: deliver an aha-moment — a 60-second video, a sample report, or a templated "try this with your data" prompt; this is the highest-lift email of the drip, do not skip it.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Send T+7 with one job: social proof — one named case study with concrete numbers and a quote from a real user; generic testimonials reduce reply rate vs a named user with a logo.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Send T+14 with one job: ask for a decision — book a call, start trial, or one-question reply ("what's stopping you?"); the open-ended reply email out-performs hard CTAs for unactivated signups on this drip stage.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Suppress the drip if the user has already converted to paid or completed activation; running the drip on already-activated users dilutes engagement signal and risks unsubscribes.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Measure four KPIs per send (open, click, primary CTA conversion, unsubscribe) and one funnel KPI (signup → activated → paid by T+30 for this cohort); compare to your non-launch baseline cohort — if the drip does not beat baseline by ≥1.5× on conversion, rewrite, do not just retry.</rule>
  <example>Indie hacker post-PH: 412 signups tagged source=launch-ph-2026-05-15. T+0 email: 71% open, 38% click on quickstart. T+2 video: 64% open, 22% used the sample report. T+7 case study (named user, 4 quotes, "saved 6 hrs/week"): 49% open, 11% clicked book-call CTA, 7 trials started. T+14 ask: 28% open, 41 one-line replies, 6 became paid. Cohort conversion 9.2% vs steady-state 4.1% → drip is keeping.</example>
</text>
