<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="monitoring-logging">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>server-craft</domain>
    <summary>Lightweight monitoring and logging for solo VPS platforms using journald, health-check scripts, and Telegram alerts without Prometheus/Grafana.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>monitoring</tag>
      <tag>logging</tag>
      <tag>journald</tag>
      <tag>health-check</tag>
      <tag>alerting</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Monitoring and Logging</title>
    <summary>Lightweight monitoring and logging for solo developer VPS platforms using journald, health-check scripts, and Telegram alerts without Prometheus/Grafana. Provides journalctl query patterns, log rotation config, FLOW-style autonomous hourly/daily reports, and status dashboard.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>A solo developer server needs 95% of enterprise monitoring value at 1% of the complexity. Journald + a few shell scripts + Telegram alerts cover service-down detection, disk/memory thresholds, OOM kills, and daily status summaries without running a full observability stack.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Setting up observability from scratch on a solo-developer VPS</item>
        <item>A service went down silently and you need alerting before it happens again</item>
        <item>Writing a health-check script for a cron job or FLOW guardian</item>
        <item>Building an autonomous monitoring loop that sends Telegram alerts on anomalies</item>
        <item>Investigating a production incident retroactively via journalctl</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Multi-server environments where Prometheus/Grafana/Loki is justified (use pro/infra/devops-engineer)</item>
        <item>Kubernetes clusters (use Datadog, Grafana Loki, or similar)</item>
        <item>Compliance-heavy environments requiring tamper-proof audit-trail log storage</item>
        <item>High-frequency trading or sub-second SLOs where journald latency is unacceptable</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="journald-patterns">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use --user flag for systemd user services; omit it only for system units like nginx or docker.</statement>
        <rationale>User services run under loginctl linger sessions and their logs are scoped separately. Using system-level journalctl silently returns no output for user services.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Prefer -p err over grepping for "ERROR" strings; journald priority filtering is structured and faster.</statement>
        <rationale>Application logs may write "error" as a string without setting priority. -p err captures systemd-level failures like OOM kills and service crashes regardless of application log format.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="common-queries">
        <example type="good">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Follow a user service in real-time
journalctl --user -u nero-core -f

# Last 50 lines of a user service
journalctl --user -u nero-core -n 50

# Errors from last 2 hours across all nero services
journalctl --user -u 'nero-*' -p err --since "2 hours ago" --no-pager

# Kernel OOM kills
journalctl -k --since "1 hour ago" | grep -i "out of memory"

# Service restart events
journalctl --user -u nero-core | grep -E "(Started|Stopped|Failed)"

# JSON output for scripted analysis
journalctl --user -u nero-core -o json --since "1 hour ago"

# Count errors per service in last 24h
for svc in nero-core nero-channel-web nero-channel-tg; do
    count=$(journalctl --user -u "$svc" -p err --since "24 hours ago" --no-pager 2>/dev/null | wc -l)
    echo "$svc: $count errors"
done
          ]]></code>
        </example>
        <example type="bad">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Wrong: omits --user, returns nothing for user services
journalctl -u nero-core -f

# Wrong: grep on raw text is fragile and slow
journalctl --user -u nero-core | grep -i error

# Wrong: no --no-pager in scripts causes blocking
journalctl --user -u nero-core | wc -l
          ]]></code>
          <note>Always add --no-pager in scripts. Use -p for priority filtering, not grep on message text.</note>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section name="filter-reference">
        <list>
          <item>-u — filter by unit name; supports glob patterns like 'nero-*'</item>
          <item>--user — scope to user-session units (loginctl linger must be enabled)</item>
          <item>-p err — priority filter: emerg, alert, crit, err, warning, notice, info, debug</item>
          <item>--since / --until — time window; accepts "2 hours ago", "today", ISO timestamps</item>
          <item>-f — follow (tail -f equivalent)</item>
          <item>-n N — last N lines</item>
          <item>-o format — output format: short, short-iso, json, cat (message only)</item>
          <item>-b / -b -1 — current boot / previous boot</item>
          <item>-k — kernel messages (dmesg equivalent via journald)</item>
          <item>--disk-usage — show total journal storage consumed</item>
          <item>--no-pager — never paginate; required in all scripts</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="journald-configuration">
      <rule>
        <statement>Set Storage=persistent so logs survive reboots; default volatile storage loses all history on each boot.</statement>
        <rationale>Incident investigation almost always needs logs from the previous boot cycle. Volatile storage makes post-reboot debugging impossible.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap SystemMaxUse at 10% of total disk; for a 100G VPS, 2G is a reasonable ceiling.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a cap, a single chatty service can fill the disk. journald enforces the cap automatically, rotating oldest logs first.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="docker-log-rotation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Always configure Docker daemon to rotate container logs before they consume unbounded disk space.</statement>
        <rationale>Docker's default log driver (json-file) has no rotation. A single high-volume container can fill the disk silently.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "log-driver": "json-file",
  "log-opts": {
    "max-size": "10m",
    "max-file": "3"
  }
}
        ]]></code>
        <note>Place at /etc/docker/daemon.json. Restart Docker after changes: sudo systemctl restart docker. Existing containers use old settings until recreated.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Starting containers without log rotation configured.</description>
        <reason>A container logging 1MB/minute fills a 100G disk in 70 days. With no rotation, the only fix is manual cleanup under incident pressure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="logrotate">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use delaycompress with compress so the currently active log file is never compressed while it may still be written to.</statement>
        <rationale>Compressing an open file corrupts it. delaycompress ensures only the previous rotation's file gets compressed.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="health-check-structure">
      <rule>
        <statement>A health-check script must cover all four layers: infrastructure (Docker), application (systemd), endpoints (HTTP), and system resources.</statement>
        <rationale>A service can be "active" in systemd but returning 500s; an endpoint check catches what systemd status misses. Resource checks catch slow degradation before hard failures.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use exit codes: 0 = healthy, 1 = warnings, 2 = errors. Never exit 0 when checks fail.</statement>
        <rationale>Cron jobs and monitoring wrappers test exit codes to decide whether to send alerts. A silent non-zero exit from a health check defeats its purpose.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Print OK/WARN/FAIL prefix on every check line so output is machine-parseable without regex.</statement>
        <rationale>Downstream scripts and log scanners can grep for FAIL without parsing natural language sentences.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="coverage-layers">
        <list>
          <item>Infrastructure: Docker daemon active, each container running (postgres, redis, rabbitmq)</item>
          <item>Application: each systemd user service active (nero-core, channel-web, channel-tg, web, beat)</item>
          <item>Endpoints: HTTP health endpoint returns 2xx, frontend returns 2xx</item>
          <item>Resources: disk percent, memory percent, CPU load vs. core count, swap usage</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="thresholds">
        <list>
          <item>Disk: warn above 80%, fail above 90%</item>
          <item>Memory: warn above 85%, fail above 95%</item>
          <item>CPU load: warn when load/cores > 90%</item>
          <item>Swap: warn when more than 50% of swap is used</item>
          <item>HTTP endpoint timeout: 5 seconds max</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
#!/bin/bash
# Minimal health-check pattern
set -euo pipefail

ERRORS=0
WARNINGS=0

ok()   { echo "OK   $1"; }
warn() { echo "WARN $1"; WARNINGS=$((WARNINGS + 1)); }
fail() { echo "FAIL $1"; ERRORS=$((ERRORS + 1)); }

check_service() {
    local name="$1" cmd="$2"
    if eval "$cmd" > /dev/null 2>&1; then ok "$name"; else fail "$name"; fi
}

# Infrastructure
check_service "Docker" "systemctl is-active docker"
check_service "PostgreSQL" "docker exec nero-postgres pg_isready -U nero -q"
check_service "Redis" "docker exec nero-redis redis-cli ping"

# Application
check_service "nero-core" "systemctl --user is-active --quiet nero-core"

# Endpoints
check_service "API /health" "curl -sf --max-time 5 http://127.0.0.1:8100/health"

# Resources
DISK_PCT=$(df / --output=pcent | tail -1 | tr -d ' %')
if [ "$DISK_PCT" -gt 90 ]; then fail "Disk: ${DISK_PCT}%"
elif [ "$DISK_PCT" -gt 80 ]; then warn "Disk: ${DISK_PCT}%"
else ok "Disk: ${DISK_PCT}%"; fi

# Exit code
[ "$ERRORS" -gt 0 ] && exit 2
[ "$WARNINGS" -gt 0 ] && exit 1
exit 0
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Wrong: always exits 0, alert wrappers never trigger
./health-check.sh || true

# Wrong: no resource checks, disk fills silently
check_service "Docker" "systemctl is-active docker"
echo "Done"
exit 0
        ]]></code>
        <note>Health checks that always exit 0 are worse than no health check — they create false confidence.</note>
      </example>
      <section name="cron-integration">
        <rule>
          <statement>Run health checks with an alert-on-failure wrapper in cron, not by piping directly to Telegram inside the check script.</statement>
          <rationale>Separating health-check logic from alerting logic lets you run the same check manually without triggering alerts.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <example type="good">
          <code lang="cron"><![CDATA[
# Run health check every 5 minutes; alert if non-zero exit
*/5 * * * * /usr/local/bin/health-check.sh || /usr/local/bin/notify-telegram.sh "Health check FAILED on $(hostname)"

# FLOW hourly monitor (alert-only, no noise on success)
0 * * * * /home/nero/workspace/scripts/flow-hourly.sh >> /var/log/nero-flow.log 2>&1
          ]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="telegram-alerting">
      <rule>
        <statement>Store TELEGRAM_BOT_TOKEN and TELEGRAM_CHAT_ID in ~/.env (chmod 600), never hardcoded in scripts.</statement>
        <rationale>Scripts in ~/bin or /usr/local/bin may be world-readable. Credentials in .env are loaded at runtime and never committed to version control.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Make the notify function accept both a positional argument and stdin so it composes with pipes.</statement>
        <rationale>Pipeline composition (command | notify-telegram.sh) is the most common usage pattern in monitoring scripts. Argument form is convenient for one-liners.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Truncate messages to 4000 characters before sending; Telegram rejects messages over 4096 chars.</statement>
        <rationale>Long error output from a failing script will silently fail to deliver if not truncated, defeating the alerting purpose.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="alert-on-failure-pattern">
        <rule>
          <statement>Wrap any critical script in an alert-on-failure pattern: run the command, alert only on non-zero exit.</statement>
          <rationale>This keeps alerting logic out of individual scripts and makes alert behavior composable via cron.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <example type="good">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# In cron: alert if backup script fails
0 3 * * * /home/nero/bin/backup.sh || notify-telegram.sh "Backup FAILED on $(hostname) at $(date '+%H:%M')"

# Wrapper function
alert_on_failure() {
    local task_name="$1"; shift
    if ! "$@" 2>&1; then
        notify-telegram.sh "ALERT: *${task_name}* failed on $(hostname) at $(date '+%H:%M')"
    fi
}

alert_on_failure "Daily Backup" /home/nero/bin/backup.sh
          ]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="flow-schedule">
      <rule>
        <statement>FLOW hourly checks must be silent on success; only send Telegram alerts when issues are detected.</statement>
        <rationale>An hourly "all OK" message would send 24 Telegram messages per day per server. Alert fatigue destroys the value of monitoring.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>FLOW daily reports send unconditionally at a fixed time regardless of issue state.</statement>
        <rationale>The daily report provides baseline visibility: uptime, resource trends, error count, backup status. It confirms monitoring is working even on quiet days.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="cron-schedule">
        <list>
          <item>Hourly (0 * * * *): silent health check, alert only on problems</item>
          <item>Daily 22:00 (0 22 * * *): full report with uptime, resources, errors, backup status</item>
          <item>Weekly Mon 7:00 (0 7 * * 1): trends, capacity, weekly error count</item>
          <item>@reboot: startup heartbeat after 30s service stabilization</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="cron"><![CDATA[
# Hourly health check (alert only on problems)
0 * * * * /home/nero/workspace/scripts/flow-hourly.sh >> /var/log/nero-flow.log 2>&1

# Daily report (22:00)
0 22 * * * /home/nero/workspace/scripts/flow-daily.sh >> /var/log/nero-flow.log 2>&1

# Startup heartbeat (boot + 35s for service stabilization)
@reboot sleep 35 && /home/nero/workspace/scripts/startup-heartbeat.sh >> /var/log/nero-startup.log 2>&1
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="alert-content-guidelines">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every alert must include: hostname, timestamp, what failed, severity. Daily reports include uptime and backup status.</statement>
        <rationale>Without hostname, alerts from multiple servers are ambiguous. Without timestamp, alert delivery delay is invisible. Without what-failed, triage requires SSH before understanding scope.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
FLOW ALERT nero 13:00:
- nero-core is DOWN
- API health check failed

Daily Report: 2026-03-21 22:00
Host: nero
Uptime: up 15 days, 3 hours
Services: nero-core active (847MB), nero-channel-web active (185MB)
Resources: CPU 1.2 load | RAM 8.5G/30G | Disk 29%
Errors (24h): 3
Backup: 20260321_030000 (285MB, 19h ago)
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Sending raw script output or stack traces as Telegram alerts.</description>
        <reason>Telegram messages render poorly for long text. Raw stack traces exceed the 4096-char limit and get dropped silently. Summarize failures, attach details to logs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/health-check.sh" purpose="Comprehensive health-check script for Docker + systemd + resources"/>
      <template path="templates/notify-telegram.sh" purpose="Minimal Telegram send function, stdin or arg mode"/>
      <template path="templates/flow-hourly.sh" purpose="FLOW-style silent-on-success hourly monitor"/>
      <template path="templates/flow-daily.sh" purpose="FLOW daily report with uptime, resources, errors, backup status"/>
      <template path="templates/journald.conf" purpose="journald.conf with size caps, persistence, rate limiting"/>
      <template path="templates/logrotate-app.conf" purpose="logrotate config for application log files"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
