<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-constitution-workflow" title="Writing Constitutions: Two-Mode Workflow">
  <summary>Procedures for creating constitution.md in two modes: analyzing an existing codebase vs. Socratic dialogue for new projects.</summary>

  <section title="Mode 1: Existing Project">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 (Detect): read directory layout, CLAUDE.md, README.md, config files (pyproject.toml, package.json, .eslintrc)</item>
      <item>Step 2 (Analyze): identify tech stack, architecture patterns, naming conventions, linter/formatter setup, testing configuration</item>
      <item>Step 3 (Present Findings): "Analysis: 1. Tech: Python 3.11, Django 4.2, PostgreSQL. 2. Architecture: layered (views→services→models). 3. Standards: black + isort + flake8. Does this match? What to change?"</item>
      <item>Step 4 (Draft and Review): incorporate feedback, write constitution.md</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>In Mode 1, let codebase analysis lead; do not write standards from memory or training data.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents copy patterns from existing code without checking if those patterns are intentional standards or technical debt. Present findings to the team before committing them as standards. What looks like a convention may be an accident.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Mode 2: New Project">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 (Vision): "Tell me about the project. What problem does it solve?" Apply Five Whys to reach the real need.</item>
      <item>Step 2 (Tech Choices): present A/B/C with pros/cons for backend, database, frontend framework</item>
      <item>Step 3 (Architecture): discuss monolith vs microservices, REST vs GraphQL, ORM vs raw SQL — with trade-offs for this specific project</item>
      <item>Step 4 (Standards): linter, formatter, type hints, testing coverage, CI/CD, git conventions</item>
      <item>Step 5 (Draft): write constitution.md</item>
      <item>Step 6 (Review): validate with team before committing</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Save and Setup">
    <list>
      <item>Create .aidocs/ directory structure: backlog/, todo/, in-progress/, done/</item>
      <item>Write constitution.md to .aidocs/constitution.md</item>
      <item>Create CLAUDE.md navigation hub in project folder</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Copying constitution sections from a different project or from training data without validating against the actual codebase.</description>
      <reason>Constitution copied without validation becomes "aspirational" rather than descriptive. When executor agents follow the constitution but the codebase contradicts it, they produce inconsistent code that fails review.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Over-engineering the constitution for a new project by specifying microservices, message queues, and multi-region deployment from day one.</description>
      <reason>Premature architectural complexity locks in decisions that should emerge from actual usage. Start with the simplest architecture that could work; the constitution can be updated when complexity is justified.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
