<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-spec-workflow" title="Writing Specifications: 6-Phase Workflow">
  <summary>Brainstorm → Research → Clarify → Draft → Review → Save procedure for writing spec.md, with Socratic dialogue techniques and anti-patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Philosophy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start every spec session with the problem statement, never the solution; ask "what pain?" before "what feature?"</statement>
      <rationale>Solution-first specs embed implementation assumptions into requirements. Problem-first specs leave design decisions to the design phase. When a spec says "add a button that exports to CSV," it has already made a UI and format decision that belongs in design.md.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Intent is source of truth — spec is the main artifact, not a reflection of a prior decision</item>
      <item>Socratic dialogue — user formulates requirements through questions, not monologue</item>
      <item>Incremental validation — show each section, get approval, then continue</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 1: Brainstorming">
    <list>
      <item>Opening: "Tell me about the problem. Who suffers and how?"</item>
      <item>Five Whys: for each answer, ask "Why?" — "Need export" → "Why?" → "Managers ask" → "Why?" → "No access" → Real problem: UX gap</item>
      <item>Alternatives: for each idea, present A/B with pros/cons, ask "Which is closer?"</item>
      <item>Challenge: "Is this needed for v1?", "What if we DON'T do this?", "Does this already exist in the codebase?"</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Ask one question at a time in Socratic dialogue; wait for response before asking the next.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents interpret "Socratic dialogue" as asking multiple questions in a batch then proceeding. Single-question pauses enforce genuine elicitation. Without this, agents hallucinate answers to unanswered questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 2-3: Research and Clarify">
    <list>
      <item>Phase 2 (Research): grep codebase for similar implementations; share findings: "Found existing export in services.py. Does this affect the approach?"</item>
      <item>Phase 3 (Clarify): user stories workshop — "As {role}, I want {goal}, so that {benefit}. How often? What happens if this fails?"; ask edge cases as questions, never assume</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 4: Draft Section by Section">
    <list>
      <item>Problem Statement → show → validate: "Is this correct?"</item>
      <item>User Stories with AC → show → validate: "Is this complete?"</item>
      <item>Functional Requirements → show → validate: "Anything redundant?"</item>
      <item>Out of Scope → show → validate: "Agree with boundaries?" (capture while fresh)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 5-6: Review and Save">
    <list>
      <item>Phase 5 (Review): verify problem is SMART, user stories follow INVEST, requirements are testable, out-of-scope is explicit; call faion-sdd-reviewer-agent (mode: spec)</item>
      <item>Phase 6 (Save): new feature → .aidocs/features/backlog/{NN}-{feature}/spec.md; existing feature → update spec.md in existing folder</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent makes assumptions instead of asking questions when user says "I don't know".</description>
      <reason>"I don't know" is valid input that must be documented as uncertainty, not interpolated. Agents that fill uncertainty with plausible answers produce specs that look complete but contain fabricated requirements.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Writing large blocks of spec without incremental validation.</description>
      <reason>Errors in section 1 propagate to sections 2-8. Show and validate each section before proceeding; fixing a requirement after five dependent sections are written requires rewriting all downstream sections.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
