<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="workflow-spec-phase Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for workflow-spec-phase as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Copying constitution sections from a different project or from training data without validating against the actual codebase.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Constitution copied without validation becomes "aspirational" rather than descriptive. When executor agents follow the constitution but the codebase contradicts it, they produce inconsistent code that fails review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Over-engineering the constitution for a new project by specifying microservices, message queues, and multi-region deployment from day one.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Premature architectural complexity locks in decisions that should emerge from actual usage. Start with the simplest architecture that could work; the constitution can be updated when complexity is justified.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent makes assumptions instead of asking questions when user says "I don't know".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"I don't know" is valid input that must be documented as uncertainty, not interpolated. Agents that fill uncertainty with plausible answers produce specs that look complete but contain fabricated requirements.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Writing large blocks of spec without incremental validation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Errors in section 1 propagate to sections 2-8. Show and validate each section before proceeding; fixing a requirement after five dependent sections are written requires rewriting all downstream sections.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
