<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-grooming-roadmap" title="Backlog Grooming and Roadmapping">
  <summary>Backlog grooming workflow with Definition of Ready checklist, and roadmapping with confidence levels (90/70/50%).</summary>

  <section title="Backlog Grooming Workflow">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Read roadmap.md and constitution.md</item>
      <item>Step 2: List features by status: in-progress, todo, backlog (P0/P1/P2)</item>
      <item>Step 3: Ask user: "What do you want to do?" — review priorities, take feature, add feature, remove feature, finish grooming</item>
      <item>Step 4: For selected feature — check document completeness</item>
      <item>Step 5: If no spec → run Writing Specifications workflow</item>
      <item>Step 6: If spec approved, no design → run Writing Design Documents workflow</item>
      <item>Step 7: If design approved, no impl-plan → run Writing Implementation Plans workflow</item>
      <item>Step 8: When all artifacts complete → move from backlog/ to todo/</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Definition of Ready">
    <rule>
      <statement>A feature is ready to move from backlog to todo only when all DoR criteria are met; features without approved spec or design must remain in backlog.</statement>
      <rationale>Moving features to todo with unapproved artifacts causes executor agents to start implementation against draft requirements, producing code that must be discarded when the spec or design changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Problem/need is clear and documented</item>
      <item>Acceptance criteria defined (Given/When/Then format)</item>
      <item>Dependencies identified and unblocked</item>
      <item>Feature is small enough for one sprint (or decomposed into multiple features)</item>
      <item>spec.md status: Approved</item>
      <item>design.md status: Approved</item>
      <item>implementation-plan.md status: Approved</item>
      <item>TASK_*.md files created and reviewed</item>
      <item>No blockers outstanding</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Roadmapping">
    <list>
      <item>When to run: after completing features, when priorities change, weekly/sprint roadmap sync, adding new ideas</item>
      <item>Phase 1 (Analyze): count completed features in done/, count backlog; review milestones</item>
      <item>Phase 2 (Review Priorities): "Are priorities current?" — update MoSCoW if needed</item>
      <item>Phase 3 (Add Features): for each new idea — Socratic dialogue, create backlog/{NN}-{name}/spec.md with problem statement, add to roadmap.md</item>
      <item>Phase 4 (Update Roadmap): Now (90%) detailed/committed, Next (70%) planned/flexible, Later (50%) thematic/vision, Done with highlights</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Roadmap "Later (50%)" items must not get detailed specs prematurely; they should have only a problem statement until promoted to "Next".</statement>
      <rationale>Agents over-specify "Later" items because spec writing is their strength. Over-specified items for distant features create false precision and waste spec effort when priorities change — which they do for 50% confidence items.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Roadmap confidence levels (90/70/50%) must be explicit; agents over-estimate confidence without this constraint.</statement>
      <rationale>Without explicit confidence levels, all backlog items look equally certain. The 90/70/50% framework forces honest uncertainty quantification and prevents "Now (90%)" items from competing for capacity with speculative "Later (50%)" work.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="scripts/backlog-audit.sh">Print feature status table across all lifecycle stages</reference>
</text>
