<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="pm" count="324">
  <methodology slug="1-1-question-bank-by-tenure" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/1-1-question-bank-by-tenure">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for 1 1 question bank by tenure that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="1on1-template-managers" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/project-manager/1on1-template-managers">
    <summary>Reusable template for 1on1 template managers that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="30-day-post-launch-review-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/30-day-post-launch-review-template">
    <summary>Reusable template for 30 day post launch review template that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ac-quality-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/ac-quality-rubric">
    <summary>A scoring rubric for acceptance criteria that flags weak ACs before sprint planning, with a fix-pattern table for each weakness type.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="account-health-scoring-model" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-operations/account-health-scoring-model">
    <summary>Green/yellow/red account health score model for micro-agencies with sub-20 retainer clients, built from observable signals not just NPS.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="action-item-carryover-tracker" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/action-item-carryover-tracker">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for action item carryover tracker that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-acquisition-prep" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-operations/agency-acquisition-prep">
    <summary>Concrete operating checklist covering agency acquisition prep — the small set of items a practitioner runs every cycle so nothing high-leverage gets skipped.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-annual-plan-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/agency-annual-plan-template">
    <summary>Reusable template for agency annual plan template that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-cash-flow-friday-routine" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/agency-cash-flow-friday-routine">
    <summary>Concrete operating checklist covering agency cash flow friday routine — the small set of items a practitioner runs every cycle so nothing high-leverage gets skipped.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-kickoff-deck-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/agency-kickoff-deck-template">
    <summary>Reusable template for agency kickoff deck template that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-pipeline-hygiene-15min" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/agency-pipeline-hygiene-15min">
    <summary>Concrete operating checklist covering agency pipeline hygiene 15min — the small set of items a practitioner runs every cycle so nothing high-leverage gets skipped.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-pnl-tracker-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/agency-pnl-tracker-template">
    <summary>Micro-agency P&amp;L template with project / retainer / productized revenue lines, contractor costs, and weekly cash-flow + utilization views.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-risk-register-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/agency-risk-register-template">
    <summary>Enterprise-level weekly risk-register template for micro-agencies covering revenue concentration, key-person risk, FX, and contractor classification — refreshable in 30 minutes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-to-saas-readiness-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-planning/agency-to-saas-readiness-checklist">
    <summary>Structured readiness audit for an agency planning a SaaS pivot — IP rights, repeatable assets, codebase ownership, retainer-base stability, founder bandwidth.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agent-pricing-and-unit-economics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/product-manager/agent-pricing-and-unit-economics">
    <summary>Per-task cost modelling, gross margin computation, and pricing-model selection (seat / task / outcome) for LLM-agent products targeting $5-100K MRR.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-ai-product-development" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/product-operations/agentic-ai-product-development">
    <summary>Methodology for designing autonomous agentic AI systems in products where the core value proposition is autonomous action (auto-triage, auto-scheduling, auto-publishing).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-ai-product-development" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/product-manager/agentic-ai-product-development">
    <summary>A product methodology for designing and shipping autonomous AI systems — agents that act toward a goal without user-triggering each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/product-manager/agents">
    <summary>Two Claude subagents for product scoping work: faion-mvp-scope-analyzer-agent analyzes competitor features to recommend a minimum feature set for a new product; faion-mlp-agent upgrades an MVP to an MLP (Minimum Lovable Product) through a five-mode sequential pipeline (analyze → find-gaps → propose → update → plan).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agile-ceremonies-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/agile-ceremonies-setup">
    <summary>Defines, configures, and continuously improves the five Scrum events — Sprint Planning, Daily Standup, Sprint Review, Retrospective, and Backlog Refinement — for a team's specific size, timezone spread, and PM tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agile-hybrid-approaches" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/agile-hybrid-approaches">
    <summary>A decision framework for selecting and tailoring a delivery mode — predictive (waterfall), agile (Scrum/Kanban), or a named hybrid pattern — based on six scored dimensions: requirement clarity, stakeholder engagement, risk tolerance, team agility, contract flexibility, and regulatory burden.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agile-hybrid-approaches" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/agile-hybrid-approaches">
    <summary>A decision framework for selecting among Predictive (waterfall), Agile (Scrum/Kanban), and Hybrid delivery models based on five project factors: requirements clarity, stakeholder availability, risk tolerance, team experience, and contract type.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-assisted-backlog-deduplication" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/pm-agile/ai-assisted-backlog-deduplication">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for ai assisted backlog deduplication that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-assisted-velocity-anomaly-detection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/pm-agile/ai-assisted-velocity-anomaly-detection">
    <summary>Detection protocol for ai assisted velocity anomaly detection — explicit signals, thresholds, and remediation paths so the failure mode is caught before it ships.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-earned-value-management" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/project-manager/ai-earned-value-management">
    <summary>Auto-compute PV/EV/AC and SPI/CPI weekly by ingesting Git commit volume, Jira completion, budget burn, and invoice cadence — replacing manual EVM entry with a sensor-driven pipeline that publishes a confidence interval, not a single point estimate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-de-risking" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/product-manager/ai-feature-de-risking">
    <summary>Evaluation method for ai feature de risking that defines test set, scoring function, pass/fail thresholds, and regression rules so quality is comparable across runs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-spec-contract" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/ai-feature-spec-contract">
    <summary>Feature-management method for ai feature spec contract — what the brief, gate, and rollout artefacts must contain to move a feature from idea to production safely.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-in-project-management" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/project-manager/ai-in-project-management">
    <summary>PMBOK 8's first dedicated AI appendix: principles for ethical AI use, AI-assisted decision traceability, and sustainable project delivery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-in-project-management" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/pm-agile/ai-in-project-management">
    <summary>Framework for applying AI to project risk scoring, schedule variance analysis, resource capacity forecasting, and stakeholder digest generation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-leverage-estimation-model" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/ai-leverage-estimation-model">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for ai leverage estimation model that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-native-product-development" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/product-operations/ai-native-product-development">
    <summary>AI integration strategy for products designed around AI from day one.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-native-product-development" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/product-manager/ai-native-product-development">
    <summary>A product strategy methodology for products where AI is not a feature but the delivery mechanism across all layers (research, design, development, testing, analytics, support).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-pm-tool-integration-recipes" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/project-manager/ai-pm-tool-integration-recipes">
    <summary>Runnable recipes that wire Jira → Claude → Slack digest, GitHub PR events → risk register update, and Loom transcripts → retro notes — with code, schemas, and the exact prompt scaffolds the PM ships.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-powered-pm-tools" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/project-manager/ai-powered-pm-tools">
    <summary>A 2026 survey of AI-augmented PM platforms: Jira+Rovo (enterprise), Monday.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-powered-pm-tools" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/pm-agile/ai-powered-pm-tools">
    <summary>Selection and integration guide for AI-augmented project management tools (Jira+Rovo, ClickUp Brain, Monday.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-risk-aging-agent" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/ai-risk-aging-agent">
    <summary>Ai Risk Aging Agent: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Distressed-project rescue (90-day turnaround)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-sprint-planning-agent" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/ai-sprint-planning-agent">
    <summary>Ai Sprint Planning Agent: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/AI-assisted sprint planning with capacity reality-check' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-status-digest-pipeline" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/ai-status-digest-pipeline">
    <summary>Ai Status Digest Pipeline: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Async cross-timezone delivery cadence (P4 outsource)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="anti-theater-retro-guardrails" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/anti-theater-retro-guardrails">
    <summary>Anti Theater Retro Guardrails: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'p6-product-dev-team/Bi-weekly retro with mistake-memory feedback' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="architecture-review-cadence-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/architecture-review-cadence-protocol">
    <summary>Architecture Review Cadence Protocol: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-software-architect/Quarterly architecture review cycle' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="async-multi-client-time-boxing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/async-multi-client-time-boxing">
    <summary>Async Multi Client Time Boxing: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'p3-technical-freelancer/Freelancer-to-SaaS transition without losing the runway' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="async-standup-methodology" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/async-standup-methodology">
    <summary>Async Standup Methodology: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Async cross-timezone delivery cadence (P4 outsource)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="async-standup-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/async-standup-template">
    <summary>Three-field written-Slack daily standup (Yesterday, Today, Blocker) for 1-3 person cross-timezone teams, with blocker-routing SLA and silence-detection rule.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="audience-okr-template-indie" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/audience-okr-template-indie">
    <summary>Audience Okr Template Indie: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Build-in-public audience growth: 0 to 5K followers over 6 months' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-devops-boards" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/azure-devops-boards">
    <summary>Microsoft's enterprise project management tool supporting four process templates (Basic, Agile, Scrum, CMMI) with a work-item hierarchy (Epic → Feature → User Story/PBI → Task), configurable Kanban boards, WIP limits, WIQL query language, and full REST API.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-devops-boards" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/azure-devops-boards">
    <summary>Azure DevOps Boards is Microsoft's enterprise project management solution supporting four process templates (Basic, Agile, Scrum, CMMI) with tight integration to Azure Pipelines, Repos, and Test Plans.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backlog-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-operations/backlog-management">
    <summary>Methodology for maintaining a prioritized, healthy backlog that connects work items to product goals.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backlog-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/backlog-management">
    <summary>Maintain a prioritized, healthy list of work connected to product goals using the DEEP principle (Detailed at top, Emergent at bottom, Estimated, Prioritized) and four buckets: Ready, Upcoming, Backlog, Icebox.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="bench-management-tiering" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/bench-management-tiering">
    <summary>Bench Management Tiering: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Build a bench of vetted subcontractors without becoming an agency-of-agencies' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="benefits-realisation-template-outsource" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/benefits-realisation-template-outsource">
    <summary>Benefits Realisation Template Outsource: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Project closure with benefits realisation and lessons learned (two weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="benefits-realization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/benefits-realization">
    <summary>Identify, quantify, assign ownership for, and track the business value that a project is expected to deliver after go-live.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="benefits-realization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/benefits-realization">
    <summary>Benefits realization tracks whether a project's promised business outcomes actually materialize after delivery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="bid-no-bid-scorecard" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/bid-no-bid-scorecard">
    <summary>Bid No Bid Scorecard: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/Fixed-price bid discovery + estimation (1 week)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="billable-vs-internal-allocation-split" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/billable-vs-internal-allocation-split">
    <summary>Billable vs Internal Allocation Split: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Run a 30-minute resource allocation review' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="billing-rollout-coordination-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/billing-rollout-coordination-checklist">
    <summary>Billing Rollout Coordination Checklist: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/Pricing experiment, hypothesis to result' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="blurred-roles-team-evolution" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-operations/blurred-roles-team-evolution">
    <summary>Modern AI-era product teams operate as overlapping Venn diagrams rather than relay-race handoffs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="blurred-roles-team-evolution" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/blurred-roles-team-evolution">
    <summary>Modern product teams operate as overlapping Venn diagrams rather than relay-race handoffs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="burndown-diagnosis-cheatsheet" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/burndown-diagnosis-cheatsheet">
    <summary>Burndown Diagnosis Cheatsheet: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Update the burndown / burnup and decide one corrective action' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="capacity-fit-calculator" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/capacity-fit-calculator">
    <summary>Lightweight per-sprint capacity vs commitment calculator for solo PMs — PTO + ceremonies + interrupt buffer subtracted; outputs a fit ratio used at sprint planning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="capacity-planning-realistic" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/capacity-planning-realistic">
    <summary>Capacity Planning Realistic: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/AI-assisted sprint planning with capacity reality-check' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="capacity-vs-ask-balancer" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/capacity-vs-ask-balancer">
    <summary>Capacity vs Ask Balancer: codified delivery-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/Quarter planning + OKR cascade' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="change-control" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/change-control">
    <summary>Route every change request through a formal log → impact analysis → tiered decision → baseline update cycle.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="change-control" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/change-control">
    <summary>Change control is the formal process that evaluates every proposed change to scope, schedule, cost, or quality against the approved baseline before any work begins.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="change-request-pricing-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/change-request-pricing-rubric">
    <summary>Change Request Pricing Rubric: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Project from kickoff to client signoff (8–12 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="change-request-rate-card-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/change-request-rate-card-template">
    <summary>Change Request Rate Card Template: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/T&amp;M to fixed-price contract conversion (6 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="clickup-setup" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/clickup-setup">
    <summary>ClickUp workspace architecture: 4-level hierarchy (Workspace → Space → Folder → List), ClickApps configuration (Sprints, Time Tracking, Custom Fields, Priorities, Multiple Assignees), custom status workflow per space, views (List, Board, Gantt, Workload, Dashboard), and automation rules for status transitions and template application.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-decision-forcing-scripts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/client-decision-forcing-scripts">
    <summary>Client Decision Forcing Scripts: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Run an escalation conversation with a stakeholder' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-handover-master-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/client-handover-master-checklist">
    <summary>Client Handover Master Checklist: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/Handover to client in-house team (3 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-health-scorecard-agency" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/client-health-scorecard-agency">
    <summary>Client Health Scorecard Agency: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Quarterly retainer review per client' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-kickoff-script" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/client-kickoff-script">
    <summary>Client Kickoff Script: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Project initiation to first delivery (kickoff to week 4)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-maturity-assessment-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/client-maturity-assessment-rubric">
    <summary>Client Maturity Assessment Rubric: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Client onboarding into our delivery cadence (two weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-status-email-template-agency" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/client-status-email-template-agency">
    <summary>Client Status Email Template Agency: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Weekly client status email batch' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-status-report-multistyle" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/client-status-report-multistyle">
    <summary>Client Status Report Multistyle: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Async cross-timezone delivery cadence (P4 outsource)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-trust-rebuild-comms-templates" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/client-trust-rebuild-comms-templates">
    <summary>Client Trust Rebuild Comms Templates: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Distressed-project rescue (six-week turnaround)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-visibility-vs-velocity-tradeoff" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/client-visibility-vs-velocity-tradeoff">
    <summary>Client Visibility Vs Velocity Tradeoff: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Async cross-timezone delivery cadence (P4 outsource)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="communications-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/communications-management">
    <summary>A structured who-what-when-how matrix (comms/plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="communications-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/communications-management">
    <summary>Plan, execute, and monitor stakeholder communications so that the right people receive the right information at the right time.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitive-positioning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-planning/competitive-positioning">
    <summary>Competitive positioning defines how a product is uniquely valuable compared to alternatives — answering "why should customers choose us?" using April Dunford's six-step framework: competitive alternatives → unique attributes → value translation → best-fit customer → market category → positioning statement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitive-positioning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/competitive-positioning">
    <summary>Competitive positioning defines how your product is uniquely valuable compared to alternatives.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="continuous-discovery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/continuous-discovery">
    <summary>Continuous discovery is a weekly cadence of user interviews, feedback synthesis, and opportunity-to-roadmap diffing that keeps product decisions connected to fresh user evidence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="continuous-discovery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/continuous-discovery">
    <summary>Integrate discovery as a recurring operational cadence rather than a one-time project-start activity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="continuous-discovery-habits" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-planning/continuous-discovery-habits">
    <summary>Teresa Torres' framework: a product trio (PM + Design Lead + Tech Lead) runs weekly customer touchpoints and maps all signals into an Opportunity Solution Tree (OST).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="continuous-discovery-habits" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/continuous-discovery-habits">
    <summary>Weekly customer discovery framework where the Product Trio (PM, Design, Tech) maintains an Opportunity Solution Tree.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contractor-audition-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/contractor-audition-rubric">
    <summary>Contractor Audition Rubric: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Hiring screen / contractor audition' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contractor-utilization-heatmap" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/contractor-utilization-heatmap">
    <summary>Contractor Utilization Heatmap: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Friday cash-flow + utilization check' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-estimation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/cost-estimation">
    <summary>Structured approach to producing a defensible project cost baseline: bottom-up estimation from a WBS, three-point (PERT) uncertainty modelling, risk-driven contingency reserve, and a separate management reserve.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-estimation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/cost-estimation">
    <summary>A bottom-up cost estimation process: decompose the WBS into work packages, apply three-point PERT estimation per package, load labor with a fully-loaded multiplier (1.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-border-tax-cheatsheet" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/cross-border-tax-cheatsheet">
    <summary>Cross Border Tax Cheatsheet: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p3-technical-freelancer/Year-end tax, legal, and cash-flow close' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-role-handoff-protocol" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/project-manager/cross-role-handoff-protocol">
    <summary>Canonical handoff protocol (definition-of-ready, artifact list, sign-off mechanism) for BA -&gt; Architect -&gt; Dev -&gt; QA -&gt; DevOps transitions in multi-week product-team flows.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-team-estimation-normalisation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/cross-team-estimation-normalisation">
    <summary>Cross Team Estimation Normalisation: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Multi-team coordination program (continuous, weekly checkpoints)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-team-handoff-tracker" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/cross-team-handoff-tracker">
    <summary>Cross Team Handoff Tracker: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Run a 30-minute cross-team dependency call' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-team-points-calibration-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/cross-team-points-calibration-protocol">
    <summary>Cross Team Points Calibration Protocol: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/Story-points estimation poker with client team' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-timezone-standup-rotation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/cross-timezone-standup-rotation">
    <summary>Cross Timezone Standup Rotation: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Run a 15-minute daily standup that surfaces blockers, not status' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-tool-migration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/cross-tool-migration">
    <summary>Six-phase ETL process for migrating a project management tool portfolio between Jira, Linear, Asana, ClickUp, GitHub Projects, Azure DevOps, and others.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="daily-standup-ai-prebrief-template" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/daily-standup-ai-prebrief-template">
    <summary>Daily Standup Ai Prebrief Template: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p6-product-dev-team/Daily standup with AI pre-brief' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="delivery-maturity-rubric" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/delivery-maturity-rubric">
    <summary>Five-level rubric across PMBoK 7 performance domains so annual delivery-process reviews score on anchored behaviours instead of opinion.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="delivery-sop-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/delivery-sop-template">
    <summary>Template for writing a productized-service runbook that lets a senior contractor execute a recurring service end-to-end without founder QA on every step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dependency-graph-reasoning" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/dependency-graph-reasoning">
    <summary>Builds, maintains, and queries a cross-task / cross-team dependency graph for multi-team product PMs — "what is at risk if X slips by 1 week" answered deterministically.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dependency-slack-thresholds" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/dependency-slack-thresholds">
    <summary>Dependency Slack Thresholds delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Run a 30-minute cross-team dependency call' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: When 'slip' becomes 'escalate' is undefined; needed for predictable handoff governan</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-review-pr-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/design-review-pr-checklist">
    <summary>PR-time design-QA checklist (tokens used, components reused, motion respects prefers-reduced-motion, a11y intact, content rules honored) — gates whether the implementation matches the design.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="distressed-project-diagnostic-script" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/distressed-project-diagnostic-script">
    <summary>Distressed Project Diagnostic Script delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Distressed-project rescue (six-week turnaround)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Rescue work is high-value but corpus has nothing on the diagnostic its</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="earned-value-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/earned-value-management">
    <summary>EVM is an objective, formula-driven approach to project performance measurement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="earned-value-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/earned-value-management">
    <summary>Earned Value Management (EVM) measures project performance by integrating scope, schedule, and cost into three numbers — Planned Value (PV), Earned Value (EV), and Actual Cost (AC) — and derives objective indices (SPI, CPI) and forecasts (EAC, TCPI) that predict final cost and completion date.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="engagement-handover-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/engagement-handover-playbook">
    <summary>Engagement Handover Playbook delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Engagement Handover / Transition Out' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: project-closure exists but is org-internal flavoured (lessons-learned, benefits-realizati</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="engineering-ladder-and-growth-plan" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/engineering-ladder-and-growth-plan">
    <summary>Ladder definitions (L1-L5 with example artifacts), growth-plan template, promo packet template — without it juniors leave.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="escalation-conversation-script" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/escalation-conversation-script">
    <summary>Scripted openers, de-escalation patterns, written-vs-verbal decision rules, and follow-up commitments for the actual conversation a PM has when a client is unhappy or a vendor missed a date.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="escalation-decision-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/escalation-decision-template">
    <summary>Escalation Decision Template delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Run an escalation conversation with a stakeholder' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: stakeholder-engagement-advanced covers theory; missing a 1-pager template th</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="estimation-calibration-loop" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/estimation-calibration-loop">
    <summary>Estimation Calibration Loop delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'AI-assisted sprint planning with capacity reality-check' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: cost-estimation templates exist; nothing for ongoing estimation calibra</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ev-for-fixed-bid-outsource" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/ev-for-fixed-bid-outsource">
    <summary>Earned Value variant for fixed-bid outsourcing where revenue is locked but vendor margin tracks against PV/EV/AC at the work-package level — the EVM flavour PMBoK does not document.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="exception-driven-standup-protocol" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/exception-driven-standup-protocol">
    <summary>Exception Driven Standup Protocol delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Daily standup with AI pre-brief' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Distributed teams waste the most time on status theater. We have ceremony pages but no op</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="experimentation-at-scale" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-operations/experimentation-at-scale">
    <summary>Enterprise experimentation is a disciplined platform — not ad-hoc A/B testing — with defined hypothesis intake, pre-registered metrics, guardrails, SRM checks, and a learning-extraction step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="experimentation-at-scale" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/experimentation-at-scale">
    <summary>Run 100+ experiments/year with statistical rigor.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-prioritization-moscow" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/feature-prioritization-moscow">
    <summary>MoSCoW categorizes requirements into Must Have, Should Have, Could Have, and Won't Have buckets for a fixed-timebox release.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-prioritization-rice" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-operations/feature-prioritization-rice">
    <summary>Quantitative scoring model that ranks features by `(Reach × Impact × Confidence) / Effort`.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-prioritization-rice" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/feature-prioritization-rice">
    <summary>Score each candidate feature as (Reach x Impact x Confidence) / Effort.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feedback-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/feedback-management">
    <summary>Pipeline to turn scattered feedback into product decisions with fixed taxonomy, weighted by segment ARR and retention risk.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feedback-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-operations/feedback-management">
    <summary>Systematic pipeline for collecting feedback from multiple channels, categorizing it against a locked taxonomy, aggregating patterns by topic and segment, linking top clusters to backlog items, and closing the loop with users when their requests ship.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fixed-price-three-point-estimation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/fixed-price-three-point-estimation">
    <summary>Three-point + Monte Carlo cost recipe tuned for outsource fixed-price bids: every WBS leaf gets O/M/P estimates anchored to senior-dev hourly economics and an AI-agent productivity factor, then 10k-run simulation produces a P85 bid price plus a separate vendor risk reserve.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fixed-price-vs-tnm-decision-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/fixed-price-vs-tnm-decision-framework">
    <summary>Fixed Price Vs Tnm Decision Framework delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Fixed-Price vs T&amp;M Estimation with AI Risk Buffer' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Decision rule (when does fixed-price burn margin, when does T&amp;M los</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="follow-the-sun-handoff-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/follow-the-sun-handoff-protocol">
    <summary>Follow The Sun Handoff Protocol delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Async cross-timezone delivery cadence (P4 outsource)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Specific to P4 outsource PMs running EU + LATAM or APAC + NA teams. No</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="foreign-client-etiquette-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/foreign-client-etiquette-playbook">
    <summary>Foreign Client Etiquette Playbook delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Foreign-Client Engagement Bootstrap' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Communication patterns differ sharply: US-direct, German-precise, Japanese-indirect,</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="foreign-client-kickoff-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/foreign-client-kickoff-checklist">
    <summary>Foreign Client Kickoff Checklist delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Foreign-client project kickoff (2 weeks)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Outsource kickoffs across US/EU/UK/AU timezones have a recurring 30+ item checkli</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="founder-as-pm-survival-kit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/founder-as-pm-survival-kit">
    <summary>The three PM artefacts a micro-agency founder must keep when there is no PM — and the dozen others to drop without guilt.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="founder-time-audit-tool" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/founder-time-audit-tool">
    <summary>Founder Time Audit Tool — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. resource-management methodology covers teams; agencies need a personal-time-allocation audit specifically for the founder bottleneck.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-capacity-model" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/freelance-capacity-model">
    <summary>Freelance Capacity Model — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. Solo-operator weekly time-allocation across delivery / pipeline / self / R&amp;D; OKR-setting alone doesn't model the brutal trade-off of 1 person's 40 hours.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-insurance-buyers-guide" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/freelance-insurance-buyers-guide">
    <summary>Freelance Insurance Buyers Guide — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. E&amp;O / professional liability / cyber insurance is a freelancer blind spot; need a methodology that scopes coverage to the kind of work delivered.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-msa-sow-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/freelance-msa-sow-templates">
    <summary>Contractual primitives the P3 freelancer signs every month: MSA + SOW skeleton with deposit, weekly invoicing, IP-transfer-on-payment, warranty clause — and an explicit gap between MSA umbrella terms and per-engagement SOW specifics that keeps both signable in a week.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-weekly-invoice-cadence" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/freelance-weekly-invoice-cadence">
    <summary>Freelance Weekly Invoice Cadence — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. 74% don't get paid on time. Need a methodology for weekly invoicing + automated reminders + escalation ladder that doesn't burn the relationship.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-client-scorecard" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/freelancer-client-scorecard">
    <summary>Freelancer Client Scorecard — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. portfolio-strategy is product-oriented. Freelancers need a 5-axis client scorecard (rate, payment, scope discipline, growth potential, energy cost) for quarterly rebalance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-handover-bundle-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/freelancer-handover-bundle-template">
    <summary>Freelancer Handover Bundle Template — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. Concrete checklist + doc template for everything a freelancer must hand over at project end (repo, runbook, creds, future-work, contact-of-record). project-closure is process-level, not artifact-level.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-personal-crm-minimal" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/freelancer-personal-crm-minimal">
    <summary>A 30-minute-to-setup personal CRM in Notion / Airtable / plaintext covering leads, active clients, follow-up cadence, and payment reliability for solo freelancers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-proposal-template-fixed-vs-tm" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/freelancer-proposal-template-fixed-vs-tm">
    <summary>Freelancer Proposal Template Fixed Vs Tm — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. Comparison template + decision tree for fixed-scope vs. T&amp;M cap vs. retainer pricing. Bigger PM methodologies cover scope/cost but not the solo's pricing-model choice.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-year-end-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/freelancer-year-end-checklist">
    <summary>Freelancer Year End Checklist — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. Single-page year-end SOP combining books, taxes, legal, insurance, and planning — none of the existing ops-* methodologies stitch these together for a solo operator.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="github-projects" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/github-projects">
    <summary>For teams already on GitHub, GitHub Projects provides native code-task traceability: "Fixes #123" in a PR automatically transitions the linked issue to Done when merged.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitlab-boards" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/gitlab-boards">
    <summary>GitLab Issue Boards integrate kanban-style project management directly into GitLab's DevOps platform.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitlab-boards" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/gitlab-boards">
    <summary>GitLab Issue Boards provide kanban-style project management integrated directly with GitLab's DevOps platform.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="handover-pack-template-outsource" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/handover-pack-template-outsource">
    <summary>Handover Pack Template Outsource — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. Project-closure handover templates exist but they are PMI-flavored. Outsource specialist rotation handover is different: usually mid-project, not final close, and aimed at peer or in-house team.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hybrid-delivery" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/hybrid-delivery">
    <summary>Hybrid delivery is a framework for programs that combine predictive (waterfall) and agile delivery modes when neither alone fits.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hybrid-delivery" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/hybrid-delivery">
    <summary>A delivery model that combines predictive (waterfall/stage-gate) and agile methods within a single program, assigning each by component risk profile.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="incident-comms-templates-internal-external" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/incident-comms-templates-internal-external">
    <summary>Incident Comms Templates Internal External — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. Communications-management is generic. Incidents need ready-to-edit templates for status page, customer email, exec brief, and internal channel; absence costs minutes during outages.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="indie-hacker-tax-and-legal-essentials" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/indie-hacker-tax-and-legal-essentials">
    <summary>MoR vs direct invoicing, Estonia e-Residency, US LLC for non-residents, VAT MOSS — the pre-first-sale tax/legal checklist with zero faion coverage today.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="indie-postmortem-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-operations/indie-postmortem-template">
    <summary>Structured postmortem template for indie hackers and small-team founders to turn failed launches into public consumption — narrative arc, learning extraction, metrics, opt-in privacy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jira-workflow-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/jira-workflow-management">
    <summary>Configure and operate Jira projects for Scrum/Kanban/JSM teams: issue type schemes, workflow states/transitions, automation rules, JQL queries, and board configuration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jira-workflow-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/jira-workflow-management">
    <summary>Jira workflow management covers project setup, issue-type scheme design, workflow state machines, automation rules, and JQL queries for Scrum and Kanban teams.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kanban-scaled-agile-ceremonies" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/kanban-scaled-agile-ceremonies">
    <summary>Alternative agile cadences for continuous-flow teams (Kanban) and multi-team programs (SAFe).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="knowledge-sharing-ritual-set" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/knowledge-sharing-ritual-set">
    <summary>Weekly tech-talk, biweekly demo, monthly architecture review, quarterly skip-level — the rituals that convert tribal knowledge to documented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="launch-raci-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/launch-raci-template">
    <summary>Launch Raci Template — testable methodology for delivery, scheduling, RACI, throughput. stakeholder-management covers communication, not the launch-specific RACI with eng / design / marketing / sales / support owners per workstream.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="launch-readiness-review" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/launch-readiness-review">
    <summary>A cross-functional pre-launch readiness review covering 8 gates (security, performance, observability, runbooks, on-call, legal, support enablement, comms tree) that turns implicit launch knowledge into a hard go/no-go decision.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="learning-speed-competitive-moat" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-operations/learning-speed-competitive-moat">
    <summary>When AI lets anyone clone product features in weeks, the durable competitive advantage is how quickly an org notices changes, updates its beliefs, and ships different answers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="learning-speed-competitive-moat" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/learning-speed-competitive-moat">
    <summary>A framework for treating organizational learning velocity as the primary competitive advantage in markets where AI lets competitors clone product experiences in weeks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lessons-learned" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/lessons-learned">
    <summary>Structured knowledge-capture process that runs continuously throughout a project, not only at close-out.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lessons-learned" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/lessons-learned">
    <summary>Continuous capture, structured categorisation, and mandatory retrieval of project knowledge so that the same mistakes are not repeated.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="linear-issue-tracking" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/linear-issue-tracking">
    <summary>Linear is purpose-built for high-velocity software teams.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="linear-issue-tracking" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/pm-agile/linear-issue-tracking">
    <summary>Linear's opinionated, minimal workflow eliminates configuration overhead — teams are productive in under an hour.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="methodologies-summary" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/methodologies-summary">
    <summary>A routing index for all 33 methodologies in pro/product/product-manager/.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="micro-mvp-cut-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/micro-mvp-cut-rubric">
    <summary>A mechanical rubric for cutting any product feature to a day-sized (≤ 8 hours) slice without losing the user value.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="micro-mvps" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/micro-mvps">
    <summary>Micro-MVPs are extremely small, high-signal experiments designed to validate one key assumption in hours to days rather than weeks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="micro-mvps" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/micro-mvps">
    <summary>Micro-MVPs are extremely small, high-signal experiments (hours to days) that validate one specific assumption before committing engineering time.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="minimum-product-frameworks" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/minimum-product-frameworks">
    <summary>A selection matrix for choosing one of nine "minimum product" frameworks — MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC — before the first spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="minimum-product-frameworks" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/minimum-product-frameworks">
    <summary>A decision matrix for choosing the right "minimum X product" framework for a given market context.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mlp-planning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/mlp-planning">
    <summary>Minimum Lovable Product planning: a four-layer audit framework (Functional → Reliable → Usable → Delightful) for evolving an MVP that users find "fine" into one they love and recommend.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mlp-planning" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/mlp-planning">
    <summary>Plan the upgrade from a validated MVP to a Minimum Lovable Product: a four-layer audit (Functional → Reliable → Usable → Delightful) that identifies the specific gap between "it works" and "I love it".</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="monthly-billing-batch-routine" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/monthly-billing-batch-routine">
    <summary>Monthly Billing Batch Routine: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Monthly invoice + contractor pay batch' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-project-allocation-tracker" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/multi-project-allocation-tracker">
    <summary>Multi Project Allocation Tracker: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Run a 30-minute resource allocation review' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mvp-scoping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/mvp-scoping">
    <summary>Define the smallest product version that validates a hypothesis: one core problem, one user, one measurable learning goal, a kill criterion, and Must-Have features capped at 60% of build capacity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mvp-scoping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/mvp-scoping">
    <summary>A six-step process for compressing a feature backlog into a minimum viable product: define the core problem, identify the single job the product must do, categorise all features with MoSCoW, validate scope fits the timeline, and define explicit "won't have" and kill-signal criteria.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="nomad-low-energy-mode" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/nomad-low-energy-mode">
    <summary>A working-mode template for digital-nomad solopreneurs that swaps stable-workstation defaults (live deploys, 4-hour focus blocks, real-time pairing) for offline-first, async-only, 2-hour-window work suitable for travel, jet-lag, and 4G hotspots.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="notion-pm" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/notion-pm">
    <summary>Notion's relational databases let teams connect tasks, projects, docs, and meeting notes in one tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="notion-pm" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/pm-agile/notion-pm">
    <summary>Notion PM uses interconnected databases (Projects, Tasks, Sprints) with relation and rollup fields to build a customizable agile workspace.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="okr-cascade-multi-squad" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/okr-cascade-multi-squad">
    <summary>Cascades a single company OKR set into 3-6 squad OKR sets with explicit dependency edges, weekly check-in cadence, and post-quarter retro.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="okr-cascade-team-to-company" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/okr-cascade-team-to-company">
    <summary>Copy-pasteable OKR cascade template for an 8-10 person multi-role product team — alignment review, contribution mapping, dependency declaration, and quarterly review cadence wired in.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="okr-setting" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/okr-setting">
    <summary>OKRs (Objectives and Key Results) connect inspiring qualitative goals to quantitative progress measures within a fixed period.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="okr-setting" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/okr-setting">
    <summary>OKRs (Objectives and Key Results) combine qualitative inspiring goals (Objectives) with quantitative outcome measures (Key Results).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="outcome-based-roadmaps" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/outcome-based-roadmaps">
    <summary>An outcome-based roadmap replaces feature commitments with measurable metric targets as the unit of planning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="outcome-based-roadmaps" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/outcome-based-roadmaps">
    <summary>An outcome-based roadmap replaces feature commitments with measurable metric movements — each row states a problem, an outcome ("metric from baseline to target by horizon"), and 2-3 candidate solutions rather than a single committed feature.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced">
    <summary>Advanced outcome roadmapping closes the gap between high-level business goals and the product experiments that move them.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced">
    <summary>Decompose a top-line business goal into 2-4 product outcomes, each with a leading indicator measurable within 4 weeks, a confidence level (low/med/high) backed by evidence, and 2-3 candidate experiments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="outsource-onboarding-one-pager-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/outsource-onboarding-one-pager-template">
    <summary>Outsource Onboarding One Pager Template: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'role-project-manager/Client onboarding into our delivery cadence (two weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="paid-trial-task-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/paid-trial-task-library">
    <summary>Paid Trial Task Library: codified pm practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Hiring screen / contractor audition' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="performance-domains-overview" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/performance-domains-overview">
    <summary>PMBoK 7 defines eight interconnected performance domains — Stakeholder, Team, Development Approach, Planning, Project Work, Delivery, Measurement, Uncertainty — that together enable successful project delivery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="performance-domains-overview" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/performance-domains-overview">
    <summary>PMBOK 7 organizes project management into eight concurrent, interconnected performance domains — Stakeholder, Team, Development Approach, Planning, Project Work, Delivery, Measurement, Uncertainty — each focused on outcomes rather than process steps.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pm-1on1-template-engineering-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/pm-1on1-template-engineering-design">
    <summary>Opinionated agenda template for weekly PM ↔ EM, design lead, support lead 1:1s — tuned for product-org reality.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pm-certification-alignment-2026" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/pm-certification-alignment-2026">
    <summary>Maps existing project-manager methodology content to the 2026 PMBOK 8 / PMP Examination Content Outline (ECO) domain weights and five exam themes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pm-certification-alignment-2026" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/pm-certification-alignment-2026">
    <summary>Curriculum and content alignment to the 2026 PMP Exam Content Outline (ECO).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pm-certification-changes-2026" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/pm-certification-changes-2026">
    <summary>The PMP exam form active from July 1, 2026 shifts domain weights significantly: People drops from 42% to 33%, Process from 50% to 41%, and Business Environment rises from 8% to 26% (+18pp).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pm-certification-changes-2026" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/pm-certification-changes-2026">
    <summary>The PMP exam ECO (Examination Content Outline) changes effective July 1, 2026: People domain drops from 42% to 33%, Process drops from 50% to 41%, and Business Environment rises from 8% to 26%.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pm-framework-focus-areas" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/pm-framework-focus-areas">
    <summary>PMBoK 8 replaces the rigid five Process Groups with five Focus Areas (Initiating, Planning, Executing, Monitoring and Controlling, Closing) distributed across seven Performance Domains.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pm-framework-focus-areas" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/pm-framework-focus-areas">
    <summary>PMBOK 8 replaces Process Groups with five method-agnostic Focus Areas — Initiating, Planning, Executing, Monitoring &amp; Controlling, Closing — distributed across 40 non-prescriptive processes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pm-tool-selection" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/pm-tool-selection">
    <summary>Structured evaluation framework for selecting or replacing a project management tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pm-tools-comparison" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/pm-tools-comparison">
    <summary>A structured framework for evaluating and selecting project management tools through a weighted scoring matrix (Core Features 30%, Usability 25%, Integrations 20%, Enterprise 15%, Cost 10%), a two-week proof-of-concept protocol, total cost of ownership (TCO) analysis, and an ADR template for recording the decision.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pm-tools-overview" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/pm-tools-overview">
    <summary>A structured framework for selecting the right project management tool based on team size, workflow complexity, compliance requirements, and ecosystem fit.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="portfolio-evm-rollup-method" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/portfolio-evm-rollup-method">
    <summary>Portfolio EVM Rollup Method — pinned method for the project manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so annual delivery-process maturity review stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="portfolio-strategy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-planning/portfolio-strategy">
    <summary>The Three Horizons portfolio model allocates engineering capacity across H1 (Core, 70%), H2 (Adjacent, 20%), and H3 (Transformational, 10%), with ratios adjustable to macro conditions (Growth 60/25/15, Stable 70/20/10, Recession 80/15/5).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="portfolio-strategy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/portfolio-strategy">
    <summary>Allocates product investment across three horizons: 70% Core (H1, known market, 0-12 months), 20% Adjacent (H2, new segments, 12-24 months), 10% Transformational (H3, breakthrough bets, 24-36 months).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="post-handover-warranty-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/post-handover-warranty-runbook">
    <summary>Post Handover Warranty Runbook — pinned runbook for the outsource delivery specialist: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so handover to client in-house team (3 weeks) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="predictive-analytics-pm" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/predictive-analytics-pm">
    <summary>Apply machine learning to historical project data to generate early-warning signals for schedule slip, budget overrun, resource contention, and material price risk — turning raw PM telemetry into probability-interval forecasts that change PMO decisions before events occur.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="predictive-analytics-pm" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/predictive-analytics-pm">
    <summary>The application of ML-based forecasting to project management: schedule delay early warning, budget overrun detection, resource utilization optimization, and risk pattern mining from issue tracker data.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="procurement-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/procurement-management">
    <summary>Six-step framework for engaging external vendors: make-or-buy decision, Statement of Work (SOW) with explicit acceptance criteria, contract type selection (Fixed Price / T&amp;M / Cost Plus), weighted vendor evaluation, contract negotiation, and ongoing vendor management.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="procurement-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/procurement-management">
    <summary>Structured vendor engagement: make-or-buy decisions, Statement of Work authoring, contract type selection, vendor evaluation scoring, and ongoing performance monitoring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-analytics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/product-analytics">
    <summary>Product analytics is measuring and analyzing user behavior to make better product decisions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-analytics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-operations/product-analytics">
    <summary>Framework for measuring user behavior to drive product decisions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-discovery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/product-discovery">
    <summary>Product discovery is a time-boxed process (1–4 weeks) for de-risking an idea before committing build resources.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-discovery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/product-discovery">
    <summary>Systematically de-risk ideas before committing engineering capacity by testing four risk types: Value (will customers use it?), Usability (can they figure it out?), Feasibility (can we build it?), and Business Viability (does it work for the business?).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-explainability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-operations/product-explainability">
    <summary>Product explainability is how clearly a product communicates its purpose, value, behavior, and limits to both humans and AI systems.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-explainability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/product-explainability">
    <summary>PM-specific lens: this methodology is a communication discipline, not a marketing artifact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-launch" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/product-launch">
    <summary>A product launch is a coordinated introduction of a product to its target market — not just a deployment, but a strategic moment to generate awareness and initial adoption.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-launch" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/product-launch">
    <summary>A product launch is the coordinated introduction of a product to its target market.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-led-growth" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-operations/product-led-growth">
    <summary>PLG uses the product itself as the primary acquisition, activation, and expansion engine: self-serve onboarding, a clearly defined "aha moment" under 5 minutes, usage-gated upgrade triggers, and PQL scoring that hands off to sales-assist at the right moment.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-led-growth" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/product-led-growth">
    <summary>PLG is a metric-driven loop, not a feature shipping cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-lifecycle" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/product-lifecycle">
    <summary>A four-stage framework (Introduction → Growth → Maturity → Decline) for diagnosing which lifecycle stage a product is in and applying the matching investment strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-lifecycle" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-operations/product-lifecycle">
    <summary>Framework for assessing which of four lifecycle stages a product is in (Introduction, Growth, Maturity, Decline) and applying stage-appropriate strategy, metrics, and investments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-operations" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-operations/product-operations">
    <summary>A dedicated Product Ops function removes operational drag — process docs, tool plumbing, status updates, metric rollups, stakeholder comms — so PMs spend more time on discovery and strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-operations" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/product-operations">
    <summary>When a Product Ops function exists, the PM is a consumer and partner — not its operator.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-trio-rituals" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/product-trio-rituals">
    <summary>Product Trio Rituals — pinned ritual for the product manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so reset prioritization war with mixed-method scoring stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="program-dependency-aging-chart-recipe" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/program-dependency-aging-chart-recipe">
    <summary>Program Dependency Aging Chart Recipe — pinned recipe for the project manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so multi-team coordination program (continuous, weekly checkpoints) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="program-weekly-note-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/program-weekly-note-template">
    <summary>Program Weekly Note Template — pinned template for the project manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so multi-team coordination program (continuous, weekly checkpoints) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="project-closure" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/project-closure">
    <summary>A formal 7-step process to end a project: verify deliverable acceptance with signed artefacts, close financial and contract obligations, conduct lessons learned before the team disperses, archive all documentation, produce a final report, hand over to operations, and recognise the team.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="project-closure" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/project-closure">
    <summary>Formal termination process for a project: obtain written deliverable acceptance, release resources, close contracts, capture lessons learned, archive documents, and transition to operations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="project-closure-with-lessons-extraction" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-closure-with-lessons-extraction">
    <summary>Project Closure With Lessons Extraction — pinned method for the project manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so distressed-project rescue (90-day turnaround) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="project-integration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/project-integration">
    <summary>The PM acts as integrator across all knowledge areas (scope, schedule, cost, quality, risk, resources, communications, procurement) through a single version-controlled integrated plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="project-integration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/project-integration">
    <summary>The PM as integrator ensures that decisions in scope, schedule, cost, quality, risk, resources, communications, and procurement are consistent and mutually reinforcing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="proposal-red-team-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/proposal-red-team-checklist">
    <summary>Proposal Red Team Checklist — pinned checklist for the outsource delivery specialist: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so fixed-price bid discovery + estimation (1 week) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="quality-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/quality-management">
    <summary>A three-process framework (Plan Quality → Manage Quality → Control Quality) applied as code-driven gates: DoD checked per PR by an automated validator, defect metrics aggregated weekly by a collector agent, and severity classified by a triager with human confirmation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="quality-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/quality-management">
    <summary>Three-process quality discipline: Plan Quality (define standards and measurable thresholds), Manage Quality / Assurance (ensure processes produce quality), and Control Quality (verify deliverables meet standards via deterministic gates).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="quarterly-retainer-review-script" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/quarterly-retainer-review-script">
    <summary>A 45-minute scripted quarterly review call for retainer clients that converts utilization data into renewal commitment.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="quit-day-job-trigger-contract" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/quit-day-job-trigger-contract">
    <summary>Quit Day Job Trigger Contract — pinned method for the solo SaaS builder: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so $0 → $4k mrr bootstrap journey stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="raci-ai-assisted" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/raci-ai-assisted">
    <summary>RACI AI Assisted — pinned method for the project manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so multi-team coordination &amp; dependency-graph reasoning (p6 product) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="raci-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/raci-matrix">
    <summary>Assign one of four roles — Responsible (does the work), Accountable (single decision owner), Consulted (provides input), Informed (notified after) — to each role for each task or deliverable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="raci-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/raci-matrix">
    <summary>A RACI matrix assigns exactly one of four roles — Responsible, Accountable, Consulted, Informed — to each stakeholder for each task or deliverable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-policy-thresholds" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/rag-policy-thresholds">
    <summary>RAG Policy Thresholds — pinned method for the project manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so write the weekly client status report (p4) / leadership update (p6) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ramp-task-difficulty-ladder" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/ramp-task-difficulty-ladder">
    <summary>Ramp Task Difficulty Ladder — pinned method for the product-dev team: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so hire + onboard a new product-team dev in 2 weeks stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ref-pmbok" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/ref-pmbok">
    <summary>Quick-reference tables for PMBoK 7 (8 performance domains, 12 principles) and PMBoK 8 (7 domains, 6 principles), plus EVM formulae, estimation accuracy bands, risk response strategies, and RAG status thresholds.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="regulatory-uncertainty-buffer" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/regulatory-uncertainty-buffer">
    <summary>Regulatory Uncertainty Buffer — pinned buffer for the outsource delivery specialist: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so fixed-price vs t&amp;m estimation with ai risk buffer stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="release-planning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/release-planning">
    <summary>Structured approach to bundling, scheduling, and communicating product releases across cross-functional teams.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="release-planning" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/release-planning">
    <summary>Six-step process for deciding what goes into each release, when it ships, and how it is communicated.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="remote-1-1-async-fallback" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/remote-1-1-async-fallback">
    <summary>Remote 1 1 Async Fallback — pinned method for the project manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so hold a focused 1:1 with a team member stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reporting-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/reporting-basics">
    <summary>Effective reporting transforms raw project data into actionable insights.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reporting-dashboards" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/reporting-dashboards">
    <summary>Automated PM reporting: tool-specific dashboard configuration (Jira, Linear, ClickUp), scheduled report generation for weekly status and sprint reviews, Slack digest delivery, and BI tool integration (PowerBI, Metabase, Grafana) via API ETL.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="resource-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/resource-management">
    <summary>Identify required skills and quantities per work package, assess real availability (capped at 75-80% effective capacity), map resources to activities, level overloads via delay/split/add/cut options, and monitor utilization weekly against plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="resource-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/resource-management">
    <summary>Plan to 70% utilisation (not 100%), map skills to tasks from a YAML roster in git, level resource load using critical-path analysis, and track allocations weekly against actuals.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="retainer-renewal-decision-rule" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/retainer-renewal-decision-rule">
    <summary>Retainer Renewal Decision Rule — pinned decision-rule for the micro-agency founder: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so quarterly retainer review per client stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="retainer-vs-project-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/retainer-vs-project-rubric">
    <summary>Retainer Vs Project Rubric — pinned rubric for the micro-agency founder: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so productize one service from custom to fixed stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="retro-action-success-criteria-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/retro-action-success-criteria-template">
    <summary>Retro Action Success Criteria Template — pinned template for the product-dev team: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so bi-weekly retro with mistake-memory feedback stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="retro-facilitation-multistyle" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/retro-facilitation-multistyle">
    <summary>Retro Facilitation Multistyle — pinned method for the project manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so async cross-timezone delivery cadence (p4 outsource) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="retro-format-rotation-guide" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/retro-format-rotation-guide">
    <summary>Retro Format Rotation Guide — pinned guide for the project manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so run sprint review + retrospective back-to-back stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="risk-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/risk-management">
    <summary>Identify threats and opportunities, rate them by probability and impact, assign owners with observable triggers, plan responses, and monitor weekly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="risk-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/risk-management">
    <summary>Risk management is a structured process for identifying, scoring, responding to, and monitoring project uncertainty — including both threats (negative risks) and opportunities (positive risks).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="risk-register" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/risk-register">
    <summary>A structured log of identified threats and opportunities, each scored by probability x impact (1-25 scale), assigned a response strategy (Avoid/Transfer/Mitigate/Accept for threats; Exploit/Share/Enhance/Accept for opportunities), and owned by a named individual.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="risk-register" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/risk-register">
    <summary>A living log of identified threats and opportunities, each with a probability (1–5), impact (1–5), risk score (P×I), chosen response strategy, named owner, trigger condition, and current status.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="risk-threshold-policy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/risk-threshold-policy">
    <summary>Pre-agreed policy that defines which risk severity gets escalated to whom, when, and via which channel — closing the gap between "log the risk" and "act on the risk".</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="roadmap-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/roadmap-design">
    <summary>A roadmap is a strategic communication tool showing where the product is going and why — not a feature list with dates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="roadmap-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/roadmap-design">
    <summary>A five-step process for building a product roadmap as a strategic communication tool, not a delivery schedule.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rpo-rto-negotiation-guide" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/rpo-rto-negotiation-guide">
    <summary>RPO/RTO Negotiation Guide: structures the product-vs-cost conversation between architect and business stakeholders so DR targets are chosen by the buyer, not invented by engineering.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="saas-stack-audit-micro-agency" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/saas-stack-audit-micro-agency">
    <summary>SaaS Stack Audit (Micro-Agency): a 60-minute quarterly review that catches duplicate / unused SaaS tools draining $200-1k/mo from a small services firm.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="schedule-development" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/schedule-development">
    <summary>A deterministic process for building a project schedule from WBS work packages: define activities, sequence with dependency types (FS/FF/SS/SF), estimate durations using three-point PERT, run forward and backward pass to compute Early Start/Early Finish/Late Start/Late Finish per activity, identify the critical path (zero float), and place buffers at merge points and project end using Critical Chain methods rather than per-task padding.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="schedule-development" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/schedule-development">
    <summary>A process for converting WBS work packages into a sequenced, resourced, and buffered schedule with an identified critical path.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-change-vs-scope-creep-detection" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/scope-change-vs-scope-creep-detection">
    <summary>AI-assisted classifier that triages every new ticket as legitimate change (→ change-control process) vs scope creep (→ structured pushback) by comparing against the baseline spec, with Jira/Linear webhook integration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/scope-management">
    <summary>Define, baseline, validate, and control project scope to prevent uncontrolled expansion.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/scope-management">
    <summary>Scope management defines, documents, and controls what a project will and will not deliver.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scrum-ceremonies" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/scrum-ceremonies">
    <summary>The five Scrum events — Sprint Planning, Daily Standup, Sprint Review, Sprint Retrospective, and Backlog Refinement — with time-boxes, facilitation patterns (including async/remote variants), tool configurations, and quality gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="seven-performance-domains" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/seven-performance-domains">
    <summary>PMBoK 8 reorganises project management into seven performance domains: Governance, Scope, Schedule, Finance, Stakeholders, Resources, Risk.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="seven-performance-domains" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/seven-performance-domains">
    <summary>PMBOK 8 replaces the 10 Knowledge Areas with seven performance domains — Governance, Scope, Schedule, Finance, Stakeholders, Resources, Risk — as the primary PM rubric.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="shadow-handover-session-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/shadow-handover-session-runbook">
    <summary>Shadow Handover Session Runbook — codifies the offshore→onshore knowledge-transfer pattern (receiver-does, outgoing-watches) so handovers stop relying on tribal memory.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="side-project-financial-runway" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/side-project-financial-runway">
    <summary>Personal-runway math: monthly burn vs MRR ramp, when to leave a job, geo-arbitrage budget — life/business hybrid doc indie hackers need.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="six-core-principles" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/six-core-principles">
    <summary>PMBoK 8 consolidates the PMBoK 7 twelve principles into six: Adopt Holistic View, Focus on Value, Embed Quality, Lead Accountably, Integrate Sustainability, Build Empowered Teams.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="six-core-principles" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/six-core-principles">
    <summary>PMBOK 7 defines six guiding principles for every project management decision: Adopt Holistic View, Focus on Value, Embed Quality, Lead Accountably, Integrate Sustainability, and Build Empowered Teams.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="small-team-comms-rhythm" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/small-team-comms-rhythm">
    <summary>Small Team Comms Rhythm — a 2-to-3-person comms cadence (founder + 1-2 ICs, no scrum master) sized for micro-agencies and indie teams where formal PM artefacts are overkill.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-burnout-tripwires" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/solo-burnout-tripwires">
    <summary>Quantitative burnout-early-warning signals (sleep, weekend creep, MRR-to-effort drift) for solo founders — fires before the breakdown, not after.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-change-order-mini-contract" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/solo-change-order-mini-contract">
    <summary>One-page change-order template a freelancer emails when the client says "just one more thing" — signed within an hour, billable from that hour, no MSA renegotiation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-context-switch-protocol" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/solo-context-switch-protocol">
    <summary>Opinionated mode-batching protocol for the solo founder day — separates building from inbox/support/ops to cut context-switch cost from hours to minutes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-late-fee-and-pause-clause-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/solo-late-fee-and-pause-clause-template">
    <summary>Boilerplate contract clauses — late-fee schedule, work-pause right, re-engagement terms — that a freelancer can drop into a SOW or master agreement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-launch-day-runbook" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/solo-launch-day-runbook">
    <summary>Hour-by-hour operational runbook for a solo founder's launch day — Stripe live, monitoring armed, mailer warm, fallback content queued, support inbox, social burst — so the one operator does not improvise on the most expensive day of the quarter.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-mrr-dashboard-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/solo-mrr-dashboard-template">
    <summary>One-sheet MRR / churn / LTV dashboard spec calibrated for a one-operator SaaS — five canonical metrics, exact Stripe-API formulas, no finance team required.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-pivot-decision-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/solo-pivot-decision-framework">
    <summary>Opinionated pivot taxonomy (segment / feature / business-model / tech / channel) with triggers, sunk-cost guardrails, and a hard rule for distinguishing a pivot from quitting.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-rate-floor-calculator" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/solo-rate-floor-calculator">
    <summary>Solo-specific effective-hourly calculator that loads target income with taxes, downtime, marketing time, benefits, and tooling cost to produce a defensible rate floor below which engagements are mathematically unprofitable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-time-tracking-discipline" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/solo-time-tracking-discipline">
    <summary>Habit-plus-tooling discipline so the solo's billable hours are captured at the moment of work and Friday reconciliation collapses from 2h to 15min.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-utilization-and-pipeline-dashboard" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/solo-utilization-and-pipeline-dashboard">
    <summary>Lightweight utilization-and-pipeline dashboard (spreadsheet or Notion) for a freelance practice — drives rate decisions and prevents feast-or-famine.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-weekly-cadence-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/solo-weekly-cadence-template">
    <summary>Sunday-review + Monday-prime weekly cadence template tailored for a one-operator product — fixed artifacts, memory hooks, time-boxed.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spec-writing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/spec-writing">
    <summary>A product specification (PRD) defines WHAT to build and WHY, leaving HOW to design and engineering.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sprint-demo-script-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/sprint-demo-script-template">
    <summary>Sprint demo script for the senior-dev-runs-the-demo-for-exec-client variant — explicit per-AC accept/reject prompt, owner-named scope-cut decisions, and a decision log entry the engagement manager signs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sprint-goal-formula" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/sprint-goal-formula">
    <summary>Compact three-part sprint-goal formula (outcome + boundary + measure) that produces a single sentence the team can recite, used to filter scope additions and to grade the sprint at review.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sprint-goal-one-liner-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/sprint-goal-one-liner-template">
    <summary>A fill-in-the-blank template that compresses a sprint into one outcome sentence ("In sprint NN, we will &lt;verb&gt; &lt;user/system&gt; so that &lt;measurable benefit&gt;, focusing on &lt;surface&gt;, deferring &lt;out-of-scope&gt;"), recitable by every team member at standup.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-disagree-and-commit-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/stakeholder-disagree-and-commit-protocol">
    <summary>Explicit disagree-and-commit protocol for product roadmap decisions — named-dissent capture, escalation thresholds, and a time-boxed revisit trigger that prevents stakeholder drift from quietly unwinding the roadmap mid-quarter.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-engagement" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/stakeholder-engagement">
    <summary>A structured process to identify all parties affected by or affecting a project, map each on the Power/Interest grid, assign an engagement strategy per quadrant, and execute a communication cadence — stored as version-controlled YAML register so changes produce a diff history and evidence-backed attitudes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-engagement" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/stakeholder-engagement">
    <summary>Systematic identification, classification, and engagement of everyone who affects or is affected by the project.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-engagement-advanced" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/stakeholder-engagement-advanced">
    <summary>A structured process for moving stakeholders from their current engagement level (Unaware, Resistant, Neutral, Supportive, Leading) to a desired level through targeted, evidence-based activities.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-engagement-advanced" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/stakeholder-engagement-advanced">
    <summary>Stakeholder lists without engagement strategies produce transactional relationships where PMs reach out only when they need something.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-operations/stakeholder-management">
    <summary>Stakeholder management identifies everyone affected by a product (end users, decision makers, influencers, builders, support, external), maps them on a Power/Interest grid with an explicit attitude column (Supporter/Neutral/Resistor), assigns a named owner and engagement cadence per stakeholder, and codifies approval gates so agents can block SDD transitions until named approvers sign off.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/stakeholder-management">
    <summary>Stakeholder management is identifying everyone affected by your product, mapping them by power and interest, and running a systematic engagement cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-register" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/stakeholder-register">
    <summary>Identify every person or group who affects or is affected by the project, analyze their influence (power) and interest, classify into Power-Interest quadrants, and define an engagement strategy per quadrant.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-register" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/stakeholder-register">
    <summary>Hidden stakeholders block projects at the worst possible moments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-sentiment-tracker" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/stakeholder-sentiment-tracker">
    <summary>Methodology for an ongoing per-stakeholder sentiment trend (supportive / cautious / hostile) built from emails, chat threads, and meeting transcripts — gives the PM early warning weeks before a sponsor goes red.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="status-report-templates-by-audience" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/status-report-templates-by-audience">
    <summary>Audience-segmented status report templates — CEO, PMO, technical sponsor, internal leadership — that replace the one-size-fits-all weekly status email with reports each audience will actually read.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="steerco-meeting-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/steerco-meeting-playbook">
    <summary>End-to-end Steering Committee (Steerco) playbook — pre-meeting prep, in-meeting facilitation, post-meeting follow-up — calibrated for outsource-PM monthly and product-PM quarterly cadences.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="team-charter-working-agreement" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/team-charter-working-agreement">
    <summary>Team Charter Working Agreement: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p6-product-dev-team/Adopt faion org-wide and override with company patterns'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="team-development" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/team-development">
    <summary>A structured approach to building high-performing teams using Tuckman's five-stage model (Forming, Storming, Norming, Performing, Adjourning), a team charter with working agreements, a skills matrix for gap planning, and retrospective cycles for continuous improvement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="team-development" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/team-development">
    <summary>A framework for building high-performing project teams using Tuckman's stages (Forming → Storming → Norming → Performing → Adjourning) as the diagnostic backbone, paired with three artifact types: team charter, skills matrix, and retrospective template.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="team-morale-pulse-survey" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/team-morale-pulse-survey">
    <summary>A 4-question anonymous pulse survey (eNPS + workload + autonomy + clarity) run mid-sprint to catch morale slides before they turn into attrition or distressed-project signals.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="technical-debt-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/technical-debt-management">
    <summary>A six-step framework for making technical debt visible, quantified, and systematically paid down — covering debt registration, impact scoring (interest × contagion / effort), capacity allocation, and prevention policies.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="technical-debt-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-operations/technical-debt-management">
    <summary>Systematic process for making technical debt visible, quantifying its interest cost, prioritizing paydown against the roadmap, and allocating 15-20% of sprint capacity continuously.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="timezone-overlap-comms-charter" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/timezone-overlap-comms-charter">
    <summary>Timezone Overlap Comms Charter: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p4-outsource-specialist/Foreign-Client Engagement Bootstrap'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="timezone-overlap-handoff-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/timezone-overlap-handoff-protocol">
    <summary>Timezone Overlap Handoff Protocol: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p4-outsource-specialist/Cross-timezone async daily standup'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tiny-bets-quarterly-cadence" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/tiny-bets-quarterly-cadence">
    <summary>Tiny Bets Quarterly Cadence: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p2-indie-hacker/Multi-product portfolio rotation: ship N small bets per year'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tm-to-fp-conversion-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/tm-to-fp-conversion-playbook">
    <summary>Tm To Fp Conversion Playbook: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p4-outsource-specialist/T&amp;M to fixed-price contract conversion (6 weeks)'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tool-consolidation-decision-rule" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/tool-consolidation-decision-rule">
    <summary>Tool Consolidation Decision Rule: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Vendor / tool consolidation review'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tool-migration-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/tool-migration-basics">
    <summary>A structured approach to migrating project management data between tools, covering pre-migration audit, field mapping, ETL execution, and post-cutover validation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tool-migration-process" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/tool-migration-process">
    <summary>A phase-by-phase execution playbook for migrating project data between PM tools at org scale: six phases (Planning → Preparation → Pilot → Full Migration → Cutover → Stabilization) with an ETL engine, cutover checklist, rollback strategy, and change-management comms plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trello-kanban" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/project-manager/trello-kanban">
    <summary>A visual, card-based kanban workflow on Trello: board structure with WIP-limited lists, card anatomy with labels and checklists, Butler automation for rule-based transitions, custom fields for story points and sprint tracking, and REST API integration for agent-driven card management.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trello-kanban" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/pm/pm-agile/trello-kanban">
    <summary>Trello is a card-based kanban tool where work items move left-to-right through 5–7 named lists.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-story-mapping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/user-story-mapping">
    <summary>User story mapping arranges stories into a two-dimensional model: user activities as the horizontal backbone (left-to-right = user journey) and tasks stacked vertically by priority within each activity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-story-mapping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/user-story-mapping">
    <summary>Arrange user stories into a two-dimensional map: backbone activities run left-to-right (user journey), tasks are stacked vertically under each activity by priority.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="value-stream-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/value-stream-management">
    <summary>Map the end-to-end flow from customer request to customer value, measure it with Flow Metrics (Lead Time, Cycle Time, Throughput, WIP, %C/A) and DORA (Deployment Frequency, Change Lead Time, Change Failure Rate, MTTR), identify the constraint per Theory of Constraints, and run targeted experiments to elevate that constraint.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="value-stream-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/value-stream-management">
    <summary>Value Stream Management (VSM) maps the end-to-end path from customer request to delivered value and measures flow using Lead Time, Cycle Time, Process Time, %Complete/Accurate, and Throughput.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vendor-eval-framework" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/vendor-eval-framework">
    <summary>Scoring matrix + trial protocol + rollback gate for in-house team buying $50-500/mo SaaS (Datadog vs Grafana, Linear vs Jira, Vercel vs Netlify).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vendor-management-pm" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/vendor-management-pm">
    <summary>Vendor Management Pm: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-project-manager/Multi-team coordination &amp; dependency-graph reasoning (P6 product)'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vendor-margin-defense-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/vendor-margin-defense-checklist">
    <summary>A 6-pattern checklist that detects silent margin-eroding behaviours (silent scope creep, free analysis, missing change requests, AI rework loops, gold-plating, sympathy discounting) before they consume 10-20% of fixed-price project margin.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vendor-risk-assessment-template" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/pm/vendor-risk-assessment-template">
    <summary>Vendor Risk Assessment Template: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p6-product-dev-team/SOC2 / GDPR audit prep (annual)'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="verbatim-to-backlog-pattern" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/verbatim-to-backlog-pattern">
    <summary>Bridges Mom-Test verbatim customer quotes to prioritised backlog cards via a 4-step transform (extract → cluster → frame → prioritise) that keeps the customer's words attached to every story.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="warranty-period-sop" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/warranty-period-sop">
    <summary>Warranty Period Sop: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p3-technical-freelancer/Project kickoff to handover (typical 6-12 week engagement)'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="wbs-creation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/wbs-creation">
    <summary>Hierarchical decomposition of project scope into deliverable-oriented work packages using the 100% rule.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="wbs-creation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/wbs-creation">
    <summary>Without a WBS, estimates are guesses and dependencies are invisible until they block progress.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="weekly-status-report-outsource-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/weekly-status-report-outsource-template">
    <summary>Weekly Status Report Outsource Template: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p4-outsource-specialist/Weekly client status report'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="work-breakdown-structure" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/project-manager/work-breakdown-structure">
    <summary>A deliverable-oriented hierarchical decomposition of project scope into work packages — noun-based nodes (outputs), not verbs (activities).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="work-breakdown-structure" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-traditional/work-breakdown-structure">
    <summary>A hierarchical decomposition of total project scope into deliverable-oriented (noun-led) work packages.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="workflows" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/workflows">
    <summary>Two core PM pipelines: Project Bootstrap (idea → constitution → TASK_000) and MLP Planning (MVP → Most Lovable Product).</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
