<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Competitor Tracker Template (Solo) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Competitor Tracker Template (Solo) application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="channel-named-per-comp" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each competitor row pins ≥3 named channels watched. Generic 'their website' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Signal-source discipline">Without specific channels operators miss launches that don't hit the homepage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="delta-not-state" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Weekly scan logs DELTAS, not current state. State snapshots are kept monthly; weekly logs only what changed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Signal-vs-noise discipline">State snapshots flood the log; delta logs surface what matters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="triage-rule-applied" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each delta entry MUST carry a triage classification (ignore / log / queue / urgent). Untriaged deltas are rejected at review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Triage-routing discipline">Untriaged deltas produce decision paralysis; classification forces a routing decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="monthly-matrix-refresh" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Monthly matrix MUST be refreshed at month-end. Stale matrices (&gt;45 days) are flagged on read.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice">Without refresh cadence the matrix becomes folklore.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="action-link-per-queue" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any delta classified 'queue' or 'urgent' MUST link to a roadmap item or decision-record. Loose 'queue' entries with no link are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Action-traceability discipline">Queue without link rots into ignored backlog.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
