<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="wbs-creation">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Hierarchical decomposition of project scope into deliverable-oriented work packages using the 100% rule and 8-80 hour sizing with explicit acceptance criteria in a WBS Dictionary.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>wbs</tag>
      <tag>scope</tag>
      <tag>decomposition</tag>
      <tag>100-rule</tag>
      <tag>dictionary</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>WBS Creation</title>

    <summary>Hierarchical decomposition of project scope into deliverable-oriented work packages using the 100% rule. Each node in the tree is a noun (an output), not a verb (an activity). The lowest level items — work packages — are estimable (8-80 hours), assignable to one owner, and have explicit acceptance criteria documented in a WBS Dictionary.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without a WBS, scope is ambiguous: estimates are guesses, dependencies are invisible, and forgotten work surfaces too late to recover. The 100% rule forces completeness at every level — if all children are done, the parent is done. Deliverable orientation (nouns not verbs) keeps the tree stable when implementation decisions change.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Predictive/waterfall projects with fixed scope at kickoff (agency contracts, ERP rollouts, hardware launches)</item>
        <item>Hybrid delivery: WBS at program level, sprints underneath each work package</item>
        <item>Cost-loaded schedules and EVM tracking — WBS is the spine for cost accounts</item>
        <item>Migration projects (data, system, vendor) where every artefact must be enumerated</item>
        <item>Compliance projects (SOC2, HIPAA, ISO 27001) where 100% rule maps to control coverage</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure-agile teams driven by a product backlog — WBS calcifies what should flex</item>
        <item>Discovery / R&amp;D where deliverables are emergent — use a hypothesis backlog instead</item>
        <item>Fast-moving startup product work where scope changes weekly — overhead exceeds value</item>
        <item>Solo work on a feature under 2 weeks — a checklist beats a WBS</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="deliverable-orientation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Name every WBS node as a noun (the output produced), never as a verb (the activity performed).</statement>
        <rationale>Deliverable names remain stable when implementation changes; activity names do not. "User Authentication Module" survives a rewrite; "Build user authentication" does not.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="bad">
        <note>Verb-based decomposition — breaks when approach changes.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1.1 Design authentication
1.2 Code authentication
1.3 Test authentication
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Deliverable-based — stable regardless of method.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1.1 Authentication Module
    1.1.1 Registration System
    1.1.2 Login / Logout
    1.1.3 Password Reset
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="100-percent-rule">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every level must capture 100% of the work in its parent — no gaps, no overlaps.</statement>
        <rationale>Gaps create forgotten work that surfaces late. Overlaps create double-counted effort and budget conflicts. The rule is verified by asking: "If all children are complete, is the parent complete?"</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Always include the following overhead branches or flag their absence as a defect: Project Management, QA, Deployment, Documentation, Training, Transition.</statement>
        <rationale>Overhead is 15-25% of real project effort. Agents and manual drafters systematically omit it, creating a budget gap from day one.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="work-package-sizing">
      <rule>
        <statement>Leaf nodes (work packages) must have an effort estimate between 8 and 80 hours. Nodes outside this range must be split or merged.</statement>
        <rationale>Below 8 hours the tracking overhead exceeds the tracking value. Above 80 hours the estimate is a guess and dependencies are invisible. The 8/80 rule is a calibration heuristic, not a law — adjust the bounds to match your tracking unit.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Stop decomposing when the 8/80 rule is satisfied; more than 4 levels rarely adds estimate accuracy.</statement>
        <rationale>Deep trees create maintenance overhead and give a false sense of precision without improving schedule or cost predictability.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="id-stability">
      <rule>
        <statement>WBS IDs are append-only: once assigned, a numeric ID (1.2.3) never changes or gets reused, even if the node is deleted.</statement>
        <rationale>Change requests, risk entries, and tasks reference WBS IDs. Renumbering breaks traceability across the whole project record.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="wbs-dictionary">
      <p>The WBS Dictionary gives each work package a verifiable definition; without it, the numbered outline is just a list of labels.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every leaf work package must have a Dictionary entry with: ID, Name, Description (scope of what is included AND what is excluded), Deliverable (the tangible output), Acceptance Criteria (observable, testable), Owner (one person or named team), Estimate (hours), Dependencies (predecessor IDs).</statement>
        <rationale>Missing acceptance criteria make formal sign-off subjective. Missing exclusions cause scope creep. Missing ownership causes handoff gaps.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Complete dictionary entry for a single work package.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Field               | Value                                                        |
|---------------------|--------------------------------------------------------------|
| WBS ID              | 1.2.2                                                        |
| Name                | Search Functionality                                         |
| Description         | Full-text search across products; excludes faceted filters   |
| Deliverable         | Working search endpoint + UI component                       |
| Acceptance Criteria | Returns relevant results in < 2 s for 10k product catalogue  |
| Owner               | Backend Team                                                 |
| Effort Estimate     | 40 hours                                                     |
| Dependencies        | 1.2.1 (Product Database)                                     |
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-wbs-examples">
      <example type="good">
        <note>E-commerce WBS showing three levels with mandatory PM branch.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1. E-commerce Website
   1.1 Project Management
       1.1.1 Planning Documentation
       1.1.2 Status Reporting
       1.1.3 Risk Management
   1.2 User Management
       1.2.1 Registration System
       1.2.2 Login / Logout
       1.2.3 Profile Management
   1.3 Product Catalog
       1.3.1 Product Database
       1.3.2 Search Functionality
       1.3.3 Category Navigation
   1.4 Shopping Cart
       1.4.1 Cart Management
       1.4.2 Checkout Process
       1.4.3 Payment Integration
   1.5 Deployment and Transition
       1.5.1 Production Deploy
       1.5.2 Monitoring Setup
       1.5.3 Handover Documentation
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>WBS without a Dictionary — just a numbered outline.</description>
        <reason>Numbers without definitions leave acceptance criteria, ownership, and scope boundaries undefined. The tree looks complete but is not actionable.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Mixing WBS with schedule — adding start/end dates to nodes.</description>
        <reason>The WBS answers "what"; the schedule answers "when". Mixing them creates churn when either changes independently.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Decomposing unevenly — 4 levels for development, 1 level for deployment.</description>
        <reason>Uneven depth signals that some branches are under-estimated; both depth and estimate accuracy should be consistent across siblings.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A subagent expands a charter or one-line goal into a hierarchical WBS, applies the 100% rule check, generates a WBS Dictionary entry per leaf, and emits both an outline and a structured YAML representation. Use a 2-pass model: pass 1 ideates major deliverables; pass 2 decomposes each. Keep depth and 8/80-rule enforcement in scripts so the LLM cannot argue around them. Human-in-loop required after each level to confirm completeness — agents systematically miss PM/QA/deployment/training packages and "non-product" deliverables (training, comms, docs, runbooks).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use recommended subagents: faion-pm-agent (primary WBS draft and Dictionary entries). faion-business-analyst (cross-checks WBS against requirements). faion-software-architect (validates that technical decomposition matches the architecture). faion-sdd-executor-agent (converts work packages to SDD TASK_*.md files).</statement>
        <rationale>Multi-agent coordination ensures the WBS matches requirements, architecture, and execution plans.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Prompt pattern for WBS generation with constraints</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Input: charter.md (goals, scope, constraints), architecture.md (optional)
Output: wbs.yaml — hierarchy of {id, name, level, kind: deliverable|work_package,
parent}. Constraints: max_depth=4; leaf size 8-80h estimate; include
required overhead packages: project_management, qa, deployment,
documentation, training, transition.
After tree: produce dictionary entries for every leaf.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Validation prompt pattern</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Validate wbs.yaml:
1. Every parent has children that cover its scope (state any gap).
2. Every requirement_id in requirements.yaml maps to at least one wbs id.
3. Leaf estimate within 8-80h; flag outliers.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>mermaid-cli — render WBS tree to SVG/PNG (https://github.com/mermaid-js/mermaid-cli)</item>
        <item>markmap-cli — markdown outline to mind map (https://markmap.js.org)</item>
        <item>yq — query/transform wbs.yaml (https://github.com/mikefarah/yq)</item>
        <item>pandoc — outline to DOCX/PDF deliverable (https://pandoc.org)</item>
        <item>tree-cli — quick tree views from indented text (npm i -g tree-cli)</item>
        <item>csvkit — pivot WBS CSV by owner/level (https://csvkit.readthedocs.io)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services">
      <list>
        <item>Microsoft Project — Desktop/SaaS. Native WBS; agent can write .mpp via python-mpxj (Partial — XML import/export).</item>
        <item>Smartsheet — SaaS. REST API + hierarchy via parent_id. Ideal for WBS + EVM (Yes — REST API).</item>
        <item>MindMeister — SaaS. REST API. Mind-map style WBS for stakeholder review (Yes — REST API).</item>
        <item>Lucidchart — SaaS. REST API. Tree visualisation (Yes — REST API).</item>
        <item>Atlassian Confluence — SaaS. REST API. Host outline + Dictionary (Yes — REST API).</item>
        <item>Notion / Airtable — SaaS. REST API. Lightweight WBS DB (Yes — REST API).</item>
        <item>Jira (Advanced Roadmaps) — SaaS. REST API. Initiative → Epic → Story → Task mirrors WBS (Yes — REST API).</item>
        <item>MindManager / XMind — Desktop. Good for whiteboard-to-WBS (Limited, file-format only).</item>
        <item>WBS Schedule Pro — Desktop. Specialist; not for agents (No API).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Deliverable-oriented (nouns), not activity-oriented (verbs). "User Authentication", not "Build user authentication".</statement>
        <rationale>Deliverable names are stable under implementation changes.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Always include the boring packages: PM, QA, Deployment, Documentation, Training, Transition. They are 15-25% of effort.</statement>
        <rationale>Overhead packages are systematically forgotten; hard-code them as required.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Each leaf produces one verifiable artefact with explicit acceptance criteria — write it before estimating.</statement>
        <rationale>Estimation is easier when the deliverable is defined; acceptance criteria prevent disputes at sign-off.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Stop decomposing when 8/80 rule is satisfied; deeper is not better.</statement>
        <rationale>More levels increase maintenance cost without improving accuracy.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Pair WBS with WBS Dictionary in the same source file (id keyed); never separate.</statement>
        <rationale>WBS without Dictionary is just a list of labels; together they are actionable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Renumber rules: append-only IDs in long-running projects so links from CRs/risks/tasks remain stable.</statement>
        <rationale>ID reuse breaks traceability; append-only prevents this.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Convert leaves into SDD TASK_*.md 1:1 — the WBS is the source of truth, tasks are derived.</statement>
        <rationale>Single source of truth prevents drift between planning and execution.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs default to activity verbs; explicitly instruct "use noun phrases for deliverables".</description>
        <reason>Without explicit instruction, agents generate activity-based WBS that breaks on implementation changes.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents skip overhead packages (PM, QA, deploy, train) — hard-code them in the prompt as required.</description>
        <reason>Agents default to product deliverables; overhead must be explicitly mandated.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Decomposition often has uneven depth: backend gets 4 levels, "Marketing" stays at level 2. Force the agent to balance.</description>
        <reason>Uneven depth hides estimate errors in under-decomposed branches.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Dictionary entries get hallucinated owners and dates; force them to come from a stakeholder register and schedule input.</description>
        <reason>Made-up owners and dates destroy traceability and accountability.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents inflate estimates symmetrically (everything is 40h); inject a few known-good estimates as anchors.</description>
        <reason>Anchoring prevents uniform inflation and calibrates agent estimates to real data.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Do not let agents "consolidate" leaves to fit a target count — that breaks 8/80; reject and re-prompt.</description>
        <reason>Consolidation violates 8/80 rule; agents use it to artificially meet targets.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>When converting WBS to tasks, beware ID drift: keep wbs_id field in every generated task for round-tripping.</description>
        <reason>Lost traceability between WBS and tasks makes re-planning impossible.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/wbs-outline.md" purpose="Hierarchical WBS outline skeleton with numbered levels"/>
      <template path="templates/wbs-dictionary-entry.md" purpose="Single work-package dictionary card with all required fields"/>
      <template path="templates/wbs-validate.py" purpose="Validator: 100% rule + 8-80h leaf check against wbs.yaml"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards/pmbok"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/learning/library/pmi-practice-standard-work-breakdown-structures-3rd-edition-6924"/>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Work_breakdown_structure"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
