<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-task-structure" title="Task Structure and Token Budget">
  <summary>INVEST criteria, token budget tiers, task definition fields, and acceptance criteria rules for implementation plan tasks.</summary>

  <section title="INVEST Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every task must pass INVEST: Independent (can start after its declared deps complete), Negotiable (implementation flexible), Valuable (traces to FR-X), Estimable (token estimate declared), Small (under 100k tokens), Testable (acceptance criteria are verifiable).</statement>
      <rationale>Tasks that fail INVEST produce incomplete agent executions. The most common failures are: not Independent (hidden deps cause ordering conflicts), not Small (context exhaustion mid-task), not Testable (no way to validate completion).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Task with acceptance criteria that say "works correctly" or "functions as expected".</description>
      <reason>Vague AC cannot be verified by a test or a quality gate check. Every AC must specify a concrete observable outcome: a status code, a file that exists, a database row, a rendered element.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Token Budget Tiers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign each task to a tier: Simple (under 30k, single file, clear pattern), Normal (30-60k, multiple files, some exploration), Complex (60-100k, many files, novel solution). Tasks over 100k must be split before execution begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents degrade non-uniformly near context limits. The 100k rule provides a safe margin for most model families. Declaring a tier forces estimation before execution.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[### TASK-003: Create user authentication middleware

- **Complexity:** Normal
- **Tokens:** ~45k
- **AD-X:** AD-002
- **FR-X:** FR-005, FR-006
- **Depends on:** TASK-001 (user model), TASK-002 (JWT utility)
- **Blocks:** TASK-005 (protected routes)

**Files:**
- CREATE `src/middleware/auth.py`
- MODIFY `src/app.py` — register middleware

**Acceptance Criteria:**
1. Given valid JWT, when request arrives, then `request.user` is populated.
2. Given expired JWT, when request arrives, then 401 response is returned.
3. Given missing Authorization header, then 401 is returned.]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Required Task Fields">
    <list>
      <item>Task ID (TASK-NNN format)</item>
      <item>Title: action verb + target (e.g., "Create auth middleware")</item>
      <item>Complexity tier and token estimate</item>
      <item>AD-X and FR-X trace references (min 1 each)</item>
      <item>Depends on (explicit list or "None")</item>
      <item>Blocks (what tasks need this to complete)</item>
      <item>Files with action (CREATE / MODIFY / DELETE) and purpose</item>
      <item>Acceptance criteria (min 2, verifiable)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
