<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-rules" title="VUI Inclusivity Rules: Accent, Language, and User Diversity">
  <summary>Rules for inclusive voice interface design: WER fairness thresholds, prompt reading-level caps, timeout defaults, and mandatory visual transcript requirements for diverse user populations.</summary>

  <section title="ASR Fairness">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure word error rate (WER) by demographic slice (accent, age group) before launch; flag any subgroup with WER more than 1.5x the overall average for remediation.</statement>
      <rationale>Major ASR engines show 1.5-2x higher error rates for non-white-male speakers. Without per-group measurement, systemic bias is invisible until users complain — at which point reputational damage is already done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Test with real user recordings from each target demographic; do not rely solely on synthesized or cloned voice data for fairness evaluation.</statement>
      <rationale>Voice clones flatten prosody and underestimate failure rates for real-world accented speech. Synthetic data is a supplement, not a substitute for real user testing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/vui_fairness.py">WER-by-demographic evaluator: groups utterances by accent and age, reports disparity</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Prompt Language">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep all voice prompts at or below Flesch-Kincaid grade 8; reject prompts with idioms, unexplained jargon, or contractions in critical instructions.</statement>
      <rationale>Non-native speakers process idioms and contractions with additional cognitive load, increasing misinterpretation and intent-routing errors. Grade 8 language is accessible to the widest literate population without being condescending.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>"Say your account number, then say done." — short, no idioms, imperative voice.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"Go ahead and rattle off your account number whenever you're ready." — idiom "rattle off", informal register, ambiguous completion signal.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Default ASR silence timeout to 3-5 seconds after end-of-speech for all users; reduce only after confirming a fast-talker user profile.</statement>
      <rationale>Users who pause to think, have word-finding difficulty, or speak with non-native prosody need extra timeout. Premature cutoffs cause repeated failure and abandonment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Visual Alternatives">
    <rule>
      <statement>Display a live transcript on every device that has a screen; do not gate this behind an "accessibility" opt-in — it is a universal default.</statement>
      <rationale>Deaf users, users in noisy environments, and users who mishear TTS all benefit from a persistent transcript. Treating it as an accessibility option reduces its visibility and adoption.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Confirm before acting on low-confidence ASR recognition; never silently route a misrecognized intent to a destructive action.</statement>
      <rationale>ASR confidence scores are not equally calibrated across demographic groups — high-confidence misrecognitions occur more often for accented speech. Explicit confirmation prevents silent mis-routing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
