<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="vui-accessibility-inclusivity Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for vui-accessibility-inclusivity as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs assuming English idioms and contractions are universally understood.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Non-native speakers process idioms with additional cognitive load, increasing misinterpretation. Agents must be prompted to lint and rewrite for ESL users with explicit reading-level constraints.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Relying solely on synthesized accent test data for WER evaluation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Voice clones flatten real prosody. Synthetic data underestimates failure rates for real-world accented speech. Complement with Common Voice recordings or commissioned real-user samples.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating high ASR confidence scores as reliable for all demographic groups.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Confidence scores are not equally calibrated across groups. High-confidence misrecognitions happen more often for accented speech, creating a false sense of reliability for exactly the population most at risk.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Designing accent calibration UX that prompts users to "speak more clearly."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Such prompts are othering and damage user trust. Accommodation must be invisible: backend model selection, extended timeout, and fallback paths — not instructions directed at the user.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
