<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="JavaScript/TypeScript Stack Practices Core Rules" version="2.0.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the practices-js-ts-stack methodology. Each pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="strict-tsconfig" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>tsconfig MUST set strict=true, noUncheckedIndexedAccess=true, noImplicitOverride=true, exactOptionalPropertyTypes=true.</statement>
      <rationale source="TypeScript handbook">Default strictness still allows arr[0] to be typed as T (not T | undefined); noUncheckedIndexedAccess closes that hole. exactOptionalPropertyTypes catches accidental undefined assignments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="esm-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>package.json MUST set "type": "module" and use an "exports" map. CommonJS require() in source is forbidden; use dynamic import() if interop is required.</statement>
      <rationale source="Node.js ESM docs">ESM is the Node + browser standard; mixed CJS/ESM trees produce dual-package hazard. Pinning type=module + exports map prevents the dual-package state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="flat-eslint-config" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ESLint MUST use the flat-config format (eslint.config.js). The legacy .eslintrc cascade is forbidden in new projects.</statement>
      <rationale source="ESLint 9 release notes">Flat config is the supported format from ESLint 9; the legacy cascade is being removed and double-configures projects that mix them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ci-typecheck-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CI MUST run a tsc --noEmit step distinct from build. Skipping typecheck because the build emits types is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — type-error postmortem">Bundlers (esbuild, tsup, swc) skip typecheck by default for speed. Without a dedicated --noEmit step, type errors land in main unnoticed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="prettier-no-overlap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prettier handles formatting; ESLint MUST NOT include stylistic rules that overlap with Prettier (use eslint-config-prettier). Two formatters fighting each other are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Prettier + ESLint integration docs">Overlapping rules produce ping-pong autofixes and break CI gates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-any-no-unused" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>@typescript-eslint/no-explicit-any and no-unused-vars MUST be errors (not warnings). Local exceptions require an // eslint-disable-next-line comment with a reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="typescript-eslint recommended-strict">Warnings get ignored; errors block CI. Requiring a reason comment makes exceptions reviewable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
