<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-connectivity" title="AWS VPC Connectivity Patterns">
  <summary>VPC Peering vs Transit Gateway decision, VPC Lattice, IPAM, and connectivity checklist.</summary>

  <section title="VPC Peering vs Transit Gateway">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use VPC Peering for 2-3 VPCs in the same region; use Transit Gateway for 4+ VPCs, cross-region connectivity, or hybrid on-premises connectivity via Direct Connect or VPN.</statement>
      <rationale>VPC Peering is simpler and has no per-hour attachment cost — ideal for small deployments. Transit Gateway uses a hub-and-spoke model that scales to thousands of attachments without N×(N-1)/2 peering connections.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure Transit Gateway route tables segmented by environment (prod/non-prod isolation); disable DefaultRouteTableAssociation and DefaultRouteTablePropagation; use blackhole routes for deprecated networks.</statement>
      <rationale>Default route tables associate all attachments together, creating unintended connectivity between production and development VPCs. Explicit route table assignment enforces environment isolation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <note>Decision quick reference: 2-3 VPCs same region → VPC Peering, 4+ VPCs or cross-region → Transit Gateway, hybrid on-prem → Transit Gateway + Direct Connect/VPN, service-to-service mesh → VPC Lattice.</note>
  </section>

  <section title="VPC Lattice">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use VPC Lattice for application-layer service-to-service connectivity across VPCs and accounts; prefer over VPC Peering when services need built-in auth, routing, and observability.</statement>
      <rationale>VPC Lattice provides per-service access controls, request-level observability, and HTTP/gRPC routing without managing security groups across peered VPCs. It replaces complex PrivateLink setups for internal service meshes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Connectivity Checklist">
    <rule>
      <statement>For VPC Peering: enable DNS resolution across peers, reference peer VPC security groups by ID, configure specific routes (not full CIDR), verify no transitive routing assumptions.</statement>
      <rationale>VPC Peering is not transitive — VPC A peered to VPC B and B peered to VPC C does not create A-to-C connectivity. Teams frequently discover this misconfiguration in production when services cannot communicate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For all multi-VPC deployments: use IPAM for central IP planning and overlap detection; document all CIDR allocations; reserve expansion ranges in each VPC.</statement>
      <rationale>CIDR overlaps block all peering and TGW attachment options. IPAM provides real-time overlap detection and prevents allocation conflicts in multi-account Organizations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Assuming VPC Peering is transitive for multi-hop connectivity.</description>
      <reason>VPC Peering is point-to-point only. Traffic cannot pass through a peered VPC to reach a third VPC. Transit Gateway or VPC Lattice is required for hub-and-spoke topologies.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
