<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-design-process" title="Survey Design Process">
  <summary>Six-step process for creating surveys that yield valid, actionable quantitative data.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Conduct at least 10 qualitative interviews before creating a survey.</statement>
    <rationale>Surveys quantify known patterns; they cannot discover unknown problems. Without prior interviews, you cannot write valid questions — you do not yet know what to ask.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Step 1 — Define Research Objective">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define one specific research question, the decision it informs, the target audience, and a minimum sample size before writing a single survey question.</statement>
      <rationale>Surveys without a defined objective drift toward vague data that cannot drive any decision. A crisp objective statement also prevents scope creep during question writing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/survey-design-doc.md">Survey design document template with objective section</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2 — Choose Question Types">
    <p>Select the question type that best fits each research goal:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Multiple choice: discrete, mutually exclusive options ("How often do you...?")</item>
      <item>Rating scale (5-point general, 7-point nuanced, 10-point NPS, binary yes/no)</item>
      <item>Ranking: priority order across 3-7 items</item>
      <item>Open-ended: one or two per survey maximum, placed at the end</item>
      <item>Matrix: multiple items against the same scale (satisfaction across features)</item>
      <item>NPS (0-10): loyalty and recommendation intent only</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3 — Write Questions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each question must be specific, single-concept, neutrally worded, and answerable from direct experience — not hypothetical intent.</statement>
      <rationale>Double-barreled items ("How easy and useful is X?") split respondent attention and make data uninterpretable. Hypothetical questions ("Would you pay X?") over-predict actual behavior by 2-5x.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Bad: "How often will you use this feature?"
Why: hypothetical future intent, not past behavior
Bad: "How satisfied and engaged are you?"
Why: double-barreled — two separate questions fused
Bad: "Don't you think X is better than Y?"
Why: leading — presupposes a preferred answer]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Good: "How often have you used similar tools in the last 30 days?"
Good: "How satisfied are you with [product]?" + separate "How engaged do you feel?"
Good: "Which do you prefer, X or Y?"]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/question-bank.md">Per-research-type question banks (pricing, satisfaction, feature prioritization)</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4 — Structure the Survey">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep total completion time under 7 minutes; longer surveys drop below 50% completion. Place screener first, demographics last, open-ended questions at the end.</statement>
      <rationale>Completion rates drop sharply past 7 minutes. Screener questions at the front disqualify off-target respondents before they waste time on core questions. Demographics last reduces abandonment from privacy-sensitive openers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Screener (1-2 questions): qualify respondents, route off-target out</item>
      <item>Attention check at Q5: "Select 'Somewhat agree' to confirm you are reading"</item>
      <item>Easy warm-up (2-3 questions): build momentum</item>
      <item>Core questions (5-10): main research objective</item>
      <item>Demographics (3-5): segmentation variables</item>
      <item>Open-ended (1-2): additional context, never more</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5 — Test and Distribute">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pilot with 5-10 people from the actual audience and measure median completion time. If median exceeds 7 minutes, cut questions until it does not.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-estimated completion time is always optimistic. Piloting reveals confusing items, technical issues, and timing reality before the main field period.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Distribution channel trade-offs: email list (qualified but biased to existing users), social media (broad reach but self-selection), paid panels (fast and targeted but expensive and variable quality), in-product (high completion but only active users), communities (engaged and specific but may be small).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>For paid panels, do not let an agent auto-launch fielding — cost spikes and ethics review require a human approval gate.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated panel launches can incur significant unexpected costs and may violate panel provider terms if attention-check criteria are not pre-configured.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6 — Analyze Results">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deduplicate on (IP, device fingerprint, completion time &lt; 30% of median) before any analysis. Paid panels return 5-30% bot or satisficer responses.</statement>
      <rationale>Drawing conclusions from unfiltered panel data overstates real market preferences and invalidates statistical significance claims.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Quantitative: response distributions, cross-tabulations by segment, statistical significance</item>
      <item>Qualitative (open-ended): theme coding with counts, verbatim quotes per theme required</item>
      <item>Report open-ended analysis with the actual corpus size explicitly stated</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
