<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules-and-antipatterns" title="Survey Design Rules and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete question-writing rules, common mistake table, and AI-agent gotchas for survey design.</summary>

  <section title="Question-Writing Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Randomize answer-option order on every multiple-choice and matrix item (except scales, where order is meaningful).</statement>
      <rationale>First-option bias inflates selection of the top-listed answer by 5-15% in self-administered surveys.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For pricing, never ask "would you pay X." Use Van Westendorp (4 price-sensitivity questions) plus a real price anchor or a pre-order page.</statement>
      <rationale>Stated willingness-to-pay is 2-5x higher than actual purchase behavior. Behavioral anchors (price anchoring, actual payment) produce calibrated estimates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor sample size to the decision, not vanity. For a directional preference split at 95% CI with ±10pp precision, n=100 per segment is sufficient.</statement>
      <rationale>Collecting 1,000 responses when 100 answer the question wastes fielding budget and adds no precision to the key decision metric.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Segment in the analysis plan before fielding. Do not slice by unplanned variables post-hoc without flagging the analysis as exploratory.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc segmentation inflates false-positive rates by increasing the number of comparisons tested on the same data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Version-control the survey JSON alongside the analysis notebook. Surveys are code.</statement>
      <rationale>Undocumented survey changes between waves make longitudinal comparisons invalid and findings unreproducible.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Leading questions that presuppose an answer ("Don't you think X is better?")</description>
      <reason>Biases responses toward the implied preferred answer; data cannot be used for unbiased inference.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Surveys with no screener questions at the front</description>
      <reason>Off-target respondents contaminate the sample; results apply to an undefined population.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Only closed questions with no open-ended field</description>
      <reason>Misses unknown motivations and verbatim language that reveals how respondents actually think about the problem.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Quantitative claims from samples below 100</description>
      <reason>Confidence intervals are too wide for actionable decision-making; switch to qualitative interviews instead.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No pilot test before full distribution</description>
      <reason>Confusing questions, broken logic, and unexpected completion times only surface in the pilot; fixing post-field is impossible.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>Run bias-linter.py on every agent-drafted question set before sending to human review. Agents drift toward double-barrel items ("How easy and intuitive is...") and leading framings that they then rationalize away.</statement>
      <rationale>Regex-based deterministic checks catch patterns the LLM rationalizes as acceptable when reviewing its own output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/bias-linter.py">Python pre-filter detecting leading, hypothetical, absolutist, and double-barrel questions</reference>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents use Likert-5 for everything without justifying scale choice per question</description>
      <reason>Scale choice affects response distribution; 5-point scales compress nuance for attitude items where 7-point is standard.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent-generated demographics duplicate or omit segments tracked in user-personas.md</description>
      <reason>Mismatched demographic options prevent cross-study comparison; always pass the personas doc as context and require options to be a subset.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent summarizes open-ended fields without disclosing how many responses were actually read</description>
      <reason>Silent corpus truncation produces hallucinated synthesis that looks like full-corpus analysis.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
