<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="portfolio-strategy Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for portfolio-strategy. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default allocation: 70% H1 (Core, 0-12 months, known market, low risk), 20% H2 (Adjacent, 12-24 months, new segments, medium risk), 10% H3 (Transformational, 24-36 months, breakthrough bets, high risk).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The 70/20/10 split balances revenue protection with innovation investment. Deviating without an explicit economic-condition trigger creates undefended drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Adjust ratios by economic condition: growth economy → 60/25/15 (more bets); stable economy → 70/20/10 (standard); recession → 80/15/5 (protect core).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Economic weakness in 2026 (Morgan Stanley forecast) warrants a defensive posture. The adjustment must be explicit and signed by the portfolio-PM, not implicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-PMF products allocate 100% to achieving PMF and do not enter the portfolio model until PMF is demonstrated. Never apply 70/20/10 to a product still searching for product-market fit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Portfolio horizon math assumes a product with known metrics and a real customer base. Pre-PMF products have a single objective that H1/H2/H3 labels actively obscure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign every PM a written role tag each quarter: product-PM (owns one product's roadmap), portfolio-PM (owns cross-product investment allocation), or mixed (with an explicit percentage of portfolio time). Resolve ambiguity in a written allocation memo before backlogs collide.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Role ambiguity is the root cause of most allocation fights. When the same person plays both hats, a written memo makes the conflict of interest visible to others who can catch drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Promote from product-PM to portfolio-PM only when the PM already owns two or more shipped products with demonstrable OKR independence. Product count alone is not sufficient — time allocation must be verified.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs and orgs alike conflate "PM owns more products" with "PM is more strategic". The decision frame shift from feature-level to cross-product investment is qualitative and must be verified.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Fund the H3 portion from a portfolio budget owned by the portfolio-PM, not from individual product budgets. No single product-PM can raid or reallocate H3 funds.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a ring-fenced H3 budget, H3 becomes overflow for late H1 features during every crunch. The portfolio-PM is the only role without a local-optimization incentive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score PMs on portfolio outcomes (cross-product H3 progress) when they own two or more products, not just per-product outcomes. Otherwise, they will silently let H3 die.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">PM career incentives skew toward H1/H2 because launches are rewarded over long bets. Metric alignment is the only scalable fix; admonishment is not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pass 1 (Product-PM pass): for each product, a sonnet agent reads the product backlog, OKRs, and recent retros and emits {product, h1_pct, h2_pct, h3_pct, key_evidence}. Weights are not yet cross-product.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Starting per-product isolates each PM's plan before aggregation. Cross-product trade-offs introduced too early cause defensiveness that blocks honest disclosure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pass 2 (Portfolio-PM pass): an opus agent aggregates across products, weighs engineering cost per product, and detects role-level anti-patterns. Output: JSON with per-product recommended horizon mix, portfolio totals, PM role findings, and a reallocation memo of at most 6 bullets naming cuts and bets.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opus for the aggregation pass because cross-cutting reasoning across multiple products with dependencies requires sustained multi-step reasoning that cheaper models abbreviate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pass 3 (Reconciliation): output a structured memo that names which product gets cut, which gets accelerated, and which PM owns the H3 budget for the next quarter. The memo goes to a human portfolio-PM for sign-off; never auto-applied.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agent-only portfolio decisions are an anti-pattern. The matrix is decision support; the portfolio-PM holds the final allocation authority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All three passes must produce JSON output; the reconciliation memo is the only prose artifact, and it must have a top-level cuts: section before the prose body.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Reconciliation memos bury the cut in prose. A required cuts: field at the top forces the agent to make trade-offs legible before the narrative justification.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-compute the cross-product dependency graph as cross_product_deps.csv (columns: item_id, depends_on_product, blocking_severity) and pass it to the portfolio-PM agent. Never let the agent infer dependencies from product descriptions alone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs will not detect cross-product dependencies unless supplied as edges in the input. Without a dependency graph, the agent invents synergies that do not exist and misses real blockers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pass owner_count (number of humans running the portfolio) alongside product data. If the stated allocation is infeasible for the headcount, the agent must flag "headcount insufficient" rather than pretend the ratio is achievable.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Solo-founder portfolios mislead the model — it will recommend a clean 70/20/10 split for one human running 6 products as if that is executable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
