<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Portfolio Strategy (70/20/10) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Three-horizon investment allocation (70% Core H1, 20% Adjacent H2, 10% Transformational H3) for a PM owning multiple shipped products; rebalances quarterly with explicit kill triggers.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="three-horizon-allocation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Portfolio investment MUST be partitioned by horizon: 70% H1 (Core, 0-12mo), 20% H2 (Adjacent, 12-24mo), 10% H3 (Transformational, 24-36mo). Drift beyond ±5pp triggers a rebalance.</statement>
      <rationale source="McKinsey Three Horizons; Google 70/20/10">Without explicit horizons, all capacity bleeds into H1 firefighting; H3 starves.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="horizon-per-product-tagged" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each product MUST be tagged H1/H2/H3 with rationale. Untagged products default to H1 (forcing the conversation).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — portfolio audits">Untagged products distort the allocation calc; default-H1 forces the operator to confirm or re-classify.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kill-trigger-per-horizon" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each horizon has its own kill trigger: H1 = sustained activation/retention slip, H2 = 18-month no-PMF, H3 = 36-month no-market-signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Horizon Three failure-mode analysis">Without horizon-appropriate triggers, the team kills H3 too fast (no signal yet) or keeps H1 too long (sunk cost).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rebalance-quarterly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The portfolio mix MUST be reviewed quarterly with a written rebalance memo. Skipping the review allows silent drift.</statement>
      <rationale source="Portfolio review cadence research">Annual-only reviews lock in stale allocations; quarterly reviews catch drift while it is cheap to fix.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="portfolio-vs-product-roles" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Portfolio strategy decisions (allocation, kill, expand) are owned at portfolio-PM level; per-product roadmap stays with product PMs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Marty Cagan — Empowered teams">Role confusion produces parallel decision-making; clear role line keeps both levels effective.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — single-product team; pre-PMF; agency/services; recent memo without trigger events), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
