<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-horizon-model" title="Three-Horizon Portfolio Model">
  <summary>Allocates product investment across Core (H1), Adjacent (H2), and Transformational (H3) horizons with ratios adjusted by economic condition and PM role.</summary>

  <section title="Standard Allocation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default allocation: 70% H1 (Core, 0-12 months, known market, low risk), 20% H2 (Adjacent, 12-24 months, new segments, medium risk), 10% H3 (Transformational, 24-36 months, breakthrough bets, high risk).</statement>
      <rationale>The 70/20/10 split balances revenue protection with innovation investment. Deviating without an explicit economic-condition trigger creates undefended drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Adjust ratios by economic condition: growth economy → 60/25/15 (more bets); stable economy → 70/20/10 (standard); recession → 80/15/5 (protect core).</statement>
      <rationale>Economic weakness in 2026 (Morgan Stanley forecast) warrants a defensive posture. The adjustment must be explicit and signed by the portfolio-PM, not implicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-PMF products allocate 100% to achieving PMF and do not enter the portfolio model until PMF is demonstrated. Never apply 70/20/10 to a product still searching for product-market fit.</statement>
      <rationale>Portfolio horizon math assumes a product with known metrics and a real customer base. Pre-PMF products have a single objective that H1/H2/H3 labels actively obscure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="PM Role Taxonomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign every PM a written role tag each quarter: product-PM (owns one product's roadmap), portfolio-PM (owns cross-product investment allocation), or mixed (with an explicit percentage of portfolio time). Resolve ambiguity in a written allocation memo before backlogs collide.</statement>
      <rationale>Role ambiguity is the root cause of most allocation fights. When the same person plays both hats, a written memo makes the conflict of interest visible to others who can catch drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Promote from product-PM to portfolio-PM only when the PM already owns two or more shipped products with demonstrable OKR independence. Product count alone is not sufficient — time allocation must be verified.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs and orgs alike conflate "PM owns more products" with "PM is more strategic". The decision frame shift from feature-level to cross-product investment is qualitative and must be verified.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="H3 Budget Governance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Fund the H3 portion from a portfolio budget owned by the portfolio-PM, not from individual product budgets. No single product-PM can raid or reallocate H3 funds.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a ring-fenced H3 budget, H3 becomes overflow for late H1 features during every crunch. The portfolio-PM is the only role without a local-optimization incentive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Score PMs on portfolio outcomes (cross-product H3 progress) when they own two or more products, not just per-product outcomes. Otherwise, they will silently let H3 die.</statement>
      <rationale>PM career incentives skew toward H1/H2 because launches are rewarded over long bets. Metric alignment is the only scalable fix; admonishment is not.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
