<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="portfolio-strategy Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for portfolio-strategy as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>The same person plays product-PM and portfolio-PM without a written allocation memo.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The framework cannot resolve a conflict of interest if the same human owns both hats. A written memo makes trade-offs visible to others who can catch drift.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Each product-PM optimizes their P&amp;L for more H1, and the aggregate portfolio drifts to 95% H1 with no transformational bets.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Local incentives aggregate to a portfolio failure. Counter: portfolio-PM owns the H3 budget separately from product budgets and cannot be lobbied out of it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>One human running 6+ products attempts a real 70/20/10 split but exploration time collapses to zero under operational load.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Document the collapse honestly instead of pretending the ratio is real. A false ratio in the portfolio memo misleads future agents and reviews.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Portfolio math does not score work that benefits multiple products simultaneously, so shared platform work is under-funded.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Product PMs resist sharing their roadmap slot to fund shared infra. The portfolio-PM must account for cross-product leverage explicitly, not assume product PMs will volunteer it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-product trade-offs negotiated 1:1 between product PMs rather than in a single portfolio memo signed by the portfolio-PM.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Bilateral deals leak budget and never balance. Each PM "wins" locally; the portfolio loses in aggregate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent conflates "PM owns more products" with "PM is more strategic" and auto-tags multi-product PMs as portfolio-PMs regardless of time allocation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The decision frame shift from feature-level to cross-product investment is qualitative. Force the classifier to use a time_allocation field, not a product count.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent recommends splitting the difference when two PMs disagree, hiding the actual trade-off.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Compromise memos avoid the hard call. Constrain the rebalancer to pick a side with a rationale; do not average positions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
