<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="spatial-ux-fundamentals Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the spatial-ux-fundamentals methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="three-field-zones" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every spatial element MUST be placed in exactly one of three field zones: near (0.3-1.0 m), mid (1.0-3.0 m), far (3.0 m+). Mixed-zone placement is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple visionOS HIG; Meta Quest comfort docs">Zones derive from human-factors research on reach + vergence + sustained viewing distance for HMDs.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="no-interactive-in-far-field" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interactive controls MUST NOT be placed in the far field (&gt;3.0 m). Far field is reserved for ambient context, environmental information, and navigation aids.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple visionOS HIG">Hand-ray jitter and gaze precision drop sharply beyond 3 m; small controls become inaccessible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="default-content-distance" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default content distance for sustained viewing (reading, video, dashboard) MUST be 1.5-2.0 m. Element below 0.4 m or above 3.0 m for sustained viewing requires explicit comfort justification.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta Quest comfort docs">1.5-2.0 m places content in comfortable vergence range for most users; outliers cause eye fatigue within minutes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="anchor-primary-hand-or-decay" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Primary controls MUST be anchored as head-locked-with-decay or hand-attached. Pure world-locked primary controls are forbidden — users drift physically and lose them.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple visionOS HIG; Meta Quest UI guidelines">World-locked primary controls force users to physically walk back to them after movement.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="chin-region-forbidden" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Critical UI MUST NOT be placed in the lower 30° of the vertical FoV (chin region). Repeated downward gaze &gt;30° from horizontal causes neck fatigue within minutes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple visionOS HIG ergonomics">Looking down &gt;30° from horizontal requires neck flexion that fatigues quickly; bottom-edge mobile patterns do not port.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="recenter-affordance-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every app MUST provide a recenter affordance (button + voice command) accessible at all times. Forced-removal of headset is not an acceptable recenter path.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple visionOS HIG">Users drift, rooms shift; without recenter, primary content becomes inaccessible without removing the headset.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
