<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-field-zones" title="Spatial UX Field Zones and Anchoring">
  <summary>Near/mid/far field zone definitions, anchoring type rules, occlusion rules, and sight-line constraints for head-mounted spatial interfaces.</summary>

  <section title="Field Zone Definitions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Organize all spatial content in three physical zones: near field (0.3–1.0 m) for primary interactions and controls, mid field (1.0–3.0 m) for content consumption and work surfaces, far field (3.0 m+) for ambient context and navigation aids only.</statement>
      <rationale>Zones derive from human-factors research on comfortable reach, vergence-accommodation, and sustained viewing distance for head-mounted displays. Placing interactive controls in the far field forces users to walk or stretch, causing abandonment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Never place interactive controls in the far field. Ambient and contextual content only.</statement>
      <rationale>Users cannot reliably reach or gaze-target elements beyond 3 m on current HMD hardware. Eye-tracking precision drops, hand-ray jitter increases, and small controls become inaccessible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Use 1.5–2.0 m as the default content distance for any surface requiring sustained viewing (reading, video, dashboard). Test both seated and standing — comfortable reach shifts approximately 15 degrees.</statement>
      <rationale>Both Quest 3 (approx. 110 degree FoV) and Vision Pro (approx. 100 degree FoV) have optical sweet spots near the display center. 1.5–2.0 m places content in comfortable vergence range for most users and reduces eye fatigue during extended sessions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anchoring Types">
    <p>Three anchoring modes, each appropriate for different content types:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Head-locked: content moves with the user's head. Reserve for critical HUD elements (battery warning, notifications). Overuse causes simulator sickness.</item>
      <item>Head-locked with decay: content follows the head with a lag, settling into world space after movement stops. Best for primary controls — feels responsive without nausea.</item>
      <item>World-locked: content is fixed in physical space. Best for persistent work surfaces (documents, dashboards). Requires a recenter affordance when users drift from the content.</item>
      <item>Hand-attached: content follows the hand. Best for tools and context menus. Switch to world-locked when the user stops moving to allow two-handed interaction.</item>
    </list>

    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor primary controls as head-locked-with-decay or hand-attached. Avoid pure world-locked for primary controls — they force users to walk back to their content after physical movement.</statement>
      <rationale>Users drift, rooms are reconfigured, and real-world obstacles appear. Primary controls that require physical walking to access are effectively inaccessible in practical use.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Occlusion and Sight-Line Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Avoid placing critical UI in the lower 30 degrees of the vertical FoV (chin region). This zone causes neck fatigue after repeated downward gaze.</statement>
      <rationale>Looking down more than 30 degrees from horizontal requires neck flexion that fatigues within minutes. Bottom-edge controls on a phone transfer directly to the chin region on an HMD — never port 2D layouts unchanged.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a "recenter" affordance (button or voice command) accessible at all times. Snapping to the home pose recovers content placement when users have drifted.</statement>
      <rationale>Without recenter, users who physically turn or move have no way to re-orient to their content without removing and replacing the headset. This is the most common usability complaint in field testing.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Text placed in the far field (3 m+) must use at minimum 60 pt font for legibility. Text at 2 m should use at minimum 36 pt.</statement>
      <rationale>Angular resolution on current HMDs ranges from 25–35 PPD. Small text that appears readable on a monitor becomes illegible at distance on headset hardware.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
