<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-antipatterns-and-workflow" title="Spatial UX Antipatterns and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>Common spatial UX antipatterns, agentic workflow for spatial spec generation, lint script reference, and agent gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Porting 2D screen layouts directly to spatial without remapping to field zones.</description>
      <reason>2D patterns assume a fixed viewport. Spatial adds depth, reach, and gaze constraints that invalidate bottom-nav, top-bar, and modal-overlay patterns. Every element must be assigned a field zone explicitly.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Placing primary CTAs or form controls in the far field (3 m+) to "give the layout breathing room".</description>
      <reason>Far field is for ambient context only. Interactive controls at 3 m+ are unreachable by hand-ray for many users (arm length, reach angle) and untargetable by gaze at typical HMD resolutions.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Generating 3D assets from LLM text-to-3D for production use.</description>
      <reason>Text-to-3D quality, polygon count, UV mapping, material assignments, and licensing are all unsuitable for production spatial apps. Agents that generate geometry must not bypass the art-direction and budget-validation pipeline.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM-generated USD or glTF with incorrect axis convention (Y-up vs. Z-up) shipped without validation.</description>
      <reason>Axis convention mismatches produce upside-down or sideways models in engine. Validate every generated asset through gltf-validator or usdview before import.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Drive Claude to translate a 2D wireframe into a spatial spec: assign each panel or control to near/mid/far field with rationale, specify world-scale in centimeters, annotate anchoring type, and flag occlusion and reach risks. A second agent runs a heuristic checklist against the spec. Use Reality Composer Pro USDA text format or a JSON spatial spec (not screenshots) as the source-of-truth artifact.</p>

    <p>Key gotchas: Claude defaults to thinking in pixels and dp. Force unit normalization to meters in every prompt or output produces nonsense scales. LLMs recommend skeuomorphic 3D buttons — reference platform Human Interface Guidelines (Vision Pro vibrancy, Quest hover states) explicitly in the prompt. Any layout element beyond 2 m or closer than 0.4 m needs a designer with HMD-on review — agents cannot judge eye fatigue or vestibular discomfort.</p>

    <reference path="templates/spatial-spec-linter.py">Validate JSON spatial spec: flag elements outside correct distance bands or interactive controls in far field</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitation Scope">
    <p>Field guidance (0–1 m / 1–3 m / 3 m+) assumes seated or standing immersive use. It does not cover: pass-through desk work (different ergonomics), walking AR (dynamic reach envelope), or 360-degree video (passive viewing, no interaction design). Apply these fundamentals only where the user is stationary and actively interacting with spatial content.</p>

    <p>Anthropometric averages in field-zone guidelines mask variance: children, wheelchair users, and users with limited arm reach all break "comfortable arm reach" assumptions. Test with at least two anthropometric edge cases per usability cycle.</p>
  </section>
</text>
