<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="spatial-ux-fundamentals Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for spatial-ux-fundamentals as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Porting 2D screen layouts directly to spatial without remapping to field zones.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>2D patterns assume a fixed viewport. Spatial adds depth, reach, and gaze constraints that invalidate bottom-nav, top-bar, and modal-overlay patterns. Every element must be assigned a field zone explicitly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Placing primary CTAs or form controls in the far field (3 m+) to "give the layout breathing room".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Far field is for ambient context only. Interactive controls at 3 m+ are unreachable by hand-ray for many users (arm length, reach angle) and untargetable by gaze at typical HMD resolutions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Generating 3D assets from LLM text-to-3D for production use.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Text-to-3D quality, polygon count, UV mapping, material assignments, and licensing are all unsuitable for production spatial apps. Agents that generate geometry must not bypass the art-direction and budget-validation pipeline.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM-generated USD or glTF with incorrect axis convention (Y-up vs. Z-up) shipped without validation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Axis convention mismatches produce upside-down or sideways models in engine. Validate every generated asset through gltf-validator or usdview before import.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
