<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="terraform-modules-security Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for terraform-modules-security. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>MUST NOT hardcode secrets, passwords, API keys, or tokens in any .tf file, .tfvars file, or module default value. Secrets MUST be referenced from a secret manager (AWS Secrets Manager, Vault, GCP Secret Manager) or passed as sensitive variables sourced from environment variables or a CI secrets store.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Git history is permanent. A secret committed and then removed is still recoverable via git log. State files containing sensitive = true attributes must be stored in encrypted backends with access controls.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The .gitignore of every Terraform project MUST exclude *.tfstate, *.tfstate.*, and *.tfvars files that contain real secrets. terraform.tfvars is excluded by default but project-specific var files must be listed explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A state file committed to a public or semi-public repo exposes all resource attributes, including passwords generated by the aws_db_instance resource.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>IAM policies in modules MUST NOT use wildcard (*) in the Action field without explicit justification documented in a code comment. Where wildcards are unavoidable (e.g., s3:*Object*), scope them with a Resource ARN condition.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Wildcard actions grant more permissions than required, violate SOC 2 and ISO 27001 least-privilege controls, and are flagged by Checkov, tfsec, and AWS Security Hub.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>IAM policies MUST be attached to roles, not to IAM users. Modules MUST NOT create IAM user access keys.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">User access keys are long-lived credentials that cannot be rotated automatically. Role-based access uses short-lived STS tokens and supports MFA enforcement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Resource-level permissions MUST be used wherever the service supports them. MUST NOT use Resource: "*" when a specific ARN pattern is known at module authoring time.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Resource: "*" on an IAM action grants that action on every resource in the account, not just the ones the module manages.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Security group ingress rules MUST NOT use cidr_blocks = ["0.0.0.0/0"] without explicit justification. Public-facing load balancers are the only acceptable exception. All other services must restrict ingress to known CIDR ranges or security group references.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Open ingress exposes services to the full internet. Even non-authenticated services can be DoS targets. Least-privilege ingress limits the attack surface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Databases MUST be placed in private subnets. MUST NOT set publicly_accessible = true on RDS instances or assign public IPs to database hosts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A publicly accessible database with a weak password is accessible to the internet. Private subnet placement requires a bastion or VPN for access, adding a layer of defense.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every module MUST pass terraform fmt -check, terraform validate, and tflint on every commit. These checks MUST be enforced in CI before any plan or apply step runs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Format check catches style drift that makes diffs hard to review. Validate catches syntax and type errors. tflint catches provider-specific anti-patterns (deprecated arguments, missing required tags).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Modules with conditional logic (count, for_each, dynamic blocks, conditionals on outputs) MUST have at least one terraform test (.tftest.hcl) that validates the conditional branches.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Uncovered conditional branches mean a misconfiguration in that branch may not be caught until a production apply.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Security scans MUST be run with Checkov or tfsec on every pull request. A clean scan MUST be a required check before merge. MUST NOT suppress findings without a documented justification in a suppressions file.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Security findings accumulate quickly if not enforced at the PR gate. Suppression files make exceptions auditable and reviewable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CI pipelines for Terraform MUST run stages in this order: (1) format check, (2) validate, (3) lint (tflint), (4) security scan (Checkov/tfsec), (5) plan (on PR), (6) apply (on main merge, with manual approval for production). Plan MUST NOT run if any earlier stage fails.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Running plan before security scan wastes CI minutes and allows a malicious or buggy plan to run against a real environment before security issues are surfaced. Cheap static stages gate expensive ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
