<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-tool-profiles" title="PM Tool Quick-Reference Profiles">
  <summary>Comparative profiles of 10 major PM tools with strengths, weaknesses, and team-size fit.</summary>

  <section title="Quick Reference">
    <p>Tool fit is determined by team size, workflow complexity, ecosystem integration, and compliance posture — not feature counts. "Best for X" labels are directional; always validate against the team's actual MoSCoW requirements.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Jira: enterprise, compliance-heavy, 50+ users. Highly customizable; complex; large ecosystem.</item>
      <item>Linear: engineering-focused, 10-100 users. Fastest UX; keyboard-first; opinionated workflow; GitHub-native.</item>
      <item>ClickUp: all-in-one consolidation, 10-500 users. Most features; some performance issues; steep learning curve.</item>
      <item>Notion: docs + light PM, 5-100 users. Flexible; beautiful; not PM-primary; weak reporting.</item>
      <item>GitHub Projects (v2): developers already in GitHub, any size. Free for OSS; GraphQL; limited PM depth.</item>
      <item>GitLab Boards: DevOps-integrated teams, 10-1000 users. Full DevOps platform; Premium for WIP limits.</item>
      <item>Azure DevOps: Microsoft-stack enterprises, 50+ users. Compliance-grade; Entra integration; CMMI support.</item>
      <item>Trello: simple Kanban, 5-50 users. Easy onboarding; limited scaling; good for low-complexity workflows.</item>
      <item>Asana: marketing and ops teams, 10-500 users. Clean UX; goals and portfolios; less dev-focused.</item>
      <item>Monday.com: non-technical teams, 10-500 users. Visual; highly flexible; expensive at scale.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Jira">
    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>Choose Jira for organizations with 50+ users, complex approval workflows, compliance requirements (SOC2, FedRAMP), or need for extensive plugin ecosystem.</statement>
      <rationale>Jira's value is in customizability and ecosystem breadth. For simpler needs, the UI complexity and performance overhead outweigh the benefits.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using Jira for a team of fewer than 10 with straightforward Kanban needs.</description>
      <reason>Jira's configuration overhead (workflows, schemes, custom fields) creates administrative burden that kills small-team productivity.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Linear">
    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>Choose Linear for developer-focused teams of 10-100 that prioritize speed, keyboard-driven UX, and tight GitHub integration over flexibility.</statement>
      <rationale>Linear's opinionated design eliminates configuration decisions, which accelerates adoption and daily use for engineering teams.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Choosing Linear when stakeholders need heavy customization, large ecosystem apps, or mature reporting.</description>
      <reason>Linear's opinionated design is a liability when teams need workflow customization that Linear does not support out of the box.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent-Friendliness">
    <list>
      <item>Jira: REST v3 + GraphQL alpha; full CRUD; JQL for queries. Best for complex query-driven workflows.</item>
      <item>Linear: GraphQL-first; fast; excellent pagination. Best for engineering-metric automation.</item>
      <item>GitHub Projects v2: GraphQL; free; tightly coupled to repo events. Best for code-adjacent workflows.</item>
      <item>GitLab: REST + GraphQL; self-host option; webhook-driven. Best for DevOps-integrated automation.</item>
      <item>Azure DevOps: REST + OData Analytics; enterprise auth. Best for Microsoft-stack traceability pipelines.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
