<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-selection-process" title="PM Tool Selection Process">
  <summary>MoSCoW requirements gathering, hard-constraint pruning, weighted scoring, and ADR output format for defensible tool selection.</summary>

  <section title="Requirements Phase">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every Must-Have requirement must have a stakeholder quote or measured pain point as evidence; requirements without evidence are downgraded to Should-Have.</statement>
      <rationale>Evidence-anchored MoSCoW prevents post-selection disputes ("I said we needed X"). It also forces specificity that reveals when requirements conflict.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply hard constraints first (price ceiling, data residency, compliance certification, IDP/SCIM support) to reduce the universe to 3-5 candidates before evaluating features.</statement>
      <rationale>Compliance posture (SOC2, ISO 27001, HIPAA, FedRAMP, GDPR data residency) can flip the entire shortlist; evaluating features before checking compliance wastes effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="POC Evaluation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Time-box the POC to two weeks using actual project data, not sample data; longer evaluation causes decision fatigue without proportional insight.</statement>
      <rationale>Real data surfaces integration gaps, performance issues, and UX friction that demo data hides. Two weeks is sufficient for most team-size decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include "do nothing" as a baseline option in the ADR with quantified cost of staying on the current tool.</statement>
      <rationale>Without the baseline, the recommendation reads as "we must switch" rather than "switching is better than staying by X%."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>POC driven only by API scenarios without any UI testing.</description>
      <reason>API success does not predict UI adoption. One Playwright test per shortlisted vendor covering the most common UI flow catches issues that break real adoption.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring and ADR">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score with weights and run sensitivity analysis; if the winner changes under plus-or-minus 20% weight perturbations, the choice is fragile and requires deeper investigation.</statement>
      <rationale>A fragile winner means requirements are genuinely contested. Surface this before commitment rather than discovering it post-implementation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Quantify migration cost (data ETL, automations, integrations, training, parallel-run period) in the ADR — typically 30-50% of year-1 TCO.</statement>
      <rationale>Migration cost is the most underestimated factor in tool selection and the most common source of post-decision regret.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[# ADR: PM Tool Selection — [Date]

## Decision
Adopt Linear for the engineering org (Jira remains for compliance projects).

## Context
Team of 45 engineers; GitHub-first; previous Jira instance at 180 custom fields.

## Requirements (MoSCoW)
### Must
- GitHub PR linking (evidence: @eng-lead, transcript offset 142)
- Sub-$15/user/month (evidence: budget doc Q3)

## Scoring (1-5 scale, weighted)
| Criterion | Weight | Linear | Jira | ClickUp |
|-----------|--------|--------|------|---------|
| UX speed  | 0.30   | 5      | 2    | 3       |
| GitHub    | 0.25   | 5      | 4    | 3       |
| Reporting | 0.20   | 2      | 5    | 4       |
| Price     | 0.25   | 4      | 3    | 4       |
| **Total** |        | **4.1**| **3.4** | **3.5** |

## Sensitivity: ranking stable under ±20% weight perturbation.

## Migration cost estimate
Data: 12,000 issues. Automations: 34 rules. Training: 45 people.
Parallel run: 4 weeks. Total: ~$28k one-time.]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/requirements-doc.md">MoSCoW requirements document template with stakeholder interview questions</reference>
  <reference path="templates/poc-runner.py">POC scenario harness for driving scripted tests against REST-enabled PM tools</reference>
</text>
