<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="pm-tools-overview Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for pm-tools-overview as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using Jira for a team of fewer than 10 with straightforward Kanban needs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Jira's configuration overhead (workflows, schemes, custom fields) creates administrative burden that kills small-team productivity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Choosing Linear when stakeholders need heavy customization, large ecosystem apps, or mature reporting.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Linear's opinionated design is a liability when teams need workflow customization that Linear does not support out of the box.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>POC driven only by API scenarios without any UI testing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>API success does not predict UI adoption. One Playwright test per shortlisted vendor covering the most common UI flow catches issues that break real adoption.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Using LLM training knowledge for current feature availability or pricing tiers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Vendor pricing pages and tier names change quarterly. Require evidence from trial instance or dated changelog, never from LLM priors.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Accepting compliance attestations from a badge or marketing page.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>SOC2, ISO27001 badges without the actual audit report are unverifiable. Require signed security questionnaire (SIG Lite or CAIQ) before shortlisting.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Letting an agent submit an RFP response or sign a DPA.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Procurement actions with legal consequences require human authorization. Agents produce drafts only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
