<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="jobs-to-be-done">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>Framework to understand customer progress by interviewing recent switchers and mapping motivations via Push/Pull/Habit/Fear forces.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>research</tag>
      <tag>jobs-to-be-done</tag>
      <tag>jtbd</tag>
      <tag>customer-progress</tag>
      <tag>switching-behavior</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Jobs to Be Done (JTBD)</title>

    <summary>A framework for understanding what progress customers are trying to make so products can be designed around stable motivations rather than shifting feature requests. Core rule: interview recent switchers (within 60-90 days), tag each response as Push / Pull / Habit / Fear, synthesize 1-3 candidate job statements in "When... I want... So I can..." form, and always capture functional, emotional, and social job dimensions.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Feature-based thinking produces roadmaps that match stated wants but miss underlying motivations. Jobs are stable over decades (communicate with family, capture thoughts, get from A to B) while solutions change. Identifying the real job reveals non-obvious competition and prevents building features that satisfy surface requests while failing the deeper progress the customer needs.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Re-framing an idea or feature in customer-progress terms before building.</item>
        <item>Diagnosing why a feature flopped: was the job mismatched or just the solution?</item>
        <item>Understanding switching: interview recent switchers using the Forces of Progress framework.</item>
        <item>Mapping a complex job into stages to find the highest-pain stage.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Optimizing an already-validated product on a known job — use A/B tests, retention analysis, and growth experiments.</item>
        <item>B2C impulse purchases (snacks, fashion) where the job is simply "feel good now."</item>
        <item>Pure infrastructure or API tooling where the job is technical and persona/feature thinking is faster.</item>
        <item>No recent switchers available to interview — JTBD without switching data is hypothesis-spinning.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="job-vs-solution">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define the job at a level of abstraction that stays stable over decades; solutions change, jobs do not.</statement>
        <rationale>Defining the job as "use Notion" locks the product to a solution. Defining it as "capture and organize thoughts" reveals how the job has been hired across paper, typewriters, Word, and Notion — and what comes next.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Job (stable): communicate with distant family. Solutions: letters, phone, email, video calls.</item>
        <item>Job (stable): capture and organize thoughts. Solutions: paper, typewriter, Word, Notion.</item>
        <item>Job (stable): get from A to B quickly. Solutions: horse, car, Uber, autonomous vehicle.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="job-dimensions">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always capture functional, emotional, and social dimensions for every job; never report only the functional dimension.</statement>
        <rationale>Emotional and social dimensions often explain price tolerance and churn. A customer who leaves a product despite it working "fine" is usually leaving over an emotional or social job failure.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Functional: get something concrete done ("file my taxes correctly").</item>
        <item>Emotional: feel a certain way as a result ("feel in control of my finances").</item>
        <item>Social: how others perceive me because of this ("appear financially responsible").</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="forces-of-progress">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Adoption occurs when Push (current pain) + Pull (new solution appeal) exceeds Habit (comfort with old) + Fear (anxiety about new). Optimize for the dominant force pair.</statement>
        <rationale>Founders over-focus on Pull (making their product attractive) and ignore Habit and Fear. For niche B2B, inertia and switching anxiety often dominate and are the actual blockers.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="CRM switch analysis">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
CRM switch analysis:
Push: old CRM loses data, clunky UI (score: high)
Pull: new CRM has automation, mobile app (score: medium)
Habit: team knows the old system (score: high)
Fear: migration might lose contacts (score: high)

Insight: Pull is not the problem; address Habit and Fear with
a migration service and a rollback guarantee before promoting features.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="hiring-and-firing">
      <p>Customers hire products when progress is needed and the current solution is inadequate. They fire products when the job is done, a better alternative exists, or the progress is no longer needed. Understanding the firing event is as important as understanding the hiring decision.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="switcher-interview-method">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Interview people who switched to, switched away from, or first adopted your product category within the last 60-90 days. Memory decay after 90 days flattens the timeline.</statement>
        <rationale>Recent memory provides specific trigger events, exact sources of friction, and authentic emotional context. Older switchers reconstruct a rationalized narrative, not the actual decision process.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Reconstruct the full timeline from first thought to current use; capture the trigger moment ("first thought") explicitly — most product investments target the wrong timeline stage.</statement>
        <rationale>Acquisition efforts usually target Active Looking (evaluation) but the opportunity to influence the decision is in Passive Looking or earlier. The trigger moment reveals what caused the job to become active.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>First Thought: "When did you first think you needed something different?"</item>
        <item>Passive Looking: "What did you first look at? How did you hear about options?"</item>
        <item>Active Looking: "When did you start seriously evaluating? What criteria mattered?"</item>
        <item>The Switch: "Walk me through the moment you decided to switch."</item>
        <item>Consumption: "What happened when you started using the new solution?"</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="job-statement-synthesis">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Synthesize job statements only after tagging at least 5 interviews; reject any statement not backed by at least 3 verbatim quotes from real switchers.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs generate plausible job statements without interview data. A statement must be testable: a stranger reading it should predict the customer's behavior in three scenarios.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Validated job statement">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Validated job statement (backed by 7 interviews):
"When I finish a client project,
 I want to send a professional invoice quickly,
 so I can get paid faster and move on to the next project."
Evidence quotes:
  - "I was losing 30 minutes per invoice fiddling with templates."
  - "The delay between sending and getting paid was stressing me out."
  - "I looked for anything that would let me send in under 2 minutes."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="job-map-8-stages">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Apply the 8-stage Job Map only to jobs with at least 3 distinct steps; forcing it onto simple jobs creates fake pain points.</statement>
        <rationale>The Job Map is a discovery tool, not a template. A simple job like "send an invoice" does not have 8 meaningful stages; artificially creating them wastes roadmap time.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Define — determine what is needed; pain: unclear requirements.</item>
        <item>Locate — find options and information; pain: information overload.</item>
        <item>Prepare — get ready to execute; pain: setup complexity.</item>
        <item>Confirm — validate the choice; pain: doubt and missing information.</item>
        <item>Execute — do the core job; pain: friction and errors.</item>
        <item>Monitor — check progress; pain: lack of feedback.</item>
        <item>Modify — make adjustments; pain: limited flexibility.</item>
        <item>Conclude — finish the job; pain: unclear completion state.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Asking "what features should we add?" instead of "what are you trying to accomplish?"</description>
        <reason>Feature requests are solution guesses, not job statements. They reveal what customers think the solution should look like, not what progress they are trying to make.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Accepting "do nothing / spreadsheets" as the real competitor without evidence from interview transcripts.</description>
        <reason>This is a meme answer that LLMs auto-generate. Require explicit mentions of "spreadsheet" or "I do it manually" in actual interview transcripts before accepting it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <how-to>
      <step>Define the target audience and context precisely (e.g., "solo founders, post-launch, &lt;$10k MRR").</step>
      <step>Recruit at least 5 recent switchers (60-90 days) via User Interviews, Respondent, or similar platforms.</step>
      <step>Conduct interviews using the timeline structure: First Thought, Passive Looking, Active Looking, The Switch, Consumption.</step>
      <step>Tag each interview transcript with Push / Pull / Habit / Fear forces; assign severity 1-5 to each force mention and capture verbatim quotes.</step>
      <step>Synthesize 1-3 candidate job statements in "When ... I want ... So I can ..." form, backed by at least 3 verbatim quotes each.</step>
      <step>For each candidate job statement, identify the functional, emotional, and social dimensions.</step>
      <step>Map the chosen statement into the 8-stage Job Map if the job involves 3+ distinct steps.</step>
      <step>Extract root causes for the top pain stages using 5-Whys analysis.</step>
    </how-to>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Four roles. Switcher-recruiter agent (haiku): drafts outreach copy + screener questions to find recent switchers. Founder/researcher conducts interviews. Forces-tagger agent (sonnet): tags Push / Pull / Habit / Fear quotes from each transcript. Job-statement synthesizer (opus): aggregates ≥5 tagged interviews into 1-3 candidate job statements; for each, lists functional / emotional / social dimensions and the real competitive set. Job-mapper agent (sonnet, optional): expands the chosen statement into 8 stages with pain hot-spots.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Interview recent switchers within 60-90 days of the switch. Memory decay after that flattens the timeline.</item>
        <item>Capture the trigger ("first thought") moment — most product investments target the wrong stage because they skip the trigger.</item>
        <item>Always tag all four forces. Founders over-index on Push and Pull and forget Habit / Fear; the latter two often dominate for niche B2B.</item>
        <item>Functional + emotional + social dimensions — record all three even if one feels dominant. Emotional and social often explain price tolerance.</item>
        <item>Job statements should be testable: a stranger reading the statement should predict the customer's behaviour in three different scenarios. If not, refine.</item>
        <item>Use the 8-stage Job Map only for jobs with ≥3 distinct steps. Forcing it on simple jobs creates fake pain points.</item>
        <item>Re-run JTBD after major market shifts (LLMs, new platform, regulation). Solutions move; jobs are stable but contexts change.</item>
        <item>Pair with problem-validation for evidence weight and pricing-research for value capture.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs generate plausible job statements without any interview data. Reject statements not backed by ≥3 verbatim quotes from real switchers.</item>
        <item>Force-tagging agents over-classify excitement as Pull and skepticism as Fear; require past-tense behaviour evidence ("I tried X first") for severity ≥4.</item>
        <item>The "milkshake job" example is so famous LLMs auto-pattern-match it onto any food/drink case. Suppress example-leakage by removing the README example from analyzer prompts.</item>
        <item>Agents conflate persona with job ("the marketing manager wants..."). Job is about progress + circumstance, not role. Lint for persona language.</item>
        <item>"Real competitor is doing nothing / spreadsheets" is a meme answer. Require evidence (competitor mention in interview transcript) before accepting.</item>
        <item>Synthetic-user simulators ("ask GPT to roleplay a switcher") fabricate forces — never substitute for real interviews.</item>
        <item>Human checkpoint: founder reviews the final job statement(s) and competitive set before any roadmap change. Statements drive feature priority — bad statements waste quarters.</item>
        <item>Cross-cultural job framing differs: emotional/social dimensions in collectivist cultures map differently than the Christensen examples; avoid copying Western templates verbatim.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <list>
        <item>"Find recent switchers" is hard outside well-trafficked categories. With &lt;5 switcher interviews, JTBD is speculation.</item>
        <item>The Push/Pull/Habit/Fear forces are seductive but not falsifiable in a single interview — agents quote them as if measured.</item>
        <item>Jobs vs. solutions distinction collapses for digital-native categories where the solution shapes the job ("scrolling Instagram" — what's the stable job?).</item>
        <item>Job statements ("When... I want... So I can...") are easy to write and easy to fake. LLMs spit out plausible statements with no interview backing.</item>
        <item>The 8-stage Job Map is overkill for simple jobs (e.g., "send invoice"); applying it indiscriminately produces busywork.</item>
        <item>"Real competition is X" framings (milkshake vs bagels) are great post-hoc stories, weak prospective tools.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/job-statement.md" purpose="Template for documenting a core job with functional, emotional, and social dimensions plus competitive set."/>
      <template path="templates/jtbd-interview.md" purpose="Full interview guide: context fields, timeline questions, forces analysis, draft job statement."/>
      <template path="templates/job-map.md" purpose="8-stage job map (Define → Locate → Prepare → Confirm → Execute → Monitor → Modify → Conclude) with pain + opportunity fields."/>
      <template path="templates/force-aggregator.py" purpose="Python script: reads tagged-transcript JSON files, aggregates Push/Pull/Habit/Fear counts and severities."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://hbr.org/2016/09/know-your-customers-jobs-to-be-done"/>
      <link href="https://jtbd.info/"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/jtbd-an-action-guide"/>
      <link href="https://www.intercom.com/blog/jobs-to-be-done-knowing-the-difference-between-customer-needs-and-customer-jobs/"/>
      <link href="https://strategyn.com/jobs-to-be-done/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
