<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="External Secrets Operator Recipe Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the External Secrets Operator Recipe methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-cluster-secret-store-identity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ClusterSecretStore MUST use cloud-identity auth (IRSA on EKS, Workload Identity on GKE, OIDC for Vault). Static token auth forbidden in production.</statement>
      <rationale source="ESO production patterns">Static token in ClusterSecretStore = static credential in cluster; same breach surface as the keys ESO is supposed to eliminate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-refresh-interval-calibrated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ExternalSecret refreshInterval MUST be calibrated to backend rate limits (default 1h is sensible; &lt;5min for high-rotation secrets like database creds with dynamic generation).</statement>
      <rationale source="Vault + AWS Secrets Manager rate limits">Sub-minute refresh hits backend rate limits; hour-long refresh delays rotation by an hour.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-rbac-namespace-scoped" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ESO RBAC MUST scope each ExternalSecret to a namespace + service account. Cluster-wide secret access via ClusterExternalSecret only with named approver.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kubernetes RBAC least-privilege">Wide RBAC turns one pod compromise into all-secret exfiltration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-sync-failure-alert" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sync failure MUST page on-call within 5 min: failure metric (eso_externalsecret_sync_calls_error_total) + log pattern. Silent staleness forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ESO observability docs">ESO failures mean secrets go stale; stale secrets cause auth errors that look like bugs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-rotation-test-runbook" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each backend secret MUST have a rotation test in runbook: rotate at backend, wait refreshInterval + grace, confirm pod picked up new value via cert/env/health check.</statement>
      <rationale source="secret rotation playbooks">Untested rotation pipeline often breaks at the pod-restart step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-secret-not-mounted-as-env" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mounted secrets MUST go to /var/run/secrets/&lt;name&gt;/ as files, not env vars. App reloads via SIGHUP or polling. Env-var injection requires named approver.</statement>
      <rationale source="twelve-factor security note + ESO patterns">Env vars persist in process state + crash dumps + logs; file mounts can be re-read on rotation without pod restart.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
