<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="hybrid-delivery">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>A framework combining predictive (waterfall) and agile delivery when neither alone fits. Define boundaries explicitly, use a single work-graph, and maintain a translation layer between vocabularies.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>hybrid</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>waterfall</tag>
      <tag>program-management</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Hybrid Delivery: Combining Predictive and Agile Approaches</title>

    <summary>Hybrid delivery is a framework for programs that combine predictive (waterfall) and agile delivery modes when neither alone fits. The boundary between modes is defined explicitly in a program.yaml work-graph: top-level milestones (predictive arm) decompose into epics, which decompose into team backlogs (agile arm). Both arms use their own vocabulary and rituals; a translation layer converts between them for steering-committee reporting.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Pure agile or pure waterfall rarely fits real programs. Hardware + software combinations, regulated environments, and enterprise rollouts all have components with different risk profiles and cadence needs. Hybrid works when the boundary is explicit; it fails — degenerating into incoherence — when the boundary is undefined or driven by politics rather than risk profile.</p>
      <p>The translation layer prevents vocabulary collisions from breaking executive trust. Milestone-vs-increment language, effort-based-vs-point-based estimation, and stage-gate-vs-iteration cadence all require explicit mapping. Without translation, steering committees lose confidence and programs revert to single-mode orthodoxy.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Programs with hardware + software components where physical-world milestones are predictive and digital iteration is agile.</item>
        <item>Regulated software (FDA, FAA, ISO 26262, SOX, GDPR) needing stage gates on top of agile execution.</item>
        <item>Enterprise transformation rollouts: portfolio-level milestones and budget cycles with Scrum/Kanban delivery teams.</item>
        <item>Vendor + internal team mixes where vendor contracts are fixed-bid and internal teams iterate.</item>
        <item>DevOps + Agile delivery with monthly/quarterly ops/finance/security governance reviews.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure software-only product teams with autonomous backlog and no compliance gates — full Scrum or Kanban is simpler.</item>
        <item>Tiny teams (under 10) where ceremony overhead exceeds coordination value — pick one mode.</item>
        <item>Pure fixed-scope delivery where iteration adds risk without value — stay predictive.</item>
        <item>"We do hybrid" without explicit boundaries — that is incoherence, not hybrid; refuse and force a real method choice.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="decision-framework">
      <p>Hybrid delivery starts with explicit risk-profile-based mode selection. Each deliverable must be assigned clearly to one mode: predictive, agile, or a hybrid pattern.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Assign each deliverable explicitly to one mode: high uncertainty + frequent change = agile; clear requirements + fixed scope = predictive; mixed characteristics = hybrid; continuous deployment needed = agile + DevOps. Document the assignment in program.yaml.</statement>
        <rationale>Mode selection by team preference or political convenience — rather than risk profile — is the primary cause of hybrid program failure.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="five-hybrid-patterns">
      <p>Five canonical patterns have emerged in practice, each suited to different risk profiles and organizational contexts.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Water-Scrum-Fall: waterfall for requirements and design, Scrum for development and testing. Use for hardware + software programs where design lock-in is required before code.</item>
        <item>Agile with Gates: agile execution inside stage-gate checkpoints. Use for regulated industries (FDA, SOX, HIPAA) needing evidence at governance boundaries.</item>
        <item>Phased Agile: multiple teams with milestone-gated phases. Use for large enterprise rollouts where each phase has a hard commitment date but internal delivery is agile.</item>
        <item>Selective Agile: some components agile, others predictive by risk profile. Use when a single program spans multiple delivery domains (hardware predictive, firmware agile, cloud-native DevOps).</item>
        <item>DevOps + Agile: continuous delivery with governance reviews. 2026 default for cloud-native programs; ship on demand, review finance/security monthly or quarterly.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="explicit-boundary-rule">
      <p>The most critical rule in hybrid delivery: the boundary between predictive and agile must be drawn explicitly and visible to every participant.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Name in writing which deliverables are predictive (charter, contracts, regulatory submissions, hardware BOMs) and which are agile (software increments, user research, internal services). If you cannot draw a literal line on an architecture or organizational diagram, the model is incoherent — do not proceed.</statement>
        <rationale>Boundary ambiguity is the dominant hybrid failure mode. Without an explicit line, every gate review becomes a negotiation about which rules apply, and the program devolves into political theatre.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Maintain one canonical work-graph (program.yaml) with milestones, epics, and team mappings. Two competing portfolios — one for governance, one for delivery — creates divergent truth that agents and humans both get wrong.</statement>
        <rationale>Tool sprawl (backlog in Jira, gantt in MS Project, deliverables in SharePoint) means agents spend more tokens reconciling than executing. One system of record prevents drift.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="tool-count-constraint">
      <p>Each additional tool introduces a reconciliation step. The number of tools should be proportional to the complexity of the boundary.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Choose a tool count proportional to boundary count: ideally one tool spans both arms (Azure DevOps, GitLab Ultimate, Jira+Plans). Two tools maximum with an explicit sync mechanism. Three or more tools is a smell indicating an unresolved process problem.</statement>
        <rationale>Each additional tool adds a reconciliation step; three+ tools guarantee drift between arms that becomes visible only at gate reviews, when correction is most expensive.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="translation-table">
      <p>Agile and predictive vocabularies are fundamentally different. A translation layer converts between them for steering-committee reporting and cross-functional coordination.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define one explicit translation table before the first steering report: epic maps to deliverable, story-points map to a declared effort estimate, velocity maps to run-rate. Use the same table for every report cycle and never mix vocabularies within a single audience.</statement>
        <rationale>Vocabulary leakage — "milestone" used in team standups, "increment" in governance packs — causes executives to lose confidence in the program; consistent translation maintains trust.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Translation table example">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Steering-committee pack uses: milestone, deliverable, planned-vs-actual labour, variance.
Team ceremony uses: increment, story, velocity, sprint goal.

Translation:
- Epic (agile) ↔ Deliverable (predictive)
- Story points (agile) ↔ Effort estimate in hours (predictive)
- Velocity trend (agile) ↔ Run-rate labour cost (predictive)
- Iteration (agile) ↔ Phase gate (predictive)

The cadence-translator-agent converts between them; humans never mix the two.
]]></code>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agile metrics (story points, velocity) presented directly to a steering committee that thinks in deliverables and labour cost.</description>
        <reason>Executive audiences interpret story points as arbitrary numbers; without translation they discount the data or demand a switch to hours, undermining agile capacity planning.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="gate-cadence">
      <p>Gate frequency must match the risk profile of the predictive arm. Too frequent gates throttle delivery; too infrequent gates miss real exposure.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Set gate frequency proportional to risk: monthly for regulated programs, quarterly for steady-state, never weekly (that is just a status meeting renamed). Gate decisions — go/no-go — are sponsor calls only; agents may flag readiness but not declare it.</statement>
        <rationale>Weekly gates produce decision fatigue and get rubber-stamped. Monthly gates align with regulatory review cadence. Quarterly gates suit established, low-risk steady-state programs.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Re-baseline the predictive arm only when scope or contract changes, not when velocity slips. Velocity slippage is handled in retrospectives and planning; it is not a baseline trigger.</statement>
        <rationale>Re-baselining on velocity drift obscures the original commitment and makes trend analysis impossible; the baseline is the contract, not the forecast.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="evm-on-agile-arm-warning">
      <p>Earned Value Management is a powerful predictive-arm tool, but it is misapplied to the agile arm with high frequency and dangerous consequences.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Applying Earned Value Management metrics (CPI, SPI computed from story-points × hourly rate) to the agile arm without an explicitly agreed conversion.</description>
        <reason>Story points are a relative planning unit, not a labour-cost proxy; EVM computed from them produces numbers that look precise but are meaningless, and finance will hold the PM accountable for them.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="organizational-anti-patterns">
      <p>Hybrid program failure is often organizational rather than methodological. Three anti-patterns dominate.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Hybrid chosen as a political compromise rather than a risk-profile decision.</description>
        <reason>PMO-wants-control + teams-want-autonomy resolved by "we do hybrid" produces neither the governance of predictive nor the adaptability of agile — it produces incoherence dressed as methodology.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agile coach distrusts gantts; PM distrusts standups.</description>
        <reason>The dominant cultural failure in hybrid programs. The solution is cross-training: PMs shadow stand-ups, coaches attend gate reviews. Neither arm is optional.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Governance drift: the predictive arm enforces a stage gate, the agile arm flies through it; or vice versa, agile is gated to a quarterly cadence and dies.</description>
        <reason>Gate frequency must match risk profile, not legacy habit or org politics. Misalignment between arms destroys the coherence that hybrid promises.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Hybrid delivery at scale requires multiple specialized subagents to maintain the work-graph, generate governance reports, and flag alignment issues.</p>

      <p>Model the program as a single work-graph (program.yaml): top-level milestones (predictive arm) decompose into epics, epics into team backlogs (agile arm). A subagent maintains the graph, flags inconsistencies (e.g., epic past its milestone date with less than 50% issues done), and drafts gate-review packs from the underlying issue tracker. The "translation layer" is owned by a custom agent that keeps stage-gate vocabulary (deliverable, baseline, variance) reconciled with agile vocabulary (story, increment, velocity). Never let the agent unilaterally close a stage gate — gate decisions are sponsor calls.</p>

      <list>
        <item>program-graph-curator-agent (sonnet): maintains program.yaml, syncs to Jira/Linear/MS Project, computes milestone-vs-epic-vs-issue alignment.</item>
        <item>gate-review-pack-agent (sonnet): one week before each gate, assembles deliverables list, evidence links, risk register slice, EVM snapshot, and produces a draft pack PR.</item>
        <item>cadence-translator-agent (haiku): converts agile cycle reports into predictive-arm vocabulary for steering-committee consumption.</item>
        <item>dual-rhythm-coach-agent (opus): activated when team velocity diverges greater than 25% from milestone burn; produces options memo (re-baseline, drop scope, add capacity, change cadence).</item>
        <item>password-scrubber-agent: runs over gate-review packs before distribution; predictive-arm packs frequently leak credentials in screenshots.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="program-graph-curator-prompt">
      <p>The program-graph-curator validates the work-graph structure and emits alignment status for each milestone.</p>

      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are the program-graph-curator agent. Inputs: program.yaml (milestones,
epics, team mappings) and a JQL/GraphQL pull of issues by epic.

For each milestone, emit STRICT JSON:
{ "milestone_id": "M-NN", "due": "YYYY-MM-DD", "epics": [...],
  "issues_total": N, "issues_done": N, "pct_complete": 0.NN,
  "burn_status": "ahead|on|behind|at_risk",
  "gate_readiness": "ready|gaps|blocked",
  "gaps": ["..."], "evidence_links": ["..."] }

Rules: do not invent issues. burn_status comes from arithmetic only. gate_readiness
must cite specific gaps if not "ready". Flag any epic with no team owner or no
linked issues as "ORPHAN".
]]></code>

      <p>Translation prompt: "Convert this cycle report into steering-committee predictive-arm vocabulary. Map: story → deliverable, increment → milestone progress, velocity → planned-vs-actual labour. Preserve dates and quantities exactly. Do not editorialize."</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>Hybrid program execution requires tools to manage both the predictive and agile arms, and to render governance artifacts.</p>

      <list>
        <item>git + tags — tag releases at gate decisions; git history = audit trail of gate outcomes.</item>
        <item>gh / glab — drive epic-level boards (predictive view) and issue-level boards (agile view).</item>
        <item>jira-cli — JQL queries to pull cross-team status into program graph.</item>
        <item>python-pptx / pandoc — render gate-review packs from markdown into the format the steering committee will accept.</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc) — render gantts + dependency diagrams from program.yaml.</item>
        <item>ganttproject-cli / taskjuggler — compute critical path and forecast on the predictive arm.</item>
        <item>mpxj (Java) — read/write MS Project .mpp files for organizations that mandate them.</item>
        <item>dvc / lakeFS — version control for non-code deliverables (CAD, datasets) on the predictive arm.</item>
        <item>pre-commit — block edits to program.yaml that change milestone dates without rationale.</item>
        <item>yq / jq — read/patch the program graph and JSON exports.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="tool-options">
      <p>Many platforms support hybrid delivery, each with different strengths for predictive vs. agile arms.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Jira (+ Advanced Roadmaps / Plans) — common hybrid host: epics+milestones in Plans, issues in team boards.</item>
        <item>Microsoft Project + Project for the Web — enterprise gantt + portfolio; predictive-arm system of truth. Pair with Azure DevOps for agile arm.</item>
        <item>Azure DevOps — native hybrid: portfolio Plans, team Boards, Pipelines for DevOps arm.</item>
        <item>GitLab Premium/Ultimate (Roadmaps + Boards + Iterations) — single-pane hybrid alternative; agent-friendly via GraphQL.</item>
        <item>Smartsheet — portfolio gantts + dashboards for organizations already on Smartsheet.</item>
        <item>Asana (Portfolios) — portfolio-level milestones with team-level boards underneath.</item>
        <item>ClickUp — all-in-one with goals + sprints; reporting depth limited at scale.</item>
        <item>Monday.com — portfolio + agile boards; weak EVM.</item>
        <item>ServiceNow SPM (formerly ITBM) — heavy enterprise PPM; required where governance is the constraint.</item>
        <item>Planview / Clarity — portfolio + EVM-grade tooling; expensive; agent integration via REST.</item>
        <item>Confluence / Notion — charters, gate-review packs, decision records — pair with the work-graph host.</item>
        <item>OpenProject / Redmine / Tuleap — self-hosted hybrid hosts for regulated/airgapped organizations.</item>
        <item>Targetprocess (Apptio) — SAFe-aligned hybrid PPM.</item>
        <item>Hansoft (Perforce) — game/aerospace heritage; backlog + gantt in one.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Draw the boundary explicitly: name in writing which deliverables are predictive (charter, contracts, regulatory submissions, hardware BOMs) and which are agile (software increments, user research, internal services). Boundary in program.yaml.</item>
        <item>Single backlog of epics, multiple team backlogs of stories — never two competing portfolios. Reconcile in code, not in slides.</item>
        <item>Make the gate cadence proportional to risk — monthly for regulated, quarterly for steady-state, never weekly (that is just a status meeting).</item>
        <item>Define one "translation table" (epic ↔ deliverable, story-points ↔ effort estimate, velocity ↔ run rate) and use it for every steering report.</item>
        <item>Run agile teams on agile rituals, predictive workstreams on stage gates — do not force standups onto regulatory submissions or gantt charts onto user-research.</item>
        <item>DevOps + Agile arm: pair with cicd-engineer/ and infrastructure-engineer/ skills; ship on demand, do not let governance throttle deployment frequency.</item>
        <item>Train both PMs and Scrum Masters on the other side; the dominant cultural failure is "agile coach distrusts gantts" or "PM distrusts standups".</item>
        <item>Budget for change-management explicitly — hybrid programs fail more on organization change than on method.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Hybrid delivery exposes specific pitfalls for automated execution. These are empirically documented across agentic hybrid deployments.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Agents over-summarize hybrid programs as "behind" because they conflate vocabulary; force the agent to report agile metrics in agile units and predictive metrics in predictive units.</item>
        <item>LLMs auto-translate epics into "deliverables" and lose information (acceptance criteria collapse to one line). Keep both views; never destroy the agile detail.</item>
        <item>Date arithmetic is unreliable across calendar conventions (work days vs. calendar days, fiscal vs. ISO weeks). Hard-code the convention in the prompt and have a tool, not the LLM, compute deltas.</item>
        <item>Stage-gate "go / no-go" decisions must never be auto-emitted — flag readiness only, leave the call to the sponsor.</item>
        <item>EVM on agile arm is a trap: agents will earnestly compute SPI/CPI from story points × hourly rate. Refuse unless the conversion is explicitly defined and accepted by finance.</item>
        <item>Cross-tool sync drift: if Jira and MS Project disagree, the agent will pick the latest; pick the system of record per field instead and pin it in program.yaml.</item>
        <item>Vocabulary leakage: predictive arm uses "milestone", "deliverable", "baseline"; agile arm uses "increment", "story", "velocity". Force terminology per audience or executives lose trust.</item>
        <item>Bulk gate-pack generation is a leak risk — every pack often pulls from confidential decks/screenshots. Run password-scrubber-agent and a manual review before sharing.</item>
        <item>Long-context drift: program graphs greater than 50 epics blow context. Page by milestone or workstream and operate on slices.</item>
        <item>Mandatory human-in-the-loop checkpoints: boundary changes, gate decisions, re-baselining, cadence changes for any team, vendor escalations.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="agile-ceremonies-setup"/>
      <ref slug="earned-value-management"/>
      <ref slug="pm-tool-selection"/>
      <ref slug="change-control"/>
      <link href="https://pmistandards.org/standards/list">PMI PMBOK 7e — Development Approach and Life Cycle Performance Domain</link>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standard">PMI Agile Practice Guide — hybrid life cycle patterns</link>
      <link href="https://www.scaledagileframework.com">SAFe — Portfolio + Large Solution + Essential layers as a hybrid blueprint</link>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/disciplined-agile">Disciplined Agile Delivery (DAD) — explicit hybrid life cycle selection</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
