<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Python Async Patterns — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every python-async application must obey.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-taskgroup-over-gather" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use asyncio.TaskGroup for fan-out where all subtasks must succeed or none. Use gather only when you need ordered partial-failure semantics with return_exceptions=True.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">TaskGroup cancels siblings on first failure; gather leaves orphans unless return_exceptions is set — and that requires manual error inspection per result.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-semaphore-inside-task" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use asyncio.Semaphore to cap concurrent I/O. Acquire the semaphore inside the task coroutine, not outside it.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">Inside-acquire lets all tasks be created cheaply while limiting concurrent execution; outside-acquire serialises task creation and defeats the purpose.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-asyncio-timeout" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use asyncio.timeout(seconds) (3.11+) for per-call deadlines. Do not use asyncio.wait_for for new code.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">asyncio.timeout is a context manager that can be extended or rescheduled; it raises TimeoutError that integrates with standard exception handling.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-no-blocking-calls" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never call time.sleep, sync requests, or sync DB drivers inside async def. Use asyncio.sleep, httpx.AsyncClient, asyncpg/aiosqlite respectively.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">A single blocking call stalls the entire event loop and freezes every other coroutine until it returns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-store-task-references" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always store the return value of asyncio.create_task in a variable or collection. Garbage-collected tasks raise 'Task was destroyed but it is pending'.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">The event loop holds only a weak reference; without a strong ref the task can be collected mid-flight.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
