<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="spatial-computing-overview Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for spatial-computing-overview. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use precise XR terminology in all design documentation: AR (digital overlay on real world, passthrough camera or optical), VR (fully immersive synthetic environment), MR (real and digital objects interact in real time), XR (umbrella term for all three).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Conflating AR and VR leads to wrong platform selection, incorrect interaction model assumptions, and deliverables that cannot be implemented on the target device.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For Apple Vision Pro: design eye-gaze + pinch as the primary interaction; no physical controller grip states; use visionOS window and volume primitives; assume high rendering quality and precision eye tracking.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">visionOS was designed around eye+hand input from the ground up; controller-centric patterns from other platforms do not translate and will feel unnatural.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For Meta Quest: design for both hand tracking and controller input as parallel paths; assume color passthrough for MR use cases; test comfort for the larger consumer user base including non-technical users.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Quest's broad consumer install base includes users unfamiliar with 3D interfaces; simpler interaction models and robust onboarding are required.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For HoloLens and Magic Leap: design for factory and field use — glove compatibility, outdoor brightness, short interaction sequences between physical work tasks, voice as primary input when hands are occupied.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Industrial XR users are performing physical tasks concurrently; interaction must be minimal and glove-compatible; content must be visible in high-ambient-light environments.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
