<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="LB High Availability Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for HA load-balanced topologies. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="two-lb-min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any production service with SLA ≥ 99.9% MUST front itself with ≥ 2 LB instances in active-active or active-passive configuration. A single LB instance is not HA regardless of how many backends sit behind it.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected + Cloud LB HA references">A single LB instance is itself a SPOF — process crash, host failure, or network partition takes the whole service down. ≥ 2 instances + automatic failover (VRRP / managed LB pair) is the minimum that satisfies N-1.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="two-az-min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Backend instances MUST be distributed across ≥ 2 availability zones. Each AZ MUST host ≥ 2 healthy backend instances (i.e., total ≥ 4 backends for N-1 in each AZ).</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected + GCP reliability docs">A single-AZ backend pool means an AZ outage takes the whole service down — the LB is healthy but every backend is unreachable. ≥ 2 AZs with ≥ 2 backends each survives one full AZ failure with capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="anycast-over-dns-for-9999" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For multi-region HA with SLA ≥ 99.99%, the global LB MUST be anycast (AWS Global Accelerator, GCP Global HTTP(S) LB, Cloudflare LB). DNS-based GSLB (Route 53 latency / geo routing, NS1, Akamai GTM) is forbidden at this SLA tier.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Global Accelerator FAQ + Cloudflare LB docs">DNS-based GSLB failover is 30 s – 5 min in practice (resolver caches ignore short TTLs); anycast failover is &lt; 30 s at the BGP layer.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="drain-on-sigterm" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Zero-downtime deployments MUST implement: (a) SIGTERM handler that flips readiness probe to 503 immediately; (b) deregistration delay / drain timeout ≥ 30 s; (c) process exit only after drain completes. Plain `kill -TERM` followed by immediate exit is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kubernetes graceful-shutdown docs + LB drain references">Without readiness flip on SIGTERM, the LB keeps sending new requests for the next 10–30 s; the dying process answers with 502/connection-reset. Drain delay lets in-flight requests complete cleanly.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="no-single-az-backends" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Multi-AZ LBs (e.g., AWS ALB with subnets in 3 AZs) MUST NOT be paired with single-AZ backend pools. The LB target group MUST have healthy targets in every subnet AZ the LB listens on.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS ELB cross-zone load-balancing docs">A multi-AZ LB with single-AZ backends still goes fully down if that one AZ fails; it merely looks HA in the dashboard.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
