<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-trends" title="BA Industry Trends 2025-2026">
  <summary>Six dominant BA industry trends for 2025-2026 with critical success factors and skill-evolution priorities.</summary>

  <section title="Top 6 BA Trends">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat these six trends as routing signals: each maps to a dedicated sibling methodology that owns the actionable workflow.</statement>
      <rationale>This index is a snapshot; the sibling methodologies (ai-enabled-business-analysis, agile-ba-frameworks, process-mining-automation, data-driven-requirements, modern-ba-framework, ba-strategic-partnership) are where procedures live.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>AI-enabled decision making — integrating AI tools into requirements elicitation and analysis workflows.</item>
      <item>Outcome-driven strategy — shifting from feature delivery to measurable business outcomes as the unit of BA work.</item>
      <item>Responsible innovation — embedding ethics, governance, and bias-checking into AI project scoping.</item>
      <item>Operational resilience — designing processes and requirements for failure recovery, not just happy paths.</item>
      <item>Digital trust — treating security, privacy, and auditability as primary requirements, not constraints.</item>
      <item>Sustainability integration — including environmental and social impact metrics in solution evaluation criteria.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Critical Success Factors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Quantify data quality before starting any AI-enabled BA initiative; 60% of AI projects fail due to poor data.</statement>
      <rationale>AI requirements analysis is only as good as the data it analyzes; the BA must assess data fitness before committing to an AI-augmented workflow.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Establish business process clarity before applying AI; 95% of enterprise AI projects fail without documented processes.</statement>
      <rationale>AI amplifies existing process structure — it cannot substitute for it. The BA must complete current-state modeling before AI tooling is introduced.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Stakeholder alignment — critical for adoption and value realization of any solution.</item>
      <item>Continuous learning — technology evolution requires ongoing skill investment.</item>
      <item>Ethical framework — trust and governance are strategic differentiators, not compliance checkboxes.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="BA Skill Evolution Priorities">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize AI/ML literacy and data analytics as immediate-action skills; treat process mining and automation analysis as 12-month targets.</statement>
      <rationale>The BA who cannot read a confusion matrix or query a data lake will be displaced by AI-assisted analysis; upskilling is not optional for 2025-2026 relevance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>AI/ML Literacy — Critical priority, immediate action required.</item>
      <item>Data Analytics — High priority, immediate action required.</item>
      <item>Agile/Enterprise Agile Framework — High priority, ongoing.</item>
      <item>Strategic Thinking — High priority, continuous development.</item>
      <item>Process Mining — Medium priority, 12-month target.</item>
      <item>Automation Analysis — Medium priority, 12-month target.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../ai-enabled-business-analysis/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../agile-ba-frameworks/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../process-mining-automation/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../modern-ba-framework/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../ba-strategic-partnership/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
