<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="viral-loops">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>growth-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Five viral loop archetypes (WOM, Inherent, Incentivized, Content, Outbreak) with K-factor ranges, share mechanics, product fit conditions, and selection guide. Never run 4 loops simultaneously.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>viral</tag>
      <tag>k-factor</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>referral</tag>
      <tag>virality</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Viral Loops and Types</title>

    <summary>Five viral loop archetypes — Word of Mouth, Inherent, Incentivized, Content, and Outbreak — each with distinct K-factor ranges, share mechanics, and product fit conditions. Pick the loop type that matches the product's natural use, then layer one secondary loop. Never run 4 loops simultaneously.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Loop type selection determines the ceiling of achievable K. Inherent virality (Slack, Zoom) can reach K=2+ because collaboration requires inviting others. Content virality (TikTok) has K=0.3-0.8 because conversion from viewer to signup is low. Choosing the wrong loop type (forcing "inherent" onto a non-collaborative product) kills NPS without raising K.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Choosing between viral loop types for a new product or vertical.</item>
        <item>Modeling growth plans: need realistic K, i, c benchmarks before committing to a target.</item>
        <item>Trying to raise K by 0.1-0.3 and needing a structured experiment plan.</item>
        <item>Instrumenting share-moment events for weekly K reporting by loop type.</item>
        <item>You want an agent to instrument share-moment events and report loop health weekly.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-retention: virality on a leaky bucket just speeds churn. Prove D30 retention first.</item>
        <item>B2B enterprise with 6-month sales cycles — loops do not compound on that timescale.</item>
        <item>Heavily regulated products (medical, financial) where outbound viral mechanics breach compliance.</item>
        <item>When you have fewer than 500 invite events — K is noise at small samples.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="loop-mechanics">
      <p>All viral loops share the same 5-step cycle: user joins → encounters trigger → sends invitation → friend converts → new user repeats the cycle. Loop type determines where the trigger occurs and how strong it is.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="word-of-mouth">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use WOM when the product is genuinely exceptional and natural share moments exist at peak satisfaction; do not engineer WOM for mediocre products.</statement>
        <rationale>WOM has low i (not everyone tells friends) but high c (personal recommendation converts strongly). Forcing WOM prompts on a product without real delight backfires — users feel pressured and NPS drops.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Typical K: 0.1-0.5</item>
        <item>Examples: Notion (early), Figma (design teams)</item>
        <item>Best for: productivity tools, exceptional consumer products, strong brand</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="inherent-virality">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use inherent virality only when the product functionally requires others to participate; do not force collaboration features onto solo-use products.</statement>
        <rationale>Inherent virality has the highest K ceiling because the invite is required, not optional. Forced inherent virality (fake "invite to see content") gets labeled spam and damages NPS.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Typical K: 0.5-2.0</item>
        <item>Examples: Slack, Zoom, Figma, Google Docs</item>
        <item>Best for: collaboration, team, and multi-player products</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="incentivized-referral">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use incentivized virality when LTV is greater than 3x CAC and the reward can be sized at 20-50% of CAC without destroying margins; implement double-sided incentives.</statement>
        <rationale>Incentivized virality boosts i but reduces authenticity, lowering c. The net K is viable when the reward economics work. Single-sided referrals feel exploitative and perform 20-30% worse.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Typical K: 0.3-1.0</item>
        <item>Examples: Dropbox (free storage), Uber ($10 credit), PayPal ($10 cash)</item>
        <item>Best for: high-LTV SaaS, fintech, e-commerce with margin room</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="content-virality">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use content virality when users naturally produce shareable artifacts (scores, results, badges, created content) that embed product branding without feeling like an ad.</statement>
        <rationale>Content virality has variable i (depends on content quality and shareability) and low c (many views, few signups). The share artifact must have novelty and social value — most imitations fail.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Typical K: 0.1-0.5 (content platforms can hit 0.8+)</item>
        <item>Examples: TikTok, Wordle (K=1.5+), Spotify Wrapped</item>
        <item>Best for: content creation platforms, social apps, entertainment products</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="outbreak-virality">
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not implement outbreak (automated contact import) virality; modern email filters and OS protections block it, and it damages brand reputation.</statement>
        <rationale>Outbreak virality automates invites to full contact lists. It was viable in 1996 (Hotmail email signature). Today it triggers spam filters, breaches CAN-SPAM, and is rejected by app stores.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="loop-selection-by-product-type">
      <list>
        <item>Collaboration tool: Inherent (primary) + WOM (secondary)</item>
        <item>Consumer app: Content (primary) + WOM (secondary)</item>
        <item>Marketplace: Incentivized (primary)</item>
        <item>Productivity tool: WOM (primary) + Inherent (secondary if team features exist)</item>
        <item>B2B SaaS: WOM (primary) + Incentivized (secondary)</item>
        <item>Gaming: Content (primary) + WOM (secondary)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run at most 2 loops in parallel; instrument them with distinct loop_type property on all invite events so K can be computed per loop separately.</statement>
        <rationale>Attribution between loops is messy without explicit tagging. Running 4 loops at once makes it impossible to know which is contributing and which is wasting engineering effort.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="share-moments-by-loop">
      <list>
        <item>WOM: user achieves their goal; user discovers unexpected value; user solves a major problem</item>
        <item>Inherent: user needs collaboration; user wants to share work; user requires team input</item>
        <item>Incentivized: user completes onboarding; user reaches usage milestone; user is on referral page</item>
        <item>Content: user creates something; user achieves a result; user wants recognition/comparison</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="required-instrumentation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Instrument invite_sent with loop_type, share_channel, and recipient_count properties before launch; without these, K cannot be diagnosed when it drops.</statement>
        <rationale>K drops silently. A redesigned share button can drop i by 40% without any alert. Weekly K split by loop_type and share_channel is the minimum for actionable monitoring.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs love to recommend "make it inherent" for non-collaborative products — forced inherent virality kills NPS.</item>
        <item>Outbreak/spam loops still get suggested by older sources; modern email and OS protections kill them and damage brand.</item>
        <item>Wordle-style content virality is survivorship-biased; most copies fail because the share artifact lacks novelty.</item>
        <item>K is volatile early; sample size for K significance is much larger than for typical conversion tests.</item>
        <item>Loop type is rarely pure — most products run 2-3 loops in parallel and attribution between them is messy.</item>
      </list>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent recommends "make it inherent" for a non-collaborative product.</description>
        <reason>Forced inherent virality creates fake invite prompts that users reject. It kills NPS without raising K. Inherent virality only works when collaboration is the core value proposition.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Computing K on fewer than 500 invite events and reporting it as meaningful.</description>
        <reason>K is volatile at small samples. Signal:noise ratio is unacceptable below ~500 invites per reporting period. Agent must flag low-power computations explicitly.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Recommending outbreak/spam loops based on outdated case studies.</description>
        <reason>Pre-2005 outbreak mechanics are blocked by modern email filters and mobile OS permissions. Always reject this suggestion regardless of source.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>On opus, a strategist agent picks 1-2 loop types per product type, drafts share-moment events, and models target K. A sonnet agent writes share-flow copy and designs the artifact (image, link preview, OG meta). A haiku ops agent computes i, c, K weekly from analytics, splits by loop and segment, and posts a delta vs previous week to a dashboard or Slack channel.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-growth-agent (opus) — loop selection, K modeling, growth simulation. Copy/sonnet subagent — share copy, artifact design brief, OG metadata. Data/haiku subagent — i, c, K computation per loop, anomaly detection.</p>

      <prompt purpose="Loop type recommendation with K modeling"><![CDATA[
Given product = {description}, user count = {N}, retention curve = {curve},
recommend 1-2 viral loop types. For each: target K, top 3 share moments,
required instrumentation events, expected time to K=0.5. Cite which
benchmark range you used.
]]></prompt>

      <prompt purpose="Weekly K computation per loop type"><![CDATA[
Compute i, c, K for last 14d split by loop_type in {events_table}.
Compare to prior 14d. Flag any loop where K dropped >20%. Return markdown
table + one-line diagnosis per loop.
]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <list>
        <item>posthog SDK — Open-source product analytics, custom K dashboards (pip install posthog)</item>
        <item>mixpanel SDK — Funnel + cohort for invite to signup conversion (pip install mixpanel)</item>
        <item>amplitude Data API — i/c/K via JQL or behavioral cohorts (https://amplitude.com/docs/apis)</item>
        <item>segment CLI — Route share events to multiple destinations (npm i -g @segment/cli)</item>
        <item>branch / appsflyer — Mobile deep-link attribution for invite flows</item>
      </list>
      <list>
        <item>Branch: SaaS, Yes (REST) — Deep links, cross-platform invite attribution</item>
        <item>AppsFlyer: SaaS, Yes (REST) — Same, larger enterprise focus</item>
        <item>PostHog: OSS, Yes (REST + self-host) — Best for agent-driven analysis on owned infra</item>
        <item>Mixpanel: SaaS, Yes (REST + JQL) — Mature behavioral cohorts</item>
        <item>Amplitude: SaaS, Yes (REST) — Strongest funnel/cohort UX</item>
        <item>Customer.io: SaaS, Yes (REST) — Trigger invite emails on share-moment events</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="viral-simulator">
      <example type="good" title="viral_sim.py — agent uses to compare loop choices">
        <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# viral_sim.py — agent uses to compare loop choices
def simulate(initial: int, k: float, cycle_days: int, days: int) -> int:
    cycles = days // cycle_days
    users = initial
    for _ in range(cycles):
        users = users + int(users * k)
    return users

# Compare 30d for K=0.4 (good WOM) vs K=0.8 (incentivized)
# print(simulate(1000, 0.4, 7, 30))  # ~3,800
# print(simulate(1000, 0.8, 7, 30))  # ~10,500
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pick the loop type that matches the product's natural use, then layer one secondary loop. Don't try to run 4 loops at once.</item>
        <item>Instrument the share moment as a first-class event with loop_type, share_channel, recipient_count properties before launch.</item>
        <item>Treat K below 0.5 as a supplement, not a strategy — pair with paid or content acquisition.</item>
        <item>Optimize cycle time as aggressively as K — halving cycle time roughly equals doubling K in compounding terms.</item>
        <item>Re-baseline K quarterly; product changes silently break loops (a redesigned share button can drop i by 40%).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas-extended">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Models confuse K with conversion rate; force the prompt to specify K = i times c.</description>
        <reason>K is the product of average invites per user (i) and invitee conversion rate (c). Conflating K with c leads to wrong optimization decisions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent pushing outbreak (auto-contact-import) loops without explicit human approval.</description>
        <reason>TOS and CAN-SPAM landmine. Outbreak mechanics are dead on modern email and mobile platforms.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Weekly K computed on fewer than 500 invites reported as meaningful signal.</description>
        <reason>K is noise below ~500 invites per reporting period; agent should flag low-power computations rather than report them.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents over-fit on Dropbox/PayPal case studies when recommending a target K.</description>
        <reason>Require it to cite a benchmark range (consumer apps: 0.1-0.3; B2B SaaS: 0.05-0.2) before recommending a target K.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Mobile attribution agents using different client_id across web and app.</description>
        <reason>Passing different IDs silently breaks K attribution. Use the same client_id consistently across all platforms.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/viral_sim.py" purpose="Python simulator comparing loop choices over N days"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.forentrepreneurs.com/lessons-learnt-viral-marketing/"/>
      <link href="https://andrewchen.com/whats-your-viral-loop"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
