<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="raci-matrix Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for raci-matrix. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every task row must have exactly one Accountable; reject any RACI with zero or multiple A values in a single row.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Zero A means no decision-maker exists; multiple A creates accountability confusion and slows decisions. The PMI PMBOK 7th edition Team Performance Domain cites this as the primary RACI failure mode.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every task row must have at least one Responsible; a task with no R has no executor and will not get done.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without an R, the task is aspirationally on the matrix but not concretely assigned. It will be deprioritized or forgotten.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Limit Consulted roles to three per row; more than three C values creates an approval bottleneck that slows every task transition.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Every C requires soliciting and integrating feedback before proceeding. Each additional C adds a round-trip delay and a potential veto point.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Name roles, not people, in the RACI matrix; map role-to-person in a separate table.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">People rotate; roles persist. A person-named matrix requires updating every time someone changes team or leaves, making it unmaintainable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tag RACI changes in version control with the commit that introduced them; treat the RACI as code.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without version history, disputes about "who agreed to this" have no authoritative record. Git history provides the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pair RACI with an escalation path specifying who holds A when the named accountable is unavailable for more than 24 hours.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-point accountability without an escalation path creates decision paralysis during PTO or unexpected absence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run raci-lint.py in CI against any Markdown RACI file before merge to enforce validation rules automatically.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Manual review of RACI tables misses constraint violations. Automated CI enforcement catches violations before they reach the team.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One A per row is the only rule that matters; everything else is style. Enforce it in CI.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Perfect enforcement of the A rule prevents the primary failure mode (unclear decision-making).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Name roles, not people. People rotate; roles stick. Map role→person in a separate table.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Person-named matrices require constant updates and become stale quickly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Extend with "S" (Support) and "V" (Verify) only if you actually use them — otherwise it's noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Extra roles add complexity without value if they are not actively used in decision-making.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tag RACI changes in version control with the commit that introduced them; lets you do git blame on accountability.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Version history provides the audit trail and historical context for disputes over ownership.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pair RACI with an escalation path: "If A is unavailable &gt;24h, escalation owner is X."</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Clear escalation paths prevent decision paralysis during absences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For agent-driven projects, declare which rows the agent is "R" on and which require human "A" sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Explicit boundaries prevent scope creep on agent authority and clarify when human judgment is required.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
