<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-raci-rules" title="RACI Matrix Rules and Validation">
  <summary>The four RACI roles, validation rules that must pass for every row, and the most common failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Role Definitions">
    <list>
      <item>Responsible (R): does the work. Multiple R per row is allowed; this is who executes the task.</item>
      <item>Accountable (A): final decision-maker for the task. Exactly ONE per row — this is the rule that matters most.</item>
      <item>Consulted (C): provides input before the decision is made. Two-way communication. Minimize to essential only.</item>
      <item>Informed (I): notified after the decision is made. One-way communication. Be generous with I.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Validation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every task row must have exactly one Accountable; reject any RACI with zero or multiple A values in a single row.</statement>
      <rationale>Zero A means no decision-maker exists; multiple A creates accountability confusion and slows decisions. The PMI PMBOK 7th edition Team Performance Domain cites this as the primary RACI failure mode.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every task row must have at least one Responsible; a task with no R has no executor and will not get done.</statement>
      <rationale>Without an R, the task is aspirationally on the matrix but not concretely assigned. It will be deprioritized or forgotten.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit Consulted roles to three per row; more than three C values creates an approval bottleneck that slows every task transition.</statement>
      <rationale>Every C requires soliciting and integrating feedback before proceeding. Each additional C adds a round-trip delay and a potential veto point.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Name roles, not people, in the RACI matrix; map role-to-person in a separate table.</statement>
      <rationale>People rotate; roles persist. A person-named matrix requires updating every time someone changes team or leaves, making it unmaintainable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>A role that is "A" on more than 60% of the tasks in the matrix.</description>
      <reason>Heavy A concentration is a bottleneck indicator — that role becomes the single point of approval for most decisions. Distribute Accountable roles across appropriate decision-makers.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>All roles assigned "I" for a task (all-I row).</description>
      <reason>An all-I row means everyone is notified but no one executes or decides. This signals the underlying task is too vague to assign ownership.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Matrix Maintenance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag RACI changes in version control with the commit that introduced them; treat the RACI as code.</statement>
      <rationale>Without version history, disputes about "who agreed to this" have no authoritative record. Git history provides the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair RACI with an escalation path specifying who holds A when the named accountable is unavailable for more than 24 hours.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-point accountability without an escalation path creates decision paralysis during PTO or unexpected absence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/raci-lint.py">Lint a Markdown RACI table; exit 1 on validation failures</reference>
  <reference path="templates/raci-template.md">Blank RACI matrix template with role columns</reference>
</text>
