<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="raci-matrix Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for raci-matrix as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>A role that is "A" on more than 60% of the tasks in the matrix.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Heavy A concentration is a bottleneck indicator — that role becomes the single point of approval for most decisions. Distribute Accountable roles across appropriate decision-makers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>All roles assigned "I" for a task (all-I row).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>An all-I row means everyone is notified but no one executes or decides. This signals the underlying task is too vague to assign ownership.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Assigning an AI agent as Accountable for any task in a RACI matrix.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents lack authority, legal accountability, and organizational standing. A-role requires a human who can be held responsible for outcomes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents assigning themselves or "AI" as Accountable in the drafted matrix.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs default to including themselves as stakeholders when generating role assignments. Explicitly forbid this in the system prompt and validate with raci-validator.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents hallucinating stakeholder names not on the provided roles list.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs invent plausible names when the list is incomplete. Pass the roles list as explicit input and instruct the agent to reject any role not on it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Storing the authoritative RACI as a Markdown table when an agent mutates it iteratively.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Markdown table parsing is brittle for programmatic mutation. Store as YAML for agent operations; render as Markdown only for human review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
