<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-platform-and-metrics" title="Platform Constraints and Performance Metrics">
  <summary>Platform-specific constraints for Alexa, Google Actions, and Siri, plus key performance metrics and their optimization levers.</summary>

  <section title="Platform Constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Respect the 8-second response time limit on Alexa; design flows so no single turn requires more processing.</statement>
      <rationale>Alexa kills skills that exceed the time limit; long async operations require progressive disclosure with intermediate acks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate all SSML against the target platform's supported subset before shipping.</statement>
      <rationale>Siri ignores most SSML; Alexa and Google support overlapping but non-identical tag sets; invalid SSML silently degrades to flat TTS.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Alexa: 8-second response limit, custom wake word not allowed, APL/Card for visual companions, certification required.</item>
      <item>Google Actions: multi-surface support (phone/speaker/display), Dialogflow for NLU, rich response cards.</item>
      <item>Siri: limited to SiriKit intents + Shortcuts, HomePod integration, privacy-focused with minimal data sharing.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Performance Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track task completion rate, average turns per task, error rate, fallback rate, and 7-day retention; act on metrics individually.</statement>
      <rationale>Each metric reveals a different failure mode: high error rate indicates utterance coverage gaps; high turns per task indicates prompt complexity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Task completion rate: target above 85%.</item>
      <item>Average turns per task: target below 3.</item>
      <item>Error rate: target below 15%.</item>
      <item>Fallback rate: target below 10%.</item>
      <item>User satisfaction (CSAT): target above 4.0/5.</item>
      <item>7-day retention: target above 40%.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track per-node abandonment; if any node exceeds 30%, the prompt fails users — rewrite before adding utterance variants.</statement>
      <rationale>Utterance variants fix recognition; a rewrite fixes comprehension. High abandonment means users understood the system but rejected it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a visual or text-input alternative for every voice interaction path.</statement>
      <rationale>Speech impediments, accents, quiet environments, and privacy concerns all make voice-only interfaces exclusionary.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not auto-deploy voice copy; stage rollouts because one bad utterance lands on all users simultaneously.</statement>
      <rationale>Voice copy ships instantly to all devices — no browser cache to clear, no app update to decline. The blast radius of a bad line is immediate and broad.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Pitfalls">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM-generated prompts default to verbose, apologetic tone.</description>
      <reason>Explicitly bound max word count and ban filler phrases ("I'd be happy to", "Just to confirm") in the system prompt — the model will not self-edit reliably.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Generated SSML includes tags rejected by the target platform.</description>
      <reason>Validate every generated SSML fragment against the platform's supported-tag list before shipping; unsupported tags render as silent drops or literal text.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>PII in transcripts sent to LLM for copy "improvement".</description>
      <reason>Redact sensitive slots before any LLM analysis call; build the sanitizer as a mandatory pipeline step, not an optional flag.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-prompt-rules.xml">Prompt rules and error recovery ladder</link>
  </see-also>
</text>
