<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="onboarding">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>hr-recruiter</domain>
    <summary>Repeatable new-hire onboarding program: preboarding checklist, Day 1 orientation, buddy pairing, 30-60-90 phases with observable artifacts, feedback loops, manager training, and remote adaptations.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>onboarding</tag>
      <tag>new-hire</tag>
      <tag>employee-experience</tag>
      <tag>retention</tag>
      <tag>recruitment</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Onboarding Program Design</title>

    <summary>An end-to-end framework for designing and operating a repeatable new-hire onboarding program: preboarding, Day 1 orientation, buddy pairing, 30-60-90 day progression, feedback loops, manager guides, and remote adaptations. Targets organizations hiring at a pace where ad-hoc handoffs produce inconsistent ramp.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Unstructured onboarding produces variable ramp speed, elevated 90-day attrition, and disconnected new hires. A program-level approach with defined phases, observable goals, and structured feedback loops surfaces problems early (week-1 pulse) rather than at attrition. SHRM data links formal onboarding to 82% higher retention at year one.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Standing up a repeatable onboarding program for the first time (replacing tribal knowledge).</item>
        <item>Hiring velocity of one or more hires per week where ad-hoc approaches diverge.</item>
        <item>Rolling out remote-first onboarding where in-office Day-1 rituals do not translate.</item>
        <item>After a 90-day-retention drop or new-hire eNPS decline.</item>
        <item>M&amp;A integration requiring two onboarding cultures to converge.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>One or two hires per year — a checklist suffices; a full program is not worth the maintenance.</item>
        <item>C-suite or executive onboarding — bespoke, board-driven; this framework does not apply.</item>
        <item>Contractor or agency placements under 90 days — limit to access provisioning and safety.</item>
        <item>Crisis backfills replacing a critical departure — collapse into knowledge transfer, not program onboarding.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="program-components">
      <p>Eight components of a repeatable new-hire onboarding program with scope and agent-workflow notes for each.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Move all paperwork, equipment shipping, and account provisioning to preboarding; Day 1 must be reserved for human connection, not e-signatures.</statement>
        <rationale>New hires who spend Day 1 on HR paperwork report lower engagement and higher anxiety. Every administrative task completed before Day 1 reduces cognitive load on the highest-anxiety workday.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Preboarding timeline: send welcome email and next-steps on offer signing; ship equipment 2 weeks before; send schedule and team-intro email 1 week before; send reminder and point-of-contact day before.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Day 1 agenda must prioritize welcome and buddy introduction in the first hour; IT setup and paperwork follow only after the human connection is established.</statement>
        <rationale>First impressions of belonging predict 90-day retention more than tool access. Reversing the order (IT first) signals that the organization values compliance over people.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Suggested Day 1 flow: 9:00 welcome and buddy intro, 9:30 HR paperwork and benefits, 10:30 IT setup, 12:00 team lunch, 13:30 company overview and culture, 15:00 manager 1:1 on expectations, 16:00 self-paced onboarding.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Assign a buddy who is peer-level and on a different reporting line from the manager; duration 90 days minimum with weekly check-ins in month 1.</statement>
        <rationale>A manager-chosen buddy from the same chain of command replicates the manager relationship rather than providing the independent, informal channel that predicts new-hire integration.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Buddy scope: culture and unwritten rules, navigating the organization, introducing cross-functional contacts. Not a second manager; the buddy does not evaluate performance.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Each onboarding phase must end with an observable artifact; never accept "understands X" or "is familiar with Y" as a milestone completion criterion.</statement>
        <rationale>Vague verbs like "understand" cannot be verified at the day-30 review; observable artifacts (PR merged, doc written, customer call completed) can.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Phase structure: days 1-30 learn (context, relationships, tools); days 31-60 contribute (first owned project); days 61-90 execute (independent delivery).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Run a 4-question pulse survey at week 1, detailed survey at day 30, check-in conversation at day 60, and full review including eNPS at day 90.</statement>
        <rationale>Rising attrition shows up in week-1 pulse data first. Waiting for the day-30 survey means losing 3 weeks of correction opportunity.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Core feedback questions: Did you feel welcomed? Was your role clear? Did you have the tools you needed? How could we improve? Keep week-1 survey to 4 questions maximum.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Train managers on the onboarding timeline and their specific actions at each milestone before the hire's first day; unprepared managers are the leading cause of poor onboarding outcomes.</statement>
        <rationale>Manager preparation (workspace set up, 1:1 schedule, expectations documented) is the variable most correlated with new-hire engagement at day 30 (Gallup).</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>For remote hires: ship laptop pre-imaged before Day 1, default Day 1 to async-plus-one-synchronous-session, and over-communicate using multiple channels.</statement>
        <rationale>Remote hires who don't receive equipment before Day 1 spend their first week without tools; the resulting frustration is disproportionate to the logistics cost of early shipping.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Remote-specific risks: isolation (mitigate with virtual coffee and buddy program), culture invisibility (explicit culture sessions and documentation), connection failure (virtual team activities in week 1).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Spread compliance modules (security, harassment, GDPR, SOC 2) across days 5-30; never schedule them all on Day 1.</statement>
        <rationale>Compliance overload on Day 1 crowds out role learning and culture absorption — the two inputs that actually predict ramp speed and retention.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <reference path="templates/preboard-gate.py">Run 5 days before start to verify all 7 preboarding conditions are GREEN before sending the welcome email.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="checklist">
      <p>Verifiable action items for each onboarding phase from before Day 1 through month 1, with completion criteria.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>All seven preboarding items must be complete before sending the Day-1 schedule to the new hire.</statement>
        <rationale>Sending a Day-1 schedule when equipment has not shipped or accounts are not provisioned sets up a failed first day and damages trust in the organization.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Before Day 1 checklist:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Equipment ordered and confirmed shipped with tracking number.</item>
        <item>Email, Slack, and primary tools accounts created and verified.</item>
        <item>Welcome email sent with first-week schedule and point-of-contact name.</item>
        <item>Team notified of start date, role, and brief intro bio.</item>
        <item>Buddy assigned and briefed on scope and first-week check-in date.</item>
        <item>Benefits enrollment instructions sent.</item>
        <item>Manager has blocked calendar for Day-1 1:1 and week-1 daily check-ins.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Day 1 checklist:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Warm welcome from team within first 30 minutes.</item>
        <item>IT setup verified complete (laptop on, tools accessible).</item>
        <item>Paperwork and benefit enrollment signed.</item>
        <item>Manager 1:1 completed: expectations discussed, first project scope shared.</item>
        <item>Introduction to buddy completed.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Week 1 checklist:</p>
      <list>
        <item>All recurring key meetings (standups, 1:1s, team syncs) added to calendar.</item>
        <item>Access to all required systems verified by the new hire.</item>
        <item>Training modules assigned with completion dates.</item>
        <item>Week-1 pulse survey sent (4 questions, anonymous).</item>
        <item>Introduction to key stakeholders outside immediate team completed.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Month 1 checklist:</p>
      <list>
        <item>30-day check-in completed with manager; goals for days 31-60 documented.</item>
        <item>Feedback collected and blockers addressed.</item>
        <item>Day-30 detailed onboarding survey sent.</item>
        <item>Buddy check-in: confirm buddy program is active and useful.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>30-day goals must be documented in a shared artifact before the check-in closes; verbal agreements decay within a week.</statement>
        <rationale>Undocumented goals cannot be referenced at the day-60 review; the hire enters phase 2 without a written contract of what success looks like.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Documentation-as-onboarding: assigning a new hire a reading list without synchronous context.</description>
        <reason>New hires do not read documentation as a primary learning mode; it is a reference, not an onboarding mechanism. An agent piping docs is a worse experience than a human explanation.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Buddy program with no check-in cadence or scope definition.</description>
        <reason>Buddy relationships degrade silently when buddies stop checking in; without a scheduled first meeting and defined scope, the buddy becomes a name on a form.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <p>Limitations and failure modes: 30-60-90 plans default to "learn / contribute / execute" but verbs are too generic to gate progress — require observable artifacts. Buddy programs degrade silently when buddies stop checking in; agents can monitor but cannot repair relationships. Documentation-as-onboarding fails — new hires don't read it; agent piping docs is worse, not better. Cultural transmission resists templating: values, unwritten rules, "how we disagree", "when to escalate" are invisible to checklists. Compliance training overload in week 1 crowds out role learning and culture absorption. Auto-generated 30-60-90 goals miss manager's real expectations and become aspirational fiction.</p>

      <p>Remote-first onboarding risks and mitigations: isolation (pair with virtual coffee scheduling and active buddy program), culture invisibility (explicit culture sessions and documentation), connection failures (virtual team activities in week 1, point-of-contact responsiveness SLA). Pre-image and ship laptops before Day 1 for remote hires; default Day 1 to async-plus-one synchronous session. Over-communicate across Slack, email, calendar, and video.</p>

      <p>Tools and service integration: BambooHR (SMB default; onboarding tasks first-class), Rippling (best end-to-end provisioning for agents), HiBob (strong workflows; clean API), Sapling (onboarding-specialist; webhook-rich), WorkBright (I-9/paperwork compliance), Lattice/15Five (30-60-90 + check-ins built-in), Donut for Slack (buddy pairing automation), Loom (async welcome videos), Notion/Confluence (de-facto wiki). Okta/Azure AD/JumpCloud for provisioning, Jamf/Kandji for zero-touch laptops. Greenhouse Onboarding bridges ATS→onboarding without re-keying.</p>

      <reference path="templates/preboard-gate.py">Automated gate: run 5 days before start; blocks welcome email if any item is RED.</reference>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/preboard-gate.py" purpose="Preboarding readiness checker: validates 7 conditions 5 days before start date; outputs GREEN/RED with blocking items."/>
    </templates>

    <checklist>
      <check>Preboarding readiness gate run 5 days before start; all 7 conditions GREEN before Day-1 schedule sent.</check>
      <check>Equipment ordered and shipping confirmed with tracking; shipped 2 weeks before start date.</check>
      <check>Accounts (email, Slack, tools) created, verified, and configured before Day 1.</check>
      <check>Welcome email sent on offer signing; includes first-week schedule and point-of-contact.</check>
      <check>Buddy assigned, peer-level, on different reporting line, briefed on 90-day scope with weekly check-in calendar.</check>
      <check>Manager calendar blocked for Day-1 1:1 and daily week-1 check-ins before hire's first day.</check>
      <check>Day 1 flow prioritizes welcome/buddy introduction first hour; IT setup after human connection.</check>
      <check>Week-1 pulse survey (4 questions max) sent by end of week 1; results reviewed by manager + buddy.</check>
      <check>Day-30 check-in: goals for days 31-60 documented in shared artifact, not verbal.</check>
      <check>Feedback loops running: week-1 pulse, day-30 survey, day-60 check-in, day-90 eNPS review.</check>
      <check>Compliance training spread across days 5-30; never all on Day 1.</check>
    </checklist>

    <note>Agentic workflow: drive as six-stage pipeline owned by `faion-onboarding-agent`. Stage 1 (preboarding, Sonnet) — kickoff equipment/accounts/welcome. Stage 2 (Day 1 plan, Sonnet) — personalized agenda. Stage 3 (30-60-90 draft, Opus) — combines JD + level + team OKRs into observable goals; manager edits before sending. Stage 4 (cadence reminders, Haiku) — nudges manager/buddy/hire at milestones. Stage 5 (feedback collection, Sonnet) — pulse surveys with coded text analysis. Stage 6 (analytics, Opus) — quarterly cohort review on attrition, ramp metrics. Mandatory human loop on every plan and survey deployment.</note>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.shrm.org/"/>
      <link href="https://www.gallup.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
