<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Statistical Significance: Application Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Statistical Significance: Application` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="require-raw-counts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Analysis MUST use raw counts (n1, x1, n2, x2). Headline percentages alone are forbidden — they hide sample size + variance.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practical Statistics for Data Scientists; experiment-design corpus">5% vs 6% sounds meaningful but at n=20 each it&apos;s noise. Raw counts let validator compute correct confidence interval; percentages do not.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="pre-committed-sample-size" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sample size for each arm MUST be pre-committed via power analysis. Stopping early based on direction is forbidden (peeking inflates Type I error).</statement>
      <rationale source="Sequential testing literature; Optimizely / Eppo guides">Peeking 5 times during a test doubles the actual alpha rate; &apos;significance&apos; at week 1 reverses by week 4. Pre-committed sample size is the only honest answer.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="declare-mde-pre-test" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Minimum detectable effect (MDE) MUST be declared pre-test. Without MDE, an &apos;inconclusive&apos; result can&apos;t distinguish &apos;no effect&apos; from &apos;underpowered&apos;.</statement>
      <rationale source="Statistics for A/B Testing — Georgi Georgiev; Eppo docs">Without MDE, a null result is meaningless. With MDE you can say &apos;we can rule out an effect &gt;= X%&apos; which is actionable; without it you can only shrug.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="two-sided-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default significance test MUST be two-sided. One-sided is allowed only with pre-registered directional hypothesis + sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="frequentist testing convention; FDA pharma guidance applied">One-sided tests halve the p-value for free — easy to abuse for &apos;significance&apos;. Two-sided is the honest default; one-sided requires explicit pre-registration.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="report-confidence-interval" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Report MUST include 95% confidence interval on the effect estimate, not just p-value. CI shows the practical magnitude; p-value alone is a yes/no with no size info.</statement>
      <rationale source="American Statistical Association p-value statement 2016">p&lt;0.05 with CI [+0.1%, +0.2%] is statistically real but practically nothing. p&lt;0.05 with CI [+5%, +25%] is meaningfully positive. Without CI, decision-maker can&apos;t distinguish.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
