<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Workflow Design Phase Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every workflow-design-phase application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-spec-accepted" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The design phase MUST NOT begin until spec.md frontmatter shows `status: Accepted`. Designing against a Draft spec wastes tokens on decisions that will be re-litigated. The Accepted gate is the human checkpoint protecting the design budget.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD spec-design hand-off research">Drafts churn; Accepted specs don't. Starting design on a Draft is the single largest source of wasted SDD effort.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-ad-x-rejected-alternatives" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every AD-X (Architectural Decision) MUST include: (1) the chosen option, (2) at least one rejected alternative with explicit rejection reason, (3) the FR-X / NFR-X requirement it satisfies, (4) the trade-off it accepts. AD records with no rejected alternative are forbidden — they hide the actual decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nygard ADRs, ATAM literature">The value of an ADR is the rejected alternative + rationale. Without those, the record is a status update, not a decision.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-survey-before-decide" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The design MUST cite at least 3 existing-codebase patterns it follows (or breaks with rationale). Designs that ignore the existing codebase produce drift; the survey step is non-skippable. Grep/Glob output alone is insufficient — at least one Read of an existing implementation is required per cited pattern.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD pattern-drift audit, Conway's Law research">Greenfield designs in a brownfield codebase create maintenance debt within one sprint. Survey forces alignment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-fr-coverage-complete" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every FR-X from spec.md MUST be addressed by at least one AD-X in design.md. Coverage gaps (FRs with no AD trace) MUST be flagged before promoting design to Accepted. Silent drops are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD traceability research">Untraced FRs become forgotten requirements that surface as user-reported regressions post-ship. Explicit coverage map is the only way to catch them pre-execution.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-file-table-actionable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The file table MUST list every file the design will touch with action ∈ {CREATE, MODIFY, DELETE} and a one-sentence scope. Vague entries ("various files", placeholder strings) are forbidden. The file table is the input contract for `writing-implementation-plans`.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD wave-planning data">Implementation plans built from vague file tables produce vague tasks; vague tasks produce broken merges. Concrete file table = predictable execution.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-00 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
