<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-design-doc-workflow" title="Writing Design Documents: Step-by-Step Workflow">
  <summary>11-phase procedure for writing design.md from approved spec through reviewer approval, with agent-specific instructions for each phase.</summary>

  <section title="Prerequisites">
    <rule>
      <statement>Verify spec.md status is Approved before starting any design work; design on a Draft spec produces decisions based on shifting requirements.</statement>
      <rationale>FR-X IDs must be stable before design starts. A spec revision after design is begun invalidates the coverage matrix and requires a full redesign of the FR → AD-X mapping.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>spec.md exists with status: Approved</item>
      <item>constitution.md exists at .aidocs/constitution.md</item>
      <item>contracts.md exists (for API features — reference it, never redefine endpoints in design)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 1-3: Extract and Research">
    <list>
      <item>Phase 1 (Read Spec): extract all FR-X, NFR-X, user stories, out-of-scope, preliminary data models</item>
      <item>Phase 2 (Read Constitution): extract architecture patterns, code standards, testing requirements</item>
      <item>Phase 3 (Read Contracts): reference contracts.md for API endpoints — do not redefine them in design.md</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run codebase research as a separate subagent call before making AD decisions — mixing discovery and decision-making in one pass produces worse decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Research and decision-making use different cognitive modes. A research agent reports findings without committing to approaches; a decision agent receives complete findings and evaluates options. Merging these phases produces decisions made with incomplete information.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Phase 4 (Research Codebase): use Grep/Glob to find similar models, services, views, existing patterns; determine reusable components and code placement</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 5-7: Architecture and Technical Approach">
    <list>
      <item>Phase 5 (AD-X): for each key decision — define context, list 2+ alternatives with pros/cons, choose, document rationale</item>
      <item>Phase 6 (Technical Approach): components, data flow (inputs → transformations → outputs), file change list (CREATE/MODIFY)</item>
      <item>Phase 7 (Testing Strategy): unit test targets, integration test flows, test data/fixtures, quality gate coverage targets</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Write the file change table after AD-X entries, not before; files are derived from decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>File tables written before decisions include speculative files not justified by any FR. Every file in the table must be explainable by an AD-X decision that implements a specific FR.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Phases 8-11: Risks, Review, Save">
    <list>
      <item>Phase 8 (Risks): for each risk — description, impact (High/Med/Low), mitigation strategy (concrete action)</item>
      <item>Phase 9 (User Review): present AD-X alternatives and technical approach — human checkpoint, cannot be automated</item>
      <item>Phase 10 (Agent Review): call faion-sdd-reviewer-agent (mode: design) — checks FR coverage, AD structure, constitution compliance</item>
      <item>Phase 11 (Save): write to {feature_path}/design.md with status: Review (human sets to Approved)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
