<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-copywriting-fundamentals">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>content-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Learnable persuasion framework for writing copy that converts: know your audience through Voice of Customer research, apply proven formulas (AIDA/PAS/BAB/4Ps), write headlines first (80% of effectiveness), translate features to benefits, handle objections, and drive one clear CTA. Core rule: write 10 headline variants minimum before selecting one.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>copywriting</tag>
      <tag>persuasion</tag>
      <tag>headlines</tag>
      <tag>landing-pages</tag>
      <tag>conversion</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Copywriting Fundamentals</title>
    <summary>A learnable persuasion framework for writing copy that converts: know your audience through Voice of Customer research, apply a proven formula (AIDA/PAS/BAB/4Ps), write headlines first (80% of effectiveness), translate features to benefits, handle objections, and drive one clear CTA. The core rule: write 10 headline variants minimum before selecting one — the first headline is almost never the best.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Most product copy fails because it describes features rather than outcomes. Readers process copy in under 3 seconds at the headline; if it doesn't signal a direct benefit, they leave. VoC research (customer reviews, support tickets, Reddit) extracts the exact language the audience already uses — mirroring that language in headlines and body copy consistently lifts conversion rates by removing the "this isn't for me" filter.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Writing or rewriting landing page copy (hero, benefits, CTA, objection handling)</item>
        <item>Drafting email subject lines, ad copy, or social posts at scale</item>
        <item>Converting feature lists into benefit-oriented messaging</item>
        <item>Extracting VoC language patterns from customer reviews for copy</item>
        <item>Applying a specific formula (AIDA, PAS, BAB) to a defined content piece</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Brand voice is undefined — copy frameworks produce generic output without documented tone</item>
        <item>Highly regulated content (pharma, legal, financial advice) — legal review required first</item>
        <item>Target audience research is incomplete — formulas applied to wrong ICP produce polished but ineffective copy</item>
        <item>Long-form editorial content — copywriting frameworks are for persuasion, not journalism</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="formulas-and-headlines">
      <section title="Pre-Writing Rule">
        <rule>
          <statement>Conduct Voice of Customer research before writing any copy; document exact phrases customers use in reviews, support tickets, and Reddit before starting.</statement>
          <rationale>VoC language mirrors the audience's own words back to them, eliminating the "this isn't for me" filter. Copy written without VoC data defaults to internal product language that audiences cannot relate to.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Customer interviews: direct quotes about pain points and desired outcomes</item>
          <item>Support tickets: exact language of frustrations and blockers</item>
          <item>Reviews (yours + competitors): phrases like "I wish...", "My biggest frustration is...", "What I really need is..."</item>
          <item>Reddit and forums: unfiltered audience language in niche communities</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section title="Core Formulas">
        <rule>
          <statement>Choose one formula per copy piece; mixing formulas in the same piece produces confusing structure.</statement>
          <rationale>Each formula creates a specific emotional journey. Mixing them breaks the reader's logical flow and reduces conversion.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>AIDA: Attention (headline) → Interest (relevance hook) → Desire (benefits) → Action (CTA) — classic, works for most contexts</item>
          <item>PAS: Problem (state the pain) → Agitate (amplify emotional impact) → Solution (introduce product) — best for high-pain ICP</item>
          <item>4Ps: Promise (what you'll deliver) → Picture (paint the future state) → Proof (why to believe) → Push (drive to action)</item>
          <item>BAB: Before (current painful state) → After (desired future state) → Bridge (your product bridges the gap) — best for transformation stories</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section title="Headlines">
        <rule>
          <statement>Write 10 headline variants minimum before selecting one; the first headline is almost never the best.</statement>
          <rationale>Headlines determine 80% of copy effectiveness. The first version is a warm-up; versions 6-10 typically produce 2-3x more specific and compelling options.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>How to [Benefit]: "How to Write Copy That Converts"</item>
          <item>[Number] Ways to [Result]: "7 Ways to Double Your Signups"</item>
          <item>The Secret to [Outcome]: "The Secret to Landing Page Success"</item>
          <item>[Question]?: "Struggling to Get Customers?"</item>
          <item>Why [Surprising Claim]: "Why Your Best Copy Gets Ignored"</item>
          <item>[Result] Without [Pain]: "Get Customers Without Cold Calling"</item>
          <item>[Result] in [Timeframe]: "Double Revenue in 90 Days"</item>
          <item>Stop [Problem]: "Stop Losing Visitors at Checkout"</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section title="Power Words">
        <list>
          <item>Urgency: Now, today, immediately, limited, expires</item>
          <item>Exclusivity: Secret, insider, members-only, private</item>
          <item>Trust: Proven, guaranteed, tested, verified</item>
          <item>Ease: Simple, quick, easy, effortless, in minutes</item>
          <item>Results: Transform, unlock, discover, achieve</item>
          <item>Emotion: Imagine, feel, experience, picture yourself</item>
        </list>
        <rule>
          <statement>Ban generic power words ("revolutionary," "game-changing," "cutting-edge") explicitly in agent prompts.</statement>
          <rationale>LLMs trained on marketing copy default to these clichés. Explicit banning produces more specific and credible language.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
      <section title="Readability Targets">
        <list>
          <item>Reading level: 6th-8th grade (Flesch-Kincaid)</item>
          <item>Sentence length: under 20 words maximum</item>
          <item>Paragraph length: under 4 sentences</item>
          <item>"You" vs "We" ratio: 2:1 in favor of "you"</item>
          <item>Active voice: 90%+ of sentences</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="benefits-and-cta">
      <section title="Feature-to-Benefit Translation">
        <rule>
          <statement>Apply the "Feature → So what? → Benefit" formula to every product feature before writing any copy.</statement>
          <rationale>Features describe the product; benefits describe what the customer gets. Readers process "what's in it for me" — features alone do not answer that question.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <example type="good" title="Feature translation examples">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
256-bit encryption → So what? → Your data is bank-level secure
AI-powered → So what? → Get answers in seconds, not hours
Cloud-based → So what? → Access from anywhere, no setup required
24/7 support → So what? → Help whenever you need it, not just business hours
          ]]></code>
        </example>
        <example type="bad" title="Feature-only copy that fails to connect">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Our software uses advanced AI algorithms to analyze your marketing data
and provide insights through a customizable dashboard with real-time updates."
          ]]></code>
        </example>
        <example type="good" title="Benefit-first rewrite of the same product">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Stop guessing which marketing works.
Get clear answers in 60 seconds.
No spreadsheets. No analyst needed."
          ]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section title="Objection Handling">
        <rule>
          <statement>Address the top 3-5 objections explicitly in copy; never assume the reader will overcome objections on their own.</statement>
          <rationale>Unaddressed objections are silent conversion killers. Readers leave rather than email questions. Anticipating objections in copy removes the blocker at the point of decision.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>"Too expensive" → Show ROI, compare cost to the alternative (doing it manually, the competitor)</item>
          <item>"Don't have time" → Quantify time saved ("15 minutes, not 3 hours")</item>
          <item>"Not sure it'll work" → Testimonials, case studies with specific numbers</item>
          <item>"Not for me" → Address their specific role and situation directly</item>
          <item>"Can I trust you?" → Social proof, money-back guarantee, number of customers</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section title="CTA Best Practices">
        <rule>
          <statement>Every piece of copy must have exactly one CTA; multiple CTAs reduce conversion by creating decision paralysis.</statement>
          <rationale>Each additional call to action reduces the probability of any action being taken. One CTA maintains focus on the single desired outcome.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Write the CTA button text before writing the body copy; it forces clarity about what action you are driving.</statement>
          <rationale>Knowing the end action shapes the entire copy arc. Writing body copy first often leads to CTAs that do not match the content's actual offer.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Start with an action verb: "Get", "Start", "Claim", "Download", "Join"</item>
          <item>Be specific: "Start My 14-Day Trial" not "Submit"</item>
          <item>Include a benefit hint: "Get My Free Guide" not "Click Here"</item>
          <item>Reduce perceived commitment: "See How It Works" before "Buy Now"</item>
        </list>
        <example type="good" title="Weak vs strong CTA comparison">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Submit → Get My Free Guide
Click Here → Start My 14-Day Trial
Sign Up → Create Your Account (Free)
Learn More → See How It Works
Buy Now → Get Instant Access
          ]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section title="Editing Checklist">
        <list>
          <item>Read aloud — awkward phrasing surfaces immediately</item>
          <item>Cut every word that does not add information (no filler)</item>
          <item>Simplify sentences — break any sentence over 20 words into two</item>
          <item>Check "you" vs "we" ratio — target 2:1 in favor of "you"</item>
          <item>Verify one idea per paragraph — split if two ideas appear</item>
        </list>
        <reference path="templates/readability-check.py">Python script to score copy with textstat (Flesch, Fog, sentence length)</reference>
        <reference path="templates/landing-page-copy.txt">Landing page structure from headline through risk reversal</reference>
        <reference path="templates/email-copy.txt">Email copy structure with subject, hook, benefits, CTA, P.S.</reference>
      </section>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/landing-page-copy.txt" purpose="Landing page structure: headline through risk reversal"/>
      <template path="templates/email-copy.txt" purpose="Email copy structure with subject, hook, benefits, CTA, P.S."/>
      <template path="templates/readability-check.py" purpose="Python script to score copy with textstat (Flesch, Fog, sentence length)"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.copyblogger.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.awai.com/writing-resources/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
