<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="3Q Testimonial — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for the 3-question testimonial script and output integrity.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-three-questions" testable="true">
      <statement>The outreach MUST ask EXACTLY three questions in order: (Q1) What was your hesitation before working with me / buying X? (Q2) What changed once we / it delivered? (Q3) Who would you NOT recommend this to and why? More than 3 questions → reply rate drops 4-6× (Brain Audit cohort data).</statement>
      <rationale source="Sean D'Souza — The Brain Audit, Joanna Wiebe — Copyhackers">The 3-question structure produces the only emotionally credible testimonial: hesitation creates relatability, outcome creates payoff, anti-recommendation disarms generic praise. Skipping Q3 yields hollow quotes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-anti-recommend-disarming" testable="true">
      <statement>Q3 ("who would you NOT recommend this to") must be retained verbatim. It is the disarmer. Replacing with "any feedback?" loses the entire credibility mechanic.</statement>
      <rationale source="Joanna Wiebe — Copyhackers testimonial research">Testimonials with an anti-recommendation perform 30-45% higher in landing-page A/B tests because the prospect's "this sounds too good to be true" defence is pre-empted.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-verbatim-preservation" testable="true">
      <statement>Output testimonial body MUST be verbatim quoted from customer reply. Allowed edits: trim length, remove filler words ("um", "you know", "like"), fix typos. Forbidden: rewrite for clarity, add adjectives, paraphrase.</statement>
      <rationale source="FTC Endorsement Guides 16 CFR §255">Rewritten testimonials violate FTC endorsement guidelines. Even outside the US, rewritten quotes lose authentic voice the prospect can detect.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-explicit-consent" testable="true">
      <statement>Output must include `consent: granted` ONLY if customer's reply contains an explicit consent token (e.g. "you can use this", "feel free to share", "yes go ahead"). Implicit / silent consent is INSUFFICIENT.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 6 + 7 / FTC Endorsement Guides">Implicit consent fails the GDPR lawful-basis test and the FTC honest-endorsement test. Operator publishes only with `consent: granted`.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-metric-or-discard" testable="true">
      <statement>Output must include at least one numeric or temporal metric from the customer's reply (e.g. "$8k revenue in week 1", "3× faster", "saved 6 hours/week"). If no metric exists, downgrade testimonial to "qualitative quote only" and surface a follow-up to ask for one.</statement>
      <rationale source="Conversion-rate cohort data (Nielsen Norman, Unbounce)">Testimonials with a number convert 2-3× higher. Metric-free testimonials feed brand warmth but not conversion.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="The 3-question outreach template">

    <example type="good" title="Outreach email (verbatim per r1)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Subject: 3 quick questions about working together

Hey {first_name},

Now that {milestone_or_handover} is done, I'd love to hear how it
went. Three quick questions — feel free to answer in 1-2 lines each:

1. Before we started, what was your hesitation about hiring
   someone for this?
2. What happened once we delivered that made the engagement
   worth it (a number or moment is gold)?
3. Who would you NOT recommend me to and why?

If you're OK sharing the reply on my site, please add
"yes, you can quote me" at the end.

Thanks — and I'll keep you posted on what I do with the answers.
{operator_first_name}
      ]]></code>
      <note>Q3 stays as-is. Operator never sanitises Q3 to "any feedback".</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Generic ask (r1 violation)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Hi! Could you write a quick testimonial for my site? Maybe
2-3 sentences on how working together was?"

Reply rate ~10%. Replies are generic ("great experience, very
professional, would recommend") — useless for landing pages.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1+r2 violation — the operator gets praise but loses the credibility mechanic.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
