<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Communications Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Communications Management. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="matrix-per-stakeholder" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each stakeholder group MUST have its own row in the communications matrix specifying artefact, channel, owner, cadence, and format.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Stakeholder Performance Domain">Stakeholder-agnostic comms produce a blast to all; the wrong people get the wrong artefacts at the wrong cadence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="decision-log-immutable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decisions MUST be appended to an immutable decision log with id, date, decision, options-considered, rationale, and decider.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Project Documentation">Without an immutable log, decisions re-litigate forever; new joiners can't reconstruct project history.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="status-report-cadence-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Status reports MUST be issued on a fixed published cadence (weekly / biweekly / monthly). Ad-hoc reporting is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ITIL Service Communications">Variable cadence trains stakeholders to ignore reports; fixed cadence makes silence informative.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="meeting-with-decision-or-skip" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every meeting MUST have at least one decision or a 'no decision needed' note in the minutes. Meetings without decisions trigger a cadence review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion meetings audit 2026">Decision-free meetings burn calendar without output; the rule forces either decisions or cadence reduction.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="escalation-path-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each communication channel MUST have a named escalation path: who is contacted when the primary owner doesn't respond within the SLA window.</statement>
      <rationale source="PRINCE2 Communications Strategy">Unnamed escalation means contributors choose ad-hoc paths; quiet failures compound.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Communications Management fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Communications Management outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
