<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Feedback Loop Customer Reply Templates Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Feedback Loop Customer Reply Templates application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="five-templates-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All replies MUST come from exactly five templates: acknowledge, build, waitlist, decline, bug. Other shapes route to manual review, not custom replies.</statement>
      <rationale source="Template-discipline research">Template-discipline research — anchors Feedback Loop Customer Reply Templates rule `five-templates-only`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="reply-within-72h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every ticket MUST receive a reply within 72h of creation. Beyond 72h = customer assumes the channel is dead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer-feedback research">Customer-feedback research — anchors Feedback Loop Customer Reply Templates rule `reply-within-72h`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="internal-tag-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every reply MUST stamp the internal tag (build / waitlist / decline / bug / clarify) before sending. Untagged tickets break reporting.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tagging-discipline practice">Tagging-discipline practice — anchors Feedback Loop Customer Reply Templates rule `internal-tag-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="decline-cites-anti-roadmap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decline replies MUST cite the relevant anti-roadmap entry by id. Bare &apos;we won&apos;t build this&apos; replies invite re-litigation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stakeholder-management research">Stakeholder-management research — anchors Feedback Loop Customer Reply Templates rule `decline-cites-anti-roadmap`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="waitlist-links-smoke-page" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Waitlist replies MUST link to a smoke page or signup form so demand is captured + visible. Pure email waitlists hide the signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Demand-tracking research">Demand-tracking research — anchors Feedback Loop Customer Reply Templates rule `waitlist-links-smoke-page`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
