<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Growth SEO Link Building Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5+ testable rules every Growth SEO Link Building application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-create-content-that" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Create content that journalists and bloggers need but that doesn't yet exist or is outdated — this is the only reliably scalable link magnet formula.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generic content earns generic results. Link magnets are assets people reference repeatedly: original data, free tools, comprehensive guides, industry benchmarks. Without a genuinely link-worthy asset, outreach volume cannot compensate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-build-a-prospect" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build a prospect list of 100+ sites before starting outreach — quality and volume both matter.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Response rates average 10-20%; link acquisition rate averages 5-10%. Starting with fewer than 100 prospects produces statistically insignificant results and cannot reveal which tactics work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-personalize-every-outreach" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Personalize every outreach email — generic emails are ignored at rates above 90%.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Outreach recipients receive dozens of generic link requests daily. A personalized first line referencing specific content they published signals genuine effort and increases response rates from ~2% (generic) to ~15-20% (personalized).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-follow-up-exactly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Follow up exactly once, 7 days after the initial send — never follow up more than once.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A single follow-up recovers responses from busy recipients who missed the first email. Multiple follow-ups damage relationship and sender reputation without proportional benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-audit-internal-links" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit internal links monthly: link new posts to relevant old content, update old posts to link to new content, build pillar-cluster structures with keyword-rich anchors.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Internal links are the highest-ROI link building tactic — zero outreach effort, immediate implementation, direct PageRank distribution, and visible ranking improvements within weeks not months.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-28 chunk-02 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
