<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Link Building Framework">
  <summary>Value-first link building: create link-worthy content, identify prospects, conduct personalized outreach, track and iterate.</summary>

  <section title="Content Types by Link Potential">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create content that journalists and bloggers need but that doesn't yet exist or is outdated — this is the only reliably scalable link magnet formula.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic content earns generic results. Link magnets are assets people reference repeatedly: original data, free tools, comprehensive guides, industry benchmarks. Without a genuinely link-worthy asset, outreach volume cannot compensate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Original research / surveys: Very High link potential</item>
      <item>Free interactive tools / calculators: Very High link potential</item>
      <item>Industry benchmarks with data: Very High link potential</item>
      <item>Ultimate / comprehensive guides: High link potential</item>
      <item>Expert roundups: Medium link potential</item>
      <item>Case studies with real data: Medium link potential</item>
      <item>Original graphics / infographics: Medium link potential</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Prospecting Methods">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build a prospect list of 100+ sites before starting outreach — quality and volume both matter.</statement>
      <rationale>Response rates average 10-20%; link acquisition rate averages 5-10%. Starting with fewer than 100 prospects produces statistically insignificant results and cannot reveal which tactics work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Competitor backlink analysis (Ahrefs): who links to competing content</item>
      <item>Resource page search: "[topic] + resources" / "[topic] + useful links"</item>
      <item>Broken link building: find broken links, offer replacement</item>
      <item>HARO / Qwoted: respond to journalist queries (High quality, inbound)</item>
      <item>Unlinked brand mentions: find mentions without links, request attribution</item>
      <item>Skyscraper technique: find linked content, create superior version</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Outreach Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Personalize every outreach email — generic emails are ignored at rates above 90%.</statement>
      <rationale>Outreach recipients receive dozens of generic link requests daily. A personalized first line referencing specific content they published signals genuine effort and increases response rates from ~2% (generic) to ~15-20% (personalized).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow up exactly once, 7 days after the initial send — never follow up more than once.</statement>
      <rationale>A single follow-up recovers responses from busy recipients who missed the first email. Multiple follow-ups damage relationship and sender reputation without proportional benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Send volume: 50 emails per day maximum to protect sender reputation</item>
      <item>Personalization: read 2-3 recent articles, reference specific content in first line</item>
      <item>Value framing: explain why linking benefits THEIR audience, not just you</item>
      <item>Easy ask: provide direct link, short description, specific reason to include</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Internal Linking">
    <rule>
      <statement>Audit internal links monthly: link new posts to relevant old content, update old posts to link to new content, build pillar-cluster structures with keyword-rich anchors.</statement>
      <rationale>Internal links are the highest-ROI link building tactic — zero outreach effort, immediate implementation, direct PageRank distribution, and visible ranking improvements within weeks not months.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Target Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Response rate: 10% = good, 20%+ = great</item>
      <item>Link acquisition rate: 5% = good, 10%+ = great</item>
      <item>Average DR of new links: 40+ = good, 60+ = great</item>
      <item>New referring domains per month: 5+ = good, 20+ = great</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Buying links or using private blog networks (PBNs)</description>
    <reason>Google manual and algorithmic penalties — site-wide ranking loss that can take months to recover from. The short-term ranking boost is not worth the existential risk.</reason>
  </antipattern>
  <antipattern>
    <description>Sending generic outreach at scale without personalization</description>
    <reason>Response rates drop below 2%, burning prospect lists and sender domain reputation simultaneously.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <reference path="templates/outreach-templates.txt">Personalized email templates for resource pages, broken links, guest posts</reference>
  <reference path="templates/campaign-tracker.md">Campaign tracking template with metrics and weekly process</reference>
</text>
