<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="plg-implementation-guide">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>conversion-optimizer</domain>
    <summary>A 5-phase sequential implementation roadmap for operationalizing a PLG model: Foundation, Free Tier Design, Activation Optimization, Monetization, and Expansion.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>plg</tag>
      <tag>implementation</tag>
      <tag>playbooks</tag>
      <tag>aha-moment</tag>
      <tag>pql</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>plg</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>PLG Implementation Guide</title>
    <summary>A 5-phase sequential implementation roadmap for operationalizing a PLG model: (1) Foundation — define Aha moment and measure TTV; (2) Free Tier Design — limits, upgrade triggers, self-serve checkout; (3) Activation Optimization — onboarding, templates, TTV under 5 minutes; (4) Monetization — PQL scoring, upgrade prompts, automated playbooks; (5) Expansion — seat/usage triggers, expansion revenue tracking. Run phases in order — each depends on prior instrumentation.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>PLG strategy without an implementation plan produces incomplete funnels: Aha moment defined but not instrumented, upgrade triggers built without PQL scoring, expansion playbooks running before activation is optimized. This guide maps the strategy (plg-basics) and tactics (plg-optimization-tactics) to engineering tickets across 5 sequential phases with concrete playbooks for freemium-to-paid, trial-to-paid, and expansion.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Operationalizing a PLG model after plg-basics selected one.</item>
        <item>Producing a phased rollout plan that maps to engineering tickets.</item>
        <item>Running freemium-to-paid, trial-to-paid, or expansion playbooks as deterministic Day-N sequences.</item>
        <item>Selecting and justifying the PLG tech stack (analytics, onboarding, billing, PQL scoring).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>High-level PLG model choice — route to plg-basics.</item>
        <item>Stage-specific tactic catalog — route to plg-optimization-tactics.</item>
        <item>Metric definitions and PQL math — route to plg-metrics.</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF teams without an Aha-moment hypothesis — running this checklist before PMF wastes engineering cycles.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Aha Moment Discovery, TTV Optimization, and 5-Phase Checklist">
      <section name="Aha Moment Discovery">
        <rule>
          <statement>Find the Aha moment using two methods: (1) behavioral correlation — find the action most correlated with Day-30 retention in converted vs churned cohorts, minimum 200 converted users; (2) qualitative validation — interview 5+ converted customers asking "when did you decide to pay?". Both must agree before treating the Aha event as validated.</statement>
          <rationale>Behavioral correlation alone overfits to noisy events. Qualitative interviews confirm causality vs coincidence. Requiring both methods reduces false Aha moment choices by ~60% vs cohort-only approaches.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Slack Aha: first message sent in a channel with teammates.</item>
          <item>Dropbox Aha: first file synced across two devices.</item>
          <item>Zoom Aha: first successful video call completed.</item>
          <item>Notion Aha: first page created and shared with a collaborator.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="TTV Reduction Tactics">
        <rule>
          <statement>Target TTV (time from signup to Aha moment) under 5 minutes. This requires: pre-configured demo state or sample data, social login option, skip option for all non-critical steps, and a single guided path to the core action.</statement>
          <rationale>TTV under 5 minutes is achievable only with templates or pre-seeded data — an empty product with a setup wizard is rarely under 15 minutes. Pre-seeding is an engineering requirement, not a UX recommendation.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Progressive onboarding (learn while doing): high impact.</item>
          <item>Pre-configured templates and example data: high impact.</item>
          <item>Interactive tutorial with guided first action: high impact.</item>
          <item>Social login (Google, GitHub): medium impact, removes password friction.</item>
          <item>Single-player mode (defer team features until solo value proven): medium impact.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="5-Phase Implementation Checklist">
        <p>Phase 1 — Foundation: define Aha moment, measure current TTV, map user journey to value, identify conversion triggers, set up product analytics.</p>
        <p>Phase 2 — Free Tier Design: choose PLG model, define free tier limits, create upgrade triggers, design self-serve checkout, build pricing page.</p>
        <p>Phase 3 — Activation Optimization: simplify signup to under 3 fields, create onboarding flow, add templates/examples, build interactive tutorial, reduce TTV to under 5 minutes.</p>
        <p>Phase 4 — Monetization: define PQL criteria, build PQL scoring (see plg-metrics), create upgrade prompts, set up automated email playbooks, add sales-assist for ACV above $1K/month.</p>
        <p>Phase 5 — Expansion: identify expansion triggers (seat growth, usage growth), build seat/usage upgrade flows, create upsell playbooks, track expansion revenue and net revenue retention.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="In-Product Upgrade Trigger Rules">
        <rule>
          <statement>Show upgrade triggers contextually at the moment of need: at 80% of limit consumption, when user attempts a gated feature, when team collaboration signal fires. Never show during first session, during a critical workflow, or more than once per session.</statement>
          <rationale>Contextual triggers convert at 3-5x time-based pop-ups. First-session prompts break trust before value is demonstrated.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>All upgrade trigger copy must reference the user's actual behavior ("You've created 4 of 5 projects") not generic upsell language ("Get more features").</statement>
          <rationale>Behavior-personalized copy converts at 2-3x generic copy in PLG upgrade prompt tests.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="Freemium-to-Paid, Trial-to-Paid, and Expansion Playbooks">
      <section name="Playbook 1: Freemium-to-Paid">
        <rule>
          <statement>Trigger the freemium-to-paid playbook at 80% of limit consumption (not 100%). All messages must queue with approved=False and require human review before send.</statement>
          <rationale>Triggering at 100% means the user has already hit a wall; at 80% the message feels helpful rather than punitive. Auto-sending campaigns without human review risks mis-sent mass communications.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Day 0: in-app limit notification — "You have 1 project remaining. Pro plan unlocks unlimited."</item>
          <item>Day 2: email if no action — value of upgrading + social proof from a similar company.</item>
          <item>Day 5: in-app reminder — remaining capacity with specific upgrade benefit.</item>
          <item>Day 7: email — time-limited discount offer (20% off first 3 months).</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Playbook 2: Trial-to-Paid">
        <list>
          <item>Trial Days 1-3 (Activation focus): welcome email with quickstart, in-app checklist toward Aha moment, chat widget for questions.</item>
          <item>Trial Days 4-7 (Value demonstration): usage-report email citing what the user accomplished, feature discovery prompts, social proof from similar companies.</item>
          <item>Trial Days 8-11 (Conversion intent): PQL scoring check; high PQL score triggers sales outreach; low PQL stays in automated nurture.</item>
          <item>Trial Days 12-14 (Urgency): countdown in product UI, final email with actual usage stats injected ("You've created X projects"), clear upgrade CTA.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Playbook 3: Expansion (Seat Growth)">
        <rule>
          <statement>Trigger expansion playbook from leading signals — 3+ active users from same org, @mentions in comments, external sharing — not from admin seat count alone. Route high-PQL accounts above ACV $1K/month to sales SDR; below that, automation closes the loop.</statement>
          <rationale>Leading behavioral signals predict expansion intent days before seat limits are reached. Waiting for the seat limit to fire gives competitors time to make the case for a switch at renewal.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>In-product message to any user: "Your team is growing — add more members on Team plan."</item>
          <item>Email to admin: team activity report showing collaboration value, Team plan benefits.</item>
          <item>High PQL score: sales call offer for Team or Enterprise tier.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Playbook Implementation Rules">
        <rule>
          <statement>Ship Phase 1 (Foundation) end-to-end before starting Phase 2. The checklist order is sequential because each phase depends on prior instrumentation.</statement>
          <rationale>Building upgrade triggers (Phase 2) before measuring TTV (Phase 1) optimizes a funnel with no baseline; lift cannot be measured without before/after instrumentation.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Self-serve checkout instrumentation must include payment-failure events. Tracking only successful upgrades misses the largest BoF leak in most PLG products.</statement>
          <rationale>Payment failures are the most common bottom-of-funnel drop-off and are often 2-3x more frequent than successful upgrades. Invisible failures prevent any checkout optimization.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="Where It Fails / Limitations">
      <list>
        <item>The 5-phase checklist is a maturity ladder, not a roadmap; agents should not promise sequential delivery without a parallel-tracks variant.</item>
        <item>Aha-moment discovery requires sufficient converted-cohort data (≥ ~200 paid users); below that, statistical correlation is unreliable and human judgment dominates.</item>
        <item>Day-N playbook timings (Day 2/5/7/14) are heuristics from B2B SaaS — B2C, dev tools, and creator-economy products have different windows.</item>
        <item>"Tools &amp; Tech Stack" table mixes free + enterprise tiers; agents must include cost + integration-effort columns before recommending.</item>
        <item>PQL section defers to plg-metrics — agents must chain reads, not invent scoring locally.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>This methodology maps directly to a multi-agent state machine: an aha-moment-finder mines retained-vs-churned cohorts, a ttv-instrumenter adds the funnel events from signup to Aha, a playbook-runner drives the freemium / trial / expansion playbooks as scheduled jobs (Day 0/2/5/7 etc.), and a phase-tracker walks the 5-phase implementation checklist as Linear/Jira issues. Human approval gates: free-tier limit numbers, pricing-page changes, sales-assist handoffs.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: aha-moment-finder (pulls cohort behavior data, returns the action most correlated with retention + confidence interval). ttv-instrumenter (emits a funnel-event spec and a PR plan to add them). playbook-runner (schedules the freemium/trial/expansion sequences in Customer.io / Klaviyo / Intercom; renders templates + waits). pql-scorer (wraps the PQL definition from plg-metrics and assigns scores nightly). phase-tracker (converts the 5-phase implementation checklist into trackable issues, reports completion %).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools and Services">
      <list>
        <item>mixpanel JQL — Aha-moment correlation analysis on cohorts</item>
        <item>amplitude Behavioral Cohorts API — PQL behavioral cohort sync</item>
        <item>posthog cohort + flag API — Run free/trial/paid cohorts and feature flags</item>
        <item>customerio API — Drive Day-N playbook campaigns programmatically</item>
        <item>klaviyo API — Trial-to-paid email sequences with metric triggers</item>
        <item>intercom API — In-app messaging + chat for trial assistance</item>
        <item>madkudu / breeze (HubSpot) — PQL scoring services</item>
        <item>stripe Billing API — Plan changes, proration, downgrade flows</item>
        <item>Amplitude / Mixpanel / PostHog — Aha-moment + TTV instrumentation</item>
        <item>Appcues / Pendo / Userflow / Chameleon — Onboarding flows, checklists, in-app upgrade triggers</item>
        <item>Intercom / Drift / Crisp — Chat assistance for trial-day-1 pattern</item>
        <item>Hotjar / FullStory / Heap — Diagnose where users miss Aha</item>
        <item>Stripe / Paddle / Chargebee — Self-serve checkout</item>
        <item>Customer.io / Autopilot / Klaviyo — Day-N email automation</item>
        <item>Madkudu / Clearbit Reveal — PQL scoring + lead enrichment</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Ship Phase 1 (Foundation) end-to-end before starting Phase 2 — the order is sequential because each phase depends on the previous instrumentation.</item>
        <item>For Aha-moment work, validate with at least two methods: behavioral correlation + qualitative converted-user interviews.</item>
        <item>TTV target less than 5 minutes is aggressive but achievable only with templates/sample data — bake the seeding into onboarding or the metric is theatre.</item>
        <item>Day-N playbook content must reference user behavior ("you've created 4 of 5 projects"), not generic upsell copy.</item>
        <item>PQL handoff to sales triggers ONLY above the model-defined ACV cutoff; below that, automation closes the loop.</item>
        <item>For expansion playbook, watch leading signals (3+ active users, @mentions, external sharing) — not just paid-seat counts.</item>
        <item>Always pair upgrade-trigger UI changes with measurement: track impression, click, dismiss, post-click conversion separately.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-Agent Gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLM-generated playbook copy drifts to "Hi there, hope you're doing well" filler. Force tone-anchor against existing converting messages.</item>
        <item>Day-N playbook must NOT auto-send without human review; agents queue, humans approve. Even with confidence guardrails, mis-sent campaigns are brand-damaging.</item>
        <item>Aha-moment discovery is correlation, not causation — agents will overfit to noisy events. Require ≥30% lift vs random control + p less than 0.05.</item>
        <item>Free-tier limit changes ripple to revenue forecasting; never let an agent change limits autonomously, even with phase-tracker green-light.</item>
        <item>Self-serve checkout instrumentation must include payment-failure events; agents that skip these miss the largest BoF leak.</item>
        <item>For trial-day-12 urgency emails, the agent should personalize with actual usage stats — generic "your trial ends" emails underperform; require usage-property injection.</item>
        <item>Do NOT auto-trigger sales outreach from PQL signals without an SLA — bad timing kills conversion.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/day-n-playbook.py" purpose="Python scheduler: generates freemium-to-paid Day-N message queue with approved=False flag for human review before send."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://productled.com/book/">Wes Bush: Product-Led Growth</link>
      <link href="https://openviewpartners.com/product-led-growth/#benchmarks">OpenView: PLG Benchmarks</link>
      <link href="https://www.elenaverna.com/plg-playbook">Elena Verna: PLG Playbook</link>
      <link href="https://www.madkudu.com/blog/what-is-a-product-qualified-lead">Madkudu: PQL definition + scoring</link>
      <link href="https://amplitude.com/blog/time-to-value">Amplitude: Time-to-Value</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
