<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="feature-prioritization-rice Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for feature-prioritization-rice. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>RICE Score = (Reach × Impact × Confidence) / Effort. Express Reach in the same unit (users/quarter) for the entire batch. Never mix monthly and quarterly denominators.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixing time periods inflates some rows 3-4x, making the ranking meaningless. Consistency in Reach units is more important than precision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reach is the number of users/customers affected per quarter. Source from analytics (funnel data, MAU counts, segment sizes). Never use "everyone" — estimate the segment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unquantified reach creates false precision. Grounding each item in an actual segment size (e.g., "4000 free-tier users trying checkout annually") makes the score defensible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use only the fixed Impact scale: 3 (massive), 2 (high), 1 (medium), 0.5 (low), 0.25 (minimal). Never invent intermediate values.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Intermediate values (1.7, 2.3) create false precision and destroy cross-feature comparability. The fixed scale forces explicit categorization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap Confidence at 50% for any item without a cited evidence URL or table reference. Reserve 100% for data-backed, tested items only.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents and humans default to 80-100% when uncomfortable. Evidence requirement prevents confidence inflation that produces false precision scores.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Express Effort in total person-months including design, dev, QA, and docs. Require a breakdown before accepting any estimate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs under-estimate effort 2-3x when not broken down. Decomposing into sub-disciplines exposes hidden work and produces calibrated estimates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 1: List all candidates. Step 2: Score each factor per item with rationale. Step 3: Calculate RICE = (R × I × C) / E. Step 4: Sort highest to lowest. Step 5: Sanity-check — any item with score greater than 2× the median requires human review before entering "Now". Step 6: Apply strategic override lane for top-2 bets to prevent crowding by easy wins.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">This sequence prevents gaming: if you score first without seeing the median, you can't anchor on it. The 2× median check catches outliers that need review. The strategic override protects large bets from being crowded out by many small quick wins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-score quarterly. Archive prior scoring files with date stamp to detect drift.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stale scores produce wrong roadmaps. Feature importance shifts as the product grows and user segments change. Historical scoring files are the primary artifact for retrospective analysis of prioritization drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
