<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-rice-formula" title="RICE Formula, Factor Definitions, and Scoring Process">
  <summary>RICE formula definition, scale for each of the four factors, scoring process, and constraints for valid scores.</summary>

  <section title="Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>RICE Score = (Reach x Impact x Confidence) / Effort. Express Reach in the same unit (users/quarter) for the entire batch. Never mix monthly and quarterly denominators.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing time periods inflates some rows 3-4x, making the ranking meaningless. Consistency in Reach units is more important than precision.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Factor Scales">
    <section title="Reach">
      <p>Number of users/customers affected per quarter. Source from analytics (funnel data, MAU counts, segment sizes). Never use "everyone" — estimate the segment.</p>
    </section>
    <section title="Impact">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use only the fixed Impact scale: 3 (massive), 2 (high), 1 (medium), 0.5 (low), 0.25 (minimal). Never invent intermediate values.</statement>
        <rationale>Intermediate values (1.7, 2.3) create false precision and destroy cross-feature comparability. The fixed scale forces explicit categorization.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section title="Confidence">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap Confidence at 50% for any item without a cited evidence URL or table reference. Reserve 100% for data-backed, tested items only.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents and humans default to 80-100% when uncomfortable. Evidence requirement prevents confidence inflation that produces false precision scores.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>100% — data-backed and tested (prototype results, A/B test, analytics correlation)</item>
        <item>80% — some data, reasonable assumptions, similar feature precedent</item>
        <item>50% — opinions, limited data, no prior evidence</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Effort">
      <rule>
        <statement>Express Effort in total person-months including design, dev, QA, and docs. Require a breakdown before accepting any estimate.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs under-estimate effort 2-3x when not broken down. Decomposing into sub-disciplines exposes hidden work and produces calibrated estimates.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>0.5 — a few days (patch, copy change, minor config)</item>
        <item>1 — about one person-month</item>
        <item>2 — two person-months</item>
        <item>3 — one quarter</item>
        <item>6+ — major project</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: List all candidates</item>
      <item>Step 2: Score each factor per item with rationale</item>
      <item>Step 3: Calculate RICE = (R x I x C) / E</item>
      <item>Step 4: Sort highest to lowest</item>
      <item>Step 5: Sanity-check: any item with score &gt; 2x the median requires human review before entering "Now"</item>
      <item>Step 6: Apply strategic override lane for top-2 bets to prevent crowding by easy wins</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-score quarterly. Archive prior scoring files with date stamp to detect drift.</statement>
      <rationale>Stale scores produce wrong roadmaps. Feature importance shifts as the product grows and user segments change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/rice-scoring-table.md">Multi-feature scoring table with R/I/C/E columns, RICE score, rank, and notes.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/rice-decision-record.md">Single-feature record: factor scores with rationale, calculation, rank, decision.</reference>
    <reference path="scripts/rice.py">Minimal scorer: reads JSON with reach/impact/confidence/effort, returns ranked output.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
