<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rice-examples" title="RICE Worked Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Two complete worked examples with scored tables and insights, plus concrete antipatterns and agent-specific failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Example: E-commerce Feature Prioritization">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Guest checkout wins despite similar effort to wishlist because of higher reach and impact</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Feature         R      I   C     E    RICE    Decision
Guest checkout  15000  2   90%   1    27000   Sprint 1
Size guide      5000   1   70%   0.5  7000    Sprint 1
Wishlist        8000   1   80%   2    3200    Sprint 2
Gift wrapping   2000   0.5 60%   1    600     Backlog

Insight: Guest checkout ranks #1 despite medium effort due to high reach (15K users
see checkout) and strong impact (removes friction for non-registered users).
Gift wrapping: only 600 reach with low confidence — clear backlog placement.
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example: SaaS Dashboard Features">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Low-effort high-confidence item (CSV export) beats high-impact complex item (custom dashboards)</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Feature            R     I   C     E     RICE    Decision
Export to CSV      3000  1   100%  0.25  12000   Sprint 1
Dark mode          5000  0.5 100%  0.5   5000    Sprint 2
Email reports      2000  2   80%   1     3200    Sprint 2
Custom dashboards  1000  3   50%   3     500     Later

Insight: CSV export wins on low effort (quarter-day) and perfect confidence.
Custom dashboards: high impact but 3 person-months + only 50% confidence → defer.
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM-generated Reach values as round numbers (5000, 10000) with no analytics citation.</description>
      <reason>Round numbers signal fabrication. Force decimal Reach from actual funnel analytics. Any Reach without a source URL or table reference must be rejected.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Same agent both proposing and scoring features.</description>
      <reason>The proposer has obvious bias toward high-scoring its own proposals. Route scoring to a different subagent than the proposer.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Silently dropping items below a RICE threshold without emitting the full ranked list.</description>
      <reason>Hidden rejections prevent review. Always emit the full ranked list with a cut line; never suppress low-scoring items from the output.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>High-RICE items with no sequencing check for dependencies.</description>
      <reason>A high-RICE item that depends on three low-RICE items cannot be started first. Dependency graph review is a required post-ranking step.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
