<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Definition Of Ready Checklist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules with rationale + source for definition-of-ready-checklist. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="eight-item-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A story is READY only when all 8 items pass: clear outcome, named acceptance criteria, design or wireframe linked, dependencies resolved, env access granted, test data identified, security/legal sign-off (if applicable), client PM accountable; less than or equal to 7/8 equals NOT READY and routes back to refinement.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBOK 7 + IIBA BABOK v3 readiness criteria">PMBOK 7 + IIBA BABOK v3 readiness criteria — applies to Definition Of Ready Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="client-side-dep-precheck" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Client-side dependency check (5 items) is mandatory and runs BEFORE engineering check: (a) client PM confirmed in writing, (b) env credentials or VPN tested by a team member, (c) realistic test dataset accessible, (d) regulator/legal/security ticket exists or is N/A in writing, (e) any required client-side IT change is ticketed with a stated SLA.</statement>
      <rationale source="Outsource delivery anti-patterns (BABOK perspective)">Outsource delivery anti-patterns (BABOK perspective) — applies to Definition Of Ready Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="compliance-named-contact" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stories carrying compliance impact (HIPAA, GDPR, SOC2, PCI) require a named compliance contact and a written N/A or sign-off attached; without it, ready=false regardless of other items.</statement>
      <rationale source="HIPAA / GDPR practitioner guidance">HIPAA / GDPR practitioner guidance — applies to Definition Of Ready Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="timebox-five-minutes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DoR check is timeboxed to 5 minutes per story in grooming; if the story cannot be evaluated in 5 minutes, mark NOT READY for 'insufficient definition' and route to a dedicated discovery session.</statement>
      <rationale source="Workshop facilitation research">Workshop facilitation research — applies to Definition Of Ready Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="failure-tracking" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every DoR failure is logged with the failing item id; the top failing item per client is the discovery focus for the next iteration.</statement>
      <rationale source="Continuous improvement (Lean)">Continuous improvement (Lean) — applies to Definition Of Ready Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-re-estimate-without-dor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-estimation of the same story is forbidden until the prior DoR failure has been cleared in writing; this enforces upstream work and removes the false comfort of re-estimating a blocked story.</statement>
      <rationale source="Agile estimation discipline">Agile estimation discipline — applies to Definition Of Ready Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="qbr-escalation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The checklist is co-owned by BA + PM and reviewed quarterly with the client; clients who consistently produce DoR failures get a written escalation in the QBR — DoR is the client-side accountability artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="Client governance / QBR practice">Client governance / QBR practice — applies to Definition Of Ready Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the team has no client-side dependencies at all or operates entirely in-house, return `skipped` — methodology overhead does not pay back.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to Definition Of Ready Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
