<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="MLP Four-Layer Model">
  <summary>The four-layer model that defines the path from a functional MVP to a Minimum Lovable Product, with a rating scale and MLP threshold rule.</summary>

  <section title="What is MLP">
    <p>Minimum Lovable Product is the smallest version that delivers core value, creates emotional connection, and gives users a reason to stay and recommend. MLP = MVP + delight. Not more features — better experience.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Every layer must be solid before adding the next. Delight built on unreliable foundations is wasted.</statement>
      <rationale>Users notice inconsistency before they notice charm. A delightful animation on a crashy flow increases frustration, not affection.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="The Four Layers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Layer 1 — Functional: core job completes, no blocking bugs, acceptable performance.</statement>
      <rationale>MVP baseline. Without this, nothing else matters.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Layer 2 — Reliable: consistent experience, error handling, edge cases covered, works as expected every time.</statement>
      <rationale>Reliability is the prerequisite for trust. Users forgive a rough UI; they do not forgive data loss or silent failures.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Layer 3 — Usable: easy to learn, efficient to use, minimal friction, good defaults.</statement>
      <rationale>Usability reduces the cognitive tax per session. High friction kills retention even when the product works perfectly.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Layer 4 — Delightful: emotional satisfaction, surprising moments, premium feel, shareable moments.</statement>
      <rationale>Delight creates word-of-mouth and emotional attachment that purely functional products cannot generate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Rating Scale and MLP Threshold">
    <rule>
      <statement>Rate each core feature 1–5 on each layer. MLP threshold: all features at 4+ on all four layers.</statement>
      <rationale>The threshold is not perfection (5) but sufficiency (4). Rating below 4 on any layer signals a gap that blocks MLP readiness.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Polish priority = user pain × frequency × visibility. Focus on high-frequency, high-visibility interactions first.</statement>
      <rationale>Delight in rarely-seen flows is invisible. The same effort on the core daily action multiplies impact across all sessions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="MVP vs MLP">
    <p>MVP goal is to validate; MLP goal is to retain. MVP focus is functionality; MLP focus is experience. MVP emotion is "it works"; MLP emotion is "I love it". Word-of-mouth is unlikely from MVP users and likely from MLP users.</p>
  </section>
</text>
