<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="MLP Planning Process">
  <summary>Five-step process for planning the gap between a validated MVP and a Minimum Lovable Product.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Audit Your MVP">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each core feature, rate 1–5 on all four layers. Any feature below 4 on any layer is a gap that must be closed before declaring MLP.</statement>
      <rationale>The audit makes the gap visible and concrete, replacing "the UX needs work" with specific layer deficits per feature.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Identify Delight Opportunities">
    <rule>
      <statement>Scan four moments for delight: first impression (onboarding), core action (the main thing users do), success moments (when they win), and recovery moments (when things go wrong).</statement>
      <rationale>Delight in error states is disproportionately memorable — it converts frustration into loyalty. Most products ignore this.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>Speed delight: faster than expected (instant search results)</item>
      <item>Simplicity delight: easier than expected (one-click checkout)</item>
      <item>Personality delight: unexpected charm (clever copywriting)</item>
      <item>Anticipation delight: knows what they need (smart defaults)</item>
      <item>Celebration delight: acknowledges success (confetti on completion)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Prioritize Polish">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the formula: polish priority = user pain × frequency × visibility. Only invest in high-frequency, high-visibility interactions.</statement>
      <rationale>Polish on a rarely-seen screen is invisible to most users. The same effort on the daily core action compounds across every session.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Define MLP Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write explicit MLP criteria for your target user segment covering all four layers with measurable outcomes. Template: "For [user segment] MLP means: [functional criteria], [reliable criteria], [usable criteria], [delightful criteria]. Measured by: [verification method]."</statement>
      <rationale>Without explicit criteria, MLP becomes subjective and the team will never agree it has been reached.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/mlp-plan.md">Full MLP plan template including completion criteria section</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Plan the Gap">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each feature, document: current state, MLP target, what is missing, and effort. This becomes the MLP backlog.</statement>
      <rationale>The gap analysis converts the audit rating into actionable tasks with known scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
