<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="MLP Planning Examples">
  <summary>Worked examples of MVP-to-MLP upgrade paths with layer-by-layer improvements and measured outcomes.</summary>

  <section title="Note-Taking App">
    <example type="good">
      <note>MVP: create, edit, delete notes, basic formatting — functional but bland. NPS 30, Day-30 retention weak.</note>
      <note>MLP additions by layer — Reliable: auto-save with visual confirmation. Usable: keyboard shortcuts, quick capture. Delight: smooth animations, satisfying micro-sounds, Zen mode for focused writing, clever empty states.</note>
      <note>Result: retention increased 40%, NPS rose from 30 to 55.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Invoicing Tool">
    <example type="good">
      <note>MVP: create invoices, send to clients — functional but clunky.</note>
      <note>MLP additions by layer — Reliable: payment confirmation notifications. Usable: templates from past invoices, client auto-fill. Delight: celebration on payment received, "You've earned $X this month" dashboard.</note>
      <note>Result: users create 2x more invoices, NPS 60.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Adding more features instead of polishing existing ones when retention is low.</description>
      <reason>More features increase scope without addressing the quality gap. Users who left due to rough UX won't return for more features with the same rough UX.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping MVP validation and going straight to MLP polish.</description>
      <reason>Polish on an unvalidated core value is expensive waste. Validate the job-to-be-done first, then polish the delivery.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Surface-level polish (color changes, fonts) without addressing interaction quality.</description>
      <reason>Cosmetic polish without fixing interaction friction does not move retention or NPS.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Generic delight not tailored to the specific audience.</description>
      <reason>Confetti on task completion delights consumer app users; it annoys enterprise finance users in the same moment. Delight must match emotional context.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Adding Layer 4 delight without completing Layers 1–3.</description>
      <reason>Delight on top of unreliable or unusable flows increases frustration. Users notice the inconsistency more than the charm.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
