<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Figma Comment Triage Protocol Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Figma Comment Triage Protocol. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-closed-taxonomy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every open comment is classified into exactly one of FIX / DECIDE / ANSWER / IGNORE; multi-tag or &apos;other&apos; classification is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Closed-taxonomy principle; F-066 grounding">Open taxonomies erode discipline; closed enums make sweeps comparable across days and trainable for agents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-named-owner-per-row" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each row carries a named owner (handle or role-with-rotation); &apos;team&apos; / &apos;we&apos; / empty are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI / single-throat-to-choke">Plural ownership produces orphan rows; named owners get pinged when SLA elapses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-sla-per-category" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each category has an SLA: FIX 48h, DECIDE 7d, ANSWER 24h, IGNORE same-day. Rows past SLA surface as a warning on next sweep.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational-SLA practice">Without SLA the queue depth grows silently; SLA + warning create a feedback loop the designer can act on.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-route-decide-to-log" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every DECIDE row produces a row in the design-decision-log (or links to an existing log row); decisions must not live in comments long-term.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-folklore convention">Figma comments are ephemeral; the log is canonical. Without routing, decisions evaporate when the file is archived.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-evidence-link-on-fix" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every FIX row carries a link to the eng ticket or commit that addresses it; resolved-without-link is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Grounded-decision convention">Resolved-without-link rows fail audit; the link makes the fix traceable to actual code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-figma-comment-triage-protocol.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
