<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Lessons Learned Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Lessons Learned. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="observation-log-continuous" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Observation log entries MUST be captured in-flight, not batched at project close. Each entry has date, observer, signal, hypothesis.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reason, Managing the Risks of Organizational Accidents">Post-hoc retros lose ~40% of observations to memory decay; continuous logging preserves the contemporaneous signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="blameless-post-mortem" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post-mortem MUST be blameless: focus on systems and processes, name no individuals. Personal mistakes describe context, not character.</statement>
      <rationale source="Etsy/Google SRE blameless post-mortem docs">Blame-laden post-mortems destroy psychological safety; future incidents go unreported; learning collapses.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="action-item-with-owner-due" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every lesson translated into an action item MUST have a named owner, due date, and acceptance criterion. Orphan actions forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Lessons Management">Action items without owner/due rot in the backlog; the lesson dies with the retro.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="publish-cross-team" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post-mortem report MUST be published cross-team in a searchable archive within 2 weeks of the milestone.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion knowledge management policy">Locked retros prevent cross-pollination; same mistake repeats across portfolio.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="sop-update-on-recurrence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the same lesson surfaces ≥2 times across projects, it MUST trigger a SOP / methodology update, not another retro entry.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion lessons-learned audit">Recurring lessons indicate the lesson hasn't propagated to procedure; the rule forces structural fix instead of repeated recognition.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Lessons Learned fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Lessons Learned outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
