<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Objection Bank Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every objection-bank entry and update must satisfy. The bank is a living artifact; these rules keep it useful past the first month.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-capture-at-source" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every demo call note, cold-outreach reply log, Product Hunt comment thread, and customer-support ticket ends with an `objections-mentioned` field listing zero-or-more objection IDs (or `none` if none surfaced). The field is mandatory; the note cannot be filed without it.</statement>
      <rationale source="information-capture friction studies; CRM data-hygiene research">Objections caught at the moment of utterance carry the exact phrasing, the trigger context, and (often) the implied price-or-trust dimension. Reconstructed-from-memory objections lose the load-bearing detail. Mandatory-field-at-source is the only capture pattern that survives a busy week.</rationale>
      <example type="good" title="Encounter log footer">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Call notes — 2026-05-19 — Acme prospect (J. Smith, head of platform)
... call discussion ...

### Objections mentioned
- price-vs-llm-spend-rounding (severity: 4/5; quote: "we already pay $4k/mo to Anthropic, your $99 is rounding error so I want to be sure the value is concrete")
- security-soc2-status (severity: 5/5; quote: "we cannot sign before SOC2 Type 2")
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-rank-by-frequency-times-revenue-impact" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each objection has a `score = encounter_count * blocked_revenue_estimate`. Encounter count is incremented at source. Blocked-revenue is the sum of the deal/MRR each objection blocked or delayed. Re-rank the top-20 weekly; this is the input to landing-copy decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="impact-weighted prioritisation; sales-pipeline data analytics">Pure frequency over-weights cheap, low-revenue customers. Pure revenue-impact over-weights one-off lost whales. The product captures both signals and orders the bank by what is actually leaking money.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-tie-back-to-copy-or-faq" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every entry in the top-10 must have a `resolved_in` field naming the landing-page section, FAQ entry, or pricing-page row that answers the objection. If the value is `unanswered`, a copy-update task is auto-filed in the marketing backlog and surfaces in the monthly diff post.</statement>
      <rationale source="conversion-rate optimisation practice; visitor-bounce analytics">An objection that is captured but never tied back to copy is shelfware. The whole point of the bank is to drive landing-page edits; the `resolved_in` field is the feedback signal that closes the loop.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-monthly-diff-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>On the first Friday of each month, the founder publishes a one-page diff post in the marketing channel: top-3 movers (rising in rank), top-3 fallers, any new entries from the past month, the unanswered-on-copy list. The post is the trigger for the monthly landing review.</statement>
      <rationale source="async-team review cadence patterns">Without a forced surfacing event, the bank rots into a write-only file. The monthly diff is short enough to read in 2 minutes and load-bearing enough that skipping it has visible consequences (objections continue to bleed deals).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-one-objection-one-counter-statement" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each entry has exactly one canonical `counter_statement` (40-80 words). It is the version used in demos, cold replies, and landing copy. Variations and tone-shifts are recorded as `variants`, never replacing the canonical. The canonical is reviewed quarterly.</statement>
      <rationale source="message-discipline research in sales playbooks">A single canonical counter forces the founder to commit to one position and lets new collaborators (contractors, VAs) be onboarded in one read. Multiple counter-statements proliferate and dilute the position; without a canonical, demo calls drift into improvisation.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Tag vocabulary">
    <list>
      <item>price — pure cost concerns</item>
      <item>trust — credibility, founder credentials, references</item>
      <item>security — SOC2, GDPR, on-prem, data residency</item>
      <item>switching-cost — migration effort, lock-in fears</item>
      <item>feature-gap — specific missing capability</item>
      <item>integration — does it work with our existing stack</item>
      <item>fit — buyer is not the right fit but is exploring anyway</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
