<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Objection Bank Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six failure modes that hollow out an objection bank within 3-6 months. Each has a detector and a repair.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="high">
      <description>Synthetic objections — agent or founder invents plausible objections from a template, with no real encounter behind them.</description>
      <detector>entry.evidence_quotes has fewer than 2 entries OR quote dates predate the encounter logs they reference</detector>
      <repair>Reject the entry on PR review. Require at least 2 verbatim quotes from real encounters with dates and source channels. Synthetic objections create copy that does not resonate; the bank exists to answer real, dated objections.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="high">
      <description>Stale entries — entries from 18+ months ago that no longer surface in current encounters keep dominating the rank because their cumulative score is high.</description>
      <detector>entry.last_seen_date older than 180 days AND entry.rank &lt;= 10</detector>
      <repair>Apply a 180-day decay: drop encounter_count by 50% for entries whose last_seen_date is older than 180 days. Reseed only if the objection actually re-surfaces. Quarterly cleanup PR purges entries with score &lt; 5% of the top entry.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Tag bloat — founder adds tags freely (price, pricing, cost, money, budget) and cannot answer "which tag wins on the pricing page".</description>
      <detector>entry.tag value not in the closed list OR new tags added without a PR updating 01-core-rules vocabulary</detector>
      <repair>Pre-commit hook rejects unknown tags. Quarterly tag-grooming PR consolidates near-duplicates and rewrites old entries.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Untied entries pile up — `resolved_in: unanswered` becomes the default for new entries because the founder defers the landing-page edit, and the unanswered list grows past the team's actionable capacity.</description>
      <detector>unanswered count &gt; 10 OR top-3 ranked entries are unanswered</detector>
      <repair>Cap the unanswered list at 10 entries. When the cap is hit, no new entries are added until at least one of the top-3 unanswered is either resolved in copy or explicitly closed as "by design, will not address" with founder rationale.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Counter-statement drift — multiple variants accumulate, the canonical never gets reviewed, and demo-call founders improvise different positions on the same objection.</description>
      <detector>entry.variants count &gt; 5 OR canonical_counter_statement.last_reviewed older than 120 days for a top-10 entry</detector>
      <repair>Quarterly review PR rewrites stale canonicals based on current product reality. Collapse variants to ≤ 3 (best-performing in cold replies, demo calls, and landing copy respectively).</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="low">
      <description>Monthly diff post skipped — busy month, founder forgets, the unanswered list never surfaces to the marketing channel, the loop dies silently.</description>
      <detector>more than 6 weeks since the last monthly_diff post</detector>
      <repair>Calendar reminder for the first Friday of each month. If a month is genuinely skipped, the next post combines two months and explicitly flags the gap so the team is aware of the lapse.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>
      A single prospect's strong objection ("your competitor said X, you need to address it") should not auto-promote into the canonical counter without corroboration. The corroboration rule (≥ 2 quotes from ≥ 2 sources) protects the bank from single-prospect distortion.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>
      Quarterly: founder reads through the top-10 entries against the current product. Some objections become moot (a feature shipped); some become more severe (a new competitor surfaced the issue). Update canonicals; archive obsolete entries with a `closed_reason` so the search history remains intact.
    </p>
  </section>
</text>
