<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Multi-Machine Offline Cache Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Multi-Machine Offline Cache application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-per-machine-cache-isolated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each machine has an isolated cache directory + machine ID. Cross-machine sync is opt-in (rsync/Git/cloud) and metadata-aware.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Shared cache via Dropbox / iCloud causes corruption + license-state confusion; explicit isolation is the safe default.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-content-addressable-store" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cache uses content-addressable storage (CAS): files keyed by SHA-256. Stale entries detected on hash mismatch; not on file timestamps.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Timestamp-based cache fails across machines (clock skew); CAS is the only reliable design.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-offline-grace-period" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cache survives offline for ≥7 days. After 7 days, prompt for online refresh. Hard-block after 30 days unless explicit offline license.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Balances usability (flights, no-internet client sites) against license auditability.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-license-activation-aware" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each machine consumes one activation slot. Re-activation on a new machine requires deactivating an old one OR upgrading license tier.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Naive licensing either fails legitimate users (no-mobile-license) or permits piracy; activation count is the industry-standard middle ground.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-cache-purge-on-license-end" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>On license expiration, cache enters read-only mode; on hard-end, purge tier-gated content within 7 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Long-tail license expiration creates piracy risk; explicit purge is the contractual safeguard.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>