<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-audience-signals-bidding" title="Audience Signals, Bidding Progression, and Learning Phase">
  <summary>Adding audience signals, bidding strategy progression from Maximize Conversions to Target CPA/ROAS, learning phase rules, and asset refresh cadence.</summary>

  <section title="Audience Signals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use your best-converting customer-match list as the primary audience signal; generic interest segments are much less effective at guiding PMax's optimizer.</statement>
      <rationale>PMax weights converter-similarity heavily. A customer-match list of actual buyers gives the optimizer strong signal. Interest segments give broad demographic hints that PMax often ignores.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Audience signals are hints, not constraints — PMax can and will expand beyond them</item>
      <item>Include: converting customer-match list, remarketing lists, similar audiences</item>
      <item>Start broad, refine based on asset group performance labels after 4-6 weeks</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using audience signals as the only targeting control and expecting PMax to respect them as hard limits.</description>
      <reason>Audience signals guide the optimizer but do not restrict inventory. PMax will bid outside the signal audiences if the optimizer finds higher conversion probability elsewhere.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Bidding Progression">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run Maximize Conversions without a target for at least 14 days and 30+ conversions; then switch to Target CPA or Target ROAS.</statement>
      <rationale>Setting a target CPA/ROAS before sufficient data forces the bidder to over-fit on sparse conversions. The learning phase needs unconstrained data collection to train the model.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep daily budget at minimum 3x target CPA; below this, PMax stalls on auction-bidding constraints and cannot exit learning.</statement>
      <rationale>PMax needs budget headroom to explore inventory and conversion paths. A budget too close to the target CPA eliminates any exploration margin and traps the campaign in learning indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Days 1-14: Maximize Conversions, no target — unconstrained exploration</item>
      <item>After 30+ conversions: add Target CPA or Target ROAS</item>
      <item>Weeks 1-6: minimize pauses and restarts — each restart resets the 4-6 week learning clock</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Asset Refresh">
    <rule>
      <statement>Replace LOW-labeled assets at least quarterly; do not trigger creative swap on performance labels under 7 days old since labels lag 7-14 days.</statement>
      <rationale>Asset performance labels have a 7-14 day lag. Swapping assets on day 3 based on PENDING or early LOW labels churns creative unnecessarily and disrupts the optimizer's learning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add account-level negative keywords for brand terms to prevent PMax from cannibalizing branded Search campaigns.</statement>
      <rationale>PMax and branded Search campaigns compete in the same auction. Without brand exclusions, PMax steals credit for high-intent branded queries at higher cost than a dedicated Search campaign.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
