<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Account Health Scoring Model (Sub-20 Accounts) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Account Health Scoring Model (Sub-20 Accounts) plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="six-signal-model" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Health score MUST aggregate exactly six observable signals (utilization variance, decision-maker engagement, scope-creep delta, payment punctuality, referral/advocacy, sponsor stability) with each signal scored 0/1/2.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gainsight Customer Health Scoring guide">NPS-only or MRR-only scoring fails at micro-agency scale where each client is statistically unique; six signals balance leading + lagging indicators.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="observable-not-opinion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every signal MUST be sourced from a system of record (timesheet, billing, calendar, repo, CRM); founder gut-feel signals are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ChurnZero playbook 2024">Founder optimism bias inflates scores on the relationships that need attention most; observable signals are the only auditable input.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="threshold-cutoffs-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tier mapping MUST use fixed cutoffs (green 10-12, yellow 5-9, red 0-4); per-account custom thresholds are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — micro-agency CS audit 2026-02">Per-account thresholds cause score laundering — the founder slides the cutoff to keep favourite accounts green; fixed cutoffs are non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="weekly-cadence-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Scoring MUST run weekly on Mondays; biweekly cadence is allowed only if all six signal sources update less than weekly.</statement>
      <rationale source="SaaStr operating playbook">Monthly cadence misses 4 weeks of leading-indicator drift; weekly is the minimum cadence that lets retention actions land before churn.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="escalation-trigger-defined" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Retention action MUST trigger when score drops 2+ in a week OR sits red for 2 consecutive weeks; triggers without action are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gainsight customer-health implementations 2024">Scoring without action is theatre; the trigger condition makes the score operationally useful rather than a dashboard ornament.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
