<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Utilization and Pipeline Dashboard Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules for a freelance utilization-and-pipeline dashboard that drives quarterly rate decisions.</summary>

  <section title="Dashboard rules">

    <rule id="r1-four-metrics-fixed" testable="true">
      <statement>The dashboard contains exactly four headline metrics: (1) weekly utilization % = billable hours / capacity hours; (2) realised $/hr = billed revenue in period / total worked hours in period; (3) pipeline coverage = (signed + qualified next-90d revenue) / 90-day revenue target; (4) rate trend = rolling-3-month realised $/hr. No fifth headline metric.</statement>
      <rationale>Above four headline metrics the freelancer skips review or fixates on a vanity number. The four chosen each drive a distinct decision (capacity, pricing, sales motion, rate trajectory).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-realised-rate-includes-admin" testable="true">
      <statement>Realised $/hr divides billed revenue by TOTAL worked hours, including admin, sales, marketing, invoicing, and project-management overhead. Dividing by billable-only hours is forbidden — it produces flattering numbers that mislead rate decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Most freelancers' hourly rate looks fine on billable-only math and breaks on total-time math. Rate decisions made on flattering math are the proximate cause of feast-or-famine cycles.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-pipeline-90d-window" testable="true">
      <statement>Pipeline coverage uses a fixed 90-day forward window. "Signed" requires a signed SOW or deposit paid; "qualified" requires a named decision-maker, a confirmed budget range, and a stated decision date. Speculative leads ("might do something with us next year") are excluded.</statement>
      <rationale>Unbounded pipeline definitions inflate coverage and trigger the "I'm fine on pipeline" comfort feeling right before a 6-week drought.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-quarterly-review-cadence" testable="true">
      <statement>The dashboard is reviewed once per calendar quarter, on a fixed date (e.g., second Monday of Q-start month). The review produces exactly one of three outcomes: (a) raise floor rate, (b) hold floor rate, (c) drop a non-fit client. Outcomes that ARE forbidden: "monitor for another quarter", "depends on the economy", "let's see how next month goes".</statement>
      <rationale>Vague outcomes are the failure mode that lets a stale rate persist for 3 years. Forcing a discrete decision converts data into action.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-rate-decision-tied-to-data" testable="true">
      <statement>Any rate change MUST cite the specific metric that triggered it (e.g., "realised $/hr rose to $138 in Q1 vs floor of $125 → raise floor to $140"). Rate changes justified by "feeling underpaid" or "competitor charges more" without a data citation are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Data-cited rate decisions survive client pushback ("the market is soft"). Feeling-driven decisions collapse in negotiation.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <code lang="txt"><![CDATA[
Q1 2026 — Dashboard review (2026-04-08)

  Utilization (rolling 12w):     71%  (target 65–75) → ok
  Realised $/hr:                $138  (floor $125)  → above floor
  Pipeline coverage (90d):      1.4x  (target ≥1.2x) → ok
  Rate trend (3m):              $122 → $128 → $138    → up

DECISION:
  Raise floor rate from $125 → $140 effective Q2 2026.
  Trigger: r5 cite — realised $138 sustained over 3 months, pipeline coverage
  >1.2x means no scarcity pressure, utilization upper-band means we're capacity
  constrained — classic raise signal.
]]></code>
    <note>Four metrics, total-time denominator, 90d pipeline window, discrete decision, data-cited rationale.</note>
  </example>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Freelancer reviews "billable hours $/hr" (excluding 8 admin hours/week), sees $185, holds rate flat, then has 3 quiet weeks and panics into discount work at $90.</description>
    <reason>Violates r2 (admin excluded from denominator) and r4 (no discrete decision when pipeline coverage was actually thin). Flattering math hid the actual exposure.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
