<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-sbi-and-radical-candor" title="SBI Model, SBII Extension, and Radical Candor">
  <summary>The Situation-Behavior-Impact model for structuring feedback, its Intent extension for opening dialogue, and the Radical Candor quadrant for calibrating delivery tone.</summary>

  <section title="SBI Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deliver feedback using the SBI structure: Situation (specific context), Behavior (observable action), Impact (concrete effect on team, project, or person).</statement>
      <rationale>SBI decouples observation from judgment. The recipient can act on "you interrupted the client twice" (behavior); they cannot act on "you were rude" (character). Specificity eliminates the "when?" ambiguity that makes feedback forgettable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Client meeting feedback using SBI.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Situation:  "In yesterday's client meeting..."
Behavior:   "When you interrupted the client twice..."
Impact:     "The client seemed frustrated and we lost momentum."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Character-based feedback — not actionable.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"You're impatient and you don't listen to clients."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="SBII Extension">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add an Intent inquiry ("Help me understand what you were trying to do?") after the Impact step when the behavior could have a legitimate reason you don't know.</statement>
      <rationale>SBII prevents the fundamental attribution error — assuming the person acted from a negative motive when there may be a good reason. It converts feedback delivery into dialogue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Code review SBII example.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"In the code review (S), when you approved without comments (B),
I was surprised because that PR had several issues (I).
Can you help me understand your thinking? (Intent)"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Radical Candor Quadrant">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deliver feedback that is simultaneously caring (you want the person to succeed) and direct (you challenge the behavior clearly). Avoid both ruinous empathy and obnoxious aggression.</statement>
      <rationale>Kim Scott's research shows most feedback failures are in the "ruinous empathy" quadrant — feedback so softened it communicates nothing actionable. The recipient feels good but does not change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Radical Candor (goal): "I care about your growth, and this needs to change"</item>
      <item>Ruinous Empathy (avoid): "It's fine..." when it is not</item>
      <item>Obnoxious Aggression (avoid): "This is garbage, what were you thinking?"</item>
      <item>Manipulative Insincerity (avoid): talking behind back, passive-aggressive</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply Radical Candor in sequence: ask first ("Can I give you some feedback?"), be specific with SBI, be immediate (within 48 hours), be private.</statement>
      <rationale>Asking permission engages the recipient as a participant rather than a subject, reducing defensiveness before the content is delivered.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
