<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="match-real-world">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>The design should speak the users' language, with words, phrases, and concepts familiar to the user, rather than internal jargon. Follow real-world conventions, making information appear in a natural and logical order.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>usability-heuristic</tag>
      <tag>language</tag>
      <tag>ux</tag>
      <tag>conventions</tag>
      <tag>localization</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Match Between System and Real World</title>

    <summary>Users encounter unfamiliar jargon and technical terms. Icons and labels do not match what users expect. Information is organized in system-centric rather than user-centric ways. Concepts from the real world are misrepresented or ignored. Without matching the real world: user confusion, learning curve increases, errors from misunderstanding, reduced adoption.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Usability Heuristic #2: The design should speak the users' language, with words, phrases, and concepts familiar to the user, rather than internal jargon. Follow real-world conventions, making information appear in a natural and logical order.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Content audit: reviewing all UI labels, error messages, and instructions for technical language</item>
        <item>Localization prep: ensuring terminology matches user vocabulary before translation</item>
        <item>Error message redesign: replacing system-generated error codes with plain language</item>
        <item>Onboarding copy review: new users encounter the most jargon because they lack domain context</item>
        <item>B2B product launches into a new industry vertical: the same feature may need entirely different terminology for finance vs. healthcare vs. logistics users</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Developer tools and CLIs intentionally targeted at technical users — technical language is correct for the audience</item>
        <item>Internal admin panels where all users are trained staff familiar with system terminology</item>
        <item>When users have explicitly indicated they prefer technical precision over simplicity (e.g., API documentation)</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="language-guidelines">
      <p>Key principles for matching real-world language:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Use familiar language - Words users actually use</item>
        <item>Follow conventions - Match real-world expectations</item>
        <item>Logical information flow - Natural order for users</item>
        <item>Meaningful metaphors - Connect digital to physical</item>
      </list>

      <p>Common terminology replacements:</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use user-friendly language in place of technical jargon: "Log out" instead of "Terminate session", "Search" instead of "Execute query", "Please enter a valid email" instead of "Invalid input", "Folder / Collection" instead of "Repository", "Sign in" instead of "Authenticate", "Update / Refresh" instead of "Synchronize".</statement>
        <rationale>Users search and think in everyday language. Technical terminology creates a barrier to entry and forces users to learn internal system concepts before accomplishing their actual goal.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Domain-specific conventions to follow:</p>
      <list>
        <item>E-commerce: Shopping cart, checkout, wishlist</item>
        <item>Documents: Files, folders, save, open</item>
        <item>Email: Inbox, sent, draft, trash</item>
        <item>Social: Friends, followers, like, share</item>
        <item>Navigation: Home, back, menu, search</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="implementation-patterns">
      <p>Practical patterns for implementing real-world language:</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Error messages must explain what happened in plain language (no error codes or HTTP status), tell the user what to do next, and match the intended tone (friendly/professional/minimal).</statement>
        <rationale>Error messages occur at moments of user frustration. A technical error code adds confusion; plain language + next steps restores user agency and reduces support load.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Natural Language in Error Messages">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Bad: "Error 403: Authentication failed"
Good: "Incorrect password. Please try again."
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Natural Language in Labels">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Bad: "DOB"
Good: "Date of birth"
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Natural Language in Instructions">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Bad: "Input alphanumeric characters only"
Good: "Use only letters and numbers"
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Logical information order must follow how the user thinks, not how the system stores data. Address forms: Street → City → State → Zip → Country (user mental model), not Country → State → City → Street → Zip (database schema).</statement>
        <rationale>Users have a cognitive map of how things are organized in the real world. Forcing them to learn the system's organization creates confusion and errors.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Logical Address Form Order">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Bad: Country > State > City > Street > Zip
Good: Street > City > State > Zip > Country
(Matches how people think about addresses)
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <note>Date selection varies by locale: US = Month / Day / Year; Europe = Day / Month / Year. Match user's locale.</note>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Icons must be paired with text labels (or tooltips if space-constrained). Icon-only controls force users to recall meaning; recognition is easier than recall.</statement>
        <rationale>Even if a metaphor is outdated (e.g., floppy disk for save), users recognize it. But unfamiliar icons are pure memorization burden.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Save: Floppy disk (legacy) or cloud</item>
        <item>Delete: Trash can</item>
        <item>Settings: Gear</item>
        <item>Search: Magnifying glass</item>
        <item>Home: House</item>
        <item>Close: X</item>
      </list>

      <p>Real-world metaphors create mental bridges:</p>
      <list>
        <item>File management: Desktop = workspace, Folders = organization, Trash = deletion (recoverable)</item>
        <item>E-commerce: Cart = collecting items, Checkout = payment area, Wishlist = items for later</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="research-and-validation">
      <p>Finding and testing user language:</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Plain-language alternatives must be sourced from support tickets and user interview transcripts, not from the team's internal vocabulary. Do not guess.</statement>
        <rationale>Plausible-sounding terminology chosen by designers often differs from what users actually search for and use. Research is the only reliable input.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Methods for discovering user language:</p>
      <list>
        <item>User interviews - Listen to how they describe tasks</item>
        <item>Support tickets - What terms do users use?</item>
        <item>Search logs - What do they search for?</item>
        <item>Card sorting - How do they categorize?</item>
        <item>Competitor analysis - Industry standard terms</item>
      </list>

      <p>Methods for testing terminology:</p>
      <list>
        <item>A/B testing - Different label variations</item>
        <item>Comprehension testing - Can users explain what it means?</item>
        <item>Task completion - Does terminology help or hinder?</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <p>Patterns that break real-world matching:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Internal jargon: Using company-specific terms</description>
        <reason>Users have no context for internal terminology; it creates a barrier to entry.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Technical language: Developer/system terminology in user-facing copy</description>
        <reason>Not all users are technical; the feature must be usable by the broadest intended audience.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Abbreviations: Unclear shortened forms</description>
        <reason>Abbreviations require recall; spelled-out terms are more discoverable in search and easier to understand.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Inconsistent terms: Same thing called different names</description>
        <reason>Inconsistency forces users to recall multiple labels for the same concept; terminology should be standardized.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Culture blindness: Not localizing properly</description>
        <reason>Metaphors and conventions vary by culture; direct translation of English terminology often produces awkward or misleading text.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="localization">
      <p>Localization is deeper than word substitution:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Translate meaning, not just words</item>
        <item>Adjust for cultural conventions</item>
        <item>Date and number formats</item>
        <item>Currency display</item>
        <item>Reading direction (LTR/RTL)</item>
        <item>Color meanings vary by culture</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For multi-locale products, have a native speaker validate terminology in each locale independently — direct translation of English user-friendly terms can produce awkward or misleading text.</statement>
        <rationale>What is plain language in one culture may be confusing or offended in another. Localization requires cultural expertise, not just language skill.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Claude subagents can audit a provided list of UI strings, error messages, and labels against a set of plain-language rules, generating a Language Audit Checklist with suggested replacements. Agents can also generate locale-appropriate copy variants when given a target locale and base English text. For systematic enforcement, agents can generate ESLint or custom linter rules that flag hard-coded technical strings.</p>

      <note>Human review is required for domain-specific terminology where the "plain language" alternative changes meaning.</note>

      <note>Recommended subagents: faion-usability-agent (language audit; generates plain-language replacements for technical UI strings); faion-sdd-executor-agent (implements terminology changes in code; updates i18n string files).</note>

      <example type="good" title="Language Audit Prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Audit the following UI strings for violations of "Match Between System and Real World" (Nielsen #2).
For each string:
1. Identify technical terms, jargon, or system-centric language
2. Suggest a plain-language alternative in the user's vocabulary
3. Flag if the meaning changes with the replacement (requires human review)

User type: {user_description}
UI strings:
{strings_list}
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Error Message Rewrite Prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Rewrite the following error messages so they:
1. Explain what happened in plain language (no error codes or HTTP status)
2. Tell the user what to do next
3. Match the tone: {tone: friendly/professional/minimal}

Current error messages:
{error_messages}
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <p>When working with agents on language matching, be aware of these failure modes:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents rewriting technical terms often change meaning subtly</description>
        <reason>"Repository" replaced with "folder" loses the version-control concept. Require the agent to flag ambiguous replacements.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Plain-language alternatives generated for generic instructions may not match the product's specific feature names</description>
        <reason>Provide a product glossary as context.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Error message rewrites default to overly apologetic tone</description>
        <reason>Agents default to "We're so sorry something went wrong!" — specify the desired tone explicitly in the prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents do not know what terms your specific user segment actually uses</description>
        <reason>Without interview or support ticket data as input, they will use generic consumer-app vocabulary. Provide research data as context.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Publishing agent-generated terminology without human review</description>
        <reason>Human checkpoint required before terminology changes are deployed — wrong plain-language replacements erode trust faster than technical jargon.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Tools for language auditing and style enforcement:</p>
      <list>
        <item>write-good: Lints prose for passive voice, weasel words, jargon (npm i -g write-good)</item>
        <item>alex: Flags insensitive or unequal language in text (npm i -g alex; alexjs.com)</item>
        <item>textlint: Extensible text linting; custom rules for domain jargon (npm i -g textlint; textlint.github.io)</item>
        <item>vale: Prose style linter for technical writing; custom vocab lists (brew install vale; vale.sh)</item>
        <item>i18next-parser: Extract i18n keys from code for audit (npm i -g i18next-parser)</item>
      </list>

      <p>SaaS and OSS services for language and localization:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Hemingway Editor (SaaS): Grade-level readability check; web-only</item>
        <item>Readable.io (SaaS, Partial): Readability API; Flesch-Kincaid scoring</item>
        <item>Vale + GitHub Actions (OSS, Yes): CI prose linting; enforce custom style guide in PRs</item>
        <item>Lokalise (SaaS, Yes): i18n management with API; stores locale string variants</item>
        <item>Phrase (Memsource) (SaaS, Yes): Translation management; API for string extraction</item>
        <item>Crowdin (SaaS, Yes): OSS-friendly localization platform with API</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="inline-script">
      <p>Scan i18n JSON for technical terms using a blocklist:</p>
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
import json, re

JARGON_BLOCKLIST = [
    r"\bauth(enticate|entication)?\b",
    r"\brepository\b",
    r"\bsync(hronize)?\b",
    r"\bvalidat(e|ion)\b",
    r"\bterminate\b",
    r"\bexecut(e|ion)\b",
    r"\bquery\b",
    r"error\s+\d{3}",  # HTTP status codes in messages
]

def audit_i18n_file(path: str) -> list[dict]:
    with open(path) as f:
        strings = json.load(f)

    violations = []
    for key, value in strings.items():
        if not isinstance(value, str):
            continue
        for pattern in JARGON_BLOCKLIST:
            if re.search(pattern, value, re.IGNORECASE):
                violations.append({
                    "key": key,
                    "value": value,
                    "pattern": pattern,
                    "action": "Replace with plain-language alternative",
                })
    return violations

for v in audit_i18n_file("en.json"):
    print(v)
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Source plain-language alternatives from support tickets and user interview transcripts, not from the team's internal vocabulary</item>
        <item>Apply terminology decisions to a shared glossary first, then update the codebase — consistent terminology across the product is more important than any single perfect label</item>
        <item>Error messages are the highest-ROI target: they occur at moments of user frustration and must be maximally clear</item>
        <item>Test terminology with a comprehension task, not a preference question — ask "what would you do after reading this?" not "which version do you prefer?"</item>
        <item>Maintain a two-column forbidden-terms list: left column system term, right column user term; feed this list to the linter and the agent's prompt</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/language-audit.md" purpose="Language audit checklist for reviewing terminology, error messages, labels, and instructions"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/match-system-real-world/"/>
      <link href="https://www.plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/"/>
      <link href="https://m3.material.io/foundations/content-design/writing"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/style-guide/brand-voice-above-all-simple-human"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
