<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Time Tracking — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for solo time-tracking discipline that protect Friday invoicing accuracy.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-single-source" testable="true">
      <statement>Choose exactly ONE source-of-truth tracker (Timing OR Toggl OR Clockify). Supplemental data (Wakatime, calendar) may flow into it, but not parallel to it. Two trackers = three numbers = wrong invoice.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo-founder operations essays (Tara Reed, Tom Critchlow)">Parallel tools drift within 14 days. Reconciliation across tools costs more time than it saves. Single source eliminates the drift class entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-capture-at-boundary" testable="true">
      <statement>Start / stop a timer at session boundaries (project switch, meeting start, break). Retro-tracking (filling in yesterday's hours) is BANNED — the data is 60% accurate at best (Toggl-published cohort study).</statement>
      <rationale source="Toggl in-app analytics, Time Doctor research">Retro-tracking accuracy degrades 10% per hour of delay. Capture at boundary is the only sustainable signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-label-discipline" testable="true">
      <statement>Every block has TWO labels: `project` (from active client list) AND `task` (from labels-taxonomy.yaml — e.g. dev, review, meeting, support). Untagged blocks &gt; 30min trigger a daily gap-alert.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brennan Dunn — Double Your Freelancing">Two-axis labelling enables both per-project invoicing AND per-task ROI analysis (e.g. "I spent 18% on support, do I need a support tier?"). Single-axis loses the second analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-write-off-tag" testable="true">
      <statement>Time that is NOT billable to a paying client must be tagged with a `write-off` reason from a closed list: SALES, ADMIN, LEARNING, UNBILLABLE-REWORK, BREAK. "Other" is forbidden — coerces to ADMIN.</statement>
      <rationale source="Patrick McKenzie — Kalzumeus rate-floor logic">Without a write-off taxonomy, non-billable time is invisible to the operator and impossible to reduce. The closed list forces classification and exposes the cost.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-friday-cadence" testable="true">
      <statement>Reconciliation MUST run weekly on the same day (default Friday 16:00). The script reads the tracker, detects gaps, prompts labels for ambiguous blocks, and emits an invoice draft. Skipping a Friday is allowed once; skipping twice resets discipline.</statement>
      <rationale source="Habit-formation research (BJ Fogg)">Habits stabilise on a fixed cue. Without a fixed cadence, reconciliation drifts to end-of-month and becomes 4-hour reconstruction. Friday 16:00 is the canonical solo slot.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Tool choice heuristic">

    <example type="good" title="Tool stack mapping">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
macOS only, want zero-friction:   Timing  (auto-track + manual override)
Cross-platform, manual start:     Toggl Track
Cross-platform, free:             Clockify
Engineer wanting code-level signal: Toggl + Wakatime (Wakatime feeds Toggl)
Multi-device, agency-style:       Harvest (worth the cost only at agency)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Whatever the tool, r1 says: pick ONE source of truth. Wakatime is signal, not source.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Multi-tool drift (r1 violation)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Operator uses Toggl on Mac, Clockify on phone, paper notebook for meetings.
Friday reconciliation: 2h spent diffing three sources.
End result: invoice rounds down by ~15% to "be safe". Operator loses ~$8k/yr.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 violation. Single-source discipline recovers the lost revenue.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
