<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Modular Monolith Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the modular-monolith methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale; the final rule is the skip-this-methodology gate referenced by the decision tree.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-one-context-per-module" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each module MUST map to exactly one bounded context. Modules named after technical layers (utils, helpers, common, lib) are not modules — they are coupling sinks and MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="DDD (Evans, Vernon); Shopify / GitHub modular-monolith case studies.">Technical-layer modules accumulate cross-context logic and recreate the tight coupling modular monolith is meant to prevent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-public-api-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cross-module calls MUST go through a declared public API (typically `__public__.py`, `Module.API`, `exports`). Direct imports of another module's domain / application / infrastructure code are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — modular-monolith boundary erosion audits.">Bypassing public APIs creates invisible coupling; internal changes silently break callers and the boundary erodes within sprints.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-schema-per-module" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each module MUST own its own database schema (separate Postgres schema or table prefix). Cross-module reads MUST go through the public API, never via SQL JOINs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Shopify Pods architecture postmortems.">Schema-per-module is the prerequisite for future extraction; cross-module JOINs create the coupling extraction has to undo.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-import-linter-in-ci" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Boundary rules MUST be enforced by a static checker (import-linter, depguard, ArchUnit) in CI. Convention without enforcement decays within weeks.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — pre/post import-linter adoption studies.">Human review misses boundary violations under deadline pressure; only mechanical enforcement preserves the architecture.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-events-not-shared-tables" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cross-module communication for write events MUST use domain events on an in-process bus (or message queue), not shared tables. Shared tables imply shared ownership and re-create the big-ball-of-mud.</statement>
      <rationale source="DDD (Vernon); Eventual Consistency patterns.">Domain events keep modules autonomous; shared tables couple data lifecycles and complicate future extraction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When prerequisites hold (bounded contexts named, dependency graph drawn, CI live, linter installed), apply r1 → r2 → r3 → r4 → r5 and emit the module spec.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology design — gate rule.">Out-of-order adoption (linter without dependency graph) catches noise; the order is gate-design.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do NOT use when (a) modules already need independent scaling, (b) polyglot stacks required, (c) throwaway prototype. Note constraint and exit.</statement>
      <rationale source="Preconditions — skip gate.">Modular ceremony for constraints it cannot satisfy wastes review time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
