<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Visibility of System Status Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every visibility-of-system-status application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-feedback-thresholds" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide visible feedback within 100ms of any user action. 1-3s → spinner; 3-10s → indeterminate progress indicator; over 10s → determinate progress bar with percentage AND cancel option.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen — response-time research (1993, updated)">Below 100ms feels instant; up to 1s preserves flow; thresholds anchored in human perception research.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-skeleton-for-known-layout" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For content-heavy known-layout pages, use skeleton screens, NOT spinners. Spinners on list pages increase perceived wait time.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — skeleton screen research">Skeleton screens set accurate spatial expectations; spinners with unknown duration increase anxiety.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-three-states" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every async-trigger element MUST implement three states: loading (disabled + indicator), success (confirmation), error (message with recovery action).</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen — H#1">Missing any state produces dead-click or silent-failure patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-disable-during-async" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Disable the trigger element immediately on click during async; re-enable on success or error. Never leave it active during processing.</statement>
      <rationale source="dead-click + double-submission research">Active triggers during async cause duplicate API calls and duplicate payments.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-aria-live-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>aria-live=polite for non-critical status (success toast). aria-live=assertive ONLY for critical errors requiring immediate attention. role=status for persistent status regions. aria-busy=true on loading elements.</statement>
      <rationale source="WCAG 2.2 + ARIA APG">Misused assertive regions interrupt users disruptively; the rubric prevents that.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-error-toast-manual" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Success toasts auto-dismiss after 3-5s. Error toasts require manual dismissal — auto-dismiss on error is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — toast notification research">Errors users must read + act on cannot disappear before they finish reading.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
