<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-decomposition-rules" title="WBS Decomposition Rules">
  <summary>Four rules that make a WBS valid: noun-based nodes, 100% rule, 8/80 leaf sizing, and ID stability — plus the required overhead packages agents skip.</summary>

  <section title="Deliverable Orientation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every WBS node must be a noun phrase describing an output — never a verb phrase describing an activity.</statement>
      <rationale>Deliverable names survive implementation changes; activity names do not. A WBS structured around activities must be rewritten every time the approach changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Activity-based — breaks when technology or approach changes.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
2.1 Design user authentication
2.2 Build user authentication
2.3 Test user authentication
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Deliverable-based — stable across implementation changes.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
2.1 User Authentication Module
    2.1.1 Registration System
    2.1.2 Login / Logout
    2.1.3 Password Reset
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="100% Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every parent node must represent exactly 100% of the scope in its children — no gaps, no overlaps. Verify by asking: "If all children are complete, is the parent complete?"</statement>
      <rationale>Gaps produce forgotten work packages that surface during execution. Overlaps produce double-counted effort and budget disputes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include these overhead branches; if any are missing, the WBS is incomplete: Project Management, QA, Deployment, Documentation, Training, Transition.</statement>
      <rationale>Overhead is 15-25% of real project effort. Agents and manual drafters systematically omit it, creating a structural budget gap that cannot be recovered during execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Work Package Sizing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Leaf nodes must have effort estimates between 8 and 80 hours. Leaves outside this range must be split (too large) or merged (too small).</statement>
      <rationale>Below 8 hours, tracking overhead exceeds value. Above 80 hours, the estimate is a guess and internal dependencies are invisible. Calibrate bounds to match your tracking unit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stop decomposing when the 8/80 rule is satisfied. Maximum 4 levels for human readability; deeper decomposition belongs in the Dictionary, not the tree.</statement>
      <rationale>Vanity depth gives a false sense of precision without improving schedule or cost predictability. Level 5+ trees are unmaintainable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="ID Stability">
    <rule>
      <statement>WBS IDs are append-only. Once assigned, a numeric ID never changes or is reused, even if the node is deleted or scope is reduced.</statement>
      <rationale>Change requests, risk entries, and task files reference WBS IDs. Renumbering breaks traceability across the entire project record.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
