<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-rules" title="Flexibility and Efficiency — Core Rules">
  <summary>Concrete rules for implementing Nielsen Heuristic #7: layered accelerators, multiple paths, progressive disclosure, customization, and bulk operations.</summary>

  <section title="Keyboard Shortcuts">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide keyboard shortcuts for all frequently repeated actions; display them in menus, tooltips, and a discoverable shortcut panel.</statement>
      <rationale>Shortcuts without discoverability give zero efficiency gain. Layered exposure (menu label → tooltip → panel) ensures novices learn them gradually while experts use them immediately.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow platform conventions before inventing custom shortcuts: Ctrl+S = Save, Ctrl+Z = Undo, Ctrl+C/V = Copy/Paste, Ctrl+F = Find.</statement>
      <rationale>Custom shortcuts that conflict with platform standards cause errors and erode trust. Conventions are non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Test all custom shortcuts against NVDA+Chrome and VoiceOver+Safari before shipping — screen readers capture many key combinations.</statement>
      <rationale>Accessibility tools intercept keyboard events at the OS level; untested shortcuts silently break screen reader workflows.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Multiple Paths">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide at least two paths to accomplish each primary task (e.g., menu click, double-click, right-click context menu, keyboard shortcut).</statement>
      <rationale>Different users have different motor skills, device types, and learned habits. A single path is an accessibility and efficiency bottleneck.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Ensure that all paths to the same goal produce identical outcomes — diverging behavior between paths fragments user mental models.</statement>
      <rationale>If double-click edits inline but right-click opens a modal, users cannot build a reliable mental model of how editing works.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Progressive Disclosure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show essential options by default; hide advanced options behind a clearly labeled toggle or "Advanced" section.</statement>
      <rationale>Exposing all options simultaneously overwhelms novices without benefiting experts, who know where to find advanced controls.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Show contextual options based on the current selection — hide unrelated options, do not grey them out in long lists.</statement>
      <rationale>Greyed-out irrelevant options create visual noise and force users to filter mentally what should be filtered by the system.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Bulk Operations">
    <rule>
      <statement>For any action that can be performed on a single item, provide a bulk version that operates on a user-defined selection.</statement>
      <rationale>Power users managing 50+ items cannot afford per-item actions; bulk ops are the primary efficiency multiplier for high-volume workflows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always show a count confirmation before executing destructive bulk operations: "Delete 14 items?"</statement>
      <rationale>Irreversible bulk actions without confirmation introduce data loss risk that no shortcut convenience justifies.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Customization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide customization (saved layouts, pinned items, custom shortcuts) only after default shortcuts and workflows are proven insufficient.</statement>
      <rationale>Premature customization multiplies QA surface and creates its own cognitive load for novice users who encounter a non-default state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always expose a "Reset to defaults" option alongside any customization to prevent users from getting permanently lost.</statement>
      <rationale>Users who customize and then forget their changes have no recovery path without a reset option.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/flexibility-audit.md">Audit template for shortcuts, customization, alternative paths, and power-user features</reference>
  <reference path="scripts/find-shortcuts.sh">Script to extract keyboard shortcut bindings from a JS/TS codebase</reference>
</text>
