<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Flexibility and Efficiency — Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete good and bad examples of flexibility and efficiency implementation across real products.</summary>

  <section title="Good Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Figma: keyboard shortcuts for all tools, Quick Actions panel (Ctrl+/), custom keyboard shortcuts, plugins for power users, simple drag-and-drop for beginners. Layered acceleration at every level of expertise.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>VS Code: command palette (Ctrl+Shift+P) as universal accelerator, customizable everything via settings JSON, extension ecosystem, multiple keybinding profiles, settings sync. A single interface serving both casual text editing and professional development workflows.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Gmail: keyboard shortcuts (opt-in in settings, respects novice/expert split), quick settings vs. all settings (progressive disclosure), canned responses, filters and rules for automation, basic vs. advanced search.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No shortcuts: complex application where every action requires mouse navigation through nested menus.</description>
      <reason>Power users who perform the same actions hundreds of times per day are permanently blocked from efficiency gains. Adoption among expert users drops.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Expert-only interface: all options visible at all times, no progressive disclosure, new users overwhelmed on first use.</description>
      <reason>Novice abandonment rate is high when the cognitive load of first use exceeds the perceived value of the product. Onboarding completion drops.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No customization: fixed layout, cannot hide unused features, cannot pin frequently used actions.</description>
      <reason>Power users with established workflows cannot optimize the interface for their repeating task patterns. Efficiency plateau is set by the default configuration.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hidden accelerators: shortcuts exist but are not documented in menus, tooltips, or any discoverable location.</description>
      <reason>Undiscoverable shortcuts provide zero efficiency gain to users who have not memorized them from external documentation. The investment in building them is wasted.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Inconsistent shortcuts: Ctrl+D deletes in one part of the app but duplicates in another.</description>
      <reason>Inconsistent shortcuts violate user trust in the shortcut system; users stop using shortcuts entirely to avoid unexpected outcomes.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="User Spectrum Framework">
    <p>Design techniques by user type:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Novice: defaults that work without configuration, wizards for guided multi-step tasks, templates as starting points, tutorials, progressive disclosure</item>
      <item>Expert: shortcuts for frequent actions, batch operations, macros and automation, customization for personalized workflow, direct manipulation to skip wizards</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
