<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="flexibility-efficiency Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for flexibility-efficiency as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>No shortcuts: complex application where every action requires mouse navigation through nested menus.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Power users who perform the same actions hundreds of times per day are permanently blocked from efficiency gains. Adoption among expert users drops.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Expert-only interface: all options visible at all times, no progressive disclosure, new users overwhelmed on first use.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Novice abandonment rate is high when the cognitive load of first use exceeds the perceived value of the product. Onboarding completion drops.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>No customization: fixed layout, cannot hide unused features, cannot pin frequently used actions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Power users with established workflows cannot optimize the interface for their repeating task patterns. Efficiency plateau is set by the default configuration.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Hidden accelerators: shortcuts exist but are not documented in menus, tooltips, or any discoverable location.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Undiscoverable shortcuts provide zero efficiency gain to users who have not memorized them from external documentation. The investment in building them is wasted.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Inconsistent shortcuts: Ctrl+D deletes in one part of the app but duplicates in another.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Inconsistent shortcuts violate user trust in the shortcut system; users stop using shortcuts entirely to avoid unexpected outcomes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents generating shortcut tables often produce conflicts with Ctrl+W (close tab), Ctrl+T (new tab), Ctrl+P (print).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Common browser shortcuts are not always top-of-mind for agents; always run a conflict check pass before shipping.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>"Multiple paths" generated by agents may silently diverge in behavior (e.g., double-click edits inline, right-click opens modal).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Behavioral divergence between paths fragments user mental models; flag these for human review before implementation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents cannot observe actual shortcut adoption; efficiency gains claimed in an audit are hypotheses until measured.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Shortcut effectiveness must be validated through usage analytics; audit recommendations are feature hypotheses, not proven optimizations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Human checkpoint required for irreversible bulk operations: agent can design the UX pattern, but confirmation dialogs and undo mechanisms must be verified by a developer.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Data loss risk is too high to implement bulk destructive operations without developer review of the confirmation flow and undo mechanism.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
