<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Performance Architecture Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the performance-architecture methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale; the final rule is the skip-this-methodology gate referenced by the decision tree.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-numeric-slos-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>SLO targets MUST be numeric (p50 / p95 / p99 in ms; availability in %; error budget in %). Qualitative SLOs ('fast', 'snappy') MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE book — SLO chapter.">Numeric targets are testable; qualitative targets cannot be load-tested and become subjective.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-measure-before-optimising" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Performance work MUST start from a baseline measurement (k6 / vegeta report). Optimisations MUST cite which percentile improves and by how much.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brendan Gregg — Systems Performance; perf-regression postmortems.">Optimisation without baseline is intuition-driven; 'rocket science' fixes often hurt the percentile that mattered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-cache-from-edge-inward" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cache layers MUST be applied edge-inward: CDN first for static + GET-cacheable, application cache (Redis) for hot reads, DB-level cache last. Skipping a layer to cache deeper requires explicit justification.</statement>
      <rationale source="CDN provider whitepapers; performance audit playbooks.">Edge cache shaves latency + cost the most; in-layer caching shifts but does not remove load.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-load-test-matches-slo" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The load-test gate MUST encode the SLO as thresholds (e.g. k6 thresholds, vegeta success rate). A test that passes while the SLO is missed is a defective test.</statement>
      <rationale source="k6 / Grafana load-test best practices.">SLO and load-test are the same contract; divergence is a latent regression source.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-scaling-trigger-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST name observable scaling triggers (CPU%, queue depth, p95 latency growth) with thresholds; auto-scaling configs MUST match the triggers.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kubernetes HPA / autoscaling postmortems.">Scaling triggered by gut produces flapping; named observable triggers tie capacity to user-visible signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When prerequisites hold (SLOs, baseline, top-3 endpoints, cache topology), apply r1 → r2 → r3 → r4 → r5 and emit the spec.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology design — gate rule.">Order encodes risk: numeric SLO first, baseline second, cache plan third, gate fourth, scaling fifth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do NOT use when (a) no latency contract exists, (b) requirements unstable, (c) headroom already &gt; 50% and SLOs met. Note constraint and exit.</statement>
      <rationale source="Preconditions — skip gate.">Spec ceremony in these contexts wastes review time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
