<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="methodologies-detail">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>Flat reference bundling 20 research methodologies as a human-readable cheat sheet with abridged summaries and agent modes. Canonical copies live in per-methodology folders.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>reference</tag>
      <tag>methodology-index</tag>
      <tag>research-methods</tag>
      <tag>cheat-sheet</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Methodologies Detail Reference</title>
    <summary>A flat reference page bundling 20 research methodologies extracted from SKILL.md v1.1 as a human-readable cheat sheet. This is not a standalone methodology - it is a TOC with abridged summaries. The canonical agent-actionable copies live in per-methodology folders under pro/research/researcher/ and pro/research/market-researcher/ and pro/research/user-researcher/.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Large codebases benefit from a single skim-readable page covering all methodology names, their frameworks, and their agent modes. This page serves that role for anyone scanning the research methodology suite without committing to deep dives on each methodology.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Human wants a quick overview of all 20 research methodologies and their agent modes in one place</item>
        <item>Agent needs to confirm a methodology name before routing to its canonical folder</item>
        <item>Generating a TOC or cross-reference for documentation</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>As the execution reference for any specific methodology - open the methodology's own folder instead</item>
        <item>For agent-integration patterns, prompt templates, or CLI tools - those live in per-methodology content files in the new shape</item>
        <item>For mode routing in orchestrators - use the Research Modes table in the parent CLAUDE.md file instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="reference-usage">
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat this page as a TOC and cheat-sheet only. Do not parse it as the source of truth for any single methodology. Fields are abridged and stub descriptions.</statement>
        <rationale>For real execution, route to the per-methodology folder. The mode to methodology map already lives in the parent CLAUDE.md file; use that for orchestrator routing.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="idea-generation-methods">
      <p>Idea generation and screening methodologies:</p>
      <list>
        <item>idea-generation - 7 Ps framework (Pain, Passion, Profession, Process, Platform, People, Product). Score each idea: Market size plus Your fit plus Urgency, max 15. Top 3 scores proceed to validation. Agent mode: ideas.</item>
        <item>paul-graham-questions - 4 questions: What is tedious but necessary? What is surprisingly hard? What do you build for yourself? What would you pay for that does not exist? Agent mode: ideas.</item>
        <item>pain-point-research - Complaint audit, workaround inventory, tool stack analysis, time tracker. Score: frequency 30%, intensity 30%, current solutions 20%, ability to solve 20%. Agent mode: ideas.</item>
        <item>niche-evaluation - 5-dimension scoring: Market size, Competition, Barriers, Monetization, Your fit (1-5 each, max 25). Proceed: 20-25. Caution: 15-19. Needs pivot: 10-14. Pass: below 10. Agent mode: niche.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="market-analysis">
      <p>Market analysis and competitive intelligence methodologies:</p>
      <list>
        <item>market-research-tam-sam-som - TAM (total addressable), SAM (serviceable), SOM (obtainable Year 1). Three methods: top-down, bottom-up, value theory. SOM typically 1-5% of SAM. Agent mode: market.</item>
        <item>trend-analysis - Macro (5-10yr), industry (2-5yr), micro (6-24mo) trend categories. Assess: growth drivers, adoption curve position, threats, timing (too early / just right / too late). Agent mode: market.</item>
        <item>competitor-analysis - Identify direct, indirect, future competitors. Map on positioning matrix. Analyse 8 dimensions. Find gaps (feature, quality, audience, price, experience). Differentiation statement. Agent mode: competitors.</item>
        <item>competitive-intelligence - Feature inventory across top 5 competitors. Feature matrix (Y/P/N per competitor). Gap categories: nobody has it, 1-2 have it (opportunity), everyone has it (table stakes). Validate gap before building. Agent mode: competitors.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="user-research">
      <p>User research and validation methodologies:</p>
      <list>
        <item>user-interviews - Problem, solution, usability interview types. 45-min structure: warm-up, current state, pain exploration, solution probing, wrap-up. Golden rules: talk less than 20%, ask about past behavior not future intent. Agent mode: validate.</item>
        <item>jobs-to-be-done - JTBD statement: When I [situation], I want to [action], so I can [outcome]. Three job dimensions: functional, emotional, social. Hiring and firing framework. Agent mode: personas.</item>
        <item>persona-building - 5 components: demographics, behaviors, pain points, goals, verbatim quote. Types: primary, secondary, negative. Minimum 5-10 interviews before building. Agent mode: personas.</item>
        <item>problem-validation - 5 criteria: frequency weekly or more, intensity 7+/10, willingness to pay, search volume exists, competition exists. Evidence types: verbatim quotes (strong), forum discussions (medium), competitor existence (weak). Agent mode: validate.</item>
        <item>pain-point-mining - Sources: Reddit, Twitter, app reviews, Quora, forums, LinkedIn. Search patterns: "[keyword] frustrating" site:reddit.com, "[competitor] alternative" site:reddit.com. Collect 50+ mentions, categorize by theme, count frequency. Agent mode: pains.</item>
        <item>customer-interview-framework - 4 interview types by stage: discovery, problem, solution, usability. Flow: warm-up, context, deep dive, concept test, wrap-up. Question types: open, probing, clarifying, summary. Anti-patterns: leading questions, future hypotheticals, pitching. Agent mode: validate.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="business-model-planning">
      <p>Business model and pricing research methodologies:</p>
      <list>
        <item>niche-viability-scoring - 5-criteria weighted model: Market size 25%, Competition 20%, Barriers 20%, Profitability 20%, Your fit 15%. Score 1-10 with justification. Decision thresholds: 7.5 or higher strong, 5.5-7.4 caution, 3.5-5.4 risks, below 3.5 pass. Agent mode: niche.</item>
        <item>business-model-research - Red vs Blue Ocean. Four actions framework: Eliminate, Reduce, Raise, Create. Strategy canvas: X-axis key competing factors, Y-axis offering level. Find uncontested space. Agent mode: niche.</item>
        <item>value-proposition-design - Customer profile: jobs, pains, gains. Value map: products/services, pain relievers, gain creators. FIT equals pain relievers address top pains plus gain creators enable top gains. Focus on pains rated 8+/10. Agent mode: personas.</item>
        <item>pricing-research - Six models: freemium, subscription, usage-based, one-time, tiered, per-seat. Selection criteria: value delivery, usage patterns, customer type, competition, marginal cost. Research: list 5 competitors pricing, calculate value delivered, Van Westendorp survey, test with early users. Agent mode: pricing.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="naming-and-domains">
      <p>Naming and domain availability methodologies:</p>
      <list>
        <item>project-naming - 7 strategies: descriptive, invented, compound, metaphor, portmanteau, alliteration, acronym. Good name criteria: easy to spell, pronounce, memorable, domain available (.com preferred), no trademark conflicts, works internationally. Generate 20+ candidates before checking availability. Agent mode: names.</item>
        <item>domain-availability - Check priority: .com (essential), .io (acceptable for tech), .co (alternative), GitHub username, Twitter handle, LinkedIn page. Alternative strategies: add "get" or "try" prefix, "app" or "hq" suffix, different TLD. Agent: faion-domain-checker-agent.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </content>
</methodology>
