<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-assessment-framework" title="Solution Assessment Framework">
  <summary>Four assessment types, five-step evaluation process, assessment criteria categories, and triggers for each assessment horizon.</summary>

  <section title="Assessment Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select assessment type before gathering evidence; each type has a different question and artefact.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing assessment types produces evidence that answers the wrong question — testing deployment readiness with post-implementation metrics, or measuring business value during the design phase.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Design Assessment (during design): validate the proposed solution design against requirements.</item>
      <item>Implementation Assessment (during build): verify correct implementation at sprint boundaries.</item>
      <item>Deployment Assessment (at go-live): confirm readiness across QA, training, ops, support, security, compliance workstreams.</item>
      <item>Post-Implementation Assessment (after deployment): measure actual value delivered against the original business case.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-Step Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run assessment as a five-step linear pipeline; do not skip or reorder steps.</statement>
      <rationale>Step 3 (business value evaluation) depends on Step 1 criteria and Step 2 compliance data; skipping or reordering produces variance columns filled with storytelling rather than measurement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Define criteria: business value, functional, performance, usability, compliance.</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Assess against requirements: compare solution to each requirement, classify as met/partial/not met/deprecated.</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Evaluate business value: measure delivered value against baseline, target, and variance.</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Identify limitations: document gaps with impact and workaround columns.</item>
      <item>Step 5 — Recommend action: accept / accept with conditions / require changes / reject.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add "deprecated" as a first-class requirement status alongside met/partial/not met; do not force stale requirements into not-met.</statement>
      <rationale>Forcing every legacy requirement written 9 months before go-live into met/not-met inflates the not-met count and wastes remediation tokens on requirements that were consciously retired.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Assessment Triggers">
    <list>
      <item>Design complete → Design review.</item>
      <item>Sprint complete → Implementation check.</item>
      <item>Before go-live → Deployment readiness (gate: all workstreams ready/conditional/blocked with one evidence item each).</item>
      <item>30 days post go-live → Initial post-implementation assessment.</item>
      <item>90 days post go-live → Full post-implementation assessment.</item>
      <item>Annually → Ongoing value assessment.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Independence Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Route the assessment through someone whose compensation does not depend on the verdict; do not let the project sponsor's team self-assess.</statement>
      <rationale>BABOK Solution Evaluation explicitly requires independence; assessments conducted by teams whose bonuses depend on the outcome systematically overstate value realization.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/solution-assessment-report.md">Full assessment report template with requirements compliance, business value, and recommendations.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/post-implementation-review.md">Post-go-live review covering business outcomes, adoption metrics, and lessons learned.</reference>
</text>
