<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="solution-assessment Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for solution-assessment. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select assessment type before gathering evidence; each type has a different question and artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixing assessment types produces evidence that answers the wrong question — testing deployment readiness with post-implementation metrics, or measuring business value during the design phase.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run assessment as a five-step linear pipeline; do not skip or reorder steps.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Step 3 (business value evaluation) depends on Step 1 criteria and Step 2 compliance data; skipping or reordering produces variance columns filled with storytelling rather than measurement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Add "deprecated" as a first-class requirement status alongside met/partial/not met; do not force stale requirements into not-met.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Forcing every legacy requirement written 9 months before go-live into met/not-met inflates the not-met count and wastes remediation tokens on requirements that were consciously retired.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Route the assessment through someone whose compensation does not depend on the verdict; do not let the project sponsor's team self-assess.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">BAKOK Solution Evaluation explicitly requires independence; assessments conducted by teams whose bonuses depend on the outcome systematically overstate value realization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Force every requirements compliance row to include an evidence_ref that resolves to a source; drop any row where evidence is missing rather than inventing a value.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs will fill in "actual" values when evidence is missing; fabricated metrics produce false accept/reject verdicts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Generate the recommendation as a single enum (accept | accept_with_conditions | require_changes | reject) before any prose; prose must be derived from, not instead of, the enum.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLM recommendation prose hedges by default ("consider exploring"); forcing an enum first prevents verdict ambiguity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
