<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="solution-assessment Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for solution-assessment as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Capturing the baseline at assessment time rather than at requirements freeze.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The "baseline" silently becomes "yesterday" and variance is zero by construction — the assessment proves nothing and is unfalsifiable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating requirements compliance as equivalent to value realization: reporting "100% requirements met" without measuring business outcomes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A solution can be 100% requirements-met and 0% value-realized; the report must surface the functional-met vs benefit-realized split explicitly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Reporting metric variance (e.g., revenue +18%) as caused by the solution without controlling for external factors.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Market tailwinds, competitor outages, or compensation-plan changes can produce the same variance. Without a control group or diff-in-diff, confidence must be marked low and external factors flagged.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Running a single 30-day post-launch assessment and treating it as definitive.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>At 30 days, users are in honeymoon mode; 12-month assessments consistently show lower satisfaction and surfaced friction that the 30-day report misses. One-shot assessments systematically overstate success.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Assessing adoption (usage rate) as a proxy for value delivered.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mandatory rollouts always show high adoption; only paired cycle-time or output metrics reveal whether the adoption was beneficial or destructive.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>User satisfaction surveys that do not reconcile survey respondent count against active-user count.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Surveys reach still-active users; n=50 with a 4.2 score can hide 200 silent leavers. Always cross-reference survey n against active user count; reject satisfaction claims where n/active-users is below a documented threshold (e.g., 10%).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
