<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="star-interview-framework">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>hr-recruiter</domain>
    <summary>Structured behavioral interviewing using STAR (Situation-Task-Action-Result) to force candidate specificity and comparability. Past behavior is the strongest predictor of job performance.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>behavioral-interview</tag>
      <tag>star</tag>
      <tag>hiring</tag>
      <tag>interview-technique</tag>
      <tag>structured-hiring</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>interview</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>STAR Interview Framework</title>
    <summary>The STAR framework (Situation-Task-Action-Result) is a structured behavioral interviewing technique that elicits four-part responses from candidates, forcing specificity and comparability across candidates. Without a response framework, candidates give generic, hypothetical, or team-credit answers that interviewers cannot score or compare. STAR follow-up probes force specificity; scored against a rubric, STAR responses become defensible hiring evidence.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Without a response framework, candidates give generic, hypothetical, or team-credit answers that interviewers cannot score or compare. STAR follow-up probes ("What was YOUR role, not the team's?", "What were the specific numbers?") force specificity. Scored against a rubric, STAR responses become defensible hiring evidence rather than gut impression.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Behavioral rounds in any structured interview process.</item>
        <item>Evaluating leadership, communication, collaboration, adaptability, or problem-solving competencies.</item>
        <item>Building a question bank for a new role or competency model.</item>
        <item>Training interviewers who ask vague or hypothetical questions.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Technical skills assessment (live coding, system design) — STAR is not the right structure.</item>
        <item>Screening for factual qualifications (certifications, tool experience) — a direct question is faster.</item>
        <item>When the candidate has very limited work history (new grads) — combine with situational ("What would you do if...") questions.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="star-components">
      <p>A complete STAR response requires all four components; accept nothing as evidence until the Action and Result are specific and attributable to the candidate personally.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>A complete STAR response requires all four components; accept nothing as evidence until the Action and Result are specific and attributable to the candidate personally.</statement>
        <rationale>Candidates default to team-credit framing ("we delivered...") and omit results because they are uncertain what to share. Probing for personal contribution and quantified outcomes converts vague stories into scorable evidence.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="component-definitions">
        <p>Situation: the context or background — who, what, when, what was at stake. The interviewer prompt: "Tell me about a time when..."</p>
        <p>Task: the candidate's specific responsibility in the situation — not the team's goal, the candidate's goal. Probe: "What was your role specifically?"</p>
        <p>Action: what the candidate specifically did — concrete steps in first-person singular. Probe: "Walk me through exactly what YOU did, not what the team did."</p>
        <p>Result: the outcome and its scope — quantified where possible, time-bounded, learning noted. Probe: "What was the outcome? What changed as a result? What would you do differently?"</p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="interview-flow">
      <rule>
        <statement>Follow the four-step flow for every behavioral question: ask, listen for the Situation, probe for missing Task and Action specificity, confirm the Result.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping probes when the story sounds good is the primary source of false positives. Compelling narratives often lack the candidate's personal contribution — probing exposes whether the role was central or peripheral.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Step 1: Ask the behavioral question. Let the candidate answer without interruption.</item>
        <item>Step 2: Listen for Situation. Note: is the context specific? Is there a timeframe? Who was involved?</item>
        <item>Step 3: Probe for Task and Action. Ask: "What was your specific responsibility?" and "Walk me through exactly what you did." Distinguish personal action from team action.</item>
        <item>Step 4: Confirm the Result. Ask: "What was the outcome?" and "What metrics can you share?" and "What did you learn?" If the result is vague, ask: "What would have happened if you hadn't done that?"</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="follow-up-probes">
      <section name="clarification-probes">
        <p>"Can you be more specific about [the situation / the decision / the outcome]?"</p>
        <p>"When did this happen? How long did it take?"</p>
      </section>
      <section name="personal-contribution-probes">
        <p>"What was YOUR contribution versus the team's?"</p>
        <p>"If you hadn't been involved, what would have happened?"</p>
        <p>"Who else was involved? What did they do specifically?"</p>
      </section>
      <section name="quantification-probes">
        <p>"What were the specific numbers or metrics?"</p>
        <p>"How did you measure success?"</p>
        <p>"How does that compare to before you made the change?"</p>
      </section>
      <section name="learning-probes">
        <p>"What would you do differently if you faced this again?"</p>
        <p>"What did you learn from this experience?"</p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="response-patterns">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Complete STAR: "When the migration project fell 3 weeks behind (S), I was responsible for unblocking the backend team's dependency on the data model changes (T). I held daily standups with the data team, reprioritized 4 schema changes to unblock the critical path, and shipped a compatibility shim that let both teams work in parallel (A). We recovered 2 of the 3 weeks and launched within 1 week of the original date; the shim became a pattern two other teams adopted (R)."</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Missing Action: "The project was falling behind, so our team fixed the dependency issues and we hit the deadline." No personal contribution visible; probe required: "What specifically did you do to fix the dependency issues?"</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Missing Result: "I led a cross-functional team and we worked really hard on the migration." No outcome; probe required: "What was the result of the migration? Did you hit the deadline? What changed for the users?"</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Hypothetical answer: "I would approach a situation like that by first aligning stakeholders, then setting up a project plan..." The question asked for a past example. Probe: "Can you give me a specific situation where you actually did this?"</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="question-bank">
      <section name="leadership">
        <rule>
          <statement>Use leadership questions for any role where the candidate will influence, direct, or develop others; do not assume leadership only applies to management titles.</statement>
          <rationale>Individual contributors lead without authority (technical decisions, driving standards, unblocking teammates). Leadership questions reveal influence mechanisms, not just direct-report management.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>"Tell me about a time you led a team through a significant change."</item>
          <item>"Describe a situation where you had to motivate an underperforming team member."</item>
          <item>"Give an example of when you made an unpopular decision and how you handled the pushback."</item>
          <item>"Tell me about a time you delegated an important task. What did you delegate and why?"</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="problem-solving">
        <rule>
          <statement>Prefer problem-solving questions where the candidate had incomplete information or time pressure; easy problems with clear solutions produce undifferentiated responses.</statement>
          <rationale>Problem-solving under ambiguity is the most differentiating signal for IC and manager roles. Questions about "a complex problem" without constraints invite retrospective polishing; adding "with incomplete information" or "under pressure" reduces the ability to construct a generic answer.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>"Describe a complex problem you solved at work."</item>
          <item>"Tell me about a time you had to make an important decision with incomplete information."</item>
          <item>"Give an example of when you identified a problem before others on the team noticed it."</item>
          <item>"Describe a time you had to troubleshoot a critical issue under time pressure."</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="communication">
        <list>
          <item>"Tell me about a time you had to deliver difficult feedback or news to someone."</item>
          <item>"Describe a situation where you had to persuade someone to change their position."</item>
          <item>"Give an example of when you had to explain something complex to a non-technical audience."</item>
          <item>"Tell me about a miscommunication that caused a problem. How did you resolve it?"</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="collaboration">
        <rule>
          <statement>Include at least one conflict or disagreement question in every behavioral loop; candidates who only describe smooth collaboration have not been stress-tested on the most predictive dimension.</statement>
          <rationale>How candidates describe conflict reveals their conflict resolution style, attribution tendencies (self-blame vs. other-blame), and ability to sustain relationships under stress — all strong predictors of team performance.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>"Describe a successful cross-functional project you worked on. What made it succeed?"</item>
          <item>"Tell me about a time you had a conflict with a colleague or stakeholder. How did you handle it?"</item>
          <item>"Give an example of when you had to work with someone whose working style differed significantly from yours."</item>
          <item>"Describe how you built a working relationship with a key stakeholder who was initially skeptical."</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="adaptability">
        <list>
          <item>"Tell me about a time you had to adapt to a major change in your role, team, or company direction."</item>
          <item>"Describe a situation where priorities suddenly shifted and you had to pivot your work."</item>
          <item>"Give an example of when you had to learn something new quickly under pressure."</item>
          <item>"Tell me about a time you failed at something important. What did you do, and what did you learn?"</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/star-scorecard.md" purpose="Per-question STAR scoring grid with component scores and overall hire recommendation."/>
      <template path="templates/interviewer-guide.md" purpose="Before/during/after interview checklist for hiring managers using STAR."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="star-interview-method"/>
      <ref slug="structured-interview-design"/>
      <ref slug="interview-methods"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
