<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="frontend" count="132">
  <methodology slug="CLAUDE-methodologies" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/CLAUDE-methodologies">
    <summary>Index and selection guide for 32 core UX methodologies covering Nielsen's 10 usability heuristics, 6 research methods (interviews, usability testing, surveys, card sorting, personas, journey mapping), 9 design methods (wireframing, prototyping, A/B testing, heuristic evaluation, cognitive walkthrough, and others), and 7 advanced topics (IA framework, IA templates, mobile UX, voice UI, diary studies, competitive analysis, content audit).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="a11y-annotation-pattern-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/a11y-annotation-pattern-library">
    <summary>A reusable library of accessibility annotations keyed to component archetypes so a11y is specified during design, not bolted on after.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="a11y-audit-per-screen-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/a11y-audit-per-screen-checklist">
    <summary>Concrete operating checklist covering a11y audit per screen checklist — the small set of items a practitioner runs every cycle so nothing high-leverage gets skipped.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ab-testing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/ab-testing">
    <summary>A/B testing is a controlled experiment that compares two versions of a UI element (control A vs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="accessibility" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/accessibility">
    <summary>Web accessibility: make interfaces perceivable, operable, understandable, and robust for all users including those using assistive technologies.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="accessibility-as-code" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/accessibility-as-code">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for accessibility as code that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="accessibility-evaluation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/accessibility-evaluation">
    <summary>A five-stage audit process for WCAG 2.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="accessibility-first-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/accessibility-first-design">
    <summary>A design-phase methodology that prevents 70-80% of WCAG 2.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ada-title-ii-compliance-2026" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/ada-title-ii-compliance-2026">
    <summary>A compliance methodology for US state and local government digital services required to meet WCAG 2.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="adobe-firefly-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/adobe-firefly-integration">
    <summary>Workflow for integrating Adobe Firefly generative AI into Creative Cloud pipelines — structured image brief generation (positive prompt, negative prompt, style preset, aspect ratio), batch generation via Firefly Services API (enterprise), and brand-compliance auditing of generated assets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="adobe-firefly-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ui-designer/adobe-firefly-integration">
    <summary>Use Adobe Firefly Services REST API to batch-generate commercial-safe images, apply Generative Fill to placeholder regions, and produce vector assets from text prompts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aesthetic-minimalist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/aesthetic-minimalist">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #8: Interfaces should not contain information which is irrelevant or rarely needed.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-accessibility-automation-2026" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/ai-accessibility-automation-2026">
    <summary>Methodology for integrating AI-powered tools into accessibility workflows: automated WCAG scanning, AI-assisted issue triage and code remediation, VPAT 2.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-assisted-accessibility" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/ai-assisted-accessibility">
    <summary>Pipeline for WCAG 2.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-design-assistant-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/ai-design-assistant-patterns">
    <summary>Methodology for selecting and specifying AI assistant interaction patterns within design tools: sidebar (persistent, long tasks), modal (single-shot high-stakes generation), and inline (micro-suggestions on selection).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-design-assistant-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ui-designer/ai-design-assistant-patterns">
    <summary>Four interaction patterns for embedding AI assistance into design tools: sidebar (always-on contextual suggestions), modal (focused batch generation), inline (micro-corrections on selected elements), and review (audit passes against a structured rubric).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-enhanced-design-systems" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/ai-enhanced-design-systems">
    <summary>AI tooling for scaling design systems with a solid token foundation: automated documentation generation from component source, token violation scanning, Figma-to-code diff, and variant generation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-enhanced-design-systems" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ui-designer/ai-enhanced-design-systems">
    <summary>AI scales a mature design system by automating component documentation, detecting hardcoded token violations, and generating variant permutations — but only when the system already has well-defined tokens, systematic component structure, and clear naming conventions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-generated-layout-review-checklist" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/ai-generated-layout-review-checklist">
    <summary>Ten-point checklist for reviewing AI-generated mockups (v0, Galileo, Figma Make, Midjourney UI prompts) before they enter a design system or ship to engineering.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-plugin-ecosystem" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/ai-plugin-ecosystem">
    <summary>Figma's plugin ecosystem accelerates repetitive design tasks but lacks a stable external API surface.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-plugin-ecosystem" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ui-designer/ai-plugin-ecosystem">
    <summary>Figma AI plugins (Magician, Automator, Content Reel, Stark, Similayer, Diagram) automate repetitive design tasks within the Figma canvas.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-spatial-computing" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/ai-spatial-computing">
    <summary>Spatial interfaces generate complex contextual data that static UI rules cannot handle.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ar-design-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/ar-design-patterns">
    <summary>AR must blend seamlessly with the real world.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="card-sorting" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/card-sorting">
    <summary>Ask users to organize content topics into groups and label those groups, revealing how users mentally categorize information.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cognitive-inclusion-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/cognitive-inclusion-design">
    <summary>A design methodology that reduces cognitive load and adapts interfaces for users with ADHD, autism spectrum, dyslexia, dyscalculia, anxiety, low literacy, and aging cognition through structural patterns (chunking, predictability, progress indicators) and optional settings (focus mode, dyslexia font, reduced motion, extended time limits).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cognitive-walkthrough" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/cognitive-walkthrough">
    <summary>A structured expert-inspection method that evaluates interface learnability by stepping through a known correct action sequence and answering four questions per step: does the user know what to do, can they see how, does the label make sense, and do they get feedback that it worked?.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitive-analysis" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/competitive-analysis">
    <summary>A structured method for examining 3-5 direct competitors, 2-3 indirect, and 1-2 aspirational examples against consistent evaluation criteria (features, user flows, UI patterns, IA, error handling, mobile experience).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="consistency-standards" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/consistency-standards">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #4: users should not wonder whether different words, situations, or actions mean the same thing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="content-audit" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/content-audit">
    <summary>A content audit is a systematic review of all content on a website or application — cataloging what exists, evaluating quality (accuracy, relevance, quality on a 1-5 scale), and deciding Keep / Update / Rewrite / Remove per item.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contextual-inquiry" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/contextual-inquiry">
    <summary>Contextual inquiry is a semi-structured interview method conducted in the user's environment while they perform their actual work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="core-vui-design-principles" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/core-vui-design-principles">
    <summary>Three foundational principles for voice user interfaces — simplicity (short, single-idea responses), natural conversation (follow-up awareness, human turn-taking), and context awareness (remembering prior turns, adapting to preferences) — that apply to all voice runtimes from Alexa Skills to LLM-powered Realtime API agents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="core-vui-design-principles" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/core-vui-design-principles">
    <summary>Three testable principles for voice user interface design: (1) Simplicity — one idea per turn, no redundant phrasing; (2) Natural conversation — sound human, offer one helpful follow-up; (3) Context awareness — use prior turns implicitly, never restate what the user just said.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-platform-token-distribution" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/cross-platform-token-distribution">
    <summary>Design tokens define a system's colors, spacing, typography, and other design properties.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-platform-token-distribution" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/cross-platform-token-distribution">
    <summary>A pipeline pattern for distributing design tokens from a single source (Tokens Studio / Figma) to multiple platform outputs — CSS variables, SCSS maps, iOS Swift, Android XML, React Native — using Style Dictionary as the transform engine.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="css-in-js-advanced" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/css-in-js-advanced">
    <summary>Zero-runtime CSS-in-JS (vanilla-extract, Panda CSS, StyleX) extracts styles at build time, producing plain CSS with no runtime serialization cost.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="css-in-js-basics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/css-in-js-basics">
    <summary>Runtime CSS-in-JS (styled-components, Emotion) co-locates styles with React/Vue components and enables prop-driven dynamic styling via a typed ThemeProvider.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-critique" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/design-critique">
    <summary>Design critique is a structured conversation about a design where participants analyze work against defined goals and principles, providing specific and actionable feedback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-review-facilitation-script" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ui-designer/design-review-facilitation-script">
    <summary>A 60-minute design-review facilitation script: agenda curation, time-boxing per artifact, structured feedback prompts, and action capture so the weekly review produces decisions not vibes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-system-success-factors" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/design-system-success-factors">
    <summary>Design systems fail most often not from technical debt but from governance and adoption gaps: no single owner, documentation that drifts from source, components teams work around.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-system-success-factors" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/design-system-success-factors">
    <summary>Four pillars that determine whether a design system succeeds: clear ownership (single DRI per pillar, not a committee), usable components (actually adoptable at v0), strong documentation (discoverable, non-decaying), and real adoption (measured across product, brand, and marketing).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-to-dev-handoff" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ui-designer/design-to-dev-handoff">
    <summary>Canonical design-to-dev handoff bundle and acceptance checklist that survives AI-generated Figma frames: tokens, states, motion, accessibility, and content rules end-to-end.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-tokens-basics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/design-tokens-basics">
    <summary>Design tokens are the atomic values of a design system — colors, spacing, typography, radii, shadows — stored as platform-agnostic data.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-tokens-fundamentals" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/design-tokens-fundamentals">
    <summary>Three-tier token architecture (primitive, semantic, component) keeps single source of truth via W3C DTCG JSON and Style Dictionary.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-tokens-fundamentals" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ui-designer/design-tokens-fundamentals">
    <summary>Design tokens are named, platform-agnostic values (colors, spacing, typography) organized in a three-tier hierarchy — global (raw values) → semantic (intent aliases) → component (scoped) — that enable consistent theming, dark mode, and single-source-of-truth updates across platforms.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-tokens-implementation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/design-tokens-implementation">
    <summary>Design tokens form a three-layer hierarchy — primitives (raw hex/rem), semantic (bg.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="diary-studies" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/diary-studies">
    <summary>A longitudinal UX research method where participants self-record experiences in the moment over days or weeks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="edge-case-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ui-designer/edge-case-checklist">
    <summary>Enumerated edge-case checklist (empty, long-content, slow-network, offline, error, permission-denied, etc.) applied at design handoff to catch state gaps before dev.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="enterprise-xr-applications" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/enterprise-xr-applications">
    <summary>Enterprise needs differ from consumer XR experiences.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="enterprise-xr-applications" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/enterprise-xr-applications">
    <summary>Methodology for designing XR (AR/VR/MR) applications for enterprise contexts: long-session comfort, tool integration, security, accessibility compliance, and ROI-measurable outcomes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-handling-in-vui" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/error-handling-in-vui">
    <summary>A three-rung re-prompt ladder for voice interface error recovery: rung 1 — brief re-ask; rung 2 — constructive re-ask with two example phrases; rung 3 — escalation to visual fallback, DTMF, or human agent.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-handling-in-vui" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/error-handling-in-vui">
    <summary>Voice recognition errors are unavoidable; the difference between a frustrating and a recoverable VUI is the error handling design.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-prevention" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/error-prevention">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #5: design out error conditions before they occur.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-recovery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/error-recovery">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #9: error messages must state what happened, why it happened, and how to fix it in plain language, without error codes, without blaming the user.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="figma-ai-ecosystem" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/figma-ai-ecosystem">
    <summary>Figma AI tools (Config 2025+) compress the prototype-to-stakeholder-review cycle from days to hours.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="figma-ai-ecosystem" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ui-designer/figma-ai-ecosystem">
    <summary>Figma's AI suite is UI-only with no agent API.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026">
    <summary>Methodology for selecting or recommending between Figma and Adobe Creative Cloud for product design teams in 2026 — using a weighted decision matrix scored against team use case, AI features, developer handoff, asset creation, enterprise security, and cost.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ui-designer/figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026">
    <summary>A structured decision methodology for choosing between Figma and Adobe Creative Cloud as the primary design platform for a team.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="flexibility-efficiency" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/flexibility-efficiency">
    <summary>Accelerators (keyboard shortcuts, batch operations, command palettes) speed expert workflows while remaining invisible to novices.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="focus-groups" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/focus-groups">
    <summary>A moderated qualitative method with 6–10 participants per group, 60–90 minutes, run in a minimum of 3 groups per segment before themes are treated as stable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="frontend-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/frontend-design">
    <summary>A four-phase workflow for UI surfaces where multiple visual directions are explored before committing: (1) capture requirements (type, style, tech), (2) brainstorm 3–5 distinct variants via agent into designs/variant-N-slug/, each with working code and a rationale, (3) user selects and refines, (4) Storybook agent builds stories and component agent finalizes typed components.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="generative-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/generative-ui-design">
    <summary>Methodology for using AI generation tools (v0 by Vercel, Claude Artifacts, Galileo, Uizard, Relume) to produce multiple UI variants rapidly in the ideation phase.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="generative-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ui-designer/generative-ui-design">
    <summary>Use AI tools (Galileo, Uizard, v0, Claude Artifacts, Relume) to generate multiple UI layout variants from a feature brief, then have a human select and refine.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="help-documentation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/help-documentation">
    <summary>Nielsen's Usability Heuristic #10: even though it is better if a system needs no documentation, help must be provided when needed.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="heuristic-evaluation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/heuristic-evaluation">
    <summary>A structured usability inspection method where 3-5 evaluators independently review an interface against Nielsen's 10 heuristics and rate each issue on a 0-4 severity scale (0=not a problem, 4=catastrophic).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="immersive-design-principles" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/immersive-design-principles">
    <summary>Immersive experiences (AR/VR/MR/XR) balance presence with comfort.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="information-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/information-architecture">
    <summary>Organize content by user tasks and goals.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="insight-to-design-ticket" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ui-designer/insight-to-design-ticket">
    <summary>A bridge protocol that converts research insights (interview tags, friction map findings) into ranked, design-ready backlog tickets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="journey-mapping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/journey-mapping">
    <summary>Visualize the complete experience a user has with a product over time — stages, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points, and opportunities.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-powered-conversational-ai" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/llm-powered-conversational-ai">
    <summary>Design and implementation methodology for conversational AI systems using LLMs — system prompt authoring with explicit topic boundaries, guardrail rules, fallback and escalation logic, and red-team testing for jailbreak vectors.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-powered-conversational-ai" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ui-designer/llm-powered-conversational-ai">
    <summary>Design and implement voice/text conversational interfaces backed by an LLM core (ASR → LLM → TTS pipeline) rather than rule-based NLU.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="match-real-world" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/match-real-world">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #2: the interface must use words, icons, and organizational patterns that match users' mental models — not internal system or developer terminology.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mobile-responsive" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/mobile-responsive">
    <summary>Mobile-first responsive design: base styles are unconditional (mobile), min-width queries layer up for larger screens.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mobile-ux" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/mobile-ux">
    <summary>Mobile UX requires mobile-first design (smallest screen first, then enhance), touch targets of at least 44x44pt (iOS) or 48x48dp (Android), primary actions in the thumb zone (bottom third of screen), and Core Web Vitals targets of LCP &lt; 2.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multimodal-vui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ux-ui-designer/multimodal-vui-design">
    <summary>Design methodology for interfaces that combine voice input with visual display — pattern-matching voice commands to on-screen card/carousel output while maintaining touch fallbacks for every voice state.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multimodal-vui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/ui-designer/multimodal-vui-design">
    <summary>Design voice + visual interfaces for smart displays by specifying four interaction patterns (voice-initiated screen-completed, screen-initiated voice-completed, voice + visual feedback, voice navigation + visual content) and enforcing a three-tier fallback hierarchy (voice → touch → keyboard).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="personas" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/personas">
    <summary>Personas are fictional characters representing key user types, based on research.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prototyping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/prototyping">
    <summary>Interactive product representation before code.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prototyping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ui-designer/prototyping">
    <summary>Prototyping is the practice of building interactive representations of a product — from paper sketches to code — at the fidelity level required to answer a specific learning objective before committing to production development.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pwa-advanced" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/pwa-advanced">
    <summary>Advanced PWA features: Web Push (VAPID subscribe → server send via `web-push`), offline data sync (IndexedDB queue + Background Sync API + retry), and update management (skipWaiting with user-visible banner).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pwa-core" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/pwa-core">
    <summary>A Progressive Web App requires three components: a Web App Manifest (manifest.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="recognition-over-recall" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/recognition-over-recall">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #6: minimize memory load by making options, actions, and context visible rather than requiring users to remember them.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="regulatory-compliance-2026" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/regulatory-compliance-2026">
    <summary>Accessibility regulation landscape shifted April 2026 (ADA Title II Final Rule → WCAG 2.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="semantic-tokens-and-modes" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/semantic-tokens-and-modes">
    <summary>A methodology for structuring design tokens in three explicit layers — reference (raw palette/scale), system (semantic, mode-aware), component (component-scoped) — and driving them through a four-stage pipeline: author (Figma Variables) → export (REST API) → transform (Style Dictionary) → consume (CSS/Swift/Compose).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="semantic-tokens-and-modes" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/semantic-tokens-and-modes">
    <summary>A semantic token layer maps primitive values (`color.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="seo-for-spas" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/seo-for-spas">
    <summary>A methodology for making JavaScript Single Page Applications indexable by search engines.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="shadcn-ui" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/shadcn-ui">
    <summary>shadcn/ui is a copy-in component system: primitives are copied to components/ui/ via the CLI (npx shadcn@latest add), not installed as an npm dependency.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="shadcn-ui-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/shadcn-ui-architecture">
    <summary>shadcn/ui components are vendored (copied, not installed as packages) into components/ui/.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-accessibility" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/spatial-accessibility">
    <summary>A methodology for designing AR/VR/MR interfaces that work across motor, visual, cognitive, and motion-sensitivity differences.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-computing-overview" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/spatial-computing-overview">
    <summary>Spatial computing blends digital content with physical space through AR, VR, and MR.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-computing-overview" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/spatial-computing-overview">
    <summary>Reference overview of spatial computing platforms, terminology, and market context for designers entering AR/VR/MR work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-design-tools" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/spatial-design-tools">
    <summary>A phase-gated tool selection methodology for spatial (AR/VR/MR) product workflows: concept in Figma + ShapesXR, prototype in Unity or Unreal, production in engine.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-design-tools" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/spatial-design-tools">
    <summary>Tool selection guide and design-to-development workflow for spatial (XR) design.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-interaction-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/spatial-interaction-patterns">
    <summary>Input modalities and interaction patterns for spatial (AR/VR/MR) computing: hand tracking, controllers, gaze, voice, and gesture.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-interaction-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/spatial-interaction-patterns">
    <summary>Reference for the five input modalities in spatial/XR interfaces (hand tracking, controllers, gaze, voice, gesture) and the three primary interaction patterns (direct manipulation, ray-casting, gaze+dwell) with their respective use cases, strengths, and accessibility implications.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-ui-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/spatial-ui-patterns">
    <summary>A pattern taxonomy for 3D user interfaces in AR/VR/MR: four panel types (world-locked, head-locked, body-locked, hand-attached), window management conventions, and ergonomic constraints (comfort distance ≥ 1 m, FoV occupancy ≤ 40°, touch targets ≥ 60×60 pt at 1 m).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-ui-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/spatial-ui-patterns">
    <summary>Panel anchoring, window management, and interaction rules for 3D/XR interfaces (visionOS, Meta Horizon OS, HoloLens, Android XR).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-ux-fundamentals" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/spatial-ux-fundamentals">
    <summary>Spatial UX organizes content in three physical zones: near field (0–1 m, primary interactions and controls), mid field (1–3 m, content consumption and work surfaces), far field (3 m+, ambient context and navigation aids).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-ux-fundamentals" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ui-designer/spatial-ux-fundamentals">
    <summary>Design principles for 3D/XR interfaces: place UI elements in near (0-1m), mid (1-3m), and far (3m+) field zones; specify element sizes in world units (meters) at placement distance; assign interaction modalities per platform constraints; and validate every layout in a physical headset before development begins.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="storybook-setup" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/storybook-setup">
    <summary>Storybook 8 with CSF 3 (Meta&lt;typeof Component&gt;, StoryObj, tags: ['autodocs']) wired to @storybook/addon-a11y, @storybook/addon-interactions, and Chromatic for visual regression.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="surveys" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/surveys">
    <summary>A research method for collecting structured data from large user populations through standardized questions — covering satisfaction (NPS, CSAT, SUS), task ease (SEQ), and feature preference — to quantify user attitudes and validate qualitative findings at scale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tailwind" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/tailwind">
    <summary>Tailwind CSS is a utility-first framework configured via tailwind.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tailwind-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/tailwind-architecture">
    <summary>Patterns for structuring Tailwind CSS in production React/Next.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tailwind-design-tokens" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/tailwind-design-tokens">
    <summary>Map design tokens (colors, spacing, typography) to Tailwind's theme config via CSS custom properties, so the design system and component library share a single source of truth.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tailwind-design-tokens" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ui-designer/tailwind-design-tokens">
    <summary>Integrating design tokens into Tailwind CSS by mapping token values to CSS custom properties and referencing them in `tailwind.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tailwind-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/tailwind-patterns">
    <summary>Tailwind Patterns covers reusable variant composition on top of an existing Tailwind project using `cva()` (class-variance-authority) for type-safe variant definitions and `cn()` (clsx + tailwind-merge) for conflict-safe class merging.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="testing-with-assistive-technology" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/testing-with-assistive-technology">
    <summary>A three-tier AT testing strategy: automated scan in CI (every PR), manual screen-reader and keyboard sweep (every release), user-with-disability session (quarterly).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="token-organization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/token-organization">
    <summary>A three-tier hierarchy for design tokens — primitives (raw values), semantic tokens (role-based aliases), and component tokens (scoped overrides) — combined with a `{category}.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="token-organization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/token-organization">
    <summary>A three-layer taxonomy — primitives (raw values) → semantic (purpose-based) → component (exceptions only) — plus a strict naming convention {category}.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tree-testing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/tree-testing">
    <summary>Tree testing evaluates the findability of topics in a website's hierarchy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ui-lib-basics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/ui-lib-basics">
    <summary>A UI component library provides reusable, accessible interface primitives (buttons, inputs, modals) built once and shared across features.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ui-lib-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/frontend-developer/ui-lib-patterns">
    <summary>Advanced patterns for UI libraries: compound components, accessible modal portals, and Storybook CSF 3 stories with testing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="usability-testing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/usability-testing">
    <summary>Observe real users completing tasks with a product to discover what works, what confuses, and where users struggle.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-control-freedom" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/user-control-freedom">
    <summary>Nielsen's Usability Heuristic #3: every interface must provide clearly marked "emergency exits" — undo, cancel, back, close, and reset — so users can recover from mistakes without going through extended processes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-interviews" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/user-interviews">
    <summary>User interviews are one-on-one conversations with users or potential users to understand needs, behaviors, motivations, and pain points.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="visibility-of-system-status" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/visibility-of-system-status">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #1: every user action must produce visible feedback within the appropriate time threshold — spinner for 1-3s, progress bar for 3-10s, progress bar with percentage and cancel for over 10s.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-ui" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/voice-ui">
    <summary>A methodology for designing speech-controlled interfaces — voice assistants, app voice commands, IVR systems — by writing sample dialogues first, then defining intents/slots, authoring prompts, and designing a 3-tier error-recovery ladder before any NLU training begins.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-ui-basics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ui-designer/voice-ui-basics">
    <summary>A process for designing voice user interfaces (VUI): write sample dialogues first, then extract intent/slot schemas, design prompts under 20 words, build a 3-attempt error recovery chain, and validate with Wizard of Oz testing before any NLU training begins.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-ui-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/voice-ui-patterns">
    <summary>Practical patterns for designing voice user interfaces: prompt writing rules, progressive error recovery (3-step ladder), multimodal voice+screen coordination, platform-specific constraints (Alexa, Google Actions, Siri), and key performance metrics.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vr-design-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/vr-design-patterns">
    <summary>User-centered VR design starts with comfort: place a visible ground plane and stable horizon, choose teleportation-first locomotion for novices, anchor UI to the world (not the head), and provide accessibility fallbacks including seated modes, subtitles, and one-handed control.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-accessibility-inclusivity" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/vui-accessibility-inclusivity">
    <summary>A methodology for designing voice interfaces that serve diverse user populations: non-native speakers, accented speech, elderly users, and those with motor or visual impairments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-conversation-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/vui-conversation-design">
    <summary>Design multi-turn voice conversations as state machines with explicit intents, entities, and prompts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-iot-integration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/vui-iot-integration">
    <summary>Smart home voice control requires cohesive intent design, multi-device synchronization, and explicit feedback for partial failures.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-iot-integration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/vui-iot-integration">
    <summary>Methodology for designing coherent voice control of smart home and IoT device ecosystems: command pattern taxonomy (direct control, scene activation, status query, conditional, scheduled), multi-device coordination flows, partial failure handling, and undo support.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-market-context" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/vui-market-context">
    <summary>Voice assistants are used by 8.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-privacy-security" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/vui-privacy-security">
    <summary>Voice interfaces handling personal data require privacy-by-design: transparency before capture, visual plus audio trust indicators, step-up authentication for sensitive actions, and PII redaction at transcript boundaries.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-privacy-security" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/vui-privacy-security">
    <summary>Five privacy principles (transparency, control, minimization, security, deletion) and a split-agent architecture for sensitive VUI operations: a policy classifier decides "is this turn sensitive?" and an executor crafts the response — the executor never sees raw sensitive values.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-testing-best-practices" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/vui-testing-best-practices">
    <summary>A four-layer VUI test strategy: unit (intent accuracy), integration (dialog flow completion), user (moderated session with 5+ real users), stress (noise, accents, interruptions).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="w3c-design-tokens-standard" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/w3c-design-tokens-standard">
    <summary>A methodology for authoring design tokens that conform to the W3C Design Tokens Community Group (DTCG) format module — using `$type`, `$value`, `$description`, and `{alias}` references — so that the same token file can round-trip between Figma, Style Dictionary v4, and native platforms without lossy remapping.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="w3c-design-tokens-standard" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ui-designer/w3c-design-tokens-standard">
    <summary>The W3C Design Tokens Community Group draft defines a vendor-neutral interchange format for design tokens using `$type` + `$value` + `$ref` fields.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="wcag-22-compliance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-ui-designer/wcag-22-compliance">
    <summary>WCAG 2.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="wireframing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-ui-designer/wireframing">
    <summary>Low-fidelity representations of UI structure, layout, and functionality without visual design details.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="wireframing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ui-designer/wireframing">
    <summary>Wireframes are low-fidelity structural representations of a UI — boxes, labels, and annotations without colors, images, or final copy — used to validate layout, hierarchy, and interaction behavior before any visual design begins.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
