<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="frontend" count="39" version="3.0" generated="2026-05-23">
  <description>L2 index of methodologies in the frontend domain. The retriever reads this after picking frontend from L1 domains.xml. Entries list slug + tier + summary; open the leaf AGENTS.md / content/*.xml for full payload.</description>
  <methodology slug="a11y-audit-per-screen-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/a11y-audit-per-screen-checklist">
    <summary>Per-screen accessibility audit checklist running 9 critical WCAG-AA checks (semantic landmarks, focus order, contrast, alt text, ARIA correctness, keyboard nav, error messaging, motion-respect, screen-reader labels); produces a per-screen pass/fail row set with named fixes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="accessibility" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/accessibility">
    <summary>Specification of accessibility expectations for a frontend codebase: WCAG-AA conformance target, tooling baseline, per-role responsibilities, and regression-prevention contract; produces an a11y spec that the team agrees to and that subsequent audits assert against.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="accessibility-as-code" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/accessibility-as-code">
    <summary>Pattern for asserting accessibility invariants in code: unit-level component contracts, integration-level axe assertions, and CI gates that block on critical violations; produces a code scaffold + CI config making a11y regressions impossible to merge silently.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="core-vui-design-principles" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/core-vui-design-principles">
    <summary>Three-pillar rubric (simplicity, naturalness, context-awareness) for auditing or designing voice-UI prompts: one idea per turn, no robotic phrasing, never restate what the user just said.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-platform-token-distribution" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/cross-platform-token-distribution">
    <summary>Pipeline spec for distributing design tokens from a single source (Tokens Studio / Figma) to CSS / SCSS / iOS Swift / Android XML / React Native using Style Dictionary, with CI-time drift detection.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="css-in-js-advanced" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/css-in-js-advanced">
    <summary>Advanced CSS-in-JS patterns covering SSR critical-CSS extraction, atomic compile-time variants, theme runtime swapping, and zero-runtime alternatives; produces a code scaffold + decision matrix selecting library (styled-components, Linaria, vanilla-extract, Panda CSS) per constraint.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="css-in-js-basics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/css-in-js-basics">
    <summary>Baseline patterns for CSS-in-JS in component libraries: prop-driven styles, theme provider, scoped class names, and TypeScript-typed style props; produces a starter scaffold matching the chosen library with naming + file-layout conventions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-system-success-factors" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/design-system-success-factors">
    <summary>Four-pillar rubric (ownership / usable components / strong docs / measured adoption) to grade a design system's health and pinpoint the weakest pillar before more components ship.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-tokens-basics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/design-tokens-basics">
    <summary>Baseline design-tokens spec covering canonical categories (color, spacing, typography, radius, shadow, motion), naming convention, alias-vs-base layering, and single-source-of-truth contract; produces a tokens.json spec consumed by both design tools and code.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-tokens-implementation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/design-tokens-implementation">
    <summary>Implementation playbook for design tokens: tokens.json schema, style-dictionary (or equivalent) build pipeline, CI sync to platform outputs, and a Figma-to-code round-trip; produces a working tokens repo with build + lint + sync scripts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="enterprise-xr-applications" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/enterprise-xr-applications">
    <summary>Spec for XR (AR/VR/MR) apps in enterprise contexts: long-session comfort budget, tool-integration map, security review, accessibility compliance, ROI-measurable outcomes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-handling-in-vui" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/error-handling-in-vui">
    <summary>Three-step error-recovery ladder (rapid reprompt → escalated prompt → bailout / escalate to human) spec for voice UIs: defines per-step copy, retry budget, telemetry, and escape route.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="frontend-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/frontend-design">
    <summary>Four-phase workflow exploring 3\u20135 distinct UI variants before committing to one: capture requirements, brainstorm via agent into designs/variant-N-slug/, user selects + refines, Storybook + component agents finalise; produces a design folder with N variants and a selected-variant manifest.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mobile-responsive" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/mobile-responsive">
    <summary>Mobile-first responsive design spec: breakpoint catalogue, container-query strategy, touch-target minimums, viewport-meta + safe-area handling, and per-component breakpoint policy; produces a spec the codebase asserts against in lint + tests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="nextjs-app-router" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/nextjs-app-router">
    <summary>Next.js App Router spec: route segments, layouts, loading/error boundaries, server vs client components, server actions, and data-fetch caching policy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pwa-advanced" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/pwa-advanced">
    <summary>Advanced PWA spec: Web Push (VAPID subscribe/send), offline data sync (IndexedDB queue + Background Sync + retry), and update management (skipWaiting + user banner).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pwa-core" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/pwa-core">
    <summary>PWA core spec: Web App Manifest (stable id + maskable icons), origin-root Service Worker, controllerchange-driven update flow, and Workbox caching strategies per route shape.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="react-component-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/react-component-architecture">
    <summary>React component architecture spec: feature-based module layout, colocation, compound components, data-vs-presentation split, and Suspense boundaries.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="semantic-tokens-and-modes" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/semantic-tokens-and-modes">
    <summary>Spec for a semantic-token layer (`color.surface.brand`, `color.text.muted`) sitting between primitives and components, with mode definitions (light/dark/high-contrast/density) and Figma variable bindings.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="seo-for-spas" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/seo-for-spas">
    <summary>SEO spec for JavaScript SPAs: SSR/SSG decision, structured-data scope, Core Web Vitals budgets, canonical/hreflang, and sitemap/robots wiring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="shadcn-ui" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/shadcn-ui">
    <summary>shadcn/ui spec: vendored copy-in components (npx shadcn add), Tailwind + Radix primitives, CVA variants, and per-component file ownership in components/ui/.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="shadcn-ui-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/shadcn-ui-architecture">
    <summary>shadcn/ui architecture spec: vendored components/ui/ layer, CVA + cn() helpers, design-token bridge to Tailwind config, and the lift-path from ui/ → composed feature components.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-computing-overview" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/spatial-computing-overview">
    <summary>Reference report of spatial-computing platforms (visionOS, Quest, HoloLens, Android XR), terminology (passthrough, anchoring, FOV, IPD), and market positioning to brief designers entering XR work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-design-tools" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/spatial-design-tools">
    <summary>Tool selection report and design-to-development workflow for spatial / XR design: Figma / Bezi / ShapesXR / Unity / Reality Composer Pro positioning, file handoff, and prototype-to-build path.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-interaction-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/spatial-interaction-patterns">
    <summary>Spec for the five spatial input modalities (hand tracking / controllers / gaze / voice / gesture) × three interaction patterns (direct manipulation / ray-casting / gaze-and-dwell) with use cases, strengths, and accessibility implications.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-ui-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/spatial-ui-patterns">
    <summary>Spec for panel anchoring (world / head / wrist), window management (single / tiled / stacked), and interaction rules for 3D / XR interfaces across visionOS / Meta Horizon / HoloLens / Android XR.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="storybook-setup" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/storybook-setup">
    <summary>Storybook 8 + CSF 3 config spec: Meta&lt;typeof Component&gt;, autodocs tags, a11y + interactions addons, and Chromatic visual-regression baseline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tailwind" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/tailwind">
    <summary>Tailwind CSS setup spec: tailwind.config.{ts,js} content paths, design-token theme extension, plugin set, and PurgeCSS-equivalent JIT discipline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tailwind-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/tailwind-architecture">
    <summary>Tailwind production architecture spec: design-tokens-as-CSS-variables, theme layers, component-variant strategy, and the layer/component-class escalation ladder.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tailwind-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/tailwind-patterns">
    <summary>Tailwind variant-composition spec: cva() (class-variance-authority) for type-safe variants and cn() (clsx + tailwind-merge) for conflict-safe class merging.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="token-organization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/token-organization">
    <summary>Three-layer taxonomy spec (primitive → semantic → component-exception) plus strict `{category}.{role}.{state}` naming rules for design tokens so the system stays navigable past 500 tokens.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ui-lib-basics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/ui-lib-basics">
    <summary>UI library foundation spec: directory layout, primitive set (button/input/modal), token bridge, Storybook stories, and CI gates (a11y + visual regression).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ui-lib-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/ui-lib-patterns">
    <summary>UI library advanced patterns spec: compound components, accessible modal portals, CSF 3 stories with interaction tests, and slot-based composition.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-ui-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/voice-ui-patterns">
    <summary>Pattern spec for designing voice UIs: prompt-writing rules, progressive error-recovery ladder, multimodal voice+screen coordination, platform constraints (Alexa / Google Actions / Siri), success metrics.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-iot-integration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/vui-iot-integration">
    <summary>VUI for smart home and IoT: command-pattern taxonomy, multi-device coordination flows, partial-failure handling and undo support, emitted as a coherent VUI flow spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-privacy-security" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/vui-privacy-security">
    <summary>Privacy- and security-hardened VUI architecture: five privacy principles, split classifier/executor agents for PII, redaction policy and audit trail emitted as a privacy spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="w3c-design-tokens-standard" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/w3c-design-tokens-standard">
    <summary>Generates a DTCG-compliant tokens.json with $type/$value/$description and {alias} references that round-trips between Figma, Style Dictionary v4, and native platforms.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="w3c-design-tokens-standard-ui-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/w3c-design-tokens-standard-ui-design">
    <summary>W3C Design Tokens Community Group draft applied as a config artefact: $type/$value/$ref structure, token group taxonomy, validator-ready JSON conforming to the spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="wcag-22-compliance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/wcag-22-compliance">
    <summary>Generates a WCAG 2.2 AA conformance report for the 9 new success criteria (focus appearance, target size, drag, auth, redundant entry, consistent help) + automated CI gate.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
