<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-schema-markup" title="Schema Markup Implementation">
  <summary>JSON-LD schema patterns for Article, FAQ, Organization, and Breadcrumb types with validation workflow.</summary>

  <section title="Validation Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate all JSON-LD schema with Google Rich Results Test before deployment. Never deploy agent-generated schema without validation.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents produce syntactically valid but semantically incorrect schema: wrong @type values, missing required fields, incorrect nesting. Invalid schema produces no rich results and may generate Search Console errors with no visible symptom.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>1. Generate schema from template or agent</item>
      <item>2. Validate JSON syntax (jsonlint.com or IDE linter)</item>
      <item>3. Test with Google Rich Results Test</item>
      <item>4. Verify no conflicting schema definitions on the same page</item>
      <item>5. Deploy and monitor Search Console for schema errors</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Schema Type Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add schema markup in order of impact: Organization (global), Article (all blog posts), FAQPage (any Q&amp;A content), BreadcrumbList (all pages with navigation hierarchy).</statement>
      <rationale>Organization schema establishes brand entity globally. Article schema is required for Google Discover inclusion. FAQPage generates rich result expansion in SERPs. BreadcrumbList appears in search results and improves topic hierarchy signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Organization + Person: brand and author entity (global, add to header/footer)</item>
      <item>Article/BlogPosting: all editorial content with author and datePublished</item>
      <item>FAQPage: Q&amp;A sections, "People Also Ask" style content</item>
      <item>HowTo: step-by-step tutorials</item>
      <item>BreadcrumbList: all pages with 2+ level hierarchy</item>
      <item>Product + Offer: e-commerce product pages</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Required Fields by Schema Type">
    <list>
      <item>Article: headline, author (@type Person, name), publisher, datePublished, image</item>
      <item>FAQPage: mainEntity array of Question + acceptedAnswer pairs</item>
      <item>Organization: name, url, logo (ImageObject), sameAs array</item>
      <item>BreadcrumbList: itemListElement array with ListItem, position, name, item (URL)</item>
    </list>
    <note>The last BreadcrumbList item (current page) should have a name but no item URL. Including a URL for the current page is technically valid but not required.</note>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/schema-article.json">Article schema JSON-LD template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/schema-faq.json">FAQPage schema JSON-LD template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/schema-organization.json">Organization + Person schema template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/schema-breadcrumb.json">BreadcrumbList schema template</reference>
</text>
