<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-social-meta-and-linking" title="Social Meta Tags and Internal Linking">
  <summary>Open Graph and Twitter Card meta tag requirements, pillar-cluster internal linking structure, and keyword cannibalization fixes.</summary>

  <section title="Open Graph Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Open Graph images must be exactly 1200x630px (1.91:1 ratio) and under 8MB. Images outside these dimensions are cropped or rejected by social platforms.</statement>
      <rationale>Facebook, LinkedIn, and most social platforms use 1200x630 as the standard preview image size. Non-conforming images display incorrectly, reducing click-through rates on shared links.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>og:title: page title (max 60 chars for optimal display)</item>
      <item>og:description: 155-160 chars, compelling summary</item>
      <item>og:image: absolute URL, 1200x630px, under 8MB</item>
      <item>og:image:alt: image description for accessibility</item>
      <item>og:url: canonical URL (must match rel=canonical)</item>
      <item>og:type: website (default) or article (for blog posts)</item>
      <item>og:locale: en_US (or appropriate locale)</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/og-meta.html">Complete Open Graph + Twitter Card meta tag block</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Twitter Card Rules">
    <list>
      <item>twitter:card: summary_large_image for articles and content</item>
      <item>twitter:title: max 70 chars</item>
      <item>twitter:description: max 200 chars</item>
      <item>twitter:image: minimum 506x506px (use the 1200x630 OG image)</item>
      <item>twitter:creator: author Twitter handle</item>
      <item>twitter:site: brand Twitter handle</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Pillar-Cluster Internal Linking">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every cluster page must link back to its pillar page using anchor text containing the pillar's primary keyword. Pillar pages must link to all cluster pages.</statement>
      <rationale>The pillar-cluster model distributes link equity from high-authority pillar pages to long-tail cluster pages, improving the ranking probability of both. Bidirectional links signal topical relationship to Google.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Identify 5-10 pillar topics (comprehensive guides on broad subjects)</item>
      <item>Create cluster pages (specific subtopics within each pillar)</item>
      <item>Pillar links to all cluster pages with keyword-rich anchor text</item>
      <item>Cluster pages link back to pillar with target keyword anchor</item>
      <item>No orphan pages — every page has at least one internal link pointing to it</item>
      <item>Maximum 3 clicks from homepage to any page</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Keyword Cannibalization Fixes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Multiple pages targeting the same primary keyword (e.g., three different pages about "SDD methodology").</description>
      <reason>Cannibalization splits link equity and authority across multiple pages, weakening all of them. Google chooses which page to rank and often picks the wrong one.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <list>
      <item>Fix: 301 redirect weaker pages to the canonical page</item>
      <item>Fix: merge similar content into one comprehensive guide</item>
      <item>Fix: increase internal links pointing to the preferred page</item>
      <item>Fix: use unique primary keywords for each page — no two pages share the same target</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
