<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-procedure" title="Foreign Client Kickoff Checklist Procedure" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six-step procedure to apply Foreign Client Kickoff Checklist end-to-end from typed inputs to a sign-off-ready checklist.</summary>

  <section title="Procedure">

    <step n="1" name="confirm-applicability">
      <input>AGENTS.md Applies-If / Skip-If predicates + current task brief</input>
      <action>Evaluate every Applies-If item (ALL must hold) and every Skip-If item (ANY kills it). If any Skip-If fires, abort and emit a "wrong-tool" note instead.</action>
      <output>Decision: proceed / skip + brief reason</output>
      <decision-gate>If skip, STOP. Do not emit the checklist.</decision-gate>
    </step>
    <step n="2" name="gather-typed-inputs">
      <input>Source paths from Prerequisites table</input>
      <action>Open each input artefact and record name + source path in the working set. Inputs that cannot be opened are flagged; do not synthesise from prior knowledge.</action>
      <output>`inputs_used[]` populated with name + source per row</output>
      <decision-gate>If a required input is missing, STOP and surface the gap to the operator.</decision-gate>
    </step>
    <step n="3" name="draft-decision">
      <input>Working input set + decision tree from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`</input>
      <action>Walk the decision tree from root question to leaf conclusion. Record the rule id at the conclusion. Draft the decision statement referencing at least one input by name.</action>
      <output>Decision + rationale draft</output>
    </step>
    <step n="4" name="self-check-against-contract">
      <input>Decision draft + `content/02-output-contract.xml` schema</input>
      <action>Walk the JSON Schema: every required key present, no forbidden pattern matches, all transformations applied. Run `scripts/validate-foreign-client-kickoff-checklist.py --file draft.json` locally.</action>
      <output>`keyword_test_passed` style flag: contract_passed = true / false</output>
      <decision-gate>If contract_passed = false, return to step 3 and repair the named violation.</decision-gate>
    </step>
    <step n="5" name="owner-attribution">
      <input>Decision draft + RACI / org chart</input>
      <action>Set `owner` to a single named human or named rotating role. Reject any plural-pronoun owner. Add a 30-day refresh trigger to the agent's task queue.</action>
      <output>Owner field set; refresh trigger recorded</output>
    </step>
    <step n="6" name="store-and-handoff">
      <input>Validated artefact + storage location</input>
      <action>Write the artefact to the storage location named in Prerequisites. Notify the named downstream consumer. Bump version per the change-class table (patch/minor/major).</action>
      <output>checklist live; consumer notified; version + last_reviewed advanced</output>
    </step>

  </section>
</text>
