<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<methodology slug="spec-writing">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>PRD defines WHAT to build and WHY. Requires: Overview, Problem, Goals, Non-Goals, User Stories, FRs, NFRs, Acceptance Criteria, Out of Scope, Open Questions.</summary>
    <tags><tag>product-management</tag><tag>specification</tag><tag>prd</tag><tag>acceptance-criteria</tag><tag>requirements</tag></tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Product Specification Writing</title>
    <summary>A product specification (PRD) defines WHAT to build and WHY, leaving HOW to design and engineering. Required sections: Overview, Problem, Goals (with current/target metric table), Non-Goals, User Stories (As-a/I-want/So-that with persona IDs), Functional Requirements (FR-N IDs), Non-Functional Requirements, Acceptance Criteria (Given/When/Then per FR), Out of Scope, Open Questions. Every FR must have at least one AC; every goal must be measurable. Spec ends at ~5 pages for most features; beyond that, split or use a Mini-Spec.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Specs that mix what and how box in engineers and are ignored; specs without acceptance criteria produce untestable scope. Non-Goals explicitly prevent scope creep—their absence is the leading cause of unplanned feature growth. The Open Questions section is mandatory: a spec that has no unknowns signals false confidence and must be questioned before any FR is marked Must.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Feature is large enough (more than one sprint) that engineers and designers need a shared written contract before work starts.</item>
        <item>Cross-team work where multiple stakeholders must approve scope.</item>
        <item>Building against an external SLA or paid customer commitment requiring traceable requirements.</item>
        <item>Onboarding a contractor—the spec is the briefing artifact.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Tiny changes (less than one day, no ambiguity)—a backlog item with acceptance criteria is sufficient.</item>
        <item>Highly exploratory discovery work where requirements change weekly. Spec the experiment, not the product.</item>
        <item>After implementation as a retroactive document—that is documentation, not a spec.</item>
        <item>When the team will not maintain the spec post-launch; outdated specs mislead more than they help.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="required-sections">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>A complete spec must contain: Overview, Problem Statement, Goals (with current/target metric table), Non-Goals, User Stories, Functional Requirements (FR-N IDs), Non-Functional Requirements, Acceptance Criteria, Out of Scope, Open Questions. Missing any section is a reject signal.</statement>
        <rationale>Each section prevents a specific class of delivery failure: Non-Goals prevent scope creep, Open Questions prevent false confidence, Acceptance Criteria prevent untestable scope.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="goals">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every goal must have a measurable current baseline and a numeric target. "Improve UX" is not a goal. "Reduce time-to-find-product from 3 min to 30 sec" is a goal.</statement>
        <rationale>Unmeasurable goals cannot be verified at launch and cannot drive prioritization decisions during delivery.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="non-goals">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>List everything explicitly excluded from this spec. Non-Goals section must be non-empty for any feature touching more than one surface.</statement>
        <rationale>The absence of Non-Goals is the leading cause of scope creep. Every unspecified behaviour becomes "obviously included" during implementation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Explicit non-goals">
        <note>Non-Goals: Advanced filters (separate feature), AI-powered recommendations, Voice search.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="user-stories">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every story uses the format: "As a [named persona], I want to [action] so that [measurable benefit]." Use persona IDs (not "the user") in every story. Include the "so that" clause—it encodes motivation and validates the story is worth building.</statement>
        <rationale>Stories without persona IDs cannot be traced to a validated user segment. Stories without "so that" cannot be evaluated for user value.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="requirements">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Functional requirements use "FR-N: The system shall [do X]" format. Cap at ~15 FRs per spec; larger features must be split. Keep implementation details out: no library names, DB schemas, or UI component names.</statement>
        <rationale>Specs mixing what and how box in engineers and are ignored. Implementation decisions belong in the design document, linked from the spec.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="open-questions">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Open Questions section must be non-empty. A spec with zero open questions signals false confidence. List technical unknowns, pending business decisions, and user research gaps with an owner per question.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs in particular will "answer" every question rather than acknowledge uncertainty. Explicitly requiring a non-empty Open Questions section forces intellectual honesty.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="length-and-versioning">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Target 1-3 pages (or ~15 FRs). Use Mini-Spec for features under one sprint. Track decisions made post-approval as a versioned addendum—never silently rewrite the original spec.</statement>
        <rationale>Beyond 5 pages, nobody reads the spec. Silent rewrites destroy the audit trail that later resolves scope disputes.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="functional-requirements-authoring">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Assign a unique ID to every FR (FR-1, FR-2, ...) and reference that ID in the corresponding acceptance criteria. An FR without a linked AC is an orphan—reject the spec.</statement>
        <rationale>Without ID-based traceability, FRs and ACs drift apart during revisions. Orphan FRs produce untested scope at launch.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Label every FR with a priority: Must (MVP blocker), Should (high value, deferrable), Could (nice-to-have). Pair with a co-signer for any FR labelled Must.</statement>
        <rationale>Unprioritized requirements produce all-or-nothing scope debates at sprint planning. Must-level FRs need sign-off because they encode strategic decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="non-functional-requirements">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every NFR must specify a measurable criterion. "The system shall be fast" is not an NFR. "FR-2 latency: results visible within 200ms at p95 for up to 50K concurrent users" is an NFR.</statement>
        <rationale>Unmeasurable NFRs cannot be verified in QA and become perpetual technical debt claims.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Generic NFR boilerplate: "99.99% uptime", "GDPR compliant" pasted without source or justification.</description>
        <reason>Generic NFRs fabricated without contractual or regulatory basis waste engineering effort on unnecessary hardening.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="acceptance-criteria">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every FR must have at least one Given/When/Then acceptance criterion. Each AC row must reference the FR ID. AC must be unique—never a restatement of the FR.</statement>
        <rationale>AC that restates the FR cannot be used for test case authoring or sprint review verification. "FR-2 search works → AC: search works" tells testers nothing.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A research agent gathers inputs (problem statement, persona notes, analytics, prior art) and emits a structured "context" object. A drafter agent fills the spec template with required sections, never inventing acceptance criteria from thin air. A reviewer agent runs the rubric ("does every FR have an AC? are NFRs measurable? are non-goals listed?"). An open-questions agent extracts unknowns and assigns owners. Humans sign off on the goals/non-goals and on any FR labelled "Must".</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-spec-reviewer-agent — primary reviewer to apply the rubric.</item>
        <item>faion-task-creator-agent — splits the approved spec into backlog items with acceptance criteria.</item>
        <item>faion-mvp-scope-analyzer-agent — feeds in if the spec must be cut to MVP scope.</item>
        <item>faion-idea-generator-agent — solution divergence before the spec freezes one approach.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Use IDs (FR-1, NFR-1, US-1) and reference them throughout. Without IDs, traceability collapses on first edit.</item>
        <item>Always include Non-Goals; they prevent scope creep more reliably than priority labels.</item>
        <item>Cap functional requirements at ~15 per spec. Larger features should be split.</item>
        <item>Make every goal measurable with a current/target table. "Improve UX" is not a goal.</item>
        <item>Keep "how" out: no library names, no schemas, no UI mocks (mocks live in design doc, linked).</item>
        <item>Open Questions section is mandatory; an empty section signals fake confidence.</item>
        <item>Specs are versioned: track decisions made post-approval as an addendum, never silently rewrite.</item>
        <item>Pair with mvp-scoping if the FR list exceeds capacity—cut to Must/Should/Could before publishing.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs default to elaborate prose; force structured templates with explicit section headings or reject output.</item>
        <item>Acceptance criteria written as restatements of FRs ("FR-2: search works → AC: search works"). Require unique G/W/T phrasing per AC.</item>
        <item>Models invent NFRs ("99.99% uptime", "GDPR compliant") without basis — strip generic NFR boilerplate unless backed by source.</item>
        <item>Open Questions section gets dropped because the model "answers" everything. Tell it explicitly: list things you do NOT know.</item>
        <item>Personas conflated with user types (e.g. "the user"). Inject persona ids and require them in every story.</item>
        <item>Long context with prior specs: agents copy-paste old FRs without updating IDs, creating duplicates. Reset numbering or reuse existing IDs deliberately.</item>
        <item>Specs containing PII / customer names: scrub via pre-publish hook; LLMs do not redact reliably.</item>
        <item>Token cost: a typical spec ≈ 4–8k tokens output; embed only the diffed sections in iteration to save context.</item>
        <item>Always require human approval on goals + non-goals before any FR work; those decisions encode strategy and cannot be delegated.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-platforms">
      <p>Spec authoring and storage platforms, with agent-friendly API support:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Notion (SaaS, REST API) — Most flexible, weak structural validation.</item>
        <item>Confluence (SaaS, REST API) — Required by many enterprises; heavyweight.</item>
        <item>Linear Docs (SaaS, GraphQL API) — Tight coupling with backlog items.</item>
        <item>Coda (SaaS, REST API) — Database-backed sections useful for FR/AC tables.</item>
        <item>GitHub Markdown in repo (SaaS, Git) — Ideal for solo founders / engineering-led teams.</item>
        <item>Productboard (SaaS, REST API) — "Spec" tab linked to features.</item>
        <item>Aha! Notebooks (SaaS, REST API) — Strong traceability to OKRs.</item>
        <item>HackMD / Outline (SaaS/OSS, REST API) — Lightweight collaborative authoring.</item>
      </list>
    </section><templates>
      <template path="templates/prd.md" purpose="Full PRD template: all required sections with placeholder guidance." />
      <template path="templates/mini-spec.md" purpose="Mini-Spec for small features: one-liner, problem, solution, requirements, exclusions." />
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2000/10/02/painless-functional-specifications-part-1-why-bother/" />
      <link href="https://www.productplan.com/glossary/product-requirements-document/" />
      <link href="https://www.aha.io/roadmapping/guide" />
      <link href="https://www.atlassian.com/agile/product-management/requirements" />
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/how-to-write-a-great-prd" />
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>