<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="user-story-mapping Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for user-story-mapping. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Arrange user stories along two axes: horizontal = user journey (activities then tasks), vertical = priority (essential at top, nice-to-have at bottom).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A flat backlog has no journey context, making release planning impossible. The two-axis structure reveals the walking skeleton — the thinnest complete slice — and lets any stakeholder see what each release delivers end-to-end.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Complete all five steps in order; skipping Step 4 (vertical priority ordering) before Step 5 (release slicing) produces release lines with no coherent narrative.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">BABOK v3 §10.46 requires the map to represent a complete user experience before slicing; partial maps yield partial release value and false sign-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Release 1 must deliver a complete user journey (thin vertical slice through all activities), not a complete implementation of one activity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A release that completes one activity fully but leaves other activities with no coverage cannot be user-tested end-to-end; the walking-skeleton check fails.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Walk the Release-1 line vertically with a real user or surrogate before sign-off: read each cell as a contiguous narrative. If it does not form a coherent story, the slice is wrong.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Jeff Patton's walking-skeleton check is the concrete test for release-1 coherence; narrative breakdown reveals missing tasks, not missing stories.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Convert each story map cell to formal BA artifacts: BRD section (problem, scope, AC), BPMN participant + task, RTM row (story_id, requirement_id, process_step, test_case_id).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">BABOK treats the map as input to Requirements Analysis and Design Definition (KA 5); without artifact translation the map is a workshop souvenir, not a BA deliverable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tag every story cell with persona_id and process_step_id at write time; retrofitting traceability after the workshop is the single biggest time sink in BA delivery.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without source tagging, the RTM must be reconstructed from memory — a lossy and slow process that delays sign-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require all five participant roles in the workshop: Product Owner, Business Analyst, Developer, UX Designer, and at least one key stakeholder; refuse to proceed if the decision-maker is absent.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A half-attended map produces false consensus — absent stakeholders discover the release plan only at review, triggering scope changes that invalidate the map's value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run story mapping as a four-stage subagent pipeline: elicitation prep → workshop facilitation → artifact translation → validation loop.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each stage requires different model capabilities (research, structured elicitation, formatting, critique); a single prompt produces weaker output than staged handoffs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not let the agent decide release boundaries; slicing is a business and risk decision. Lock the agent to "suggest releases" mode, never "commit releases".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Release boundaries require authority the agent does not have; auto-committed slices bypass stakeholder sign-off and invalidate the validation loop.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After story generation, run an INVEST critic pass: reject stories that are too large (epic in disguise) or non-independent ("as a system").</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs produce stories that pass a superficial format check but violate INVEST; an explicit critic pass before BA acceptance catches these failures cheaply.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enforce four mandatory human checkpoints: backbone approval before tasks, Release-1 slice approval before stories, BRD+RTM diff review before publication, NFR register review before sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each checkpoint prevents downstream artifact cascades from building on a flawed foundation; skipping any one checkpoint increases rework cost by at least one stage.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
