<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="User Story Mapping: Structure and Procedure">
  <summary>Two-dimensional story map structure, five-step mapping procedure, release-slicing strategies, and MVP definition.</summary>

  <section title="Story Map Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Arrange user stories along two axes: horizontal = user journey (activities then tasks), vertical = priority (essential at top, nice-to-have at bottom).</statement>
      <rationale>A flat backlog has no journey context, making release planning impossible. The two-axis structure reveals the walking skeleton — the thinnest complete slice — and lets any stakeholder see what each release delivers end-to-end.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>The backbone is the sequence of user Activities (coarse-grained goals). Under each Activity sit Tasks (specific interactions). Under each Task stack Stories (user story cards) ordered by priority. Horizontal lines drawn across the full map define release boundaries.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-Step Mapping Procedure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Complete all five steps in order; skipping Step 4 (vertical priority ordering) before Step 5 (release slicing) produces release lines with no coherent narrative.</statement>
      <rationale>BABOK v3 §10.46 requires the map to represent a complete user experience before slicing; partial maps yield partial release value and false sign-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Identify User Activities: map high-level goals in user-journey sequence (e.g., Browse → Select → Purchase → Track → Return).</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Break Down into Tasks: for each Activity, list specific interactions the user performs (e.g., Purchase → Add to cart, Enter shipping, Enter payment, Confirm order).</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Write User Stories: for each Task, write stories using "As a [persona], I want [goal] so that [benefit]" format.</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Arrange Vertically by Priority: top = essential for minimum viable experience; bottom = nice-to-have.</item>
      <item>Step 5 — Slice into Releases: draw horizontal lines to define Release 1 (walking skeleton), Release 2 (enhancements), Release 3 (polish).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Release Slicing Strategies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Release 1 must deliver a complete user journey (thin vertical slice through all activities), not a complete implementation of one activity.</statement>
      <rationale>A release that completes one activity fully but leaves other activities with no coverage cannot be user-tested end-to-end; the walking-skeleton check fails.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Horizontal slice — cut off entire activities when activities are independent (rarely the right choice for Release 1).</item>
      <item>Vertical slice — thin cut through all activities delivering minimum viability (correct approach for MVP).</item>
      <item>Mixed — combination; most common in practice.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Walk the Release-1 line vertically with a real user or surrogate before sign-off: read each cell as a contiguous narrative. If it does not form a coherent story, the slice is wrong.</statement>
      <rationale>Jeff Patton's walking-skeleton check is the concrete test for release-1 coherence; narrative breakdown reveals missing tasks, not missing stories.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="BA Artifact Translation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Convert each story map cell to formal BA artifacts: BRD section (problem, scope, AC), BPMN participant + task, RTM row (story_id, requirement_id, process_step, test_case_id).</statement>
      <rationale>BABOK treats the map as input to Requirements Analysis and Design Definition (KA 5); without artifact translation the map is a workshop souvenir, not a BA deliverable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag every story cell with persona_id and process_step_id at write time; retrofitting traceability after the workshop is the single biggest time sink in BA delivery.</statement>
      <rationale>Without source tagging, the RTM must be reconstructed from memory — a lossy and slow process that delays sign-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/render-ba-package.py">Converts story-map JSON to BRD.md + RTM.csv</reference>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Capturing non-functional requirements (performance, security, accessibility, audit) as story map cells.</description>
    <reason>NFRs have no natural cell on the map and are routinely dropped in the vertical-slice mentality. Capture them in a parallel NFR register linked to the map header; review per release slice, not per cell.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Treating a single-axis prioritized backlog as a story map.</description>
    <reason>A list with no horizontal journey axis loses the context that explains why stories exist; BAs cannot trace them to process steps or write a coherent RTM.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
