<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-workshop" title="User Story Mapping: Workshop and Agent Workflow">
  <summary>Workshop facilitation agenda, participant roles, common mistakes, and agent-specific gotchas for BA-led story mapping.</summary>

  <section title="Workshop Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require all five participant roles in the workshop: Product Owner, Business Analyst, Developer, UX Designer, and at least one key stakeholder; refuse to proceed if the decision-maker is absent.</statement>
      <rationale>A half-attended map produces false consensus — absent stakeholders discover the release plan only at review, triggering scope changes that invalidate the map's value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Duration: 2-4 hours for a complete map; break into two sessions if scope exceeds 5 activities.</item>
      <item>Materials: large wall or whiteboard, sticky notes in 3 colors (activities/tasks/stories), markers.</item>
      <item>Agenda: personas + goals (15 min) → backbone activities (30 min) → tasks (30 min) → stories (60 min) → vertical prioritization (30 min) → release slices (30 min).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Flat backlog — stories written without journey context.</description>
      <reason>No horizontal axis means no way to detect missing tasks or trace requirements to process steps.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Technical stories on the map ("As a system, I want to batch-process orders").</description>
      <reason>INVEST requires user perspective; technical stories belong in a separate architectural backlog, not the story map.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No release lines defined — map becomes a prioritized list.</description>
      <reason>Without horizontal slice boundaries, the team has no commitment to what ships together and cannot plan iterations.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Capturing exception/unhappy paths only implicitly.</description>
      <reason>Workshops optimize the happy path; add a red-sticky row for exception paths below each task band so they are visible, not forgotten.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run story mapping as a four-stage subagent pipeline: elicitation prep → workshop facilitation → artifact translation → validation loop.</statement>
      <rationale>Each stage requires different model capabilities (research, structured elicitation, formatting, critique); a single prompt produces weaker output than staged handoffs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not let the agent decide release boundaries; slicing is a business and risk decision. Lock the agent to "suggest releases" mode, never "commit releases".</statement>
      <rationale>Release boundaries require authority the agent does not have; auto-committed slices bypass stakeholder sign-off and invalidate the validation loop.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>After story generation, run an INVEST critic pass: reject stories that are too large (epic in disguise) or non-independent ("as a system").</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs produce stories that pass a superficial format check but violate INVEST; an explicit critic pass before BA acceptance catches these failures cheaply.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Facilitation prompt pattern constrains the agent to grounded output only.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a BABOK-aligned BA facilitator. Persona pack: {personas}.
Current backbone: {activities}. We are decomposing activity "{a}" into tasks.
Ask 3 elicitation questions targeting the persona's goal, constraints, and
exception path. Output JSON: {questions: [], suggested_tasks: []}.
No prose. No invented tasks not grounded in a question.]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Translation prompt enforces full BA artifact output with gap detection.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Input: story-map.json (activities, tasks, stories, releases).
For each Release-1 story emit: BRD section (problem, scope, AC), BPMN
participant + task, RTM row (story_id, requirement_id, process_step,
test_case_id). Flag any story missing AC or persona reference.
Output strict JSON matching schema {brd, bpmn, rtm, gaps}.]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-the-Loop Checkpoints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce four mandatory human checkpoints: backbone approval before tasks, Release-1 slice approval before stories, BRD+RTM diff review before publication, NFR register review before sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale>Each checkpoint prevents downstream artifact cascades from building on a flawed foundation; skipping any one checkpoint increases rework cost by at least one stage.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
