<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="user-story-mapping Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for user-story-mapping as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Capturing non-functional requirements (performance, security, accessibility, audit) as story map cells.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>NFRs have no natural cell on the map and are routinely dropped in the vertical-slice mentality. Capture them in a parallel NFR register linked to the map header; review per release slice, not per cell.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating a single-axis prioritized backlog as a story map.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A list with no horizontal journey axis loses the context that explains why stories exist; BAs cannot trace them to process steps or write a coherent RTM.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Flat backlog — stories written without journey context.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>No horizontal axis means no way to detect missing tasks or trace requirements to process steps.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Technical stories on the map ("As a system, I want to batch-process orders").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>INVEST requires user perspective; technical stories belong in a separate architectural backlog, not the story map.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>No release lines defined — map becomes a prioritized list.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without horizontal slice boundaries, the team has no commitment to what ships together and cannot plan iterations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Capturing exception/unhappy paths only implicitly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Workshops optimize the happy path; add a red-sticky row for exception paths below each task band so they are visible, not forgotten.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
