<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Prototyping Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Prototyping. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-one-hypothesis-per-loop" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each prototype loop tests exactly ONE falsifiable hypothesis; multi-hypothesis sprints are split.</statement>
      <rationale source="Lean Startup principle">Multi-hypothesis sprints produce ambiguous outcomes; one hypothesis per loop keeps signal clean.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-smallest-viable-variant" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Variant is the smallest possible artefact that can test the hypothesis; over-built prototypes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="MVP principle">Over-built prototypes drift toward production and slow the loop; smallest viable keeps iteration fast.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-evidence-not-opinion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Outcome is decided by evidence (5-user test / metric / structured review); opinion-only outcomes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Grounded-decision convention">Opinion-only outcomes produce folklore; evidence-driven outcomes are auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-three-outcomes-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Outcome is one of (kept | rolled-back | shipped-with-changes); ambiguous &apos;partial&apos; is split into two iterations.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-rule stability">Ambiguous outcomes hide regret; trinary forces a clear next step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-log-row-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every iteration produces a row via prototype-iteration-log-template; unlogged iterations are folklore.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-folklore convention">Without logs, iterations vanish; the log row creates the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-prototyping.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
