<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Prototyping — Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Prototype type examples, tool guidance, and antipatterns for prototype scope and fidelity decisions.</summary>

  <section title="Prototype Types">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Paper prototype: draw screens on paper, cut out interactive elements, user points to indicate "clicks," swap paper to show next screen. Pros: fast (hours), cheap, anyone can do it, no tool skills required. Use for: concept testing, early flow validation, workshop ideation.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Clickable prototype (Figma): create screen designs, add hotspots, link screens, define transitions. Pros: quickly shareable, testable on real devices, no code required. Use for: flow testing, stakeholder alignment, remote usability studies.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Code prototype (React/HTML): self-contained interactive implementation covering a single flow end-to-end. Pros: tests real performance and loading states, most realistic fidelity. Use for: technical feasibility validation, edge case discovery, high-stakes interactions where Figma fidelity is insufficient.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Tool Selection">
    <p>Paper: earliest ideas, no tool skills needed. Figma: all-around choice, low to high fidelity. Framer: complex interactions, code-based. ProtoPie: advanced animations without code. Storybook: component-level interactive demos. Code (React): highest fidelity, technical validation.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Prototype built to too high a fidelity before any user testing has been conducted.</description>
      <reason>High-fidelity prototypes take weeks to build. If the first user test reveals a fundamental navigation problem, the investment is discarded. Low-fidelity is appropriate until the structure is validated.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Prototype with no defined learning objective — testing "the whole product."</description>
      <reason>Unfocused prototypes produce unfocused findings. Testers cannot distinguish signal from noise; the synthesis session produces a list of problems with no prioritization basis.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Findings documented as raw session notes, not discrete prioritized issues.</description>
      <reason>Engineering teams cannot act on raw qualitative notes. Findings must be synthesized into discrete, severity-rated issues before sharing — otherwise they are ignored in favor of concrete backlog items.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Prototype overwrites previous version — no version history maintained.</description>
      <reason>Design decisions frequently regress when new constraints emerge. Without previous versions accessible, teams rebuild earlier explorations from memory.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>High-fidelity Figma prototype treated as a complete specification for engineers.</description>
      <reason>Figma hotspots communicate navigation but not state transitions, animation timing, conditional behavior, or edge cases. An interaction spec document is always required alongside the prototype.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
