<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="prototyping Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for prototyping as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Prototype built to too high a fidelity before any user testing has been conducted.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>High-fidelity prototypes take weeks to build. If the first user test reveals a fundamental navigation problem, the investment is discarded. Low-fidelity is appropriate until the structure is validated.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Prototype with no defined learning objective — testing "the whole product."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unfocused prototypes produce unfocused findings. Testers cannot distinguish signal from noise; the synthesis session produces a list of problems with no prioritization basis.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Findings documented as raw session notes, not discrete prioritized issues.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Engineering teams cannot act on raw qualitative notes. Findings must be synthesized into discrete, severity-rated issues before sharing — otherwise they are ignored in favor of concrete backlog items.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Prototype overwrites previous version — no version history maintained.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Design decisions frequently regress when new constraints emerge. Without previous versions accessible, teams rebuild earlier explorations from memory.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>High-fidelity Figma prototype treated as a complete specification for engineers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Figma hotspots communicate navigation but not state transitions, animation timing, conditional behavior, or edge cases. An interaction spec document is always required alongside the prototype.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs generating prototype code do not know the design system; inject component library docs or a token file into context first.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent-generated code uses arbitrary component APIs; providing design system context ensures consistency.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents over-scope: constrain to a single named flow in the prompt or the output will be unmanageable.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without explicit scope constraint, agents attempt to build the entire product, producing unmaintainable code.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Figma API returns node IDs, not screen names — pre-map IDs to names before passing to an agent.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents cannot parse node IDs meaningfully; pre-mapping enables agent to reference screens by human-readable names.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Generated React prototypes often use useState in ways that break multi-step flows; agent should be told to use a simple state machine or step counter.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without explicit state management guidance, agents generate fragile state handling.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Prototype quality review requires a human designer — do not let an agent declare the prototype "ready for testing".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents cannot assess design quality; human review is the only valid quality gate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>When agents write session scripts (facilitator guides), they omit think-aloud instructions; always append the standard preamble manually.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents produce generic scripts without the human-centric facilitation guidance needed for valid testing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
