<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="recognition-over-recall Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for recognition-over-recall. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Common actions must be visible, not hidden in menus. Navigation should use visible tabs for main sections instead of hidden hamburger menus.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Recognition requires only identifying the right option from visible choices. Recall requires users to remember what exists and where it is, adding cognitive burden and errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Forms with reference data must show the context in a sidebar. When editing an order, show order details so the user cannot forget what they are editing. In multi-step processes, show a summary of previous selections.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Context visibility prevents cognitive load of remembering earlier decisions. Multi-step forms without a summary force users to mentally track their previous entries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Recognition aids must replace recall requirements: file browser shows thumbnails for images (not just filenames); recent items are shown prominently; search includes autocomplete and suggestions; icons are paired with text labels (or tooltips if space-constrained).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Thumbnails, recent items, and search suggestions let users recognize what they want instead of recalling it. Icons without labels force memorization; labels reduce recall load to near-zero.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Progressive disclosure: show essential options always, reveal advanced options on demand. Users do not need to remember what is available.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Novice users see only what they need; expert users can access advanced features. No one has to memorize the full feature set.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Smart defaults: pre-fill forms with likely values (from user history or profile). Users recognize and confirm rather than recall and enter.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Pre-filled values reduce typing and recall. Users verify rather than generate; recognition of correct values is faster and more reliable than recalling what to type.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Search and filter: instead of asking users to browse hundreds of options or recall item locations, let users search and see results. Recognition of results is easier than recall of location.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Search and filter shift the cognitive model from recall (where is it?) to recognition (which one is it?).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>History and recents: show recent documents, recent searches, frequently used items, and favorites. Consistent placement keeps elements in the same location so users recognize location without recalling where to look.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Recency and frequency are strong recognition cues. Consistent placement becomes predictable after a few uses.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
