<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="recognition-over-recall Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for recognition-over-recall as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Adding too many recognition aids (labels, tooltips, recent items, suggestions) simultaneously creates visual clutter</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Recognition support has diminishing returns. Balance recognition with aesthetic simplicity and scannability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Autocomplete systems surfacing wrong suggestions erode trust faster than blank fields</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Poor suggestions are worse than no suggestions. Test autocomplete logic with real user data.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Recent items panels can expose sensitive data to shared-device users</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Consider privacy implications; offer session-scoped history rather than persistent history on shared devices.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Recognition aids add implementation complexity (state management for recents, fuzzy matching for search)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Teams often deprioritize these under time pressure. Plan complexity budget for recognition features upfront.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Static checklist audits miss dynamic state transitions where recognition fails</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A multi-step wizard with no summary panel is harder to audit than visible UI. Test with real user flows and state transitions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents auditing UI from text descriptions will miss visual recognition failures</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Two similar icons adjacent to each other look the same; text descriptions cannot capture this. Provide annotated screenshots or component names with their icon descriptions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents implementing "recent items" tend to use localStorage without considering session isolation or PII implications</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Specify storage scope explicitly (session-scoped, no PII) in the implementation prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Autocomplete suggestions generated by agents may not account for the latency cost</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Specify debounce timing (typically 150-300ms) in the implementation prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Recognition audit severity ratings by agents default to "Medium" for everything</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require explicit criteria: High = task cannot be completed without recall, Medium = slows task, Low = friction only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents can identify technical violations but not judge visual design balance</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Human checkpoint required for visual design decisions — whether added labels harm the aesthetic balance of the layout.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
