<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="IP-Sensitive Workflow Design Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every IP-Sensitive Workflow Design application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-device-separation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Personal-project work MUST happen on a personally-owned device. Mixing on the day-job laptop is rejected even briefly.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Device ownership is the cleanest provenance signal an arbitrator will accept; one mixed commit on company gear can shift the IP attribution argument.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-credential-separation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Personal-project credentials (GitHub, registry, deploy keys) MUST live in a credential store distinct from any day-job vault. Shared 1Password vaults are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Credential co-mingling indicates resource-mixing; separating vaults preserves the 'not on company resources' defence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-time-fence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Commit timestamps MUST fall outside contracted day-job working hours OR be explicitly marked PTO/unpaid in the day-job timesheet. Working-hour commits are flagged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Time-of-commit is the second-strongest evidence after device; the fence prevents 'on company time' disputes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-namespace-isolation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Personal repos MUST live under a personal GitHub/GitLab namespace, not a shared org. Cross-org forks are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Org membership is sticky; even an apparently personal fork inside the client's org can be claimed.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-attribution-log" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every commit MUST emit an IP-attribution log entry: device id, location, hours-fenced flag, credential store id. Logs MUST be retained 7 years.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">When a dispute arises, the log is the contemporaneous record; without it the defence relies on memory and metadata, both weak.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
