<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Shared Infra Capacity Board Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules every shared-infra capacity board must enforce so it surfaces capacity demand instead of merely logging it.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every row MUST carry four required fields: resource (named), team, projected_delta (numeric with unit), need_by_date (concrete date). Free-form notes belong in a separate column, not in lieu of these four.</statement>
      <rationale>Cross-team architects fight over shared infra because each team plans capacity in isolation; without typed numeric demand, the weekly sync degenerates into vibes. Required typed fields make conflicts arithmetic, not rhetorical.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[- resource: redis-prod
  team: checkout
  projected_delta: "+12 GB memory"
  need_by_date: 2026-06-10
  owner: "@alex.kim"
  note: "Cart-session TTL increase per spec-1024"]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The board MUST be updated weekly, on the same recurring day, before the architecture sync; stale rows (last_updated &gt;14 days) are flagged for archival.</statement>
      <rationale>An untouched capacity board is decoration. Pinning updates to the sync forces decisions to consume the artefact, which keeps the artefact alive.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every row MUST name a single accountable owner (handle) — not the team. No bare "team-name" entries.</statement>
      <rationale>Plural ownership = no ownership. When two teams' projections collide on the same resource, the resolution needs two named humans, not two team names that nobody can DM.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>When two rows project conflicting demand on the same resource within overlapping windows, the conflict MUST be tagged "CONFLICT" and assigned a resolution owner before the sync ends.</statement>
      <rationale>The board's only job is to surface fights early; if conflicts get noted but not assigned, they re-emerge at deploy time exactly as before. The tag + owner + deadline turn surfacing into action.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Closed or resolved rows MUST be moved to an archive section with the realised outcome (delivered / cancelled / partially-met) and a one-line learning note; rows are never silently deleted.</statement>
      <rationale>The archive becomes the ground truth for next quarter's capacity-planning calibration — teams who consistently over-estimate or under-estimate are identifiable only with the history.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
