<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="backlog-grooming-roadmapping Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for backlog-grooming-roadmapping. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain backlog in five stages: ideas/ (raw, not yet validated), validated/ (aligned with vision, feasibility checked), specified/ (has spec.md), designed/ (has design.md), ready/ (has implementation plan and tasks). Only score validated/ items. Ideas/ are unscored.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Scoring unvalidated ideas wastes effort on work that may be dropped. The stage gates ensure agent RICE scoring operates on items with sufficient information to produce meaningful numbers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never let the backlog exceed 40 unscored items. Schedule agent-assisted triage when it crosses 20 validated items without RICE scores.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unscored backlogs default to recency or vocal stakeholder bias, not impact-adjusted effort. An agent can score 20-40 items in one pass given real data inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>RICE Score = (Reach × Impact × Confidence) / Effort. Reach: 1-10 (users affected). Impact: 0.25/0.5/1/2/3 (per user). Confidence: 50%/80%/100%. Effort: person-months (0.5/1/2/3/6+). Flag any item lacking real data for Reach or Impact as estimate-needed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agent-generated RICE numbers are hallucinated if inputs are not grounded in real data. Flagging estimate-needed items prevents false ranking precision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Must = ~60% of scope, Should = ~20%, Could = ~20%. Document Won't items explicitly with a reason. If Must exceeds 60%, reprioritize. Everything being Must means nothing is prioritized.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">All-Must priority is the most common cause of missed milestones. The 60/20/20 split forces prioritization decisions that surface trade-offs before implementation begins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use theme-based roadmaps for solo projects. Use time-based roadmaps for teams with committed delivery windows and external stakeholders. Never use both simultaneously in the same document.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Theme-based roadmaps are more stable. Themes do not shift when quarters slip. Time-based roadmaps create false commitment pressure that causes rushed decisions when dates approach.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Now items must have a target milestone and status (On Track / At Risk / Delayed). Next items must have a confidence level (High/Medium/Low). Later items carry only thematic groupings. No dates, no status.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Precision decreases with planning horizon. Forcing concrete dates on Later items creates false precision for work that will change as earlier work lands and requirements evolve.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-run grooming every 4-6 weeks, not once per quarter. Later items drift. Roadmaps not refreshed regularly become obstacles rather than guides.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Quarterly roadmap reviews are too infrequent for fast-moving projects. Items in Later bucket will have changed priority. Failing to update the roadmap means the team is working against stale priorities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document items explicitly excluded from the roadmap with a reason. A Won't do list prevents repeated re-prioritization of the same rejected idea.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without an explicit exclusion list, rejected ideas re-enter grooming sessions on each cycle. Documenting why they were rejected short-circuits the debate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
