<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Backlog Grooming and Roadmapping Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Backlog Grooming and Roadmapping. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-weekly-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Grooming runs on a fixed weekly cadence; missed weeks are logged as risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — backlog-drift audit">Skipping grooming for 2+ weeks lets stale items dominate the top of the list.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-every-item-sized-scored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every backlog item carries a size estimate AND a priority score after each grooming pass; un-scored items are top of the next pass.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mike Cohn — Agile Estimating and Planning">Un-scored items hide cost; sized items can be traded against capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-theme-tag" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every item is tagged with the active quarter theme OR explicitly marked &apos;theme-orphan&apos; for review.</statement>
      <rationale source="OKR practice — line-of-sight">Theme-orphans accumulate; tagging makes them visible for explicit decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-1-3-12-horizons" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Roadmap is split into three horizons (1 month / 3 month / 12 month); items move only one band per grooming.</statement>
      <rationale source="Geoffrey Moore — three horizons of growth">Multi-band jumps signal panic re-planning; one band per week keeps drift visible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-cull-stale" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Items with no movement for 90 days are culled or promoted; the backlog never grows unboundedly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — backlog hygiene">An unbounded backlog cannot be groomed thoroughly; staleness pressure forces decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-named-owner-per-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each horizon band has a named owner accountable for its health.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo-team accountability">Anonymous bands rot; named owners feel the pressure to keep them clean.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md &quot;Applies If&quot; do not all hold, OR any &quot;Skip If&quot; disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-backlog-grooming-roadmapping.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
