<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-grooming-process" title="Backlog Structure and Grooming Process">
  <summary>The five-stage backlog structure (ideas/validated/specified/designed/ready), the four-part weekly grooming process, RICE scoring formula, and MoSCoW scope allocation rules.</summary>

  <section title="Backlog Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain backlog in five stages: ideas/ (raw, not yet validated), validated/ (aligned with vision, feasibility checked), specified/ (has spec.md), designed/ (has design.md), ready/ (has implementation plan and tasks). Only score validated/ items — ideas/ are unscored.</statement>
      <rationale>Scoring unvalidated ideas wastes effort on work that may be dropped. The stage gates ensure agent RICE scoring operates on items with sufficient information to produce meaningful numbers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Weekly Grooming Process">
    <p>Four parts, run weekly in 30-60 minutes:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Part 1 (10 min): Review new ideas — assess alignment with vision, move to validated/ or drop.</item>
      <item>Part 2 (20 min): Re-score top 20 backlog items with latest data, reorder by priority.</item>
      <item>Part 3 (20 min): Refine upcoming items — add detail, clarify ACs, identify dependencies, break into tasks if needed.</item>
      <item>Part 4 (10 min): Archive old items, remove duplicates, update estimates, flag blockers.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never let the backlog exceed 40 unscored items. Schedule agent-assisted triage when it crosses 20 validated items without RICE scores.</statement>
      <rationale>Unscored backlogs default to recency or vocal stakeholder bias, not impact-adjusted effort. An agent can score 20-40 items in one pass given real data inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="RICE Scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>RICE Score = (Reach × Impact × Confidence) / Effort. Reach: 1-10 (users affected). Impact: 0.25/0.5/1/2/3 (per user). Confidence: 50%/80%/100%. Effort: person-months (0.5/1/2/3/6+). Flag any item lacking real data for Reach or Impact as "estimate-needed".</statement>
      <rationale>Agent-generated RICE numbers are hallucinated if inputs are not grounded in real data. Flagging estimate-needed items prevents false ranking precision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Feature: Add social login (Google, GitHub)
Reach: 8 (80% of users would use it)
Impact: 1 (medium — convenience feature)
Confidence: 80% (competitor data available)
Effort: 1 (1 person-month)
RICE Score: (8 × 1 × 0.8) / 1 = 6.4

Feature: Add dark mode
Reach: 3 (30% of users requested)
Impact: 0.5 (cosmetic improvement)
Confidence: 100% (clear requirement)
Effort: 0.5 (~2 weeks)
RICE Score: (3 × 0.5 × 1.0) / 0.5 = 3.0

Decision: Social login (6.4) > Dark mode (3.0). Do social login first.
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="MoSCoW Allocation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Must = ~60% of scope, Should = ~20%, Could = ~20%. Document Won't items explicitly with a reason. If Must exceeds 60%, reprioritize — everything being Must means nothing is prioritized.</statement>
      <rationale>All-Must priority is the most common cause of missed milestones. The 60/20/20 split forces prioritization decisions that surface trade-offs before implementation begins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents marking everything as Must priority.</description>
      <reason>Violates MoSCoW allocation and creates scope overrun risk. Enforce: Must cannot exceed 60% in the prompt explicitly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
