<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-roadmap-structure" title="Roadmap Structure and Format">
  <summary>Time-based vs theme-based roadmap tradeoffs, Now/Next/Later structure with confidence levels, and antipatterns that undermine roadmap usefulness.</summary>

  <section title="Format Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use theme-based roadmaps for solo projects. Use time-based roadmaps for teams with committed delivery windows and external stakeholders. Never use both simultaneously in the same document.</statement>
      <rationale>Theme-based roadmaps are more stable — themes do not shift when quarters slip. Time-based roadmaps create false commitment pressure that causes rushed decisions when dates approach.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Now/Next/Later Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Now items must have a target milestone and status (On Track / At Risk / Delayed). Next items must have a confidence level (High/Medium/Low). Later items carry only thematic groupings — no dates, no status.</statement>
      <rationale>Precision decreases with planning horizon. Forcing concrete dates on Later items creates false precision for work that will change as earlier work lands and requirements evolve.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-run grooming every 4-6 weeks, not once per quarter. Later items drift; roadmaps not refreshed regularly become obstacles rather than guides.</statement>
      <rationale>Quarterly roadmap reviews are too infrequent for fast-moving projects. Items in Later bucket will have changed priority; failing to update the roadmap means the team is working against stale priorities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/roadmap.md">Roadmap skeleton with Now/Next/Later sections, Not Planned list, Dependencies, Change Log.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Won't Do List">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document items explicitly excluded from the roadmap with a reason. A "Won't do" list prevents repeated re-prioritization of the same rejected idea.</statement>
      <rationale>Without an explicit exclusion list, rejected ideas re-enter grooming sessions on each cycle. Documenting why they were rejected short-circuits the debate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Roadmap treated as a commitment: "We promised Q2 for this feature."</description>
      <reason>Roadmap is a plan, not a promise. It must be updated as learning occurs. Treating it as a commitment prevents honest updates when circumstances change.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Too many P0/Must items (more than 3 simultaneous "most important" features).</description>
      <reason>If everything is most important, nothing is. Forces hard prioritization decisions before the roadmap is published.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Grooming session run as a status update meeting.</description>
      <reason>Grooming focuses on prioritization, not updates. Status belongs in stand-up or async reports. Combining them dilutes both.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
