<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Risk Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the methodology. Every produced register must satisfy all five.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="every-risk-has-trigger-and-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every register row MUST have a named human owner and an observable trigger condition (metric, calendar event, or signal). Rows missing either are not managed risks — they are wishes.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK 7 + faion-network pm audit">Without an owner, no one monitors the trigger; without a trigger, no one knows when to activate the response. Both gaps guarantee the risk materialises without a prepared response.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pi-score-cites-source" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Probability and Impact score MUST carry a one-line rationale citing the source artefact (charter, HR data, vendor SOW, base-rate archive). Scores without rationale converge to Medium and lose discrimination.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kahneman — anchoring; PMI risk-analysis practice">Subjective scoring is anchoring-prone; teams default to Medium without evidence forcing functions, which makes the register useless for prioritisation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="emv-rolls-into-single-contingency" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per-risk EMV (Probability × Impact in currency) MUST be summed into a single contingency line attached to the cost baseline. Per-risk reserves are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK 7 — contingency reserves">Finance only funds aggregate contingency; per-risk reserves create budget gaming and prevent honest portfolio reasoning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="weekly-review-or-stale" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The register MUST be reviewed every weekly status cycle. A register not reviewed within 14 days is flagged stale and rejected by the validator.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — programme post-mortems Q4 2025">Risks materialise, mutate, and trigger secondaries continuously; a static register represents kickoff state, not today, and silently misleads the team.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="closure-with-outcome-never-delete" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Closed risks MUST be retained with an outcome label (`materialized`, `passed_without_triggering`, `merged_into_R-NN`) and a close date. Deletion is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Blameless-postmortem practice (Allspaw)">Retained closed risks build the base-rate corpus for future calibration; deletion destroys the audit trail and lessons-learned pool.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
