<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Risk Management Framework">
  <summary>Risk types, the four-step management process, P×I scoring with EMV, and response strategies for both threats and opportunities.</summary>

  <section title="Risk Types">
    <list>
      <item>Threat — negative risk; if it occurs, it harms scope, schedule, cost, or quality.</item>
      <item>Opportunity — positive risk; if it occurs, it improves the project outcome.</item>
      <item>Known risk — identified and plannable (e.g., integration complexity, key-person dependency).</item>
      <item>Unknown risk — not identifiable in advance (black swans); managed via contingency reserves and resilience, not response plans.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track opportunity risks in the same register as threats, color-coded; teams that log only threats systematically under-manage upside and miss scope to exploit favorable conditions.</statement>
      <rationale>Opportunity risks require active strategies (exploit, enhance, share) to realize; passive acceptance of positive risks leaves value on the table.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Four-Step Process">
    <p>Step 1: Identify risks. Use brainstorming, lessons-learned reviews, PROMPT-list (Political, Regulatory, Organizational, Market, People, Technical), and expert interviews. Seed from project-specific artifacts: charter, ADRs, vendor SOWs — generic risks produce generic responses.</p>
    <p>Step 2: Analyze risks. Apply qualitative P×I scoring first; escalate to quantitative EMV for risks where contingency must be defended to finance. Record one-line rationale per score citing the source artifact.</p>
    <p>Step 3: Plan responses. Assign a strategy and response owner for every risk. Threats: Avoid / Transfer / Mitigate / Accept. Opportunities: Exploit / Enhance / Share / Accept.</p>
    <p>Step 4: Monitor and update. Review the register weekly; verify trigger conditions; close risks with documented outcomes; conduct risk reviews at every milestone.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="P×I Scoring and EMV">
    <rule>
      <statement>Record a one-line rationale citing the source artifact for every P and I score; scores without rationale converge to "Medium" by default and lose discrimination.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams anchor on the middle of the scale unless forced to justify; requiring source evidence prevents the normalization of everything to "Medium" that makes the register useless for prioritization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>EMV (Expected Monetary Value) = Probability × Impact (in currency). Roll all EMVs into a single contingency line; finance only funds aggregates, not per-risk reserves.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Risk: Key developer leaves mid-project. P=0.30 (source: HR attrition data for this role), Impact=$30,000 delay cost (source: cost-estimation baseline). EMV=$9,000. Mitigation: cross-training + knowledge documentation. Residual EMV=$3,000 added to contingency.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Response Strategies">
    <p>For threats:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Avoid — change the plan to eliminate the risk entirely (e.g., avoid unproven technology).</item>
      <item>Transfer — shift the financial impact to a third party (insurance, fixed-price contracts).</item>
      <item>Mitigate — reduce probability or impact (cross-training, redundancy, testing).</item>
      <item>Accept (passive) — acknowledge the risk; take no proactive action.</item>
      <item>Accept (active) — set aside contingency reserves for the risk's expected impact.</item>
    </list>
    <p>For opportunities:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Exploit — take deliberate action to ensure the opportunity occurs.</item>
      <item>Enhance — increase probability or impact of the opportunity.</item>
      <item>Share — partner with another party better positioned to capture the opportunity.</item>
      <item>Accept — take the opportunity if it presents itself without active investment.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/risk-response-plan.md">Individual risk response plan template</reference>
  </section>
</text>
