<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Risk Management Rules and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Rules for trigger conditions, register freshness, contingency aggregation, closure discipline, and agentic risk identification; anti-patterns that make risk registers theatre.</summary>

  <section title="Triggers and Ownership">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every risk must have a named owner and an observable trigger condition; risks without both are not managed — they are listed.</statement>
      <rationale>Without an owner, no one monitors the trigger. Without a trigger, no one knows when to activate the response plan. Both gaps guarantee the risk materializes without a prepared response.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the top-five risks visible on the project status report; everything else goes in the appendix.</statement>
      <rationale>Sponsors and steering committees scan status reports; burying the critical risks in a detailed register means they are never discussed at the level where resources can be committed.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Calibration and Freshness">
    <rule>
      <statement>Calibrate the team's probability buckets once per quarter using base-rate exercises; otherwise the team defaults to "Medium" and the register loses prioritization value.</statement>
      <rationale>Subjective probability estimation is anchoring-prone; base-rate calibration (what actually happened on previous similar projects) gives teams a shared reference that improves discrimination.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Update the risk register at every weekly status cycle; a register not reviewed in two sprints is stale and actively misleads the project team.</statement>
      <rationale>Risks materialize, disappear, change probability, and trigger new secondary risks continuously; a static register represents the state of the project at kickoff, not today.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Closure Discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Close risks explicitly with an outcome label ("materialized", "passed without triggering", "merged into RISK-NN") and a date; never delete closed risks.</statement>
      <rationale>Deleted risks vanish from the audit trail and lessons-learned pool; retained closed risks build the base-rate data that improves future project risk identification and scoring.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Risk Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>The risk-identification agent must cite a source artifact for every candidate risk and mark every score with a one-line rationale; agents that invent risks without grounding produce generic registers with no project specificity.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM-generated registers default to "vendor delay", "scope creep", "key person leaves" — patterns present in training data, not analysis of the actual project. Source-grounded risks are specific and actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>The risk agent emits a diff (NEW, CHANGED_SCORE, CLOSED, STALE) against the prior register and never mutates fields directly; humans review and apply the diff.</statement>
      <rationale>Silent field mutation destroys the audit trail; a diff review ensures every change is intentional and documented, preserving the register's value as evidence for compliance and lessons-learned.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/emv.py">EMV scorer for Markdown risk registers</reference>
    <reference path="templates/risk-register.md">Risk register template</reference>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Leaving risk owners blank in the agent-generated register for a human to fill in "later."</description>
      <reason>"Later" rarely comes; unowned risks are reviewed by no one and their triggers go unmonitored. The agent should flag owner as "needs_assignment" in the output schema to force immediate assignment.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
