<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="adobe-firefly-integration Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for adobe-firefly-integration. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Firefly generation request must include a positive prompt, a negative prompt, a style preset (photo / art / graphic), and an aspect ratio. Requests without a negative prompt produce stock photo aesthetic defaults.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Firefly is trained on Adobe Stock. Without exclusion constraints ("no watermark, no logo, no text, no realistic photo"), outputs default to generic stock photography that rarely matches brand guidelines.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reference brand colors by name in prompts (e.g., "deep teal background"), not by hex value. Firefly interprets color names but ignores hex codes in prompts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Firefly's prompt parser has no hex color understanding. Hex values are silently ignored. Color names produce more consistent output even though post-processing color correction is often still needed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Generate 3+ variants per prompt and have a human art director select before using any asset in production. Firefly output is non-deterministic — identical prompts produce different results.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Non-determinism means no asset is guaranteed before generation. Single-variant generation creates bottlenecks when the single output is rejected at review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store generation prompts alongside assets in metadata (exiftool, C2PA content credentials) for reproducibility and content provenance documentation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Regulatory transparency requirements (C2PA) and internal reproducibility require that AI-generated assets carry generation provenance. Prompt metadata enables regeneration and audit trails.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Direct API automation of Firefly requires Adobe Firefly Services enterprise contract with beta access. Standard Creative Cloud accounts cannot trigger Firefly generation programmatically. Agent automation without this access is not possible.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">There is no public Firefly API for individuals as of 2026. Agents that claim to automate Firefly without enterprise access are using unofficial workarounds that violate Adobe ToS or are hallucinating the capability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track generative credit consumption before scheduling batch jobs. Credits expire and consumption per asset is not always predictable — running out during a campaign launch is a real operational risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generative credits are consumed per variation, not per prompt. A batch job requesting 10 variants per asset at 50 assets consumes 500 credits. Validate credit balance and rate before any production batch run.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agents operate in two layers of Firefly integration: (1) design-brief generation — produce structured prompts from brand guidelines and content briefs; (2) post-processing review — analyze generated images for brand consistency (color, composition, subject matter). Direct generation requires enterprise Firefly Services API access.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These two layers are the highest-value agentic tasks in a Firefly workflow. Brief generation improves prompt quality at scale; post-processing review catches non-compliant assets before they reach production.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
