<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="adobe-firefly-integration Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for adobe-firefly-integration as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent assumes a public Firefly API exists and attempts direct generation calls without enterprise access</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>There is no public Firefly API for individuals. Attempts to call it will fail or use unofficial workarounds. Agents must check for enterprise access before attempting API automation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent runs a batch job requesting many variants per asset without checking available credit balance</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Credits are consumed per variation. A large batch job can exhaust monthly allowance. Always validate credit balance and estimate consumption before scheduling batch generation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent treats identical prompts as deterministic and stores only one variant</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Firefly output is non-deterministic. Store all generated variants with their prompts; human-select before publishing. Never assume the first generated output is production-ready.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent interprets silent rejection (Firefly content moderation error) as a network error and retries without modifying the prompt</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Firefly silently rejects certain subjects without explanation. Agents must detect rejection-type errors, rephrase the prompt (remove triggering elements), and retry with modified content.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent validates generated assets against brand color by visual description alone</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Color descriptions in prompts are interpreted loosely. Post-processing color validation requires programmatic comparison (colormath or ImageMagick) against brand palette values, not visual description matching.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Firefly-generated assets used in production without human review</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Firefly outputs trend toward Adobe Stock aesthetic and may not match brand personality. Always involve a human art director in the selection and approval process before any asset goes to production.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Typography and text effects from Illustrator used directly as production SVG icons without manual refinement</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Firefly's text-to-vector produces decorative vectors with complex, non-editable paths unsuitable for UI iconography. Proofs in Illustrator at intended print or screen size are required; manual path simplification is often necessary.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
