<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="strategy-analysis-change-strategy Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for strategy-analysis-change-strategy. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Change strategy MUST evaluate a minimum of 3 substantive options plus the status-quo baseline. Strategies with fewer than 3 options plus status-quo MUST be returned to the change-strategy-agent for option expansion. The option count cap is 5 plus status-quo; more than 5 collapses into noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Fewer than 3 options is a coronation of the preferred choice. More than 5 collapses decision quality. The status-quo documents the cost of inaction, which leadership needs to authorize spending.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Option order in every evaluation prompt MUST be randomized. The change-strategy-agent MUST NOT list the recommended option first or last without randomization; order bias causes the agent to favor whichever option is mentioned first or last in the narrative.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents favor first/last position in option lists. Randomizing order before evaluation and re-randomizing on re-runs prevents systematic bias toward the "obvious" choice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The change strategy MUST include a scored status-quo option. The status-quo option MUST carry a risk score that documents the consequence of inaction (regulatory escalation, revenue loss rate, etc.) with evidence and a time horizon.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without the status-quo option, the strategy is advocacy; the steering committee cannot see what happens if they defer. A scored status-quo with a time-bounded risk is the most persuasive element of the document for forcing a decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
