<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agile BA Frameworks Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>9 testable rules including a `skip-this-methodology` rule. Each pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="assign-ba-per-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign specific BA deliverables to each Scrum phase. Treating BA work as a single undifferentiated 'refinement' activity is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 Agile Extension">Unassigned BA activities are skipped or done ad-hoc, causing AC defects to surface only at Sprint Review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="safe-role-mapping-pre-pi" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map BA role to SAFe level BEFORE PI Planning. Default 'team-level only' rejected when initiative requires Program or Portfolio BA work.</statement>
      <rationale source="SAFe role doctrine">SAFe lacks an explicit BA role; without explicit mapping, BA defaults to team-level tasks even when initiative needs Program/Portfolio scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="technique-by-purpose" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select agile BA technique by purpose, not familiarity. Each technique has a distinct trigger (user stories vs example mapping vs story mapping vs impact mapping).</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK Agile techniques">Default-to-user-stories leaves discovery gaps that surface as missed requirements after Sprint Review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-per-principle" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score each of the 7 IIBA Agile-Extension principles with a quoted evidence line. Reject any score row lacking a citation.</statement>
      <rationale source="evidence-based audit">Unevidenced scores reduce to opinion; only cited artefacts survive CCBA/CBAP audit and provide actionable gap data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="single-canonical-anchor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose ONE canonical framework as the anchor and label techniques borrowed from others explicitly. Mixed IIBA AE + DA + SAFe vocabulary without declared anchor is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="vocabulary discipline">Mixed vocabulary creates false precision and forces future BAs to relitigate framework choices every sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="single-da-lifecycle" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select a single DA primary lifecycle plus at most one alternative. 'All lifecycles apply' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="DA Way-of-Working doctrine">DA documents 6 lifecycles; an agent given all options picks all, making the choice useless for team planning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="one-shot-trigger" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run framework fit as a one-shot decision on initiative setup or major team/scope change — NOT a periodic cron.</statement>
      <rationale source="trigger design">Framework choices are not daily tasks; scheduled re-runs produce stale recommendations that erode trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="version-pin-and-refresh" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin framework versions in the constitution; refresh fit-report on major team or scope change (M&amp;A, regulatory shift, team-size doubling).</statement>
      <rationale source="versioning + decay discipline">Without version pins, agent output drifts as upstream content updates; without refresh triggers, recommendations rot.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip for single-team Scrum with no scaling concern and no regulatory bar OR greenfield product discovery (use continuous-discovery) OR non-software domain (vocabulary misapplies).</statement>
      <rationale source="scope guard">Methodology overhead exceeds value on simple Scrum; cross-domain misapplication creates false precision.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
