<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="plg-metrics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>conversion-optimizer</domain>
    <summary>A metrics methodology for Product-Led Growth: the full funnel from acquisition through expansion, including activation rate, time-to-value (TTV), free-to-paid conversion, Product-Qualified Lead (PQL) scoring, net revenue retention (NRR), and cohort analysis.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>plg</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>activation</tag>
      <tag>conversion</tag>
      <tag>analytics</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>PLG Metrics and Tracking</title>

    <summary>A metrics methodology for Product-Led Growth: the full funnel from acquisition through expansion, including activation rate, time-to-value (TTV), free-to-paid conversion, Product-Qualified Lead (PQL) scoring, net revenue retention (NRR), and cohort analysis. Every metric must have a single owner, a machine-verifiable definition tied to a single event in a single table, and a "who acts and how" runbook line attached to each dashboard tile.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Single-number product metrics hide the truth about PLG health. NRR above 100% can conceal logo churn; global TTV median hides SMB vs. Enterprise variance. PQL scores drift as the product evolves and misroute sales motion within 1-2 quarters if not recalibrated. Metric definitions that live only in dashboards (not version-controlled) diverge silently from the underlying events. Cohort analysis is the floor — every metric must be cohorted to be actionable.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Standing up a PLG dashboard with activation, conversion, expansion, and retention metrics in one place</item>
        <item>Defining or refining the activation event ("aha moment") and time-to-value for a SaaS product</item>
        <item>Designing a PQL scoring model from product behavior signals</item>
        <item>Running cohort analysis for retention and free-to-paid conversion</item>
        <item>Quarterly PLG strategy review where freemium vs. trial model and gating thresholds are on the table</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Sales-led motions where the buyer never logs in before purchase — PLG metrics produce noise</item>
        <item>Pre-product-market-fit startups: vanity metrics dominate, PQL scoring overfits to a tiny sample</item>
        <item>Self-hosted or single-tenant deployments where event telemetry is not centralized</item>
        <item>Hardware or one-time-purchase products without recurring usage signals</item>
        <item>Regulated industries where logging granular user behavior requires consent gates that break funnel completeness</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="metric-ownership-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Assign one owner per metric. Define the activation event as ONE event, in ONE table, fired in ONE place.</statement>
        <rationale>Without an owner, metric definitions drift and the dashboard becomes folklore. Cross-source UNION aggregations for activation always break when schemas evolve. A single-source activation event is the prerequisite for reliable funnel analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep the metric catalog version-controlled (dbt + Git). Pair every dashboard tile with a runbook line: "if this metric moves, who acts and how."</statement>
        <rationale>Dashboards that change metric definitions silently are net-negative — they create false confidence. Without a runbook, teams review the metric but take no action, which is the same as not measuring it.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="core-metrics-with-benchmarks">
      <list>
        <item>Sign-up to Activation: activated / signups — benchmark 40-60%.</item>
        <item>Free to Paid Conversion: paid / free users — benchmark 2-5% (freemium), 10-25% (trial).</item>
        <item>Time to Value (TTV): median time from signup to aha moment — target under 5 minutes.</item>
        <item>Natural Rate of Growth: (organic + viral) / total signups — target above 50%.</item>
        <item>PQL to Customer: customers / PQLs — benchmark 15-30%.</item>
        <item>Expansion MRR: expansion MRR / total MRR — target above 30%.</item>
        <item>Net Revenue Retention: (MRR + expansion - churn) / MRR — target above 120%.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="nrr-vs-gross-dollar-retention">
      <rule>
        <statement>Always track both NRR and gross dollar retention (GDR). Never report NRR alone.</statement>
        <rationale>NRR above 100% can conceal logo churn: expansion revenue from remaining accounts masks a shrinking customer base. GDR reveals the erosion that NRR hides.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ttv-segmentation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Track TTV segmented by cohort, acquisition source, user segment (SMB vs Enterprise), and onboarding path — never as a single global median.</statement>
        <rationale>Global TTV median hides large variance between segments. An Enterprise-heavy cohort with 30-minute TTV and an SMB cohort with 2-minute TTV produce a misleading median that drives wrong optimization decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="pql-scoring">
      <rule>
        <statement>Calibrate PQL score thresholds against actual close rates monthly. Adjust before sales workload drifts.</statement>
        <rationale>PQL scores drift as the product evolves. Weights that predicted conversion 2 quarters ago may now route the wrong users to sales, wasting sales capacity on low-intent users and missing high-intent users who changed behavior.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>High-weight signals (3 pts each): 100+ actions/week; invited 5+ members; attempted gated feature.</item>
        <item>Medium-weight signals (2 pts each): 10+ hours/month; 3+ integrations connected; exported or shared data.</item>
        <item>Score thresholds: below 6 = nurture; 6-8 = automated upgrade prompt; 9+ = sales outreach.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>When an agent proposes PQL weights, require it to report sample size and confidence band. Reject proposals based on samples under 200 converters + 200 churned trials.</statement>
        <rationale>PQL weight proposals based on small samples overfit. An agent reporting weights without sample size and confidence is producing a plausible-but-unvalidated scoring model that will misroute sales motion.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cohort-discipline">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cohort every metric. Minimum: M0, M1, M3, M6 retention columns per signup month.</statement>
        <rationale>Single-number metrics hide the truth. Cohort tables reveal whether recent cohorts are better or worse than historical ones, which is the leading indicator of product-market fit changes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Cohort tables displayed in dashboards with no action attached per cohort.</description>
        <reason>Retention diagnosis without root-cause analysis and an assigned experiment is theater. Each underperforming cohort needs a hypothesis and a next sprint action, not just a colored cell.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent proposes SQL aggregations on event tables without including a test query against a known sample.</description>
        <reason>LLMs produce plausible-but-wrong SQL: UNION over UNION ALL, missed deduplication on user_id, off-by-one in window functions. Always require the agent to output both the SQL and a validation query.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent summarizes cohort retention as "retention improved" when M3 dropped 2 percentage points.</description>
        <reason>LLMs rephrase directional changes to sound positive. Demand verbatim numbers in cohort summaries; no rounding, no rephrasing of direction.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Sending per-user event data (including emails, IPs, names) to an external LLM for analysis.</description>
        <reason>Per-user event data must be aggregated before sending to any external model. Sanitize PII before any LLM call that processes analytics data.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent conflates "activation" with "onboarding completion" in cohort summaries.</description>
        <reason>Activation (reaching the aha moment) and onboarding completion (finishing the setup wizard) are different events with different causal relationships to retention. Confusion between them invalidates the analysis. Inject the glossary into every analytics prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>One owner per metric. Without an owner, definitions drift and the dashboard becomes folklore.</item>
        <item>Define the activation event as ONE event, in ONE table, fired in ONE place. Cross-source unions for activation always break.</item>
        <item>Cohort everything. Single-number metrics hide the truth; M0/M1/M3/M6 retention is the floor.</item>
        <item>Track both NRR and gross dollar retention (GDR). NRR-only conceals churn.</item>
        <item>Calibrate PQL thresholds against actual close rates monthly; adjust before sales workload drifts.</item>
        <item>Keep the metric catalog version-controlled (dbt + Git). Dashboards that change definitions silently are net-negative.</item>
        <item>Pair every dashboard tile with an "if this moves, who acts and how" runbook line.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/pql-score.py" purpose="Signal-weighted PQL scoring function with band classification"/>
      <template path="templates/dashboard.md" purpose="Monthly PLG metrics dashboard template with acquisition/activation/monetization/expansion/retention sections"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://openviewpartners.com/blog/product-led-growth-metrics/"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/how-to-measure-product-led-growth"/>
      <link href="https://www.madkudu.com/resources/product-qualified-lead"/>
      <link href="https://chartmogul.com/resources/net-revenue-retention/"/>
      <link href="https://amplitude.com/blog/cohort-analysis"/>
      <link href="https://docs.getdbt.com/docs/build/about-metricflow"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
