<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="user-interviews Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for user-interviews. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every interview question must reference a past specific event, not a hypothetical future. Scan questions for would, imagine, hypothetically, do you think. If found, rewrite as past-tense behavioral.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hypothetical questions elicit wishful thinking and what people think they should want. Specific past events reveal actual behavior and real constraints.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>End every interview with a referral ask: Do you know 2-3 other people who face similar challenges? Referrals dominate cold recruiting and reduce warm-network sample bias.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Warm-network recruits skew positive and homogeneous. Referrals from satisfied customers provide credibility and reach similar (but not identical) audiences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Record plus transcribe everything (with consent). Memory after 4 interviews is worthless. Pre-prime transcription tools with a glossary of likely technical terms and proper nouns to reduce mis-attribution.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Recording prevents recall bias and provides exact quotes for synthesis. Transcription allows pattern detection across interviews without memory decay from interview fatigue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tag pains by severity AND frequency separately. High frequency plus low severity is noise. Low frequency plus extreme severity is opportunity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Frequency and severity move independently. A problem appearing once but destroying workflow is more actionable than minor annoyance everyone mentions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
