<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Change Control Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Change Control. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="cr-log-immutable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every change request MUST be logged in an immutable register with id, requester, timestamp, status, tier, and decision. Edits create new revisions; rows are never deleted.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Change Management">Without an immutable log there is no audit trail; scope-creep disputes become he-said-she-said.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="impact-analysis-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every CR MUST carry an impact analysis covering cost delta, schedule delta, scope delta, and risk delta BEFORE it reaches the approver tier.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Integrated Change Control">Approvers without impact data either approve blindly or stall indefinitely; both destroy project flow.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="tier-gated-approval" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CRs MUST route to a tiered approver based on cost+schedule impact: tier-1 (PM, &lt;2% baseline), tier-2 (sponsor, 2-10%), tier-3 (CCB, &gt;10%).</statement>
      <rationale source="PRINCE2 Manage Stage Boundaries">Single-approver designs either bottleneck on the sponsor or under-govern small changes; tiered design preserves both speed and rigour.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="baseline-re-version" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a CR is approved, the project baseline MUST be re-versioned with the CR id recorded. The old baseline is retained read-only.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Configuration Management">Without versioned baselines, EVM calculations break and historical comparisons become impossible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="rejection-recorded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rejected CRs MUST remain in the register with rejection rationale and rejecting approver. Silent deletion is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO 21500 Project Management">Silent rejection encourages re-submission with cosmetic changes; recorded rejection creates a teachable trail.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Change Control fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Change Control outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
