<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-change-process" title="Change Control Process">
  <summary>Six-step change control cycle from request capture to baseline update, with tiered decision authority and mandatory impact analysis areas.</summary>

  <section title="Process Flow">
    <p>Every change request follows: Request → Log → Analyze → Decide → Implement → Close. No step is skippable; informal approval is not approval.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>The agent prepares the impact packet; a human approver signs off before implementation begins — never auto-approve.</statement>
      <rationale>Change approval has organizational and contractual consequences. Automated approval removes the accountability trace that auditors, sponsors, and clients require.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Decision Tier Authority">
    <list>
      <item>Minor: &lt; 1 day impact, &lt; $500 cost → Project Manager approves</item>
      <item>Medium: 1-5 days impact, &lt; $5,000 cost → Sponsor approves</item>
      <item>Major: &gt; 5 days OR &gt; $5,000 OR high-risk → CCB approves</item>
      <item>Any CR that increases risk score above threshold → CCB regardless of cost/days</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tier the process by impact size; a 2-week CCB cadence for minor changes creates informal workarounds.</statement>
      <rationale>When the formal process is too slow, requesters route around it. Informal "just do it" approvals reappear as scope creep. Minor changes approved at PM level maintain process speed without bypassing governance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Impact Analysis Areas">
    <list>
      <item>Scope — what features, deliverables, or WBS elements are affected?</item>
      <item>Schedule — how many working days added or removed?</item>
      <item>Cost — what additional budget is required?</item>
      <item>Quality — does the change affect standards, testing coverage, or technical debt?</item>
      <item>Risk — what new risks does the change introduce?</item>
      <item>Resources — which team members must work on it, and what does that displace?</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run impact analysis against current baselines (scope, schedule, budget), not against the original plan.</statement>
      <rationale>The original plan is stale. Impact must be measured from the current approved baseline so the delta is accurate. Comparing to the original plan understates accumulated drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Change Register Status Values">
    <list>
      <item>Submitted — received, not yet reviewed</item>
      <item>Under Review — impact analysis in progress</item>
      <item>Approved — will be implemented; baselines must be updated before work starts</item>
      <item>Rejected — will not be implemented; reason documented for repeat-CR detection</item>
      <item>Deferred — postponed to future phase or release</item>
      <item>Implemented — completed; baseline updates verified</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track rejected CRs forever; use them to detect repeat asks and as evidence for descope discussions.</statement>
      <rationale>Rejected requests rarely die — they re-submit under a new title. A history of rejections with documented reasons allows the PM to identify repeat patterns and address the root demand.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/change-request.md">CR form with description, justification, impact table, options, decision block</reference>
    <reference path="templates/change-register.md">Change register table for tracking all CRs</reference>
    <reference path="scripts/cr-router.py">Assign approval tier from impact YAML</reference>
  </section>
</text>
