<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-change-antipatterns" title="Change Control Antipatterns and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Common change control failures, process traps, and agent-specific pitfalls for automated change request handling and impact analysis.</summary>

  <section title="Process Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No formal process — changes happen informally via chat and verbal agreements.</description>
      <reason>Informal changes have no impact analysis, no audit trail, and no baseline update. They compound invisibly until the schedule or budget collapses with no documented cause.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>PM approves every change regardless of size, bypassing Sponsor and CCB.</description>
      <reason>PM authority is limited by tier. Overreach on major changes removes the sponsor's ability to protect the project's ROI case and creates contractual exposure.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Implementing an approved CR without updating the scope, schedule, and budget baselines simultaneously.</description>
      <reason>Baselines that lag behind approved changes make EVM calculations and future change impact analysis inaccurate. Update baselines atomically with implementation confirmation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Rejecting changes without documenting the reason.</description>
      <reason>Undocumented rejections allow the same CR to re-appear under a different title. A rejection log with reasoning enables pattern detection and deflects repeat requests with evidence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require the agent's impact analysis to walk specific WBS node IDs, not handwave "schedule impact".</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs underestimate ripple effects because they reason at the summary level. Walking specific WBS elements forces the agent to consider dependency chains and resource conflicts that summary-level analysis misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Agents recommend Option A (full implementation) by default; explicitly require ranking all options including defer and decline</item>
      <item>Generated business justifications paraphrase the request instead of citing metrics; force quoting stakeholder evidence or measurement data</item>
      <item>"Approval drift" via Slack threads: agent must refuse to mark a CR Approved without an explicit decision artefact (signed form, ticket transition, email sign-off)</item>
      <item>Agents merge or rebase implementation branches without confirming baseline updates; add a checklist gate before branch merge</item>
      <item>Set a CR rate metric: &gt; 1 CR/week per $1M scope = symptom of poor initial scoping; surface to sponsor rather than silently processing</item>
      <item>Near-duplicate CRs: compare new CR against last 90 days of rejected CRs; flag similarity &gt; 0.7 with prior rejection reasons</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
