<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="change-control Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for change-control as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>No formal process — changes happen informally via chat and verbal agreements.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Informal changes have no impact analysis, no audit trail, and no baseline update. They compound invisibly until the schedule or budget collapses with no documented cause.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>PM approves every change regardless of size, bypassing Sponsor and CCB.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PM authority is limited by tier. Overreach on major changes removes the sponsor's ability to protect the project's ROI case and creates contractual exposure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Implementing an approved CR without updating the scope, schedule, and budget baselines simultaneously.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Baselines that lag behind approved changes make EVM calculations and future change impact analysis inaccurate. Update baselines atomically with implementation confirmation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Rejecting changes without documenting the reason.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Undocumented rejections allow the same CR to re-appear under a different title. A rejection log with reasoning enables pattern detection and deflects repeat requests with evidence.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
