<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-wbs-process" title="WBS — Four-Step Construction Process">
  <summary>How to build a valid WBS: start with deliverables, decompose to work packages, write the dictionary, and validate the 100% rule at every level.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Start with Major Deliverables">
    <rule>
      <statement>Begin with noun-led major deliverables (working software, documentation, training materials, infrastructure), not activities or phases.</statement>
      <rationale>WBS shows WHAT is delivered, not HOW or WHEN. Verb-led entries (Design, Build, Test) create Gantt disguised as WBS and lose the deliverable focus.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Decompose to Work Packages">
    <rule>
      <statement>Decompose each deliverable until every leaf satisfies all four work-package criteria: assignable to one person or team, estimable in 8–80 hours, measurable completion, and produces a tangible output.</statement>
      <rationale>The 8–80h rule prevents both over-decomposition (tasks too small to track) and under-decomposition (tasks too large to estimate reliably). It is the single most practical heuristic for stopping decomposition at the right level.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Depth maximum: 5 levels. Beyond level 5, the WBS becomes a schedule and should move to the activity list.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Create the WBS Dictionary">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write a dictionary entry for every work package: ID, name, description (inclusions and exclusions), acceptance criteria, owner, estimate, and dependencies.</statement>
      <rationale>Without acceptance criteria in the dictionary, Definition-of-Done is ambiguous downstream. Dictionary entries dated more than 90 days are suspect and should be refreshed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/wbs-dictionary-entry.md">WBS dictionary entry form for a single work package.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Validate with the 100% Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>At every parent node, the children must represent exactly 100% of the parent scope — no overlap, no gaps.</statement>
      <rationale>Silent 100%-rule violations leave scope holes that surface as missed deliverables late in execution. Validate explicitly at every parent; do not assume.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Development (100%) = Frontend (40%) + Backend (35%) + Integration (25%). Each child is mutually exclusive; together they cover all of development scope.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Verb-led leaf: "2.1 Design the auth flow" instead of "2.1 Auth Flow Design".</description>
      <reason>Verb-led names shift focus from deliverable to activity, making the WBS function as a Gantt rather than a scope baseline.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Baseline and Maintenance Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the WBS at level 3–4 as the scope baseline; post-baseline changes go through Change Control with a new WBS ID — never reuse or renumber removed IDs.</statement>
      <rationale>Downstream artefacts (contracts, schedules, EVM) reference WBS IDs. Renumbering destroys traceability and invalidates contract line items.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/wbs-outline.md">Hierarchical WBS outline template for six standard project phases.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/wbs-check.py">Lint script that enforces noun-led names, max depth 5, and 8–80h leaf estimate bounds.</reference>
</text>
