<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples-antipatterns" title="WBS — Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Worked WBS examples for MVP launch and solo content product, plus the five most common WBS antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>MVP Launch WBS (8 weeks): 1.0 Planning (define scope, timeline, resources), 2.0 Core Features (auth, dashboard, core workflow, settings), 3.0 Quality (testing, bug fixes, performance), 4.0 Launch (production deploy, monitoring, announcement). Each parent covers 100% of its domain; leaves are nouns (not verbs), each estimable in under a week.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Online Course (solopreneur): 1.0 Content Creation (outline, scripts, recording, worksheets), 2.0 Platform Setup (Teachable account, course structure, payment integration), 3.0 Marketing (sales page, email sequence, social promo), 4.0 Launch (beta testers, feedback iteration, public launch). Single-owner work packages, each producing a tangible deliverable.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Too detailed too early — decomposing to day-level tasks before scope is stable.</description>
      <reason>Early over-decomposition wastes planning effort; scope changes at the leaf level cascade into massive re-planning. Start high-level; add detail when the next planning horizon is confirmed.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Verb-based names: "2.1 Design authentication" instead of "2.1 Authentication Design".</description>
      <reason>WBS shows WHAT is delivered, not HOW. Verb-led names convert the WBS into a task list, losing the deliverable-traceability that makes WBS useful for scope control and contract management.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Missing the 100% rule — parent A has children B and C that together cover only 80% of A's scope.</description>
      <reason>The silent 20% gap becomes "out-of-scope" later, causing missed deliverables or unapproved change requests that surprise the customer.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No WBS dictionary — leaf names exist without acceptance criteria or ownership.</description>
      <reason>Without a dictionary, estimates are guesses and Definition-of-Done is negotiated at delivery time, which always favors the side that did not do the work.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating WBS as a schedule — adding start/end dates and sequencing to WBS nodes.</description>
      <reason>WBS shows WHAT, not WHEN. Mixing schedule information into the WBS entangles scope baseline with time baseline; a single schedule change forces WBS re-publication.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
