<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="work-breakdown-structure Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for work-breakdown-structure as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Verb-led leaf: "2.1 Design the auth flow" instead of "2.1 Auth Flow Design".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Verb-led names shift focus from deliverable to activity, making the WBS function as a Gantt rather than a scope baseline.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Too detailed too early — decomposing to day-level tasks before scope is stable.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Early over-decomposition wastes planning effort; scope changes at the leaf level cascade into massive re-planning. Start high-level; add detail when the next planning horizon is confirmed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Verb-based names: "2.1 Design authentication" instead of "2.1 Authentication Design".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>WBS shows WHAT is delivered, not HOW. Verb-led names convert the WBS into a task list, losing the deliverable-traceability that makes WBS useful for scope control and contract management.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Missing the 100% rule — parent A has children B and C that together cover only 80% of A's scope.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The silent 20% gap becomes "out-of-scope" later, causing missed deliverables or unapproved change requests that surprise the customer.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>No WBS dictionary — leaf names exist without acceptance criteria or ownership.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a dictionary, estimates are guesses and Definition-of-Done is negotiated at delivery time, which always favors the side that did not do the work.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating WBS as a schedule — adding start/end dates and sequencing to WBS nodes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>WBS shows WHAT, not WHEN. Mixing schedule information into the WBS entangles scope baseline with time baseline; a single schedule change forces WBS re-publication.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
