<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-requirements" title="Requirements Engineering and Acceptance Criteria">
  <summary>SMART criteria for functional requirements, FR format with traceability, MoSCoW prioritization, Given-When-Then acceptance criteria, and the AC coverage checklist.</summary>

  <section title="SMART Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every FR must satisfy SMART: Specific, Measurable, Achievable, Relevant, Time-bound (priority-assigned).</statement>
      <rationale>Non-SMART requirements are unverifiable. An agent cannot determine whether "users need auth" is implemented; it can verify "unregistered users cannot create accounts."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Specific: exactly who and what (bad: "Users need auth" → good: "Unregistered users cannot create accounts")</item>
      <item>Measurable: how to measure success (bad: "Should be fast" → good: "Login &lt;500ms p95")</item>
      <item>Achievable: technically feasible (bad: "AI reads minds" → good: "OAuth 2.0 with Google")</item>
      <item>Relevant: tied to business goal (bad: "Nice to have" → good: "Blocks monetization")</item>
      <item>Time-bound: priority assigned (bad: "Eventually" → good: "Must have for MVP")</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Requirement Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use "System SHALL" for must-have requirements; use "System SHOULD" for should-have; never use passive voice or conditional language.</statement>
      <rationale>SHALL is unambiguous obligation. Conditional language ("should", "could", "may") allows agents to skip requirements under their own interpretation of priority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### FR-001: Email Registration

**Requirement:** System SHALL allow users to register with email and password.
**Rationale:** Enables user identification for premium features.
**Traces to:** US-001
**Priority:** Must
**Validation Rules:**
- Email: RFC 5322 format, unique in system
- Password: min 8 chars, 1 uppercase, 1 digit
      ]]></code>
      <note>Traces to a user story. Priority is explicit. Validation rules are concrete, not prose.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="MoSCoW Prioritization">
    <list>
      <item>Must: MVP requirement, cannot launch without</item>
      <item>Should: important feature, include if possible</item>
      <item>Could: nice to have, only if time allows</item>
      <item>Won't: explicit exclusion, not in this release</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Given-When-Then Acceptance Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every FR must have at least one AC in Given-When-Then format with concrete, specific values — no vague terms.</statement>
      <rationale>ACs produced by agents are often too happy-path. Error handling, boundary conditions, and security scenarios require explicit prompting. A spec without these ACs produces implementations that handle only the success case.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### AC-001: Successful Registration

Given: User is on registration page
And: Email "test@example.com" does not exist in system
When: User enters email "test@example.com" and password "SecurePass1"
And: User clicks "Register" button
Then: Account is created in database
And: User receives verification email within 30 seconds
And: User is redirected to dashboard
And: Success message "Check your email" is displayed
      ]]></code>
      <note>Concrete values throughout: specific email, specific password, specific timeout (30 seconds), specific redirect destination, specific message text.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="AC Coverage Checklist">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every feature must have ACs covering: happy path, error handling, boundary conditions, security scenarios, performance scenarios (if NFRs exist), and accessibility.</statement>
      <rationale>Without explicit coverage requirements, agents write only happy-path ACs. Security scenarios (auth bypass, injection attempts) are almost never included without explicit instruction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Happy path: main success scenario with expected outputs</item>
      <item>Error handling: validation failures, service unavailability, timeout</item>
      <item>Boundary conditions: min/max values, empty states, null inputs</item>
      <item>Security scenarios: auth bypass attempt, injection attempt</item>
      <item>Performance scenarios: load handling, response time under concurrency</item>
      <item>Accessibility: screen reader, keyboard navigation</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/spec-api.md">API endpoint spec template with error shapes</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-spec.txt">Prompts for writing and reviewing specs</reference>
</text>
