<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="cognitive-walkthrough">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Expert-inspection method evaluating interface learnability by stepping through correct action sequences with four structured questions per step.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>usability</tag>
      <tag>evaluation</tag>
      <tag>learnability</tag>
      <tag>expert-review</tag>
      <tag>methodology</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Cognitive Walkthrough</title>
    <summary>A structured expert-inspection method that evaluates interface learnability by stepping through a known correct action sequence and answering four questions per step: does the user know what to do, can they see how, does the label make sense, and do they get feedback that it worked?</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Cognitive walkthrough finds learnability failures before any user is recruited—cheaper and faster than moderated testing. It is especially sensitive to problems that block first-time users: invisible actions, ambiguous labels, and missing progress feedback. A 2-4 person team can cover a full onboarding flow in under two hours and produce a prioritized fix list.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Evaluating learnability for first-time users: kiosks, sign-up flows, onboarding.</item>
        <item>Pre-launch sanity check before recruiting participants for usability testing.</item>
        <item>Auditing a defined task path (checkout, account setup) where the correct sequence is known.</item>
        <item>Government / public-service flows where novice users dominate.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Open-ended exploratory tasks (browsing)—no single correct sequence exists.</item>
        <item>Replacing real user research: walkthrough finds learnability issues, not preference or value.</item>
        <item>Subjective brand or aesthetic review—heuristic evaluation is the right method.</item>
        <item>Late-stage efficiency tuning for expert users—use keystroke-level model (KLM) or GOMS.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="prerequisites">
      <p>A successful cognitive walkthrough requires advance preparation:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Define persona, task, and the complete correct action sequence in writing before the walkthrough session begins.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a pre-agreed sequence the walkthrough devolves into freeform critique; you cannot answer Q4 without knowing what "progress" looks like.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Target persona: name, experience level, prior knowledge, goal.</item>
        <item>Task: single clear statement (e.g., "Create a new account and complete profile setup").</item>
        <item>Correct sequence: ordered list of actions with expected UI result for each step.</item>
        <item>Interface: prototype or live URL, accessible to all evaluators before the session.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Group size: 2-4 evaluators. Larger groups converge too quickly; smaller groups miss blind spots.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="the-four-questions">
      <p>The core of cognitive walkthrough: four questions answered per step of the correct action sequence.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Answer all four questions for every step independently; do not skip steps where the answer seems obvious.</statement>
        <rationale>Evaluators with product familiarity skip steps that first-time users actually fail at—the methodology's value is systematic coverage.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Q1: Will the user try to achieve the right effect? (Motivation and goal awareness)</statement>
        <rationale>Assesses whether the user knows they need to take an action at this step. Failure modes: user does not realize this step is necessary, or believes the task is already complete.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Q2: Will the user notice that the correct action is available? (Visibility and location)</statement>
        <rationale>Assesses whether the control or element is perceptually obvious. Failure modes: button hidden in a menu, link uses passive language, control is off-screen.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Q3: Will the user associate the correct action with the desired effect? (Label clarity and affordance)</statement>
        <rationale>Assesses whether the label or visual cue communicates what happens when the action is performed. Failure modes: vague label ("Submit" vs. "Create Account"), misleading icon, affordance does not match platform conventions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Q4: If the correct action is performed, will the user see that progress is being made? (Feedback adequacy)</statement>
        <rationale>Assesses whether the system provides feedback (visual, auditory, haptic) confirming the action was received and the system is advancing toward the goal. Failure modes: no loading indicator, page load goes silent, success message does not appear.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="issue-documentation">
      <p>How to record findings from the walkthrough:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>For every "No" or "Partial" answer, document: problem description, question number, severity (H/M/L), and a one-sentence fix proposal.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a fix proposal the walkthrough produces a problem list with no actionable next step; forcing a proposal reveals whether the issue is real or cosmetic.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Severity levels: High—blocks task completion for the persona; must fix before launch. Medium—slows user by more than one additional turn or exchange; fix soon. Low—polish issue; fix when capacity allows.</statement>
        <rationale>Clear severity definitions prevent severity inflation and support prioritization.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="evaluator-calibration">
      <p>Rules for keeping expert evaluators aligned and accurate:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Each evaluator must answer each question independently before discussion; reveal answers simultaneously.</statement>
        <rationale>Group-think from fast consensus causes evaluators to adopt the first answer rather than their genuine assessment of the interface.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use only the persona profile as the reference frame; ignore personal familiarity with the product.</statement>
        <rationale>Evaluators with product knowledge answer "Yes" to Q2 and Q3 because they know where the button is—the novice persona does not.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-walk the sequence after fixes are implemented; never assume a fix resolves the issue without verification.</statement>
        <rationale>Fixes for Q2 (visibility) sometimes introduce Q3 failures (label confusion); a re-walk catches regressions cheaply.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>How to apply cognitive walkthrough with AI agents:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use a subagent as the "naive persona"—feed it a screen capture or DOM snapshot plus the persona file, and have it answer the four CW questions per step. A second agent role-plays an "advocate" arguing the opposite, then a synthesizer extracts genuine ambiguities. Humans confirm prioritized issues and own the fix list.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents excel at systematic application of a protocol. Dividing the agent role into persona evaluator, devil's advocate, and synthesizer reduces agent bias and improves coverage.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <rule>
        <statement>faion-usability-agent drives the four-question protocol per step. faion-ux-researcher-agent converts findings into research-grade report and recruits real users for confirmation. faion-sdd-executor-agent applies UI fixes (label, position, feedback) once approved.</statement>
        <rationale>Each subagent specializes in a phase: protocol execution, research synthesis, and implementation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <p>Effective prompts for cognitive walkthrough agents:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Persona evaluation: "You are the persona [persona profile] on screen [screenshot/DOM]. The correct next action is [action]. Answer Yes/No/Partial with 2-sentence rationale for: Q1 right effect; Q2 action visible; Q3 label associates with effect; Q4 progress feedback. Be skeptical."</statement>
        <rationale>Seeding the persona, showing the interface, and naming the target action anchors the agent's evaluation. "Be skeptical" combats the agent's default charity bias.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Issue extraction: "Take all No/Partial answers and produce: severity (H/M/L), WCAG/heuristic tag, smallest fix in 1 sentence, owner team."</statement>
        <rationale>Structured output forces the agent to translate findings into actionable recommendations.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-specific-gotchas">
      <p>Common mistakes when AI agents run cognitive walkthroughs:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM agent answers "Yes" to Q2 and Q3 without positive evidence from the screenshot or DOM.</description>
        <reason>Agents default to charitable interpretation; require "Yes only if the screenshot shows X" in the prompt to force grounding.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent conflates Q1 (does user know they need to act?) with Q3 (does label match the action?).</description>
        <reason>These are distinct failure types—Q1 is motivational, Q3 is labelling—separate prompts prevent cross-contamination.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent answers Q4 for the page transition rather than for the user's stated goal.</description>
        <reason>A page load is not progress feedback; the user's internal narrative ("did I complete step X?") is the correct reference.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Persona file not reseeded each step; agent forgets the persona midway through a long session.</description>
        <reason>LLMs drift from persona context over long conversations; reseed the persona description at each step.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent marks all issues as High severity.</description>
        <reason>Severity inflation renders prioritization meaningless; apply the H/M/L rubric explicitly: H = blocks task, M = extra turn, L = polish.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>What cognitive walkthrough does not measure:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Walkthrough finds learnability issues, not preference, satisfaction, or value—do not replace user research.</item>
        <item>Motivational issues ("user knows what to do, just does not want to") are invisible to the method.</item>
        <item>Accessibility is ignored unless the persona explicitly includes AT (assistive technology) use.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>Tools for capturing interface state and automating walkthrough steps:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>playwright (page.screenshot() / page.accessibility.snapshot()): Capture per-step DOM/AX trees. Docs: playwright.dev.</statement>
        <rationale>Screenshot and accessibility tree in one command; enables systematic per-step documentation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>axe-core CLI: Tag a11y issues alongside CW. Docs: deque.com/axe.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated accessibility audit to supplement CW findings.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>pa11y-ci: Repeatable a11y baseline per route. Docs: pa11y.org.</statement>
        <rationale>Track accessibility regression across iterations.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Storybook + interaction tests: Walk through each step in isolation. Docs: storybook.js.org.</statement>
        <rationale>Isolate UI states for systematic evaluation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Lighthouse CLI: Snap perf/accessibility per step. Docs: github.com/GoogleChrome/lighthouse.</statement>
        <rationale>Quantify performance and accessibility alongside usability findings.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-platforms">
      <p>External services for cognitive walkthrough support:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Maze: SaaS. Partial agent support via REST for results. Auto-tracks first-click, time-to-complete.</statement>
        <rationale>Complements CW with real-user first-click and path data.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>UserTesting: SaaS. Partial agent support via REST API. Real-user complement after CW.</statement>
        <rationale>After CW fixes, validate with real users via UserTesting.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Lookback: SaaS. Manual observation. Use only for live observation.</statement>
        <rationale>Moderated usability testing; use after CW to confirm findings.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Useberry: SaaS. Agent-friendly with REST API. First-click + path data feeds CW question 2.</statement>
        <rationale>API-driven first-click testing directly informs Q2 (visibility) findings.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Loom + transcript LLM: Mixed approach. Loom API captures evaluator narrative, LLM summarizes.</statement>
        <rationale>Automate walkthrough documentation via video transcription.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write the correct action sequence before evaluation; if you cannot, the task is too vague to walkthrough.</statement>
        <rationale>The sequence is the foundation of the method; vague sequences produce vague findings.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use a *novice* persona—for expert flows, run a separate session with a power-user persona.</statement>
        <rationale>Walkthrough is most valuable for first-time users; expert users have different pain points.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Score each question independently per step; do not let evaluators see prior answers until the end.</statement>
        <rationale>Independence prevents group-think and anchoring bias.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>For each issue, force a one-sentence fix proposal—"report the bug, propose the fix" rule.</statement>
        <rationale>A fix proposal forces clarity and prevents vague problem statements.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-walk after fixes; CW iterations are cheap and catch regressions.</statement>
        <rationale>Fixes sometimes introduce new issues; iteration is the fastest validation path.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pair with one round of moderated usability testing on the top 5 issues.</statement>
        <rationale>Expert review is efficient but has blind spots; user confirmation validates prioritization.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-when-it-fails">
      <p>Conditions where cognitive walkthrough is less effective:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Evaluators bring tacit knowledge—"obvious" buttons aren't obvious to the persona.</description>
        <reason>Product familiarity is the largest source of evaluator bias. Explicitly bracket this knowledge and stick to the persona.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Group-think when 2-4 evaluators converge fast on the first answer; structure each question independently.</description>
        <reason>Social dynamics lead to premature consensus. Independent answering and simultaneous reveal prevents this.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Misses motivational issues ("user knows what to do, just does not want to").</description>
        <reason>CW is a learnability method, not a preference or value method. If motivation is the failure mode, use different research.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ignores accessibility unless persona explicitly includes AT use.</description>
        <reason>CW evaluates learnability, not accessibility. Pair with an accessibility audit (axe, pa11y) to catch WCAG issues.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="references">
      <p>Academic and practitioner sources on cognitive walkthrough:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Wharton, Rieman, Lewis, Polson—*The Cognitive Walkthrough: A Practitioner's Guide* (1994).</item>
        <item>NN/g, "Cognitive Walkthrough"—nngroup.com/articles/cognitive-walkthrough-workshop/</item>
        <item>IDF, "How to Conduct a Cognitive Walkthrough"—interaction-design.org/literature/article/how-to-conduct-a-cognitive-walkthrough</item>
        <item>Usability.gov, "Cognitive Walkthroughs"—usability.gov/how-to-and-tools/methods/cognitive-walkthroughs.html</item>
        <item>Spencer, "Streamlined Cognitive Walkthrough"—uxbooth.com</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/walkthrough-plan.md" purpose="Pre-session plan: persona, task, correct sequence table, interface link, scope."/>
      <template path="templates/evaluation-form.md" purpose="Per-step evaluation: Q1-Q4 answers, issues table, screenshot slot."/>
      <template path="templates/summary-report.md" purpose="Post-session report: executive summary, findings by step, priority recommendations."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/cognitive-walkthrough-workshop/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/how-to-conduct-a-cognitive-walkthrough"/>
      <link href="https://www.usability.gov/how-to-and-tools/methods/cognitive-walkthroughs.html"/>
      <link href="https://uxbooth.com/articles/streamlined-cognitive-walkthrough/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
