<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="RACI Matrix Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the raci-matrix methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="exactly-one-accountable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every task must have exactly one Accountable — no shared A, no A/A splits.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI literature; field experience">Two Accountables means neither can make a final decision unilaterally; teams compromise on 'A1/A2' which hides escalation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="at-least-one-responsible" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every task must have at least one Responsible.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI literature">A task with only A, C, or I has no one committed to doing the actual work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="consulted-cap-4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap Consulted at 3-4 per task; more than 4 is a bottleneck signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field experience">Each Consulted requires a round-trip communication; beyond 4 coordination overhead exceeds value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="walk-in-kickoff" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Walk the RACI in the kickoff meeting cell-by-cell with all roles present.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — RACI rollout audits">Silent paper sign-off produces false consensus; verbal walkthrough surfaces 'I didn't know I was Accountable' before work begins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="role-titles-not-names" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use role titles, not individual names — roles survive personnel changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field experience">Person-named matrices become stale on every transition.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="diff-not-rewrite" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When updating an existing RACI, output a unified diff showing what changed, not a full rewrite.</statement>
      <rationale source="Configuration management practice">Full rewrites hide which roles changed and break the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>One-person solo task with no external stakeholders</item>
      <item>Pure agile teams with collective code ownership and one PO — flattens to PO=A everywhere</item>
      <item>Highly emergent work where roles shift weekly — matrix decays faster than it is updated</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
