<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="raci-matrix Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for raci-matrix. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every task must have exactly one Accountable — no shared A, no A/A splits.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Two Accountables means neither can make a final decision unilaterally. Teams compromise on "A1/A2", which hides the escalation path and requires a third party to break ties at the worst possible moment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every task must have at least one Responsible.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A task with only A, C, or I has no one committed to doing the actual work. It will be ignored until the Accountable notices it has not been done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap Consulted at 3-4 per task; more than 4 is a bottleneck signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each Consulted requires a round-trip communication before work proceeds. Beyond 4, the coordination overhead exceeds the value of the input received.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Walk the RACI in the kickoff meeting cell-by-cell with all roles present.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Paper sign-off on a matrix nobody read produces false consensus. Verbal walkthrough surfaces "I didn't know I was Accountable for that" before work begins, not at the deadline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Force-feed the cap "Consulted ≤ 4 per task" into every agent prompt that generates RACI assignments.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents default to including every stakeholder as Consulted because it seems inclusive. Without explicit constraint, every matrix balloons to 8+ Consulted per task, rendering the matrix unusable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require agents to output a violation report (using raci-validate.py) before finalizing any matrix.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents miss edge cases like "all-I rows" and "A=R antipatterns" if you do not force a structured validation step. The script surfaces violations; the human decides resolution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When updating an existing RACI, output a unified diff (CSV row-by-row) showing what changed, not a full rewrite.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Full rewrites hide which roles changed, making it hard to discuss impacts. Diffs make role changes explicit and traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
