<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-raci-rules" title="RACI Rules and Validation">
  <summary>Role definitions, construction steps, and four validation rules for RACI matrices covering project tasks or deliverables.</summary>

  <section title="Role Definitions">
    <list>
      <item>R — Responsible: does the work; can be multiple people per task</item>
      <item>A — Accountable: single final decision maker; escalation endpoint; only ONE per task</item>
      <item>C — Consulted: provides input before decision; two-way communication; keep to minimum</item>
      <item>I — Informed: notified after decision; one-way communication; be generous with I</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every task must have exactly one Accountable — no shared A, no A/A splits.</statement>
      <rationale>Two Accountables means neither can make a final decision unilaterally. Teams compromise on "A1/A2", which hides the escalation path and requires a third party to break ties at the worst possible moment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every task must have at least one Responsible.</statement>
      <rationale>A task with only A, C, or I has no one committed to doing the actual work. It will be ignored until the Accountable notices it has not been done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap Consulted at 3-4 per task; more than 4 is a bottleneck signal.</statement>
      <rationale>Each Consulted requires a round-trip communication before work proceeds. Beyond 4, the coordination overhead exceeds the value of the input received.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Construction Steps">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — List tasks: use WBS work packages or deliverables as rows</item>
      <item>Step 2 — List roles: use role titles, not individual names — roles survive personnel changes</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Assign RACI values: start with A (who owns the outcome?), then R (who does the work?), then C and I</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Validate: check all four rules; do NOT auto-resolve violations — flag for human</item>
      <item>Step 5 — Walk in kickoff: review cell-by-cell with all roles present; silent acknowledgement is not consent</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Walk the RACI in the kickoff meeting cell-by-cell with all roles present.</statement>
      <rationale>Paper sign-off on a matrix nobody read produces false consensus. Verbal walkthrough surfaces "I didn't know I was Accountable for that" before work begins, not at the deadline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Validation Rules">
    <list>
      <item>No A: assign an Accountable or escalate to sponsor to pick one</item>
      <item>Multiple A: force a single choice; surface the conflict to the sponsor if roles dispute ownership</item>
      <item>No R: assign a Responsible party or remove the task from scope</item>
      <item>All I in a row: the role is not needed for this task — remove from matrix</item>
      <item>C count &gt; 4: reduce to essential Consulted only; convert remainder to I</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="scripts/raci-validate.py">CSV validator checking all four rules with per-violation error output</reference>
    <reference path="templates/raci-matrix.md">Blank RACI grid template</reference>
  </section>
</text>
