<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-raci-examples" title="RACI Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Worked RACI examples for a feature development team and a solopreneur setup, plus common antipatterns and agent-specific pitfalls.</summary>

  <section title="Feature Development Example">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Task                | PM | Product | Engineering | Design | QA
--------------------|----|---------|--------------|---------|----|
Define requirements |  C |    A    |      C       |    C   |  I
Create mockups      |  I |    C    |      I       |    R   |  I
Approve design      |  I |    A    |      C       |    R   |  I
Write code          |  I |    C    |      R       |    I   |  I
Code review         |  I |    I    |      A       |    I   |  I
Write tests         |  I |    I    |      C       |    I   |  R
Deploy to staging   |  C |    I    |      R       |    I   |  C
UAT sign-off        |  I |    A    |      I       |    I   |  R
Production deploy   |  A |    I    |      R       |    I   |  C
]]></code>
      <note>Engineering is A for Code Review (code quality) but R for Write Code — Accountable and Responsible are separated to preserve escalation paths.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Solopreneur with Contractors Example">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Task        | You  | Designer | Developer | VA
------------|------|----------|-----------|----
Vision      | A/R  |    I     |     I     |  I
UI design   |  A   |    R     |     C     |  I
Development |  A   |    C     |     R     |  I
Testing     |  A   |    I     |     C     |  R
Launch      | A/R  |    I     |     I     |  C
]]></code>
      <note>Even with small teams, RACI prevents "I thought you were handling that" disputes with contractors who have parallel commitments.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>A=R for the senior role on every task.</description>
      <reason>LLMs and inexperienced PMs assign A=R to the project lead because charters say "PM owns delivery". The Accountable should not be doing the work — that conflation breaks the escalation chain.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Assigning C to every named role "to be thorough".</description>
      <reason>Every C requires a feedback round-trip. A matrix with 8 Consulted per task is a meeting schedule, not a responsibility model. Set an explicit cap (3-4 C per task) in the generation prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Storing RACI only in Confluence with no version history.</description>
      <reason>Role changes are invisible without diffs. Keep RACI in source control as CSV; generate Markdown view for Confluence. Agents should output a unified diff when updating, not a full rewrite.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent silently fixes violations by reassigning roles without human review.</description>
      <reason>Every role change has organizational implications. Violations must surface to the human Accountable for resolution — the agent flags but never resolves autonomously.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
