<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-execution" title="Migration Execution, Cutover, and Validation">
  <summary>Three-run migration strategy, freeze period, post-cutover validation, parallel-run period, and rollback requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Run Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the migration three times: dev-environment test, full dry-run with rollback on a clone of production, real cutover; each run catches a different class of bug.</statement>
      <rationale>Dev test catches logic errors. Full dry-run catches rate limits, size limits, and data-edge cases that only appear at scale. Real cutover catches timing and concurrency issues under live load.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Run 1 (dev test): validate field mappings, auth, and basic ETL flow on a small data sample.</item>
      <item>Run 2 (dry-run): run against a full production data clone; validate counts, comments, and attachments; confirm rollback path.</item>
      <item>Run 3 (real cutover): freeze source, execute migration, validate three numbers, declare success or rollback.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Freeze Period">
    <rule>
      <statement>Freeze the source tool 4 hours before cutover; route new tickets created during the window to a known "intake" queue and re-key them by hand after cutover.</statement>
      <rationale>Issues created during migration create reconciliation complexity. A short freeze with a manual intake queue is simpler and less risky than attempting live-sync.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Post-Cutover Validation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate three numbers before declaring migration successful: total issue count, total comment count, and total attachment volume by byte.</statement>
      <rationale>Three independent counts at different granularities catch distinct failure modes: issues lost, comments orphaned, and attachments silently dropped at size limits.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Manually sample-validate 50 random issues by hand, comparing source to target field-by-field; automated count validation does not catch field-content corruption.</statement>
      <rationale>Status mapping bugs, Markdown-to-HTML conversion failures, and @mention resolution failures appear in field content, not in counts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>After migrating 12,000 Jira issues to Linear: count matched (12,000 = 12,000); comment count matched (47,831 = 47,831); attachment bytes matched (8.4 GB = 8.4 GB). Manual sample of 50 issues revealed 3 with status mapping errors (Resolved → Done instead of In Review). Fix applied; re-run of status correction script; re-validate.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Parallel Run and Rollback">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the source tool read-only for at least 30 days after cutover; users will need to look up historical context for months after the switch.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-cutover lookup requests are predictable and frequent. Read-only access at no cost is safer than full decommission and cheaper than rebuilding access when needed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Decommissioning the source tool immediately after cutover success.</description>
      <reason>"Inevitably someone needs to look up what was decided in PROJ-456" — this is guaranteed to happen within days. Premature decommission forces re-provisioning under pressure.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/count-check.py">Source vs target count comparison with 1% drift threshold</reference>
  <reference path="templates/field-mapping.md">Field mapping table with "won't migrate" documentation column</reference>
</text>
