<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-well-architected" title="Azure Well-Architected Framework">
  <summary>Five pillars of the Azure Well-Architected Framework with concrete implementation guidance per pillar.</summary>

  <section title="Reliability">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design for failure recovery at every scale: deploy across availability zones, implement circuit breakers and retry with exponential backoff, and plan explicit data recovery paths.</statement>
      <rationale>Azure SLA for single-VM is 99.9%. Zone-redundant deployments achieve 99.99%. The difference is 8 hours vs 52 minutes of downtime per year.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Use availability zones for critical VMs, databases, and load balancers</item>
      <item>Configure geo-redundant storage (GRS/GZRS) for data with RTO &lt; 4h requirements</item>
      <item>Implement health checks and auto-healing via VMSS or AKS readiness probes</item>
      <item>Define and test recovery procedures for ransomware — Azure Backup immutable vaults</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Security">
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement Zero Trust: never trust, always verify. Use Microsoft Entra ID for all identity, Managed Identity for service-to-service auth, and Private Endpoints for PaaS service access.</statement>
      <rationale>Network perimeter security fails when an attacker is already inside the network. Zero Trust authenticates every request regardless of source, reducing lateral movement after initial compromise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Replace service principal keys with Managed Identity wherever possible</item>
      <item>Use PIM (Privileged Identity Management) for just-in-time admin access</item>
      <item>Enable Microsoft Defender for Cloud and respond to Secure Score recommendations</item>
      <item>Use customer-managed keys (CMK) in Azure Key Vault for regulated data</item>
      <item>Private Endpoints for Azure Storage, SQL, Key Vault — no public internet exposure</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Cost Optimization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Right-size before committing: use Azure Monitor metrics to identify P95 CPU/memory usage, then apply Azure Reservations for a 1-3 year commitment at 40-72% discount.</statement>
      <rationale>Reservations without right-sizing commits to overprovisioned resources. Right-sizing alone without reservations pays on-demand prices. Both steps together maximize savings.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Azure Reservations: up to 72% savings on VMs, 40% on SQL</item>
      <item>Azure Savings Plans: up to 65% across compute families</item>
      <item>Spot VMs: up to 90% for interruptible workloads (CI, batch, dev)</item>
      <item>Auto-shutdown dev VMs on schedule: 50%+ savings on dev environments</item>
      <item>Use Azure Cost Management + budgets + alerts to prevent surprise bills</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Operational Excellence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deploy all infrastructure via IaC (Bicep or Terraform); never make manual changes in the portal for production resources.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual portal changes create configuration drift that is invisible to code reviewers, cannot be rolled back, and is not reproducible for disaster recovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Use Azure Verified Modules (AVM) for new deployments — maintained by Microsoft with security best practices baked in</item>
      <item>Automate deployments through CI/CD pipelines with staging environment first</item>
      <item>Use Azure Monitor + Log Analytics + Application Insights for unified observability</item>
      <item>Define runbooks for all Tier 1 operations — no tribal knowledge</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Performance Efficiency">
    <rule>
      <statement>Scale horizontally before vertically — add instances via VMSS or AKS HPA before increasing VM size.</statement>
      <rationale>Vertical scaling requires downtime or live migration. Horizontal scaling is elastic and resilient. Azure VMSS supports autoscale based on CPU, memory, and custom metrics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Use Azure Cache for Redis to eliminate repeated database reads for hot data</item>
      <item>Azure CDN / Front Door for static assets and global routing</item>
      <item>Use Async processing (Service Bus, Event Grid) to decouple heavy operations from request path</item>
      <item>Establish performance baselines in staging before production release</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
