<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="API-First Principles and Toolchain">
  <summary>Core principles of API-first development, the design-to-deploy workflow, and the canonical toolchain for OpenAPI 3.1.</summary>

  <section title="Core Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design the API contract (OpenAPI spec) before writing any implementation code.</statement>
      <rationale>The contract is the first artifact. All downstream work — server stubs, client SDKs, mock servers, documentation, contract tests — is generated from or validated against the spec. This prevents implementation-driven API shapes that are inconsistent across services.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the spec as the single source of truth: generate code, tests, and docs from it, never the reverse.</statement>
      <rationale>When code is the source of truth, documentation drifts within weeks. Generating from spec ensures structural consistency; deviations are caught by Spectral linting and contract tests (Dredd, Pact).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Design endpoints for API consumers, not for implementation convenience.</statement>
      <rationale>Consumer-driven design surfaces usability problems before code is written. Implementation-convenient designs often expose internal data structures, forcing consumers to do transformation work the API should handle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Deploy a mock server (Prism) from the spec before any backend code exists.</statement>
      <rationale>Mock servers enable parallel frontend/backend development. Frontend teams build against the contract; backend teams implement against it. Both converge on the same interface without blocking each other.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Workflow">
    <p>DESIGN → VALIDATE → MOCK → IMPLEMENT → TEST → DEPLOY</p>
    <list>
      <item>DESIGN: Write OpenAPI 3.1 YAML spec (endpoints, schemas, auth, errors)</item>
      <item>VALIDATE: Run Spectral linting; fix errors before proceeding</item>
      <item>MOCK: Start Prism mock server; share with frontend team</item>
      <item>IMPLEMENT: Generate server stubs from spec; implement business logic</item>
      <item>TEST: Run Dredd or Pact contract tests against running server</item>
      <item>DEPLOY: Gate on contract tests passing in CI before merge</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="OpenAPI 3.1 Key Features">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use OpenAPI 3.1 (not 3.0) for all new specs; use type: ['string', 'null'] for nullable fields, not nullable: true.</statement>
      <rationale>OAS 3.1 aligns with full JSON Schema 2020-12 vocabulary. The nullable: true pattern is OAS 3.0-only and produces incorrect schema validation in 3.1-aware tools. Agents default to 3.0 patterns — specify version explicitly in every prompt.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>JSON Schema alignment: full JSON Schema vocabularies supported (not subset)</item>
      <item>Webhooks: new top-level element for event-driven/outbound APIs</item>
      <item>$ref improvements: better reference handling, circular refs supported</item>
      <item>Nullable: use type: ['string', 'null'] not nullable: true</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Toolchain">
    <list>
      <item>Specification: OpenAPI 3.1 (REST), AsyncAPI 2.x (event-driven)</item>
      <item>Linting: Spectral (configurable rules), Redocly CLI (bundle + lint)</item>
      <item>Mocking: Prism (mock server from spec), WireMock (stateful mocking)</item>
      <item>Documentation: Swagger UI, Redoc, Stoplight</item>
      <item>Code generation: openapi-generator-cli (server stubs + client SDKs)</item>
      <item>Contract testing: Dredd (spec vs. server), Pact (consumer-driven)</item>
      <item>Breaking change detection: bump diff (CI diff on every PR)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/openapi-3.1-skeleton.yaml">Minimal complete OpenAPI 3.1 spec skeleton</reference>
  <reference path="scripts/api-first-check.sh">Lint spec with Spectral + start Prism mock server</reference>
</text>
