<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-checklist" title="API-First Development Checklist">
  <summary>Phase-by-phase checklist from spec design through contract testing, covering the eight stages of API-first workflow.</summary>

  <section title="Phase 1: Spec Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define API title, version, description, authentication method, rate limiting strategy, and server URLs before writing any endpoint.</statement>
      <rationale>Global settings establish the contract envelope. Authentication schemes defined globally and referenced per-operation prevent inconsistent security definitions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Define API title, version (semantic), and description with auth + rate limit docs</item>
      <item>List production and staging server URLs</item>
      <item>Plan versioning strategy (/v1/, /v2/) before writing first endpoint</item>
      <item>Define global security schemes (bearerAuth, apiKey, OAuth2)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 2: Endpoint Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign an operationId to every endpoint; without it, SDK generators and mock routers produce unusable output.</statement>
      <rationale>openapi-generator uses operationId for function names. Prism uses it for routing. Blank operationIds produce conflicts or random names that break generated code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Design all resource endpoints (/resources, /resources/{id})</item>
      <item>Define HTTP methods per endpoint (GET/POST/PUT/DELETE/PATCH)</item>
      <item>Assign camelCase operationId to every operation</item>
      <item>Define request parameters (path, query, body) with types and constraints</item>
      <item>Design success responses (200, 201) and all error responses</item>
      <item>Include at least one example per POST/PUT/PATCH endpoint</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 3: Schema Definition">
    <list>
      <item>Define all reusable schemas under components/schemas</item>
      <item>Mark required properties explicitly</item>
      <item>Set format hints (uuid, date-time, email, uri)</item>
      <item>Define validation constraints (minLength, maxLength, minimum, maximum, pattern)</item>
      <item>Use $ref for all shared schemas — never inline the same shape twice</item>
      <item>Define global error schema and reference from all error responses</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 4: Validation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run Spectral linting before generating mock servers or code; lint errors that break mock server routing are blocking, style issues are deferrable.</statement>
      <rationale>Spectral catches $ref to non-existent components, missing required fields, and naming violations. Unresolved $refs crash Prism. Style issues can be addressed after first mock deployment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Run Spectral with project ruleset (.spectral.yaml)</item>
      <item>Categorize violations: (1) errors blocking mock server, (2) SDK generation warnings, (3) deferrable style issues</item>
      <item>Verify all operations have examples</item>
      <item>Check consistent naming conventions across all endpoints</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phases 5-8: Mock, Codegen, Contract Testing">
    <list>
      <item>Generate mock server: prism mock openapi.yaml --port 4010</item>
      <item>Test all endpoints with mock data before backend implementation starts</item>
      <item>Generate server stubs from spec: openapi-generator-cli generate</item>
      <item>Generate client SDKs for all consumer languages</item>
      <item>Write contract tests (Dredd/Pact) that run in CI on every PR</item>
      <item>Gate merge on contract tests passing — prevents spec drift</item>
      <item>Run bump diff on every PR to surface breaking changes</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
