<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="api-first-development Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for api-first-development as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Writing the spec after the implementation is complete.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The spec becomes documentation, not a contract. Inconsistencies between spec and implementation are never caught because there are no contract tests. Consumers build against the spec and hit unexpected behavior from the real server.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>No versioning strategy planned before the first endpoint is written.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Retroactively adding /v1/ prefix requires breaking changes for all existing consumers. Plan for v1 and v2 from the start; adding /v2/ for breaking changes is expected, not a failure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Regenerating server stubs after manually modifying generated code.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Regeneration overwrites customizations. Generated stubs must be treated as read-only scaffolding; all business logic lives in separate service files that stubs delegate to.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Spec and implementation live in separate PRs or repositories.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Spec diverges from implementation within days. Version the spec file in the same commit as the first implementation task: breaking the spec-code coupling is the root cause of most API contract drift.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates valid OpenAPI syntax but uses nullable: true in an OAS 3.1 spec.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>nullable: true is OAS 3.0 syntax. In 3.1, nullable fields require type: ['string', 'null']. Spectral flags this; un-linted agent output will produce incorrect schema validation in 3.1-aware parsers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates syntactically valid spec with $ref pointing to a non-existent component.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Prism and SDK generators crash on unresolved $refs. Agents produce valid YAML that references #/components/schemas/Foo where Foo is never defined. Always run Spectral after agent-generated specs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Frontend code written against mock server silently breaks when connecting to real backend.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mock servers serve spec-driven stubs, not real business logic. Mocks enforce contract shape but not business rules (e.g., stock validation, price calculation). Agents writing frontend against mocks miss this gap.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent modifies backend implementation without updating the spec.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Contract drift: Dredd/Pact tests fail on next run, not immediately. Configure CI to run contract tests and fail the PR; without this gate, spec and implementation diverge silently.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
