<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Single Channel Bet Selector Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that turn channel-picking from intuition into a written, falsifiable decision a solo founder can commit to for 90 days.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The selection MUST be a written rubric (single page, version-controlled or dated doc) listing every candidate channel scored on three named axes; verbal "I think SEO feels right" is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>Solo founders fail by trying four channels poorly; the failure mode is invisible because each pivot is justified verbally. A written rubric makes the decision falsifiable and re-readable in 90 days when the bet is graded.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Each candidate channel MUST be scored on three axes: founder_fit (1–5, will you actually do it weekly without quitting), ICP_density (1–5, are 50%+ of your customers already there), early_traction (1–5, have you had at least one inbound lead from this channel unsolicited).</statement>
      <rationale>Channels list methodologies enumerate options but do not help pick the ONE that fits founder DNA + ICP. The three-axis intersection forces alignment between what you'll execute, who you serve, and what already works — failing any one axis is a leading indicator of 90-day failure.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[| Channel | Founder fit | ICP density | Early traction | Total |
|---------|-------------|-------------|----------------|-------|
| SEO     | 2           | 5           | 4              | 11    |
| LinkedIn| 5           | 4           | 4              | 13 ← |
| Cold email | 1        | 3           | 1              | 5     |
| Podcast tour | 3      | 4           | 2              | 9     |]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The chosen channel MUST score ≥12/15 total AND ≥3/5 on every individual axis; channels below the floor are rejected even if total is high.</statement>
      <rationale>A channel that scores 5/5/2 (no early traction) burns 90 days of execution to discover what the rubric already said. The per-axis floor prevents the spreadsheet from rationalising a known-bad bet.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The founder MUST commit to exactly ONE channel for 90 days and document this commitment alongside the rubric; channels 2 and 3 are explicitly parked, not pursued in parallel.</statement>
      <rationale>The whole point is that solo founders fail by trying 4 channels poorly. Parallel pursuit destroys the per-channel signal-to-noise ratio and means none of them gets enough reps to compound. Writing down the parking lot makes the trade-off visible and reversible at the 90-day grade.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The plan MUST name a written 90-day kill criterion (e.g. "if I have not produced X leads / Y signups by week 12, the bet failed and I re-run the rubric").</statement>
      <rationale>Without a kill criterion, the bet has no exit and either drags on indefinitely or gets abandoned secretly. An explicit pre-committed metric removes the founder's emotional sunk-cost vote at week 12.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Kill criterion (set 2026-05-20):
If LinkedIn posts have not produced ≥10 qualified demo requests
AND ≥1 paying customer by 2026-08-20, the bet has failed.
On that date I re-score the rubric and pick a new single channel.]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
