<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="error-handling-in-vui Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for error-handling-in-vui. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply a three-tier escalation for any failed recognition: Tier 1 — simple retry prompt; Tier 2 — retry with example phrases; Tier 3 — offer a different modality (visual interface, human agent). Never loop back to Tier 1 after Tier 2 has failed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Repeating the same prompt provides no new information and drives abandonment; each tier must add information or a new path forward to break the failure loop.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For ambiguous input, name the top two interpretations explicitly and ask the user to confirm one — do not guess silently.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Silent resolution of ambiguous input is the most common cause of unexpected VUI behavior; users cannot debug what they cannot see.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For system errors, acknowledge the failure immediately, apologize without blaming the user, and offer a concrete next action (retry, switch to app, call support).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Silent failures or vague "something went wrong" messages leave users without a recovery path and damage trust disproportionately to the severity of the error.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never phrase an error response as the user's fault. Omit "I didn't understand you" in favor of "I didn't catch that" or "I'm having trouble."</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Blame language increases user anxiety, reduces confidence in the system, and causes abandonment — particularly for non-native speakers and users with speech impediments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always provide a visual fallback path — display a list of options, a text input, or a menu — at Tier 3. Voice-only dead-ends must not exist.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Some users will never succeed with voice recognition in certain contexts (strong accent, noise, speech impediment); a visual path is mandatory to maintain access.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
