<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="wbs-creation">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Decompose project scope into deliverable-oriented, hierarchically numbered work packages that are estimable, assignable, and measurable — grounded in the 100% rule and WBS dictionary.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>planning</tag>
      <tag>wbs</tag>
      <tag>scope-management</tag>
      <tag>pmi</tag>
      <tag>decomposition</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Work Breakdown Structure Creation</title>

    <summary>Without a WBS, estimates are guesses and dependencies are invisible until they block progress. Deliverable-oriented decomposition forces the team to answer "what will be produced?" before "how will we produce it?", which surfaces scope gaps and prevents activity-focused planning that omits unassigned outputs. The WBS dictionary transforms numbered IDs into testable acceptance criteria.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without a WBS, estimates are guesses and dependencies are invisible until they block progress. Deliverable-oriented decomposition forces the team to answer "what will be produced?" before "how will we produce it?", which surfaces scope gaps and prevents activity-focused planning that omits unassigned outputs. The WBS dictionary transforms numbered IDs into testable acceptance criteria.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>New projects where scope is fixed enough to decompose into deliverables (more than four weeks of work).</item>
        <item>Fixed-bid proposals where each work package needs an hours/cost line for the estimate.</item>
        <item>Programs requiring a contractual scope baseline with WBS IDs for traceability.</item>
        <item>Migration or cutover projects where a missing deliverable is expensive.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure-Scrum backlog work where the product backlog serves the same role.</item>
        <item>Exploratory R&amp;D — the deliverables are unknown before the work begins.</item>
        <item>Single-week tasks — a checklist is faster.</item>
        <item>Continuous operations or service catalog work — use the service catalog instead.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="deliverable-orientation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every WBS node name must be a noun (deliverable or sub-deliverable), never a verb or activity; verbs belong in the schedule, not the WBS.</statement>
        <rationale>Activity-oriented WBSs silently drift into Gantt charts, losing the deliverable focus that enables acceptance criteria, traceability, and cost rollup. A noun-named WBS forces the team to answer "what will exist?" before "what will we do?"</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad" title="Verb-led WBS names">
        <note>Design database schema, Implement user authentication, Test payment integration — these are schedule activities, not deliverables.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Noun-led WBS names">
        <note>Database schema, User authentication module, Payment integration — completion of each produces a testable artifact.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="hierarchical-decomposition">
      <p>WBS levels follow a standard hierarchy:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Level 1 — Project (one node, the project name).</item>
        <item>Level 2 — Major deliverables (product components, project phases, or functional areas).</item>
        <item>Level 3 — Sub-deliverables within each major deliverable.</item>
        <item>Level 4 — Work packages: the lowest level, estimable and assignable.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Limit WBS depth to five levels maximum; branches deeper than five are over-decomposed and belong in the task list or schedule, not the WBS.</statement>
        <rationale>Over-decomposition produces a WBS that functions as a task list, losing its value as a high-level scope map. Level 5 work packages are typically under eight hours and cannot be meaningfully baselined or controlled at the WBS level.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="100-percent-rule">
      <rule>
        <statement>At every level, the sum of child nodes must capture 100% of the parent's scope — no more, no less; verify by asking "if all children are complete, is the parent complete?"</statement>
        <rationale>100% rule violations are the primary cause of forgotten scope; missing items at any level create work that must be absorbed informally, driving schedule and cost overrun without appearing as a scope change.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include a "Project Management" branch (e.g., 1.X) capturing planning, status reporting, stakeholder management, and project closure; projects that omit PM scope underestimate effort by 10-20%.</statement>
        <rationale>PM work is real work; not scoping it creates a structural underestimate that forces the PM to absorb costs from other work packages, distorting EVM indices and schedule performance.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="work-package-criteria">
      <p>A valid work package meets all four criteria:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Estimable — can be assigned a credible hours or days estimate (8-80 hour guideline).</item>
        <item>Assignable — can be delegated to one person or one team with clear accountability.</item>
        <item>Measurable — has a clear "done" criterion against which completion can be verified.</item>
        <item>Mutually exclusive — does not overlap with any sibling work package.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="wbs-dictionary">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write a WBS dictionary entry for every work package before locking the baseline; numbers without definitions confuse estimators and make acceptance criteria disputes inevitable.</statement>
        <rationale>WBS IDs become references in contracts, schedules, RTMs, and risk registers; without a dictionary, WBS-1.2.3 means different things to different readers, breaking traceability at every integration point.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Required dictionary fields per work package: WBS ID, name, description, deliverable (what is produced), acceptance criteria (how completion is verified), owner, predecessor WBS IDs, effort estimate, cost estimate.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="id-stability">
      <rule>
        <statement>Never renumber WBS IDs after baseline lock; mark removed nodes as "deprecated" and their ID as retired; IDs are referenced by contracts, schedules, and registers that cannot be retroactively updated.</statement>
        <rationale>Re-numbering after baseline creates a version mismatch: change requests reference WBS-1.2.3 which no longer exists in the current structure, making the audit trail unresolvable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Lock the WBS at the work-package level for the baseline; detail below work-package level (individual tasks, sub-tasks) belongs in the schedule and can evolve without a scope change request.</statement>
        <rationale>Locking task-level detail in the WBS baseline makes minor scheduling adjustments into scope changes, which adds bureaucratic overhead without improving control.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-wbs-authoring">
      <rule>
        <statement>The WBS-authoring agent must produce noun-led names only; the system prompt must enforce this constraint because LLMs default to activity-oriented (verb-led) decomposition.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs are trained on project management content that mixes WBS and task-list formats; without explicit enforcement, the output looks like a schedule, not a WBS, and the deliverable focus is lost.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>The agent must emit a coverage rationale per parent node ("this node is 100% covered by its children because...") to support the 100% rule verification that human reviewers cannot mechanically verify at scale.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated 100% rule checking is difficult without domain knowledge; the agent's coverage rationale shifts the verification burden to explaining its reasoning, which human reviewers can evaluate faster than checking completeness from scratch.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <note>Recommended subagents: faion-pm-agent (owns WBS authoring; drafts hierarchy from scope statement), faion-sdd-planning agent (connects WBS work packages to SDD task breakdown), faion-business-analyst agent (useful for requirements-to-WBS traceability matrix). LLMs love to write activity-oriented WBSs; system prompt must enforce noun-led naming. Agents over-decompose ("Login button color" as a leaf) — cap depth at 5 in the prompt. 100% rule is hard to verify automatically; require the agent to emit a coverage rationale per parent. Never let the agent renumber the WBS after baseline — IDs are referenced by contracts, schedules, and registers. WBS dictionaries written by LLMs read generic; seed each entry with the parent's acceptance criteria text, not just the name. Human-in-loop checkpoints: (1) initial draft review, (2) 100%-rule validation, (3) baseline lock with sponsor sign-off.</note>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-anti-patterns">
      <p>Activity-oriented WBSs (verbs everywhere) silently drift toward Gantt charts and lose deliverable focus. Inconsistent depth across branches — one branch detailed to level 5, another stays at level 2 — produces inconsistent work-package sizes. 100% rule violations are invisible without explicit verification. WBS Dictionary is the part everyone skips, then estimates become hand-waving. For multi-team programs, naming collisions (two "API" branches) break traceability.</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Inconsistent decomposition depth across branches — one branch detailed to level 5, another stays at level 2.</description>
        <reason>Inconsistent depth produces inconsistent work-package sizes; large packages are unestimable and hide dependencies, small packages add tracking overhead without control benefit. Aim for consistent 40-80 hour work packages across the WBS.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Use nouns at every level; activities belong in the schedule, not the WBS. Always include a "1.0 Project Management" branch — captures planning, status, closure work. Number every node (1.2.3 style) and never reuse numbers when refactoring; mark removed nodes as deprecated. Lock the WBS at the work-package level for the baseline; deeper detail can evolve via the schedule. Cross-reference each work package to (a) requirements, (b) acceptance criteria, (c) responsible owner. For SDD repos, mirror leaf work packages as files in .aidocs/ so the structure is grep-able.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/wbs-outline.md" purpose="WBS outline template in Markdown outline format"/>
      <template path="templates/wbs-dictionary-entry.md" purpose="WBS dictionary entry template for a single work package"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/wbs_lint.py" purpose="Lints a YAML WBS for verb-led names, depth violations, and missing PM branch"/>
    </scripts>

    <commands>
      <command name="python3 scripts/wbs_lint.py wbs.yaml">Lint WBS for naming discipline, depth violations, and structure issues</command>
    </commands>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/">PMI PMBOK Guide 7th ed., Planning Performance Domain</link>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/">PMI Practice Standard for Work Breakdown Structures, 3rd ed.</link>
      <link href="https://www.amazon.com/Effective-Breakdown-Structures-Gerry-Haugan/dp/1567261418">G. Haugan, Effective Work Breakdown Structures (2002)</link>
      <link href="https://www.dtic.mil/whs/directives/corres/pdf/mil-std-881f.pdf">DoD MIL-STD-881F — WBS for defense programs</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
