<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Gcp Networking Vpc Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for the gcp-networking-vpc methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale + concrete remediation hook.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="custom-vpc-regional-subnets" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production VPCs MUST be custom-mode with explicit per-region subnets; auto-mode VPCs are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="VPC mode docs">Auto-mode allocates fixed-range subnets in every region — wastes IP space and conflicts with hybrid topologies.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="sa-based-firewall-rules" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Firewall rules MUST target service accounts (`--target-service-accounts`) rather than network tags wherever both are available.</statement>
      <rationale source="VPC firewall best-practices">Service-account-based rules are identity-bound and survive instance replacement; tag-based rules drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="hierarchical-firewall-policies" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Org- and folder-wide rules MUST be expressed via hierarchical firewall policies, not duplicated per-VPC.</statement>
      <rationale source="Hierarchical firewall docs">Policy duplication across VPCs is unauditable; hierarchical policies are inherited and centrally managed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="flow-logs-and-mirroring" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production VPCs MUST have VPC Flow Logs enabled; security-sensitive subnets SHOULD additionally enable Packet Mirroring to an IDS.</statement>
      <rationale source="VPC Flow Logs + Packet Mirroring docs">Flow logs cover the metadata; Packet Mirroring covers the payload for high-sensitivity workloads.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="subnet-secondary-ranges-for-gke" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Subnets hosting GKE clusters MUST declare secondary ranges for pods + services at creation time; retrofitting is impossible.</statement>
      <rationale source="GKE VPC-native docs">GKE VPC-native (IP-aliasing) requires secondary ranges; adding them later requires cluster recreation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the input fails ALL "Applies If" preconditions or matches ANY "Skip If" disqualifier, do not apply this methodology — route the task to the adjacent sibling instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Even flat checklists need an explicit skip leaf in the decision tree; this rule is the universal terminal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
