<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Freelancer Personal CRM Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every solo-freelancer CRM application must enforce. These are the HARD rules; team-CRM features must not override them.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-three-tables-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use exactly three tables: Leads, Clients, Invoices. Reject any schema with more than three top-level tables for solo use.</statement>
      <rationale source="solo-ops empirical pattern">Solo operators abandon CRMs that ask for &gt; 3 tables within 14 days. Three is the cognitive ceiling for weekly maintenance without rituals decaying.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-five-fields-per-table" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each table has at most five mandatory fields. Leads: name, source, stage, next_action_date, value_estimate. Clients: name, start_date, hourly_or_fixed, retainer_end_date, health. Invoices: client, amount, issued_date, due_date, status.</statement>
      <rationale source="Notion/Airtable abandonment studies">Field count past 5 correlates with first-week neglect &gt; 60%. Optional fields are added later only when a real workflow demands them.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-deterministic-state-machine" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lead stages are a closed enum: new → qualified → proposal_sent → negotiating → won OR lost. Transitions require an explicit dated note. No "kinda qualified" or freeform stages.</statement>
      <rationale source="pipeline-leak audits">Freeform stages let 30-40% of leads die in undefined states. Closed enum forces a decision per touch.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-follow-up-cadence-3-7-14-30" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default cadence after each cold outreach: 3 days, 7 days, 14 days, 30 days. After day 30 with no reply: mark lost. Operator may extend only after dated proof of "asked me to wait."</statement>
      <rationale source="B2B inbound benchmarks">Reply probability past day 30 without a wait-signal drops below 4%. Continuing past that wastes capacity and pollutes the pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-payment-alarm-day-30" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any invoice unpaid 30 days past due_date triggers a hard alarm in the weekly review. At 45 days, the operator must either send a final-notice email or pause work on that client. No silent aging beyond 45 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="freelancer collections data">Probability of collecting an invoice drops from ~95% at day 30 to &lt; 50% at day 90. Day 30 is the cheapest intervention point.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Minimal Leads row">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
name:               Acme Corp / Jane Doe
source:             LinkedIn DM 2026-05-10
stage:              proposal_sent
next_action_date:   2026-05-22
value_estimate:     $4,800 (6 weeks × $200/hr × 4 hrs/day)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2 and r3: 5 fields, closed-enum stage, dated next action.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Bloated schema that gets abandoned">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Fields: name, company, role, email, phone, linkedin, twitter, website,
        budget_min, budget_max, ICP_score, lead_score, BANT_authority,
        BANT_need, BANT_timing, custom_field_1, custom_field_2, ...

Result: 18 fields. Operator stops updating after 9 days. CRM rot.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2 violation. Solo CRMs that look like Salesforce die from maintenance debt.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="good" title="Invoice aging alarm">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
issued_date: 2026-04-01
due_date:    2026-04-15
today:       2026-05-20
days_overdue: 35  → ALARM (rule r5, past day 30)
action:      send final-notice email by Friday OR pause work
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r5: day-30 alarm forces decision before collection probability collapses.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
