<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-pricing-intelligence" title="Pricing Intelligence">
  <summary>Triangulating list price against realized ACV, packaging diff detection, and AB-test interference rules.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Triangulate competitor pricing three ways: posted list price, G2 reviewer-disclosed spend, and ex-customer or buyer interview. Publish the median and the spread — not a single number.</statement>
    <rationale>B2B SaaS discounting averages 15-35% off list price. Published list price is aspirational; realized ACV from buyer disclosures is the actual competitive benchmark. Single-source pricing intel is misleading.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Pricing Data Sources (ranked by reliability)">
    <list>
      <item>1st — Ex-customer or buyer interview: actual invoiced amount, contract length, included seats/usage</item>
      <item>2nd — Vendr/Tropic realized-price indexes: negotiated benchmarks from procurement platforms</item>
      <item>3rd — G2 reviewer-disclosed spend: reviewer-reported price band with contract renewal status</item>
      <item>4th — Pricing page scrape: list price, requires 3+ independent fetches over 14 days to confirm</item>
      <item>5th — Press releases or analyst reports: directional only; cite as "secondary"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="All-In Take Rate (Marketplaces)">
    <rule>
      <statement>For marketplaces, always compute all-in take rate: commission + payment processing + seller subscription + ad platform fees. Never report headline commission alone.</statement>
      <rationale>Headline commission (e.g., Etsy 6.5%) understates the real take by 2x or more when seller subscriptions, payment fees, and ad revenue are included. All-in rate is what sellers actually experience.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="AB-Test Detection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require at least 3 independent fetches of a competitor pricing page over 14 days before declaring a pricing change. Single-fetch divergence is likely AB testing, not a price change.</statement>
      <rationale>Competitors run pricing AB tests continuously; a daily fetch sees noise. Premature "competitor dropped prices" signals based on one fetch trigger incorrect strategic responses.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Packaging Schema">
    <p>Normalize all competitor pricing to a canonical schema: tier name, included seats or usage quota, overage rate, add-on price, contract length options, billing period (monthly/annual), currency, and source URL with retrieval date. Without normalization, cross-competitor comparisons mix incompatible denominators.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin currency, billing period, unit (per-seat / per-org / per-usage), and contract length in the pricing schema. "$10/month" without these fields cannot be compared across competitors.</statement>
      <rationale>Currency and term ambiguity is the number-one cause of pricing benchmark errors. A per-seat monthly price cannot be added to a per-org annual price without normalization.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
