<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="competitive-intelligence Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for competitive-intelligence as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Mixing "no_decision" outcomes with competitive losses in win-rate calculations</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Inflates the denominator of competitive loss rate; stalled-pipeline rate requires different treatment and different corrective action than competitive displacement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using only rep notes without any buyer-side quote for loss coding</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Rep notes systematically over-attribute losses to "price" and "competition" to avoid admitting process or product failures that reflect on rep performance.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Reporting a single median price instead of a range (P25/P50/P75)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Single medians create false precision. The spread between P25 and P75 is often the strategic signal — it shows whether the market has standardized pricing or wide negotiation room.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Anchoring on the loudest competitor in review-site analysis</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Market-share leaders dominate review-site volume; emerging threats are invisible until they take a deal. Stratify by segment and deal-size, not raw mention count.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Citing the Crayon "16% to 45% win rate" case study without attribution control</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>That uplift conflates CI rollout with new pricing, new battlecards, and new sales hires. Attributing it solely to CI misleads leadership about expected ROI.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent invents a loss reason from rep notes without a buyer-side quote</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force the output schema to require at least 1 verbatim quote with a speaker field; reject rows where evidence_quotes is empty.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent reports "no Enterprise tier exists" when competitor hides it behind "Contact Sales"</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mitigate with G2-disclosed price ranges and LinkedIn job posts mentioning ACV bands. Absence of a public pricing page does not mean absence of an Enterprise tier.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent defends sales rep narrative ("buyer was confused about the pricing")</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use adversarial prompt framing: "Argue the buyer was right to choose the competitor; cite evidence." This surfaces the buyer-side perspective the rep omits.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent paraphrases buyer quotes, losing attribution</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Preserve speaker_role, company_size, and segment end-to-end, never the buyer's name. Paraphrased quotes are useless to leadership — they cannot be cited or challenged.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent adds new loss-reason categories each run, breaking trend lines</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin the loss-reason enum in the output schema; flag deals that do not fit for human triage rather than silently expanding the taxonomy.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
