<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-positioning-signals" title="Market Positioning Signals">
  <summary>Extracting and clustering positioning signals from buyer language, competitor copy, and analyst mentions by job-to-be-done.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Positioning extracted from buyer reviews outweighs positioning declared by competitor marketing copy. Hero copy reflects aspiration; G2 reviews reflect what buyers actually experience. The gap is your wedge.</statement>
    <rationale>Competitors write hero copy for the positioning they want; buyers describe the product they got. The gap between declared positioning and buyer-described positioning is where an entrant can credibly differentiate.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Signal Sources (ranked by buyer-centricity)">
    <list>
      <item>1st — Buyer win/loss interview quotes (highest buyer-centricity, smallest sample)</item>
      <item>2nd — G2/TrustRadius review headlines and "what problems does this product solve" sections</item>
      <item>3rd — Reddit and community forum discussions where buyers compare tools</item>
      <item>4th — Analyst quadrant/wave positioning language (Gartner, Forrester) — directional, lagging</item>
      <item>5th — Competitor homepage hero copy, "compare to" pages — aspirational, least reliable</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="JTBD Clustering">
    <p>Extract verbatim quotes from buyers and competitors before running any LLM summarization. Cluster by job-to-be-done using seed labels established at the beginning of the quarter. Do not let the model auto-assign cluster names — it collapses distinct categories (e.g., "agent platform" + "automation platform" + "iPaaS" into one cluster) and loses the wedge.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use k-means with manual seed labels per quarter; reject auto-clustering output. Re-run with the same seed labels each quarter to maintain trend comparability.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-clustering by LLMs merges adjacent categories that are actually distinct buyer segments with different purchase criteria. Manual seed labels preserve the signal that category definitions are shifting.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Re-Baseline Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-baseline positioning analysis every quarter. Publish dated artifacts (competitive-analysis-YYYY-MM-DD.md). A stale market map is worse than no map — it guides decisions toward the wrong target.</statement>
      <rationale>Pricing, packaging, and positioning shift continuously. Sales enablement teams trust dated artifacts because they know what version they are working from.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
