<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-funnel-stages" title="Recruitment Funnel Stages and Benchmarks">
  <summary>Six-stage hiring funnel with benchmark conversion rates and optimization levers per stage.</summary>

  <section title="Funnel Stages">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track conversion rate at every funnel stage; a stage without a metric cannot be optimized.</statement>
      <rationale>Funnel leakage is invisible without conversion data. ATS and career-page analytics provide the raw counts; the ratio reveals the bottleneck.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Stage 1: Awareness">
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure career page views and apply-click rate as the Awareness-to-Application indicator.</statement>
        <rationale>No benchmark exists for awareness volume alone; what matters is whether visitors convert to applicants.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Optimization levers: career page SEO, employer brand content, job board and aggregator distribution, employee referral program, social media presence.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Stage 2: Application">
      <rule>
        <statement>Application conversion benchmark is 8-12%; below 8% signals JD friction or application UX problems.</statement>
        <rationale>A long application form, missing mobile support, or unclear JD causes candidates to abandon before submitting.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Optimization levers: simplify application to under 5 minutes, remove non-essential fields, ensure mobile-friendly form, send auto-response on submit.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Stage 3: Screening">
      <rule>
        <statement>Screen-to-interview conversion benchmark is 20-30%; outside this range signals sourcing quality or criteria clarity problems.</statement>
        <rationale>Below 20% means sourcing is generating noise; above 30% may mean screening criteria are too loose.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Optimization levers: define clear screening criteria before posting, automate initial resume pass, schedule phone screen within 1 week, send timely rejections.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Stage 4: Interview">
      <rule>
        <statement>Interview-to-offer conversion benchmark is 15-25%; deviation indicates process efficiency or evaluation consistency issues.</statement>
        <rationale>Too low means the interview process is filtering beyond the intended bar or taking too long. Too high may indicate insufficient rigor.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Optimization levers: structured interview process, calibrated interviewers, scheduling within 1 week, positive candidate experience, timely feedback.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Stage 5: Offer">
      <rule>
        <statement>Offer acceptance benchmark is 85-95%; below 85% requires root-cause analysis of declined reasons before adjusting compensation.</statement>
        <rationale>Declines split across compensation, competing offers, and role/location mismatches. Each has a different fix; conflating them wastes budget.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Optimization levers: issue offer within 48 hours of decision, make a personal hiring-manager call, prepare for negotiation with defined limits, preempt competing offers with verbal commitments.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Stage 6: Onboarding">
      <rule>
        <statement>Track 90-day retention as the funnel's terminal metric; target 90%+.</statement>
        <rationale>A hire who leaves in 90 days represents the full recruiting cost with zero return. Onboarding quality is a recruiting metric, not only an HR metric.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Report time-to-fill, cost-per-hire, and quality-of-hire alongside conversion rates; volume metrics alone mask quality degradation.</statement>
      <rationale>Optimizing application volume without tracking quality-of-hire floods the funnel with mismatched candidates and inflates downstream costs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Metric targets: time-to-fill under 45 days; cost-per-hire under $4,000; offer acceptance above 85%; quality-of-hire (meeting expectations at 1 year) above 80%.</p>
  </section>
</text>
