<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-diagnosis" title="Funnel Drop-Off Diagnosis and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Structured approach for identifying and fixing the root cause of candidate drop-off at any funnel stage.</summary>

  <section title="Diagnosis Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Diagnose each stage with one question: is the metric above or below benchmark? If below, list the top 3 possible causes before acting.</statement>
      <rationale>Acting on the first plausible cause (usually compensation) without data repeats the diagnosis cycle after the fix fails.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Diagnosis Questions per Stage">
      <p>Awareness: Are we attracting enough candidates? — check career page analytics; if low, improve employer brand or distribution.</p>
      <p>Application: Are they applying? — check apply-click rate; if low, simplify application form and clarify JD.</p>
      <p>Screening: Are we screening efficiently? — check time-to-screen and screen-to-interview; if slow, add automation or tighten criteria.</p>
      <p>Interview: Are interviews predictive? — check interview-to-offer rate and post-hire performance; if low, add structured process.</p>
      <p>Offer: Are offers accepted? — check acceptance rate and decline reasons; segment by compensation vs. competing offer vs. role fit.</p>
      <p>Onboarding: Are hires staying? — track 90-day retention; if low, audit onboarding quality and day-30/60 check-ins.</p>
    </section>

    <example type="good">
      <note>Offer acceptance dropped from 90% to 70%. Decline analysis: 4 for compensation (40%), 3 competing offers accepted faster (30%), 2 changed mind on role (20%), 1 location (10%). Fix: market benchmarking for compensation, verbal offer before written for speed, improved JD clarity for role expectations. Three months later: acceptance back to 88%.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Optimizing conversion at one stage without checking impact on downstream quality.</description>
      <reason>Broadening screening criteria raises screen-to-interview rate but may lower interview-to-offer rate and quality-of-hire; the funnel looks better while the outcome worsens.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Using industry-wide benchmarks for specialized or executive roles.</description>
      <reason>A senior ML engineer role has structurally different conversion rates than a sales SDR role; applying the same benchmarks produces false alarms and missed signals.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Fixing symptoms (e.g., adding more job boards) without diagnosing the root stage.</description>
      <reason>If drop-off is at offer acceptance, increasing top-of-funnel volume only magnifies the waste; the fix must match the broken stage.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>No candidate-experience survey, relying only on internal funnel data.</description>
      <reason>Candidates who drop off after screening often don't give visible signals; exit surveys surface real reasons (slow response, poor communication) that internal data misses.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
