<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="recruitment-funnel-optimization Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for recruitment-funnel-optimization as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Optimizing conversion at one stage without checking impact on downstream quality.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Broadening screening criteria raises screen-to-interview rate but may lower interview-to-offer rate and quality-of-hire; the funnel looks better while the outcome worsens.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using industry-wide benchmarks for specialized or executive roles.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A senior ML engineer role has structurally different conversion rates than a sales SDR role; applying the same benchmarks produces false alarms and missed signals.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Fixing symptoms (e.g., adding more job boards) without diagnosing the root stage.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If drop-off is at offer acceptance, increasing top-of-funnel volume only magnifies the waste; the fix must match the broken stage.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>No candidate-experience survey, relying only on internal funnel data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Candidates who drop off after screening often don't give visible signals; exit surveys surface real reasons (slow response, poor communication) that internal data misses.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
