<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="marketing" count="276">
  <methodology slug="aarrr-pirate-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/aarrr-pirate-metrics">
    <summary>A five-stage growth measurement framework — Acquisition, Activation, Retention, Revenue, Referral — that provides a complete picture of the user journey.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ab-testing-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/ab-testing-basics">
    <summary>A/B testing (split testing) is a controlled experiment that compares two versions of a change by splitting traffic 50/50, measuring which variant performs better on a pre-registered primary metric, and deciding based on statistical significance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ab-testing-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/ab-testing-setup">
    <summary>A/B testing setup covers the technical and analytical groundwork for a valid experiment: accurate sample-size calculation (statsmodels NormalIndPower, not the simplified 16×p(1-p)/MDE² teaching formula), traffic-split configuration with deterministic-hash bucketing, SRM monitoring from day 1, and a plan-and-results template that an analyst agent fills in deterministically.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="activation-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/activation-framework">
    <summary>A 7-step framework for diagnosing and improving activation rate: define the activation event (behavior correlated with D30+ retention), measure baseline, map the funnel step by step, find the biggest drop-offs, reduce friction, increase motivation, and iterate with A/B tests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="activation-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/activation-metrics">
    <summary>A methodology for defining, measuring, and improving the activation rate — the percentage of signups who reach their first value moment (the "Aha moment").</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="activation-tactics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/activation-tactics">
    <summary>Concrete techniques for increasing the percentage of new signups that reach the Aha moment: progressive onboarding, templates/presets, activation checklists, empty state redesign, time-to-value reduction, activation emails, and in-app guidance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ad-account-hygiene-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ad-account-hygiene-checklist">
    <summary>Concrete operating checklist covering ad account hygiene checklist — the small set of items a practitioner runs every cycle so nothing high-leverage gets skipped.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-ab-testing-ads" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-ab-testing-ads">
    <summary>Scientific method applied to ad creative: pre-register one hypothesis (one variable changed), calculate required sample size before launching, run control vs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-analytics-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-analytics-setup">
    <summary>Three-layer analytics implementation — Collect, Analyze, Attribute — covering GA4 property creation, event tracking plan, conversion designation, UTM naming conventions, and dashboard setup.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-attribution-models" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-attribution-models">
    <summary>Attribution models define how conversion credit is distributed across ad touchpoints in a customer journey.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-budget-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-budget-optimization">
    <summary>Allocate budgets using efficiency ratios and the 70-20-10 rule.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-conversion-tracking" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-conversion-tracking">
    <summary>Multi-platform conversion tracking setup: define macro and micro conversion events with dollar values, install browser-side pixels (Meta Pixel, Google Tag, LinkedIn Insight Tag), implement server-side APIs (Meta CAPI, Google Ads offline upload), verify all events fire correctly, and configure attribution windows.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-google-campaign-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-google-campaign-setup">
    <summary>Structured process for creating Google Ads Search campaigns via the API: conversion tracking first, then campaign with PAUSED status, ad groups by theme, Responsive Search Ads (RSA), and extensions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-google-keywords" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-google-keywords">
    <summary>Targeting the right keywords is critical for profitable campaigns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-google-reporting" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-google-reporting">
    <summary>Google Ads data is abundant but insights are rare.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-linkedin-ads" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-linkedin-ads">
    <summary>B2B advertising on LinkedIn using job title, seniority, company size, and ABM targeting.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-meta-campaign-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-meta-campaign-setup">
    <summary>End-to-end checklist for launching a Facebook/Instagram campaign via Meta Ads Manager: install and verify the Meta Pixel, choose the correct campaign objective, configure the three-tier structure (Campaign → Ad Set → Ad), set targeting and placements, upload at least 3 creative variations per ad set, and avoid editing during the learning phase.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-meta-creative" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-meta-creative">
    <summary>AIDA-driven creative production for Meta Ads: stop the scroll with a strong visual hook (faces, before/after, bold contrast), write benefit-led copy with a tested hook formula (question/claim/curiosity/social-proof/direct), produce both 1:1 and 9:16 format variants, and test creatives systematically by isolating one variable at a time.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-meta-reporting" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-meta-reporting">
    <summary>Structured analyze-decide-act cycle for Meta Ads: set up custom column presets (CPM, CTR, CPC, CVR, CPA, ROAS), run weekly breakdowns by age/placement/device, and diagnose performance issues by mapping symptoms (high CPA, low CTR, high frequency) to root causes (creative fatigue, audience fatigue, landing page failure).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-meta-targeting" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-meta-targeting">
    <summary>Three-tier audience strategy for Meta Ads: Core (interest/demographic/behavior) for cold traffic, Custom (pixel + email + engagement) for warm traffic, and Lookalike (1%, 2-3%, 5-10% of a quality source) for scaling.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-retargeting" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-retargeting">
    <summary>Full-funnel retargeting strategy: segment past visitors by intent (all visitors → blog readers → product viewers → pricing viewers → cart abandoners), tailor ad messaging to each segment's stage, apply frequency caps to prevent fatigue, and always exclude recent converters from acquisition campaigns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ads-twitter-ads" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/ads-twitter-ads">
    <summary>Twitter/X advertising for tech and niche audiences: choose the right objective (Website Traffic or Conversions for most campaigns), target via follower lookalikes and keyword conversations, write native-looking copy in hook/value/CTA format, set realistic CPM/CPC budgets, and refresh creatives every two weeks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="affiliate-program-solo" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/affiliate-program-solo">
    <summary>Solo-scale affiliate / referral program setup using built-in platform tools (Lemon Squeezy, Gumroad, Stripe, Rewardful) with fraud and refund safeguards.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-case-study-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/agency-case-study-template">
    <summary>Five-part case-study skeleton (Context, Problem, Approach, Outcome, Lessons) for freelancers and micro-agencies, with quantified outcomes and one verbatim client quote.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-cashflow-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/agency-cashflow-management">
    <summary>Agency Cashflow Management: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p5-micro-agency-founder/general'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-content-pillars-niche" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/agency-content-pillars-niche">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for agency content pillars niche that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-decline-templates" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/agency-decline-templates">
    <summary>Reusable template for agency decline templates that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-discovery-call-scorecard" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/agency-discovery-call-scorecard">
    <summary>Numeric scoring rubric for agency discovery call scorecard that converts qualitative judgment into a comparable 0-100 (or 1-5 weighted) signal usable across cohorts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-ip-nda-boilerplate" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/agency-ip-nda-boilerplate">
    <summary>Reusable template for agency ip nda boilerplate that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-niche-positioning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/agency-niche-positioning">
    <summary>Forces a micro-agency to pick a vertical narrower than feels safe, refuse out-of-niche work, and repackage past portfolio to look like the target niche.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-pricing-tiers" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/agency-pricing-tiers">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for agency pricing tiers that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-proposal-template-system" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/agency-proposal-template-system">
    <summary>Tiered (good / better / best) anchored-pricing proposal template system for micro-agency founders converting inbound leads to signed retainers in 4-6 weeks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-rebrand-methodology" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/agency-rebrand-methodology">
    <summary>Drives an agency rebrand (founder-name → company, narrowed niche, raised prices) with client comms, portfolio migration, SEO continuity, and contract addenda.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-to-agency-referral" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/agency-to-agency-referral">
    <summary>Cultivates referral relationships with other agencies (capacity overflow, out-of-niche, conflict-of-interest) as the highest-conversion lead source for a micro-agency.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-commerce-future-trends" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/growth-marketer/agentic-commerce-future-trends">
    <summary>AI agents autonomously complete entire purchase flows — comparing options, making recommendations, executing transactions — without human search.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-content-quality-review" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/ai-content-quality-review">
    <summary>A discrete rubric that catches shallow AI-drafted content (entity-thin, citation-free, no original POV, generic intro padding, hallucinated stats) before publish.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-content-strategy" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/content-marketer/ai-content-strategy">
    <summary>A workflow where AI handles research, outlines, and first drafts while humans add first-hand experience, proprietary data, expert quotes, and opinionated takes — producing content that passes Google's E-E-A-T criteria and stands out from generic AI-only output.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-marketing-tools-stack-2026" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/content-marketer/ai-marketing-tools-stack-2026">
    <summary>A curated stack of AI marketing tools organized by function: GEO/AEO optimization (Semrush AI Visibility, Otterly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-overview-content-template" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/growth-marketer/ai-overview-content-template">
    <summary>A concrete content-section template — definition block, comparison table, numbered list, citation row — that retrofits existing posts to be eligible for AI Overview citation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-overview-monitoring" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/growth-marketer/ai-overview-monitoring">
    <summary>A documented monitoring approach for AI Overview presence, Perplexity citation, and ChatGPT-Search visibility — weekly cadence, citation counts per query, and an action ladder when presence drops.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-overview-presence-tracker" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/ai-overview-presence-tracker">
    <summary>A recurring measurement of AI Overview presence per priority query so that AIO optimization tactics become testable rather than aspirational.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-overview-risk-scoring" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/growth-marketer/ai-overview-risk-scoring">
    <summary>A scoring approach that classifies each priority query as skip / target / hedge based on zero-click risk from AIO, so the marketer redirects wasted effort to AIO-citation hunting on queries that pay.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-product-marketing-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/ai-product-marketing-patterns">
    <summary>Marketing patterns specific to AI products: demo variance, prompt-driven value, workflow-not-feature, dangerous comparison pages, amplified trust signals.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-slop-detector-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/ai-slop-detector-checklist">
    <summary>Ai Slop Detector Checklist: codified growth-marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Blog post brief → AI draft → human polish (per-post)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="anchor-diversification-rules" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/anchor-diversification-rules">
    <summary>Anchor Diversification Rules: codified growth-marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Internal-link audit on one cluster (60 min)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="anti-slop-rubric" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/anti-slop-rubric">
    <summary>Anti Slop Rubric: codified growth-marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Content Engine Build from Zero (12 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="audience-to-customer-funnel" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/audience-to-customer-funnel">
    <summary>Audience to Customer Funnel: codified growth-marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Distribution-First Idea Validation (audience before product)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="audience-to-paid-conversion-loop" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/audience-to-paid-conversion-loop">
    <summary>Audience to Paid Conversion Loop: codified growth-marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Audience-to-customer conversion sprint' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="blended-cac-model" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/blended-cac-model">
    <summary>Blended Cac Model: codified growth-marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Paid-Ads Campaign Launch (4 weeks: research → creative → launch → optimize)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="brand-voice-consistency-system" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/brand-voice-consistency-system">
    <summary>Brand Voice Consistency System: codified growth-marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Synthesis: Ship one piece of content into 10 channels with AI-assisted atomization' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="build-in-public-cadence" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/build-in-public-cadence">
    <summary>Daily-to-weekly build-in-public rhythm (capture → hook → ship → log) plus a fan-out schedule across X, IH, and newsletter that prevents 6-8 week burnout cycles.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="build-in-public-content-engine" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/build-in-public-content-engine">
    <summary>End-to-end build-in-public content engine for solo founders — cadence, formats, hook patterns, repurposing chain, and metric loop — packaged as a single playable system.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="build-log-content-template-pack" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/build-log-content-template-pack">
    <summary>Build Log Content Template Pack: codified growth-marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Build-in-Public Weekly Cadence (X + IH + newsletter, single source)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cannibalization-detection-sop" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/cannibalization-detection-sop">
    <summary>Cannibalization Detection Sop: codified growth-marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Annual SEO Audit &amp; Refresh (6 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="churn-save-email-pack-indie" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/churn-save-email-pack-indie">
    <summary>Churn Save Email Pack Indie: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Newsletter → paid product funnel: convert 1K free readers into 200 customers' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-firing-and-graceful-offboarding" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/client-firing-and-graceful-offboarding">
    <summary>Client Firing And Graceful Offboarding: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p3-technical-freelancer/Freelancer-to-SaaS transition without losing the runway' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-firing-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/client-firing-protocol">
    <summary>Criteria, transition plan, contract clean-exit, and post-mortem for firing a toxic agency client — the methodology the corpus has never offered.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cohort-implementation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/cohort-implementation">
    <summary>Cohort implementation moves cohort analysis from ad-hoc analytics-tool reports to warehouse-native dbt models that refresh daily, survive schema changes, and feed BI dashboards.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitor-creative-scrape-ai" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/competitor-creative-scrape-ai">
    <summary>Competitor Creative Scrape Ai: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Synthesis: Weekly CRO experiment cadence on a primary landing page' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="content-atomization-engine" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-atomization-engine">
    <summary>Content Atomization Engine: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Synthesis: Ship one piece of content into 10 channels with AI-assisted atomization' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="content-attribution-model" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/content-attribution-model">
    <summary>Content Attribution Model: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Content Engine Build from Zero (12 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="content-distribution-orchestration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/content-distribution-orchestration">
    <summary>Content Distribution Orchestration: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Synthesis: Ship one piece of content into 10 channels with AI-assisted atomization' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="content-refresh-sop" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/content-refresh-sop">
    <summary>Refresh-or-kill decision flow + execution checklist for evergreen content that has decayed in traffic, rank, or conversion.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="conversion-tracking" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/conversion-tracking">
    <summary>Implementation patterns for tracking conversion events across the full user lifecycle — GA4 goal setup, funnel step instrumentation, A/B test exposure and conversion events, SaaS user-lifecycle events (signup, activation, retention, purchase, referral), content engagement, and video tracking.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="creative-brief-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/creative-brief-template">
    <summary>Creative Brief Template: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Paid-Ads Campaign Launch (4 weeks: research → creative → launch → optimize)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-channel-cpa-rollup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/cross-channel-cpa-rollup">
    <summary>A normalized cost-per-acquisition rollup across paid channels — last-click + view-through caveat, organic baseline, and a per-channel cohort lens — replaces "every channel reports a different CPA" with a single defensible view.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="daily-ads-anomaly-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/daily-ads-anomaly-checklist">
    <summary>Daily Ads Anomaly Checklist: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Daily paid-ads spend + CPA check (15 min)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="daily-marketing-standup-checklist" tier="free" path="skills/faion/knowledge/free/marketing/daily-marketing-standup-checklist">
    <summary>Daily Marketing Standup Checklist: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Daily 15-min content + social pulse check' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="deliverability-incident-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/deliverability-incident-runbook">
    <summary>Deliverability Incident Runbook: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Lifecycle email send + post-send analytics (per send)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dm-personalisation-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/dm-personalisation-template">
    <summary>Dm Personalisation Template delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Cold DM outreach batch (10 prospects)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: growth-cold-outreach is high-level; indie DM batches need a per-prospect 1-line personali</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dormant-lead-reactivation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/dormant-lead-reactivation">
    <summary>Dormant Lead Reactivation delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Quarterly portfolio rebalance (cash, clients, capacity)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Reactivation sequence specifically for service-business dormant pipelines</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="eeat-signal-pass-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/eeat-signal-pass-template">
    <summary>Eeat Signal Pass Template delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Blog post brief → AI draft → human polish (per-post)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: EEAT is talked about everywhere but no operational checklist exists in faion</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="email-lifecycle-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/email-lifecycle-architecture">
    <summary>Acquisition → activation → engagement → retention → resurrection → churn lifecycle map with triggers, frequency caps, suppression rules, consent management — the system layer atomic email programs miss.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="email-preflight-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/email-preflight-checklist">
    <summary>Email Preflight Checklist delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Lifecycle email send + post-send analytics (per send)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: growth-email-marketing covers theory but no concrete pre-send checklist — U</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="experiment-hypothesis-scoring" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/experiment-hypothesis-scoring">
    <summary>Experiment Hypothesis Scoring delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Synthesis: Weekly CRO experiment cadence on a primary landing page' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: `growth-conversion-optimization` exists at solo+pro but tr</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="experiment-ledger-discipline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/experiment-ledger-discipline">
    <summary>Experiment Ledger Discipline delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Synthesis: Weekly CRO experiment cadence on a primary landing page' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: No methodology covers the compounding-knowledge layer of CR</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="experiment-verdict-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/experiment-verdict-template">
    <summary>Single "verdict card" format that closes A/B and campaign experiments on a fixed cadence — kills zombie tests, captures the learning, and routes the decision to a named owner.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="facebook-ads" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/facebook-ads">
    <summary>Meta Marketing API v20+ campaign hierarchy: objectives, CBO, bid strategies, creative upload flow, status lifecycle, and budget in cents not dollars.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-launch-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/feature-launch-checklist">
    <summary>Feature Launch Checklist delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'GTM Plan for New Product Feature (4 weeks)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Solo growth marketers need a single canonical checklist that covers messaging, assets,</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="first-5-paying-customers-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/first-5-paying-customers-checklist">
    <summary>Operating checklist that bridges shipped-MVP to first 5 paid charges — the single biggest survival cliff for solo SaaS.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fixed-vs-hourly-decision-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/fixed-vs-hourly-decision-framework">
    <summary>Fixed Vs Hourly Decision Framework delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Inbound-to-signed-retainer in one client cycle' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: SOW playbook assumes fixed-price. Freelancers daily face 'do I quote this</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="founder-deal-kill-rule" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/founder-deal-kill-rule">
    <summary>Founder Deal Kill Rule delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Monday lead-pipeline review' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Deals stick around forever because founders hate killing them. A rule-based kill checklist would offload</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="founder-led-qualification-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/founder-led-qualification-rubric">
    <summary>Founder Led Qualification Rubric — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. Founders without sales background overqualify; a simple yes/no rubric prevents wasted proposal cycles.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-pilot-pricing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/freelance-pilot-pricing">
    <summary>Freelance Pilot Pricing — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. Generic pricing-strategy doesn't cover the pilot/founder-price tactic that productized services rely on to land first 3-5 customers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-rate-jump-tactics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/freelance-rate-jump-tactics">
    <summary>Defensibly raise rates 30-50% inside a niche pivot via four staged moves: credential proof-building, anchor recalibration against the new niche, case-study sequencing that justifies the jump, and a graduated rollout that splits existing clients from new leads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-referral-program-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/freelance-referral-program-design">
    <summary>Freelance Referral Program Design — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. growth-referral-programs targets B2C product loops. Service-business referral mechanics (incentives, NDA-safe testimonials, partner-swap) need their own playbook.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-saas-billing-decision" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/freelance-saas-billing-decision">
    <summary>Freelance Saas Billing Decision — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. Subscription vs usage vs hybrid decision-tree at the seed stage — current subscription-models is single-axis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-tax-cashflow-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/freelance-tax-cashflow-basics">
    <summary>Freelance Tax Cashflow Basics — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. ops-tax-basics and ops-financial-basics under gtm-strategist are SaaS-CFO-flavored (revenue recognition, runway). Freelancers need: quarterly self-employment-tax setoff, EU reverse-charge VAT for cross-border B2B, sole-trader vs LLC threshold math, separate-account...</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-niche-positioning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/freelancer-niche-positioning">
    <summary>Single-person service-business positioning: a one-line 'I do X for Y so they Z' that survives Upwork search and LinkedIn skim, validated against three external signals (search-find, peer recall, buyer paraphrase) before anything else changes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-positioning-content-calendar" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/freelancer-positioning-content-calendar">
    <summary>Freelancer Positioning Content Calendar — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. 12-month topic rotation matrix mapping niche pillars to weekly posts, sourcing topics from actual work. Avoids 'what do I post' decision fatigue.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="from-hourly-to-fixed-transition" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/from-hourly-to-fixed-transition">
    <summary>A framework for moving an active book of business off hourly billing to fixed-price or productized engagements without revenue collapse.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="funnel-basics-examples" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/funnel-basics-examples">
    <summary>Concrete before/after case studies across SaaS, e-commerce, mobile app, B2B lead gen, and subscription funnels, paired with industry conversion benchmarks by step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="funnel-basics-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/funnel-basics-framework">
    <summary>A 7-phase process for systematically improving conversion at each step of a user journey: map steps, measure rates, find the biggest drop, diagnose the cause, generate testable hypotheses, run A/B tests, and repeat on the next biggest drop.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="funnel-tactics-advanced" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/funnel-tactics-advanced">
    <summary>Industry-specific drop-off benchmarks, personalization by segment, exit-intent recovery, retargeting sequences, ICE-scored test prioritization, and analytics event tracking patterns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="funnel-tactics-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/funnel-tactics-basics">
    <summary>A stage-indexed tactic catalog with quantified lift bands for improving conversion at each funnel stage (Top of Funnel, Middle of Funnel, Bottom of Funnel, and Onboarding), plus four stage-specific checklists (landing page, signup form, checkout, onboarding) for pre-launch audits.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="google-ads-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/google-ads-basics">
    <summary>OAuth 2.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="google-ads-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/google-ads-optimization">
    <summary>Google Ads API patterns for bidding strategy management, conversion action setup, offline conversion upload, and GA4 integration: create portfolio bidding strategies (Target CPA, Target ROAS), apply them to campaigns, set device bid adjustments, define conversion actions with counting and attribution, upload offline conversions via gclid, and query imported GA4 conversion data.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="google-ads-reporting" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/google-ads-reporting">
    <summary>GAQL-based reporting, scheduled automation, and error handling patterns for Google Ads accounts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="google-ai-overviews-optimization" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/seo-manager/google-ai-overviews-optimization">
    <summary>A methodology for structuring content so Google's AI Overviews extract and cite it.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="google-analytics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/google-analytics">
    <summary>GA4 setup, event taxonomy, custom dimensions, Data API reporting, and framework integrations (React/Gatsby, Django, Measurement Protocol).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="google-display-ads" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/google-display-ads">
    <summary>Python patterns for creating DISPLAY_NETWORK campaigns, adding contextual (keyword/placement) and audience targeting to ad groups, building responsive display ads with required asset sets (1-5 headlines, long headline, 1-5 descriptions, 1-15 images), and querying placement-level performance reports.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="google-pmax" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/google-pmax">
    <summary>Performance Max uses Google AI to automatically optimize across all Google inventory (Search, Display, YouTube, Gmail, Discover, Maps).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="google-search-ads" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/google-search-ads">
    <summary>Master Google Search campaign setup via API: network targeting, ad group creation, keyword match types, Quality Score optimization, and Search Terms Report analysis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="google-shopping-ads" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/google-shopping-ads">
    <summary>Master Google Shopping campaigns via API: feed setup, Merchant Center integration, product partition strategies, campaign structure, bidding progression, and authentication across two APIs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-affiliate-marketing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/growth-affiliate-marketing">
    <summary>A structured approach to building partner-driven acquisition channels where third-party publishers earn commissions on sales they refer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-app-store-optimization" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/growth-app-store-optimization">
    <summary>ASO is the discipline of improving app visibility in Apple App Store and Google Play through metadata, visual assets, and review strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-brand-positioning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/growth-brand-positioning">
    <summary>A six-step framework for owning a specific position in a target customer's mind: define the customer ruthlessly precisely, map competitive alternatives, identify a single "only we" differentiator, choose a category strategy, craft an internal positioning statement plus one-liner, and validate through customer interviews.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-cold-outreach" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/growth-cold-outreach">
    <summary>A structured approach for converting strangers into customers via targeted cold email and LinkedIn: build a focused prospect list, personalize using research, keep emails under 5 sentences, and follow up 4–5 times.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-community-building" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/smm-manager/growth-community-building">
    <summary>A step-by-step playbook for building a product or professional community with lasting engagement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-content-marketing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-content-marketing">
    <summary>A systematic framework for generating consistent organic traffic through content: define pillars, research keywords, create content, distribute, measure, iterate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-conversion-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/growth-conversion-optimization">
    <summary>A research-driven cycle for systematically improving conversion rates across web funnels: measure where users drop off, research why, form testable hypotheses, run A/B tests to statistical significance (95%+, 100+ conversions/variant, 2+ weeks), implement winners, and document learnings in a reusable library.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-copywriting-fundamentals" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-copywriting-fundamentals">
    <summary>A learnable persuasion framework for writing copy that converts: know your audience through Voice of Customer research, apply a proven formula (AIDA/PAS/BAB/4Ps), write headlines first (80% of effectiveness), translate features to benefits, handle objections, and drive one clear CTA.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-customer-testimonials" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-customer-testimonials">
    <summary>A systematic process for collecting, strengthening, and placing customer testimonials to reduce purchase friction.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-email-marketing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-email-marketing">
    <summary>A value-first email marketing framework covering list building, welcome sequences, newsletter strategy, segmentation, and sales email sequences.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-experiment-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/growth-experiment-design">
    <summary>An end-to-end pipeline for designing growth experiments — hypothesis → ICE score → control → instrumentation → write-up — distinct from the statistical mechanics of A/B testing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-gtm-strategy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/growth-gtm-strategy">
    <summary>Five-question GTM framework: define one ICP with anti-ICP, craft positioning using For/Who/Is/Unlike/We formula, select 2-3 channels, choose sales motion by ACV, and plan phased launch.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-hacker-news-launch" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/growth-hacker-news-launch">
    <summary>A launch strategy for Hacker News (Show HN) focused on substance over marketing: build account reputation through genuine participation first, write descriptive non-hypey titles, post at 8–10 AM ET on weekdays, and stay engaged with all feedback for 24–48 hours.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-indiehackers-strategy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/growth-indiehackers-strategy">
    <summary>A give-first community strategy for IndieHackers: spend 2–4 weeks helping others before any self-promotion, then build an audience through transparent build-in-public updates (monthly revenue reports, wins, losses).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-influencer-marketing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/growth-influencer-marketing">
    <summary>Four-phase influencer framework: discover micro-influencers (10K–100K) by engagement quality, vet for audience match and fraud signals, personalized outreach, FTC-compliant disclosures, track ROI.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-landing-page-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/conversion-optimizer/growth-landing-page-design">
    <summary>AIDA-structured landing page copy methodology: Attention (hero captures interest in 5 seconds), Interest (benefits not features), Desire (social proof), Action (single CTA per section).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-linkedin-strategy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/smm-manager/growth-linkedin-strategy">
    <summary>A systematic playbook for building B2B authority and generating inbound leads on LinkedIn.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-loops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/growth-loops">
    <summary>A framework for designing self-reinforcing acquisition and engagement systems where the output of one cycle becomes the input for the next.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-newsletter-growth" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-newsletter-growth">
    <summary>A systematic subscriber acquisition framework for newsletters: defining positioning, creating a lead magnet, optimizing signup forms, driving traffic (free + paid), and running a referral program.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-onboarding-emails" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-onboarding-emails">
    <summary>Behavior-triggered email sequences that guide new users from signup to activation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-paid-acquisition" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/growth-paid-acquisition">
    <summary>A test-and-scale framework for profitable paid advertising: calculate LTV:CAC before spending, start with one channel, run 3-5 audience and creative variations with $20-50 per ad before judging, kill ads with CTR below 0.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-podcast-strategy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-podcast-strategy">
    <summary>Two-track podcast strategy: being a guest on others' shows (faster ROI) and hosting your own show (long-term authority asset).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-press-coverage" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/growth-press-coverage">
    <summary>Relationship-driven press outreach: identify journalists by tier (Tier 3 niche first, Tier 1 only after coverage history), research each journalist's beat and recent articles, craft a newsworthy story angle (first/trend/data/milestone/contrarian), send a personalized pitch under 150 words with one specific article reference and three concrete assets offered, then maximize coverage impact through social sharing and relationship maintenance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-product-hunt-launch" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/growth-product-hunt-launch">
    <summary>Four-phase Product Hunt launch system: build 500+ email list (4-8 weeks), secure niche hunter (1000+ followers), launch 12:01 AM PT Tue-Thu, reply within 1 hour.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-reddit-marketing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-reddit-marketing">
    <summary>A long-game community marketing approach for Reddit: lurk for 2–4 weeks, build 100+ karma and account age of 30+ days through genuine participation, then post high-value educational content (guides, case studies, AMAs) with a 10:1 value-to-promo ratio.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-referral-programs" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/growth-referral-programs">
    <summary>Structured programs that turn satisfied customers into acquisition channels via the TRIGGER-ACTION-REWARD model.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-seo-fundamentals" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/seo-manager/growth-seo-fundamentals">
    <summary>The three-pillar SEO framework — Technical (crawlability), On-Page (content and intent match), Off-Page (backlinks and trust) — covering audit checklists, content optimization by search intent, link building strategy overview, keyword research approach, and key metrics for organic growth.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-seo-link-building" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/seo-manager/growth-seo-link-building">
    <summary>A value-first link building methodology: create genuinely link-worthy content, identify who would link and why, conduct personalized outreach, and measure results iteratively.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-social-media-strategy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/smm-manager/growth-social-media-strategy">
    <summary>The PACE framework (Platform → Audience → Content → Engagement) for solopreneurs building an audience on social media.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-tiktok-basics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-tiktok-basics">
    <summary>TikTok account setup and content strategy for B2B/SaaS.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-tiktok-strategies" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-tiktok-strategies">
    <summary>Advanced TikTok tactics for accounts past the setup phase: hook formula mastery, algorithm signal optimization, posting cadence, trend usage, conversion funnel, and growth loops (duets, stitches, series cliffhangers).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-twitter-x-growth" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/smm-manager/growth-twitter-x-growth">
    <summary>A positioning-first Twitter/X growth system: define a unique angle, post 3-5 times daily, write 1-2 threads per week, and reply 20-30 times daily to accounts larger than you.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-viral-loops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/growth-viral-loops">
    <summary>Viral loops are self-reinforcing growth cycles where a user action creates an artifact that is shared or exposed, motivating new users to join and repeat the action.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-webinar-delivery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-webinar-delivery">
    <summary>The execution half of webinars: deliver an engaging live session (polls every 10 minutes, energy higher than normal, camera-at-eye level), convert attendees via a time-limited offer during Q&amp;A, then run a 5-email follow-up sequence over 5 days.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-webinar-planning" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-webinar-planning">
    <summary>A structured framework for planning and promoting webinars to generate leads and demonstrate expertise.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="growth-youtube-strategy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/growth-youtube-strategy">
    <summary>A content-discovery loop for building a YouTube channel around a product or personal brand: niche positioning, searchable video formats, hook-first structure, thumbnail + title optimization, and a sustainable publishing cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gumroad-ops-playbook" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gumroad-ops-playbook">
    <summary>Gumroad Ops Playbook — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. Gumroad is the default distribution channel for indie digital products (templates, ebooks, mini-tools). No methodology covers listing optimization, A/B copy, affiliate setup, EU VAT handling, license key delivery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hook-bank-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/hook-bank-template">
    <summary>Reusable hook-bank schema (hook text, format, platform, result) that compounds over months, cuts daily social-writing time in half, and surfaces what actually works on each platform.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hourly-rate-floor-calculation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/hourly-rate-floor-calculation">
    <summary>Compute the per-hour billable rate a freelancer / contractor must charge to hit a target take-home income at realistic billable utilization (40-60%), not 100%.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="icp-fit-scorecard-solo" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/icp-fit-scorecard-solo">
    <summary>Icp Fit Scorecard Solo — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. Per-customer ICP scoring that drives anti-customer removal + onboarding tone; nothing operationalises this today.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="icp-message-mining-from-ai-conversations" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/icp-message-mining-from-ai-conversations">
    <summary>Mining support chats, sales transcripts, and AI-agent conversation logs for jobs-to-be-done phrases, objections, and success language — VOC for the 2026 stack.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ih-build-update-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/ih-build-update-template">
    <summary>Ih Build Update Template — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. growth-indiehackers-strategy is high-level; no per-post fill-in template optimised for IH algorithm (TL;DR + numbers + ask).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="in-issue-ad-format-library" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/in-issue-ad-format-library">
    <summary>In Issue Ad Format Library — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. Self-promoting inside one's own newsletter is awkward without conventions. A small library of in-issue ad formats (top banner, soft P.S., mid-issue case, dedicated send) with conversion benchmarks is missing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="indie-mini-crm-notion" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/indie-mini-crm-notion">
    <summary>A Notion-shaped mini-CRM for indie hackers tracking newsletter subscribers, affiliate partners, cold-DM outreach, and customer-success touches without a paid CRM.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="instagram-ads" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/instagram-ads">
    <summary>Instagram ads via Meta API: Feed, Stories, Reels, Explore placements with per-placement creative specs, ad set targeting, shopping creatives, and placement breakdowns for budget allocation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="instagram-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/smm-manager/instagram-basics">
    <summary>Instagram strategy prioritizing Reels (80%) for discovery, Stories (15%) for engagement, Feed (5%).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="instagram-growth" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/smm-manager/instagram-growth">
    <summary>A Reels-first growth system for Instagram: post 1-2 Reels daily, run Stories daily, engage 30 minutes per day, and convert via DM triggers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="internal-link-audit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/internal-link-audit">
    <summary>SOP for auditing and rewiring internal links across a content site to support topic clusters, distribute authority, and surface orphan pages.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="internal-link-rotation-schedule" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/internal-link-rotation-schedule">
    <summary>Internal Link Rotation Schedule — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. topical-authority talks about clusters but does not prescribe a rotation. Without one, audits never happen.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="internal-linking-strategy-graph" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/internal-linking-strategy-graph">
    <summary>Internal Linking Strategy Graph — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. Only `growth-seo-link-building` exists, which covers external link acquisition. Internal linking — the single cheapest SEO lever a solopreneur owns — has no dedicated methodology. Needs to cover hub-spoke topology, anchor-text discipline, link-equity flow, orphan...</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="late-invoice-dunning-sequence" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/late-invoice-dunning-sequence">
    <summary>B2B 30/60/90-day invoice dunning: reminder cadence, escalation script, late-fee trigger, work-stoppage trigger, collections/small-claims gate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="launch-day-warroom-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/launch-day-warroom-template">
    <summary>Coordinated war-room template for launch day — channels, roles, escalation paths, hourly checkpoints, and rollback playbook.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="launch-retro-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/launch-retro-template">
    <summary>A marketing-specific launch retrospective template that feeds lessons back into messaging, creative, and channel mix — distinct from engineering retros.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lead-magnet-for-solo-consultancy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/lead-magnet-for-solo-consultancy">
    <summary>Lead Magnet For Solo Consultancy — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. Existing growth-marketer/lead-magnet-style content is SaaS-list-building. Solo consultancy lead magnets are different: niche-specific audit checklist, opinionated benchmark report, code snippet pack, calculator. No methodology covers picking ONE that filters to ...</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="learnings-database-schema" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/learnings-database-schema">
    <summary>Learnings Database Schema — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. Even pro teams lose test learnings. Need a minimal schema (test, hypothesis, result, why, where-applicable) for cumulative compounding.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lemon-squeezy-ops-playbook" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/lemon-squeezy-ops-playbook">
    <summary>Lemon Squeezy Ops Playbook — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. Merchant-of-record alternative to Stripe (handles global tax). The standard pick for non-US nomads. Zero faion coverage; pricing/subscription docs assume Stripe-direct.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lifetime-deal-pricing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/lifetime-deal-pricing">
    <summary>Lifetime Deal Pricing — testable methodology for growth, acquisition, content, GTM. `ops-pricing-strategy` + `ops-subscription-models` cover SaaS recurring pricing. LTDs (AppSumo, Gumroad LTDs) are how indie hackers raise instant cash for nomad runway — completely absent from corpus.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="linkedin-founder-post-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/linkedin-founder-post-template">
    <summary>Linkedin Founder Post Template: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Weekly LinkedIn positioning post' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lookalike-and-retargeting-audience-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/lookalike-and-retargeting-audience-design">
    <summary>Seed-audience selection, exclusion logic, lookalike degree, audience-overlap auditing, frequency-cap discipline — audience design IS the paid-ads moat post-iOS17.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="marketing-tool-stack-rationalization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/marketing-tool-stack-rationalization">
    <summary>Marketing Tool Stack Rationalization: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Content Engine Build from Zero (12 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="marketplace-platform-tradeoffs" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/marketplace-platform-tradeoffs">
    <summary>Upwork / Toptal / Contra / Arc / Braintrust / Malt comparison — fee structure, lead quality, exclusivity, ranking algorithm; pick the right platform for positioning + rate band.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="messaging-house-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/messaging-house-template">
    <summary>A concrete fillable messaging house template tying one-line value → 3 pillars → proof points → per-channel variants.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="meta-audience-targeting" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/ppc-manager/meta-audience-targeting">
    <summary>Meta audience construction: demographics, interests, custom audiences (pixel/CRM/engagement), lookalikes, exclusions, reach estimation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-touch-attribution-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/multi-touch-attribution-modeling">
    <summary>Multi Touch Attribution Modeling: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Synthesis: Ship one piece of content into 10 channels with AI-assisted atomization' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="newsletter-issue-template-indie" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/newsletter-issue-template-indie">
    <summary>Newsletter Issue Template Indie: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Weekly newsletter ideation + draft' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="newsletter-to-paid-funnel-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/newsletter-to-paid-funnel-template">
    <summary>Newsletter To Paid Funnel Template: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Newsletter → paid product funnel: convert 1K free readers into 200 customers' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="niche-positioning-for-solo-dev" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/niche-positioning-for-solo-dev">
    <summary>Niche Positioning For Solo Dev: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p3-technical-freelancer/Productize a recurring engagement into a fixed-scope offer' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="north-star-metric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/north-star-metric">
    <summary>A framework for identifying, validating, and operationalizing a single metric that captures the core value a product delivers to customers — predicts long-term revenue, aligns all teams, and serves as the root of the OKR tree.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="objection-bank" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/objection-bank">
    <summary>A living objection bank discipline that captures every recurring buyer objection from outreach, landing-page bounces, and sales calls into a single, ranked, regularly-updated artifact tied back to landing copy and FAQ.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="objection-faq-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/objection-faq-library">
    <summary>Objection Faq Library: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Proposal customization from base template' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="on-page-seo-checklist-2026" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/on-page-seo-checklist-2026">
    <summary>On Page Seo Checklist 2026: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Weekly content &amp; SEO atomic push' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="onboarding-flows" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/onboarding-flows">
    <summary>A design framework for guiding new users from signup to their first "Aha moment" as fast as possible.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-annual-planning-process" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-annual-planning-process">
    <summary>A structured five-stage planning framework for solopreneurs: Reflect (year-in-review with cited metrics), Envision (12-month vision statement), Strategize (max 3 priorities — hard cap enforced), Plan (annual → quarterly → monthly task tree), Execute (weekly/monthly/quarterly review rhythm).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-annual-planning-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-annual-planning-templates">
    <summary>A set of fill-in-the-blank Markdown templates for the annual planning lifecycle: Annual Plan (vision, goals, strategic priorities, quarterly breakdown, budget, not-doing list), Quarterly Review (results vs goals, wins, misses, learnings, adjustments), Annual Review (executive summary, year-by-numbers, accomplishments, personal reflection), Monthly Plan (focus, metrics, weekly breakdown), OKR template (objective, key results with baseline and target, initiatives), and Year-in-Review.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-automation-workflow" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/growth-marketer/ops-automation-workflow">
    <summary>A methodology for identifying, prioritizing, and building business automations that replace repetitive manual tasks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-churn-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/ops-churn-basics">
    <summary>Churn measurement is the prerequisite for retention intervention.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-churn-prevention" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/ops-churn-prevention">
    <summary>Churn prevention is an operational playbook for reducing involuntary and voluntary cancellations through three phases: early intervention (re-engagement before the user decides to leave), save offers (at the cancellation flow), and win-back campaigns (after churn).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-contractor-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-contractor-basics">
    <summary>A five-step framework for solopreneurs hiring their first contractors: Identify (delegation matrix and ROI calc), Find (sourcing channels and job-post template), Evaluate (screening stages, red/green flags), Onboard (paid test task before commitment), Manage (communication norms and tool setup).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-contractor-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-contractor-management">
    <summary>A four-phase operational framework for managing hired contractors after the contract is signed: onboard with documentation and tool access, establish async communication rhythm (daily/weekly/monthly), assign tasks with explicit scope and examples, and evaluate performance monthly using an SBI-R (Situation-Behavior-Impact-Request) feedback structure.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-customer-success-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-customer-success-basics">
    <summary>A proactive framework for ensuring customers achieve their goals with your product before they churn.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-customer-success-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-customer-success-metrics">
    <summary>Effective CS operations require a health score system that combines usage frequency, feature adoption, support sentiment, engagement level, and payment status.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-customer-support" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-customer-support">
    <summary>A self-serve-first support hierarchy for solopreneurs: build FAQ and knowledge base before adding any async channel, define SLA tiers by plan (Free = 24-48h, Paid = 4-24h, Enterprise = 1-4h), and use weekly ticket pattern reviews to feed product improvements.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-dashboard-setup" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/growth-marketer/ops-dashboard-setup">
    <summary>A framework for centralizing business metrics into a single, actionable view.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-financial-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-financial-basics">
    <summary>Subscription business viability hinges on understanding unit economics: how much each customer is worth over their lifetime (LTV), how much you pay to acquire them (CAC), and whether you recover that cost in reasonable time (payback period).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-financial-planning" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-financial-planning">
    <summary>Forward-looking financial methodology for solopreneurs: project cash flow (3-month and 12-month), calculate runway (cash / monthly burn), allocate profits using the reinvestment framework (reserve 20% first, then split reinvestment vs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-legal-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-legal-basics">
    <summary>Before accepting customers, you need three legal documents: Terms of Service that govern the relationship and limit your liability, a Privacy Policy that discloses how you collect and handle user data (required by GDPR, CCPA), and trademark registration to protect your brand name.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-legal-compliance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-legal-compliance">
    <summary>An index and routing methodology for online-business legal compliance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-legal-compliance-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-legal-compliance-checklist">
    <summary>A stage-gated compliance tracker for online businesses: Day 1 (entity, EIN, bank account, core policies), Month 1 (website legal pages, data protection, payment processing, IP), Year 1 (tax compliance, employment/contractor law, marketing law, industry-specific, insurance), and Ongoing (policy update cycle, data management, audits, legal counsel).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-metrics-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/ops-metrics-basics">
    <summary>A practical metrics management system for solopreneurs and small teams: choose 5-10 actionable metrics, implement collection from existing data sources, set targets and alerts, and establish a review cadence (daily pulse, weekly review, monthly deep-dive).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-partnership-strategy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-partnership-strategy">
    <summary>A five-stage framework for creating mutually beneficial partnerships that extend reach beyond your own audience: identify partnership type (affiliate, co-marketing, integration, reseller, white-label), score candidates on reach/relevance/trust/effort/risk, structure the deal with clear mutual value, outreach with the partner's benefit in the first paragraph, and maintain with a 30-60-90 review cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-pricing-strategy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-pricing-strategy">
    <summary>A value-based framework for setting prices: calculate cost floor, estimate customer value ceiling, research willingness to pay, choose a pricing model, and test.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-subscription-models" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-subscription-models">
    <summary>A framework for designing and operating subscription businesses: choose model type (SaaS, membership, replenishment, curation), structure tiers with strategic feature allocation, instrument MRR/churn/LTV metrics, automate billing recovery (dunning), and manage the full customer lifecycle from trial through win-back.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-tax-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-tax-basics">
    <summary>A US-centric framework for solopreneur tax management: understanding tax types (income, self-employment, state, sales), selecting a tax-efficient business structure, tracking deductible expenses, maximizing tax-advantaged accounts (SEP-IRA, Solo 401k, HSA), and computing quarterly estimated payments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-tax-compliance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-tax-compliance">
    <summary>An operational checklist for US-based solopreneurs to stay penalty-free: compute quarterly estimated payments using the safe-harbor rule (100% of prior-year tax, 110% if AGI exceeds 150K), pay by the IRS quarterly due dates, maintain a structured record-keeping system, execute year-end deduction sweep (retirement contributions, Section 179, expense acceleration), and file on time or extend.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ops-upselling-cross-selling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/ops-upselling-cross-selling">
    <summary>A trigger-based expansion revenue framework: detect usage signals (account at 80% of limit, advanced feature use, team growth), match each trigger to a specific upgrade offer framed around the customer's own data point ("900 of 1,000 subscribers"), present with one-click upgrade and prorated billing, and track Net Revenue Retention monthly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="outcome-based-pricing-calculator" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/outcome-based-pricing-calculator">
    <summary>A structured outcome-based-pricing calculator for solo freelancers and micro-agencies that anchors price to delivered outcome value (revenue lift, cost saved, risk reduced) instead of hours, with a defensible discount-to-confidence ladder.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="outreach-crm-minimal-schema" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/outreach-crm-minimal-schema">
    <summary>Outreach Crm Minimal Schema: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Outreach batch: backlinks + influencers + community (90 min, weekly)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="outreach-personalization-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/outreach-personalization-rubric">
    <summary>Outreach Personalization Rubric: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Outreach batch: backlinks + influencers + community (90 min, weekly)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="paid-ads-creative-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/paid-ads-creative-library">
    <summary>Versioned + tagged creative library that survives campaign rotations and powers AI-assisted creative iteration — the meta-asset PPC manuals miss.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="partner-swap-deal-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/partner-swap-deal-template">
    <summary>Partner Swap Deal Template: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p3-technical-freelancer/Reputation + referral pipeline ramp (90-day flywheel)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="partnership-co-marketing-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/partnership-co-marketing-playbook">
    <summary>Find co-marketing partners with overlapping ICPs, propose a swap, structure a joint asset (webinar/research report/bundle), measure attribution — the highest-leverage zero-CAC channel.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ph-launch-day-runbook" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/ph-launch-day-runbook">
    <summary>Hour-by-hour, time-zoned Product Hunt launch-day runbook covering the comment-back ritual (triage classes, reply templates, signup conversion) — checklist format, not theory.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ph-maker-dm-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/ph-maker-dm-template">
    <summary>Ph Maker Dm Template: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Product Hunt launch campaign: 4-week prep to #1-of-day' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="platform-native-format-matrix" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/platform-native-format-matrix">
    <summary>Platform Native Format Matrix: codified marketing practice that turns the recurring 'role-growth-marketing/Social cadence post: X / LinkedIn / threads (per-post, 20 min)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="plausible-analytics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/growth-marketer/plausible-analytics">
    <summary>Privacy-first, cookie-free web analytics for Gatsby, React, and static sites.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="plg-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/plg-basics">
    <summary>Product-Led Growth (PLG) is a go-to-market strategy where the product is the primary vehicle for acquiring, activating, and retaining customers — no sales team required for self-serve tiers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="plg-implementation-guide" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/plg-implementation-guide">
    <summary>A 5-phase sequential implementation roadmap for operationalizing a PLG model: (1) Foundation — define Aha moment and measure TTV; (2) Free Tier Design — limits, upgrade triggers, self-serve checkout; (3) Activation Optimization — onboarding, templates, TTV under 5 minutes; (4) Monetization — PQL scoring, upgrade prompts, automated playbooks; (5) Expansion — seat/usage triggers, expansion revenue tracking.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="plg-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/plg-metrics">
    <summary>A metrics methodology for Product-Led Growth: the full funnel from acquisition through expansion, including activation rate, time-to-value (TTV), free-to-paid conversion, Product-Qualified Lead (PQL) scoring, net revenue retention (NRR), and cohort analysis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="plg-optimization-tactics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/conversion-optimizer/plg-optimization-tactics">
    <summary>A tactics catalog for improving activation, free-tier-to-paid, and expansion conversion in an existing PLG product.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="positioning-diff-log" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/positioning-diff-log">
    <summary>An ADR-style positioning diff log that captures every change to a product's positioning statement with the trigger, the old wording, the new wording, the expected effect, and the metric to check 30 / 90 days later — so positioning iterations stop disappearing into git history without rationale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="post-launch-conversion-drip" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/post-launch-conversion-drip">
    <summary>T+0 / T+2 / T+7 / T+14 launch-day-spike drip pack — converts the 70% of post-launch traffic that signs up but never returns into paying or qualified users.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pricing-experiment-runbook" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/gtm-strategist/pricing-experiment-runbook">
    <summary>A step-by-step pricing-experiment runbook for Stripe-based solo SaaS that pre-commits the test design (variant, audience, duration, success metric), pins grandfathering rules, handles billing edge cases (proration, refunds, currency, taxes), and forces an explicit go / no-go decision after the test window.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="privacy-compliance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/privacy-compliance">
    <summary>Privacy-compliant analytics means implementing a consent management platform (CMP) with default-deny analytics, GA4 Consent Mode v2 wiring, CCPA Global Privacy Control (GPC) signal handling, and IP anonymization — so tracking only activates after explicit user consent.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="programmatic-seo-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/programmatic-seo-patterns">
    <summary>Template-driven pages backed by structured data: comparison pages, tool listings, location pages — the dominant SaaS growth lever Faion has zero coverage of.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="proposal-from-discovery-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/proposal-from-discovery-template">
    <summary>Proposal From Discovery Template — pinned template for the technical freelancer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so inbound-to-signed-retainer in one client cycle stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rate-increase-notice-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/rate-increase-notice-template">
    <summary>Rate Increase Notice Template — pinned template for the technical freelancer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so quarterly portfolio rebalance (cash, clients, capacity) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rate-raise-conversation-script" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/rate-raise-conversation-script">
    <summary>When to raise (utilization, market signals), how much (10-25%), the conversation script, the bluff-call response — for annual rate raises on retainer/hourly clients.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reference-program-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/reference-program-playbook">
    <summary>Operational playbook for converting existing happy clients into reference assets — named references, case studies, peer calls, and warm introductions — as the primary acquisition channel for micro-agencies.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="referral-ledger" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/referral-ledger">
    <summary>Referral Ledger — pinned ledger for the indie hacker: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so affiliate / referral check + payout stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reply-guy-protocol" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/reply-guy-protocol">
    <summary>Reply Guy Protocol — pinned protocol for the indie hacker: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so build-in-public audience growth: 0 to 5k followers over 6 months stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="repurposing-matrix-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/repurposing-matrix-template">
    <summary>Repurposing Matrix Template — pinned template for the growth marketer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so content engine build from zero (12 weeks) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="retainer-conversion-script" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/retainer-conversion-script">
    <summary>Converts a one-shot project client into a recurring retainer through a 3-touchpoint script during the final 4 weeks of the engagement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="retainer-pricing-methodology" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/retainer-pricing-methodology">
    <summary>Retainer Pricing Methodology — pinned method for the technical freelancer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so inbound-to-signed-retainer in one client cycle stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="retention-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/retention-metrics">
    <summary>Retention metrics quantify how many users return over time.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="retention-strategies" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/retention-strategies">
    <summary>A catalogue of retention loop patterns (content, social, progress, stored-value, workflow, network-effect) paired with engagement mechanics (streaks, achievements, variable rewards, commitment devices) and a re-engagement campaign playbook.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-creep-prevention-on-hourly" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/scope-creep-prevention-on-hourly">
    <summary>Hourly-specific countermeasure: explicit weekly-budget gate, billable-vs-non-billable taxonomy, async approval-before-work rule.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="search-everywhere-optimization" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/content-marketer/search-everywhere-optimization">
    <summary>Multi-platform visibility strategy targeting Google, ChatGPT, Perplexity, YouTube, and TikTok simultaneously.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="search-intent-to-brief" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/search-intent-to-brief">
    <summary>Convert a target query into a structured content brief — intent class, must-cover entities, JTBD framing, SERP-feature inventory — before any drafting starts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="seo" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/seo-manager/seo">
    <summary>Comprehensive SEO and AEO (Answer Engine Optimization) methodology covering technical SEO, on-page optimization, multilingual hreflang, schema markup, llms.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="seo-audit-runbook" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/seo-audit-runbook">
    <summary>Step-by-step annual SEO audit runbook covering crawl, on-page, off-page, content decay, and tech-SEO with the tool inventory (GSC + Screaming Frog + Ahrefs alternatives).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="seo-basics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/seo-manager/seo-basics">
    <summary>Core technical SEO foundations: robots.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="seo-techniques" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/seo-manager/seo-techniques">
    <summary>Advanced SEO tactics covering schema markup (JSON-LD), AI search optimization (llms.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serp-intent-classification-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/serp-intent-classification-rubric">
    <summary>Rubric that forces explicit intent classification (I/C/T/N + sub-types) for every target query before drafting, with falsifiable SERP-anchored evidence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serp-movement-alert-rules" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/serp-movement-alert-rules">
    <summary>Alerting rule set for SEO operators — defines exactly which Search Console + rank-tracker thresholds trigger immediate review (impressions wow drop, position delta, AI Overview appearance, click-through collapse) so fast SERP moves are caught within 48 hours.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="shutdown-customer-email-pack" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/shutdown-customer-email-pack">
    <summary>Shutdown Customer Email Pack — three-email template set (announce, refund/migrate, final thanks) for gracefully sunsetting a paid indie product without scorching the goodwill.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="single-channel-bet-selector" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/single-channel-bet-selector">
    <summary>Single Channel Bet Selector — a decision rubric that picks ONE primary growth channel by intersecting founder strengths, ICP behaviour, and proof-of-traction signal, instead of trying four poorly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="single-operator-funnel-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/single-operator-funnel-rubric">
    <summary>Single Operator Funnel Rubric — a Friday-metrics diagnostic for solo founders that maps visit → signup → paid → retained to one-person evidence sources without an analytics team.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="single-page-case-study-generation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/single-page-case-study-generation">
    <summary>Single Page Case Study Generation — a service-engagement case-study template (problem / approach / outcome / numbers / pull-quote / NDA fallback) for technical freelancers productizing recurring work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="social-proof-harvest" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/social-proof-harvest">
    <summary>Proactive pipeline that scrapes tweets, DMs, and comments mentioning the product, asks for permission, and routes approved quotes onto a testimonial wall — without manual hunting.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-content-calendar-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/solo-content-calendar-template">
    <summary>One-asset-per-week content calendar template anchored to the ICP's pain ladder — enforces cadence + topic relevance, no team, no editorial calendar tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-freelancer-contract-clauses" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/solo-freelancer-contract-clauses">
    <summary>Lean contract clause pack for solo freelancers — IP-on-payment, late-fee with auto-stop-work, kill fee, mutual NDA, freelancer-jurisdiction default — no MSA pre-requirement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-lead-qualification-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/conversion-optimizer/solo-lead-qualification-rubric">
    <summary>ICE-style qualification rubric tuned to solo freelance signals (budget clarity, decision authority on call, sane timeline, no scarring contractor history) that replaces BANT for one-person services.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-niche-disqualifier-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/solo-niche-disqualifier-checklist">
    <summary>Fast-filter signal list (wrong industry, sub-floor rate, vague brief, indecisive founder) that lets a specialised freelancer say no to a lead in under 5 minutes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-niche-narrative-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/gtm-strategist/solo-niche-narrative-framework">
    <summary>Personal-brand positioning sharpener that refines the "I am the &lt;X&gt; for &lt;Y&gt; who needs &lt;Z&gt;" statement quarterly using paying-customer evidence rather than aspirational positioning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-retainer-reactivation-cadence" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/solo-retainer-reactivation-cadence">
    <summary>30/60/90-day post-project check-in scripts engineered to re-open a retainer without feeling salesy — no CS team required.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-x-analytics-review" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/solo-x-analytics-review">
    <summary>Weekly X / Twitter analytics review optimised for an indie audience-growth strategy — five metrics, fixed 20-minute slot, one written experiment per week.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stat-power-precheck" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/growth-marketer/stat-power-precheck">
    <summary>A short pre-test power calculation that tells solopreneurs and small-team marketers whether their primary landing page has enough traffic to detect a stated lift at a stated confidence within a stated window — before they launch an A/B test.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="statistics-application" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/statistics-application">
    <summary>Practical tools for applying significance testing: raw-count templates, power analysis template, three worked examples (significant result, insufficient data, underpowered test), and Python helpers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="statistics-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/statistics-basics">
    <summary>Core statistical concepts for growth marketers running A/B tests: null hypothesis, p-value, significance level (alpha), statistical power, confidence intervals, and Type I/II errors.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="substack-beehiiv-pick" tier="free" path="skills/faion/knowledge/free/marketing/substack-beehiiv-pick">
    <summary>Substack Beehiiv Pick: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p2-indie-hacker/Weekly newsletter ideation + draft'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="substack-to-product-funnel" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/substack-to-product-funnel">
    <summary>Substack-specific monetization: paid tier as product, recommendations, cross-posts — the distinct discipline newsletter-growth doesn't cover.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sunset-customer-comms-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/sunset-customer-comms-template">
    <summary>Sunset Customer Comms Template: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Pivot from failed v1 to v2'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="swipe-file-tweet-hooks" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/swipe-file-tweet-hooks">
    <summary>Swipe File Tweet Hooks: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p2-indie-hacker/Build-in-public audience growth: 0 to 5K followers over 6 months'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="technical-seo-for-ai" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/marketing/seo-manager/technical-seo-for-ai">
    <summary>Technical optimizations that make content accessible and trustworthy to AI crawlers (GPTBot, Claude-Web, PerplexityBot): creating `llms.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="testimonial-capture-microsurvey" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/testimonial-capture-microsurvey">
    <summary>Testimonial Capture Microsurvey: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Bi-weekly case-study / testimonial capture'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="testimonial-harvest-sop" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/conversion-optimizer/testimonial-harvest-sop">
    <summary>End-of-engagement standard operating procedure that yields a written quote, a Loom video, and one outcome metric from every closed service engagement — built on the 3-question script with project-handover triggers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="threads-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/smm-manager/threads-basics">
    <summary>A setup and content strategy methodology for Meta Threads, a text-first social platform that leverages an existing Instagram audience.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="threads-growth" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/smm-manager/threads-growth">
    <summary>A conversation-first growth system for Threads: post 5+ short punchy posts per day, reply thoughtfully to large accounts to drive discovery, and adapt content from Instagram or Twitter to Threads' casual tone.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="topic-cluster-architecture-with-eeat" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/topic-cluster-architecture-with-eeat">
    <summary>Topic Cluster Architecture With Eeat: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-growth-marketing/Synthesis: Build a topical-authority cluster end-to-end with E-E-A-T evidence'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="topical-authority" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/seo-manager/topical-authority">
    <summary>Build topical authority by covering an entire subject comprehensively through topic clusters: one pillar page (broad overview) plus 8-30 supporting subtopic articles, all internally linked, refreshed at least every 6 months.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tweet-thread-launch-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/smm-manager/tweet-thread-launch-template">
    <summary>A 7-tweet launch-thread structure (hook → demo gif → problem → solve → price → CTA → social proof) optimised for the indie-hacker Twitter/X audience and Product Hunt launch day.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="twitter-x-monetization-thread-to-product" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/twitter-x-monetization-thread-to-product">
    <summary>Twitter X Monetization Thread To Product: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p2-indie-hacker/Distribution-First Idea Validation (audience before product)'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="utm-taxonomy-discipline" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/utm-taxonomy-discipline">
    <summary>Utm Taxonomy Discipline: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-growth-marketing/Synthesis: Ship one piece of content into 10 channels with AI-assisted atomization'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="viral-loops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/viral-loops">
    <summary>Five viral loop archetypes — Word of Mouth, Inherent, Incentivized, Content, and Outbreak — each with distinct K-factor ranges, share mechanics, and product fit conditions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="viral-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/viral-metrics">
    <summary>The viral coefficient K = i * c, where i is average invites sent per user and c is the conversion rate of those invites.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="viral-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/growth-marketer/viral-optimization">
    <summary>Viral loop optimization iterates on an existing measured K-factor by decomposing it into its two drivers — i (invites sent per user) and c (invitee conversion rate) — identifying the bottleneck, and running A/B tests on the weakest leg.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="weekly-growth-review-rhythm" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/weekly-growth-review-rhythm">
    <summary>Solo growth review ritual: 5-7 metrics, hypothesis log, decision template — operational backbone connecting channel methodologies to compounding outcomes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="weekly-gsc-diagnostic-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/weekly-gsc-diagnostic-template">
    <summary>Weekly Gsc Diagnostic Template: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-growth-marketing/Weekly Search Console + analytics review (60 min)'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="white-label-partnership-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/white-label-partnership-design">
    <summary>Evaluating, pricing, and contracting white-label work — distinct from partnership-strategy because the buyer is an agency, the brand is hidden, and the legal shape differs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="worker-misclassification-self-audit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/worker-misclassification-self-audit">
    <summary>Worker Misclassification Self Audit: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Build a bench of vetted subcontractors without becoming an agency-of-agencies'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="year-in-review-as-marketing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/marketing/year-in-review-as-marketing">
    <summary>Year In Review As Marketing: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p3-technical-freelancer/Year-end tax, legal, and cash-flow close'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="zero-click-search-adaptation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/marketing/seo-manager/zero-click-search-adaptation">
    <summary>Optimize for citation-based visibility in AI Overviews (cited brands earn +35% clicks) instead of raw traffic — 83% of AIO-served searches end without a click.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
