<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="product-operations">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-operations</domain>
    <summary>A dedicated Product Ops function removes operational drag — process docs, tool plumbing, status updates, metric rollups, stakeholder comms — so PMs spend more time on discovery and strategy.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>product-ops</tag>
      <tag>operations</tag>
      <tag>automation</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>process</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>operations</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Product Operations</title>
    <summary>A dedicated Product Ops function removes operational drag — process docs, tool plumbing, status updates, metric rollups, stakeholder comms — so PMs spend more time on discovery and strategy. 96% of orgs now have this function; 50% report to CPO. Maturity runs from Level 1 (process docs) to Level 3 (AI automation). Agents are a near-perfect fit because Product Ops work is repetitive, system-of-record-driven, and benefits from deterministic automation.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Product teams spend 30–40% of time on operational tasks instead of discovery and strategy. A structured ops function (or an agent-driven equivalent) recaptures that capacity. Without it, every PM re-invents status updates, templates, and metric definitions — creating artifact drift and decision latency. With it, PMs can focus on the work only humans can do.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solopreneur or small team where a human Product Ops hire isn't justified but the weekly operational tax (status updates, roadmap snapshots, metric rollups) still needs to be paid.</item>
        <item>Multi-product / multi-team setup with 3+ PMs working in different tools causing artifact drift.</item>
        <item>Migrating from ad-hoc PM workflows to a documented system.</item>
        <item>Pre-fundraise / board-prep cycles requiring recurring "state of product" packs from 5–10 sources.</item>
        <item>Org-wide release calendars, dependency maps, capacity planning across squads.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>A team with one PM and one product — the operational tax is too small; agent flows add more maintenance overhead than they save.</item>
        <item>During the first 30 days of a new product where workflows haven't stabilized.</item>
        <item>Strategic product decisions (pricing, positioning, kill/scale) — Product Ops enables those decisions, it does not make them.</item>
        <item>Heavily regulated environments where every status update has compliance implications.</item>
        <item>When PM tools have no public API — no API means no agents.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Core Responsibility Areas">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pick one canonical store and write all agents against it. Never let agents query Jira and Linear directly for the same question; sync into Postgres or Notion first.</statement>
        <rationale>Cross-system reconciliation is the dominant source of Product Ops debt. A single read surface eliminates the problem permanently rather than managing it query by query.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Define the consumer before building any automation. Every dashboard, digest, and rollup must have a named human reader. If you cannot name one, kill the automation.</statement>
        <rationale>Product Ops debt is mostly orphan reports — automated outputs that nobody reads. Naming the consumer at creation time is the only reliable prevention.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply a two-week TTL on every automated insight. Agents stamp every status pack with a freshness window; consumers see "stale" rather than stale numbers presented as current.</statement>
        <rationale>Stale data presented as fresh is worse than no data. An explicit TTL forces consumers to request a refresh rather than act on outdated information.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Maturity Model">
      <p>Level 1 (Tactical): process documentation, tool management, naming conventions. Level 2 (Strategic): data infrastructure, insights delivery, ceremony design. Level 3 (Transformational): AI automation, predictive analytics, adaptive capacity planning.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Agents must enforce maturity progression, not bypass it. Refuse Level 3 requests (predictive analytics, AI roadmap analysis) until Level 1 artifacts exist (template registry, ceremony list, KPI dictionary).</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping Level 1 to Level 3 automates undocumented chaos. The automation codifies the wrong shape and produces confident-sounding wrong answers.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Automating an unstable process in the first 30 days of a new product or team.</description>
        <reason>Automating before workflows stabilize locks in the wrong shape. Wait for at least one full delivery cycle before encoding any process as an agent flow.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-Native Ops Patterns">
      <p>Automated status updates, AI-powered roadmap analysis, predictive capacity planning, and automated stakeholder communication are the four Level 3 patterns. All require Level 1 and Level 2 foundations.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Version templates as code. Roadmap, spec, retro, and OKR templates live in the repo (templates/), not Notion pages. Agents read from the repo so a git diff shows process changes.</statement>
        <rationale>Templates in Notion pages drift untracked. Versioning in git gives an audit trail, enables rollback, and makes template changes visible in code review.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use PR-style writes for all agent outputs. No agent writes to Jira/Productboard/Notion directly on a fresh observation. Open a draft, post the diff, wait for human acknowledgment, then commit.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent writes that bypass human review create data quality problems that are invisible until a stakeholder meeting. PR-style review catches them at the cheapest point.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="2026 Adoption Stats">
      <p>96% of organizations now have a Product Ops function. 75% of dedicated teams work centralized. 50% report directly to CPO. Top challenge: role clarity and responsibilities.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Three-Layer Architecture">
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat Product Ops as three layers: (1) scheduled scrapers pulling state from PM/issue/analytics tools into a normalised store; (2) on-demand subagents for specific asks; (3) a narrow set of write-back automations. Agents propose; humans merge.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing layers — agents that both ingest and write in the same flow — removes the human review gate that catches agent errors before they reach systems of record.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>Treat Product Ops as three layers: (1) scheduled scrapers (cron / GitHub Actions) that pull state from PM/issue/analytics tools into a normalised store (Postgres or Notion DB); (2) on-demand subagents invoked by PMs or dashboards for specific asks (status pack, roadmap diff, capacity check, stakeholder summary); (3) a narrow set of write-back automations (Jira ticket creation, OKR doc updates, Slack digests). The orchestrator is a faion-product-ops-agent that reads the stored state and dispatches specialised subagents per request type. Every write must be reviewable in PR-style format before it lands in a system-of-record — agents propose, humans merge.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-product-manager — Domain owner for portfolio/lifecycle/release questions; consumes the normalised state Product Ops produces. Pair it with this methodology when a PM asks "what changed this week?"</item>
        <item>faion-research-agent — Use in mode=competitors or mode=market when Product Ops needs to refresh the competitive snapshot inside a board pack.</item>
        <item>faion-sdd / feature-executor — Downstream consumers: when Product Ops detects a roadmap promise without a spec.md, it can spawn an SDD task to fill the gap.</item>
        <item>brainstorm — Use diverge-converge cycles when designing a new ceremony, template, or KPI definition; Product Ops then ships the converged template into the org.</item>
        <item>improver — Run Product Ops itself through a quarterly self-audit: which automations are still read, which dashboards are stale, which templates were never used.</item>
        <item>General Task subagent with the methodology's content as system context — when no specialised agent exists yet, e.g. one-off "explain this 60-ticket epic to a non-technical exec."</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Prompt Patterns for Agent Workflows">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Weekly portfolio rollup (scheduled):</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Pull from Linear: all teams, last 7 days. From Productboard: feature status
changes. From PostHog: top-20 metrics deltas.
Produce ops-rollup-<YYYY-MM-DD>.md: 1) shipped this week, 2) at-risk (slip
>2 days), 3) blocked >3 days, 4) metric movers >10%.
Source-link every line. Skip empty sections. Output to Notion DB id=<xxx>.]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>On-demand status pack:</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Generate a stakeholder pack for <audience: board | exec | engineering>.
Audience=board → 1-page TL;DR + 3 risks + 3 wins + ask.
Audience=exec → 1-pager + portfolio heatmap.
Audience=engineering → release calendar + dependency graph.
Use only data from /ops-store/ updated within 48h. If older, write
"stale, refresh" and stop.]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Template enforcement on a new feature:</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[A new entry was created in roadmap. Verify it has: outcome statement,
target metric, dependency list, owner, AC. Missing fields → comment on the
entry with a checklist; do not auto-fill.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent metric definitions that re-derive "DAU" from prose instead of reading pinned SQL.</description>
        <reason>LLMs hallucinate metric definitions. Always pin metric SQL in metric_kpi.definition_sql; never let the agent re-derive a definition from narrative context.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Status-update theatre: AI-generated status updates that no one reads.</description>
        <reason>Tie every automated post to a named consumer, or do not generate it. Signal-to-noise collapse kills trust in the entire ops function.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Roadmap merge conflicts when nightly agent sync overwrites a concurrent PM edit.</description>
        <reason>Use updated_at watermarks and conflict logs, not last-write-wins. Cross-system ID collisions (same feature in Productboard, Jira, and Linear) require an explicit mapping table.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Scheduled rollups using AskUserQuestion in a headless cron context.</description>
        <reason>Cron jobs have no human; design every automation as headless-first with Slack-based async confirmations for write actions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Unbounded historical pulls without a since/limit/max_pages guard.</description>
        <reason>"Show me all incidents this quarter" silently fetches tens of thousands of tickets and blows the context window. Always pass explicit bounds.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Privacy / PII leakage when customer names, emails, support transcripts in feedback tools touch agent context.</description>
        <reason>Strip PII at sync time before the agent context ingests product feedback. This is non-negotiable in regulated environments.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Silent webhook drops from Linear/Productboard that the agent never detects.</description>
        <reason>Add a heartbeat ticket per source: "Source X last delivered N seconds ago." Without visibility of webhook failures, dashboards silently decay.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents promoted past their charter, e.g. a status-pack agent deciding to close a feature or rename a KPI.</description>
        <reason>Bound write scopes per agent in code, not just in the prompt. Enforce these bounds at the orchestrator layer.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated metric definitions: agents re-derive "DAU = users who logged in in 24h" but the team's actual definition excludes internal users and bots.</description>
        <reason>Always pin metric SQL in metric_kpi.definition_sql; never let the agent re-derive a definition from prose. Cross-check against the canonical schema.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Roadmap merge conflicts when two PMs edit the same Productboard feature in parallel and the agent's nightly sync overwrites one.</description>
        <reason>Use updated_at watermarks and conflict logs, not last-write-wins. Cross-system ID collisions (same feature in Productboard, Jira, Linear) require an explicit mapping table.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Stakeholder summary tone drift: agents reflexively produce "all-green" digests because they pattern-match on past on-track packs.</description>
        <reason>Inject a hard rule: every status pack must surface at least 1 risk or explicitly state "no risks identified, list of checks performed: ...".</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>OKR cargo-culting: LLMs love producing OKR docs but are bad at saying "this OKR is meaningless, kill it."</description>
        <reason>Pair OKR generation with a critique pass and require human sign-off on the kill list before committing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Limitations and Failure Modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Source-of-truth fragmentation: roadmap in Productboard, sprint in Jira, OKRs in Lattice, retros in Notion.</description>
        <reason>An agent that "centralises metrics" without a canonical schema produces a different set of numbers than the PMs see in their own tools, and trust collapses.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Role-clarity gap: agents accelerate delivery but cannot resolve "who owns what."</description>
        <reason>If the human Product Ops charter is undefined, automating it codifies confusion. Define roles before building agents.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Status-update theatre: AI-generated status updates that no one reads waste tokens and kill signal-to-noise.</description>
        <reason>Tie every automated post to a named consumer, or do not generate it. Status updates without a known reader are pure waste.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Predictive capacity planning is fragile: "AI predicts sprint completion" only works on a stable team with 6+ months of clean ticket history.</description>
        <reason>New squads, churn, scope volatility break the model — and bad predictions are worse than none. Wait for baseline stability before automation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Maturity-model jumps fail: skipping Level 1 (process docs) to Level 3 (AI automation).</description>
        <reason>Automating undocumented chaos means you automate the wrong shape. Agents must enforce maturity progression, not bypass it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>API rate limits at scale: "weekly portfolio rollup" across 20 squads in Jira hits rate limits fast.</description>
        <reason>Without caching + incremental sync the job times out. Use webhooks over polling; implement exponential backoff.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools">
      <list>
        <item>linear (Linear CLI / @linear/sdk) — Pull issues, cycles, projects. npm i -g @linear/sdk</item>
        <item>jira-cli (ankitpokhrel/jira-cli) — Pull/post Jira tickets, JQL queries. https://github.com/ankitpokhrel/jira-cli</item>
        <item>gh — GitHub issues, releases, projects v2. https://cli.github.com</item>
        <item>notion-cli / @notionhq/client — Read/write Notion DBs. https://developers.notion.com</item>
        <item>productboard-api (REST + Python wrappers) — Roadmap and feature state. https://developer.productboard.com</item>
        <item>posthog CLI / SDK — Product analytics extraction. pip install posthog</item>
        <item>dbt — Modelled metrics layer. https://docs.getdbt.com</item>
        <item>slack-cli — Post digests, threaded comments. https://api.slack.com/automation/cli</item>
        <item>gcalcli — Release calendar / ceremony scheduling. pip install gcalcli</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc) — Render dependency graphs / lifecycle diagrams. npm i -g @mermaid-js/mermaid-cli</item>
        <item>sql-fluff + Postgres client — Validate the canonical metrics SQL before publishing. pip install sqlfluff</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Services and Apps">
      <list>
        <item>Linear (SaaS, Yes) — First-choice issue tracker; clean API, fast.</item>
        <item>Jira Cloud (SaaS, Yes) — Premium tier needed for advanced JQL + roadmaps.</item>
        <item>Productboard (SaaS, Yes) — Source-of-truth for feature/roadmap intake.</item>
        <item>Aha! (SaaS, Yes) — Heavy on enterprise PMs; agent integrations are slower.</item>
        <item>Notion (SaaS, Yes) — Best canonical store for narrative artifacts; keep numbers in SQL, prose in Notion.</item>
        <item>PostHog (OSS / SaaS, Yes) — Self-hostable, perfect for an agent's metrics layer.</item>
        <item>Amplitude / Mixpanel (SaaS, Yes) — Usage analytics; Amplitude has a query API.</item>
        <item>Lattice / 15Five (SaaS, Yes) — OKR + check-ins; pull progress for status packs.</item>
        <item>Slack (SaaS, Yes) — Distribution channel for digests, do not store state here.</item>
        <item>Pendo (SaaS, Partially) — Feature adoption; expensive but widely used in Product Ops.</item>
        <item>Productlane / Canny (SaaS, Yes) — Customer feedback intake; feeds Productboard or replaces it.</item>
        <item>n8n (OSS, Yes) — Workspace already runs an n8n instance; ideal glue.</item>
        <item>Airtable (SaaS, Yes) — Lightweight canonical store for small teams.</item>
        <item>Metabase / Lightdash (OSS, Yes) — Dashboards layered over the dbt model.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pick one canonical store and write all agents against it. Do not let agents query Jira and Linear directly for the same question; sync into Postgres/Notion first.</item>
        <item>Define the consumer before the automation. Every dashboard, digest and rollup must have a named human reader. If you cannot name them, kill the automation.</item>
        <item>Codify the maturity model in the agent itself. The orchestrator should refuse "Level 3" requests (predictive analytics, AI roadmap analysis) until "Level 1" artifacts exist (template registry, ceremony list, KPI dictionary).</item>
        <item>Version templates as code. Roadmap, spec, retro, OKR templates live in the repo (templates/), not Notion pages. Agents read from the repo so a git diff shows process changes.</item>
        <item>Two-week TTL on every automated insight. Agents stamp every status pack with a freshness window; consumers see "stale" instead of stale numbers presented as fresh.</item>
        <item>PR-style writes. No agent writes to Jira/Productboard/Notion directly on a fresh observation. Open a draft, post the diff to Slack, wait for human ack, then commit.</item>
        <item>Track agent ROI. Log every Product Ops agent invocation with consumer, read_seconds_estimate, tokens_spent. Quarterly review kills automations no one reads.</item>
        <item>Separate the metrics layer from the narrative layer. Numbers in dbt + Postgres + Metabase. Prose in Notion + Markdown. Agents compose, never originate, the numbers.</item>
        <item>Prefer webhooks over polling. Linear/Jira/Productboard/GitHub all support webhooks; subscribe and react instead of cron-scraping. Fewer rate-limit failures, fresher data.</item>
        <item>Run improver against the Product Ops surface every quarter. It is the methodology's own self-audit prescription, mapped to an agent.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ops-rollup.sh" purpose="Weekly rollup from Linear + PostHog, outputs Markdown to stdout"/>
      <template path="templates/ops-schema.sql" purpose="Canonical ops-store schema: feature, release, risk, metric_kpi tables"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://productoperations.com">Product Operations Institute</link>
      <link href="https://www.productboard.com/research/state-of-product-ops/">Productboard State of Product Ops (annual)</link>
      <link href="https://www.mindtheproduct.com/tag/product-ops/">Mind the Product on Product Ops</link>
      <link href="https://developers.linear.app">Linear API docs</link>
      <link href="https://developer.atlassian.com/cloud/jira/platform/rest/v3">Jira REST v3</link>
      <link href="https://developer.productboard.com">Productboard API</link>
      <link href="https://posthog.com/docs/api">PostHog API</link>
      <link href="https://developers.notion.com">Notion API</link>
      <link href="https://docs.getdbt.com">dbt docs</link>
      <link href="https://slack.dev/bolt-js">Slack Bolt</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
