<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stakeholder Walkthrough Script Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that convert a one-hour design walkthrough from a demo into a recorded decision meeting.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The first sentence the designer says in the meeting MUST be the design problem; the second sentence MUST be the explicit decision-ask. Opening with portfolio context ("let me walk you through what we've been working on...") is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>The first 30 seconds set the meeting's frame. Problem + decision-ask first positions the stakeholders as deciders; portfolio-first positions them as audience. Audience-mode meetings end without decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The walkthrough MUST present 2 or 3 labelled options addressing the decision-ask (e.g., "Option A: dense list", "Option B: card grid", "Option C: hybrid filter"). A single option is not a walkthrough; 4+ options are a discovery session — both are rejected from this script.</statement>
      <rationale>Single option triggers polite agreement, not decision; too many options trigger paralysis. 2-3 is the empirical sweet spot for evoking real comparative reasoning in a one-hour window.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The body of the hour MUST walk through trade-offs option-by-option (not artefact-by-artefact chronologically). Each option gets equal screen time and an explicit "here's where this option costs us" segment, not just its strengths.</statement>
      <rationale>Chronological artefact walks are how designers think; trade-off-per-option walks are how stakeholders decide. Forcing the cost-segment per option prevents the "all options look great, hard to choose" outcome.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The meeting MUST close with a written decision line typed into the design log live in the room: `Decision: option &lt;X&gt; chosen by &lt;named stakeholder&gt; on &lt;date&gt;. Deferred sub-decisions: &lt;list&gt;.` The designer MUST read it aloud and wait for verbal confirmation before the meeting ends.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholders often "agree" verbally and remember differently the next day. Read-back-and-confirm is what turns the agreement into an artefact; without it the meeting is a feeling.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>If no decision can be taken in the meeting, the script EXITS with a re-schedule action: name the blocker (missing data, missing decider, new option needed), book the follow-up, and DO NOT extend the current meeting past the hour. "Let's keep talking" is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>Extending past the hour without a decision trains stakeholders that the script is theatre — they will not bring decision authority next time. Hard exit + named blocker preserves the seriousness of the format.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Designer (00:00): "The problem: users abandon checkout on step 3 at 38%.
By the end of this hour, we need a decision on the new step-3 layout.
I'll show you three options and the trade-offs of each."

[Walks Option A — strengths, costs (10 min).
 Walks Option B — strengths, costs (10 min).
 Walks Option C — strengths, costs (10 min).
 Open trade-off discussion (15 min).]

Designer (00:55): "Decision: Option B chosen by Maria Lopes (VP Ops) on
2026-05-20. Deferred sub-decisions: copy variants on confirmation toast
(scheduled for next walkthrough)."

Maria: "Confirmed."

Designer logs entry to design-log/2026-05-20-checkout-step3.md before
leaving the meeting.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Problem + ask in first 20s. Three labelled options with explicit costs. Written decision read back and confirmed.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Designer: "Hi everyone, let me walk you through what the team has been
working on this sprint. We started with these initial sketches, then
moved to wireframes, then mid-fi, and now we have the hi-fi mocks..."

[55 minutes of chronological artefact walk.]

Designer: "What do you think?"

Maria: "Looks great. Let's keep iterating."

[Meeting ends. No decision logged.]
      ]]></code>
      <note>Demo-mode open, chronological walk, no labelled options, no decision-ask, no closing decision. Hour spent; no artefact produced.</note>
    </example>

  </section>
</text>
