<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stakeholder Walkthrough Script Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Stakeholder Walkthrough Script. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-decision-ask-first-5-min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Walkthrough opens with the decision-ask stated as a single sentence in the first 5 minutes; meetings that drift into demo-mode are halted by the facilitator.</statement>
      <rationale source="Facilitation-discipline practice">Decision-ask first prevents the demo-mode &apos;pretty pictures&apos; trap that produces compliments instead of decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-present-options-not-artefacts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Designer presents 2-3 options at comparable fidelity with explicit trade-offs; presenting a single &apos;finished&apos; artefact is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-quality convention">Single artefact triggers polite agreement; options force trade-off thinking and produce real signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-signed-decision-line" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Walkthrough closes with a signed-decision line stated verbally and captured in design-decision-log; walkthroughs without a signed decision count as failed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-velocity practice">Without a captured decision, the same walkthrough recurs in 2 weeks; the signed line ends the loop.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-park-off-scope-via-template" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Off-scope ideas are PARKED using scope-creep-park-list-template; mid-meeting debate is halted by the facilitator.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cross-method composition">Parking ritual preserves stakeholder trust without expanding scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-recap-at-meeting-close" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Final 10 minutes are reserved for recap: decision + parked items + revisit-gates. Skipping recap is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Closure-quality convention">Recap converts verbal agreement into a captured artefact; without it the decision evaporates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-stakeholder-walkthrough-script.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
