<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-webinar-delivery Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-webinar-delivery. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test audio, video, screenshare, and backup plan 30 minutes before going live. Close all notifications and non-essential apps. Have a co-host who can take over if technical issues occur.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Technical issues in the first 5 minutes lose 20–30% of attendees permanently. Recovery from a bad start is impossible; prevention is the only strategy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trigger engagement touchpoints at: start (poll about audience situation), every 10 minutes (question to audience), midpoint (interactive exercise), end (final poll or survey). Never go more than 10 minutes without audience interaction.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Passive audiences disengage within 7–10 minutes. Each interaction resets attention and generates reciprocity. Polls also provide data that can be referenced throughout the session, making the content feel personalized to the room.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deliver energy 30% higher than feels natural. Look directly at the camera lens, not the screen. Stand if possible. The camera flattens expression — what feels like normal energy looks flat on screen.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Video compression and the screen medium reduce perceived energy by approximately 30%. A presenter who feels "energetic" appears "neutral" on camera. Forced overcorrection reads as natural.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deliver the offer during Q&amp;A, not before. Frame with: audience qualifier, offer description, deadline, objection handling, explicit next step.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Delivering the CTA too early (before value is established) signals the webinar was just a sales pitch. During Q&amp;A, trust and interest are at peak. The explicit next step must be a single click, not a multi-step hunt through the website.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send 5 emails over 5 days: immediate (replay + offer), Day 1 (key takeaways + offer), Day 2 (case study + testimonial), Day 3 (FAQ + deadline reminder), Day 5 (deadline extension if used). Each email must carry the offer with a deadline.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Most conversions happen on Day 1–3 but a meaningful portion (15–25%) come from Day 3–5 when urgency of the deadline becomes real. A single "replay available" email leaves this conversion window unused.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Repurpose every webinar into at least 5 assets before publishing or discarding the recording. A 60-minute webinar contains enough raw material for 10+ distinct content pieces.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A single live webinar production effort (preparation, promotion, delivery) costs significant time. Without repurposing, 90% of the production value is consumed once and discarded. Each repurposed asset reaches a different audience segment or platform.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Transcribe first (Day 0), extract clips (Day 1), create blog post and YouTube upload (Day 2–3), release remaining assets spread over 2–4 weeks.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Spreading repurposed assets over weeks creates a content drip from a single production event. Releasing everything at once dilutes distribution attention and looks like spam to followers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
