<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-delivery-tactics" title="Live Webinar Delivery Tactics">
  <summary>Pre-go-live technical checklist; engagement techniques timed across the session; presentation energy and camera rules; CTA delivery script structure.</summary>

  <section title="Pre-Go-Live Checklist">
    <rule>
      <statement>Test audio, video, screenshare, and backup plan 30 minutes before going live. Close all notifications and non-essential apps. Have a co-host who can take over if technical issues occur.</statement>
      <rationale>Technical issues in the first 5 minutes lose 20–30% of attendees permanently. Recovery from a bad start is impossible; prevention is the only strategy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Engagement Techniques by Timing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Trigger engagement touchpoints at: start (poll about audience situation), every 10 minutes (question to audience), midpoint (interactive exercise), end (final poll or survey). Never go more than 10 minutes without audience interaction.</statement>
      <rationale>Passive audiences disengage within 7–10 minutes. Each interaction resets attention and generates reciprocity. Polls also provide data that can be referenced throughout the session, making the content feel personalized to the room.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Presentation Delivery Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deliver energy 30% higher than feels natural. Look directly at the camera lens, not the screen. Stand if possible. The camera flattens expression — what feels like normal energy looks flat on screen.</statement>
      <rationale>Video compression and the screen medium reduce perceived energy by approximately 30%. A presenter who feels "energetic" appears "neutral" on camera. Forced overcorrection reads as natural.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="CTA Delivery Script">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deliver the offer during Q&amp;A, not before. Frame with: audience qualifier, offer description, deadline, objection handling, explicit next step.</statement>
      <rationale>Delivering the CTA too early (before value is established) signals the webinar was just a sales pitch. During Q&amp;A, trust and interest are at peak. The explicit next step must be a single click, not a multi-step hunt through the website.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>CTA script structure for webinar-only offer.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"For those of you who want to [desired outcome]..."
[Show offer slide: what they get, price, deadline]
"This offer is only available until [specific date and time]."
"If you're on the fence, [handle one main objection]."
"Click the link in the chat to [exact action]."
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
