<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-repurposing" title="Webinar Content Repurposing Workflow">
  <summary>10-asset repurposing workflow from a single 60-minute recording; tools for each step; sequencing to maximize output efficiency.</summary>

  <section title="Repurposing Principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Repurpose every webinar into at least 5 assets before publishing or discarding the recording. A 60-minute webinar contains enough raw material for 10+ distinct content pieces.</statement>
      <rationale>A single live webinar production effort (preparation, promotion, delivery) costs significant time. Without repurposing, 90% of the production value is consumed once and discarded. Each repurposed asset reaches a different audience segment or platform.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="10-Asset Workflow">
    <list>
      <item>Transcribe — use Otter.ai or Descript. This unlocks all text-based repurposing.</item>
      <item>Blog post — edit the transcript of the best 15-minute section into a standalone article. Add images.</item>
      <item>YouTube video — upload full recording with chapter timestamps. Title as a search query (not webinar name).</item>
      <item>Podcast episode — export audio-only version. Add intro/outro. Submit to podcast hosting.</item>
      <item>Social clips — cut 3–5 highlight clips of 60–90 seconds for LinkedIn, Instagram, Twitter.</item>
      <item>Infographic — visual summary of the 5 key takeaways. Use Canva.</item>
      <item>Email series — each key point becomes one email in a nurture sequence.</item>
      <item>Slide deck — share slides on SlideShare with alt text for each slide.</item>
      <item>Quote graphics — extract 3–5 memorable quotes as image posts for social.</item>
      <item>LinkedIn article — expanded version of a specific section, tailored for professional audience.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Sequencing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Transcribe first (Day 0), extract clips (Day 1), create blog post and YouTube upload (Day 2–3), release remaining assets spread over 2–4 weeks.</statement>
      <rationale>Spreading repurposed assets over weeks creates a content drip from a single production event. Releasing everything at once dilutes distribution attention and looks like spam to followers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
