<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Build Or Waitlist Decision Tree Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Build Or Waitlist Decision Tree application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="three-request-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build OR waitlist only if ≥3 distinct customer requests exist (named customer + verbatim quote). Below the floor → decline with anti-roadmap entry.</statement>
      <rationale source="Demand-evidence research">Demand-evidence research — anchors Build Or Waitlist Decision Tree rule `three-request-floor`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="capacity-check-pre-build" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before promising a build, founder MUST verify current sprint capacity has ≥4 free hours for the work. Promise without capacity = broken commitment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Capacity-management discipline">Capacity-management discipline — anchors Build Or Waitlist Decision Tree rule `capacity-check-pre-build`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="roadmap-alignment" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build MUST advance a published roadmap outcome. Off-roadmap builds trigger a roadmap re-review, not silent inclusion.</statement>
      <rationale source="Roadmap-discipline practice">Roadmap-discipline practice — anchors Build Or Waitlist Decision Tree rule `roadmap-alignment`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kill-criterion-before-build" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every build decision MUST carry a kill-criterion (metric + threshold + observation window) BEFORE work starts. Builds without kill-criteria run forever.</statement>
      <rationale source="Falsifiability discipline">Falsifiability discipline — anchors Build Or Waitlist Decision Tree rule `kill-criterion-before-build`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="decision-record-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every ask MUST produce a single decision-record (build / waitlist / decline) with rationale + revisit date. Verbal-only rulings are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-record practice">Decision-record practice — anchors Build Or Waitlist Decision Tree rule `decision-record-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
