<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="backup-recovery">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>server-craft</domain>
    <summary>PostgreSQL + Redis backup strategy with 3-2-1 rule, pg_dump verification, restic encrypted offsite to B2/S3, retention policy, and disaster recovery runbook.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>backup</tag>
      <tag>disaster-recovery</tag>
      <tag>postgresql</tag>
      <tag>restic</tag>
      <tag>3-2-1</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Backup & Recovery Strategy for Solo VPS</title>

    <summary>Backup strategy and disaster recovery for solo developer VPS platforms: PostgreSQL with pg_dump, Redis RDB snapshots, configuration file capture, and encrypted offsite backup via restic to Backblaze B2 or S3-compatible storage. Includes retention policy, restore procedures, and a full disaster recovery runbook.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>A solo VPS hosts databases, secrets, and configuration that cannot be reconstructed from Git. The 3-2-1 rule (3 copies, 2 media, 1 offsite) is the minimum viable insurance. Restic provides encryption, deduplication, and retention pruning in a single tool. Without tested backups, an RTO of "hours" becomes "days or never."</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>After initial server bootstrap — set up backups before any data lands</item>
        <item>Before destructive operations: database migrations, major upgrades, config refactors</item>
        <item>As part of an automated nightly cron pipeline</item>
        <item>Creating a disaster recovery runbook for a new project</item>
        <item>Auditing existing backup coverage before a production launch</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Ephemeral data that can be fully reconstructed from Git or external APIs</item>
        <item>Application code (already in Git — no separate backup needed)</item>
        <item>Docker images (in registry), Python venvs, node_modules (fully rebuildable)</item>
        <item>Large media files where cloud object storage with versioning is the source of truth</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="backup-strategy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Follow the 3-2-1 rule: 3 copies, on 2 different media, with 1 stored offsite.</statement>
        <rationale>Server disk failure and accidental deletion are the most common data loss scenarios; they are both solved by local backups. Datacenter-level events (fire, provider outage) require offsite. Any fewer than 3 copies creates a single point of failure.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="what-to-backup">
        <list>
          <item>PostgreSQL database — critical, daily, pg_dump -Fc</item>
          <item>Redis RDB snapshot — important, daily, docker cp</item>
          <item>.env / secrets — critical, on change via restic</item>
          <item>nginx configs and SSL certificates — important, on change</item>
          <item>systemd unit files — important, on change</item>
          <item>WireGuard config — important, on change</item>
          <item>SSH sshd_config — important, on change</item>
          <item>Crontab — important (crontab -l)</item>
          <item>Application attachments / uploads — daily via restic</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="what-to-skip">
        <list>
          <item>Application code — already in Git, clone from GitHub on restore</item>
          <item>Python .venv directories — rebuilt from requirements.txt</item>
          <item>Docker images — pulled from registry</item>
          <item>RabbitMQ messages — transient by design</item>
          <item>node_modules, build artifacts — regenerated at deploy time</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="retention-policy">
        <list>
          <item>Local backups: keep last 14 days, delete older via find -mtime +14</item>
          <item>Offsite (restic): --keep-daily 7 --keep-weekly 4 --keep-monthly 6</item>
          <item>7 daily snapshots cover recovery from the most common scenario: "yesterday worked, today is broken"</item>
          <item>4 weekly + 6 monthly cover slow-burn issues discovered weeks later</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="rpo-rto">
        <list>
          <item>RPO (max data loss): up to 24 hours of database changes with daily backups</item>
          <item>RTO (recovery duration): 60-90 minutes with a documented runbook on a pre-provisioned server</item>
          <item>Reduce RPO to 1 hour by running pg_dump hourly and keeping only the last 24 hourly dumps locally</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <rule>
        <statement>Set up backups before any production data lands on the server, not after the first incident.</statement>
        <rationale>The cost of setting up backups is fixed and small. The cost of data loss is unbounded. Waiting until after the first incident guarantees at least one incident with no recovery path.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="postgresql-backup">
      <rule>
        <statement>Always use the custom format (-Fc) for pg_dump; it is compressed, supports parallel restore, and enables selective table restore.</statement>
        <rationale>Plain SQL dumps are large, uncompressed, and cannot restore individual tables. Custom format is smaller, faster to restore, and more flexible for targeted recovery.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Verify every dump immediately after creation with pg_restore --list; a corrupt dump discovered during a restore doubles the disaster.</statement>
        <rationale>pg_dump can succeed (exit 0) but produce a truncated file if disk space runs out mid-write. --list reads the dump catalog without restoring data and fails on corruption.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="dump-commands">
        <example type="good" title="PostgreSQL dump commands">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Custom format: compressed, selective restore, preferred choice
docker exec -t nero-postgres pg_dump -U nero -Fc nero_db > nero_db_$(date +%Y%m%d).dump

# Verify dump integrity immediately
pg_restore --list nero_db_$(date +%Y%m%d).dump > /dev/null && echo "OK" || echo "CORRUPT"

# All databases (for full server backup)
docker exec -t nero-postgres pg_dumpall -U nero > all_databases_$(date +%Y%m%d).sql

# Specific tables only
docker exec -t nero-postgres pg_dump -U nero -Fc -t conversations -t messages nero_db > tables.dump
]]></code>
        </example>

        <example type="bad" title="PostgreSQL dump anti-patterns">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Wrong: no verification; corrupt dumps discovered only at restore time
docker exec -t nero-postgres pg_dump -U nero nero_db > backup.sql

# Wrong: plain SQL is large and cannot restore individual tables
pg_dump -h localhost -U nero nero_db > backup.sql
]]></code>
          <note>Always verify. Always use -Fc unless you specifically need human-readable SQL for auditing purposes.</note>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section name="restore-commands">
        <example type="good" title="PostgreSQL restore commands">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Restore custom format (clean = drop+recreate existing objects)
docker exec -i nero-postgres pg_restore -U nero -d nero_db \
    --clean --if-exists < nero_db.dump

# Restore specific table only
docker exec -i nero-postgres pg_restore -U nero -d nero_db \
    -t conversations nero_db.dump

# Restore plain SQL
docker exec -i nero-postgres psql -U nero -d nero_db < backup.sql
]]></code>
        </example>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Restoring into a running production database without --clean and without --if-exists.</description>
          <reason>Without --clean, existing tables accumulate duplicate data. Without --if-exists, restore fails on the first table that does not yet exist, leaving the database in a partial state.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>

      <section name="format-reference">
        <list>
          <item>-Fc (custom): compressed, selective restore, recommended default</item>
          <item>-Fd (directory): splits into files per table, suitable for parallel restore of very large databases</item>
          <item>-Ft (tar): no compression, archive-compatible, supports selective restore</item>
          <item>default (plain SQL): uncompressed, human-readable, no selective restore, largest output</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="restic-offsite">
      <rule>
        <statement>Store the restic repository password in a password manager and in a local ~/.restic-password file (chmod 600), not in the backup itself.</statement>
        <rationale>If the repository password is stored inside the restic repository, it is inaccessible if you need to recover from a total server loss — which is the primary disaster scenario. The password must live somewhere independent of the backup.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Run restic forget with --prune in the same command as the backup job, not as a separate weekly task.</statement>
        <rationale>Running forget without prune marks snapshots for deletion but does not reclaim space. Running prune separately doubles the number of cron jobs to maintain. Combined, retention enforcement is always current.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="repository-setup">
        <example type="good" title="restic repository initialization">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Install restic
sudo apt install restic

# Set environment variables (from .env)
export RESTIC_REPOSITORY="b2:nero-backups:server"
export RESTIC_PASSWORD_FILE="/home/nero/.restic-password"
export B2_ACCOUNT_ID="..."
export B2_ACCOUNT_KEY="..."

# Initialize repository (one-time)
restic init

# Verify repository health
restic check
]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section name="backup-workflow">
        <example type="good" title="restic backup and retention workflow">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Run backup
restic backup \
    /home/nero/backups/database/ \
    /home/nero/backups/redis/ \
    /home/nero/backups/configs/ \
    --tag "daily,$(date +%A)" \
    --exclude-caches \
    --quiet

# Apply retention and prune in one step
restic forget \
    --keep-daily 7 \
    --keep-weekly 4 \
    --keep-monthly 6 \
    --prune \
    --quiet
]]></code>
        </example>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Backing up the entire server filesystem including .venv, node_modules, and Docker image layers.</description>
          <reason>Rebuilding venvs and pulling Docker images is faster than transferring gigabytes of them to B2. Oversized backups exhaust retention budgets faster and increase backup duration.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>

      <section name="restore-commands">
        <example type="good" title="restic restore commands">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# List all snapshots
restic snapshots

# Restore latest snapshot to a directory
restic restore latest --target /tmp/restore

# Restore specific file from latest
restic restore latest --include "/home/nero/backups/database/nero_db.dump" --target /tmp

# Restore a specific snapshot by ID
restic restore abc12345 --target /tmp/restore

# Mount repository as FUSE filesystem (browse files interactively)
restic mount /mnt/restic-backup
]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section name="wrapper-pattern">
        <rule>
          <statement>Create a restic-wrapper.sh that pre-loads all environment variables from .env so restic commands can be called without manually exporting variables.</statement>
          <rationale>restic requires RESTIC_REPOSITORY, RESTIC_PASSWORD_FILE, and cloud credentials on every invocation. Without a wrapper, each ad-hoc restore command requires manually loading 4+ variables.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/backup.sh" purpose="Full daily backup: pg_dump + Redis + configs + restic upload + retention"/>
      <template path="templates/verify-backup.sh" purpose="Verify latest backup: dump integrity, age check, required files present"/>
      <template path="templates/restic-wrapper.sh" purpose="Convenience wrapper pre-loading restic env from .env"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="monitoring-logging"/>
      <ref slug="secrets-management"/>
      <ref slug="cron-automation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
