<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Service Delivery SOP Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Service Delivery SOP Template. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="input-per-step-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every SOP step MUST declare its named inputs (artefact/data) AND where those inputs come from. Implicit inputs forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO 9001 process documentation">Implicit inputs cause first-execution failures: contractor pings founder mid-step, defeating delegation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="decision-branches-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every 'it depends' moment in the source service MUST be formalised as a decision step with explicit branch conditions evaluable without founder input.</statement>
      <rationale source="Lean process literature; decision-table modeling">Implicit branches encode founder expertise; contractor breaks on first edge case.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="quality-gate-per-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every step MUST define at least one quality gate: pass/fail check on the operator's own work before proceeding.</statement>
      <rationale source="Toyota jidoka; CMMI process maturity">Without per-step gates, defects propagate downstream; rework cost compounds.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="escalation-path-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every decision step AND quality gate MUST link to a named escalation owner with channel + bundle. Recurring escalations (≥3 times) trigger SOP update.</statement>
      <rationale source="ITIL incident escalation; Faion ops audit">Unnamed escalation → contractor flies blind OR escalates everything to founder, defeating delegation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="time-budget-per-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each step MUST declare a target time budget. Steps exceeding 2× budget flag SOP for review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Empirical SOP-execution audits">Time budgets surface drift fast; signal of SOP error or hidden complexity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Service Delivery SOP Template fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Service Delivery SOP Template outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
