<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Service Delivery SOP — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for writing a productized-service SOP that a senior contractor can execute without founder QA on every step.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-input-per-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every step in the SOP MUST declare its named inputs (what artifact / data the operator needs in hand before starting) AND where those inputs come from (prior step output, client intake form, external tool). Steps without declared inputs are not executable.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO 9001 process documentation, E-Myth franchise SOP patterns">Implicit inputs are the #1 reason an SOP fails on first contractor execution. The contractor stops mid-step to ping the founder, defeating the purpose. Naming inputs forces the SOP author to discover hidden dependencies.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-decision-branches" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every "it depends" moment in the original service MUST be formalized as a decision step with explicit branch conditions. The condition must be evaluable by the operator without founder input. Forbidden: "use your judgment" without a documented heuristic.</statement>
      <rationale source="Lean process literature, decision-table modeling">"It depends" is implicit founder expertise. Without formalization, the SOP encodes only the simple path and breaks on the first real engagement. Even "if unclear, escalate" is a valid branch — just make it explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-quality-gate-per-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every step MUST define at least one quality gate: a check the operator can run on their own work before proceeding to the next step. Gates are pass/fail with concrete criteria (file exists at path X, value within range Y-Z, screenshot matches checklist).</statement>
      <rationale source="Toyota Production System jidoka principle, CMMI process maturity literature">Without per-step gates, defects propagate downstream and are caught only at engagement-end, when rework is expensive. Per-step gates let the operator self-correct in flight.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-escalation-path" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every decision step AND every quality gate MUST link to a named escalation path: who to ask, by what channel, with what bundle, if the operator cannot resolve on their own. Default to founder, but every escalation that recurs &gt;= 3 times triggers an SOP update.</statement>
      <rationale source="Service ops literature, ITIL incident escalation patterns">Without a named escalation owner, contractors either fly blind (quality drops) or escalate everything to the founder (defeating delegation). The "3-times triggers SOP update" rule prevents the SOP from going stale.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-time-budget-per-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each step MUST declare a target time budget (e.g., "30-45 min"). If a step exceeds 2x budget on a real execution, it is flagged for SOP review. Budgets are guides for the operator, not contractual deadlines.</statement>
      <rationale source="Empirical SOP-execution audits, Pomodoro-style time-boxing literature">Time budgets surface drift fast. If a step balloons, either the SOP is wrong (input incomplete, gate impossible) or the engagement has a hidden complexity. Both warrant attention before the contractor burns more hours.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical example">

    <example type="good" title="A step with input, decision branch, gate, escalation, budget">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Step 04: Configure analytics for client site

Inputs:
  - GA4 property ID (from step 02 output)
  - Client's CMS admin credentials (from intake form, secrets vault)
  - List of conversion events to track (from step 03 output)

Action:
  - Install GA4 via GTM (use template gtm-base-v3.json)
  - Configure each conversion event with name + parameters

Decision:
  - IF client has consent management (CMP): integrate via GTM consent
    template -> branch A.
  - IF no CMP: install with default-deny consent + flag for sales upsell
    -> branch B.

Quality gate:
  - GA4 DebugView shows page_view events from a private test session
  - Each conversion event fires in DebugView when test-triggered
  - GTM preview mode shows no broken tags

Escalation:
  - DebugView shows no events after 10 min -> escalate to founder via
    #delivery channel with screenshot + GTM container ID.

Budget: 60-90 min
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1-r5: inputs sourced, decision branched, gate concrete, escalation named, budget set.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Implicit step that breaks on first delegation">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Step 04: Set up analytics

"Install GA4 on the client site. Configure events. Make sure it works.
Use your judgment on the conversion setup based on the client's needs."

Result on first contractor execution:
  - Contractor pinged founder 4 times in 90 min ("which property?",
    "which events?", "what counts as working?", "consent setup?").
  - SOP failed its first delegation; founder time saved = zero.

Repair: apply r1-r5. Each phrase ("install on the site", "configure
events", "use your judgment") becomes an explicit named input,
decision branch, or quality gate.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1-r2 violations — implicit inputs and unbranched judgment calls.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
