<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="STAR Interview Framework Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the STAR Interview Framework methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale. Hard rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every competency in the rubric has 5 behavior-anchored levels; collapsing to 3 (poor/ok/great) loses the resolution needed for hire-bar arguments.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal STAR calibration audit Q1 2026">Five-level anchors keep inter-rater agreement above the operational target; three-level scales collapse 'near-bar' and 'on-bar' into one bucket and force reviewers to fight over a single threshold.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Calibration session MUST include ≥2 interviewers scoring the same transcripts; a one-person calibration is theatrical.</statement>
      <rationale source="Structured Hiring practice handbook">Single-author rubrics encode the author's biases without surfacing them; running a second scorer through the same evidence is the only way to detect them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Anchors describe observable behaviors, not traits; 'shows ownership' is rejected, 'drove the post-mortem to written action items with named owners' is accepted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Behavioral interviewing literature (Janz et al.)">Trait-language anchors invite re-interpretation per candidate; behavior-language anchors pin the evidence the reviewer must cite.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Inter-rater agreement target ≥0.6 (Cohen's kappa or equivalent) on a pilot cohort before the rubric is published; otherwise rewrite the disagreement-heavy anchors.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — calibration retro Q4 2025">Publishing an uncalibrated rubric exports the disagreement into hiring decisions; the pilot gate is the only place to catch this cheaply.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Debrief contract is published with the rubric: who writes first, how dissent is recorded, decision rule (consensus / hiring-manager / vote).</statement>
      <rationale source="Structured Hiring practice handbook">Without a debrief contract, the loudest voice wins the room; explicit contract neutralizes seniority effects on hire decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
