<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Proposal From Discovery Template — Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules + one skip rule grounding the methodology. Each pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-fixed-shape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The proposal artefact MUST use the canonical section list with three named options (light / standard / outcome-based). Practitioners fill sections; they do not invent new ones per use.</statement>
      <rationale source="Standardisation literature — Gawande, The Checklist Manifesto; information-architecture canon">Variable structure across instances destroys comparability and prevents future audit. Fixed shape makes filled artefacts diff-able and reviewable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-evidence-fields" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every claim or recommendation in the proposal MUST carry an evidence link (call transcript, dashboard URL, ticket, measurement). Unevidenced sections are rejected at validation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Evidence-based delivery practice; Lean Startup validated-learning rules">Templates without evidence anchors decay into opinion-capture. Tagging evidence at fill-time makes the proposal defensible and reusable in retro / audit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-version-and-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Header MUST carry `version` (semver), `last_reviewed` (ISO date), and a named human owner. Templates without ownership age into untrusted folklore.</statement>
      <rationale source="Documentation-as-code practice; Diátaxis maintainability model">Anonymous templates rot because no one is on the hook for refresh. A named owner pins refresh accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-fill-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Fill budget MUST be ≤30 minutes from discovery-call notes to draft. Drafts that exceed it are split into a short variant + an extended variant.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cognitive-load research; field experience with operational templates">If filling the template costs more than the artefact yields, freelancers route around it. A budgeted template enforces leverage and same-cycle turnaround.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-action-block" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every filled instance MUST end with an action block (≥1 next-action: owner + due_date + action) so the proposal becomes an operating tool, not reading material.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-journal practice (Annie Duke, How To Decide); GTD next-action discipline">Without an action block the proposal becomes a deck rather than a commit; the close-rate review at the next iteration loses its anchor.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold (recurrence ≥3/yr, named owner, discovery notes present), execute the full proposal-fill procedure from `04-procedure.xml`.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's affirmative leaf.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any of the Skip-If conditions hold (one-off deal, &lt;3 instances/year, RFP-driven, no owner), do NOT apply this methodology; route to a one-off proposal email or the upstream RFP-fill methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's skip leaf; prevents over-application of the heavyweight artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
