<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-campaign-asset-groups" title="PMax Campaign Creation and Asset Group Setup">
  <summary>Creating a Performance Max campaign via the Google Ads API, setting up asset groups, and meeting minimum asset count requirements before submission.</summary>

  <section title="Campaign Creation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always create PMax campaigns with status PAUSED; require explicit human approval before enabling.</statement>
      <rationale>PMax starts spending immediately upon enable. A paused-first approach gives time to validate asset counts, conversion goals, and URL expansion settings before budget flows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure conversion goals at the account level before creating a PMax campaign; PMax silently optimizes for the wrong action if account-level goals are not set correctly.</statement>
      <rationale>Unlike Search campaigns that can target specific conversion actions, PMax uses account-level conversion goals. Wrong goals produce campaigns that optimize for micro-conversions (e.g., page views) instead of purchases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>advertising_channel_type: PERFORMANCE_MAX</item>
      <item>Bidding: maximize_conversions (no target_cpa_micros) for first 30 conversions</item>
      <item>url_expansion_opt_out: True for lead-gen; False for e-commerce with clean site</item>
      <item>Budget: minimum 3x target CPA daily in micros (dollars * 1,000,000)</item>
      <item>start_date and end_date: set explicitly</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Asset Group Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate minimum asset counts before submitting an asset group: 5 headlines (30 chars), 5 long headlines (90 chars), 4 descriptions (90 chars), 4 marketing images. Campaigns go nowhere without meeting minimums.</statement>
      <rationale>PMax campaigns with fewer than the minimum asset counts per type cannot enter the auction for placements that require those assets. The campaign runs but delivers zero impressions on major inventory.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>HEADLINE: 5 required, max 30 chars each — distinct value props</item>
      <item>LONG_HEADLINE: 5 required, max 90 chars each</item>
      <item>DESCRIPTION: 4 required, max 90 chars each (include CTA)</item>
      <item>MARKETING_IMAGE: 4 required (1200x628 landscape)</item>
      <item>BUSINESS_NAME: 1 required</item>
      <item>final_urls: 1 required (must be HTTPS)</item>
      <item>Videos (YouTube): optional but strongly recommended for YouTube placements</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>final_urls must use HTTPS; HTTP URLs fail with a generic auth error that does not indicate the scheme problem.</statement>
      <rationale>Google requires HTTPS for all ad destination URLs. The error message for HTTP URLs is misleading, making this a time-consuming bug to diagnose.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Asset Upload Flow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Upload image assets first via mutate_assets, then reference their resource names in asset group asset operations; assets and asset groups cannot be created in the same API call.</statement>
      <rationale>Asset resources must exist before they can be linked to an asset group. Agents that attempt to create and link in one step receive resource-not-found errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/asset-audit.py">Pull asset performance labels (BEST/GOOD/LOW/PENDING) grouped by asset type for weekly refresh decisions</reference>
  </section>
</text>
