<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Architecture Decision Records (ADRs) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every architecture-decision-records application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-immutable-history" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Accepted ADRs are immutable. Updates happen via a new ADR that references and supersedes the prior one. Deleting or silently editing an Accepted ADR is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nygard original guidance; ATC governance">Mutable history destroys the audit trail and is the leading cause of ADR programs failing within a year.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-format-lock" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ADR-0001 locks the chosen format (Nygard, MADR, Y-Statement). All subsequent ADRs follow that template. Changing format requires a new ADR superseding ADR-0001.</statement>
      <rationale source="ATC governance; team consistency">Format drift destroys grep-ability and breaks ADR tooling (adr-lint, decay detector).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-alternatives-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every ADR documents ≥2 alternatives with explicit rejection reasons. Single-option ADRs are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="MADR best practice">Single-option ADRs are decision laundering; they provide no audit value because no choice was made.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-status-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Status field is one of Proposed | Accepted | Deprecated | Superseded. Custom values forbidden. Superseded ADRs include a `superseded_by: ADR-NNN` field.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nygard original">Closed status enum lets tooling (adr-lint, decay detector) reason about the portfolio.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-ci-enforced" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A CI lint runs on every PR that touches docs/adr/, blocking merges that violate the format, miss alternatives, or break the status discipline.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational rigour">Without CI enforcement the format drifts in two quarters; CI keeps the gate active without reviewer fatigue.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-23 chunk-00 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
