<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="portfolio-strategy">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>70/20/10 allocation framework: Core (H1), Adjacent (H2), Transformational (H3). Separates single-product PM execution from portfolio-level cross-product trade-offs.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>portfolio</tag>
      <tag>allocation</tag>
      <tag>horizons</tag>
      <tag>investment</tag>
      <tag>pm-role</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>strategy</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Portfolio Strategy (70/20/10)</title>
    <summary>Allocates product investment across three horizons: 70% Core (H1, known market, 0-12 months), 20% Adjacent (H2, new segments, 12-24 months), 10% Transformational (H3, breakthrough bets, 24-36 months). In economic downturns shift to 80/15/5; in growth periods to 60/25/15. The PM-level focus is separating single-product PM execution from portfolio-PM cross-product trade-offs.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Without explicit horizon allocation, PMs optimize locally — all backlog items drift to H1 because launches are rewarded over long bets. At scale, the aggregate portfolio becomes 95% H1 with no transformational work. The 70/20/10 model forces a written allocation memo that makes cross-product trade-offs visible and defensible.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>A single PM owns two or more shipped products and backlogs are starting to collide.</item>
        <item>Promoting an IC PM to Group PM / Portfolio PM: their decision frame must shift from feature-level to cross-product investment.</item>
        <item>Two product squads both have defensible quarterly plans but the org cannot fund both at full speed.</item>
        <item>Defining the handoff line between portfolio strategy (CPO) and product PM execution.</item>
        <item>Quarterly review when product-level OKRs are met but the portfolio is unbalanced (all H1, no H3).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-product PM with one product line — use feature-prioritization (RICE / WSJF / Kano) instead; no portfolio exists at the PM level.</item>
        <item>Pure team-topology or hiring decisions — use Team Topologies, not portfolio strategy.</item>
        <item>Roadmap-internal trade-offs inside one product (feature A vs feature B in the same SKU).</item>
        <item>Resource arguments that are really about sprint capacity or on-call rotation.</item>
        <item>Crisis quarter where one product is on fire — defer portfolio review until the fire is out.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Standard Allocation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Default allocation: 70% H1 (Core, 0-12 months, known market, low risk), 20% H2 (Adjacent, 12-24 months, new segments, medium risk), 10% H3 (Transformational, 24-36 months, breakthrough bets, high risk).</statement>
        <rationale>The 70/20/10 split balances revenue protection with innovation investment. Deviating without an explicit economic-condition trigger creates undefended drift.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Adjust ratios by economic condition: growth economy → 60/25/15 (more bets); stable economy → 70/20/10 (standard); recession → 80/15/5 (protect core).</statement>
        <rationale>Economic weakness in 2026 (Morgan Stanley forecast) warrants a defensive posture. The adjustment must be explicit and signed by the portfolio-PM, not implicit.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pre-PMF products allocate 100% to achieving PMF and do not enter the portfolio model until PMF is demonstrated. Never apply 70/20/10 to a product still searching for product-market fit.</statement>
        <rationale>Portfolio horizon math assumes a product with known metrics and a real customer base. Pre-PMF products have a single objective that H1/H2/H3 labels actively obscure.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="PM Role Taxonomy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Assign every PM a written role tag each quarter: product-PM (owns one product's roadmap), portfolio-PM (owns cross-product investment allocation), or mixed (with an explicit percentage of portfolio time). Resolve ambiguity in a written allocation memo before backlogs collide.</statement>
        <rationale>Role ambiguity is the root cause of most allocation fights. When the same person plays both hats, a written memo makes the conflict of interest visible to others who can catch drift.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Promote from product-PM to portfolio-PM only when the PM already owns two or more shipped products with demonstrable OKR independence. Product count alone is not sufficient — time allocation must be verified.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs and orgs alike conflate "PM owns more products" with "PM is more strategic". The decision frame shift from feature-level to cross-product investment is qualitative and must be verified.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="H3 Budget Governance">
      <rule>
        <statement>Fund the H3 portion from a portfolio budget owned by the portfolio-PM, not from individual product budgets. No single product-PM can raid or reallocate H3 funds.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a ring-fenced H3 budget, H3 becomes overflow for late H1 features during every crunch. The portfolio-PM is the only role without a local-optimization incentive.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Score PMs on portfolio outcomes (cross-product H3 progress) when they own two or more products, not just per-product outcomes. Otherwise, they will silently let H3 die.</statement>
        <rationale>PM career incentives skew toward H1/H2 because launches are rewarded over long bets. Metric alignment is the only scalable fix; admonishment is not.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Three-Pass Agentic Pipeline">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pass 1 (Product-PM pass): for each product, a sonnet agent reads the product backlog, OKRs, and recent retros and emits {product, h1_pct, h2_pct, h3_pct, key_evidence}. Weights are not yet cross-product.</statement>
        <rationale>Starting per-product isolates each PM's plan before aggregation. Cross-product trade-offs introduced too early cause defensiveness that blocks honest disclosure.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pass 2 (Portfolio-PM pass): an opus agent aggregates across products, weighs engineering cost per product, and detects role-level anti-patterns. Output: JSON with per-product recommended horizon mix, portfolio totals, PM role findings, and a reallocation memo of at most 6 bullets naming cuts and bets.</statement>
        <rationale>Opus for the aggregation pass because cross-cutting reasoning across multiple products with dependencies requires sustained multi-step reasoning that cheaper models abbreviate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pass 3 (Reconciliation): output a structured memo that names which product gets cut, which gets accelerated, and which PM owns the H3 budget for the next quarter. The memo goes to a human portfolio-PM for sign-off; never auto-applied.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent-only portfolio decisions are an anti-pattern. The matrix is decision support; the portfolio-PM holds the final allocation authority.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>All three passes must produce JSON output; the reconciliation memo is the only prose artifact, and it must have a top-level cuts: section before the prose body.</statement>
        <rationale>Reconciliation memos bury the cut in prose. A required cuts: field at the top forces the agent to make trade-offs legible before the narrative justification.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Pre-Run Preparation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pre-compute the cross-product dependency graph as cross_product_deps.csv (columns: item_id, depends_on_product, blocking_severity) and pass it to the portfolio-PM agent. Never let the agent infer dependencies from product descriptions alone.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs will not detect cross-product dependencies unless supplied as edges in the input. Without a dependency graph, the agent invents synergies that do not exist and misses real blockers.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pass owner_count (number of humans running the portfolio) alongside product data. If the stated allocation is infeasible for the headcount, the agent must flag "headcount insufficient" rather than pretend the ratio is achievable.</statement>
        <rationale>Solo-founder portfolios mislead the model — it will recommend a clean 70/20/10 split for one human running 6 products as if that is executable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Portfolio Strategy Antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Role ambiguity: the same person plays product-PM and portfolio-PM without a written allocation memo.</description>
        <reason>The framework cannot resolve a conflict of interest if the same human owns both hats. A written memo makes trade-offs visible to others who can catch drift.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Local optimization drift: each product-PM optimizes their P&amp;L for more H1, and the aggregate portfolio drifts to 95% H1 with no transformational bets.</description>
        <reason>Local incentives aggregate to a portfolio failure. Counter: portfolio-PM owns the H3 budget separately from product budgets and cannot be lobbied out of it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Solo-founder collapse: one human running 6+ products attempts a real 70/20/10 split but exploration time collapses to zero under operational load.</description>
        <reason>Document the collapse honestly instead of pretending the ratio is real. A false ratio in the portfolio memo misleads future agents and reviews.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Cross-product synergy invisibility: portfolio math does not score work that benefits multiple products simultaneously, so shared platform work is under-funded.</description>
        <reason>Product PMs resist sharing their roadmap slot to fund shared infra. The portfolio-PM must account for cross-product leverage explicitly, not assume product PMs will volunteer it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Bilateral deals: cross-product trade-offs negotiated 1:1 between product PMs rather than in a single portfolio memo signed by the portfolio-PM.</description>
        <reason>Bilateral deals leak budget and never balance. Each PM "wins" locally; the portfolio loses in aggregate.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent conflates "PM owns more products" with "PM is more strategic" and auto-tags multi-product PMs as portfolio-PMs regardless of time allocation.</description>
        <reason>The decision frame shift from feature-level to cross-product investment is qualitative. Force the classifier to use a time_allocation field, not a product count.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent recommends splitting the difference when two PMs disagree, hiding the actual trade-off.</description>
        <reason>Compromise memos avoid the hard call. Constrain the rebalancer to pick a side with a rationale; do not average positions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Name the role explicitly each quarter. Each PM gets a written tag: product-PM or portfolio-PM or mixed (X% portfolio time). Ambiguity here is the root cause of most allocation fights.</item>
        <item>Separate budgets, not just labels. The H3 portion must be funded out of a portfolio budget that no single product PM can raid; otherwise it becomes overflow for late H1 features.</item>
        <item>Score PMs on portfolio outcomes, not just product outcomes, when they own two or more products. Otherwise they will silently let H3 die because no one rewards them for it.</item>
        <item>Cross-product trade-offs go in one memo, signed by the portfolio-PM, not negotiated 1:1 between product PMs. Bilateral deals leak budget and never balance.</item>
        <item>Every product gets a lifecycle_stage field (pre-PMF / scaling / mature / declining). Apply different horizon rubrics per stage — pre-PMF products allocate 100% to PMF and only enter the portfolio model after.</item>
        <item>Run the role-skew script before reviews, not after. Surfacing "PM B is 100% H1 across 3 products" lets the conversation start at the diagnosis instead of at the symptom.</item>
        <item>Document the kill criteria for cross-product bets at funding time. Shared-platform investments that don't ship in 2 quarters are silently subsidized forever.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow and Subagents">
      <p>Drive this with three role-aware passes. (1) Product-PM pass — for each product, a sonnet agent reads the product's backlog + OKRs + recent retros and emits a per-product allocation in horizon terms ({product, h1_pct, h2_pct, h3_pct, key_evidence}). (2) Portfolio-PM pass — an opus agent aggregates across products, weighs cost-of-engineering per product, and detects role-level anti-patterns ("PM A is 100% H1; PM B is 100% H3; portfolio is bimodal not balanced"). (3) Reconciliation pass — output a structured memo that names which product gets cut, which gets accelerated, and which PM owns the H3 budget for the next quarter. All three passes must produce JSON; the reconciliation memo is the only prose artifact, and it goes to a human PM-of-PMs for sign-off, never auto-applied.</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-brainstorm — when product PMs deadlock over which product is H3-eligible, run a diverge / converge / review cycle with each PM as a synthetic role.</item>
        <item>faion-improver — quarterly meta-loop: read last quarter's portfolio memo, the actual delivered allocation, and the PM-level OKR scores; log "what the portfolio said vs what the PMs actually shipped" as a recurring mistake-pattern.</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — once the portfolio memo is signed off, spin per-product SDD plans whose scope is bounded by the agreed allocation.</item>
        <item>Custom pm-role-classifier subagent (worth creating): input = a PM's quarterly plan; output = {role_mode: "product"|"portfolio"|"mixed", scope_overlap_with_other_pms, recommended_handoff_line}. Use it before promotions or re-orgs.</item>
        <item>faion-feature-executor — for the H1 portion of each product, where execution discipline matters more than strategic exploration.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Prompt Patterns">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a portfolio PM. Inputs: list of products with {product_id, owner_pm,
quarterly_plan, eng_cost_usd, current_revenue_usd, lifecycle_stage}. Output JSON:
{
  per_product: [{product_id, recommended_horizon_mix:{h1,h2,h3}, rationale}],
  portfolio_total: {h1,h2,h3},
  pm_role_findings: [{owner_pm, role_mode, risk}],
  reallocation_memo: "<<= 6 bullets, plain English, names cuts and bets>>"
}
Constraints:
- Do NOT invent products not in the input.
- If two PMs own overlapping scope (>30%), flag as `role_conflict` in pm_role_findings.
- Never recommend >10% H3 for a product whose lifecycle_stage = "pre-PMF".]]></code>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a single-product PM defending allocation. Given your product's backlog
and the portfolio's target {th1, th2, th3}, output JSON:
{
  agreed_cuts: [{item_id, reason}],
  contested_cuts: [{item_id, counter_argument, evidence_url}],
  cross_product_dependencies: [{item_id, depends_on_product, blocking_severity}]
}
Stay inside your product. Do not propose cuts to other products.]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="Tools and Services">
      <section name="CLI Tools">
        <list>
          <item>linear API (@linear/sdk) — Read per-project (= per-product) issue counts, owners, labels; aggregate per-PM</item>
          <item>productboard API — Pull "products" + "objectives"; map each PM's owned objectives to a horizon</item>
          <item>airtable CLI / API — Cheap per-product roster ↔ PM matrix; agents can read both sides</item>
          <item>notion API — If portfolio memo lives in Notion, agent posts the reconciliation memo as a draft for human sign-off</item>
          <item>gh (GitHub CLI) — Map PM → owned repos / projects v2 boards; useful when "product" = "repo"</item>
          <item>pandas + seaborn — Local pivot: PM × horizon × eng_cost heatmap, flag bimodal portfolios</item>
          <item>claude CLI — Drive the portfolio-PM pass on aggregated JSON; emit the reconciliation memo as Markdown</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Services and Apps">
        <list>
          <item>Productboard (SaaS, agent-friendly): "Products" + "owners" map cleanly to PM-portfolio view</item>
          <item>Aha! Roadmaps (SaaS, partial): Strong portfolio module, weak per-PM cuts</item>
          <item>Lattice / 15Five (SaaS, agent-friendly): PM OKRs by person — pair with portfolio data to detect role-skew</item>
          <item>Linear (SaaS, agent-friendly): Each team ≈ one product; PM-level rollups via labels</item>
          <item>Jira Plans (SaaS, agent-friendly): Heaviest; needed when PMO already enforces it</item>
          <item>Notion + database views (SaaS, agent-friendly): Cheapest portfolio register for solo / small teams</item>
          <item>Reforge / Ravio benchmarking (SaaS, read-only): Useful for sanity-checking PM-to-product ratios against industry</item>
          <item>GitHub Projects v2 (SaaS, agent-friendly): Works for repo-as-product orgs</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-Agent Gotchas">
      <p>LLMs conflate "PM owns more products" with "PM is more strategic". They will tag the multi-product PM as portfolio-PM regardless of how that PM actually spends their time. Force the classifier to use a time_allocation field, not a product count.</p>
      <p>Agents over-recommend "promote IC PM to Group PM" because the prompt sounds like a career arc. Suppress this — the framework is about scope partitioning, not titles.</p>
      <p>When two PMs disagree, agents default to splitting the difference. That hides the actual trade-off. Constrain the rebalancer to pick a side and explain why, not to compromise.</p>
      <p>Reconciliation memos generated by an LLM read fluent but bury the cut. Require a cuts: section at the very top of the JSON, and inspect that field before reading the prose.</p>
      <p>Agents will quietly drop the pre-PMF exception. Pass it as a hard constraint, not a sentence in the prompt body.</p>
      <p>LLMs will not detect cross-product dependencies unless they are present as edges in the input. Always pre-compute the dep graph (a separate cross_product_deps.csv) and pass it; otherwise the agent invents synergies that don't exist.</p>
      <p>Solo-founder portfolios mislead the model — it will recommend a clean 70/20/10 split for one human running 6 products. Pass owner_count and let the agent flag "headcount insufficient for stated allocation" rather than pretend the ratio is achievable.</p>
      <p>The agent's confidence on PM-role classification is unreliable below ~5 quarters of history. Treat single-quarter outputs as advisory, not decisional.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="References and Related Skills">
      <list>
        <item>Marty Cagan — Empowered (2020), chapters on product leadership vs portfolio leadership.</item>
        <item>Roman Pichler — Strategize (2nd ed., 2022) — portfolio canvas, role separation between PM and product strategist.</item>
        <item>Melissa Perri — Escaping the Build Trap (2018) — the "feature factory" failure mode that single-product PMs replicate at portfolio scale.</item>
        <item>Lenny's Newsletter / Reforge essays on Group PM vs Director PM scope (2022–2024).</item>
        <item>Team Topologies (Skelton &amp; Pais, 2019) — for the team-shape angle, complementary to PM-role allocation.</item>
        <item>Companion file: pro/product/product-planning/portfolio-strategy/agent-integration.md — strategy-side rubric, classifier, rebalancer, allocator script.</item>
        <item>Linear API: https://developers.linear.app</item>
        <item>Productboard API: https://developer.productboard.com</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/pm-role-skew.sh" purpose="Detects single-product vs portfolio PM patterns from a CSV; flags H1-only, H3-zombie, bimodal-no-bridge."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-portfolio-pm.txt" purpose="LLM prompt for portfolio-PM pass: aggregates per-product allocations, detects role-level anti-patterns."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-product-pm.txt" purpose="LLM prompt for single-product PM defending allocation within portfolio targets."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="mlp-planning"/>
      <ref slug="minimum-product-frameworks"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
