<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Kubernetes Cluster Backup with Velero Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the backup-kubernetes-velero methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced by the decision tree.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="velero-1-15-no-restic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Velero installations MUST use the Kopia data mover (default in 1.15+); the Restic uploader is deprecated and MUST NOT be enabled for new clusters.</statement>
      <rationale source="Velero docs — Data Mover, Velero v1.15 release notes">Restic uploader is marked deprecated; new install paths default to Kopia which is faster and uses native CSI snapshots.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="csi-snapshots-enabled" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The cluster MUST have a CSI driver with VolumeSnapshotClass installed; Velero MUST use CSI snapshots (`--features=EnableCSI`) rather than restic-file-copy fallback when available.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kubernetes CSI Volume Snapshot docs">File-copy fallback is order-of-magnitude slower and loses application-consistent snapshot semantics.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="pre-post-hooks-for-stateful" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Schedule CRDs targeting stateful workloads (Postgres, MySQL, Mongo) MUST declare `pre.hook.backup.velero.io/command` (quiesce / fsfreeze) and `post.hook.backup.velero.io/command` (unfreeze).</statement>
      <rationale source="Velero docs — Backup Hooks">Without quiesce, the snapshot is crash-consistent only; application data files may be torn mid-write.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="backup-storage-location-separate-cloud" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>BackupStorageLocation MUST point to an object store in a DIFFERENT cloud or region than the cluster's control plane.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal DR review">Co-located backups die with the cluster in a regional outage; cross-region/cluster is the only resilient pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="schedule-retention" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Schedule CRD MUST set `ttl` explicitly (no infinite retention); recommended ttl: daily=168h, weekly=720h, monthly=2160h.</statement>
      <rationale source="Velero docs — Schedule">Unbounded retention grows object-store cost linearly without RTO benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If all in-cluster state is reconciled from Git + external object storage (pure GitOps, no PVC state), this methodology MUST be skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitOps principles, Kubernetes Backup Whitepaper">Backing up derived state duplicates the source of truth; reconcile-from-Git is faster restore than Velero.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
