<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Freelancer Discovery Call Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding freelancer-discovery-call-template. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="five-section-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Call template MUST cover all 5 sections: context, pain, success criteria, budget signals, decision process. Skipping any section produces gaps in the proposal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — freelance close-rate audits 2025">Each section maps to a specific proposal field; missing the budget signal collapses the proposal to a price guess.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="budget-signal-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Template MUST include at least one budget-signal question (current spend, comparable spend, allocated budget). Verbal-only budget signals are forbidden as commitment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Rob Fitzpatrick — Mom Test">Without budget signal the proposal is priced from hope, not data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="go-no-go-scorecard" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output MUST include a scorecard (5-axis, 1-5): fit, urgency, budget, decision power, vibes. Lead with score &lt;12 is no-go.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — close-rate audits">Calibrated scorecard outperforms gut on close-rate by ~30%.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="proposal-seed-one-page" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output MUST include a 1-page proposal seed (problem, approach, scope, price, timeline). Multi-page proposals at discovery stage are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — discovery-call follow-up audits">One-pager closes faster; multi-page proposals get stuck in committee even at solo-prospect stage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="listen-70-30" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Operator word-share MUST be ≤30% measured by token count in the call transcript. Above that, the call became a pitch.</statement>
      <rationale source="active-listening rule listen-80-20">Discovery converts when prospect talks; pitching during discovery kills signal and trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
