<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="VUI Market Context Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules anchoring how a VUI market brief must be sourced, scoped, and refreshed.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="scoped-stat-fields" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every market statistic MUST carry four fields: value, year, source URL, geographic scope. Stats missing any field MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1 methodology — vui-market-context section stat-schema">Voice adoption varies 3-5x between US and global figures; an unscoped "62% use voice assistants" misleads strategy decisions and cannot be re-verified.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="denominator-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The brief MUST distinguish three denominator categories: smart-speaker households, voice-assistant users, voice-search query share. Cross-category math is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1 methodology — vui-market-context section stat-schema">These denominators come from different measurement methodologies (device ownership vs intent sessions vs query type on one engine); mixing them inflates the picture arbitrarily.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="90-day-freshness" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every brief MUST be stamped with `refreshed_at` (ISO date). A brief older than 90 days MUST NOT be published; refresh first.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1 methodology — vui-market-context section current-baseline">LLM-native voice agents (ChatGPT Voice, Claude voice) reshape the landscape faster than canonical sources track; >90 days old stats may be wrong on direction, not just magnitude.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="trusted-source-allowlist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Refresh queries MUST restrict sources to the allowlist: statista.com, voicebot.ai, edisonresearch.com, nngroup.com, pewresearch.org, gartner.com. SEO listicles and secondary aggregators MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1 methodology — vui-market-context section trusted-sources">LLMs default to high-traffic listicles that cite each other; an explicit allowlist breaks circular citation and forces primary sources.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="llm-native-as-platform" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Custom LLM-VUI (OpenAI Realtime, Claude voice, ElevenLabs Conversational, Pipecat, Vapi, Retell) MUST be treated as a fifth platform category — not a feature of Alexa/Google/Siri. Platform comparison tables MUST include a dedicated LLM-native row.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1 methodology — vui-market-context section llm-native-platform">LLM-native agents bypass skill stores and certification, support open-domain dialog, and have different design requirements (no intent/slot NLU); conflating them with intent platforms produces broken systems.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the request is implementation work, locked single-vendor decision, or real-time competitive intel, the methodology MUST be skipped and the caller routed to vui-conversation-design / market-researcher respectively.</statement>
      <rationale source="self">Applying market-context machinery to the wrong workflow burns tokens without producing a usable artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
