<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="VUI Market Context Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed when agents assemble VUI market briefs; each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="hallucinated-stats" severity="high">
      <symptom>Agent returns plausible-looking adoption figures with fake or unresolvable source URLs.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="v1 methodology — vui-market-context section ai-agent-gotchas">LLMs synthesise numbers that pattern-match training data and confabulate URLs without verifying them.</root-cause>
      <fix>Require source_url for every data row. Reject rows where the URL host is outside the trusted-source allowlist; HEAD-check every URL during validation.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="mixed-denominators" severity="high">
      <symptom>Brief claims "62% adoption" combining smart-speaker household share with voice-assistant user share as if they measured the same thing.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="v1 methodology — vui-market-context section ai-agent-gotchas">Different sources publish in different denominators; synthesis pipelines collapse them.</root-cause>
      <fix>Enforce the `denominator` enum (smart-speaker-households | voice-assistant-users | voice-search-query-share) on every row; the validator refuses cross-denominator arithmetic.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="geo-scope-confusion" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Brief presents a US-only Pew figure as global; platform comparison weighted on wrong geography produces a wrong-platform recommendation.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="v1 methodology — vui-market-context section ai-agent-gotchas">Geo field stripped during summarisation; downstream consumer assumes worldwide.</root-cause>
      <fix>`geo` is required per data row; platform comparison table MUST tabulate per target geo (US, EU, APAC) before recommendation.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="stale-brief" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Brief over a year old reused for a 2026 platform decision; the data predates LLM-native voice category and recommends Bixby for a non-Korean market.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="v1 methodology — vui-market-context section ai-agent-gotchas">Briefs lack freshness gating; consumers reuse without checking refreshed_at.</root-cause>
      <fix>Validator refuses publish when today − refreshed_at &gt; 90 days; refresh-script.py is the canonical refresh entry point.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
