<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Semantic Tokens and Modes Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the semantic-tokens-and-modes methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="three-layer-strict" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tokens MUST be organized in exactly three layers: reference (raw palette/scale), system (semantic, mode-aware), component (component-scoped). Component-layer tokens MUST resolve via the system layer; direct component → reference references are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nathan Curtis — Naming Tokens in Design Systems">The system layer is the isolation boundary that makes theme swaps cheap. Jumping component → reference defeats the abstraction; rebrands then require N component edits.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="one-intent-per-token" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each semantic token MUST encode exactly one intent. Splitting brand and interactive roles is mandatory (e.g., `brand.primary` vs `action.primary`).</statement>
      <rationale source="Adobe Spectrum tokens docs">Dual-purpose tokens couple unrelated concerns; a contrast fix for the action color must not change the brand color.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="mode-coverage-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every semantic token MUST have a value in every required mode of its collection (e.g., light, dark, high-contrast, brand). Missing mode values MUST fail the CI build.</statement>
      <rationale source="Figma Variables docs">Missing mode values fall back to default at runtime — invisible until a user switches theme. Build-time enforcement catches the gap at authoring.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="dtcg-format" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Token source files MUST use the W3C Design Tokens Community Group format (`$value`, `$type`). Proprietary token formats are forbidden in the source-of-truth files.</statement>
      <rationale source="W3C DTCG Format spec">DTCG is the emerging standard; adopting it now keeps Style Dictionary, Tokens Studio, and Specify interoperable and avoids migration cost when tools converge.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="no-raw-hex-in-components" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Component code MUST NOT contain raw hex values or direct references to reference tokens. Lint MUST reject `#RRGGBB` and `var(--color-blue-500)`-style direct reference-token usage in component files.</statement>
      <rationale source="Material Design 3 token system">Raw values and direct reference-token usage bypass the semantic layer and break on theme switch. Automated lint is the only reliable enforcement.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="visual-regression-per-mode" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The token pipeline CI run MUST snapshot every mode in visual regression (Chromatic / Percy / Loki). A diff in any mode without an explicit "expected" annotation blocks merge.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — observed dark-mode regression Q4 2025">Mode-swap regressions are invisible in code diff; only visual comparison catches an accidental color swap.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
