<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Semantic Tokens and Modes Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed in real token-system migrations. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="reference-jumping" severity="high">
      <symptom>Component CSS contains `var(--color-blue-500)` or raw hex `#0066cc`; dark-mode swap leaves buttons blue on dark surface.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Internal — observed in component refactor PRs">Author skipped the system layer and pulled directly from reference, defeating the abstraction.</root-cause>
      <fix>Enable `reject_raw_hex_in_components` + `reject_direct_reference_in_components` lint rules; require redirect to semantic alias such as `var(--color-action-primary)`.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="brand-mode-duplication" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Adding brand-b doubled token count; every brand-a token is mirrored with a brand-b copy that differs only in two values.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Style Dictionary issue tracker">Author duplicated the full token tree instead of overlaying only the delta values per mode.</root-cause>
      <fix>Use mode overlays: each semantic token has one definition with `values_by_mode` keyed by mode name. Reject PRs that introduce parallel token namespaces per brand.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="missing-platform-transform" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Style Dictionary build emits iOS Swift tokens with pixel values; physical device renders text 2× too large.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Style Dictionary architecture docs">Config omitted `size/pxToPt` (iOS) or `size/pxToSp` (Android) transforms; agent generated config from web template without platform translation.</root-cause>
      <fix>Pipeline config MUST declare per-platform transformGroups (`web` / `ios` / `android`) and visual-regression MUST run on each target.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="missing-mode-coverage" severity="high">
      <symptom>Production dark-mode shows white text on white surface; CI never caught the gap.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Figma Variables docs — missing mode value falls back to default">A semantic token shipped without a value in one mode; build did not enforce mode coverage.</root-cause>
      <fix>Run `templates/check-modes.mjs` in CI; fail the build when any semantic token is missing a value in any required mode. Snapshot every mode in visual regression.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
