<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="semantic-tokens-and-modes Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for semantic-tokens-and-modes as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent minting new reference colors instead of reusing existing palette when adding a token.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Reference token proliferation defeats the palette abstraction. Lint must reject reference tokens that duplicate existing palette entries within a configurable delta.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent duplicating all tokens when asked to add a brand mode instead of overlaying only the delta values.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Full duplication creates N copies of every token, each requiring independent maintenance. A mode overlay contains only the tokens that differ from the base mode.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Style Dictionary configs generated by agents missing platform-specific transforms (e.g., size/pxToPt for iOS).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without the iOS pxToPt transform, point values are treated as pixel values, producing layout bugs that are only visible on physical devices — not in simulators.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent writing CSS like var(--color-blue-500) directly in component files.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Direct reference-token usage in components bypasses the semantic layer and breaks on theme switch. Lint rule must redirect to the semantic equivalent (e.g., var(--action-primary)).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
