<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-concepts" title="Scope Management Core Concepts">
  <summary>Definitions of product scope, project scope, scope baseline, and scope creep — the vocabulary required to manage and defend project boundaries.</summary>

  <section title="Scope Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Distinguish product scope (features and functions) from project scope (work required to deliver them); confusion between the two creates phantom deliverables.</statement>
      <rationale>A team that conflates the two may build the right product but omit required project work (testing, migration, training), or track project tasks as if they were product requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Core terms every PM must apply consistently:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Product Scope — features and functions of the product being delivered.</item>
      <item>Project Scope — all work required to deliver the product scope, including PM, testing, documentation, migration.</item>
      <item>Scope Baseline — the approved scope statement + WBS + WBS dictionary; the reference against which all changes are measured.</item>
      <item>Scope Creep — uncontrolled expansion of scope without formal change-control approval; the primary cause of budget and schedule overrun.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Requirement Types">
    <p>Classify every requirement at collection time to ensure completeness:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Business requirements — why the project exists (e.g., increase revenue 20%).</item>
      <item>Stakeholder requirements — what stakeholders need (e.g., executive dashboard).</item>
      <item>Solution / functional requirements — capabilities the system must have.</item>
      <item>Transition requirements — what is needed to move from current to future state (data migration, training).</item>
      <item>Non-functional requirements — performance, security, usability constraints.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Collect all five requirement types before closing the scope statement; missing transition requirements are the most common hidden scope.</statement>
      <rationale>Transition work (data migration, staff training, parallel-run periods) is often scoped out by accident, then absorbed mid-project as "of course that was included."</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="MoSCoW Prioritization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply MoSCoW (Must/Should/Could/Won't) to all requirements at elicitation; rejecting nothing is committing to everything.</statement>
      <rationale>Unlabeled requirements are implicitly "Must", which makes every requirement equally non-negotiable and prevents meaningful trade-off conversations when scope pressure arrives.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Must — required for the release to be viable; failure to deliver = project failure.</item>
      <item>Should — high value but workable without; defer to next iteration if needed.</item>
      <item>Could — nice to have; include only if time and budget allow.</item>
      <item>Won't — explicitly excluded from this release; documented to prevent re-entry.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
