<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Scope Management Process">
  <summary>The five-step scope management process: collect requirements, define scope, validate scope, control scope, and maintain a requirements traceability matrix.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Collect Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use at least two elicitation techniques per stakeholder group; interviews alone miss tacit knowledge that workshops and observation surface.</statement>
      <rationale>Each technique reaches different requirement types: interviews uncover explicit needs, observation reveals unstated workflows, prototyping exposes gaps in stated requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Interviews — one-on-one to surface individual needs and constraints.</item>
      <item>Workshops — cross-functional groups resolve conflicts and surface interdependencies.</item>
      <item>Observation — watching users perform tasks reveals requirements they cannot articulate.</item>
      <item>Questionnaires — scale across many stakeholders; good for quantitative priorities.</item>
      <item>Prototyping — trigger concrete feedback on gaps and misunderstandings.</item>
      <item>Document analysis — extract requirements from existing systems, contracts, regulations.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/requirements-doc.md">Requirements documentation template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Define Scope">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every scope statement must include an explicit "Out of Scope" section; if it is not listed as excluded, stakeholders will assume it is included.</statement>
      <rationale>Disputes at project end almost always involve something absent from the scope statement but also absent from the exclusions list — ambiguity defaults to "included" in client interpretation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>A complete scope statement contains: objectives (measurable), product scope description, deliverables with acceptance criteria, explicit exclusions, constraints, and assumptions.</p>
    <reference path="templates/scope-statement.md">Scope statement template with approval block</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Validate Scope">
    <rule>
      <statement>Obtain formal written acceptance for each deliverable against pre-agreed acceptance criteria before moving to the next phase; verbal acceptance is not acceptance.</statement>
      <rationale>Verbal sign-off degrades with time — stakeholders forget what they approved and scope disputes become "he said / she said" with no documentary evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Deliverable formally accepted: written acceptance form with criteria checked, reviewer name, date, signature. Stored in project document repository.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>PM emails "looks good to me" after a demo. No criteria checked, no named reviewer. Client later denies acceptance.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Control Scope">
    <rule>
      <statement>Route every scope change through the formal change-control process before any work begins; informal "small" changes are how projects absorb 30% of unplanned work.</statement>
      <rationale>Six small changes each consuming two days equals 12 unplanned days — equivalent to a major change that would have required CCB approval. The aggregation is invisible without the register.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Monitor scope baseline weekly against actual deliverables and WBS.</item>
      <item>Evaluate every change request for scope, schedule, cost, and risk impact.</item>
      <item>Update scope documents only after formal approval.</item>
      <item>Communicate all approved changes to the full team before implementation.</item>
    </list>
    <see-also>
      <link path="../change-control/">Change Control methodology</link>
    </see-also>
  </section>

  <section title="Requirements Traceability">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every requirement must trace to design, build, test, and acceptance evidence; 100% RTM coverage is a release gate, not a nice-to-have.</statement>
      <rationale>RTM coverage is the only mechanism that prevents requirements from being dropped silently during delivery — coverage gaps are acceptance risk made visible before go-live.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/rtm_coverage.py">RTM coverage audit script — exits non-zero on gaps</reference>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Maintaining the RTM only at project start and never updating it during delivery.</description>
      <reason>An abandoned RTM creates a false sense of coverage; gaps accumulate invisibly and surface as acceptance failures or post-launch defects.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
