<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules" title="Scope Control Rules and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Concrete rules for preventing scope creep, writing testable acceptance criteria, and operating the scope-guard agentic workflow.</summary>

  <section title="Scope Creep Prevention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every approved scope change with a cost and schedule re-estimate in the same change request; reject standalone scope deltas that arrive without impact analysis.</statement>
      <rationale>Scope without impact analysis is a blank check; teams accept scope and absorb the cost silently, which destroys schedule and budget discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a scope creep retro monthly: review accepted "small" changes, count cumulative days added, present the aggregate to the sponsor.</statement>
      <rationale>Small changes are invisible individually; aggregating them monthly makes the drift visible and creates a natural escalation trigger before it becomes a crisis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When declining a scope request, offer an alternative (next phase, separate project) and document the decision; "no" with no alternative breeds work-arounds.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholders who are rejected without alternatives find informal channels to get their request implemented anyway, bypassing scope control entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Acceptance Criteria Quality">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write acceptance criteria as testable assertions in Given/When/Then form, or as explicit numeric thresholds; reject criteria that are not independently verifiable.</statement>
      <rationale>Narrative criteria ("the system should be fast") produce acceptance disputes; Gherkin or numeric criteria produce pass/fail verdicts that both parties can measure independently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Acceptance criterion: "The search should return relevant results quickly." — Not testable; "relevant" and "quickly" are undefined.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Acceptance criterion: "Given a catalog of 10,000 products, when a user submits a search query, then results appear within 2 seconds and the top result matches the query keyword." — Independently verifiable.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Scope Guard">
    <rule>
      <statement>Scope baseline lives in version-controlled YAML (scope/baseline.yaml); CODEOWNERS restricts direct edits to the sponsor; every baseline change requires an approved change-request ID in the commit message.</statement>
      <rationale>Wiki-hosted scope documents have no diff history and no access control; git-tracked YAML makes changes auditable, and CODEOWNERS makes unauthorized edits impossible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>A scope-guard agent reviews PRs and new tickets against the WBS baseline and emits a verdict (in_scope / out_of_scope / ambiguous / gold_plating); humans merge — the agent never auto-approves.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent verdicts remove routine triage labor; the human-in-loop on merge ensures political and contextual judgment is applied before scope boundaries are crossed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Locking scope baseline too early without adequate stakeholder validation, then defending it against legitimate clarifications.</description>
      <reason>Premature baseline lock traps the project in obsolete decisions; balance with disciplined change control that distinguishes clarifications (no cost/schedule impact) from scope additions (require approval).</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Gold plating — developers adding unrequested features to "improve" the product.</description>
      <reason>Gold plating consumes contingency, delays tested deliverables, and introduces unreviewed scope that may fail acceptance or create downstream support burden.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
