<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="terraform-modules-versioning Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for terraform-modules-versioning. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Major version bumps (X.0.0) MUST be used for any change that requires consumers to update variable names, remove previously supported variables, or change output names. A migration guide MUST accompany every major release.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a clear signal, consumers cannot distinguish a bug fix from a breaking change at a glance. Major bumps give teams a predictable gate for planning upgrades.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Minor version bumps (0.X.0) MUST be used for new optional variables, new outputs, or new resources that are backward-compatible. Existing callers MUST continue to work without modification.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Consumers who rely on ~&gt; constraints (see below) will pick up minor versions automatically. Breaking backward compatibility in a minor bump violates consumer expectations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Patch version bumps (0.0.X) MUST be used for bug fixes that do not add new features or change behavior. No consumer code changes required.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Patch bumps signal safe auto-adoption for consumers using pessimistic constraints.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All module source references that include a version argument MUST use the pessimistic constraint operator (~&gt;) to allow patch and minor updates within a major version, or an explicit range. The exact-pin operator (=) MUST only be used when a specific patch is known to fix a critical bug.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">~&gt; 5.0 allows 5.0.1, 5.1.0, 5.9.9 but blocks 6.0.0 — safe for routine updates while blocking breaking changes. Exact pins require manual bumps for every patch release, increasing maintenance burden.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Registry and GitHub module sources MUST always include the version argument. Local path sources (./modules/X) MUST NOT include a version argument.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Local modules have no separate release lifecycle — the version argument is ignored and its presence misleads maintainers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every published module MUST maintain a CHANGELOG.md in the module root. Each release MUST document: the version number, release date, and categorized changes (Added, Changed, Breaking Changes, Fixed, Deprecated, Removed). Breaking changes MUST be in their own section and include migration instructions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Consumers deciding whether to upgrade need to evaluate impact without reading the full diff. A categorized CHANGELOG reduces the upgrade decision from O(diff) to O(CHANGELOG section).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
