<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Retention Metrics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Retention Metrics` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="locked-sql-per-metric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each retention metric MUST have a single canonical SQL definition stored in a metrics-store. Recomputations in BI tools forbidden — must query metrics-store.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mode / Looker LookML / dbt metrics-store practice">Same name + different SQL across reports yields uncomparable numbers. Locked SQL = single source of truth for the entire org.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="d1-d7-d30-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cohort retention MUST include D1, D7, D30 (or 1d/7d/30d) at minimum. Each measures a different layer: activation (D1), habit (D7), retention (D30).</statement>
      <rationale source="Andrew Chen retention curves; Mixpanel benchmarks">Single retention number averages activation + habit + retention failures. D1/D7/D30 separates them; each has different intervention. D30 alone misses early-funnel breaks.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="dau-mau-ratio-with-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DAU/MAU MUST be reported with a numerator and denominator floor (e.g. exclude weeks with &lt; 100 MAU) and segmented by plan / cohort.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sequoia / a16z engagement benchmarks">DAU/MAU in tiny populations is volatile and misleading. Floor + segmentation surfaces real engagement, not noise from small numbers.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="churn-risk-score-backtested" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Churn-risk score MUST be backtested on 6+ months of historical churners. Live-deployed without backtest is forbidden — produces noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer success ML operations corpus">Untested scores produce high false positive rate; CS team ignores. Backtesting on real churners surfaces which signals actually predict and at what threshold.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="monthly-not-quarterly-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default retention reporting cadence MUST be monthly with quarterly deep-dives. Quarterly-only reporting hides month-by-month decay.</statement>
      <rationale source="SaaS finance operating cadence">Quarterly cadence misses early signals — by the time the quarter ends, 3 months of decay are baked in. Monthly catches inflection; quarterly contextualizes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
