<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="retention-metrics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for retention-metrics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Computing DAU from event_count &gt; 0 instead of COUNT(DISTINCT user_id).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multi-session users inflate DAU; the metric becomes non-comparable across time periods.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Reporting D30 retention for cohorts that are only 10 days old.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Diagonal effect: newest cohorts have incomplete history; D30 comparisons are meaningless until the cohort matures to 30+ days.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Comparing cohort retention across periods with different traffic mixes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A paid-channel expansion confounds the trend; always segment by acquisition source before declaring retention improvement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Churn-risk model trained on Q1 data scoring Q3 cohorts without retraining.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Product changes and seasonal patterns shift the feature distributions; a stale model misclassifies users and wastes intervention budget.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Push-notification spikes from re-engagement campaign counted as "retention improvement".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Notification-induced short-term returns must be separated from habitual return — distinguish them by checking D7 retention of reactivated users vs organic baseline.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
