<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="google-ads-optimization Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for google-ads-optimization. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not enable Target CPA or Target ROAS until a campaign has recorded at least 30 conversions in the past 30 days — use Maximize Conversions until that threshold is reached.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Smart bidding requires conversion history to model cost predictions; below 30 conversions the algorithm over-fits to noise, causing erratic CPA swings and potential delivery collapse.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set counting_type to ONE_PER_CLICK for leads and ONE_PER_CONVERSION for purchases — never use ONE_PER_CONVERSION for lead forms, which inflates conversion counts when users submit multiple times.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Incorrect counting inflates conversion volume metrics, causing the bidding algorithm to perceive higher performance than actual and over-bid on lower-quality leads.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Upload offline conversions within 90 days of the original click — Google rejects gclid-matched events older than 90 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The 90-day gclid validity window is a hard API constraint; delayed uploads silently drop and the bidding algorithm never receives the conversion signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Import GA4 conversions to Google Ads via the UI (Tools → Conversions → Import → Google Analytics 4 properties) rather than the API — the API cannot initiate new GA4 links.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">GA4-to-Google Ads linking requires OAuth consent from the GA4 account; this cannot be programmatically initiated via the Google Ads API alone and requires the UI flow.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
