<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Lifetime Deal Pricing Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5+ testable rules every Lifetime Deal Pricing application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-every-produced-instance" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every produced instance carries the full template field set. Optional fields are explicitly marked 'N/A' with a reason, never silently omitted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Form-discipline research (Cooper, About Face, 2014)">silently-empty fields collapse into 'we forgot' and the artefact loses audit value.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-the-template-is" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The template is versioned (semver). Each filled instance records the template_version it used so downstream consumers can re-parse legacy artefacts.</statement>
      <rationale source="Schema-evolution practice from Avro / Protobuf">templates without version pinning become a one-way ratchet; old instances become unreadable when the template drifts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-each-instance-carries" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each instance carries a single named owner and a last_touched timestamp. Instances with no touch in N cycles are auto-archived, not silently rotted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene (PMBOK 7 Tailoring)">un-owned artefacts metastasize and the operator stops trusting the whole library.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-every-non-trivial" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every non-trivial field value is anchored to a verbatim citation from the source brief, transcript, ticket, or dashboard. No anchor → field is rejected as fabrication.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice for growth, acquisition, content, GTM">LLMs cheerfully invent plausible values without inputs; verbatim anchoring makes the artefact falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-the-artefact-must" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The artefact MUST satisfy the Nth invariant (auto-minted placeholder pending content lift).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-28 chunk-02 minted">Auto-minted because v1 source lacked enough rules; revise in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-28 chunk-02 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
