<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Internal Link Rotation Schedule Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every internal-link rotation schedule must enforce. Hard rules; designed to prevent schedule-slip, SLA-erosion, audit-theatre, and missing retrospectives.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-one-cluster-per-fortnight" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exactly 1 cluster is audited per fortnight (every 2 weeks). For 3-10 clusters, rotation covers the site in 6-20 weeks.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-cadence research; solo-operator capacity benchmarks">More frequent than fortnightly burns operator time; less frequent than monthly lets issues compound between audits.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-sixty-minute-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit window is fixed at 60 minutes. Overruns are deferred (logged into the deferred-fix register), not absorbed by extending the slot.</statement>
      <rationale source="Time-boxing research; solo-operator sustainability">Time-boxed audits sustain over quarters; unbounded audits get cancelled by the third rotation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-deferred-fix-30-day-sla" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every deferred fix carries a 30-day SLA from audit date. Fixes past SLA escalate into the next rotation's first slot.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operations-SLA discipline">Without an SLA, deferred-fix lists become graveyards; the 30-day cap forces resolution before stale-rot.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-fixed-rotation-order" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cluster rotation order is fixed at quarter start. Reorderings mid-quarter are forbidden — favouring one cluster creates blind spots elsewhere.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-completeness research">Operators tend to repeatedly audit the "interesting" cluster and skip the boring ones; fixed order breaks the bias.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-skipping" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No rotation slot is skipped. If the operator cannot run a slot, the schedule pauses (with reason logged) rather than silently rolling forward.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cadence-integrity research">Silent skips become the new norm; explicit pause makes the gap visible and recoverable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-end-of-quarter-retrospective" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>End of quarter: write a 1-page retrospective summarising fixes shipped, SLA misses, recurring offender clusters, and rotation-order adjustments for the next quarter.</statement>
      <rationale source="Retrospective discipline; Deming cycle">Without retrospective, the schedule loops without learning. The retrospective is the only mechanism that improves cluster-specific rules over time.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies-If hold and no Skip-If trigger applies, walk the 5-step procedure end-to-end and run the validator before declaring the schedule live.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory run leaf">Decision-tree run leaf for canonical execution path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the Applies-If preconditions are not met OR any Skip-If disqualifier holds.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory skip leaf">Decision-tree skip leaf for non-applicable inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
