<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ops-financial-basics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>Understand unit economics: LTV, CAC, payback period, LTV:CAC ratio. Track monthly P and L with revenue, COGS, gross margin, and operating expenses to validate business viability.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>unit-economics</tag>
      <tag>financial</tag>
      <tag>ltv</tag>
      <tag>cac</tag>
      <tag>pnl</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Financial Fundamentals for Subscription Businesses</title>
    <summary>Subscription business viability hinges on understanding unit economics: how much each customer is worth over their lifetime (LTV), how much you pay to acquire them (CAC), and whether you recover that cost in reasonable time (payback period). The golden ratio, LTV:CAC greater than or equal to 3, means each customer generates three times their acquisition cost. A monthly P and L with revenue, COGS, gross margin, and operating expenses reveals where cash is flowing and what expenses are unsustainable.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Many SaaS founders operate on intuition, assuming "if we have paying customers, we're profitable." This fails because CAC can exceed LTV, burning cash while appearing to grow. Unit economics make the math transparent: Is the business fundamentally viable, or are you subsidizing every customer?</p>
      <p>A monthly P and L separates revenue sources from costs and calculates gross margin (what's left after direct costs) and operating profit (what's left after overhead). Without this visibility, founders make wrong prioritization calls (e.g. "acquire more customers" when gross margin is negative, or "cut costs to profitability" when CAC is too high).</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Early SaaS founders (pre-Series A) validating business model before scaling marketing spend.</item>
        <item>Evaluating a new pricing tier or customer segment: unit economics must improve or stay consistent, not degrade.</item>
        <item>Deciding between product expansion vs. customer success investment. Unit economics reveal which lever moves the needle.</item>
        <item>Presenting to investors or co-founders about business health and sustainability.</item>
        <item>Launching marketing campaigns: calculate expected CAC and validate it against LTV before spending.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-product-market-fit businesses where cohort retention is below 60% at 3 months — improving retention comes before optimizing CAC.</item>
        <item>One-time purchase or marketplace products — LTV formula assumes recurring revenue and breaks for non-subscription models.</item>
        <item>Fully bootstrapped single-person businesses with minimal overhead — the unit economics formula is overkill when you're not acquiring customers at scale.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="unit-economics-framework">
      <p>Unit economics quantifies the health of your customer acquisition model. Five metrics drive the decision: ARPU (average revenue per user per month), monthly churn rate, customer acquisition cost (CAC), gross margin, and the payback period.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Calculate LTV equals ARPU divided by monthly churn rate. Calculate CAC equals total marketing spend divided by new customers acquired. Calculate LTV:CAC ratio; target greater than or equal to 3. Calculate payback period equals CAC divided by (ARPU times gross margin); target less than or equal to 12 months. If LTV:CAC is less than 3, reduce CAC (optimize marketing efficiency or increase ARPU). If payback is greater than 12 months, either increase ARPU, decrease CAC, or reduce COGS (to improve gross margin).</statement>
        <rationale>LTV tells you the total lifetime value a customer generates; divide by CAC to see how many times over the business recovers acquisition cost. LTV:CAC greater than or equal to 3 is the VC-backed standard: it means the business can profitably scale. Payback period less than or equal to 12 months ensures the business does not run out of cash while waiting for customers to become profitable. These three metrics are the primary litmus tests for subscription business viability.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Healthy unit economics">
        <description>SaaS product: ARPU $50, monthly churn 5%, CAC $150, gross margin 75%. LTV equals $50 divided by 0.05 equals $1000. LTV:CAC equals $1000 divided by $150 equals 6.7x (excellent). Payback equals $150 divided by ($50 times 0.75) equals 4 months (very fast). This business is highly profitable; customer acquisition is sustainable.</description>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Unsustainable unit economics">
        <description>SaaS product: ARPU $30, monthly churn 10%, CAC $600, gross margin 60%. LTV equals $30 divided by 0.10 equals $300. LTV:CAC equals $300 divided by $600 equals 0.5x (disastrous). Each customer costs twice their lifetime value. Payback equals 33 months (cash-flow death). This business is losing money on every customer and will run out of cash.</description>
      </example>
      <warning>
        <p>Suppress this analysis below 100 paid customers — the denominator (new customers acquired) becomes too small and noise dominates signal. Wait until you have meaningful customer volume (greater than or equal to 100) before relying on these metrics.</p>
      </warning>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Calculating LTV and CAC but ignoring gross margin. A company with ARPU $100, churn 5%, and CAC $50 appears to have LTV:CAC equals 2x, but if gross margin is only 40%, the true margin per customer is $40, not $100.</description>
        <reason>Gross margin is essential because it represents the cash available to cover the acquisition cost and future expenses. A high ARPU with low margin is fragile; a lower ARPU with high margin is more resilient.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="monthly-pnl-structure">
      <p>A monthly P and L aggregates revenue sources, calculates the cost of delivering that revenue (COGS), computes gross profit and margin percentage, then subtracts operating expenses to arrive at operating profit. This structure reveals both margins and cash burn.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Prepare a monthly P and L with: (1) Revenue (subscriptions/MRR, one-time sales, services, affiliate/other); (2) COGS (hosting, transaction fees, direct labor); (3) Gross Profit and Gross Margin percentage; (4) Operating Expenses by category (marketing, tools/software, contractors, administrative); (5) Operating Profit and margin percentage; (6) Owner Pay/Distribution and Tax Reserve. Set budget targets per category; if any exceeds 120 percent of budget, investigate. Flag unusual one-time items (chargebacks, refunds, write-offs). Publish monthly on a fixed day so the team has a predictable financial rhythm.</statement>
        <rationale>A standardized P and L structure enables month-over-month comparison and trend spotting. Budget targets per category enforce spending discipline. Gross margin percentage reveals whether the core product delivery is economical; operating margin percentage reveals overall profitability after overhead. Flagging unusual items prevents them from hiding in the noise of routine expenses.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Healthy monthly P and L">
        <description>Month: $50k revenue (subscriptions), 0 one-time. COGS: $12.5k hosting, $1.5k payment fees, 0 labor equals $14k total, 28 percent margin. OpEx: $10k marketing, $3k tools, $2k contractors, $500 admin equals $15.5k total, 31 percent of revenue. Operating profit: $20.5k (41 percent). Trend: steady MoM revenue growth, COGS ratio stable, marketing spend hitting CAC targets.</description>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="P and L with hidden issues">
        <description>$40k revenue, but COGS is $20k (50 percent) due to unoptimized hosting. OpEx is $25k (62 percent) because contractor spend is unchecked. Operating profit is negative $5k. Founder assumes "growth covers the loss," but gross margin is barely above break-even. Scaling revenue will not fix this; COGS and OpEx must improve.</description>
        <note>A P and L reveals that growth alone does not guarantee profitability. Margins matter as much as top-line revenue.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Including non-cash expenses (depreciation, stock options, accrued vacation) in the P and L without tracking cash burn separately.</description>
        <reason>A founder can be "profitable on paper" while burning cash. Track cash-basis P and L (cash in / cash out) separately from accrual-basis for decision-making.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="gross-margin-optimization">
      <p>Gross margin (revenue minus COGS, divided by revenue) is the single most important metric for SaaS profitability. A 75 percent or above gross margin means you have room to invest in sales, marketing, and product. A 50 percent margin means you're burning cash to acquire customers.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Target gross margin greater than or equal to 70 percent for SaaS. Audit COGS monthly: hosting (should scale with customer count or usage), payment processing (typically 2.9 percent plus $0.30 per transaction), and direct labor (if any). If gross margin is below 70 percent, reduce hosting cost (switch providers, optimize compute), negotiate payment processor rates (Stripe's 2.9 percent is not fixed; volume discounts exist), or increase ARPU. Do not pursue customer acquisition until gross margin is greater than or equal to 70 percent.</statement>
        <rationale>70 percent or above gross margin is the industry standard for self-sustaining SaaS. Below 70 percent, the business is either not yet at scale or has a flawed cost structure. Growing revenue on a 50 percent gross margin means you're spending $1 to earn $1; doubling customers doubles losses. Fix margin first, then scale.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Gross margin optimization workflow">
        <description>Startup has 150 customers, $5k MRR, but gross margin is 65 percent (hosting $2k, payment fees $150, no direct labor). Founder recognizes the margin gap and: (1) switches from on-demand to reserved instances (saves $600/month), (2) negotiates 2.2 percent processing rate with Stripe (saves $60/month). New margin: 73 percent. Now they can scale marketing without cash burn.</description>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Acquiring customers aggressively while gross margin is 55 percent, assuming "we'll optimize later."</description>
        <reason>"Later" does not come. Every new customer at 55 percent margin accelerates cash burn. Investors and co-founders will pressure for profitability, not for optimization. Fix margin before scaling.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="cogs-structure-for-saas">
      <p>COGS in SaaS typically includes hosting/infrastructure, payment processing fees, and direct labor. Most SaaS companies have low variable COGS because software scales horizontally.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Break down COGS by type: (1) hosting/infrastructure (reserved instances, managed databases, CDN, monitoring); (2) payment processor fees (typically 2.9 percent plus $0.30 per transaction for Stripe, negotiable below 2 percent at scale); (3) direct labor (contractor onboarding support, custom integrations). For each component, calculate what percentage of revenue it consumes. Hosting should be below 10-15 percent of revenue; payment fees below 3 percent; direct labor below 5-10 percent (if any). If any category exceeds these benchmarks, investigate substitution (e.g. buy a managed service instead of self-hosting) or eliminate the service (if custom integrations are below 5 of customers, do not build them).</statement>
        <rationale>SaaS COGS is mostly fixed (hosting) at small scale and scales with usage at large scale. Payment processor fees are negotiable; at greater than $1M MRR, most processors offer below 2 percent rates. Direct labor erodes margin; if greater than 10 percent of customers require custom integration, productize the integration. Benchmarking against industry standards prevents margin creep.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="COGS breakdown at $10k MRR">
        <description>Hosting: $1.2k (12 percent), payment fees: $290 (3 percent), direct labor: 0. Gross margin: 85 percent. Hosting is the only variable cost and it is reasonable. As the company scales to $100k MRR, hosting should grow to $15-18k (15-18 percent of revenue); if it exceeds 25 percent, optimization is needed.</description>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Offering unlimited free customer support or custom integrations for every customer, disguising labor costs in "customer success" instead of COGS.</description>
        <reason>Hidden labor costs erode margin in invisible ways. If 20 customers require 5 hours of custom integration each (100 hours), at $100/hour contractor cost, that is $10k/month in hidden COGS. Recognize it, price for it, or eliminate the service.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="opex-management">
      <p>Operating expenses (OpEx) include marketing, software tools, contractors, and administrative overhead. Many founders confuse OpEx with COGS; OpEx scales with ambition, not customer count.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Set OpEx budget targets as percentage of revenue: Marketing 10-30 percent (depends on GTM strategy), Tools/Software 5-10 percent, Contractors 10-30 percent (depends on how much work is outsourced), Administrative 2-5 percent. If actual OpEx exceeds 120 percent of budget in a category, investigate. Do not defer all OpEx optimization to "when we raise funding"; a self-sustaining business controls OpEx from day one. Monthly review of OpEx breakdown (marketing spend per acquisition channel, tool subscriptions in use, contractor hours) prevents category creep.</statement>
        <rationale>OpEx is where founder discipline matters most. A $50k MRR business can support $15-20k OpEx; overspend by $5k and you're unprofitable. Benchmarking OpEx per category against peers (other bootstrapped SaaS) keeps the business on track. Many founders maintain software subscriptions they no longer use or pay contractors beyond what the work requires; monthly OpEx review catches waste.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="OpEx discipline">
        <description>$30k MRR SaaS: Marketing $6k (20 percent), Tools $2k (7 percent), Contractors $7k (23 percent), Admin $1.5k (5 percent). Total OpEx: $16.5k (55 percent of revenue). Gross profit is $9k (30 percent margin). OpEx is controlled; the founder reviews each line monthly and cuts unnecessary tool subscriptions (saved $200 that month).</description>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Enabling every team member to subscribe to any tool they request, resulting in $500 plus monthly in duplicate or unused subscriptions.</description>
        <reason>Tool sprawl is insidious because each subscription feels small until they aggregate. A CEO using Slack, HubSpot, Notion, Zapier, Intercom, and Calendly may have 6 subscriptions times $100-500 each equals $2k plus monthly with no visibility. Require procurement approval for tools greater than $50/month.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/unit-economics.py" purpose="Python calculator for unit economics: LTV, CAC, LTV:CAC ratio, payback period, gross margin, and health alerts for SaaS/subscription businesses."/>
      <template path="templates/monthly-pnl.md" purpose="Monthly P and L template: revenue sources, COGS, gross profit, operating expenses by category, operating profit, owner pay, tax reserve, and notes for unusual items."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.profitwell.com/blog/saas-unit-economics"/>
      <link href="https://www.serena-venture.com/blog/saas-metrics/"/>
      <link href="https://review.firstround.com/the-unit-economics-foundation-of-successful-saas/"/>
      <ref slug="ops-subscription-models"/>
      <ref slug="ops-financial-planning"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
