<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="card-sorting">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Ask 15-20+ users to organize content cards into groups and generate names for those groups. Results reveal users' mental models for content organization before locking in navigation structure.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>card-sorting</tag>
      <tag>ia-research</tag>
      <tag>information-architecture</tag>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>qualitative-research</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>research</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Card Sorting</title>

    <summary>Navigation categories that make sense internally often fail users because they mirror org charts or product taxonomies rather than user mental models. Card sorting surfaces the actual groupings users expect before IA decisions are locked in. Run 15-20 participants for open sorts (where users create categories), 30+ for closed sorts (where users place content into predefined categories), use 30-60 cards written in user language, and analyze results via similarity matrix to identify high-confidence groupings and ambiguous items.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Navigation design based on internal org structure leads to patterns like "Corporate" and "Solutions" that confuse users searching for "Account Settings" or "Pricing." Card sorting reveals what groupings and labels users naturally create, providing objective evidence for structural decisions.</p>
      <p>Similarity matrices (showing that 15 of 20 users grouped items together) prevent subjective interpretation. Items grouped together more than 70% of the time become definite groupings; items grouped together 40-70% of the time need further investigation; items below 40% stay separate.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing or redesigning primary navigation—validate category labels and groupings before implementation.</item>
        <item>When analytics show high search use and low navigation use—users cannot find content in the current IA.</item>
        <item>Before tree testing—generate the structure that tree testing will then validate.</item>
        <item>When migrating content to a new IA—ensure the new structure matches user expectations.</item>
        <item>When internal opinion on IA is divided—card sort results provide neutral, data-driven evidence.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When the IA is already validated and stable—card sorting is generative; use tree testing to validate an existing structure instead.</item>
        <item>With fewer than 15 participants for open sort—below that threshold, patterns are unreliable and may reflect individual quirks rather than shared mental models.</item>
        <item>When cards exceed 60 items—cognitive fatigue degrades result quality; participants rush the final cards. Split oversized sets into multiple focused sorts.</item>
        <item>For navigation with fewer than 10 items—direct user interviews are faster and surface more detailed reasoning.</item>
        <item>When IA is constrained by legal or regulatory requirements that cannot change regardless of user preference.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <how-to>
      <step>Define the goal: what IA decision will this sort inform? (e.g., "Validate category structure for product navigation" or "Determine if users group support topics by problem type or by product?")</step>
      <step>Prepare cards: write 30-60 content labels in user language (no jargon, no internal terminology). Run labels past a non-technical person to catch product-speak before the study.</step>
      <step>Choose format: Open sort (users create categories) for exploration; Closed sort (users place cards into predefined categories) for validation; Hybrid when refining an existing IA with some decisions locked and others open.</step>
      <step>Recruit participants: 15-20 for open sort (patterns emerge reliably at this volume); 30+ for closed sort (placement percentages need statistical stability). Match the target user profile.</step>
      <step>Conduct sessions: give standard instructions without examples. Examples bias grouping decisions. For open sorts, ask participants to label their groups while the rationale is fresh; delayed labeling produces generic names.</step>
      <step>Analyze results: compute similarity matrix (% of participants who placed each pair of cards in the same group). Apply thresholds: above 70% = definite grouping, 40-70% = consider grouping, below 40% = keep separate. For open sorts, aggregate participant-generated category names and identify consensus labels.</step>
      <step>Follow with tree testing: card sort reveals how users group content; tree testing validates that users can find content in the resulting structure. Run tree testing on the proposed IA before implementing.</step>
    </how-to>

    <section name="format-choice">
      <p>Open and closed sorts answer different questions and require different sample sizes.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use open sort for early exploration when IA structure is uncertain. Use closed sort for validation when structure is proposed and you need to test whether users can place content correctly. Use hybrid when some categories are locked and others are flexible.</statement>
        <rationale>Open sort reveals what categories users would naturally create—most generative, least constrained. Closed sort tests whether users accept the categories you proposed—more constraint, more efficiency, but misses novel groupings. Hybrid is for refinement.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Open sort requires 15-20 participants. Closed sort requires 30+ participants. These thresholds ensure statistical reliability: patterns emerge at 15+ for open sort; placement percentages stabilize at 30+ for closed sort.</statement>
        <rationale>Fewer than 15 participants in open sort produce unreliable similarity matrices where individual outliers dominate. Closed sort with fewer than 30 participants produces percentages that are too noisy for decision-making.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="card-preparation">
      <p>Card quality directly determines result quality. Jargon and ambiguous wording produce noisy groupings.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use 30-60 cards written entirely in user language. Remove internal jargon, system terminology, and product-specific acronyms. Each card should be a noun or short noun phrase (e.g., "Upgrade Account" not "Tier Migration").</statement>
        <rationale>Over 60 cards causes cognitive fatigue, degrading sort quality on the final 20%. Jargon tests vocabulary knowledge rather than mental models—a user who groups "SSO" and "Authentication" together may not do so because they are related, but because they do not understand "SSO." Below 30 cards under-represents the content space and produces oversimplified structures.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not present cards in alphabetical order. Alphabetical order biases groupings toward alphabetic proximity.</statement>
        <rationale>Participants unconsciously group alphabetically adjacent items together even when they are conceptually unrelated. Randomize card order before the sort begins.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run a pilot sort with one internal person (someone who did not design the IA) to catch confusing card wording before the real study.</statement>
        <rationale>A single pilot sort surfaces labeling problems that will derail the actual research. Better to catch these before recruiting real participants.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="analysis-and-thresholds">
      <p>Similarity matrix analysis is the core of card sorting. Without thresholds, interpretation is subjective.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Apply similarity matrix thresholds to make grouping decisions explicit: above 70% agreement = definite grouping (create category), 40-70% = ambiguous (needs further research or tree testing), below 40% = keep separate. Document the threshold logic in your report.</statement>
        <rationale>Without thresholds, analysts interpret matrices subjectively, producing inconsistent conclusions. Fixed thresholds make the decision rule explicit and repeatable across analysts and projects.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For open sorts, flag outlier groupings (unusual groupings made by 1-2 participants). Do not discard them—investigate whether they represent an underserved user segment. If 20% of participants share an outlier grouping, it is not noise; it is a segment.</statement>
        <rationale>Majority-based analysis can miss important minority needs. An outlier shared by 20% of users may be as important as the majority pattern, especially if that 20% represents high-value customers or power users.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For open sorts, compute standardization score (consistency of category structures across participants). Low standardization indicates that users do not share a clear mental model; high standardization indicates consensus.</statement>
        <rationale>Standardization is a confidence metric. High standardization means the proposed IA is backed by strong consensus; low standardization suggests the topic space may not have a natural structure or that your cards are ambiguous.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Including more than 60 cards in a single sort session.</description>
        <reason>Participants experience cognitive fatigue past 60 cards. The groupings made in the final third of the sort are rushed and lower-quality. Split oversized sets into focused sub-sorts by content area.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Not asking participants why they grouped items together during in-person sessions or immediately after remote sessions.</description>
        <reason>The similarity matrix shows what was grouped, not why. "Why" questions reveal label preferences, mental model distinctions, and conceptual overlaps that quantitative data cannot capture. Asking participants "Why did you put these together?" produces the richest insights.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating open card sort results as a final IA. "Users grouped it this way, so we ship this structure."</description>
        <reason>Card sorting reveals mental models; it does not validate that users can navigate the resulting structure. Tree testing—where users search for specific items in the proposed IA—provides that validation. Always follow card sorting with tree testing before implementation.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using inconsistent card labels across open sort groups. Some cards say "Reports" (internal language) and others say "View Your Performance" (user language).</description>
        <reason>Inconsistency confuses participants and produces noisier groupings. Label all cards consistently, either all internal or all user-facing (prefer user-facing).</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="pipeline-to-tree-testing">
      <p>Card sorting is the input to tree testing, not a final decision. The pipeline maximizes learning.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always follow open card sorting with tree testing before implementing the proposed IA.</statement>
        <rationale>Card sorting reveals how users group content; tree testing validates that users can navigate the resulting structure and find specific items. The two methods answer different questions. Card sort alone produces an IA that feels logical to users but may be hard to navigate; tree test alone validates navigation but does not validate labels. Together they de-risk the implementation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Pipeline: Card Sort → proposed structure → Tree Test → refined structure → implement.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use ambiguous items from card sort (those scoring 40-70% agreement or above) as the focus for tree testing. Test whether users can find those items in the proposed structure, and which category they expect to find them in.</statement>
        <rationale>Items with high agreement need no further testing. Items with low agreement are the bets; tree testing on those items determines whether the proposed structure handles them well or needs adjustment.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/card-sort-plan.md" purpose="Plan skeleton: objectives, method, participants, card list, categories (if closed sort), timeline."/>
      <template path="templates/results-report.md" purpose="Results report: user-created categories, agreement matrix, placement percentages, segment analysis, recommendations."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/card-sorting-definition/"/>
      <link href="https://www.optimalworkshop.com/learn/101s/card-sorting/"/>
      <link href="https://boxesandarrows.com/card-sorting-a-definitive-guide/"/>
      <link href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/information-architecture-4th/9781491913529/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
