<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Speech-to-Text — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules: default provider by accuracy/cost, self-host break-even, input validation, chunking with overlap, mandatory fallback.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-default-provider" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default to GPT-4o Mini Transcribe for accuracy at low cost ($0.003/min); switch to AssemblyAI when diarization or structured output (summaries, chapters) is needed; pick Deepgram when custom vocabulary boost matters.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenAI / AssemblyAI / Deepgram pricing 2026">GPT-4o Mini Transcribe offers the best accuracy/cost ratio for single-speaker audio. AssemblyAI's LeMUR pipeline adds post-processing (summaries, action items) without extra calls. Deepgram custom vocab cuts WER 20-40% on domain-specific terms.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-self-host-break-even" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use faster-whisper (Large-v3 Turbo) for self-hosted production. Break-even vs API is at ≈30,000 minutes/month (≈500 hours). Below that, APIs are cheaper and have no ops burden.</statement>
      <rationale source="A10G GPU cost vs OpenAI API pricing 2026">Fixed GPU cost is ≈$276/mo minimum. Above 30K minutes, faster-whisper Large-v3 Turbo delivers 216× real-time on a single A10G and amortises the GPU. Below threshold, API is the rational choice.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-input-validation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Validate file format, sample rate, and size locally before calling any STT API. Return a structured error for unsupported inputs rather than letting the API fail mid-transfer.</statement>
      <rationale source="API operational reports">Large file uploads to APIs fail after consuming bandwidth and time. Pre-validation catches unsupported formats and oversized files locally before any network cost is incurred. WAV ≥8kHz mono is the floor; lower is garbage in.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-chunking-with-overlap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Chunk audio files &gt;25MB into ≤5-minute segments with a 5-second overlap. Words spanning chunk boundaries MUST not be lost.</statement>
      <rationale source="Whisper docs; production transcription lessons">Without overlap, words that span a chunk boundary are split and the fragment gets dropped or mis-transcribed. A 5-second overlap ensures every word lands fully in at least one chunk; downstream dedup picks one copy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-mandatory-fallback" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Configure a fallback provider; never let a single-provider outage block a transcription pipeline. Fallback may be a second cloud OR local faster-whisper.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenAI / AssemblyAI 2025-2026 incident reports">Each major STT provider has had endpoint-specific outages while other parts of their API stayed up. Single-provider deployment causes feature-level downtime; a fallback eliminates it for minimal code overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
