<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Ideation Methods: SCAMPER, Mind Mapping, Starbursting Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding ideation-methods. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="subject-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>SCAMPER MUST have a concrete existing subject. Applying SCAMPER to a vacuum produces nonsense.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bob Eberle — SCAMPER (1971)">SCAMPER's lenses operate on the subject's attributes; no attributes, no operation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="scamper-7-lenses-all" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>SCAMPER MUST apply all 7 lenses (Substitute, Combine, Adapt, Modify, Put to other use, Eliminate, Reverse) — skipping lenses produces an under-explored variant set.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bob Eberle — SCAMPER">Each lens surfaces a distinct variant class; partial application leaves the most novel ones uncovered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="mindmap-3-level-min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mind Map MUST have at least 3 levels of depth from the central node. Single-level branching is a list, not a map.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tony Buzan — Mind Mapping">Depth surfaces second- and third-order connections that flat lists miss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="starbursting-5wh-complete" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Starbursting MUST cover all 6 question types (Who, What, Where, When, Why, How) with ≥3 questions each before any answer is attempted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Starbursting facilitation guide">Skipping a W/H type leaves a blind spot; the lazy default is to skip 'Why' which is the highest-signal one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="output-is-worksheet" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output MUST be a structured worksheet (SCAMPER table, Mind Map node tree, or Starbursting matrix), not a raw list.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — output-format audits">Worksheets force completeness checks and produce inputs that downstream PMs can act on.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
