<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-scamper" title="SCAMPER: Systematic Creativity via Seven Transformation Lenses">
  <summary>SCAMPER applies seven transformation lenses (Substitute, Combine, Adapt, Modify, Put to other uses, Eliminate, Reverse) to an existing product or process to systematically generate improvement ideas.</summary>

  <section title="SCAMPER Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply each SCAMPER lens in sequence, spending 5-10 minutes per lens generating 3-5 ideas — do not evaluate until all seven lenses are complete.</statement>
      <rationale>Premature evaluation blocks exploration. The Eliminate and Reverse lenses produce the most disruptive ideas and are most often skipped when teams run out of time — forcing a fixed time per lens ensures coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Substitute: What materials, people, or processes can we replace?</item>
      <item>Combine: What features, audiences, or ideas can we merge?</item>
      <item>Adapt: What works in a similar industry that we can copy and improve?</item>
      <item>Modify: What can we change in size, shape, color, speed, or frequency?</item>
      <item>Put to other uses: Who else needs this? What other markets exist?</item>
      <item>Eliminate: What is not essential? What rules can we break?</item>
      <item>Reverse/Rearrange: What if we did the opposite? Changed the sequence?</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="SCAMPER Worked Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Applying SCAMPER to a coffee shop.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Substitute: Plant-based milk default, robot baristas
Combine:    Coffee + coworking, Coffee + laundry
Adapt:      Copy hotel concierge service, airline loyalty program
Modify:     24/7 hours, subscription model, tiny/huge cup sizes
Put to use: Evening wine bar, podcast studio rental
Eliminate:  No cash, no menu (AI recommends), no seating
Reverse:    Customers make own coffee, mobile shop comes to you
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/scamper-worksheet.md">SCAMPER worksheet with slots for 3 ideas per lens and top-3 synthesis</reference>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Rushing through all lenses in under 15 minutes total.</description>
    <reason>The disruptive ideas (Eliminate, Reverse) require more cognitive effort and only emerge after the obvious ideas are exhausted. Rushing produces the same ideas brainstorming produces without structure.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
