<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-mind-mapping-and-starbursting" title="Mind Mapping, Starbursting, and Combining Methods">
  <summary>Mind Mapping for visual exploration of connections between ideas, Starbursting for systematic question generation before solution-jumping, and recipes for combining methods.</summary>

  <section title="Mind Mapping">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with a single central topic, radiate main themes as branches, add details as sub-branches, then draw connections between related ideas across different branches.</statement>
      <rationale>The connection-drawing step is the highest-value phase: it surfaces non-obvious relationships between ideas that linear brainstorming misses. Most teams stop at sub-branches and skip connections.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use single words or short phrases per node — never full sentences.</statement>
      <rationale>Full sentences force sequential processing; single words allow the eye to skip and pattern-match across the map, which is how the mind finds connections.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Digital tools: Miro, Mural (collaborative), MindMeister, XMind (dedicated), FigJam, Whimsical</item>
      <item>Start broad (main branches), then go specific (sub-branches)</item>
      <item>Use different colors for different themes</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Starbursting">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before answering any question about a new idea, use Starbursting to generate all six question types (Who, What, Where, When, Why, How) — at least 5 questions per type — then prioritize the top 10 to answer.</statement>
      <rationale>Most failed products result from teams answering the wrong questions early. Starbursting delays solution commitment until the question landscape is mapped, exposing assumptions that would otherwise remain invisible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Starbursting a new mobile app idea.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
WHO:   Who are the users? Who pays? Who maintains? Who are competitors?
WHAT:  What problem does it solve? What features are essential?
WHERE: Where will users use it? Where is data stored?
WHEN:  When do users need it? When to launch?
WHY:   Why would users choose us? Why now vs. later?
HOW:   How to monetize? How to acquire users? How to measure success?

Priority questions (top 10 to research first):
1. Why would users choose us over [existing alternatives]?
2. How do we acquire the first 100 users?
...
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/starbursting-worksheet.md">Starbursting worksheet with 5W+H capture and priority questions section</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Combining Methods">
    <rule>
      <statement>Combine SCAMPER + Mind Map when improving an existing product: create a mind map of the current product, then apply SCAMPER to each branch.</statement>
      <rationale>The mind map ensures SCAMPER covers all product dimensions (not just the obvious ones); SCAMPER ensures each dimension gets systematic transformation, not just free-form brainstorming.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Combine Starbursting + Brainstorming for new project planning: use Starbursting to generate the question list, then run a brainstorm session per priority question.</statement>
      <rationale>Brainstorming on the wrong question produces well-elaborated wrong answers. Starbursting first ensures the brainstorm is directed at the highest-leverage unknowns.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
