<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Buyer Interview Script for Freelancers Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Buyer Interview Script for Freelancers plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="hiring-trigger-must-be-elicited" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The script MUST elicit the buyer's last hiring trigger (event + date + decision-maker) within the first 15 minutes; scripts without trigger elicitation MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bob Moesta — Demand-Side Sales (2020)">Buyer hiring triggers are the leading indicator of when freelancers can land work; without this the interview is generic advice-fishing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="budget-authority-named-explicitly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The script MUST surface the named budget owner (or 'no budget'); declined-to-answer responses MUST be logged as unverified.</statement>
      <rationale source="Rob Fitzpatrick — The Mom Test">Unnamed budget authority leads to proposals routed to the wrong person; explicit elicitation prevents wasted-pitch cycles.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="vendor-preference-pattern-captured" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The script MUST capture vendor-preference patterns (referrals / RFP / inbound search) for the last 3 freelance hires; one-hire generalisations MUST be flagged.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — freelancer GTM research 2025">Single-hire data overweights an outlier engagement; 3-hire patterns reveal the channel reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="switching-pain-evidenced" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Switching-pain claims MUST be evidenced with concrete cost (dollars, hours, deals lost) or labelled hypothetical; uncosted pain MUST be re-asked.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford — Sales Pitch (2024)">Hypothetical switching-pain inflates willingness-to-pay; only costed pain predicts real switches.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-pitching-during-interview" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The freelancer MUST NOT pitch their service during the interview; pitch contamination MUST cause the transcript to be excluded from synthesis.</statement>
      <rationale source="Rob Fitzpatrick — The Mom Test">Pitching turns the interview into a sales call and corrupts the response distribution; the no-pitch rule is the protocol's integrity gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
