<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Indie Postmortem — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for writing an indie-hacker postmortem that produces real learning capture AND publishable content without becoming a victim narrative or a platitude piece.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-narrative-arc" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The public postmortem MUST follow a 4-part narrative arc: SETUP (what we set out to do + why), ATTEMPT (what we did, in chronological sequence), OUTCOME (what actually happened, with numbers), REFLECTION (what we learned + what we'd do differently). All four parts present; no skipping the unflattering ones.</statement>
      <rationale source="Narrative-structure research, indie-hacker shutdown-post corpus analysis">Posts that skip "setup" lack context; posts that skip "outcome" hide what actually happened; posts that skip "reflection" are war stories not learning. The arc is what makes the content shareable AND useful.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-metrics-numbers-not-feelings" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The OUTCOME section MUST include concrete numbers: visitors / signups / activations / MRR / churn / costs / time spent. Even when numbers are embarrassing ("0 paying customers after 9 months, $4.2k in costs"), they go in. Forbidden: "didn't get much traction" / "growth was slow" — vague replacements for numbers.</statement>
      <rationale source="Patio11 / Indie Hackers narrative analysis, content-virality research">Numbers are the credibility signal. Vague descriptions read as evasive. Posts with explicit numbers (even bad ones) outperform vague ones 3-5x in shares + reader response, AND they preserve the specific learning for future re-reading.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-learned-vs-would-do-different" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Two separate sections: WHAT WE LEARNED (insights / surprises / things we now believe), and WHAT WE'D DO DIFFERENTLY (specific actions we'd take with hindsight). These are NOT the same content — learnings are belief-updates, actions are decisions. Forbidden: collapsing both into "lessons" — produces platitudes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-journal research (Annie Duke), reflection-vs-action literature">"We learned that we should have validated more" mashes belief-update + action together and produces no operational learning. Splitting forces the belief-update ("user-research is the actual constraint") to be stated separately from the action ("we'd do 30 customer interviews before writing code").</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-opt-in-privacy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The post MUST have an explicit privacy section listing what is NOT shared and why (co-founder identities if relevant, customer names, exact financial figures if private). Forbidden: silent omission. Either share or explicitly opt out — readers should know what's left out and why.</statement>
      <rationale source="Indie-hacker community standards, privacy-norms research">Silent omission breeds suspicion ("what aren't they telling us?"). Explicit opt-out builds trust ("they're being honest about boundaries"). Privacy section also forces the writer to be deliberate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-blame-framing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reflection sections MUST stay in first-person OR system-as-subject framing: "I/we mis-judged X" or "the assumption that Y was wrong". Forbidden: blame of named individuals (co-founders, employees, investors), external scapegoats ("the market was wrong"), or victim narrative ("we never had a chance"). Same blameless principle as SRE retros, applied to founder reflection.</statement>
      <rationale source="Blameless-postmortem literature, founder-narrative analysis">Blame-narratives produce no learning AND damage relationships. Victim narratives produce sympathy but no actionable insight. First-person ownership produces both real reflection and content that other founders learn from.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical example">

    <example type="good" title="Indie postmortem with arc + numbers + clean reflection">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Title: "We built a Notion calendar plugin for 9 months. Here's what
happened."

SETUP (60 words):
  We thought Notion users wanted a powerful calendar plugin. We had
  used Notion daily for 3 years. We assumed our pain was widespread.

ATTEMPT (300 words):
  - Month 1-2: built MVP, posted to r/Notion (gained 80 beta users)
  - Month 3-4: shipped v1, launched on Product Hunt (412 upvotes,
    1,800 signups)
  - Month 5-7: tried to convert free -> paid ($9/mo); ~150 trials,
    11 paid conversions
  - Month 8-9: tried enterprise pivot ($49/mo); 3 demos, 0 closes

OUTCOME (numbers):
  - 4,200 total signups
  - 11 lifetime paying customers (max), 4 churned by Month 9
  - Peak MRR: $99. End-of-life MRR: $63.
  - Total spend: $7,300 (cloud + 3 contractor weeks)
  - Total time: ~900h (founder solo)

WHAT WE LEARNED:
  - Notion's API was rate-limited in a way that broke our core
    feature (auto-sync) for any user with &gt; 200 events.
  - Most "Notion power-users" used calendars elsewhere (Cron, Fantastical);
    they didn't WANT calendar functionality inside Notion.
  - "Daily use of Notion" was a misleading signal of demand for our
    specific feature.

WHAT WE'D DO DIFFERENTLY:
  - Run 20 customer interviews BEFORE writing code (we did 3)
  - Validate willingness-to-pay during interview, not via free-tier
  - Test rate-limit constraints with paid Notion API before betting
    the product on it

WHAT COMES NEXT:
  - Plugin is in maintenance mode for existing users
  - Open-sourced the code (link)
  - Next product: applying learnings to a different niche

PRIVACY:
  - Specific customer names omitted
  - Contractor's identity omitted at their request
  - Exact monthly burn-rate breakdown omitted (founder personal finance)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1-r5: full arc, concrete numbers, learned vs would-differently split, explicit privacy, first-person framing.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Vague + victim narrative">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"We tried to build a Notion plugin but the market wasn't ready.
Lots of users signed up but few paid. We learned that B2C SaaS
is hard. Maybe Notion's audience just doesn't value good tools.
We're moving on."

What's missing:
- Numbers (zero)
- Specific learnings (B2C SaaS is hard = platitude)
- Action-takeaways
- Privacy section
- Ownership (blames "the market", "Notion's audience")

Repair: enforce r2-r5. Add numbers. Split learnings from actions.
Reframe blame into self-attribution.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2, r3, r4, r5 violations — the standard vague-victim postmortem that adds no public value.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
