<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-landscape-mapping" title="Competitive Intelligence: Competitor Landscape Mapping">
  <summary>Four competitor types, 2x2 positioning matrix methodology, whitespace identification rules, and orchestrator prompt pattern for the landscape-mapping sub-methodology.</summary>

  <section title="Four Competitor Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every competitor list must include all four types: direct (same solution, same customer), indirect (different solution, same problem), substitute (alternative approach entirely), and potential (could enter market). Reject any list missing substitute and indirect rows.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams default to 3-5 obvious head-on competitors. Substitutes (spreadsheets, email, "do nothing") are the actual churn cause but rarely surface from a Google query — they must be explicitly prompted.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Project management tools: Direct (Asana, Monday, ClickUp), Indirect (Spreadsheets, Slack, Email), Substitute (pen and paper, meeting-based coordination), Potential (AI-native PM tools, no-code builders). Whitespace identified: AI-native PM for solopreneurs.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Project management tools: Direct only (Asana, Monday, ClickUp, Notion, Linear). Missing indirect, substitute, and potential types — misses the "do nothing" and "spreadsheet" competition that drives 60% of SMB status quo.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="2x2 Positioning Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-commit the two positioning axes with named exemplars for each pole before running the matrix. Do not let the agent choose axes that maximize visual separation after seeing the data.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc axis selection produces a map that looks clean but reflects LLM output aesthetics, not buyer decision criteria. Example of correct anchoring: x-axis "simple" = Notion-shaped vs "complex" = Salesforce-shaped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>After identifying whitespace, pair every candidate whitespace cell with a demand-validation step before acting on it. An empty cell is empty for a reason 80% of the time.</statement>
      <rationale>Whitespace may be empty because: no demand, technically hard, regulated, or unprofitable. A cell being empty is a hypothesis to test, not a greenlight.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Orchestrator Prompt Pattern">
    <p>Seed with category name. Produce 15-20 competitors covering all four types. For each, output a structured row with name, type, founded, funding_usd, team_size, pricing (model, entry_usd, url), positioning (≤140 chars), top_features, and evidence_urls (≥2, at least one third-party). Unknown fields → "unknown". No marketing copy verbatim.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require evidence_urls length ≥2 with at least one third-party source per competitor row. Reject any row with only the competitor's own marketing site as evidence.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs paraphrase the competitor's homepage tagline as "positioning" and call the matrix done. Third-party evidence (review site, community thread, screenshot) provides independent verification.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/landscape-table.md">Competitor landscape table template with all four types</reference>
</text>
