<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-feature-matrix" title="Competitive Intelligence: Feature Matrix and Gap Validation">
  <summary>Feature inventory process, Y/P/N + quality-score matrix schema, gap-validation critic with forced skip budget, and evidence-URL rule.</summary>

  <section title="Feature Matrix Schema">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each (feature, competitor) cell: capture status Y|P|N, quality 0-3, and evidence_url. "Y" requires an evidence_url; if no public proof exists, write "N" and add note "no public proof".</statement>
      <rationale>Evidence URL per cell (not per row) eliminates ~80% of the hallucination class. Without it, agents fill 100% of cells with Y even when the feature is undocumented.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a quality column (0-3) per cell in addition to Y/P/N. Quality 0 = feature exists but unusable; 3 = best-in-class implementation.</statement>
      <rationale>Y/N hides quality differences — "their search is checkbox-Yes but unusable" looks like parity without the quality column. Catching this stops false feature-parity conclusions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Allow "unknown" as a valid status for cells where no public proof exists. Require ≥80% known cells to ship the report; below that threshold, flag for primary research.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents fill cells even when no proof exists, defaulting to "N". An explicit "unknown" status distinguishes "we checked and found nothing" from "we didn't check".</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Gap Validation Critic">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a gap-validator critic after the feature matrix with a forced ≥40% skip budget. For each candidate gap, answer three questions: (1) Why does no competitor have it? (technical/regulatory/unprofitable/unaware). (2) Do customers actually want it? (review quotes, forum links, search volume). (3) Can we build it materially better? Verdict: pursue | investigate | skip. Default = skip when any answer is weak.</statement>
      <rationale>Default LLM tone is helpful — agents recommend every gap as an opportunity. The forced skip budget (≥40%) and adversarial three-question test counter pursuit-bias systematically.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair feature-gap identification with review-mining (G2/Reddit top-5 complaints per competitor) before validating. A gap nobody complains about is rarely a real gap.</statement>
      <rationale>Review-mining gives demand-side evidence for whether a gap matters to buyers; without it, gap-validation answers question (2) with "seems likely" rather than "50+ feature requests".</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain a kill-list of gaps marked "skip" with reasons. The orchestrator must not re-recommend a killed gap in future runs without new evidence.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a persistent kill-list, the same low-quality gaps get re-proposed every quarter and consume review cycles that should be spent on new discoveries.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Synonym Merging">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before filling the feature matrix, merge synonyms: "AI search", "semantic search", "natural-language search" all refer to the same capability. Run a synonym-merge pass before the matrix filler runs.</statement>
      <rationale>Without synonym merging, a single capability splits across 3-4 rows with inconsistent Y/N/P values, making the matrix impossible to aggregate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/feature-matrix.md">Feature matrix with Y/P/N, quality score, evidence_url, and gap-validation block</reference>
  <reference path="templates/competitor-signals.py">Multi-source per-competitor signal collector for evidence URL population</reference>
</text>
