<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="competitive-intelligence-methods Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for competitive-intelligence-methods as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating the competitive analysis as a standing document rather than a dated snapshot.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A feature matrix without a capture date is an undated fact claim that degrades silently. Readers cannot tell if they are looking at last week's reality or last year's.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Running the feature matrix without synonym merging across competitor feature names.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The same capability under different names produces multiple rows with conflicting Y/N/P values, making aggregation impossible and gap identification unreliable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating listed prices on enterprise tiers as ACVs for B2B pricing analysis.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"Talk to Sales" tiers are anchors, not ACVs — actual discounts can be 50-80% off list. Tag these rows with confidence: low, and cross-reference with G2 reviewer-reported pricing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Marketing-page parroting: LLM paraphrases the competitor's homepage tagline as "positioning" without checking third-party sources.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force evidence_urls length ≥2 with at least one third-party source. Homepage taglines are marketing copy, not observable positioning in buyer perception.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Numeric hallucination: funding totals, ARR, headcount fabricated without source_url.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Reject any numeric field without source_url. "Unknown" is the correct output when API access is absent, not a plausible invention.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Optimistic gap recommendations: LLM default helpful tone recommends every gap as an opportunity without adversarial review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The gap-validator critic with a forced skip budget ≥40% is non-negotiable. Without it, the gap list becomes a feature-bloat backlog.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Token blowup from passing full G2 review HTML to the matrix filler.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Never paste full review HTML into the matrix-filler. The review-miner must distill to top-5 complaints per competitor first, then pass the distillation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Human-in-the-loop checkpoint missing: gap list becomes spec input without founder review of the kill-list rationale.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents under-skip (helpful bias), founders over-skip (loss aversion) — the diff between their lists is the real shortlist. Skip the checkpoint and you get either feature bloat or missed opportunities.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
