<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules-and-antipatterns" title="Competitive Intelligence: Rules and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Hard rules for evidence discipline, snapshot diffing, and agent-specific failure modes with concrete mitigations.</summary>

  <section title="Evidence Discipline Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Date every competitive report as competitive-analysis-YYYY-MM-DD.md. Store in version control so quarterly re-runs produce diffable deltas. The deltas are the actual decision input, not the absolute values.</statement>
      <rationale>A one-time matrix decays in 3-6 months; without a re-run cadence the analysis becomes a stale anchor that biases decisions long after market conditions changed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Visualping the top-5 competitor pricing pages weekly. A weekly diff on pricing pages provides 80% of the "competitive monitoring" value for minimal cost.</statement>
      <rationale>Pricing changes are the highest-severity competitive event; daily manual checking is impractical, while a weekly automated diff catches changes within the relevant decision window.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never act on a whitespace cell found in the current session. Log it, validate against demand signals (review mining or interview transcripts), decide in the next run.</statement>
      <rationale>A 2-week sanity gap prevents impulsive roadmap additions based on a single session's gap analysis that may be incomplete or based on missing evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Static-Snapshot Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating the competitive analysis as a standing document rather than a dated snapshot.</description>
      <reason>A feature matrix without a capture date is an undated fact claim that degrades silently. Readers cannot tell if they are looking at last week's reality or last year's.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running the feature matrix without synonym merging across competitor feature names.</description>
      <reason>The same capability under different names produces multiple rows with conflicting Y/N values, making aggregation impossible and gap identification unreliable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating listed prices on enterprise tiers as ACVs for B2B pricing analysis.</description>
      <reason>"Talk to Sales" tiers are anchors, not ACVs — actual discounts can be 50-80% off list. Tag these rows with confidence: low, and cross-reference with G2 reviewer-reported pricing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Marketing-page parroting: LLM paraphrases the competitor's homepage tagline as "positioning" without checking third-party sources.</description>
      <reason>Force evidence_urls length ≥2 with at least one third-party source. Homepage taglines are marketing copy, not observable positioning in buyer perception.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Numeric hallucination: funding totals, ARR, headcount fabricated without source_url.</description>
      <reason>Reject any numeric field without source_url. "Unknown" is the correct output when API access is absent, not a plausible invention.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Optimistic gap recommendations: LLM default helpful tone recommends every gap as an opportunity without adversarial review.</description>
      <reason>The gap-validator critic with a forced skip budget ≥40% is non-negotiable. Without it, the gap list becomes a feature-bloat backlog.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Token blowup from passing full G2 review HTML to the matrix filler.</description>
      <reason>Never paste full review HTML into the matrix-filler. The review-miner must distill to top-5 complaints per competitor first, then pass the distillation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Human-in-the-loop checkpoint missing: gap list becomes spec input without founder review of the kill-list rationale.</description>
      <reason>Agents under-skip (helpful bias), founders over-skip (loss aversion) — the diff between their lists is the real shortlist. Skip the checkpoint and you get either feature bloat or missed opportunities.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
