<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Distribution First Ideation Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Distribution First Ideation application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="named-channel-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision-record MUST name the distribution channel (newsletter URL, Reddit subreddit, Twitter handle, etc.) with current reach metric. &apos;Word of mouth&apos; fails the test.</statement>
      <rationale source="Distribution-first research">Distribution-first research — anchors Distribution First Ideation rule `named-channel-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="smoke-page-traffic-target" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Smoke page MUST hit a named traffic target within 14 days (default: ≥500 visitors). Missing the target = channel does not have the implied reach for this idea.</statement>
      <rationale source="Smoke-page validation">Smoke-page validation — anchors Distribution First Ideation rule `smoke-page-traffic-target`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="waitlist-conversion-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Waitlist conversion MUST be ≥10% of smoke-page traffic. Below = audience interest is not strong enough; route to a different idea.</statement>
      <rationale source="Conversion-rate research">Conversion-rate research — anchors Distribution First Ideation rule `waitlist-conversion-floor`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kill-on-negative-signal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If smoke-page traffic OR waitlist conversion misses target, the idea MUST be killed (or paused with revisit date). Sunk-cost continuation rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Falsifiability discipline">Falsifiability discipline — anchors Distribution First Ideation rule `kill-on-negative-signal`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="decision-record-go-no-go" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output is a single decision-record per idea with channel + smoke URL + traffic + conversion + verdict. Verbal-only decisions forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-record practice">Decision-record practice — anchors Distribution First Ideation rule `decision-record-go-no-go`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
