<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="funnel-tactics-basics Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for funnel-tactics-basics. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run these six quick-win tactics first — they are high-impact, low-effort, and have the strongest benchmark evidence. Always validate on mobile and desktop separately; a win on desktop can be a loss on mobile.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Quick wins build organizational confidence in CRO programs and fund investment in larger experiments. Skipping directly to complex tests wastes momentum.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every tactic in the test backlog must be pinned to: (1) a measurable stage event, (2) a current baseline rate, and (3) a target lift band. Reject any tactic without all three.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">"Improve copy" without a conversion metric and baseline is not a testable hypothesis. Unpinned tactics produce inconclusive tests and wasted sprint capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always test and report tactics on mobile and desktop segments separately. Never report a combined conversion rate when segments represent materially different surfaces.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A form-field reduction that lifts desktop by 20% can drop mobile by 10% if the mobile layout does not adapt. Combined metrics mask the mobile regression.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap concurrent A/B tests on the same page to one. Do not start the next test until the current one has reached statistical significance (95% confidence, minimum sample size met).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Running two tests on the same page at the same time prevents isolating the effect of either change. This is the "testing too many things" error that inflates false-positive rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Urgency and scarcity tactics (countdown timers, low-stock messages) must reflect real constraints. Never generate fake countdown timers or inventory counts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Fake urgency is deceptive, creates legal and brand risk, and undermines trust when users discover the timer resets on refresh.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
