<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-stage-tactics" title="Stage-Indexed Tactics and Quick Wins">
  <summary>Conversion tactics organized by funnel stage (ToF, MoF, BoF) with aggregate lift bands, plus six high-impact quick wins with concrete benchmarks.</summary>

  <section title="Top of Funnel (Awareness)">
    <p>Goal: get users to engage with your product or content. Levers: headline clarity, page speed, ad targeting precision, social proof, value proposition specificity.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Clearer headlines (one concrete benefit, not feature list): +10-30% engagement.</item>
      <item>Page load under 3 seconds: +5-20% conversion (each second after 2s costs ~7%).</item>
      <item>Better ad targeting (narrow audience, specific message): +15-40% qualified traffic.</item>
      <item>Social proof above fold (user count, logos, testimonials): +5-15% trust signal.</item>
      <item>Value prop clarity (what, for whom, why different): +10-25% bounce reduction.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Middle of Funnel (Consideration)">
    <p>Goal: get users to take action (signup, demo, trial). Levers: form field count, progress indicators, trust badges, CTA design, friction removal.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Reduce form fields to minimum required: +10-25% completion (B2B SaaS typical; B2C lead gen can reach +100%).</item>
      <item>Add progress indicators for multi-step flows: +5-15% completion.</item>
      <item>Trust badges (security, certifications, guarantees) near CTA: +8-18% conversion.</item>
      <item>Action-oriented CTA in high-contrast color: +5-20% click rate.</item>
      <item>Remove friction (no credit card required, guest checkout): +15-40% signup rate.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Bottom of Funnel (Conversion)">
    <p>Goal: complete purchase or activation. Levers: guest checkout, payment method variety, error clarity, urgency (must be honest), risk reversal.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Guest checkout (no forced account creation): +15-30% checkout completion.</item>
      <item>Multiple payment options (card, Apple Pay, PayPal): +10-20% checkout completion.</item>
      <item>Clear, specific error messages that tell users exactly how to fix the issue: +5-15% form recovery.</item>
      <item>Money-back guarantee visible at decision point: +8-15% conversion.</item>
      <item>Exit-intent popups (desktop only — no mouse-leave on mobile): +5-12% recovery.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Six Quick Wins">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run these six quick-win tactics first — they are high-impact, low-effort, and have the strongest benchmark evidence. Always validate on mobile and desktop separately; a win on desktop can be a loss on mobile.</statement>
      <rationale>Quick wins build organizational confidence in CRO programs and fund investment in larger experiments. Skipping directly to complex tests wastes momentum.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Form fields: remove all non-essential fields; gather additional info after signup via progressive profiling. B2B target: 3 fields or fewer for initial signup.</item>
      <item>Progress bar: add step indicator to any multi-step process. +15% completion rate.</item>
      <item>Button contrast: if CTA is not in top-3 clicked elements on heatmap, increase contrast. High-contrast green/orange: +50% click rate vs low-contrast gray.</item>
      <item>Social proof placement: near CTA (+15% conversion) and above fold (+20% trust). User count + logos + 1 testimonial with photo and name is the minimum viable set.</item>
      <item>Page speed: target LCP under 2s. Each second over 2s costs 7% conversion. Quick fixes: WebP images, lazy load, CDN, minify CSS/JS.</item>
      <item>Copy simplification: replace jargon with one concrete outcome statement. "Ship projects faster with AI planning" outperforms "enterprise-grade, cloud-native workflow optimization solution".</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
