<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-checklists-and-rules" title="Stage Checklists, ICE Rules, and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Four stage-specific optimization checklists, mandatory ICE ranking, mobile segmentation rule, statistical significance enforcement, and antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Stage Checklists">
    <p>Landing page checklist: clear headline (1 benefit, under 10 words); subheadline names target audience; hero image/video shows product in use; social proof above fold; single primary CTA; mobile responsive; loads under 3 seconds.</p>
    <p>Signup form checklist: 3 or fewer fields for initial signup; value proposition visible near form; social login options (Google, GitHub); progress indicator if multi-step; clear error messages; "what happens next" explanation.</p>
    <p>Checkout checklist: guest checkout available; all costs shown upfront (no surprise fees); multiple payment methods; security badges visible; easy to edit cart; clear refund policy; auto-save progress.</p>
    <p>Onboarding checklist: welcome with clear single next step; 3 or fewer onboarding screens; skip option always available; core value demonstrated immediately; contextual tips triggered by actions (not upfront tutorial); progress saved automatically.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Mandatory Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every tactic in the test backlog must be pinned to: (1) a measurable stage event, (2) a current baseline rate, and (3) a target lift band. Reject any tactic without all three.</statement>
      <rationale>"Improve copy" without a conversion metric and baseline is not a testable hypothesis. Unpinned tactics produce inconclusive tests and wasted sprint capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always test and report tactics on mobile and desktop segments separately. Never report a combined conversion rate when segments represent materially different surfaces.</statement>
      <rationale>A form-field reduction that lifts desktop by 20% can drop mobile by 10% if the mobile layout does not adapt. Combined metrics mask the mobile regression.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap concurrent A/B tests on the same page to one. Do not start the next test until the current one has reached statistical significance (95% confidence, minimum sample size met).</statement>
      <rationale>Running two tests on the same page at the same time prevents isolating the effect of either change. This is the "testing too many things" error that inflates false-positive rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Urgency and scarcity tactics (countdown timers, low-stock messages) must reflect real constraints. Never generate fake countdown timers or inventory counts.</statement>
      <rationale>Fake urgency is deceptive, creates legal and brand risk, and undermines trust when users discover the timer resets on refresh.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Optimizing small funnel leaks before fixing the largest drop-off stage.</description>
      <reason>Fixing a 5% checkout drop-off while a 50% bounce rate on the landing page exists wastes all effort — the checkout improvement cannot compound when most users never reach checkout.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Recommending "remove all form fields" without a recovery plan for the trimmed fields.</description>
      <reason>Progressive profiling — gathering removed fields after signup via in-app prompts — must be specified alongside any field-reduction recommendation or the data is permanently lost.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-publishing landing page variants without experiment flag and human review.</description>
      <reason>Direct production changes bypass the A/B test framework, contaminate existing tests, and prevent clean rollback if the change causes a regression.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/form-audit.py">Playwright signup form auditor: field count, social login, CTA, load time</reference>
</text>
