<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="recognition-over-recall">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #6: minimize memory via visible options, context, and recognition aids. Recognition faster and more accurate than recall. Apply when auditing UIs.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>recognition</tag>
      <tag>recall</tag>
      <tag>usability-heuristics</tag>
      <tag>cognitive-load</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Recognition Rather Than Recall</title>

    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #6: minimize memory load by making options, actions, and context visible rather than requiring users to remember them. Users should recognize what to do from visible cues rather than recall it from memory. Apply when auditing UIs, reviewing component specs, or designing multi-step flows.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Recognition requires seeing and choosing; recall requires remembering without a cue. Recognition is faster, more accurate, and available to all user populations including occasional users, older users, and users with cognitive disabilities. Every recall burden adds cognitive load that increases errors, slows task completion, and reduces adoption.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Auditing an existing UI for hidden options, icon-only toolbars, or multi-step flows with no context carry-over.</item>
        <item>Reviewing wireframes or component specs for places where users must remember prior screen content.</item>
        <item>Designing search, navigation, or command interfaces — autocomplete and recents are high-ROI here.</item>
        <item>Reviewing AI chat or developer-tool UIs for missing help text, suggestions, or history.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Power-user tools where recall is intentional (vim, SQL terminals, CAD shortcuts) — violating recall norms breaks expert efficiency.</item>
        <item>Micro-optimization on a product not past alpha — this heuristic is for refining, not architecting.</item>
        <item>When the interface is already fully recognition-based and validated — audit adds no value.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="recognition-vs-recall">
      <p>Recognition: user sees options and chooses. Recall: user must remember without a cue. Recognition is always faster, more accurate, and more accessible across user populations.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Prefer recognition-based UI patterns over recall-based ones whenever design permits.</statement>
        <rationale>Recall requires active memory retrieval, which fails under time pressure, cognitive load, infrequent use, and stress — all common in real product contexts. Recognition merely requires matching a visible stimulus to memory, which is far more reliable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <p>Menu selection (recognition) vs. command-line with syntax recall. Autocomplete (recognition) vs. blank search field (recall).</p>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="four-design-principles">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Make options visible: show common actions, do not hide them in menus or right-click contexts.</statement>
        <rationale>Hidden options require users to remember they exist and know where to look — double recall burden.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Provide context: keep relevant information visible across multi-step tasks.</statement>
        <rationale>When context disappears between steps, users must remember prior selections — a cross-screen recall burden that causes errors and backtracking.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use recognition aids: icons paired with text labels, thumbnails for files, previews for documents.</statement>
        <rationale>Icons alone require users to memorize icon meanings. Pairing with text labels converts recall to recognition at minimal space cost.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Support retrieval: implement recent items, search with autocomplete, and frequently-used-item lists.</statement>
        <rationale>Recent items surface what the user has already interacted with — zero recall required. Autocomplete shows candidates matching partial input, reducing the recall burden to a fragment.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="accessibility-connection">
      <p>Recognition-based design disproportionately benefits: users with cognitive disabilities, older users, occasional users, users under stress or time pressure, and mobile users with divided attention. It is not a nice-to-have — it is a baseline accessibility requirement.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="visible-options">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Expose primary actions in a visible toolbar or navigation; reserve menus for secondary and infrequent actions.</statement>
        <rationale>Hidden menus require users to remember the menu exists and what it contains — double recall burden. Visible toolbars convert both to recognition.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Visible tabs for main sections of an app">
        <p>Rather than a hamburger menu that hides all navigation behind a tap.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="All actions behind right-click context menu">
        <p>Users must remember right-click exists and recall what actions are available.</p>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="contextual-information">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>In multi-step flows, show a persistent summary of all prior selections visible alongside the current step.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a context panel, users must remember what they entered on previous screens. A sidebar showing prior selections eliminates the most common cross-screen recall failure.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Checkout step 3 shows context sidebar">
        <p>Selected items, shipping address entered on step 1, and payment method selected on step 2 — all visible in a sidebar summary.</p>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="labels-and-tooltips">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pair every icon with a text label; use tooltips only in space-constrained areas where label cannot be shown inline.</statement>
        <rationale>Icon-only interfaces require users to memorize icon meanings. Text labels eliminate this entirely. Tooltips are acceptable fallback when screen space prevents inline labels.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep tooltips at 7 words or fewer; show them on hover with a 300ms delay to avoid noise.</statement>
        <rationale>Long tooltips that appear instantly become visual noise that users learn to ignore. Short, delayed tooltips are read when needed and dismissed otherwise.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="autocomplete-and-recent-items">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Add autocomplete to every search and command input; show at least 5 recent items immediately on focus.</statement>
        <rationale>Autocomplete is the single highest-ROI recognition aid. Search with suggestions converts blank-field recall to candidate recognition. Recent items list surfaces past actions without requiring memory retrieval.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Recent items must update immediately after use; a stale list is worse than no list.</statement>
        <rationale>A stale list teaches users the feature is unreliable, causing them to stop using it. Immediate update maintains trust and utility.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="progressive-disclosure">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Show essential options always; reveal advanced options on demand via expansion rather than hiding by default in menus users must discover.</statement>
        <rationale>Progressive disclosure reduces visual noise while keeping options discoverable through visible "More options" or "Advanced" controls — not hidden menus users must know to look for.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="good-examples">
      <example type="good" title="Google Search">
        <p>Recent searches shown on focus, autocomplete suggestions, "Did you mean" corrections, related searches. All are recognition aids that eliminate recall of prior queries.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="VS Code Command Palette">
        <p>Fuzzy search for commands, recent files shown, icons and labels in menus. Turns command recall into command recognition.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Spotify">
        <p>Album art thumbnails, recently played prominent on home screen, visual playlists. Users recognize what they want to play; they do not recall album names.</p>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="bad-examples">
      <example type="bad" title="Product code recall">
        <p>Enter product code: ___ — user must recall an arbitrary alphanumeric code. Better: product picker with images and names. Recognition replaces recall entirely.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Multi-step checkout without context">
        <p>Prior address entered on step 1 is not visible on step 3. User must recall what they typed. Better: summary sidebar showing all prior selections.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Unlabeled icon toolbar">
        <p>Toolbar with 12 icons and no labels. Users must memorize what each icon means. Better: icon + text label for all actions, tooltip fallback for space-constrained areas.</p>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Icon-only toolbars where users must memorize icon meanings.</description>
        <reason>Icons without labels require recall of meaning. Even "universal" icons (save floppy disk, hamburger menu) are not universally recognized by all user populations.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Multi-step forms with no progress summary of prior selections.</description>
        <reason>Cross-screen recall burden is the most common form of heuristic #6 violation and is invisible in static design reviews — requires prototype testing to detect.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A Claude agent receives a list of UI screens (as descriptions, wireframe annotations, or component specs) and applies the Recognition Audit template to each screen: identifying recall demands (what must users remember?), hidden options, icon-only elements, and missing recent-item affordances. The agent outputs a structured findings list with severity and a specific recognition alternative for each recall burden found. This audit feeds directly into a heuristic evaluation report or a design system backlog.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent flags all icon-only elements including universally understood icons (magnifying glass for search, X for close).</description>
        <reason>Provide agent a list of safe icon exceptions before running audit. Magnifying glass and X are recognized across all user populations and do not need labels.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent audits static wireframes and misses cross-screen recall failures.</description>
        <reason>Information visible on screen A but gone on screen B is a dynamic property. Note this limitation explicitly in audit output; require prototype testing to validate cross-screen context.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-limitations">
      <p>Recognition aids (menus, autocomplete, thumbnails) consume screen real estate — agents auditing for recall will sometimes recommend additions that create visual clutter. Fully enumerated recognition UIs (giant dropdowns, mega menus) can paradoxically increase cognitive load via choice overload; the heuristic has a ceiling. Agents reviewing static screenshots cannot detect the most common recall failure: information that was visible on screen A but disappears on screen B. "Context maintained across multi-step tasks" is a dynamic property requiring prototype or live product to evaluate; cannot be audited from specs alone.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>axe-cli: Accessibility audit that surfaces missing labels (icon-only, unlabeled inputs) (npm i -g axe-cli, github.com/dequelabs/axe-cli). pa11y: Automated accessibility scan — catches missing aria-label on icon buttons (npm i -g pa11y, pa11y.org). Lighthouse CLI: Audit for missing autocomplete attributes on form fields (npm i -g lighthouse, developers.google.com/web/tools/lighthouse).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <p>Figma (Plugin API): Read layer names and component properties to detect icon-only instances. Storybook (OSS): Enforce label/tooltip story variants as part of component review. FullStory / Hotjar (SaaS): Session replay data shows where users pause, search, or use help — indirect recall signal. Dovetail (SaaS): Tag usability findings from sessions with "recall burden" label for pattern tracking.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Apply the heuristic per user segment: novice users need recognition aids everywhere; experts can tolerate more recall in power-user flows, but even then tooltips on shortcuts cost nothing. Autocomplete on search and command inputs is the single highest-ROI recognition aid — prioritize this over visual thumbnails. For multi-step forms: a persistent summary sidebar showing all previous answers eliminates the most common cross-screen recall burden. Recent-items lists should show at least 5 entries and update immediately after use — a stale list is worse than no list. When adding tooltips as a recall aid, keep them at 7 words and show them on hover with a 300ms delay to avoid noise.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/recognition-audit.md" purpose="Audit table: task, recall required, recognition alternative, priority"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-audit.txt" purpose="LLM prompt for auditing a screen description against this heuristic"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/recognition-and-recall/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/books/design-everyday-things-revised/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/human-memory"/>
      <link href="https://m3.material.io/foundations/navigation"/>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/navigation"/>
      <ref slug="ux-ui-designer"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
