<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-register" title="Stakeholder Register: Schema, Evidence, Hidden Stakeholders">
  <summary>Rules for building and maintaining a stakeholder register with mandatory evidence for attitude assertions and a hidden-stakeholder review step.</summary>

  <section title="Register Schema">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store the register in YAML in git (stakeholders/register.yaml), not in a wiki or spreadsheet. Git diffs become the engagement history; CODEOWNERS gates sign-off on attitude changes.</statement>
      <rationale>Wikis erase history; spreadsheets create competing versions. Git-backed YAML makes every change auditable with timestamp and author.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Required fields per stakeholder: id, name, category (Sponsor/User/Customer/Team/Regulator/Supplier/Influencer), power (H/M/L), interest (H/M/L), attitude (+/0/-/unknown), quadrant, evidence list, cadence, channel, owner, last_engaged date.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing fields create ambiguity about who manages the relationship and what the current engagement state is.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Evidence and Attitude Policy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every attitude assertion must have at least one evidence entry (meeting quote, transcript line, ticket link, survey response). No evidence means attitude defaults to "unknown", not "supportive".</statement>
      <rationale>Agents and humans both have politeness bias — they label stakeholders as "supportive" without behavioural evidence. Unsupported optimistic classification causes under-attention to real resistors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Triangulate self-reported attitude with at least one behavioural signal: meeting attendance rate, response time to requests, escalation count, survey delta. Single-source attitude is unreliable.</statement>
      <rationale>People say "supportive" in workshops and undermine in private. Cross-referencing behaviour reduces misclassification.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Hidden Stakeholder Review">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a mandatory "hidden stakeholder" review at project kickoff: check legal, infosec, procurement, works council/union, accessibility, downstream consumers, FinOps, and any community/NGO affected parties.</statement>
      <rationale>These categories are systematically missed when the register is seeded from the org chart alone. Each has blocked or derailed projects when discovered late.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never invent stakeholder names or roles; seed from a real org chart export or directory. Any name not in the source list must be flagged "suggested_to_verify" and confirmed by the PM.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents invent plausible-sounding personas when the register is built without a grounding source. Invented stakeholders create phantom engagement and miss real ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Privacy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the stakeholder register as PII under GDPR Art. 9 if attitude fields imply political opinion or health status. Never send the full register to a third-party model without a Data Processing Agreement.</statement>
      <rationale>Attitude, role sensitivity, and relationship context are personal data. GDPR and equivalent regulations require a legal basis for processing and restrict third-party transfer.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
