<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-engagement" title="Engagement Strategy: Quadrants, Cadence, Refresh, Antipatterns">
  <summary>Quadrant-based engagement rules, default cadence by power/interest combination, mandatory refresh triggers, and stakeholder engagement antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Quadrant Engagement Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default cadence by quadrant: High-High (Manage Closely) → weekly 1:1; High-Low (Keep Satisfied) → biweekly summary; Low-High (Keep Informed) → monthly digest; Low-Low (Monitor) → release notes only. Override only with explicit rationale documented in the register.</statement>
      <rationale>Default cadences are calibrated to stakeholder attention tolerance by quadrant. Ad-hoc cadences without rationale produce either stakeholder fatigue or gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>"Manage Closely" is not one strategy — a CFO and a regulator require different tone, content, and channel even if both are High-High. Document per-stakeholder overrides in the register.</statement>
      <rationale>Uniform high-touch engagement for all Manage Closely stakeholders conflates power with content needs. Regulators require compliance evidence; CFOs require financial narrative.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Refresh Triggers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Refresh the register quarterly at minimum, monthly in volatile contexts (post-merger, leadership change, regulator activity). An unrefreshed register older than 6 weeks is incorrect, not just stale.</statement>
      <rationale>Power and interest change with project phase and org events. A 3-month-old classification of a stakeholder who has since been promoted or reassigned produces misdirected engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap agent edits to 5 stakeholders per run and require human review of the diff before applying. Bulk reclassification erases nuance and creates liability if attitude fields contain sensitive signals.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated bulk updates bypass the validation that human judgment provides on sensitive relationship data.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Calendar Audit">
    <rule>
      <statement>If any stakeholder appears in more than 3 recurring weekly meetings, consolidate or remove one. Stakeholder fatigue erodes goodwill and reduces meeting attendance — the opposite of engagement.</statement>
      <rationale>Well-meant high-touch engagement burns goodwill if asks exceed tolerance. Engagement frequency must be calibrated to the stakeholder's actual capacity to absorb.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-sending communications to executives, regulators, or board members without PM approval.</description>
      <reason>These stakeholders are high-stakes; an error in an automated message to an executive or regulator has disproportionate reputation and legal consequences. Agent drafts; PM or sponsor approves.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Conflating stakeholder (real named person with decision power) with persona (synthesised archetype).</description>
      <reason>Stakeholders require personalised engagement plans; personas are for UX design. Mixing them produces engagement plans that address a fictional composite rather than real decision-makers.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying Western-norm engagement defaults to high-context cultures (JP, KR, parts of EU/MEA).</description>
      <reason>Influence routes through indirect networks in high-context cultures; a direct weekly 1:1 invitation to a Japanese executive may be perceived as disrespectful. Add cultural_context field and adjust approach.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
