<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="interface-analysis Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for interface-analysis. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Classify every identified connection point into one of four types before specifying it; mixed-type specifications produce documents with missing fields and incomplete error handling.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each type has a distinct attribute set (protocol for system interfaces, device specifics for hardware interfaces, flow/trigger for communication interfaces); misclassification causes incomplete specifications discovered during integration testing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Complete the interface questions checklist for every interface: who/what is on each end, what data is exchanged, what format, how triggered, frequency, volume, failure modes, error handling, security, and ownership.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Interface specifications with missing error handling, missing volume estimates, or missing security requirements are the most common cause of integration failures discovered during performance testing or production incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>**Pass 1 — Discovery subagent** ingests CMDB exports, API gateway access logs, iPaaS (Workato/Boomi/MuleSoft) catalogues, and produces a raw inventory. Do NOT invent interfaces not present in inputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The discovery pass must be conservative; inventing interfaces creates phantom entries the BA must later explain and removes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>**Pass 2 — BA subagent** classifies each interface by business capability, criticality (1–4), data sensitivity (public/internal/confidential/restricted), and ownership; emits the integration landscape register. Capabilities must come from a closed list (the org's capability map).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Capability mapping is a business judgment, not a technical metric; constraining to an approved capability list prevents hallucinated capabilities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>**Pass 3 — Governance subagent** diffs the register against the enterprise contract standard (naming, versioning, auth, SLA fields) and opens findings. Cite the standard line number for every finding.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Structured governance rules (encoded as Spectral rules or similar) are more enforceable than written PDFs alone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>**Pass 4 — Human-in-the-loop review** with architecture and security before publication. Mandatory sign-offs: (1) capability-to-system mapping by Architecture, (2) sensitivity classification by Data Office, (3) tier-1 criticality by business owner, (4) deprecation decisions before retirement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These judgments involve business stakeholders and cannot be automated; mandatory sign-off creates accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>**Quarterly audit pass**: re-pull CMDB + iPaaS feeds, diff against committed register, open SDD tasks for new/retired interfaces. Any interface in the register without traffic in the gateway for 90 days → candidate for retirement; any traffic without a register entry → governance violation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Active-traffic reality checks keep the register honest and surface shadow IT.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each row in the landscape register represents one logical interface (source-target pair) with a stable IF-ID. Single source of truth per interface: the OpenAPI/AsyncAPI/Protobuf file in the owning team's repo. The register only references it (link + commit hash), never copies field-level details.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Duplicating interface specs across the register and per-interface documents creates drift; one source of truth is enforceable via CI checks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capability-first IDs: tie every interface to a business capability code (`CAP-FIN-AR-01`) so retirement decisions are made at capability level, not by team.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">When a business capability retires (e.g., manual expense reports → automated), all its interfaces are retirement candidates; capability-first IDs make this traceability explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Criticality tiers drive policy: tier-1 interfaces require contract tests, breaking-change review, and 24/7 monitoring; tier-4 needs only the register row.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Criticality is a business judgment about impact; different tiers justify different governance overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Data sensitivity inherited from data catalogue: do not re-classify at interface level; pull from Purview/Collibra/Atlan. If unknown, emit `unknown` and surface for human review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Field-level truth lives in the data catalogue; interface-level classification is a lossy aggregate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deprecation calendar: every interface has a `valid-until` date or "evergreen"; agents scan quarterly and warn on stale ones.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Interfaces without planned retirement are governance debt; date-stamping them surfaces the decision for renewal or retirement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Standards as code: encode the API contract standard as Spectral rules and run them in every team's CI; written PDFs alone are ignored.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">CI gates enforce compliance on every change; governance boards review exceptions only. This scales to polyglot portfolios.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Two views, one register: capability view for executives (heatmap), technical view for engineers (sequence + auth); generate both from the same register.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single register, multiple views prevents stakeholder groups from seeing inconsistent state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Federated governance over central: a small standards team curates rules; product teams own their interfaces; quarterly review board handles exceptions only.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Centralized governance becomes a bottleneck; federated with clear escalation paths scales to large portfolios.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r16" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plain-text artefacts: register in Markdown/CSV in Git, not in a proprietary EA tool only — agents need to read and diff.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Plain text in Git enables CI checks, diff reviews, and automated governance; proprietary tools are agent-unfriendly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
