<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-interface-types" title="Interface Analysis: Types, Procedure, and Specification">
  <summary>Four interface types, five-step analysis procedure, data element specification, behavior definition, and validation checklist.</summary>

  <section title="Interface Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every identified connection point into one of four types before specifying it; mixed-type specifications produce documents with missing fields and incomplete error handling.</statement>
      <rationale>Each type has a distinct attribute set (protocol for system interfaces, device specifics for hardware interfaces, flow/trigger for communication interfaces); misclassification causes incomplete specifications discovered during integration testing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>User interface — human interaction points: screens, reports, forms, dashboards.</item>
      <item>System interface — system-to-system connections: REST/SOAP APIs, file transfers, database connections, message queues.</item>
      <item>Hardware interface — physical device connections: scanners, printers, sensors, POS terminals.</item>
      <item>Communication interface — data exchange protocols: HTTP, SFTP, EDI X12, HL7, SWIFT, EDIFACT, fixed-width files.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-Step Analysis Procedure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Complete the interface questions checklist for every interface: who/what is on each end, what data is exchanged, what format, how triggered, frequency, volume, failure modes, error handling, security, and ownership.</statement>
      <rationale>Interface specifications with missing error handling, missing volume estimates, or missing security requirements are the most common cause of integration failures discovered during performance testing or production incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Identify: list all connection points by asking what systems connect, what data flows in/out, who are the users, what devices are involved, what external parties interact.</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Document: capture all attributes per interface (name, type, direction, source/target, data, format, protocol, frequency, volume, security, error handling).</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Define data elements: specify each field (element name, type, required flag, validation rules, description).</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Specify behaviors: normal flow, error scenarios, retry logic, timeout handling, idempotency requirements.</item>
      <item>Step 5 — Validate with stakeholders: technical teams of connected systems, users for UI interfaces, operations for monitoring, security for access control.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/interface-specification.md">Per-interface specification template covering all attributes</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Specifying only the happy-path flow without error scenarios.</description>
      <reason>Real integrations fail; undocumented error handling produces ad-hoc implementation decisions at development time that are inconsistent across interfaces and invisible to operations teams.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Omitting volume and frequency estimates from the interface specification.</description>
      <reason>Systems cannot handle unexpected load; volume underestimates are the leading cause of production performance failures at integration points.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Specifying authentication and security as "TBD" or "standard security".</description>
      <reason>Security requirements left unspecified default to the developer's judgment, producing inconsistent auth mechanisms, missing encryption, and audit failures.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Interface versioning not specified at initial design time.</description>
      <reason>Unversioned interfaces break downstream consumers on every change with no migration path; versioning strategy must be decided before the interface is published.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
