<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="interface-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for interface-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Specifying only the happy-path flow without error scenarios.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Real integrations fail; undocumented error handling produces ad-hoc implementation decisions at development time that are inconsistent across interfaces and invisible to operations teams.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Omitting volume and frequency estimates from the interface specification.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Systems cannot handle unexpected load; volume underestimates are the leading cause of production performance failures at integration points.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Specifying authentication and security as "TBD" or "standard security".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Security requirements left unspecified default to the developer's judgment, producing inconsistent auth mechanisms, missing encryption, and audit failures.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Interface versioning not specified at initial design time.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unversioned interfaces break downstream consumers on every change with no migration path; versioning strategy must be decided before the interface is published.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Inventory rot: an interface register collected by spreadsheet ages within one quarter; without an automated feed (CMDB + API gateway logs + iPaaS catalogue) the doc becomes a liability.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Automate the discovery pass quarterly; diff against the committed register to surface drift. Make the audit part of the SDD cycle.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Shadow integrations (Zapier, Make, manual SFTP scripts on someone's laptop, Excel macros pulling from SharePoint) never make it onto the BA's diagram and cause every audit finding.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Explicitly task a separate discovery pass against email/Slack/Workato/Power Automate logs to surface candidates. Make shadow IT discovery a sub-task.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Capability-to-system mapping disagrees across Architecture, Finance, and IT — the BA inherits the political fight, not just the modelling task.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Get architecture sign-off on the capability-to-system map before launching the landscape discovery. Store the mapping as a separate approved artifact.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Governance theatre: contract review boards approve in hours what teams need to ship in minutes; ungoverned channels appear (slack DMs, untracked dev keys).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Encode governance rules in CI (Spectral, oasdiff) so teams get instant feedback; escalate only genuine exceptions to a review board.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>PII/data-classification is best-guessed at landscape level; field-level truth lives in the per-interface spec, so the landscape view is structurally lossy.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pull sensitivity classification from the data catalogue (Purview/Collibra/Atlan), not from interface specs. Mark unknowns explicitly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM agents over-collapse heterogeneous flows ("all integrations are REST") — async/file/EDI/SWIFT/HL7 v2/EDIFACT channels are routinely misclassified.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require the agent to cite a payload sample or gateway log line per row. Preserve the protocol family in a separate column for diversity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents conflate "interface" with "endpoint" — one interface can have many endpoints; force the prompt to use IF-ID = logical contract, not URL path.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Define interface explicitly in the prompt: "one logical contract between source and target; one row per source-target pair; multiple endpoints under one interface are subsumed."</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Direction perspective drift: across a portfolio, "inbound" depends on which system you sit at. Anchor each row to source→target, never relative terms.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Enforce source→target direction in every row. Use consistent naming (Source, Target, not Upstream/Downstream).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Channel misclassification (REST vs RPC vs Webhook vs Event) — require the agent to cite a payload sample or gateway log line per row.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require evidence: each row has a `payload_sample_link` or `gateway_log_ref`. Reject rows without evidence.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Capability mapping invented from system names: agents hallucinate capability codes; require a closed list (the org's capability map) as input.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pass the capability map to the agent as a closed vocabulary. Reject any capability code not in the list.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Sensitivity classification: agents default to "internal" when unsure — instead instruct them to emit `unknown` and surface for human review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Forbid the agent from guessing; mandate `unknown` for any row without explicit classification in the source system.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Owner fields auto-filled from system name pattern guesses; only accept owners present in CMDB output.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Validate every owner against the CMDB extract. Reject agents' guesses; flag as `tbd` and escalate to human.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Criticality is a business judgement, not a technical metric — never let the agent set tier-1 without explicit human sign-off.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Forbid the agent from setting criticality &gt; 2 without explicit approval. Tier-1 requires business owner sign-off.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-18" severity="medium">
      <description>Long-tail integrations (EDI X12, SWIFT, HL7 v2, EDIFACT, fixed-width files) get squashed into "file transfer" — preserve the protocol family in a separate column.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Keep protocol, channel, and format as separate columns. Preserve heterogeneity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-19" severity="medium">
      <description>Shadow IT: agents will not find what is not in their inputs. Explicitly task a separate pass against email/Slack/Workato/Power Automate to surface candidates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Shadow IT discovery is a separate pass with human spot-checking. Do not expect agents to find what is hidden.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
