<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Founder As Pm Survival Kit Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Founder As Pm Survival Kit must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep exactly 3 PM artefacts: a weekly cash-and-capacity dashboard, a 1-page client-status doc per active engagement, and a kill-list of stuck work. All other PMBoK artefacts are explicitly DROPPED.</statement>
      <rationale source="Eliyahu Goldratt, theory-of-constraints">the founder bottleneck is attention, not documentation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Time-box weekly PM work to 90 minutes. Anything that requires more is automation-debt or hire-debt.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-Parkinson PM practice">Mike Michalowicz, Profit First framing extended to attention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Forbid any artefact that needs a stakeholder to read it. Founders run a closed loop; artefacts are for the founder's own future-self.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-user methodology principle: do not optimize for an audience that doesn't ">Single-user methodology principle: do not optimize for an audience that doesn't exist.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Anchored application">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Trigger: Run 2–3 person team comms without a full-time PM
Artefact: structured output meeting the contract in content/02-output-contract.xml
Evidence: ≥1 named source per rule (URL, ticket, transcript_id)
Decision: downstream consumer can act without re-deriving reasoning
]]></code>
      <note>Demonstrates the closed loop the methodology creates — trigger → artefact → decision — with auditability at each step.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Un-anchored application">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Trigger: 'we should do this thing'
Artefact: prose paragraph, no schema
Evidence: 'industry best practice'
Decision: ambiguous — every reader interprets differently
]]></code>
      <note>Each ambiguity above is a failure mode catalogued in content/03-failure-modes.xml. The methodology exists to prevent exactly this shape.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
