<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="HealthTech FHIR BA Pack Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every HealthTech FHIR BA Pack application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-fhir-resources-mapped" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map every patient-data field to an FHIR resource (Patient, Encounter, Observation, Condition, Procedure, MedicationStatement). Custom fields require a FHIR extension.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">FHIR is the interop standard; ignoring it adds 2-5× integration cost at later stages.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-hipaa-baa-or-gdpr-dpa-signed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Business Associate Agreement (HIPAA) or Data Processing Agreement (GDPR) signed BEFORE any patient data is touched. No exceptions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Unsigned BAA + touching PHI = statutory violation regardless of intent.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-irb-consent-flow" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the engagement is research, IRB protocol + informed consent flow are designed BEFORE software design. Consent revocation must be honored end-to-end.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Research without IRB is unethical + uninsurable; consent revocation must propagate to all derived data.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-audit-log-immutable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit log of every PHI access is immutable (append-only, hash-chained, OR external WORM storage). Mutable logs fail HIPAA audit.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Mutable logs are not legal evidence; immutability is the only safe design.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-minimum-necessary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply minimum-necessary standard: every PHI access is gated to the least data required for the role. No 'select * from patients' anywhere.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">HIPAA minimum-necessary is enforced in audit; broad SELECTs are immediate findings.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>