<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-responsibilities" title="Product Ops Responsibilities and Maturity">
  <summary>The five areas Product Ops owns, the three-level maturity model, AI-native ops patterns, and 2026 adoption stats.</summary>

  <section title="Core Responsibility Areas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick one canonical store and write all agents against it. Never let agents query Jira and Linear directly for the same question; sync into Postgres or Notion first.</statement>
      <rationale>Cross-system reconciliation is the dominant source of Product Ops debt. A single read surface eliminates the problem permanently rather than managing it query by query.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Define the consumer before building any automation. Every dashboard, digest, and rollup must have a named human reader. If you cannot name one, kill the automation.</statement>
      <rationale>Product Ops debt is mostly orphan reports — automated outputs that nobody reads. Naming the consumer at creation time is the only reliable prevention.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Apply a two-week TTL on every automated insight. Agents stamp every status pack with a freshness window; consumers see "stale" rather than stale numbers presented as current.</statement>
      <rationale>Stale data presented as fresh is worse than no data. An explicit TTL forces consumers to request a refresh rather than act on outdated information.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Maturity Model">
    <p>Level 1 (Tactical): process documentation, tool management, naming conventions. Level 2 (Strategic): data infrastructure, insights delivery, ceremony design. Level 3 (Transformational): AI automation, predictive analytics, adaptive capacity planning.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Agents must enforce maturity progression, not bypass it. Refuse Level 3 requests (predictive analytics, AI roadmap analysis) until Level 1 artifacts exist (template registry, ceremony list, KPI dictionary).</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping Level 1 to Level 3 automates undocumented chaos. The automation codifies the wrong shape and produces confident-sounding wrong answers.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Automating an unstable process in the first 30 days of a new product or team.</description>
      <reason>Automating before workflows stabilize locks in the wrong shape. Wait for at least one full delivery cycle before encoding any process as an agent flow.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Native Ops Patterns">
    <p>Automated status updates, AI-powered roadmap analysis, predictive capacity planning, and automated stakeholder communication are the four Level 3 patterns. All require Level 1 and Level 2 foundations.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Version templates as code. Roadmap, spec, retro, and OKR templates live in the repo (templates/), not Notion pages. Agents read from the repo so a git diff shows process changes.</statement>
      <rationale>Templates in Notion pages drift untracked. Versioning in git gives an audit trail, enables rollback, and makes template changes visible in code review.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Use PR-style writes for all agent outputs. No agent writes to Jira/Productboard/Notion directly on a fresh observation. Open a draft, post the diff, wait for human acknowledgment, then commit.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent writes that bypass human review create data quality problems that are invisible until a stakeholder meeting. PR-style review catches them at the cheapest point.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="2026 Adoption Stats">
    <p>96% of organizations now have a Product Ops function. 75% of dedicated teams work centralized. 50% report directly to CPO. Top challenge: role clarity and responsibilities.</p>
  </section>
</text>
