<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-operations Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-operations as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Automating an unstable process in the first 30 days of a new product or team.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Automating before workflows stabilize locks in the wrong shape. Wait for at least one full delivery cycle before encoding any process as an agent flow.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent metric definitions that re-derive "DAU" from prose instead of reading pinned SQL.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs hallucinate metric definitions. Always pin metric SQL in metric_kpi.definition_sql; never let the agent re-derive a definition from narrative context.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Status-update theatre: AI-generated status updates that no one reads.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tie every automated post to a named consumer, or do not generate it. Signal-to-noise collapse kills trust in the entire ops function.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Roadmap merge conflicts when nightly agent sync overwrites a concurrent PM edit.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use updated_at watermarks and conflict logs, not last-write-wins. Cross-system ID collisions (same feature in Productboard, Jira, and Linear) require an explicit mapping table.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Scheduled rollups using AskUserQuestion in a headless cron context.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cron jobs have no human; design every automation as headless-first with Slack-based async confirmations for write actions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Unbounded historical pulls without a since/limit/max_pages guard.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"Show me all incidents this quarter" silently fetches tens of thousands of tickets and blows the context window. Always pass explicit bounds.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy / PII leakage when customer names, emails, support transcripts in feedback tools touch agent context.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Strip PII at sync time before the agent context ingests product feedback. This is non-negotiable in regulated environments.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Silent webhook drops from Linear/Productboard that the agent never detects.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add a heartbeat ticket per source: "Source X last delivered N seconds ago." Without visibility of webhook failures, dashboards silently decay.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents promoted past their charter, e.g. a status-pack agent deciding to close a feature or rename a KPI.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Bound write scopes per agent in code, not just in the prompt. Enforce these bounds at the orchestrator layer.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Hallucinated metric definitions: agents re-derive "DAU = users who logged in in 24h" but the team's actual definition excludes internal users and bots.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always pin metric SQL in metric_kpi.definition_sql; never let the agent re-derive a definition from prose. Cross-check against the canonical schema.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Roadmap merge conflicts when two PMs edit the same Productboard feature in parallel and the agent's nightly sync overwrites one.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use updated_at watermarks and conflict logs, not last-write-wins. Cross-system ID collisions (same feature in Productboard, Jira, Linear) require an explicit mapping table.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Stakeholder summary tone drift: agents reflexively produce "all-green" digests because they pattern-match on past on-track packs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Inject a hard rule: every status pack must surface at least 1 risk or explicitly state "no risks identified, list of checks performed: ...".</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>OKR cargo-culting: LLMs love producing OKR docs but are bad at saying "this OKR is meaningless, kill it."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pair OKR generation with a critique pass and require human sign-off on the kill list before committing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Source-of-truth fragmentation: roadmap in Productboard, sprint in Jira, OKRs in Lattice, retros in Notion.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>An agent that "centralises metrics" without a canonical schema produces a different set of numbers than the PMs see in their own tools, and trust collapses.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Role-clarity gap: agents accelerate delivery but cannot resolve "who owns what."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If the human Product Ops charter is undefined, automating it codifies confusion. Define roles before building agents.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Status-update theatre: AI-generated status updates that no one reads waste tokens and kill signal-to-noise.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tie every automated post to a named consumer, or do not generate it. Status updates without a known reader are pure waste.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Predictive capacity planning is fragile: "AI predicts sprint completion" only works on a stable team with 6+ months of clean ticket history.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>New squads, churn, scope volatility break the model — and bad predictions are worse than none. Wait for baseline stability before automation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-18" severity="medium">
      <description>Maturity-model jumps fail: skipping Level 1 (process docs) to Level 3 (AI automation).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Automating undocumented chaos means you automate the wrong shape. Agents must enforce maturity progression, not bypass it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-19" severity="medium">
      <description>API rate limits at scale: "weekly portfolio rollup" across 20 squads in Jira hits rate limits fast.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without caching + incremental sync the job times out. Use webhooks over polling; implement exponential backoff.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
