<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Impl Plan Components Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Impl Plan Components. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-component-per-task" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every TASK references exactly one primary component; cross-component changes split into multiple TASKs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — task-scope audit">Multi-component tasks block parallel execution and hide dependency edges.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-named-components-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Components are named by stable identifier (file path, module name, service name); ad-hoc labels rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — naming convention">Ad-hoc labels prevent dependency graphs from matching the codebase.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-explicit-dependencies" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every TASK lists its upstream-component dependencies; implicit dependencies rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Build-graph practice">Implicit dependencies cause race conditions in parallel execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-no-cycles" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Component dependency graph is acyclic; cycles indicate a layering bug to be resolved before execution.</statement>
      <rationale source="DAG scheduling theory">Cycles cannot be executed in order; the impl-plan must be restructured.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-codeowner-per-component" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each component lists at least one owner; orphan components rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="CODEOWNERS practice">Orphan components rot; explicit ownership forces accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-graph-emitted" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Final artefact includes the component dependency graph as adjacency list; downstream tools consume it.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — artefact-machine-readability">Without a machine-readable graph, parallel schedulers cannot plan.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md &quot;Applies If&quot; do not all hold, OR any &quot;Skip If&quot; disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-impl-plan-components.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
