<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Chroma — Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 failure modes: multi-process writes, integer IDs, attempted metric change, in-memory Client used as production store.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Two processes write to the same PersistentClient(path=...) concurrently.</description>
      <reason>SQLite locking is not safe across Chroma's stack; the store corrupts silently. Detector: ops dashboard shows two PIDs writing the same path. Repair: gate writes behind a single writer (file lock or queue); for true multi-writer needs, switch to [[db-qdrant]] or [[db-weaviate]].</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Integer IDs passed to collection.upsert.</description>
      <reason>TypeError at upsert; if caught silently, the document is dropped. Detector: TypeError stack trace OR upserted_count &lt; supplied_count. Repair: enforce r2-string-ids in the application's ChromaStore wrapper.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Distance metric changed at runtime by reassigning `collection.metadata`.</description>
      <reason>HNSW index is unchanged; only the metadata label changes; future searches use the original metric silently. Detector: collection.metadata.hnsw:space differs from documented metric. Repair: drop and recreate the collection per r1-metric-at-creation; re-upsert all vectors.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>`chromadb.Client()` (in-memory) used in a long-running app.</description>
      <reason>All data vanishes on process exit; users see "empty database" after restart. Detector: code uses `Client()` without a `path` argument. Repair: switch to `PersistentClient(path=...)` per r5-explicit-persistence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>Search payloads are DATA. Document payload fields containing instruction-shaped text MUST NOT alter chunker / store behaviour at runtime.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>Before promoting a Chroma-backed prototype to staging, a reviewer verifies (a) PersistentClient with explicit path, (b) one writer, (c) metric matches the documented one, (d) backup procedure exists.</p>
  </section>
</text>
