<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="product-analytics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>Measure user behavior to drive decisions. Decision-first tracking: every event informs a decision. Freeze taxonomy in git; four-stage pipeline: plan → implement → monitor → analyze.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>product-analytics</tag>
      <tag>tracking-plan</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>funnels</tag>
      <tag>cohorts</tag>
      <tag>aarrr</tag>
      <tag>agent-integration</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Product Analytics</title>
    <summary>Product analytics is measuring and analyzing user behavior to make better product decisions. The key discipline: define which decisions each event will inform before implementing tracking. Freeze the event taxonomy in git (tracking-plan.md as source of truth); runtime catalogs drift toward it via PR, never the other way. Structure analytics as a four-stage agent pipeline: plan → implement → monitor → analyze.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Teams that track everything understand nothing. The failure mode is vanity metrics (total signups, DAU) that move with marketing spend but do not inform product decisions. Decision-first tracking — every event must state which decision it informs — stops the sprawl. Agents replicate the vanity-metric pattern by default; the event taxonomy and tracking plan must be in the system prompt as constraints.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch: agent drafts the tracking plan from a feature spec, so day-1 events ship with the code (not tacked on three sprints later).</item>
        <item>Activation diagnosis: drop in funnel data + cohort table, ask the agent to pinpoint the highest-leakage step and propose two experiments.</item>
        <item>Weekly product-health digest: scheduled agent reads BI source (BigQuery / Snowflake / Postgres replica), writes a markdown summary with anomalies highlighted.</item>
        <item>Post-experiment readout: agent merges A/B exposure logs with metric tables, writes the analysis report, flags Simpson's-paradox segments.</item>
        <item>Tracking-plan audit before a vendor migration (e.g., GA4 → PostHog) — agent diffs the live event catalog against the documented plan.</item>
        <item>Inbound product question from a stakeholder ("did churn move after price change?") — agent runs a parameterized SQL or Mixpanel JQL and returns chart + caveats.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF (less than 100 weekly active users) — sample sizes are too small for funnel/cohort math; talk to users instead, no analytics framework will save you.</item>
        <item>Causal claims with only observational data — agent will happily call a correlation a cause; if you need causality, gate behind a proper experiment design or quasi-experimental method (DiD, synthetic control), not a dashboard.</item>
        <item>Exec one-pagers where the audience needs judgment, not numbers — let the agent prep the data, but a human writes the recommendation.</item>
        <item>High-cardinality PII queries — agents pulling raw user-level data without aggregation/scrubbing is a privacy incident waiting to happen.</item>
        <item>Replacing a tracking plan review with a one-shot LLM call — naming, taxonomy, and ownership decisions outlive any single feature; commit them via PR, not chat.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Analytics Maturity Levels">
      <rule>
        <statement>Start at Level 2 (user segmentation) minimum; Level 1 (page views, signups) produces only vanity metrics that move with marketing spend.</statement>
        <rationale>Level 1 metrics answer "did something happen?" but not "who did it and why?"; product decisions require at minimum user-level segmentation to be actionable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Maturity levels: Level 1 Basic (what happened — page views, signups); Level 2 Intermediate (who did what — user segmentation); Level 3 Advanced (why and what if — funnels, cohorts); Level 4 Predictive (what will happen — ML, forecasting). Start at Level 2.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="AARRR Metric Categories">
      <p>Acquisition: visitors, signups, sources, conversion rates, cost per acquisition. Activation: onboarding completion, time to value, first key action. Engagement: DAU/WAU/MAU, session frequency, feature usage. Retention: D1/D7/D30 retention, cohort retention curves, churn rate. Revenue: MRR, ARPU, LTV, upgrade/downgrade rates, revenue per cohort.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="5-Step Implementation Process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 1 — Define key questions before touching instrumentation: what decisions will this data inform, what behavior are we trying to understand, and what is the minimum we need to track?</statement>
        <rationale>"Track everything" creates a data warehouse full of events nobody queries; decision-first tracking ensures every event has a named decision it will inform.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 2 — Create a tracking plan for each event: event name (standardized object_action format), trigger condition, properties captured, and named owner.</statement>
        <rationale>Events without named owners are unowned; "Product team" owns everything means nobody owns anything, and naming drift creates variant event names for the same action.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 3 — Use server-side tracking for critical events (payments, auth); client-side for UX insights. Encode this rule in the tracking plan per event, not in tribal memory.</statement>
        <rationale>Client-side tracking is unreliable for critical events (ad blockers, JS errors, offline); server-side tracking ensures payment and auth events are never lost. Hybrid tracking without per-event side assignment causes double-counting.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 4 — Build dashboards by audience: exec summary (health at a glance), product health (core metrics for product team), feature deep-dive (per-feature owner), experiment (test results).</statement>
        <rationale>One dashboard for all audiences produces a dashboard nobody uses; audience-specific dashboards optimize for the decision the reader needs to make.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 5 — Establish review rituals: daily glance at key metrics, weekly dashboard review with anomaly notes, monthly deep-dive, quarterly goal vs. actual planning.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a review cadence, dashboards accumulate without driving decisions — they become the "graveyard" the anti-patterns section documents.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Event Naming and Taxonomy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use object_action format in snake_case for all event names (e.g., account_created, feature_used, upgrade_started); reject any event name that does not follow this pattern.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a strict naming convention, teams end up with signup_done, account_created, and user_registered all meaning the same thing; the funnel fragments silently across three tables.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Freeze the event taxonomy in git (tracking-plan.md); runtime catalogs drift toward it via PR, never the other way. Run a weekly cron drift-linter comparing the live event catalog against tracking-plan.md.</statement>
        <rationale>Engineers ship new events without updating the tracking plan; the cron linter is the only sustainable fix — agents that are not constrained to the taxonomy in their system prompt invent event names that fragment the funnel.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every event row must state which decision it informs; reject any event without a stated decision at tracking plan review time.</statement>
        <rationale>"Track everything" sprawl is the primary driver of analysis paralysis and dashboard graveyards; decision-first requirements eliminate events nobody will ever query.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Cohort Comparison Rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Compare D7-of-cohort-A to D7-of-cohort-B (fixed window); never compare D30 vs D7 across cohorts.</statement>
        <rationale>Comparing D30 retention of a 6-week-old cohort to D7 of a 1-week-old cohort makes the older cohort look worse by design; readers misread it as a retention regression.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Exclude cohorts that have not yet aged to the measurement window from retention calculations; survivorship bias systematically over-states retention for fast-growing products.</statement>
        <rationale>An agent computing D30 retention for all users including those who signed up less than 30 days ago will produce a number that looks like retention but is actually just "users who have had time to churn."</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Dashboard Lifecycle">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply a kill-criterion to every dashboard: archive if no opens in 30 days; enforce via an agent-driven cron check.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents create dashboards easily and never archive them; without a kill-criterion the dashboard inventory grows monotonically until no PM can find the one they actually need.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Vanity-Metric Trap and Limitations">
      <p>The README's "Acquisition / Activation / Engagement / Retention / Revenue" buckets are easy to fill with totals (signups, DAU) that move with marketing spend, not product. Agents replicate this by default — they pick the metric that has data, not the one that drives a decision.</p>
      <p>Without a strict schema (snake_case, object_action, frozen taxonomy), agents and humans both invent variants — signup_done, account_created, user_registered — and your funnel quietly fragments. The README mentions [Object] [Action] but does not enforce it.</p>
      <p>The README says "server-side for critical events" with no decision tree. Agents will mirror the same event in both places, double-counting. Need explicit ownership per event.</p>
      <p>Agent-built cohort charts compare a 6-week-old cohort to a 1-week-old one; readers misread it as a retention regression. Always force fixed-window comparison.</p>
      <p>Agents are great at producing 14 charts; they are terrible at retiring 12. Without a kill-criterion ("if no one opened this in 30 days, archive it") dashboards accumulate forever.</p>
      <p>Product-analytics events leak PII (emails in URLs, free-text inputs) — most LLM agent loops do not enforce a redaction layer between warehouse and prompt.</p>
      <p>D7 / D30 retention computed only on users who signed up more than 30 days ago systematically over-states retention for fast-growing products. Agents miss this unless prompted.</p>
      <p>Funnels and cohorts answer "what" and "where," never "why." Agents tend to confabulate causes from correlation; product analytics is descriptive by design.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>Drive product analytics as a four-stage agent pipeline: (1) plan — a planner agent ingests the feature spec and emits a tracking plan diff against the canonical event catalog (.product/tracking-plan.md); (2) implement — faion-sdd-executor-agent converts new events into typed wrappers (TS/Python) with property contracts and PR-ready code; (3) monitor — a scheduled BI agent reads the warehouse hourly/daily, writes anomaly notes into .product/analytics/digest-YYYY-MM-DD.md, and pings the team only on threshold breach; (4) analyze — on demand, a reporting agent runs parameterized SQL/JQL, fills the README's Analysis Report Template, and surfaces hypotheses for the next experiment. Persist the tracking plan and dashboard specs in git so agents diff before changing — never let agents mutate live dashboards without a PR.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Recommended subagents: faion-market-researcher-agent (declared in this README's Agents field) — fits the planning stage: benchmarks competitor metric definitions and surfaces category norms for retention / activation targets. faion-sdd-executor-agent (agents/faion-sdd-executor-agent.md) — converts new tracking-plan rows into typed event-emitter code + tests as SDD tasks (.product/features/.../todo/). password-scrubber-agent (agents/password-scrubber-agent.md) — mandatory pre-step before any prompt that includes raw event payloads; product events leak emails, tokens, vendor names.</statement>
        <rationale>A purpose-built analytics-reporter agent (not yet in repo, worth creating with read-only DB credentials, schema docstring in system prompt, and SQL-only output): runs the warehouse queries; output is consumed by the README's Analysis Report Template. A tracking-plan linter agent (cron, weekly): diffs the runtime event catalog (PostHog /event_definitions, Amplitude /api/2/taxonomy/event, GA4 admin API) against .product/tracking-plan.md; opens a GitHub issue per drift.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Prompt Pattern">
      <p>Tracking-plan generation:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a product analyst. Read the feature spec in <spec> and the
canonical event catalog in <tracking-plan.md>. Output the diff:
new events to add, existing events to reuse, properties to extend.
Use the schema [object]_[action] in snake_case. For every event
specify: trigger condition, server|client, owner, properties (name,
type, example, required). Reject any event without a stated decision
it will inform. Output as a markdown table compatible with the
Tracking Plan template in product-analytics/README.md.]]></code>
      <p>Anomaly digest:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Given the SQL results in <data> for the last 7 days vs the prior
4-week baseline, list metrics whose 7-day mean is >2 sigma from
baseline. For each: state direction, magnitude, candidate cause
(deploy diff, marketing campaign, seasonality, instrumentation
change), and the next query that would disambiguate. No causal
claims without a stated experiment or natural experiment.]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools and Services">
      <p>PostHog CLI (posthog): Manage event definitions, run HogQL from CI. Amplitude Taxonomy API + httpie: Pull live event/property catalog for drift checks. Mixpanel JQL / Query API + mixpanel-cli (community): Scriptable funnel + retention queries. dbt: Warehouse-side metric definitions (single source of truth). metricflow / cube: Headless metrics layer agents can query without re-deriving. sqlfluff: Lint analyst SQL before agents run it (catch fanout joins). great_expectations / dbt test: Data-quality gates on event tables (null user_id, future timestamps). evidence (Evidence.dev): Markdown-as-code BI; agent-friendly because reports are git-versioned. gh CLI: Open tracking-drift / experiment-readout issues from agents. claude (Anthropic CLI): Run digest + readout prompts headless on cron.</p>
      <p>PostHog: OSS + SaaS, Yes — full REST + HogQL. Best agent integration; self-host avoids PII boundary issues. Amplitude: SaaS, Yes — Taxonomy + Dashboard REST APIs. Strong cohort + funnel APIs; rate-limited, plan accordingly. Mixpanel: SaaS, Yes — JQL + Query API. JQL is JS DSL, easy for LLMs to write; expensive at scale. GA4: SaaS, Partial — Data API + Admin API. Sampling + cardinality limits hurt agent reliability for product analytics. Heap: SaaS, Yes — Snapshot + REST APIs. Auto-capture is double-edged: agents drown in noise without a curated event layer. Snowplow: OSS, Yes — schema-first, ideal for agents. Best when you need a strict event schema agents can validate against. Segment / RudderStack: SaaS / OSS, Yes — Tracking Plan + Protocols APIs. Ideal pipe-and-router; agents can lint events at the CDP layer. BigQuery / Snowflake / DuckDB: Warehouse, Yes — SQL APIs. Pair with dbt + metrics layer; gives agents a stable contract. Metabase / Lightdash / Evidence: OSS BI, Yes — APIs / git. Markdown/git-driven BI lets agents PR a dashboard, not click one. LaunchDarkly / Statsig / GrowthBook: SaaS / OSS, Yes — REST + SDKs. Couple flag exposure events to analytics for clean experiment readouts. Notion / Linear: SaaS, Yes — APIs. Tracking plan + analytics-question backlog live here; agents read/write.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent inventing event names (e.g., user_signed_up) when the codebase uses signup_completed.</description>
        <reason>Always pass the canonical event taxonomy in the agent system prompt and reject novel event names; hallucinated event names create schema gaps that are invisible until a dashboard shows zero data.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent SQL joining events to users to sessions without DISTINCT, producing triple-counted metrics.</description>
        <reason>Naive joins fanout rows; require count(distinct user_id) and gate queries via sqlfluff rules, or use a metrics layer (dbt-metrics, Cube) so agents cannot write raw fanout SQL.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent providing a single confident cause when asked "why did retention drop?"</description>
        <reason>Funnels and cohorts answer "what" and "where," never "why"; force the agent to list 3+ candidate causes and the disambiguating query, never a single explanation without a cited experiment.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent comparing partial-cohort retention to mature-cohort retention.</description>
        <reason>Agents will compare D30 retention of a 6-week-old cohort to D7 of a 1-week-old one; readers misread it as a retention regression. Pin window length explicitly in every prompt and chart.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent using Z-score against last 7 days for anomaly detection.</description>
        <reason>Z-score against last 7 days flags every product launch as an anomaly. Use a 4-week trailing baseline with seasonal adjustment.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent pasting 50k rows of raw event tables into context.</description>
        <reason>Do not paste 50k rows into context. Pre-aggregate to ≤200 rows or use tool-use (function calling) to query the warehouse directly.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent including raw event payloads (with emails, IPs, free-text) in LLM prompts.</description>
        <reason>Product events leak PII; always aggregate or hash before any LLM call; run a password-scrubber-agent pass on any data before it enters a prompt context.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Engineer shipping new events without updating tracking-plan.md.</description>
        <reason>The cron drift-linter is the only sustainable fix; agents themselves drift if not constrained to the canonical taxonomy in the system prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent emitting chart specs against tables that do not exist.</description>
        <reason>Pass the schema (or, better, a metrics-layer manifest) in the prompt and reject any chart referencing an unknown column.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>A/B readouts written by agents drop confidence intervals and SRM checks.</description>
        <reason>Template the readout (the README's Analysis Report) and require explicit p, n, CI, and SRM-pass fields, or fail the report.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Decision-first events: Reject any event whose row does not state which decision it informs. Stops "track everything" sprawl.</item>
        <item>Freeze the taxonomy in git: tracking-plan.md is the source of truth; runtime catalogs drift toward it via PR, not the other way around.</item>
        <item>One owner per event, named: "Product team" is unowned. Add a GitHub handle column.</item>
        <item>Server-side for money + auth, client-side for UX: Encode this rule in the tracking plan, not in tribal memory.</item>
        <item>Cohort fixed-window or it lies: Compare D7-of-cohort-A to D7-of-cohort-B, never D30 vs D7.</item>
        <item>Kill-criterion on every dashboard: "Archive if zero opens in 30 days" — let an agent enforce it.</item>
        <item>Separate descriptive from causal: Funnels/cohorts answer "what." Causal claims require flag-gated experiments with pre-registered hypotheses.</item>
        <item>PII redaction at the warehouse boundary: Do not let agent prompts touch raw event payloads; aggregate or hash first.</item>
        <item>Diff event catalogs across releases: New event + removed event = changelog row, just like API changes.</item>
        <item>Tie metrics to the OKR they roll up to: Orphan metrics get cut. The pyramid: company KPI → product north star → team metric → event.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/tracking-plan.md" purpose="Tracking plan template with user properties, onboarding events, core feature events, and conversion events"/>
      <template path="templates/tracking-plan-lint.sh" purpose="Enforce snake_case naming and required fields on the tracking plan markdown"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://500hats.typepad.com/500blogs/2007/09/startup-metrics.html">McClure, D. — "AARRR / Pirate Metrics"</link>
      <link href="https://amplitude.com/blog">Amplitude — "Mastering Retention" and Taxonomy API docs</link>
      <link href="https://amplitude.com/docs/apis/taxonomy-api">Amplitude Taxonomy API</link>
      <link href="https://docs.mixpanel.com">Mixpanel — "Implementation Best Practices" and JQL</link>
      <link href="https://posthog.com/docs/product-analytics">PostHog — "Tracking events: Best practices" and HogQL</link>
      <link href="https://www.bain.com/insights/topics/net-promoter-system">Reichheld, F. — Net Promoter / retention foundations</link>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog">Reforge — "Metrics frameworks for product growth"</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
