<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-moscow-categories" title="MoSCoW Category Definitions and Rules">
  <summary>Four category definitions, test questions for Must Have, effort proportion targets, and the post-lock change escalation rule.</summary>

  <section title="Must Have">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the must-test literally: a requirement is Must only if at least one is true — product fails completely without it, there is no reasonable workaround, or it is legally/contractually required.</statement>
      <rationale>Must inflation is the #1 MoSCoW failure mode. If all three test conditions are false, the requirement is at most Should. Strict application forces real trade-off conversations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Target: 60% of sprint/release capacity. Examples: user authentication for a SaaS, payment processing for e-commerce, core value proposition feature.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Should Have">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every Should Have item must have a documented workaround. If no workaround exists, re-evaluate for Must.</statement>
      <rationale>Should without a workaround is just Must without the courage to say so. The workaround field forces honesty about what users can actually do without the feature.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Target: 20% of capacity. Examples: password reset (support can issue manual reset), search/filter (users can scroll), notifications (users can check manually).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Could Have">
    <p>Nice to have. Delight features, minor enhancements, secondary integrations. Target: up to 20% of capacity; first to cut when budget tightens. Examples: dark mode, keyboard shortcuts, cosmetic improvements.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Won't Have">
    <rule>
      <statement>Won't Have must contain at least 3 explicitly documented exclusions. It is required, not optional.</statement>
      <rationale>Won't Have is the most-skipped category and the most valuable. Explicit exclusions prevent scope creep mid-sprint, set stakeholder expectations, and focus discussions on what was decided.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Won't Have is "explicitly not in this release" — not "rejected forever". Examples: mobile app (web first), team features (solo focus), advanced analytics (basic first).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Effort Proportions and Lock Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Must + Should must not exceed 80% of capacity. If over budget: move Should to Could, move Could to Won't. Never move Must to Should to resolve a budget overrun.</statement>
      <rationale>Moving Musts down to resolve budget is self-deception — it either ships broken or the Must gets added back mid-sprint, causing scope chaos.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Once stakeholders align and lock the matrix, changing a Must requires explicit human escalation — not a quiet edit.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-lock Must changes reset scope expectations for everyone. Silent edits cause sprint replanning without the team knowing why scope changed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running MoSCoW without a fixed timebox and capacity number.</description>
      <reason>Without constraints, MoSCoW degrades into a wish-list exercise. The technique requires "does this fit in X days?" to produce real trade-offs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="templates/moscow-matrix.md">Full release matrix: context, Must/Should/Could/Won't tables with effort, summary totals.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
