<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-moscow-process" title="MoSCoW Process, Agent Workflow, and Worked Examples">
  <summary>Six-step MoSCoW process, capacity validation, agent workflow with prompt patterns, worked examples, and agent gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Process Steps">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: List all requirements from stakeholders, user research, technical needs, competitive analysis</item>
      <item>Step 2: Define the timebox — fixed sprint capacity or release budget in person-days</item>
      <item>Step 3: Categorize each item using the must-test (fails without? workaround exists? legal/contractual?)</item>
      <item>Step 4: Validate effort proportions — Must + Should must not exceed 80% of capacity</item>
      <item>Step 5: Stakeholder review — share, discuss disagreements, document decisions and rationale</item>
      <item>Step 6: Lock Must and Won't; Should/Could can flex during sprint if capacity changes</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/moscow-matrix.md">Release matrix with effort totals per category and capacity summary.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/moscow-discussion-guide.md">Single-requirement debate template: proposed category, arguments for each, questions, final decision.</reference>
    <reference path="scripts/moscow-check.py">Validates 60/20/20 budget split; reports violations when Must is over/under-allocated.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Workflow">
    <list>
      <item>categorizer agent: maps each requirement to M/S/C/W with rationale and workaround field (required for S/C)</item>
      <item>capacity-checker agent: sums effort by bucket, flags violations of 60/20/20 split</item>
      <item>reviewer agent: challenges every Must with three test questions; downgrades any that fail all three</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not let the same agent both propose and categorize requirements. Use proposer → categorizer → reviewer triad.</statement>
      <rationale>An agent that proposes features and then categorizes them has obvious bias toward marking its own proposals as Must. Separation enforces the must-test objectivity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Worked Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Invoice app MVP — 40 person-days capacity, clean 60/20/20 split</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Must Have (24 days, 60%):
  User authentication, Create invoice, Send invoice, Basic dashboard

Should Have (8 days, 20%):
  PDF export (workaround: screenshot), Client management (workaround: manual notes),
  Payment reminders (workaround: manual follow-up)

Could Have (8 days, 20%):
  Invoice templates, Recurring invoices, Basic analytics

Won't Have:
  Mobile app, Team features, Third-party integrations

Outcome: launched on time with Must + most Should complete.
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent defaulting to "Should" for ambiguous items without applying the must-test.</description>
      <reason>LLMs hedge on ambiguity. Force must_test booleans (fails_without, no_workaround, legal_or_contractual) as required fields in the output schema; category=="M" only if any is true.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent silently dropping Won't Have from output when the array would be empty.</description>
      <reason>Empty Won't Have is a failure signal, not a valid result. Make it a required non-empty array in the output schema with a minimum of 3 items.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent using raw day counts for effort when given ambiguous requirements.</description>
      <reason>Raw day counts from LLMs are unreliable. Require T-shirt sizes (XS/S/M/L/XL) mapped to day ranges, validated against team past velocity.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-Loop Checkpoints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Three mandatory human checkpoints: Must lock-in, Won't Have lock-in, any post-lock Must promotion.</statement>
      <rationale>Each of these has downstream scope and expectation consequences. Agents must not apply these changes without explicit human confirmation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
