<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-flow-monitoring" title="FLOW Multi-Frequency Monitoring Pattern">
  <summary>FLOW is a multi-frequency autonomous monitoring pattern where the server monitors itself at increasing detail per cadence: hourly silent health checks (alert only on problems) and daily/weekly reports that always send.</summary>

  <section title="FLOW Schedule Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>The hourly check must be silent on success — only send an alert when problems are detected. Daily and weekly reports always send regardless of server state.</statement>
      <rationale>An hourly alert that fires when everything is OK trains operators to ignore alerts. Silence = OK for the hourly check. For daily/weekly reports, always-send provides the baseline that makes deviations visible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Hourly   — quick health check (services, Docker, disk, memory, API) — silent on success</item>
      <item>Every 3h — summarize recent hourly checks</item>
      <item>Daily    — full status report (services, resources, errors, backup) — always sends</item>
      <item>Weekly   — trends (restarts, errors by day, disk growth) — always sends</item>
      <item>@reboot  — boot notification with service count</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="FLOW Crontab Entries">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="cron"><![CDATA[
# FLOW Monitoring
0 * * * *            /home/nero/workspace/scripts/flow-hourly.sh >> /var/log/nero-flow.log 2>&1
5 6,9,12,15,18,21 * * * /home/nero/workspace/scripts/flow-summarize.sh >> /var/log/nero-flow.log 2>&1
0 22 * * *           /home/nero/workspace/scripts/flow-send-daily.sh >> /var/log/nero-flow.log 2>&1
0 7 * * 1            /home/nero/workspace/scripts/flow-send-weekly.sh >> /var/log/nero-flow.log 2>&1
15 7 1 * *           /home/nero/workspace/scripts/flow-send-monthly.sh >> /var/log/nero-flow.log 2>&1
@reboot sleep 30 && /home/nero/workspace/scripts/startup-heartbeat.sh >> /var/log/nero-startup.log 2>&1
]]></code>
      <note>Summarize runs 5 minutes after hourly to avoid race condition. Startup heartbeat has sleep 30 to wait for services to stabilize.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Hourly Health Check Pattern">
    <rule>
      <statement>In the hourly script, collect issues into a variable. Only send a Telegram alert if the issues variable is non-empty. Log "All OK" on success for the log file, but send nothing externally.</statement>
      <rationale>Alert fatigue is the failure mode of monitoring. Silent-on-success hourly checks ensure that when an alert does fire, operators treat it as actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
ISSUES=""
add_issue() { ISSUES="${ISSUES}- $1\n"; }

# Check services
for svc in nero-core nero-web; do
    systemctl --user is-active --quiet "$svc" || add_issue "$svc is DOWN"
done

# Check disk
DISK_PCT=$(df / --output=pcent | tail -1 | tr -d ' %')
[ "$DISK_PCT" -gt 90 ] && add_issue "Disk: ${DISK_PCT}%"

# Report only on problems
if [ -n "$ISSUES" ]; then
    echo -e "FLOW ALERT $(hostname):\n$ISSUES" | /usr/local/bin/notify-telegram.sh
    log "ALERT: $(echo -e "$ISSUES" | tr '\n' ' ')"
else
    log "All OK"
fi
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Log Rotation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a logrotate rule for every new cron log file, or use a fixed-size log with truncation for low-value logs. Cron log files grow indefinitely otherwise.</statement>
      <rationale>A backup script logging 5 lines per day produces ~1800 lines per year, manageable. An hourly health check logging 10 lines produces ~87,600 lines per year — logrotate is required.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
