<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Contractor Agreement Template Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules. Each prevents a specific enforceability failure observed in cross-border micro-agency engagements.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-jurisdiction-match" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The template variant MUST match the contractor's jurisdiction of residence, not the engaging entity's jurisdiction and not the contractor's nationality. A US LLC hiring a UK resident uses the UK variant. The selected template is named in the agreement preamble.</statement>
      <rationale source="Choice-of-law analysis in cross-border contractor engagements">Worker-protection laws of the contractor's residence usually apply regardless of governing-law clauses. Picking by entity jurisdiction creates a template that the contractor's local labor authority can disregard.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-classification-tests" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each agreement MUST pass the relevant classification test BEFORE signing: US IRS 20-factor / 1099 indicators, UK IR35 status (CEST tool or qualified assessment), EU per-country indicators (DE Scheinselbständigkeit, FR salariat déguisé, ES TRADE). The classification-risk-check.py output is attached as an appendix; HIGH risk requires an attorney sign-off line.</statement>
      <rationale source="HMRC IR35 enforcement actions 2020-2025, BMAS guidance, IRS misclassification penalties">A contract that says "contractor" while the relationship looks like employment is reclassified by the authority. The financial penalty + backdated employer taxes routinely exceed the entire engagement value.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-ip-assignment-specific" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>IP assignment language MUST be specific to the jurisdiction: US "work made for hire" + present-tense assignment; UK explicit assignment with moral-rights waiver where permitted; EU explicit assignment with country-specific carve-outs (e.g., German UrhG moral rights are non-waivable — use exclusive license + exploitation rights). Boilerplate "all IP belongs to Client" does not work uniformly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Comparative IP law: US Copyright Act §101 vs UK CDPA 1988 vs EU Directive 2001/29/EC and national implementations">"Work made for hire" is a US concept that does not exist in UK/EU. An attempted WFH assignment for an EU contractor fails — the work remains the contractor's without a properly worded assignment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-payment-tax-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Payment terms MUST state: currency, gross/net basis, who bears VAT/GST/sales tax, withholding-tax handling (W8-BEN for non-US contractors paid by US entity, etc.), payment cadence, late-payment interest rate (UK Late Payment of Commercial Debts Act default applies if not specified). Tax form requirements (1099, W8, IR35 declaration) are listed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cross-border payment disputes are the most common source of contractor friction; ambiguous VAT handling alone accounts for ~30% of disputes per ICAEW practice notes">Without explicit tax handling, the contractor invoices VAT the founder did not budget for, or the founder withholds tax the contractor did not expect. Both produce cash-flow surprises.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-termination-and-ip-survival" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Termination clause MUST specify: notice period, payment for work-in-progress, return-of-materials, and survival of IP assignment / confidentiality clauses after termination. Survival is not implicit — must be stated explicitly. Mid-engagement IP transfer trigger MUST be defined (on payment for each deliverable, OR on engagement completion).</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-drafting practice; IP that does not transfer until 'completion' creates ambiguity when engagement ends acrimoniously">Without explicit IP-transfer trigger, ownership is litigable. Without survival, post-termination confidentiality is unenforceable. Both are deal-killers in any later acquisition due-diligence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply the contractor agreement template to one engagement per pass. Multi-contractor batches MUST be split. Skip this methodology entirely when (a) hiring as employee, (b) Employer-of-Record provides the contract, or (c) jurisdiction is outside US/UK/EU.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 content-completion; sibling methodology routing">Anti-conflation + sibling-methodology routing: batched contracts hide per-jurisdiction nuance, and templates do not generalise to non-target jurisdictions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Specific IP-assignment clause (UK variant)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Contractor hereby assigns to Client all present and future copyright, design rights,
database rights, and other intellectual property rights in the Deliverables, with full
title guarantee, on the date of payment for the relevant Deliverable. Contractor waives
all moral rights in the Deliverables to the extent permitted by law."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Specific assignment + payment-triggered + moral-rights waiver with jurisdiction-aware caveat. Enforceable under CDPA 1988.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Generic boilerplate that fails in EU">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"All work product is a 'work made for hire' and the Client owns all rights."
      ]]></code>
      <note>WFH does not exist in EU/UK law. The clause is non-operative for an EU contractor and the IP stays with the contractor.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
