<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="error-prevention Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for error-prevention. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Replace open text fields with constrained inputs (pickers, selects, steppers) whenever the valid value set is finite or format-bound.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A date picker eliminates the entire class of invalid-date errors at zero user effort. A dropdown for country eliminates spelling variations, case differences, and unknown country codes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-fill fields with the most likely correct value; require confirmation rather than entry from scratch.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Recognition is more reliable than recall. A pre-filled field that the user confirms is faster and less error-prone than a blank field the user must populate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Validate on blur for most fields; validate on change only for password strength indicators.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">On-change validation for standard fields triggers error states before users finish typing, which is frustrating and counterproductive. On blur gives feedback when the user signals they are done with the field.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use confirmation dialogs for irreversible or high-consequence actions only; never for routine, easily reversible operations.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dialog fatigue from overuse causes users to dismiss confirmations without reading them, defeating the purpose. Reserve dialogs for permanent delete, subscription cancellation, and bulk destructive operations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The confirmation button label must name the specific object and action, not a generic "OK" or "Confirm".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Specific labels ("Delete 47 files") force users to process what they are confirming. Generic labels ("OK") are dismissed as reflexively as ad popups.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Show format hints before the user enters data (placeholder or helper text), not only as error messages after incorrect input.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Error messages after entry waste user effort. Pre-entry guidance prevents the error from occurring. Provide examples: "(XXX) XXX-XXXX" for phone, "MM/DD/YYYY" for date.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide autocomplete on search, email, and address fields; provide auto-formatting for phone and credit card fields.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Autocomplete reduces entry errors by completing from a validated set. Auto-formatting normalizes input format and gives real-time feedback that the field is interpreting input correctly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use a numeric keyboard on mobile for any numeric field; apply min/max constraints; provide increment/decrement buttons for bounded ranges.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Numeric keyboard prevents letters from entering numeric fields. Min/max constraints prevent out-of-range values. Stepper buttons make small adjustments faster and less error-prone than direct entry.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always use a date picker for date input; never use a free text field for dates.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Free text date fields accept invalid dates (31st of February), format variations (MM/DD vs DD/MM), and relative terms ("next week") that require complex parsing and still produce errors at downstream validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use confirmation dialogs only for: permanent delete, subscription cancellation, bulk destructive operations. Never for: saving a file, moving to trash (reversible), logging out, or any routine action.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dialog overuse trains users to dismiss confirmations reflexively, defeating the protection mechanism for genuinely dangerous actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Position Cancel as the default focus in confirmation dialogs for destructive actions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The default focus determines what happens if the user presses Enter or Space without reading. Default-to-Cancel prevents accidental destructive action via keyboard.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Validate on blur for standard fields; validate on change only for password strength indicators.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">On-change validation for email, name, and other fields triggers error states before users finish typing, creating jarring red error messages that are immediately proven wrong as typing continues. Password strength is the exception because users benefit from real-time feedback while choosing a password.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
