<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-patterns" title="Error Prevention Patterns by Field Type">
  <summary>Field-type-specific prevention patterns and confirmation dialog rules.</summary>

  <section title="Text Fields">
    <list>
      <item>Character counter for fields with limits (visible, updates as user types)</item>
      <item>Format hints before entry (placeholder or helper text), not only as error messages</item>
      <item>Autocomplete suggestions for email, address, and known value sets</item>
      <item>Real-time validation on blur (not on change, which triggers errors mid-typing)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Numeric Fields">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a numeric keyboard on mobile for any numeric field; apply min/max constraints; provide increment/decrement buttons for bounded ranges.</statement>
      <rationale>Numeric keyboard prevents letters from entering numeric fields. Min/max constraints prevent out-of-range values. Stepper buttons make small adjustments faster and less error-prone than direct entry.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Date Fields">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always use a date picker for date input; never use a free text field for dates.</statement>
      <rationale>Free text date fields accept invalid dates (31st of February), format variations (MM/DD vs DD/MM), and relative terms ("next week") that require complex parsing and still produce errors at downstream validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Confirmation Dialog Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use confirmation dialogs only for: permanent delete, subscription cancellation, bulk destructive operations. Never for: saving a file, moving to trash (reversible), logging out, or any routine action.</statement>
      <rationale>Dialog overuse trains users to dismiss confirmations reflexively, defeating the protection mechanism for genuinely dangerous actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>"Delete 47 items permanently? This action cannot be undone. All selected files will be permanently removed." [Cancel] [Delete 47 Items] — specific, consequence-clear, Cancel is prominent.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"Are you sure?" [Cancel] [OK] — vague consequence, generic button label, user may dismiss without reading.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Position Cancel as the default focus in confirmation dialogs for destructive actions.</statement>
      <rationale>The default focus determines what happens if the user presses Enter or Space without reading. Default-to-Cancel prevents accidental destructive action via keyboard.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Inline Validation Timing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate on blur for standard fields; validate on change only for password strength indicators.</statement>
      <rationale>On-change validation for email, name, and other fields triggers error states before users finish typing, creating jarring red error messages that are immediately proven wrong as typing continues. Password strength is the exception because users benefit from real-time feedback while choosing a password.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/error-prevention-audit.md">Audit template for systematically reviewing form fields against these patterns</reference>
  </section>
</text>
