<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Error Prevention Examples and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>Good and bad real-world examples, anti-patterns, and agentic audit workflow for forms and code review.</summary>

  <section title="Good Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Gmail compose: "Did you mean to attach a file?" detects the word "attached" in body without an attachment. Warns about empty subject line. Undo send option for 30 seconds. Each is a targeted prevention for a specific, common error.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Google Forms: required fields marked with asterisk before user begins. Real-time validation catches format errors per field. Field types (email, number, date) constrain input to valid values. No errors discovered only at submit.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Amazon checkout: address validation with suggestions as user types. Payment validation before order placed. Estimated delivery date shown before confirming. Order review screen before final submit.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Bad Examples">
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Long form where user fills all fields and clicks Submit, then sees 5 error messages at the top of the page. User must scroll up to find the first error, then navigate back to each field. All errors could have been caught inline as the user typed.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Email field accepts invalid format on input. Confirmation email fails to send. User never discovers the email was wrong until they wonder why they received no confirmation.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Validation only on form submit.</description>
      <reason>User wastes effort filling subsequent fields after making an error in an early field. Inline validation catches errors while context is fresh and the field is still in focus.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Adding confirmation dialogs to every action.</description>
      <reason>Dialog fatigue causes users to dismiss confirmations without reading them, defeating protection for genuinely dangerous actions. Reserve confirmations for irreversible, high-consequence actions only.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Agent reads form spec or component definition, applies Error Prevention Audit template: for each field identifies input type, constraints, validation timing, smart default opportunities, and whether associated actions are destructive enough to require confirmation. For code review, agent scans form handler code for missing server-side validation and unguarded mutation endpoints.</p>
    <reference path="templates/error-prevention-audit.md">Audit template for systematic form review</reference>
    <reference path="templates/zod-schema-generator.py">Python stub that generates Zod schema from a field spec list</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-audit.txt">LLM prompt for auditing a form spec against Heuristic #5</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent reviews only the frontend form without also reviewing the API handler.</description>
      <reason>Client-side validation alone is insufficient. A missing constraint in the API handler allows invalid data from any client (API, curl, other frontends). Always audit both layers in the same pass.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent generates Zod/Pydantic schemas that miss cross-field validation rules.</description>
      <reason>Schemas generated from field lists do not account for dependencies (end date must be after start date, password must match confirmation). Flag cross-field validations as needing manual implementation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
