<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="error-prevention Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for error-prevention as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Validation only on form submit.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>User wastes effort filling subsequent fields after making an error in an early field. Inline validation catches errors while context is fresh and the field is still in focus.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Adding confirmation dialogs to every action.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Dialog fatigue causes users to dismiss confirmations without reading them, defeating protection for genuinely dangerous actions. Reserve confirmations for irreversible, high-consequence actions only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent reviews only the frontend form without also reviewing the API handler.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Client-side validation alone is insufficient. A missing constraint in the API handler allows invalid data from any client (API, curl, other frontends). Always audit both layers in the same pass.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates Zod/Pydantic schemas that miss cross-field validation rules.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Schemas generated from field lists do not account for dependencies (end date must be after start date, password must match confirmation). Flag cross-field validations as needing manual implementation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
