<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="iac-patterns-cicd Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for iac-patterns-cicd. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The CI pipeline MUST run: (1) fmt -check, (2) validate, (3) tflint, (4) security scan (checkov/tfsec), (5) plan on PR with comment output, (6) apply only on merge to main. Apply MUST require all previous stages to pass.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each stage catches a different failure class: fmt catches formatting drift, validate catches syntax errors, tflint catches provider-specific issues, security scan catches policy violations, and the plan review is the human gate before any cloud mutation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cloud authentication in CI MUST use OIDC (id-token: write permission + configure-aws-credentials with role-to-assume). NEVER store long-lived IAM access keys as CI secrets.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">OIDC tokens are short-lived (15 minutes) and scoped to the specific workflow run; a leaked token has minimal blast radius compared to a long-lived IAM key that persists until manually rotated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production apply jobs MUST use a GitHub Environments deployment gate requiring manual approval. Apply from main branch only; never allow direct apply from feature branches.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">An approval gate before production apply is the last human checkpoint; it prevents accidental production deploys from merged-but-unreviewd PRs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Configure a scheduled drift detection job that runs terraform plan daily (or hourly for critical infrastructure) and alerts when plan output is non-empty. Do NOT auto-apply drift remediation — require human review of each drift incident.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Auto-remediation of drift can destroy intentional manual changes made during an incident response. Alert and require human judgment for each drift detection event.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
