<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Insight Evidence Card Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Insight Evidence Card Template application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="one-claim-per-card" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each card pins ONE atomic claim. Compound claims ('users want X and Y') are split into two cards.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atomic-insight discipline">Compound claims defy evidence aggregation; atomic cards make confidence calculable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="verbatim-quote" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each card carries the strongest verbatim quote backing the claim. Paraphrases are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Verbatim-evidence practice">Paraphrase drift turns evidence into opinion within two synthesis cycles.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-count-tracked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each card pins evidence_count = number of distinct interviews that surface the claim. Claims with count=1 are tagged 'anecdotal'; claims with count≥3 can feed opportunity tree.</statement>
      <rationale source="Triangulation discipline">Count-based gating prevents single-interview anecdotes from inflating the tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="segment-tag" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each card names the segment the claim applies to. 'All users' is rejected unless the segment map has a single segment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Segment-aware research practice">Cross-segment claims hide where the claim breaks; segment tagging makes the claim falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="confidence-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each card carries a confidence band (low / medium / high) keyed to evidence_count + recency + interviewer diversity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Confidence-calibration practice">Without confidence band stakeholders default to high-confidence reading.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
