<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Dark Knowledge Extraction Protocol Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Dark Knowledge Extraction Protocol application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-five-themed-sessions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Protocol MUST run exactly 5 themed 90-minute sessions: architecture, hot files &amp; landmines, on-call history, key contacts &amp; politics, AI-agent rules. Ad-hoc 'just tell me what you know' sessions are rejected as low-yield.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Themed sessions force the leaver to recall in different modes (spatial, narrative, social); empirical comparison vs unstructured shows 2-3x more captured items per hour.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-repo-walk-pairing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>At least one session MUST be a screen-shared repo-walk where the interviewer asks the leaver to open files cold and narrate. Pure-conversation interviews are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Tacit knowledge surfaces in front of the actual artefact; abstract recall under-samples landmines that the leaver only remembers when they see the line of code.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-scribe-not-interviewer" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interviewer and scribe MUST be different people. Same person doing both produces sanitised, summary-shaped notes that lose the texture.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Cognitive load of asking + listening + writing simultaneously degrades each output; separating roles is standard interview-research practice.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-receiving-engineer-validates" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Receiving engineer MUST execute 3 representative tasks against the pack within 14 days of handover; gaps found are fed back as a v1.1 patch.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Hand-over packs that are never used decay invisibly; the validation tasks force the pack to face reality before the leaver loses context.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-ai-agent-rules-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pack MUST include a section 'do not let the AI agent do X here' with concrete file globs + reasons. Generic 'AI agents must be careful' notes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">AI agents now write a meaningful share of the code; a hand-over that skips this section creates immediate post-rotation incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
