<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-app-store-optimization Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-app-store-optimization. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Place primary keyword in app name (30 chars) and subtitle (30 chars) — these carry the highest weight in iOS ranking.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Apple's algorithm weights title and subtitle fields most heavily. Keywords appearing here rank faster and higher than those only in the keywords field.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use the 100-character iOS keywords field for secondary terms only: no spaces, comma-separated, no duplicates of name/subtitle, singular only (Apple auto-pluralizes).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Duplicating name/subtitle terms in the keywords field wastes scarce characters. Apple pluralizes singular terms automatically, so adding plural forms is redundant.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Place primary keyword in the first sentence of the Google Play short description (80 chars) and repeat key terms 3–5 times naturally in the full description (4000 chars).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Google Play indexes the full description as a web document. Keyword density and placement in the short description (shown in search results) directly affect ranking.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Research keywords from five sources before writing any metadata: competitor analysis, store autocomplete, review mining, related searches, and ASO tools (Sensor Tower, AppTweak, data.ai).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-source research misses long-tail terms that competitors haven't targeted. Review mining surfaces the words actual users use — often different from marketing language.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score every keyword candidate on relevance (0–10), volume (High/Med/Low), and difficulty (High/Med/Low) before prioritizing. Target high-relevance, medium-difficulty keywords first.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">High-volume keywords are dominated by top apps. Medium-difficulty keywords offer ranking opportunity while still delivering meaningful traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Design icon with one focal element, no text, and brand colors. A/B test at least two variants before finalizing.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Icons render at 29x29 pixels in some placements. Text becomes unreadable. Single-element icons are recognized faster in peripheral vision and crowded search results.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>First two screenshots must show the core value proposition — assume most visitors never scroll to screenshot 3+.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Eye-tracking studies show 60%+ of store visitors view only the first two screenshots. Burying the key feature in screenshot 4 costs conversion from the majority of visitors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Add a benefit headline as text overlay on each screenshot. Show the app in active use, not empty states.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Text overlay explains what the user sees. Empty states (blank dashboards, sign-up screens) communicate nothing about the product's value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use consistent visual style across all screenshots (same font, color palette, device frame).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Inconsistent screenshots signal a low-quality or abandoned product and reduce trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep preview video to 15–30 seconds. Hook in first 3 seconds. Show real app usage only. No narration.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Most users autoplay with sound off. Narration adds nothing. The first 3 seconds determine whether the viewer continues; starting with a menu screen or splash animation loses viewers immediately.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trigger in-app review prompt only after a positive action (task completed, goal reached) and after the user's 3rd+ session. Never prompt on first launch or after negative events.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Early prompts interrupt onboarding and elicit neutral/negative reviews from users who haven't experienced value. Post-positive-action timing captures peak satisfaction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Apple's SKStoreReviewRequest API (iOS) or Google's In-App Review API (Android) — do not build custom review gates or incentivize reviews. Both are policy violations.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Review gating (only showing the store prompt to users who said they liked the app) is banned on both platforms and can result in removal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Respond to all negative reviews within 24 hours: acknowledge the issue, describe the fix or workaround, and ask the user to update their review if the issue is resolved.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Public responses demonstrate support quality to prospective users scanning reviews. Users who see a thoughtful response are more likely to update their rating. App stores surface developer responses prominently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Localize in this order: English (US/UK), Spanish (LATAM + Spain), Portuguese (Brazil), German (DACH), French, Japanese, Korean, Chinese (Simplified). Localize name, subtitle, description, screenshot text overlays, and keyword field for each locale.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These locales represent the largest App Store revenue pools. Translating only the description while keeping English screenshots leaves 30–50% of conversion potential unrealized in non-English markets.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
