<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-ranking-factors" title="ASO Ranking Factors and Keyword Research">
  <summary>iOS and Google Play ranking factors with controllability ratings; keyword research process; metadata character limits and placement rules.</summary>

  <section title="iOS App Store Ranking Factors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place primary keyword in app name (30 chars) and subtitle (30 chars) — these carry the highest weight in iOS ranking.</statement>
      <rationale>Apple's algorithm weights title and subtitle fields most heavily. Keywords appearing here rank faster and higher than those only in the keywords field.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the 100-character iOS keywords field for secondary terms only: no spaces, comma-separated, no duplicates of name/subtitle, singular only (Apple auto-pluralizes).</statement>
      <rationale>Duplicating name/subtitle terms in the keywords field wastes scarce characters. Apple pluralizes singular terms automatically, so adding plural forms is redundant.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Google Play Ranking Factors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place primary keyword in the first sentence of the Google Play short description (80 chars) and repeat key terms 3–5 times naturally in the full description (4000 chars).</statement>
      <rationale>Google Play indexes the full description as a web document. Keyword density and placement in the short description (shown in search results) directly affect ranking.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Keyword Research Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Research keywords from five sources before writing any metadata: competitor analysis, store autocomplete, review mining, related searches, and ASO tools (Sensor Tower, AppTweak, data.ai).</statement>
      <rationale>Single-source research misses long-tail terms that competitors haven't targeted. Review mining surfaces the words actual users use — often different from marketing language.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Score every keyword candidate on relevance (0–10), volume (High/Med/Low), and difficulty (High/Med/Low) before prioritizing. Target high-relevance, medium-difficulty keywords first.</statement>
      <rationale>High-volume keywords are dominated by top apps. Medium-difficulty keywords offer ranking opportunity while still delivering meaningful traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Controllable vs. Uncontrollable Factors">
    <p>Fully controllable: name, subtitle/short description, keywords field, full description, icon, screenshots, video. Partially controllable: download velocity (via UA spend), ratings (via review prompts), engagement metrics (via UX quality). Not controllable: competitor activity, algorithm changes.</p>
  </section>
</text>
