<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-visual-conversion" title="Visual Assets and Conversion Optimization">
  <summary>Rules for icon, screenshots, and preview video; before/after optimization example showing impact on conversion and download volume.</summary>

  <section title="App Icon Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design icon with one focal element, no text, and brand colors. A/B test at least two variants before finalizing.</statement>
      <rationale>Icons render at 29x29 pixels in some placements. Text becomes unreadable. Single-element icons are recognized faster in peripheral vision and crowded search results.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Screenshot Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>First two screenshots must show the core value proposition — assume most visitors never scroll to screenshot 3+.</statement>
      <rationale>Eye-tracking studies show 60%+ of store visitors view only the first two screenshots. Burying the key feature in screenshot 4 costs conversion from the majority of visitors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a benefit headline as text overlay on each screenshot. Show the app in active use, not empty states.</statement>
      <rationale>Text overlay explains what the user sees. Empty states (blank dashboards, sign-up screens) communicate nothing about the product's value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use consistent visual style across all screenshots (same font, color palette, device frame).</statement>
      <rationale>Inconsistent screenshots signal a low-quality or abandoned product and reduce trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Preview Video Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep preview video to 15–30 seconds. Hook in first 3 seconds. Show real app usage only. No narration.</statement>
      <rationale>Most users autoplay with sound off. Narration adds nothing. The first 3 seconds determine whether the viewer continues; starting with a menu screen or splash animation loses viewers immediately.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Before/After Conversion Example">
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Before optimization: generic name, vague subtitle, narrow keyword set, low review count.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Name: MyApp
Subtitle: The best app
Keywords: productivity,work,business
Rating: 3.8 stars (50 reviews)
Conversion (page view → download): ~20%
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>After optimization: keyword in name, benefit subtitle, expanded keyword field, review prompt added. Results: 3x organic downloads, 40% conversion, top 10 for "todo list".</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Name: MyApp - Task Manager
Subtitle: To-do lists & productivity
Keywords: todo,checklist,planner,organize,tasks,reminder,daily,habit
Rating: 4.6 stars (500 reviews)
Conversion (page view → download): ~50%
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
