<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-reviews-and-localization" title="Reviews, Ratings, and Localization">
  <summary>Review acquisition timing and targeting; negative review response protocol; localization priority order and scope of assets to translate.</summary>

  <section title="Review Acquisition">
    <rule>
      <statement>Trigger in-app review prompt only after a positive action (task completed, goal reached) and after the user's 3rd+ session. Never prompt on first launch or after negative events.</statement>
      <rationale>Early prompts interrupt onboarding and elicit neutral/negative reviews from users who haven't experienced value. Post-positive-action timing captures peak satisfaction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Apple's SKStoreReviewRequest API (iOS) or Google's In-App Review API (Android) — do not build custom review gates or incentivize reviews. Both are policy violations.</statement>
      <rationale>Review gating (only showing the store prompt to users who said they liked the app) is banned on both platforms and can result in removal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Negative Review Response">
    <rule>
      <statement>Respond to all negative reviews within 24 hours: acknowledge the issue, describe the fix or workaround, and ask the user to update their review if the issue is resolved.</statement>
      <rationale>Public responses demonstrate support quality to prospective users scanning reviews. Users who see a thoughtful response are more likely to update their rating. App stores surface developer responses prominently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/review-response.txt">Negative review response template with variable fields.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Localization Priority">
    <rule>
      <statement>Localize in this order: English (US/UK), Spanish (LATAM + Spain), Portuguese (Brazil), German (DACH), French, Japanese, Korean, Chinese (Simplified). Localize name, subtitle, description, screenshot text overlays, and keyword field for each locale.</statement>
      <rationale>These locales represent the largest App Store revenue pools. Translating only the description while keeping English screenshots leaves 30–50% of conversion potential unrealized in non-English markets.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Keyword stuffing: packing keywords unnaturally into the description or name (e.g., "todo task list checklist planner reminder organizer").</description>
      <reason>Both stores penalize unnatural keyword repetition. Human-readable copy converts better and avoids algorithmic penalties.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring reviews for more than 48 hours.</description>
      <reason>Unanswered negative reviews accumulate in visible positions and signal poor support. The window to convert a negative reviewer to a neutral one closes quickly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Never updating the store listing after launch.</description>
      <reason>Both stores factor update frequency into ranking. Stale listings signal abandonment and hurt position over time.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
