<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Sprint Goal Formula Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that produce a single-sentence sprint goal the team can recite and the review can grade pass/fail.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every sprint MUST have exactly one written sprint goal containing all three formula parts: (a) outcome — verb + user/system change, (b) boundary — explicit in/out scope edge, (c) measure — verifiable signal. A goal missing any part fails the planning gate.</statement>
      <rationale>One-or-two-part goals collapse under pressure: a goal with no measure cannot be graded; a goal with no boundary invites scope creep; a goal with no outcome is a task list. All three parts together make the goal operational.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The sprint goal MUST fit in one sentence under 30 words. If it cannot, the sprint is targeting two goals and MUST be either split or de-scoped.</statement>
      <rationale>Compactness is the recitability test. A goal the team cannot remember at standup does not function as a goal — it functions as documentation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Any scope addition raised mid-sprint MUST be graded against the goal using the binary test: "does this advance the outcome inside the boundary?" If yes → may enter the sprint with PM approval. If no → goes to next sprint backlog. A "maybe / sort of" answer counts as no.</statement>
      <rationale>The "maybe" path is how sprint goals die: each individually small addition seems aligned enough, and the goal silently drifts. The binary test forces a clean ruling.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>At sprint review, the measure portion of the goal MUST be evaluated as pass or fail — no partial credit, no narrative qualifier. A failed measure triggers a retrospective root-cause discussion as the first agenda item.</statement>
      <rationale>Soft grading erodes the goal's signal: if "kind of passed" is allowed, the formula stops shaping behaviour. Binary grading + automatic retro link makes failure productive instead of demoralising.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>A team MUST NOT commit to two concurrent sprint goals. If two genuinely independent outcomes are needed, the team is over-allocated; the PM MUST escalate to staffing or descope one outcome before sprint start.</statement>
      <rationale>"Two goals" is the second-place coping pattern after "no goal" — it preserves the appearance of focus while removing the function. Enforcing single-goal-per-sprint forces the real conversation about capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Goal:
  Reduce new-user signup drop-off by enabling email-only signup for web (not mobile),
  measured by signup completion rate ≥ 65% on staging cohort.

Parts:
  outcome  = reduce new-user signup drop-off via email-only flow
  boundary = web only, not mobile
  measure  = signup completion rate ≥ 65% on staging cohort
      ]]></code>
      <note>One sentence under 30 words. Outcome, boundary, and measure all present and falsifiable.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Goal: "Improve the checkout experience and clean up tech debt."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Two goals, no boundary, no measure. At review, nothing can be graded. Fails the formula on every rule.</note>
    </example>

  </section>
</text>
