<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="User Research at Scale Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the User Research at Scale methodology. Every rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale, plus the universal skip-this-methodology gate.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="frozen-codebook-plus-overflow" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Coding MUST apply a frozen codebook; novel themes go to a proposed_codes overflow channel for weekly review, never auto-applied.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — coding-drift audit Q4 2025">Auto-extending the codebook produces theme drift; the overflow channel preserves novelty without polluting the book.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="n-fifty-per-finding" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any published finding MUST be supported by &gt;=50 coded observations across &gt;=10 sessions and &gt;=2 segments.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — finding-floor policy">Below the floor, findings reflect noise or coding bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="hitl-gate-before-publish" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Findings MUST pass a human-in-the-loop review before publish; no auto-publish.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Q3 2025 publish-incident">AI coding mistakes propagate; HITL catches them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="zdr-only-for-pii" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interview transcripts and any PII MUST be processed through ZDR-eligible LLM endpoints only.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anthropic ZDR policy + DSA">Privacy + DSA compliance; non-ZDR retention is a legal liability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="interviewer-turn-strip" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Transcripts MUST be speaker-attributed; interviewer turns are stripped before coding.</statement>
      <rationale source="Looppanel docs + internal — Q4 2025 audit">Coding interviewer prompts as user statements inflates false themes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="idempotent-api-writes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All writes to Dovetail/Notion/CRM via API MUST use idempotency keys (hash of source + date).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Q2 2025 duplicate-record incident">Without idempotency, retries multiply records.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only if all entries in `## Applies If` hold and none of `## Skip If` triggers; otherwise abort and route to the correct methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — decision tree minimum form">A misrouted methodology produces wrong-shape output; the explicit skip rule is the universal default branch from the decision tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
