<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-tools-and-services" title="Research at Scale Tools, Services, and Best Practices">
  <summary>CLI tools for transcription and analysis, platform service landscape, and operational best practices for large-scale research pipelines.</summary>

  <section title="CLI Tools">
    <list>
      <item>whisperx: forced-aligned transcription with diarization, faster than vanilla Whisper</item>
      <item>pyannote-audio: speaker diarization when WhisperX is insufficient</item>
      <item>ffmpeg: slice session recordings into per-task clips for AI scoring</item>
      <item>yt-dlp: pull session videos from CDN URLs given by panel platforms</item>
      <item>jq / duckdb: query coded JSONL transcripts and platform exports</item>
      <item>pandas + sentence-transformers: embed and cluster open-ended survey responses</item>
      <item>bertopic: topic modeling on large response corpora</item>
      <item>dvc / lakefs: version control for transcripts + codebooks (audit trail)</item>
      <item>presidio: PII redaction before sending to external LLMs</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Gate on Whisper confidence score >= 0.6 per transcript before coding — low-quality audio produces confident-but-wrong text that the coder cannot distinguish from accurate transcription.</statement>
      <rationale>Downstream coding errors from bad transcription are undetectable at the finding layer. The confidence gate catches the problem at the source.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Platform Services">
    <list>
      <item>UserTesting (enterprise): REST API + webhook; largest panel, AI Insights add-on</item>
      <item>Userlytics (mid+): REST API; 2M+ panel, AI analytics, EU-friendly</item>
      <item>Maze (self-serve+): API + Zapier; bias detection, dynamic follow-ups</item>
      <item>dscout (enterprise): API; mobile ethnography and longitudinal diaries</item>
      <item>Dovetail (all tiers): REST + GraphQL; repository + AI tagging, codebook host</item>
      <item>Sprig (mid): API + JS SDK; in-product micro-surveys at session scale</item>
      <item>Hotjar / FullStory (mid): API; session replay + heatmaps for behavior layer</item>
      <item>Rally / User Interviews (mid): API; recruitment and scheduling automation</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cache full transcripts in the LLM context using prompt caching when coding hundreds of quotes against the same codebook — the savings are substantial at scale.</statement>
      <rationale>Repeated codebook context is identical across all transcript coding calls. Prompt caching eliminates the redundant token cost of loading the codebook on every call.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Publish disconfirming quotes alongside confirming ones — outliers are signal, not noise.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM summarization compresses outliers. The most valuable insights often come from the user who had the unexpected reaction. Requiring outlier inclusion in the quote bank prevents systematic suppression.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stratify panels by behavior (active/lapsed/new), not just demographics — demographic-only sampling hides usage truth.</statement>
      <rationale>Demographic similarity does not predict usage similarity. Active and churned users of the same age have opposite perspectives on the product's value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Triangulate every finding with AI sentiment + behavioral analytics + verbatim quote — never report from one source alone.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-source findings have low reliability at scale. Three-source triangulation with confidence tiers (high >= 3 types, medium = 2, low = 1) enables stakeholders to calibrate trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a "draft/published" gate on every finding — dashboards auto-update faster than humans can vet.</statement>
      <rationale>Unvetted AI findings reaching a product meeting without a human review can redirect roadmap decisions based on hallucinated patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
