<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-capture" title="Lesson Capture: Schema, Triggers, Specificity Rules">
  <summary>Rules for capturing lessons with sufficient specificity to be actionable, including the required schema and capture timing.</summary>

  <section title="When to Capture">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture lessons within 24 hours of the trigger event. Weekly retros lose specifics; project-close retros lose everything from earlier phases.</statement>
      <rationale>Memory decays exponentially. Within 24 hours, the context, numbers, and causal chain are still accessible; a month later only the emotion remains.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Capture triggers: after each milestone, when problems occur, when successes happen, during retrospectives, at project close.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Lesson Schema">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every lesson must have all five fields: situation (facts), impact (effect on project), root_cause (why), lesson (insight), recommendation (actionable change with a verb, an owner type, and a measurable outcome).</statement>
      <rationale>Missing any field makes the lesson unusable: no situation = no context, no recommendation = no change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/lesson-validator.py">Validator that rejects incomplete or vague lessons</reference>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Lesson: "Communication was bad." No situation, no root cause, no actionable recommendation. This is the median entry in most lessons databases.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Situation: new framework introduced with no training time budgeted. Impact: development 40% longer. Root cause: excitement about new tech, no training estimate. Lesson: new technology requires explicit ramp time. Recommendation: add 25% buffer when introducing a framework new to the team and schedule a dedicated 2-day training sprint before development begins.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Specificity Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reject any recommendation that lacks an action verb, an owner type, and either a metric or a process change. "Improve estimation" fails; "Add 25% buffer to estimates when introducing a framework new to the team" passes.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague recommendations are re-logged identically on the next project. Specificity is what makes the lesson transferable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag lessons by context, not just category: technology stack, team size, vendor involvement, regulated domain. Retrieval needs context match, not just topic match.</statement>
      <rationale>A lesson about API integration on a regulated healthcare project is not the same as one on an unregulated internal tool, even if both are tagged "technical".</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Lessons captured only at project end.</description>
      <reason>Recency bias and survivorship bias dominate: only the last few weeks are memorable, and only people still on the project participate.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Blame sessions framed as lessons-learned meetings.</description>
      <reason>Teams stop sharing honestly when the session becomes a post-mortem of individual failures. Facilitator must enforce "process not people" ground rule actively.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM summarisation of retro notes producing generic platitudes.</description>
      <reason>Summarisation compresses two distinct lessons into one homogeneous statement. Preserve verbatim quotes alongside derived summaries.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
