<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-retrieval" title="Lesson Retrieval: Retro Structure, Kickoff Briefing, Storage">
  <summary>Rules for making lessons-learned databases queryable and actually consulted, covering retro session structure, mandatory kickoff retrieval, and storage/tagging discipline.</summary>

  <section title="Mandatory Kickoff Retrieval">
    <rule>
      <statement>At every project kickoff, retrieve the top 3–5 lessons matching the project context (tech, team size, vendor count, regulated flag) and read them aloud with the team. An unread database is dead weight.</statement>
      <rationale>The only way to break the write-only pattern is to make retrieval a mandatory step in the kickoff agenda, not an optional pre-read.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Sunset lessons older than 24 months or re-validate them against current context. Stale lessons reflect a different technology and team environment and can mislead.</statement>
      <rationale>Industry tooling, team norms, and project contexts drift; a 3-year-old lesson about a deprecated framework is actively harmful.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Retro Session Structure">
    <p>Six-phase structure: (1) open with ground rules (process not people, equal participation, honest), (2) what worked — 15 min, (3) what did not work — 15 min, (4) root causes — 15 min, (5) recommendations with owners — 15 min, (6) action items with due dates — 10 min.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Prompt explicitly for negative lessons: "what slowed us down?" must be asked with equal weight to "what worked?". Positive-framed prompts produce 3:1 positive-to-negative ratio by default.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs and human facilitators both have politeness bias; negative lessons require explicit prompting to surface.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Storage and Tagging">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a closed tag enum for category: planning | execution | technical | team | vendor | stakeholder | other. Reject free-text categories — they drift into ungroupable noise within three projects.</statement>
      <rationale>Consistent tagging is the prerequisite for semantic search; ad-hoc categories produce a lookup table that no query matches reliably.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track which lessons led to checklist or template updates — these are the high-value ones. Archive the rest after 24 months if they produced no process change.</statement>
      <rationale>A lesson that has been re-logged three times without producing a process change is not a lesson — it is a complaint. Archive it and fix the underlying process.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Feedback Loop">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every lesson recommendation must trace to a concrete artifact update (checklist item added, template modified, onboarding doc updated) or be flagged as "recommendation not implemented" in the next quarterly review.</statement>
      <rationale>Recommendations with no artifact update are decorative. The close-the-loop step is what differentiates a learning organisation from a complaint archive.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
