<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="feature-prioritization-rice">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-operations</domain>
    <summary>Quantitative scoring model ranking features by (Reach × Impact × Confidence) / Effort. Replaces gut-driven HiPPO prioritization with shared math artifact. Re-score quarterly.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>prioritization</tag>
      <tag>rice</tag>
      <tag>product-ops</tag>
      <tag>scoring</tag>
      <tag>roadmap</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Feature Prioritization (RICE)</title>

    <summary>Quantitative scoring model that ranks features by `(Reach × Impact × Confidence) / Effort`. Reach is users per quarter from analytics; Impact uses a fixed 5-point scale (3/2/1/0.5/0.25); Confidence is capped at 50% without cited evidence; Effort is total person-months including design, dev, QA, and docs. Higher score = higher priority. Re-score quarterly; archive prior scoring files with date stamps.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Feature prioritization driven by gut feeling or the HiPPO (Highest Paid Person's Opinion) produces inconsistent, unstable roadmaps. RICE replaces negotiation with a shared math artifact: every stakeholder can challenge the inputs, but the formula is neutral. The Effort denominator corrects for scope creep — large high-impact features that take a quarter still lose to small quick wins that unlock the same users.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Backlog has 10+ candidates needing an objective, repeatable rank for the next quarter or release.</item>
        <item>Stakeholders disagree on priority and you need a math-based artifact to defuse HiPPO.</item>
        <item>A subagent drafts a roadmap from a raw idea list and needs a defensible default ordering.</item>
        <item>You have at least funnel/MAU data plus an effort estimate per item.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-feature decisions — RICE adds noise versus a one-liner rationale.</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF / 0-to-1 products where Reach is unknowable — use opportunity solution trees or Kano.</item>
        <item>Compliance, security, or contractual must-haves — they bypass RICE and go straight into the plan.</item>
        <item>Cross-portfolio bets where strategic fit dominates the score (RICE has no strategy term).</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="rice-formula-and-factors">
      <p>The RICE formula combines four factors: Reach, Impact, Confidence, and Effort. Each factor has a defined scale to ensure comparability across features.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>RICE Score = (Reach × Impact × Confidence) / Effort. Express Reach in the same unit (users/quarter) for the entire batch. Never mix monthly and quarterly denominators.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing time periods inflates some rows 3-4x, making the ranking meaningless. Consistency in Reach units is more important than precision.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Reach is the number of users/customers affected per quarter. Source from analytics (funnel data, MAU counts, segment sizes). Never use "everyone" — estimate the segment.</statement>
        <rationale>Unquantified reach creates false precision. Grounding each item in an actual segment size (e.g., "4000 free-tier users trying checkout annually") makes the score defensible.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use only the fixed Impact scale: 3 (massive), 2 (high), 1 (medium), 0.5 (low), 0.25 (minimal). Never invent intermediate values.</statement>
        <rationale>Intermediate values (1.7, 2.3) create false precision and destroy cross-feature comparability. The fixed scale forces explicit categorization.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Cap Confidence at 50% for any item without a cited evidence URL or table reference. Reserve 100% for data-backed, tested items only.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents and humans default to 80-100% when uncomfortable. Evidence requirement prevents confidence inflation that produces false precision scores.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>100% — data-backed and tested (prototype results, A/B test, analytics correlation)</item>
        <item>80% — some data, reasonable assumptions, similar feature precedent</item>
        <item>50% — opinions, limited data, no prior evidence</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Express Effort in total person-months including design, dev, QA, and docs. Require a breakdown before accepting any estimate.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs under-estimate effort 2-3x when not broken down. Decomposing into sub-disciplines exposes hidden work and produces calibrated estimates.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>0.5 — a few days (patch, copy change, minor config)</item>
        <item>1 — about one person-month</item>
        <item>2 — two person-months</item>
        <item>3 — one quarter</item>
        <item>6+ — major project</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="scoring-process">
      <p>The RICE scoring process is a six-step algorithm from candidate list through strategic override lanes.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Step 1: List all candidates. Step 2: Score each factor per item with rationale. Step 3: Calculate RICE = (R × I × C) / E. Step 4: Sort highest to lowest. Step 5: Sanity-check — any item with score greater than 2× the median requires human review before entering "Now". Step 6: Apply strategic override lane for top-2 bets to prevent crowding by easy wins.</statement>
        <rationale>This sequence prevents gaming: if you score first without seeing the median, you can't anchor on it. The 2× median check catches outliers that need review. The strategic override protects large bets from being crowded out by many small quick wins.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Re-score quarterly. Archive prior scoring files with date stamp to detect drift.</statement>
        <rationale>Stale scores produce wrong roadmaps. Feature importance shifts as the product grows and user segments change. Historical scoring files are the primary artifact for retrospective analysis of prioritization drift.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="E-commerce feature prioritization">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Feature | R | I | C | E | RICE | Decision |
|---------|---|---|---|---|------|----------|
| Guest checkout | 15000 | 2 | 90% | 1 | 27000 | Sprint 1 |
| Size guide | 5000 | 1 | 70% | 0.5 | 7000 | Sprint 1 |
| Wishlist | 8000 | 1 | 80% | 2 | 3200 | Sprint 2 |
| Gift wrapping | 2000 | 0.5 | 60% | 1 | 600 | Backlog |

Insight: Guest checkout ranks #1 despite medium effort due to high reach (15K users see checkout) and strong impact (removes friction for non-registered users). Gift wrapping: only 600 reach with low confidence — clear backlog placement.
        ]]></code>
        <note>Each row has all four factors populated and cited. The highest-effort item (wishlist at 2 PM) ranks third because low impact and reach drag the score down.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="SaaS dashboard prioritization">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Feature | R | I | C | E | RICE | Decision |
|---------|---|---|---|---|------|----------|
| Export to CSV | 3000 | 1 | 100% | 0.25 | 12000 | Sprint 1 |
| Dark mode | 5000 | 0.5 | 100% | 0.5 | 5000 | Sprint 2 |
| Email reports | 2000 | 2 | 80% | 1 | 3200 | Sprint 2 |
| Custom dashboards | 1000 | 3 | 50% | 3 | 500 | Later |

Insight: CSV export wins on low effort (quarter-day) and perfect confidence. Custom dashboards: high impact but 3 person-months + only 50% confidence → defer.
        ]]></code>
        <note>Low-effort high-confidence item beats high-impact complex item. This is the power of RICE — it surfaces unglamorous quick wins that unlock the most value-per-month.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM-generated Reach values as round numbers (5000, 10000) with no analytics citation.</description>
        <reason>Round numbers signal fabrication. Force decimal Reach from actual funnel analytics. Any Reach without a source URL or table reference must be rejected and re-estimated.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Same agent both proposing and scoring features.</description>
        <reason>The proposer has obvious bias toward high-scoring its own proposals. Route scoring to a different subagent than the proposer.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Silently dropping items below a RICE threshold without emitting the full ranked list.</description>
        <reason>Hidden rejections prevent review. Always emit the full ranked list with a cut line; never suppress low-scoring items from the output.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>High-RICE items with no sequencing check for dependencies.</description>
        <reason>A high-RICE item that depends on three low-RICE items cannot be started first. Dependency graph review is a required post-ranking step.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-gotchas">
      <p>RICE is powerful but has known limitations. Garbage in produces false precision; confidence inflation destroys signal; effort is routinely under-estimated.</p>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Garbage in, garbage out: 80% of the score variance comes from Reach guesses; fabricating it produces false precision. Audit Reach every quarter against actual analytics.</statement>
        <rationale>If Reach is made up, the entire ranking is made up. The formula cannot distinguish between "based on real data" and "plausible fiction." Quarterly audit forces grounding.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Effort is the most-hallucinated factor; require breakdown into design / dev / QA / docs sub-estimates and sum them.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs default to "seems reasonable" without accounting for edge cases, testing, documentation, and team ramp-up. A bottom-up breakdown catches hidden months.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>No discount for sequencing: a high-RICE item that depends on three low-RICE items can still be wrong to start. Dependency graph review is mandatory post-ranking.</statement>
        <rationale>RICE optimizes for absolute value, not execution order. Always re-check dependencies before committing to the ranked order.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>RICE encourages many small wins, which can starve large strategic bets. Pair RICE with a "20% strategic" carve-out: reserve capacity for top-2 vision-critical features even if they score low.</statement>
        <rationale>Pure RICE ranking will fill the roadmap with quick wins because the Effort term penalizes large work. Strategic override lanes prevent the roadmap from drifting into death by a thousand cuts.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>When the LLM both proposes and scores features, bias toward its own proposals is automatic. Route scoring to a different subagent.</statement>
        <rationale>An LLM that created a feature will naturally score it highly; separation of concerns is required for fair scoring.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflows">
      <p>AI agents excel at coordinating the data gathering, scoring, and ranking steps. Structured output and human-in-loop gates maintain rigor.</p>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Drive RICE as a structured-output pipeline. A discovery subagent gathers Reach evidence (analytics, ticket counts, segment sizes) and Impact evidence (test results, similar features). A scorer subagent emits one JSON row per candidate with R/I/C/E plus a `rationale` field per factor. A reviewer subagent challenges any score with C ≥ 80% that lacks cited evidence, and any E ≤ 1 that has no decomposition.</statement>
        <rationale>Structured output forces completeness and makes review mechanical. The reviewer subagent is the human-in-loop checkpoint — it validates evidence before a score enters the decision set.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Any item with score greater than 2× the median requires human review before it enters "Now". Emit the full ranked list with cut line, not just the survivors.</statement>
        <rationale>Outlier scores are either real gems or mismeasured. Human review catches both. Showing the full list (even losers) prevents silent rejection and lets humans see what was deprioritized.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Agentic RICE workflow">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Step 1: Discovery subagent pulls analytics (funnel data, segment sizes, similar feature adoption)
Output: reach_evidence.json with source URLs for each feature

Step 2: Scorer subagent reads reach_evidence + proposal list, emits JSON:
  [{id: "feature-1", reach: 5000, reach_source: "url", impact: 2, impact_rationale: "...", confidence: 80%, confidence_evidence: "url", effort: 1, effort_breakdown: "design: 0.25, dev: 0.5, qa: 0.25"}]

Step 3: Reviewer subagent validates:
  - Any C ≥ 80% has a confidence_evidence URL
  - Any E ≤ 1 has a breakdown showing >0 design or dev
  - Rejects rows with fabricated Reach (no source)

Step 4: Ranking agent sorts by RICE score descending, flags outliers > 2× median

Step 5: Human review: outliers and top 5

Step 6: Commit as rice-<quarter>.md under .aidocs/
        ]]></code>
        <note>Each step is a separate agent. The division prevents proposer bias and ensures evidence is always cited.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/rice-scoring-table.md" purpose="Multi-feature scoring table with R/I/C/E columns, RICE score, rank, and per-feature notes."/>
      <template path="templates/rice-decision-record.md" purpose="Single-feature record: factor scores with rationale, calculation, rank, decision, dependencies, strategic alignment."/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/rice.py" purpose="Minimal Python scorer: reads JSON list with reach/impact/confidence/effort fields, computes scores, returns ranked output."/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.intercom.com/blog/rice-simple-prioritization-for-product-managers/"/>
      <link href="https://www.productplan.com/glossary/rice-scoring-model/"/>
      <link href="https://www.romanpichler.com/blog/"/>
      <ref slug="roadmap-design"/>
      <ref slug="backlog-management"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
