<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-gtm-strategy">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>GTM framework: define one ICP with anti-ICP, craft positioning using For/Who/Is/Unlike/We, select 2-3 channels, choose sales motion by ACV, plan phased launch.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>gtm</tag>
      <tag>go-to-market</tag>
      <tag>strategy</tag>
      <tag>icp</tag>
      <tag>launch</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="growth-brand-positioning"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Go-to-Market Strategy</title>

    <summary>Five-question GTM framework: define one ICP with anti-ICP, craft positioning using For/Who/Is/Unlike/We formula, select 2-3 channels, choose sales motion by ACV, and plan phased launch. Mark unverified claims as ASSUMPTION.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Most founders skip GTM planning and build features nobody wants for an audience they never validated. Without a single ICP, messaging is generic, channels are diluted, and sales chases bad-fit deals. A structured GTM doc forces the choices that trading intuition avoids — which customer, which channel, which motion — and provides a measurable baseline for monthly reviews.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Drafting an initial GTM plan from product brief and market data.</item>
        <item>Building a competitive positioning map by analyzing G2, Capterra, SimilarWeb, and competitor sites.</item>
        <item>Generating multiple GTM hypotheses (channel × motion × pricing) and stress-testing against unit economics.</item>
        <item>Monthly metric review to flag off-track KPIs and propose strategy adjustments.</item>
        <item>Preparing launch-readiness reports across phases (private beta → public beta → GA).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>No validated product yet — GTM without product-market fit validation is fiction; run customer-discovery interviews first.</item>
        <item>Late-stage pivots driven by emergent insight from a single customer call — human must own strategic shifts; agent optimizes on outdated assumptions.</item>
        <item>Regulated industries with heavy licensing gates (medical devices, fintech, defense) — GTM constraints are legal, not market-driven.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="ideal-customer-profile">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define exactly ONE ICP for the first 6 months; define the anti-ICP explicitly alongside it.</statement>
        <rationale>Splitting GTM effort across multiple segments dilutes messaging, channel focus, and product priorities. "SMB and Enterprise" means building two different products and running two different sales motions simultaneously — both suffer. The anti-ICP prevents sales from chasing bad-fit deals that look like revenue but destroy retention and referenceability.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>ICP components for B2B: Industry, Company size, Revenue range, Tech stack signals, Specific pain point, Buyer role and decision power. ICP components for B2C: Age range, Goals and frustrations, Budget and decision timeline, Information sources (where they learn).</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>ICP defined as "SMBs, startups, and enterprises across all industries".</description>
        <reason>This is not an ICP — it is a market. An ICP must be specific enough that you can name 50 companies or people who fit it. If you cannot name them, the ICP is too broad to guide channel or messaging decisions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="value-proposition">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Write the value proposition using the For/Who/Is/Unlike/We formula; mark every unverified claim as ASSUMPTION.</statement>
        <rationale>The formula forces specificity at each step: who the customer is, what problem they have, what category the product belongs to, who the competitors are, and what is genuinely different. "ASSUMPTION" tagging prevents treating an unvalidated value prop as a foundation for channel spend.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Value proposition using the formula">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
For: solopreneurs building digital products
Who: struggle with scattered tools and no methodology
Our: Faion Network
Is: an AI-powered development framework
That: provides 282 proven methodologies and AI agents
Unlike: generic courses or just-tools platforms
We: combine education with working software

[ASSUMPTION: "282 proven" requires validation against user outcomes data]
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="channel-selection">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Select 2-3 channels maximum; master them before adding a third; assign each channel a funnel role (awareness / consideration / conversion), not just a name.</statement>
        <rationale>Seven channels listed by an LLM ("SEO, content, Product Hunt, LinkedIn, cold email, paid, community") means seven partial efforts that none receive enough focus to compound. Two channels mastered produce more results than seven channels half-tried. Each channel must be assigned a role: awareness-only channels should not be held accountable for CPA.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Organic: SEO, content, social, community — long-term, low CAC, slow to start.</item>
        <item>Paid: Google Ads, Meta Ads, LinkedIn Ads — fast start, scalable, requires conversion data to optimize.</item>
        <item>Outbound: email, events, cold calls — high-value B2B where human relationship matters.</item>
        <item>Partnerships: affiliates, integrations — leverage existing audiences, slow to build.</item>
        <item>Product-led: freemium, viral loops, self-serve — requires product that demonstrates value immediately.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="sales-motion">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Choose sales motion based on ACV and CAC payback; validate with unit economics before committing to motion.</statement>
        <rationale>Self-serve works when ACV is too low to justify a human sales touch (under $5K/year). Enterprise requires human sales when ACV justifies multi-month sales cycles. Choosing enterprise motion for a $99/month product burns sales resources; choosing self-serve for a $50K deal loses the contract to a competitor with a dedicated rep.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/gtm-feasibility.py">Unit-economics check: LTV, CAC payback, motion eligibility by ACV range</reference>
      <list>
        <item>Self-serve: ACV $60-$5K/year, max payback 6 months. Product must be self-explanatory.</item>
        <item>Sales-assisted: ACV $1.2K-$30K/year, max payback 12 months. Inside sales + demos.</item>
        <item>Enterprise: ACV $25K+/year, max payback 18 months. Field sales, legal, procurement.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="phased-launch">
      <p>Three-phase launch reduces risk and generates learning before full investment: Private Beta (50-100 hand-picked users, high-touch feedback, critical bug fixes), Public Beta (open waitlist, early-access pricing, gather testimonials), General Availability (full launch, PR push, paid acquisition starts).</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not start paid acquisition until the product achieves a measurable retention threshold in private or public beta.</statement>
        <rationale>Paid acquisition into a leaky product accelerates churn, not growth. Spending on acquisition before retention is validated means the budget is funding users who will leave before the CAC is recovered. Establish a retention baseline (e.g., 40% D7 for consumer) before opening paid channels.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="monthly-review-cadence">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Review GTM performance monthly (not weekly, not quarterly); each review writes a delta entry to the GTM doc — not a rewrite.</statement>
        <rationale>Weekly reviews are too noisy for strategy signals; quarterly reviews discover off-track KPIs too late to course-correct. Delta entries (not rewrites) preserve the decision history — you need to know why you made previous choices to evaluate whether current results are a strategy failure or an execution failure.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Monthly review agenda: actual vs. target 90-day metrics, channel CAC/LTV by segment, ICP validation (are we actually acquiring the ICP?), anti-ICP drift (are sales chasing bad-fit deals?), top 3 risks and kill-switches.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="competitive-positioning">
      <p>Build a 2x2 competitive map with two dimensions that matter to your ICP. Position yourself in an open quadrant. Key competitors: list 3-5 with their strengths, weaknesses, and where you win. Update when a new competitor emerges or a significant feature launches.</p>
      <reference path="templates/competitive-map.md">Competitive landscape table and positioning statement template</reference>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Competitive analysis that sources all claims from a single review platform (G2 or Capterra).</description>
        <reason>G2 reviews are gamed; companies encourage positive reviews and dispute negative ones. SimilarWeb traffic is noisy at under 100K MAU. Triangulate across at least 3 independent sources: review platforms, Crunchbase/LinkedIn funding data, and direct user interviews.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-constraints-and-limitations">
      <p>LLM-generated ICPs default to "tech-savvy SMB founders" or similarly generic personas. Without disciplined input data (won-deal interview transcripts, churn-call notes), output is flattering noise. Competitive analysis from public web is shallow — pricing pages lie, G2 reviews are gamed, SimilarWeb traffic is noisy at less than 100K MAU. Agent must triangulate, not single-source. Sales-motion choice is sensitive to ACV math the LLM gets wrong (CAC payback, LTV/CAC); always wire actual financial inputs and do not let the model reason from priors. Channel rec ("SEO, content, Product Hunt") becomes uniform across briefs; agent must constrain channel set per ICP behavior data, not blanket recommendations. Phased launch timelines proposed by an LLM ignore real engineering capacity; plug in the actual roadmap or the plan is fantasy.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Every GTM doc produced by an agent must have explicit ASSUMPTION tags on unverified claims. Reject docs without them.</item>
        <item>Channels listed must each have an assigned funnel role and explicit reasoning tied to ICP behavior data, not generic recommendations.</item>
        <item>Pricing experiments require legal sign-off (price discrimination rules, regional pricing law). Agent surfaces this gate; does not implement pricing changes unilaterally.</item>
        <item>ICP derived from won-deal data only has survivorship bias. Agent must also analyze lost deals and never-tried segments.</item>
        <item>Strategy and tactics are distinct. A GTM strategy is category-level decisions (which channel, which motion, which ICP). A task list ("write 10 blog posts") is execution. Reject strategy outputs that are actually task lists.</item>
        <item>A "vision" sentence written by an LLM regresses to the mean — it will be forgettable. Humans write the vision; agents draft options for humans to choose from.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A multi-agent GTM workflow: (1) researcher subagent scrapes competitor sites + review platforms + community discussions; (2) brainstorm subagent diverges on ICP/positioning/channel combinations; (3) strategist subagent converges, produces a one-pager with explicit assumptions and unknowns; (4) reviewer subagent critiques against unit-economics constraints and prior failed bets; (5) human approves and locks the doc. Monthly: a metrics agent reads dashboards, flags drift, and queues a strategy review.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-content-agent (drafts positioning copy, GTM one-pager, value prop variations); faion-brainstorm (multi-perspective diverge/converge for ICP and channel choice; useful before any single-strategy commitment); faion-sdd-executor-agent (runs GTM as an SDD feature: spec, design, test-plan, implementation-plan); faion-improver (quarterly review session that audits prior GTM doc against actuals).</p>
      <p>Prompt pattern: Goal: produce GTM one-pager v1 for product P. Inputs: product brief, 5 won-deal transcripts, 5 lost-deal transcripts, competitor list, current MRR/CAC/LTV. Constraints: ONE ICP (not three); name the anti-ICP; pick 2-3 channels with explicit reasoning; sales motion must reconcile with CAC payback less than 12 months. Output: filled GTM one-pager template; mark every unverified claim as "ASSUMPTION".</p>
      <p>Red-team pattern: Goal: red-team GTM doc D. Method: list 5 ways this strategy fails in 6 months. For each, state the leading indicator and a kill-switch. Output: risk register; do not rewrite the doc.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/gtm-one-pager.md" purpose="Full GTM one-pager: ICP, value prop, channels, motion, pricing, timeline, metrics"/>
      <template path="templates/competitive-map.md" purpose="Competitive landscape table and positioning statement"/>
      <template path="templates/gtm-feasibility.py" purpose="Unit-economics check: LTV, CAC payback, motion eligibility by ACV range"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="growth-brand-positioning"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
