<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-lifecycle-stages" title="Requirements Lifecycle Stages and States">
  <summary>Six lifecycle stages, eight requirement states with valid transitions, and the distinction between validation and verification.</summary>

  <section title="Six Lifecycle Stages">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every requirement must pass through six stages in sequence: Identify (discover from sources), Analyze (categorize, detect conflicts, prioritize), Specify (formal documentation with ID and template), Validate (confirm correctness with stakeholders), Verify (confirm implementation matches spec), Manage (version control, change control, traceability).</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping stages produces requirements that are captured but not analyzed, or documented but never validated — the most common sources of implementation mismatch.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Eight Requirement States">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every requirement must be in exactly one of: Draft, Proposed, Approved, Rejected, Implemented, Verified, Deferred, Deleted. State must be visible in the requirements register at all times.</statement>
      <rationale>Hidden state produces version confusion; teams implement Rejected requirements or skip Deferred ones because state is not tracked explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Valid transitions: Draft → Proposed → Approved → Implemented → Verified. From Proposed: also Rejected or Deferred. From Approved: also Deferred. Deferred requirements return to Proposed in a later cycle. No other transitions are permitted without a change request.</statement>
      <rationale>Restricting transitions prevents backward-state corruption (e.g. moving Implemented back to Draft) which breaks traceability and audit trails.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Validation vs. Verification">
    <rule>
      <statement>Validation answers "Are we building the right thing?" — conducted during requirements using stakeholder reviews, walkthroughs, and prototype reviews. Verification answers "Are we building it right?" — conducted after implementation using testing, code inspection, and user acceptance.</statement>
      <rationale>Conflating validation and verification causes teams to skip one or the other; "requirements review" is not a substitute for post-implementation testing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Requirements Attributes">
    <p>Track these attributes for every requirement: ID (unique, immutable), Name (short title), Description (full text), Status (current state), Priority (MoSCoW or 1-5), Source (stakeholder or document), Owner (responsible role), Version (current version number), Created (date), Modified (last update date), Author (who wrote it).</p>
  </section>
</text>
