<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-change-control" title="Requirements Change Control">
  <summary>Change request process, impact analysis categories, approval roles, and common lifecycle management failures.</summary>

  <section title="Change Request Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every change to an Approved or Implemented requirement must be initiated via a formal change request that documents the current text, proposed change, reason, and impact analysis across requirements, design, development, testing, schedule, and cost before any approval decision.</statement>
      <rationale>Ad-hoc changes without impact analysis produce cascading failures: a changed requirement breaks test cases, design documents, and dependent requirements without anyone knowing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Change requests must be approved by at minimum the BA (requirements impact), project manager (schedule and cost impact), and sponsor (business decision). All approvals must be recorded with name, decision, and date.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-approver change control is bypassed under schedule pressure; multi-role sign-off distributes accountability and forces the full impact to be acknowledged.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When a change request is approved, increment the requirement version number and create a new version history entry with the change description, author, and date before updating the requirement text.</statement>
      <rationale>In-place edits without version history make it impossible to reconstruct what was approved at each point in time — a critical audit trail requirement.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No version control — teams work from the "latest" document without knowing if they have the current version.</description>
      <reason>Use numbered versions and a single authoritative location; version history must be auditable to support compliance reviews.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping validation — assuming requirements are correct because stakeholders provided them.</description>
      <reason>Stakeholders state what they think they want, not necessarily what they need; walkthroughs and prototype reviews surface misunderstandings before development starts.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Status not updated — requirements tracking becomes fiction because nobody updates state after approvals and implementations.</description>
      <reason>Define who is responsible for status updates at each stage transition and make it a team ritual, not an optional task.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No baseline — cannot compare current requirements to approved version to measure scope creep.</description>
      <reason>Baseline at each major milestone (project kickoff, sprint planning, release) and store the baseline snapshot separately from the working document.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/change-request.md">Change request form with impact analysis and approval table</reference>
  <reference path="templates/requirements-status-log.md">Requirements status register</reference>
</text>
