<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="requirements-lifecycle Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for requirements-lifecycle as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>No version control — teams work from the "latest" document without knowing if they have the current version.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use numbered versions and a single authoritative location; version history must be auditable to support compliance reviews.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping validation — assuming requirements are correct because stakeholders provided them.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Stakeholders state what they think they want, not necessarily what they need; walkthroughs and prototype reviews surface misunderstandings before development starts.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Status not updated — requirements tracking becomes fiction because nobody updates state after approvals and implementations.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Define who is responsible for status updates at each stage transition and make it a team ritual, not an optional task.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>No baseline — cannot compare current requirements to approved version to measure scope creep.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Baseline at each major milestone (project kickoff, sprint planning, release) and store the baseline snapshot separately from the working document.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
