<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Anchor Diversification Rules Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `Anchor Diversification Rules` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="exact-match-cap-15-pct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exact-match anchor text MUST be ≤ 15% of internal-link anchors pointing to any single target page. Above this cap, dilute with branded / partial-match / generic anchors.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google Webmaster Guidelines + SEO audit corpus 2024-2026">Exact-match concentration &gt; 15% triggers algorithmic penalty signals; the 15% cap is empirically safe across audit samples.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="branded-mix-floor-20-pct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Branded anchor text (containing the site / product name) MUST be ≥ 20% of internal-link anchors per target page. Below this floor, internal-link profile looks penalty-engineered.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal-link distribution audit 2024-2026">Sites with zero branded anchors look like SEO-engineered networks; branded floor is the natural-link signature search engines expect.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="generic-ceiling-30-pct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Generic anchor text (&apos;click here&apos;, &apos;learn more&apos;, &apos;read this&apos;) MUST be ≤ 30% of internal-link anchors per target page. Above this ceiling, you waste internal-link equity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal-link equity flow audits">Generic anchors pass equity but no topical signal; 30% ceiling preserves the equity flow without over-spending on signal-free anchors.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="hub-spoke-ratio-5-to-1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hub-pages MUST have ≥ 5 inbound spoke-links from cluster pages, and spokes MUST link back to the hub with branded or partial-match anchor. Hub-pages with &lt; 5 inbound spokes signal weak cluster cohesion.</statement>
      <rationale source="Topical-cluster SEO research 2024">Hub-spoke ratios below 5:1 lose the topical-authority signal; the explicit ratio enforces the cluster shape.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="audit-evidence-linked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each anchor-distribution finding in the checklist MUST link to the Search Console / Screaming Frog / Ahrefs report row that surfaced it. Hand-wave findings are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice">Findings without source links lead reviewers to skip verification; evidence links force the reviewer to read the actual data.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>