<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-automation-assessment" title="Automation Candidate Assessment">
  <summary>Six-criterion scoring matrix for automation readiness, RPA vs. intelligent automation comparison, and key vendor landscape.</summary>

  <section title="Automation Readiness Scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score every automation candidate against six criteria: Volume (high = more than 100 transactions/day), Standardization (high = rule-based with few exceptions), Stability (medium = process unchanged more than 6 months), Digital Input (medium = structured data available), Error Rate (medium = high manual error frequency), ROI Potential (high = high labor cost with measurable payback). Total out of 30. Recommend: full automation above 24, partial automation 18-24, process improvement first 12-18, not suitable below 12.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a scoring matrix, automation selection is based on who has the loudest stakeholder voice. The matrix forces objective measurement across dimensions that predict automation success.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="RPA vs. Intelligent Automation">
    <list>
      <item>RPA: rule-based repetitive tasks, predefined decision logic, structured data only, no learning, human escalation for exceptions — best for high-volume stable processes</item>
      <item>Intelligent Automation: complex variable tasks, AI-driven decisions, structured and unstructured data, continuous learning, autonomous exception handling — best for variable processes with document complexity or judgment requirements</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Vendor Landscape (2025-2026)">
    <list>
      <item>UiPath: largest pure-play RPA, enterprise leader, strong developer ecosystem and test automation integration</item>
      <item>Automation Anywhere: cloud-native architecture, strong AI integration, IQ Bot for document processing</item>
      <item>Blue Prism: enterprise governance and auditability focus, preferred in regulated industries</item>
      <item>Microsoft Power Automate: M365 integration, low barrier for Microsoft shops, desktop and cloud flows</item>
      <item>Celonis: process mining combined with automation recommendations, action engine triggers RPA from discovered bottlenecks</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Market Context">
    <p>RPA market: $35.27 billion in 2026 growing to $247.34 billion by 2035. 58% of enterprises will use RPA with AI/ML by 2026. 44% already use AI-enabled RPA for document processing. By 2026, 30% of enterprises will automate more than 50% of network activities.</p>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/automation-assessment.md">Automation assessment matrix template</reference>
</text>
