<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ads-google-keywords">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>ppc-manager</domain>
    <summary>Keyword strategy balances reach with relevance: research intent, match types, ad group organization, negatives, and continuous optimization to prevent wasted spend.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>google-ads</tag>
      <tag>ppc</tag>
      <tag>keywords</tag>
      <tag>search</tag>
      <tag>intent</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Google Ads Keyword Strategy</title>
    <summary>Targeting the right keywords is critical for profitable campaigns. Broad keywords waste budget on irrelevant clicks; too narrow and you miss opportunities. The right strategy balances reach with relevance through intent-first keyword research, match type selection, ad group organization, negative list management, and continuous optimization.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Without understanding keyword intent and match types, campaign budget is wasted on irrelevant traffic. Broad match without negatives triggers on dozens of unrelated searches. Too many keywords per ad group dilutes ad relevance. A systematic approach prevents budget leakage while maximizing qualified volume.</p>
      <p>Quality Score directly impacts CPC and ad rank. When keywords, ads, and landing pages align perfectly, CTR improves, Quality Score rises, and CPCs drop. This creates a virtuous cycle where better-targeted campaigns become cheaper to run.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Building a new search campaign from scratch requiring seed keywords, expansion, clustering, and match type assignment.</item>
        <item>Weekly Search Terms Report mining to extract new negatives and identify new keyword themes.</item>
        <item>Migrating existing spend from broad-only to a phrase + exact + tight-negatives structure.</item>
        <item>Reorganizing overgrown accounts where single ad groups have 100+ mixed-intent keywords.</item>
        <item>Harvesting SEO keyword data and converting it to paid keyword plans.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Performance Max campaigns—PMax does not expose individual keywords; use audience signals and asset groups instead.</item>
        <item>Smart campaigns—Google automatically selects keywords based on themes you provide.</item>
        <item>Display or YouTube campaigns—keyword hints on display are weak signals; topics and audiences dominate.</item>
        <item>Brand-only campaigns with a tight, converged keyword list—agent optimization loops add noise.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="keyword-research">
      <p>Keyword research is the foundation. Sources include Google Keyword Planner (volume and competition data), Google Search autocomplete suggestions, competitor ad analysis, your site search logs, customer language and problem descriptions, and SEO tools like Ahrefs or SEMrush.</p>
      <p>Using Keyword Planner: go to Tools &amp; Settings → Planning → Keyword Planner, select "Discover new keywords," enter seed keywords or a URL, filter by volume and competition, then export relevant keywords. Look for product keywords, problem keywords, comparison keywords, alternative keywords, competitor keywords, and long-tail variations.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="keyword-intent">
      <p>Intent categories determine which keywords deliver conversions and which waste budget:</p>
      <p><term name="Navigational">Brand names or branded searches like "[company] login."</term></p>
      <p><term name="Informational">How, what, or why questions like "how to manage projects."</term></p>
      <p><term name="Commercial">Best, top, compare searches like "best project management tool."</term></p>
      <p><term name="Transactional">Buy, pricing, trial, or sign-up searches like "project management software pricing."</term></p>
      <p>Focus budget on transactional and commercial first. A high-value hierarchy: Transactional → Commercial → Informational → Navigational.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="match-types">
      <p>Google Ads offers three keyword match types, each with different reach and precision:</p>
      <p><term name="Broad">keyword—triggers on related searches and synonyms. Offers maximum reach but high irrelevant traffic risk. Use sparingly with tight negative lists.</term></p>
      <p><term name="Phrase">"keyword"—triggers when the exact phrase appears in the search. Balances reach and relevance.</term></p>
      <p><term name="Exact">[keyword]—triggers on exact match or close variants. Provides tight control but limits reach.</term></p>
      <p>Starting strategy: begin with phrase match, add exact match for top performers, use broad sparingly with tight negatives.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="ad-group-organization">
      <p>Keyword organization affects ad relevance and Quality Score. Common approaches include SKAG (Single Keyword Ad Groups, very tight) and themed grouping (related keywords together).</p>
      <p>Recommended themed approach: group 10-20 related keywords sharing the same intent into one ad group. All keywords in that group should trigger ads matching their theme. Separate ad groups by intent: one for "project management software," another for "task management," etc. Keep match types together if possible.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="negative-keywords">
      <p>Negative keywords prevent wasted spend by blocking irrelevant searches. Categories include unqualified (free, cheap, DIY), wrong intent (jobs, careers, salary), wrong product, competitors (if not targeting), and wrong audience (students, hobbyists).</p>
      <p>Negative match types work like positive keywords: negative broad blocks if any word matches, negative phrase blocks if phrase appears, negative exact blocks exact match only.</p>
      <p>Build and maintain negative lists by reviewing the Search Terms report weekly, filtering by cost, adding irrelevant searches as negatives, creating shared negative lists, and applying them across campaigns.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="ongoing-optimization">
      <p>Weekly keyword tasks include reviewing the Search Terms report to find new negatives and keyword ideas, checking Quality Scores for low-performers, adjusting bids based on performance, adding new keywords from Search Terms insights, and pausing keywords with high cost and no conversions.</p>
      <p>Quality Score is influenced by expected CTR, ad relevance, and landing page experience. Improve Quality Score by using the keyword in ad copy, matching landing pages to keyword intent, improving CTR through better ads, and creating tighter ad groups.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Never use all broad match keywords without a comprehensive negative list. Broad match triggers on dozens of unrelated searches, wasting budget on irrelevant traffic.</statement>
        <rationale>Broad match is designed for reach; it requires discipline with negatives to control waste.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not mix intents in a single ad group. Separate transactional keywords from informational keywords so ads can match the user's actual intent.</statement>
        <rationale>Ad relevance is measured per keyword; mixing intents causes ads to be irrelevant to many triggered keywords, lowering CTR and Quality Score.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep 10-20 keywords per ad group, not 100+. Diluted keyword lists reduce relevance for each search term.</statement>
        <rationale>Smaller ad groups with tight themes allow ads to match search intent more precisely.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ignoring the Search Terms report for weeks or months. New irrelevant searches accumulate and burn budget.</description>
        <reason>Trending searches and user language evolve; weekly review catches waste early.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Setting bid-only campaigns to "set and forget" without optimization. Declining relevance and competitive pressure erode performance.</description>
        <reason>Campaigns need active management to maintain Quality Score and respond to market changes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="benchmark-metrics">
      <p>Use these performance benchmarks to assess keyword health:</p>
      <p><term name="Quality Score">Poor: &lt;5, Average: 5-6, Good: 7+</term></p>
      <p><term name="CTR">Poor: &lt;2%, Average: 3-4%, Good: 5%+</term></p>
      <p><term name="Conversion rate">Poor: &lt;2%, Average: 3-5%, Good: 7%+</term></p>
      <p><term name="Impression share">Poor: &lt;50%, Average: 60-70%, Good: 80%+</term></p>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/keyword-plan.md" purpose="Spreadsheet template for keyword research with match type, volume, competition, and intent columns."/>
      <template path="templates/harvest-search-terms.py" purpose="Python script to export and analyze Search Terms report data."/>
      <template path="templates/negative-keyword-list.md" purpose="Template for organizing negative keywords by category."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://ads.google.com/home/tools/keyword-planner/"/>
      <link href="https://support.google.com/google-ads/answer/7478529"/>
      <link href="https://support.google.com/google-ads/answer/140351"/>
      <ref slug="ads-google-campaign-setup"/>
      <ref slug="ads-conversion-tracking"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
