<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-pipeline-rules" title="GitLab CI/CD: Pipeline Structure and Performance Rules">
  <summary>Rules for DAG with needs, workflow rules, job templates, and caching strategy to build fast, parallelized pipelines.</summary>

  <section title="DAG Pipeline Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the `needs` keyword to define job dependencies explicitly instead of relying on sequential stages.</statement>
      <rationale>Sequential stages force all jobs in one stage to complete before any job in the next stage starts. The `needs` keyword unlocks DAG execution: independent jobs run in parallel while dependent jobs wait only for their direct dependencies.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set `interruptible: true` on all build and test jobs so newer pipeline runs can cancel stale ones.</statement>
      <rationale>Without `interruptible: true`, pushing multiple commits in quick succession causes all pipelines to run fully, wasting runner capacity on intermediate commits that are already superseded.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Workflow Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define `workflow: rules` at the top of `.gitlab-ci.yml` to control when a pipeline is created; target: default branch, merge requests, and tags only.</statement>
      <rationale>Without workflow rules, GitLab creates a pipeline for every branch push including feature branches without merge requests, causing unnecessary CI runs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Standard workflow rules covering main branch, MR pipelines, and release tags.</note>
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
workflow:
  rules:
    - if: $CI_COMMIT_BRANCH == $CI_DEFAULT_BRANCH
    - if: $CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID
    - if: $CI_COMMIT_TAG
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Job Templates with extends">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use `extends` with hidden job templates (`.template-name`) to share configuration across jobs; use YAML anchors only for single-file reuse.</statement>
      <rationale>`extends` merges deeply across the entire pipeline definition and works with GitLab's `include` for cross-file sharing. YAML anchors only work within the same file.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Caching Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Key caches on dependency lock files (`package-lock.json`, `Gemfile.lock`, `requirements.txt`) to invalidate automatically when dependencies change.</statement>
      <rationale>Keying on the lock file hash means cache misses occur exactly when they should (dependency update) and hits occur on all other runs without manual cache management.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use `policy: pull` for jobs that only read the cache and `policy: pull-push` for the job that builds it; define a fallback key for initial cache population.</statement>
      <rationale>Without pull-only policy, every parallel job tries to update the same cache key simultaneously, causing write contention on distributed cache backends (S3/GCS).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
