<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-environments" title="GitLab CI/CD: Environments, Review Apps, and Deployment Patterns">
  <summary>Rules and patterns for review apps, auto-stop, manual production gates, and environment URL configuration.</summary>

  <section title="Review Apps">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deploy review apps for every merge request using `CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID` as the environment name suffix; set `auto_stop_in: 1 week` to prevent orphaned namespaces.</statement>
      <rationale>Review apps let reviewers test changes in a live environment before merge. Without auto_stop_in, each merged or abandoned MR leaves a running environment that consumes cluster resources indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always pair a review-deploy job with a review-stop job (same environment name, `action: stop`, `when: manual`) to enable manual early cleanup.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-stop waits for the timeout; manual stop lets developers clean up immediately after review is complete, reclaiming resources and reducing cloud costs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Production Deployment">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require manual approval (`when: manual`) for all production deployments; automate staging deployments on default branch.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated production deployments without a human gate increase blast radius for any CI/CD misconfiguration or untested code path that slips past automated checks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set `environment.url` on all deployment jobs so GitLab tracks the live URL and shows it in MR and environment views.</statement>
      <rationale>Without the URL, team members cannot navigate to the deployed environment directly from GitLab, reducing visibility into what is actually deployed.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <note>Review app deploy and stop jobs with auto-stop after one week.</note>
    <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
review-deploy:
  stage: deploy
  environment:
    name: review/$CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID
    url: https://$CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID.review.example.com
    on_stop: review-stop
    auto_stop_in: 1 week
  script:
    - kubectl create namespace review-$CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID --dry-run=client -o yaml | kubectl apply -f -
    - envsubst < k8s/review/deployment.yaml | kubectl apply -f -
    - kubectl rollout status deployment/app -n review-$CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID --timeout=5m
  rules:
    - if: $CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID

review-stop:
  stage: deploy
  variables:
    GIT_STRATEGY: none
  environment:
    name: review/$CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID
    action: stop
  script:
    - kubectl delete namespace review-$CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID --ignore-not-found
  when: manual
  rules:
    - if: $CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID
]]></code>
  </example>
</text>
