<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ads-linkedin-ads">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>ppc-manager</domain>
    <summary>B2B advertising on LinkedIn by job title, seniority, company, and ABM. CPCs $5-15; minimum $50/day budget. Lead Gen Forms parallel with Website Conversions. Refresh every 14-21 days.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>linkedin</tag>
      <tag>b2b</tag>
      <tag>ads</tag>
      <tag>abm</tag>
      <tag>lead-generation</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>LinkedIn Ads</title>

    <summary>B2B advertising on LinkedIn using job title, seniority, company size, and ABM targeting. CPCs run $5-15; minimum $50/day budget is required for the optimizer to exit the learning phase. Use Lead Gen Forms in parallel with Website Conversions — LGF has higher volume but lower intent. Refresh creative every 14-21 days. Never increase budget more than 25% in one step without human approval.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>LinkedIn is the only ad platform with reliable professional identity targeting (title, seniority, company). This precision makes it the correct channel for reaching narrow B2B ICPs — VPs at fintech, Directors at mid-market SaaS — that are unreachable at equivalent cost on Meta or Google. The tradeoff is cost: CPM of $30-80 and CPC of $5-15 require AOV or LTV above ~$1k to be viable.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>B2B campaigns where the buyer is identifiable by job title, seniority, or company (ABM)</item>
        <item>Lead-gen forms with LinkedIn-prefilled fields (email, company, title) for high-quality MQLs</item>
        <item>Reaching narrow ICPs unreachable on Meta or Google at acceptable CPL</item>
        <item>Retargeting site visitors with the LinkedIn Insight Tag for warm-funnel B2B nurture</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>B2C, low-AOV products, or impulse purchases — CPC of $5-15 destroys unit economics below ~$1k LTV</item>
        <item>Daily budgets under $50 — LinkedIn's optimizer cannot exit learning phase</item>
        <item>Audiences under 20k — costs spike, learning never converges, frequency fatigue triggers early</item>
        <item>Pure brand awareness on a tight budget — Meta/YouTube cost-per-impression is 5-10x cheaper</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="campaign-objectives">
      <p>Objective selection determines the optimization signal and which metrics are prioritized in the campaign.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Brand Awareness — top of funnel, impressions</item>
        <item>Website Visits — traffic, clicks</item>
        <item>Engagement — reactions and comments on content</item>
        <item>Video Views — video content views</item>
        <item>Lead Generation — native lead gen forms</item>
        <item>Website Conversions — signups, demo requests, purchases</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Default to Lead Generation or Website Conversions for B2B campaigns; use Brand Awareness only when ICP audience size exceeds 50,000.</statement>
        <rationale>B2B budget is too expensive for pure awareness goals below $1k LTV. Conversion-optimized objectives produce measurable pipeline outcomes from day one.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="targeting-strategies">
      <p>LinkedIn's professional targeting is its core strength. Build audiences in distinct layers to enable independent performance diagnosis and scaling decisions.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Build audiences in three layers — ABM list (named accounts) + ICP (title + size + industry) + similar audience expansion — run as separate campaigns, not one targeting blob.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing audiences in a single campaign prevents performance diagnosis. A separate campaign per layer reveals which audience converts at what CPL and lets you scale or cut independently.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Job Title: exact titles or title functions — primary B2B signal</item>
        <item>Job Seniority: entry to C-level</item>
        <item>Company Size: 1-10 to 10,000+</item>
        <item>Company Name: specific accounts for ABM (upload CSV)</item>
        <item>Industry: 140+ categories</item>
        <item>Skills: professional skills</item>
        <item>Groups: LinkedIn groups membership</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Minimum audience size for conversion campaigns: 20,000. Minimum for awareness: 50,000. Below 20,000, learning never converges and CPL spikes.</statement>
        <rationale>LinkedIn's optimizer needs a large enough pool to find efficient buyers. Narrow audiences cause excessive frequency, high CPMs, and no statistical learning signal.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ad-formats">
      <p>LinkedIn supports multiple ad formats optimized for different messaging objectives and audience sizes.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Single Image: 1200x627 — standard promotion, most common</item>
        <item>Carousel: 3-10 cards — multiple products or features</item>
        <item>Video: 3-30 seconds — storytelling, demos</item>
        <item>Text Ads: text only — low-budget awareness</item>
        <item>Message Ads: Sponsored InMail — direct outreach</item>
        <item>Lead Gen Forms: native forms pre-filled with LinkedIn data</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use Lead Gen Forms in parallel with Website Conversions; LGF has higher volume but lower intent — track both to revenue, not just CPL.</statement>
        <rationale>Lead Gen Forms convert at higher rates due to pre-filled fields, but leads show lower purchase intent than those who visited the landing page. Both signals are needed to understand pipeline quality.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="b2b-ad-copy-formula">
      <p>LinkedIn CPCs of $5-15 only justify budget when copy speaks precisely to the ICP's role-specific problem. Generic messaging produces low CTR and wastes the targeting advantage.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Structure LinkedIn ad copy as: intro (problem or question for the role), headline (solution or value prop), CTA (clear action); never use generic copy that could target any professional.</statement>
        <rationale>LinkedIn CPCs of $5-15 only justify budget when the copy speaks precisely to the ICP's role-specific problem. Generic copy produces low CTR (under 0.3%) and wastes the targeting advantage.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Intro text: 150 chars shown — hook with role-specific problem or question</item>
        <item>Headline: 70 chars — clear value proposition</item>
        <item>Description: 100 chars — supporting detail or proof point</item>
        <item>CTA options: Learn More, Download, Sign Up, Request Demo</item>
        <item>Image: 1200x627, professional quality</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="budget-and-cost-expectations">
      <p>LinkedIn's cost structure is significantly higher than Meta but justified by professional targeting precision.</p>
      <list>
        <item>CPM: $30-80 typical range</item>
        <item>CPC: $5-15 typical range</item>
        <item>Cost per lead (LGF): $30-100+</item>
        <item>Minimum daily budget: $50</item>
        <item>Minimum test budget: $2,000-5,000 (enough data for optimization)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not run LinkedIn campaigns with a daily budget under $50; the optimizer cannot exit the learning phase and burns budget on noise.</statement>
        <rationale>LinkedIn's algorithm requires a minimum number of daily actions (clicks or leads) to optimize. Below $50/day, the optimizer never achieves statistical significance within a reasonable window.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="bidding-progression">
      <p>Campaign bidding strategy should evolve as conversion data accumulates and the optimization algorithm learns.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Bid manually (CPC) for the first 14 days of any new campaign until 50+ form fills accumulate; then switch to Maximum Delivery for the optimizer to use the data.</statement>
        <rationale>Maximum Delivery needs conversion history to optimize efficiently. Without data, it makes random bidding decisions that waste the first weeks of spend.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Weeks 1-2: Manual CPC — full bid control, data collection</item>
        <item>After 50+ form fills: Maximum Delivery (automatic)</item>
        <item>Cost cap: set target CPA after sufficient data — constrains optimizer</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="optimization">
      <p>Ongoing creative refresh and performance tuning are essential for sustained ROI on LinkedIn campaigns.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Refresh creative every 14-21 days on LinkedIn; CTR decay is faster than Meta because the feed is sparser and users see the same ads more quickly.</statement>
        <rationale>LinkedIn's professional audience is smaller and more targeted than Meta's. High frequency against a small ICP list leads to ad fatigue within 2-3 weeks.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>CTR benchmark: 0.4% good, 0.8%+ great</item>
        <item>Lead form rate: 10% good, 15%+ great</item>
        <item>CPL target: &lt;$75 good, &lt;$50 great</item>
        <item>Lead quality: track MQL rate and cost per opportunity, not just CPL</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Exclude existing customers and converted leads via uploaded customer-list audiences; LinkedIn has no native exclude-converters toggle.</statement>
        <rationale>Without exclusions, budget is wasted showing acquisition ads to existing customers, inflating lead counts with people who cannot convert again.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="api-versioning">
      <p>LinkedIn's API versioning scheme requires active maintenance to prevent deprecation errors.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include the LinkedIn-Version header in every API call and refresh the pinned version within 6 months; outdated versions return 410 deprecation errors.</statement>
        <rationale>LinkedIn changes its API versioning monthly. Agents pinning a version over 6 months old will hit 410 responses without a clear migration path in the error message.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Refresh OAuth access tokens before they expire (60-day lifetime); implement a token refresh flow that runs proactively, not reactively after a 401.</statement>
        <rationale>LinkedIn access tokens expire in 60 days. Agents relying on 401 errors to trigger refresh fail silently at midnight when the token expires mid-run, losing that day's data.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cost-units">
      <p>Cost measurement on LinkedIn uses a different unit system than other ad platforms, creating a common conversion bug.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>LinkedIn cost data is in costInLocalCurrency as a decimal float (e.g., 45.50 USD), NOT in micros like Google Ads. Do not divide by 1,000,000.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents porting Google Ads micros logic to LinkedIn will divide costs by 1,000,000 and report CPLs of $0.000065 instead of $65 — undetectable if alerts are set in micros units.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="rate-limits-and-quotas">
      <p>API quota management is critical for multi-account or multi-app scenarios.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Rate limits apply per app, not per account; multi-tenant agents must implement a per-app token bucket and back off on 429 responses.</statement>
        <rationale>LinkedIn enforces rate limits at the OAuth app level, not per ad account. An agent managing 10 accounts with the same app will hit the limit 10x faster than a single-account agent.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Assuming Lead Gen Form field order is stable across form versions.</description>
        <reason>Custom question fields are auto-keyed (e.g., question_1ab23). Field order and keys change if the form is edited. Agents must cache the field-map per form version, never assume index positions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="attribution-lag">
      <p>LinkedIn's reporting lag and multi-touch attribution window require patience and discipline in campaign evaluation.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Wait 24-48 hours for LinkedIn metrics to stabilize before evaluating campaign performance; do not retune based on same-day data.</statement>
        <rationale>LinkedIn reporting has a 24-48 hour lag before conversion numbers are stable. Early optimization based on incomplete data causes over-reaction to noise.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Insight Tag conversions backfill for up to 90 days; do not declare a campaign a loser before the lookback window closes.</statement>
        <rationale>View-through conversions and delayed form completions backfill over 90 days. Cutting a campaign at 30 days permanently loses attribution for late-converting leads.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="human-in-loop-checkpoints">
      <p>Even with full automation capability, these decision points require human judgment or explicit approval.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Budget increase above 25% in one step: human approval required</item>
        <item>Final ad copy approval before launch: human required</item>
        <item>ABM target-account list sign-off: human required</item>
        <item>Changing campaign objective: human required</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/campaign-checklist.md" purpose="Pre-launch checklist: targeting, creative, budget, lead gen form"/>
      <template path="templates/ad-copy.md" purpose="B2B ad copy template: intro, headline, description, CTA"/>
      <template path="templates/pacing-audit.py" purpose="Daily spend pacing check against daily budget cap"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/linkedin/marketing/"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/linkedin/marketing/conversions/"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/linkedin/marketing/integrations/ads/lead-sync/"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/linkedin/marketing/audiences/"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/linkedin/marketing/versioning"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
