<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Multi-Region Active-Active Pattern Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Multi-Region Active-Active Pattern application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-residency-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map data residency requirements per dataset BEFORE topology design. EU PII may NOT replicate to US-east; financial data may require home-region only.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Topology designed without residency analysis is rebuilt at audit; residency-first prevents.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-rto-rpo-explicit-per-service" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each service has explicit RTO (Recovery Time) + RPO (Recovery Point) target. Active-active = RTO seconds + RPO seconds; active-passive = RTO minutes + RPO minutes; backup-only = RTO hours + RPO ≥ 1h.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Without per-service targets, every service gets gold-plated; cost balloons.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-conflict-resolution-deterministic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Active-active requires conflict resolution: last-write-wins, vector clocks, CRDT, or app-level merge. Choice documented per data type.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Conflicts are inevitable in active-active; undefined resolution = silent data loss.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-failover-drill-quarterly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly failover drill: actually fail a region in production (or staging-with-prod-traffic). Drills that don't fail are theater.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Untested failover is broken failover; quarterly cadence catches drift before real incident.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-traffic-steering-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Traffic steering policy explicit: geo-DNS, latency-based, weighted, or sticky. Mix of policies = unpredictable behavior.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Steering policy is the user-visible behavior; ad-hoc mix creates support nightmares.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>