<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Multi-Region Active-Active Pattern Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of multi-region-active-active-pattern enforces. Each rule has a statement, a rationale anchored to industry practice, and a source citation.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every writable data class has an explicit conflict policy (last-writer-wins, vector-clock CRDT, leader-per-key, custom merge) — defaults are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="DynamoDB Global Tables design guide">Without an explicit policy, conflicts get resolved silently and surprise users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cross-region replication latency is monitored and treated as an SLI; breach triggers a degraded mode, not silent stale reads.</statement>
      <rationale source="Vogels — Eventual Consistency">Stale reads in active-active are the silent-corruption vector.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Failover drills run quarterly at minimum, with both regions exercised; the drill produces a runbook update.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Multi-Region Reference Architecture 2026">Untested failover = no failover; quarterly cadence keeps muscle memory.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Traffic steering at the edge respects residency constraints — e.g. EU users never routed to a non-EU region even on failover.</statement>
      <rationale source="Banking-core data residency rules">Failover that violates residency is a regulatory incident.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Region partition is a tested mode; the system has a defined behaviour for 'lost peer region' (degraded, read-only, paused).</statement>
      <rationale source="Jepsen — distributed consistency reports">Untested partition = the system improvises during the actual partition.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, skip this methodology and route to the adjacent one referenced in Related.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 skill-authoring conventions">A skip rule keeps the decision tree closed: every branch ends at a real rule id.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>