<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-audience-types" title="Meta Audience Types: Core, Custom, Lookalike">
  <summary>Definitions, setup steps, and selection rules for the three Meta audience types: Core (cold), Custom (warm), and Lookalike (scale).</summary>

  <section title="Core Audiences">
    <p>Core audiences target cold traffic by demographics, interests, and behaviors. Components: Location, Age, Gender, Languages, Interests (hobbies/brands/topics), Behaviors (purchase behavior, device use), Demographics (job title, education, life events).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Minimum Core audience size is 500K; ideal range is 1-5M. Below 500K, CPM spikes and delivery becomes constrained.</statement>
      <rationale>Meta's ad auction requires sufficient audience depth to find the right users at a competitive price. Too narrow and the algorithm cannot optimize; CPM rises sharply and reach plateaus.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Interest targeting strategy: start with 5-10 related interests. Finding relevant interests: competitor brands, industry publications, related tools the audience uses, communities they belong to.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Audiences">
    <p>Custom audiences use first-party data: website pixel events, email lists, app activity, video engagement, lead form interactions, Facebook/Instagram page engagement.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Install and verify the Meta Pixel with standard events before creating any website custom audience.</statement>
      <rationale>Without pixel events firing correctly, website audiences will not populate or will include the wrong users. Verify event completeness in Events Manager before launch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Website audience segments ranked by intent: Purchasers (180d) → Add to cart (7d) → Pricing page (14d) → Product page (30d) → Blog visitors (60d) → All visitors (180d).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always create exclusion audiences (purchasers, active subscribers) before running acquisition campaigns.</statement>
      <rationale>Showing acquisition ads to existing customers wastes spend and degrades ad relevance scores. Exclusions also prevent the algorithm from optimizing toward already-converted users who inflate conversion metrics without representing net-new customers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Lookalike Audiences">
    <p>Lookalike audiences let Meta find users similar to a source audience. Percentages: 1% = highest quality/smallest, 2-3% = balanced, 5-10% = scale/lower quality.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use purchasers or high-value customers as the Lookalike source, not all website visitors.</statement>
      <rationale>The source audience defines the match pattern. Visitors include bounced traffic and irrelevant browsers; purchasers are the highest-quality signal. A LAL from visitors finds people who might visit; a LAL from purchasers finds people who might buy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Best source audiences ranked: 1) Purchasers/customers, 2) High-value customers, 3) Leads who converted, 4) Website visitors with action, 5) Email subscribers.</item>
      <item>Minimum source size: 1,000 people. Ideal: 2,000-10,000. More data = better matching.</item>
      <item>Strategy: LAL_Purchasers_1% for best quality, LAL_Purchasers_2-3% for balance, LAL_Purchasers_5-10% for scale.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Audience Size Guidelines">
    <list>
      <item>Core/Interest: minimum 500K, ideal 1-5M.</item>
      <item>Custom source: minimum 1,000, ideal 5,000+.</item>
      <item>Lookalike output: 500K-2M depending on country.</item>
      <item>Retargeting: minimum 1,000, ideal 10,000+.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-testing-and-exclusions.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/custom-audience-library.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
