<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Escalation Conversation Script Core Rules">
  <summary>The conversation discipline that keeps an escalation from spiraling into a relationship break or a half-promise the PM cannot deliver.</summary>
  <section title="Conversation rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true">
      <statement>Open with acknowledgement before any explanation. The first sentence names the other party's concern in their words and confirms it is taken seriously. Explanations, context, or counterclaims come only after the acknowledgement has been heard back ("yes that's the issue").</statement>
      <rationale>Explanations delivered before acknowledgement read as deflection and double the temperature. Acknowledgement-first is the single intervention research on conflict de-escalation consistently shows lowers the affect register enough to make the rest of the conversation possible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true">
      <statement>Use one of three named patterns to move the conversation forward: (a) acknowledge-park-redirect — acknowledge, park the broader frustration for a separate channel, redirect to the immediate decision; (b) fact-fork — propose two specific factual interpretations and ask which matches their view; (c) costed-options — present 2-3 concrete next steps each with explicit cost and tradeoff. Free-form arguing is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>Improvised escalation responses anchor on the loudest emotion in the room. Named patterns force structure; the PM stays in the driver seat without overriding the other party's agency.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true">
      <statement>Switch from verbal to written when any of three triggers fire: a commitment is being made that affects scope/cost/dates, a legal or contractual term enters the conversation, or the other party requests something the PM cannot unilaterally approve. Verbal-only conversations on these triggers are escalated to email or a memo within 24h, repeating back exactly what was discussed.</statement>
      <rationale>Verbal-only commitments on scope, cost, or contract create the next escalation. Written follow-up within 24h is the cheapest way to convert a fragile verbal agreement into a record both sides can act on.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true">
      <statement>Every escalation conversation ends with three explicit follow-ups: (1) what the PM will do by when, (2) what the other party will do by when, (3) the date of the next checkpoint. None of the three may be vague ("soon", "next week"); each names a date or specific event.</statement>
      <rationale>Open-ended endings rebuild the same frustration two weeks later. Three dated follow-ups make accountability mutual and turn the next conversation into a status review, not a re-escalation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true">
      <statement>Never agree to a remedy in the conversation that exceeds the PM's authority. If the other party demands such a remedy, the PM uses the named script: "I need to confirm with [name/role] before committing; I can do that by [time] today and respond by [time]". Improvising authority leads to walked-back promises that destroy trust further.</statement>
      <rationale>Walked-back promises are worse than the original escalation because they signal the PM cannot be trusted to know their limits. Naming the confirmer and the response time protects both the PM and the relationship.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
PM: "I hear you — the missed Tuesday demo damaged your team's confidence in this engagement, and that's a serious concern. Did I get that right?"
Client: "Exactly."
PM: "Let me park the broader pattern question for our Friday check-in. Right now we need one decision: do we (a) rerun the demo tomorrow with the current build (lower polish, faster) or (b) push to Friday for the prepped version (higher polish, longer wait)?"
Client: "Friday."
PM: "Friday. I'll send a written confirmation today with: my commitment to send the agenda by Wednesday, your commitment to confirm attendees by Thursday, and our retro on the missed Tuesday at the Friday check-in."
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
PM: "Actually the demo wasn't missed — there was a confusion about the timezone, and our engineer was waiting on your approval to the staging env, so technically..."
Client: "..."
]]></code>
      <note>No acknowledgement, defensive context-first, no decision asked, no follow-ups — the next conversation will be louder.</note>
    </example>
  
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Skip-If predicate in AGENTS.md fires, abort Escalation Conversation Script and emit a one-line "wrong-tool" note instead of the artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology selection discipline">Forcing the wrong methodology onto a case wastes the operator's time and pollutes the artefact store with low-confidence outputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
</section>
</text>
