<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="design-critique">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Structure design conversations where participants analyze work. Feedback: Observation → Principle → Impact → (Optional suggestion).</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>design-critique</tag>
      <tag>feedback</tag>
      <tag>design-review</tag>
      <tag>collaboration</tag>
      <tag>async</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Design Critique</title>

    <summary>Design critique is a structured conversation about a design where participants analyze work against defined goals and principles, providing specific and actionable feedback. Every piece of feedback must follow: Observation → Principle/Goal → Impact → (Optional suggestion). Feedback not tied to a stated goal is opinion, not critique.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Unstructured design reviews become opinion battles where personal preferences override user evidence. Structured critique produces specific, goal-anchored feedback that the designer can act on. The Observation → Principle → Impact chain forces reviewers to justify feedback, filtering taste from insight.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-session preparation: generating a structured critique brief from design goals and constraints</item>
        <item>Async critique: reviewing a design description against stated goals and producing structured feedback</item>
        <item>Post-session synthesis: organizing critique notes into prioritized action items</item>
        <item>Solo work: using an agent as a structured sounding board when no human reviewers are available</item>
        <item>Training designers to give and receive goal-based feedback</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Replacing human critique sessions — critique is partly a social alignment process that builds shared design language</item>
        <item>When design goals are undefined — critique without objectives degrades to preference-based feedback</item>
        <item>Final production polish decisions — agent cannot assess micro-interaction feel or animation timing</item>
        <item>When stakeholder buy-in is the primary goal — human-led critique creates co-ownership</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="critique-vs-criticism">
      <p>Critique: based on stated goals, specific and actionable, about the work, asks questions, improves design.</p>
      <p>Criticism: based on personal preference, vague, about the designer, makes judgments, hurts feelings.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every piece of feedback must be connected to a stated design goal or usability principle.</statement>
        <rationale>Feedback not anchored to a goal is preference; preference-based feedback cannot be evaluated objectively and degrades into opinion battles.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="roles">
      <p>Presenter — shows work, states goals and constraints, asks for specific feedback type.</p>
      <p>Facilitator — keeps discussion on track, ensures all voices are heard, redirects opinion to goals.</p>
      <p>Participants — ask clarifying questions before giving feedback, connect observations to goals.</p>
      <p>Note-taker — captures key feedback, questions raised, decisions made, action items.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The presenter decides what feedback to incorporate; it is their design, their call.</statement>
        <rationale>Removing designer agency from critique sessions destroys ownership and produces resentful implementation; the presenter's authority over their work must be explicit.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="stage-appropriate-feedback">
      <p>Directional feedback (Is this the right approach?) — for exploration stage; many options open.</p>
      <p>Refinement feedback (How can this be better?) — for iteration stage; one direction being developed.</p>
      <p>Polish feedback (Is this ready to ship?) — for final stage; micro-decisions and completeness.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>State the design stage before showing designs; polish feedback on exploration work is harmful.</statement>
        <rationale>Polish feedback on early exploration locks in a direction prematurely and wastes time debating details that may be discarded.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="five-step-process">
      <p>Step 1: Set context — problem, user, constraints, stage, feedback type requested.</p>
      <p>Step 2: Present the work systematically — explain decisions made, point out areas of uncertainty, do not over-apologize.</p>
      <p>Step 3: Clarifying questions — participants ask to understand, not judge, before giving feedback.</p>
      <p>Step 4: Give structured feedback — Observation → Principle/Goal → Impact → (Optional suggestion).</p>
      <p>Step 5: Capture and prioritize — note-taker documents feedback, questions, decisions, and action items.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Well-formed feedback">
        <note>Observation: "The submit button is below the fold." Principle: "Users frequently miss below-fold CTAs on mobile." Impact: "This could hurt conversion on small screens." Suggestion: "What if we added a sticky footer button?"</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Preference-based feedback">
        <note>"I don't like the colors." — preference statement with no observation, no principle, no impact. Not actionable.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="giving-feedback-rules">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Limit major concerns to five items maximum per critique session.</statement>
        <rationale>Longer lists dilute priority and overwhelm the designer; five major concerns force prioritization and produce actionable output.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Ask clarifying questions before giving feedback; do not assume you understand the constraint space.</statement>
        <rationale>Feedback based on misunderstood constraints wastes the session and erodes trust; clarification first prevents this.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Provide at least two observations about what is working well, not only concerns.</statement>
        <rationale>Critique that identifies only problems gives the designer no signal about what to preserve; positive observations are as valuable as negative ones for iteration.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>No stated design goals before critique begins.</description>
        <reason>Feedback without criteria defaults to taste; the session degrades into preference-based debate with no resolution mechanism.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Solutioning instead of critiquing — redesigning the product in the meeting.</description>
        <reason>The critique session is for analysis and feedback, not real-time redesign; solutioning prevents the designer from incorporating multiple feedback sources into their own solution.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Presenter defending every point instead of listening.</description>
        <reason>Defensive presenter blocks feedback reception; thanking participants for honest feedback is the appropriate response during the session.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-usage-rules">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Provide a list of decisions already made (not open for discussion) when requesting agent critique.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent may critique deliberate trade-offs it is unaware of; pre-specifying closed decisions prevents churn on settled questions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Require agent to steelman the current design before critiquing when used for solo work.</statement>
        <rationale>Steelmanning surfaces the designer's own rationale explicitly and produces more balanced critique output.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Agent critique output is a starting point for human review, not the final critique record.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent cannot replicate the back-and-forth clarification dynamic of real critique, and it may contradict design system rules it is unaware of.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A Claude subagent receives: (1) a design brief (problem, user, constraints, stage), (2) design goals with success criteria, and (3) a description of the design (screen-by-screen walkthrough, element list, or annotated screenshot text). It outputs structured critique in the standardized format (Observation → Principle/Goal → Impact → Optional suggestion), organized by severity: Major concerns first, then Minor, then Positive observations. A second optional pass compresses the critique into a prioritized action item table for the presenter.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-sdd-executor-agent to manage critique sessions as structured SDD tasks with input/output artifacts, or a general Claude subagent with reviewer role to generate the critique document from design description.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Figma REST API: Export frame/component tree as JSON for structured agent input.</p>
      <p>jq: Parse Figma JSON exports to extract element names, types, and hierarchy.</p>
      <p>Loom CLI: Share screen recordings of prototype walkthroughs for async critique (web interface).</p>
      <p>Playwright: Screenshot specific flows in a live prototype for structured agent review.</p>
      <p>Figma (SaaS, partial REST): Export frame structure; agent reads element tree but not rendered visuals without vision.</p>
      <p>Loom (SaaS): Async video critique; useful for human reviewers, not for agent input.</p>
      <p>Notion (SaaS, API): Store critique sessions, action items, and decisions; agent writes structured output via API.</p>
      <p>Linear (SaaS, API): Convert critique action items directly to design tickets.</p>
      <p>GitHub Discussions (API): Async critique threads for design work stored in repos; agent can post/parse via GitHub API.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Always include the design stage in the critique request — agent feedback calibrated for "Exploration" looks different from "Polish"</item>
        <item>Provide stated design goals with measurable success criteria; without them, agent critique defaults to generic heuristics</item>
        <item>Require the agent to limit feedback to 5 major concerns maximum — longer lists dilute priority and overwhelm the designer</item>
        <item>Run the Observation → Principle → Impact chain strictly; reject agent outputs that skip the principle/goal link</item>
        <item>Use agent critique output as a starting point for human review, not as the final critique record</item>
        <item>For solo work, ask agent to steelman the current design before critiquing — this surfaces the designer's own rationale explicitly</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/critique-session.md" purpose="Full critique session doc: context, design goals, notes, action items, decisions"/>
      <template path="templates/feedback-framework.md" purpose="Observation → Principle → Impact → Suggestion format with worked example"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/design-critiques/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/how-to-run-a-design-critique"/>
      <link href="https://basecamp.com/shapeup"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
