<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Certificate Rotation Pipeline (cert-manager / Terraform / Compose) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the cicd-cert-rotation-pipeline methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced by the decision tree.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="no-private-keys-in-git" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Private keys MUST NOT be committed to Git; the pipeline MUST emit keys only into a secrets manager (Vault, AWS Secrets Manager, K8s Secret) and reference them by name.</statement>
      <rationale source="OWASP Cryptographic Storage Cheat Sheet">Private keys in Git are unrecoverable from a security standpoint — rotation cost is non-trivial and historical exposure is permanent.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="iac-author-render-scan-apply" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pipeline MUST follow author → render → scan → apply: cert-manager Certificate CRD or Terraform module is authored; CI renders effective YAML; a scanner (`kubectl-validate`, `tflint`) gates; only then is it applied.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal IaC review">Direct kubectl apply bypasses review and lint; render-scan-apply is the minimum safe path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="renewal-30-days-before-expiry" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Renewal MUST trigger at least 30 days before NotAfter; cert-manager's `spec.renewBefore` MUST be set explicitly (not relying on the 2/3-lifetime default for short-lived certs).</statement>
      <rationale source="cert-manager docs — Certificate Resource">Without an explicit `renewBefore`, short-lived certs may renew too late; explicit configuration is the safe path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="expiry-alert-7-days" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prometheus MUST alert when any certificate in the cluster has &lt; 7 days to expiry; cert-manager metrics `certmanager_certificate_expiration_timestamp_seconds` MUST be scraped.</statement>
      <rationale source="cert-manager docs — Metrics">Renewal failures are silent until the alert fires; 7 days is the floor for operator response.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="issuer-isolated-per-env" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each environment MUST use its own ClusterIssuer / Terraform ACM module; staging and prod MUST NOT share an issuer.</statement>
      <rationale source="cert-manager docs — Issuers, Internal security review">Shared issuers cross-pollinate rate-limit budgets and create blast-radius coupling between environments.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If TLS termination is fully handled by a managed load balancer (AWS ALB + ACM, GCP HTTPS LB + Google-managed cert) with auto-renewal, this methodology MUST be skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS ACM docs, GCP managed cert docs">Managed-LB certs renew transparently; an IaC pipeline duplicates and risks drift.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
