<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="topical-authority Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for topical-authority. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Structure content as topic clusters: one pillar page (broad overview of the topic) supported by 8-30 cluster articles (specific subtopics), with bidirectional internal links between them.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Google's helpful-content and semantic-relevance systems assess topical coverage, not just individual keyword optimisation. A cluster of 10-30 interlinking articles on RAG signals deeper expertise than a single article — even one highly optimised for the target keyword. AI Overviews preferentially cite recognised topical authorities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Answer all related questions, cover edge cases, and refresh content at least every 6 months — comprehensive coverage signals topical expertise more than article length alone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Google's helpful-content evaluation rewards content that fully satisfies user intent. Thin cluster articles that repeat what the pillar already covers dilute rather than amplify authority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Link from pillar to all cluster articles; link from each cluster article back to the pillar and to 2-4 related clusters; use keyword-rich anchor text that describes the destination content.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Internal linking distributes PageRank across the cluster and signals to Google that these pages form a related content group. Anchor text reinforces keyword relevance without the manipulation risk of external anchor text over-optimisation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
