<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-topic-clusters" title="Topical Authority via Topic Clusters">
  <summary>Build topical authority through the pillar-cluster model: one comprehensive pillar page plus supporting subtopic articles, all internally linked.</summary>

  <section title="Core Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure content as topic clusters: one pillar page (broad overview of the topic) supported by multiple cluster articles (specific subtopics), with bidirectional internal links between them.</statement>
      <rationale>Google's algorithms assess topical coverage, not just individual keyword optimization. A cluster of 10-30 interlinking articles on RAG signals deeper expertise than a single article — even one highly optimized for the target keyword.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Pillar: "Complete Guide to RAG" linking to cluster articles: "What is RAG?", "RAG vs Fine-tuning", "RAG Architecture Patterns", "RAG Evaluation Methods", "RAG Tools Comparison", "RAG Case Studies"</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Publishing standalone articles targeting individual keywords without cluster structure</description>
      <reason>Without topical coverage depth, individual articles compete against established authorities that already cover the full topic — a fight you lose unless your domain has equivalent overall authority.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Depth Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Answer all related questions, cover edge cases, and update content regularly — comprehensive coverage signals topical expertise more than article length alone.</statement>
      <rationale>Google's "helpful content" evaluation rewards content that fully satisfies user intent. Thin cluster articles that repeat what the pillar already covers dilute rather than amplify authority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Pillar page: comprehensive overview, 2000+ words, links to all cluster articles</item>
      <item>Cluster articles: deep coverage of specific subtopic, link back to pillar and related clusters</item>
      <item>Answer "People Also Ask" questions within the cluster</item>
      <item>Cover edge cases and advanced scenarios in dedicated cluster articles</item>
      <item>Update cluster articles when the topic evolves — stale content degrades authority</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="External Authority Signals">
    <list>
      <item>Quality backlinks to pillar and cluster pages</item>
      <item>Brand mentions in industry publications</item>
      <item>Social signals and expert citations</item>
      <item>Author credentials and expertise signals (About page, author bios)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Internal Linking Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Link from pillar to all cluster articles; link from each cluster article back to the pillar and to related clusters; use keyword-rich anchor text that describes the destination content.</statement>
      <rationale>Internal linking distributes PageRank across the cluster and signals to Google that these pages form a related content group. Anchor text reinforces keyword relevance without the manipulation risk of external anchor text over-optimization.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
