<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spatial-interaction-patterns">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Five input modalities (hands, controllers, gaze, voice, gesture) and three patterns (direct, ray-casting, gaze+dwell) for XR interfaces with accessibility guidance.</summary>
    <category>spatial</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>spatial-interaction</tag>
      <tag>xr</tag>
      <tag>input-modality</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
      <tag>gesture</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Spatial Interaction Patterns</title>

    <summary>Reference for the five input modalities in spatial/XR interfaces (hand tracking, controllers, gaze, voice, gesture) and the three primary interaction patterns (direct manipulation, ray-casting, gaze+dwell) with their respective use cases, strengths, and accessibility implications.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Spatial interfaces support multiple simultaneous input modalities; choosing the wrong primary modality for a task leads to arm fatigue (gorilla arm), precision errors, or excluded user groups. Mapping task type to input modality early in design prevents these problems at prototype stage rather than after development.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing interaction flows for an XR application</item>
        <item>Selecting primary and fallback input modalities for a spatial feature</item>
        <item>Evaluating an existing XR interaction for accessibility (gaze+dwell as motor-impairment fallback)</item>
        <item>Writing interaction specifications for XR developers</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>2D touch or mouse-based interfaces — different interaction model</item>
        <item>Voice-only VUI design — use error-handling-in-vui or vui-accessibility-inclusivity instead</item>
        <item>Platform selection decisions — use spatial-computing-overview instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="input-modalities">
      <list>
        <item>Hand tracking: direct manipulation of virtual objects; most natural feel; requires clear camera view of hands; best for close-range interactions</item>
        <item>Controllers: precise 6DOF input with physical haptic feedback; best for gaming, creative work, and precision tasks; less natural than hand tracking</item>
        <item>Gaze: selection and navigation via eye direction; best for accessibility, passive browsing, and cursor replacement; requires dwell confirmation to avoid Midas touch</item>
        <item>Voice: text entry, commands, navigation; best for hands-free contexts and when hands are gloved or occupied; sensitive to noise and recognition errors</item>
        <item>Gesture: defined hand poses for shortcuts (thumbs up, peace sign); best for frequent quick actions; requires user training; recognition less reliable than explicit input</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Design at minimum two input modalities for every interaction: a primary modality and a fallback. Gaze+dwell serves as the universal accessibility fallback for users with motor impairments who cannot perform hand gestures.</statement>
        <rationale>Single-modality XR interfaces exclude users whose primary modality is unavailable (gloved hands, controller battery, arm fatigue); a fallback is a functional accessibility requirement.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="direct-manipulation">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use direct manipulation (grab, pinch-resize, two-hand rotate, throw) for objects within arm's reach in the interaction zone. Provide physics-based feedback — resistance, snap-to-grid, collision — to make virtual objects feel real.</statement>
        <rationale>Direct manipulation maps to existing physical world intuitions and requires no learned grammar; it is the most learnable interaction pattern for new XR users.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Requiring sustained arm extension above shoulder height for direct manipulation of frequently accessed objects.</description>
        <reason>Sustained arm elevation (gorilla arm) causes rapid muscle fatigue and is the primary cause of session abandonment in training and productivity XR applications.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="ray-casting">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use ray-casting (laser pointer from hand or controller) for selecting objects at distance, activating menus, and interacting with wall-mounted or ceiling-mounted content. Require an explicit confirmation action (click, pinch) to prevent accidental activation.</statement>
        <rationale>Ray-casting extends the interaction range beyond arm's reach without requiring physical movement; it is the standard far-field interaction pattern across platforms.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Ray-casting with gaze highlight and pinch confirmation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Pattern: Gaze highlights target → Ray confirms pointing → Pinch activates
Use for: menu items, far panels, ceiling-mounted status displays
Avoid for: precise 3D manipulation where direct touch is more accurate
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="gaze-and-dwell">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use gaze+dwell (look at target for 1-2 seconds to activate) as the accessibility fallback for any interaction that normally uses hand or controller input. Display a visible countdown indicator during the dwell period.</statement>
        <rationale>Gaze+dwell enables full XR interaction for users with motor impairments who cannot perform hand gestures or hold controllers; the countdown indicator confirms intent and prevents surprise activations.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Set dwell time to a minimum of 1 second for destructive actions and 0.5 seconds for safe, reversible selections. Make dwell time configurable in accessibility settings.</statement>
        <rationale>Fixed dwell times that are too short cause accidental activations (Midas touch); too long causes fatigue; individual variability requires a configurable range.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration">
      <p>Use Claude as an "interaction-pattern selector": given a feature spec + target headset, it returns a primary modality, a fallback, and the gesture spec (event names, dwell timings, haptic cues). A second pass generates platform-specific scaffolding — Unity XR Interaction Toolkit components, RealityKit Gesture modifiers, or WebXR XRInputSource handlers. Hand off to a developer subagent for code-level implementation; reserve a human in-headset session for ergonomics sign-off before merge.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: general-purpose Claude subagent for modality selection + interaction spec; faion-sdd-executor-agent to implement once spec is approved; custom xr-gesture-author prompt to emit Unity / RealityKit / WebXR gesture stubs from JSON spec.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <list>
        <item>Unity XR Interaction Toolkit (UPM): Standard XR input abstraction (com.unity.xr.interaction.toolkit)</item>
        <item>OpenXR Loader (Unity / Unreal): Cross-vendor XR runtime (https://www.khronos.org/openxr/)</item>
        <item>Apple xcrun simctl + visionOS sim: Test interactions in simulator (Xcode 15+)</item>
        <item>Meta ovrmetricstool: Measure hand-tracking jitter / latency (Quest Developer Hub)</item>
        <item>webxr-emulator (Chrome ext.): Debug WebXR XRInputSource events (https://github.com/MozillaReality/WebXR-emulator-extension)</item>
        <item>gltf-transform: Bake interaction colliders into glTF (npm i -g @gltf-transform/cli)</item>
      </list>
      <p>SaaS services: Unity XR Interaction Toolkit (OSS, UPM, Unity CLI); Apple RealityKit (OS framework, Swift codegen); Meta Interaction SDK (OSS, hand-tracking pose library); Microsoft MRTK3 (OSS, UPM, HoloLens + cross-platform); ShapesXR (SaaS, no public API); WebXR Device API (web standard, JS codegen); Ultraleap (SaaS+SDK, mid-air haptics + hand tracking).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>One primary modality per feature; secondary is a fallback, not a co-equal.</item>
        <item>Ray-cast for far (&gt; 0.8 m), direct-grab for near (&lt; 0.8 m); never mix in the same target.</item>
        <item>Always include haptic / audio confirmation; visual-only feedback is insufficient in XR.</item>
        <item>Respect Vision Pro's eye+pinch convention — don't invent a gaze-dwell pattern users have to relearn.</item>
        <item>Provide a "rest pose" for hands; constant arm-up gestures cause gorilla arm in &lt; 60 s.</item>
        <item>Map every gesture to a discoverable affordance (highlight, glow, label); XR has no tooltips.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Claude conflates Vision Pro and Quest interaction grammars; pin the headset name explicitly in every prompt.</item>
        <item>Hand-tracking false positives (pinch detected on grab) are invisible to the agent; require human QA.</item>
        <item>Agent may suggest "swipe in air" patterns that have no physical anchor — they fail in practice.</item>
        <item>Generated Unity XRI code often targets deprecated 1.x API; pin XRI 2.5+ in the prompt.</item>
        <item>Privacy: gaze data is biometric; agent should warn before logging eye-tracking events to analytics.</item>
        <item>Don't let an agent auto-tune dwell time; sub-optimal values trigger nausea or false selections.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/eyes"/>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/gestures"/>
      <link href="https://developers.meta.com/horizon/design/hands-design-intro/"/>
      <link href="https://docs.unity3d.com/Packages/com.unity.xr.interaction.toolkit@2.5/manual/index.html"/>
      <link href="https://www.khronos.org/openxr/"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/mixed-reality/design/interaction-fundamentals"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
