<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Multimodal VUI Design Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six testable rules grounding the multimodal voice-UI spec. Every rule pairs a binary check with a rationale and an attributable source.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-asr-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The spec MUST declare a Word Error Rate (WER) budget for each target language and a recovery ladder for utterances that exceed it. WER without a recovery ladder is a half-spec.</statement>
      <rationale source="ASR research; Apple Siri / Google Assistant published guidelines">Real-world WER varies by language, accent, and noise. Without a budget the team ships voice features that fail silently on minority accents; without a recovery ladder the same utterance loops forever instead of falling back to visual or a different intent.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-persona-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Persona voice constraints (pitch range, formality, locale-specific cadence) MUST be signed off by brand before TTS samples ship to engineering. Default vendor voices are not a persona decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brand voice audits 2024-2025; Mailchimp voice &amp; tone guidelines">Default TTS voices erode brand equity — every product sounds the same. Forcing brand sign-off at spec time prevents post-launch persona disputes that block releases.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-language-scope" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The spec MUST list languages covered AND languages explicitly out-of-scope. Implicit "we'll add more later" without a coverage policy is FORBIDDEN.</statement>
      <rationale source="i18n product audits; EU Digital Services Act language guidance">Voice products that ship "English first, others later" without a documented coverage policy accumulate broken edge cases for non-English users that look like quality regressions instead of scope decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-fallback-ladder" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The spec MUST define a fallback ladder: ASR retry → confirm → visual readout → human-or-other-modality. Each rung names its trigger and the dwell time before falling further.</statement>
      <rationale source="Multimodal interaction research; in-car VUI usability studies">Without an explicit ladder, error states become "model retries until the user gives up". A documented ladder is the difference between a polite VUI and a frustrating one.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-a11y-and-haptic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Visual or haptic affordances that support voice MUST be specified per task — including reduced-visual mode, haptic-only confirmations, and screen-reader parity for the same intent.</statement>
      <rationale source="WCAG 2.2 Success Criteria 2.5.4 (Motion Actuation), 1.3.5 (Identify Input Purpose); inclusive design research">Voice-only does not satisfy accessibility for deaf-hard-of-hearing users; visual-only excludes blind users. Multimodal means parity across modalities, not voice with optional visual sugar.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-platform-boundary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When the experience runs inside a third-party voice platform (Alexa, Google Assistant), the spec MUST document which rules the platform owns and which the team owns. Don't re-document what the platform enforces; do document what the platform leaves to the team.</statement>
      <rationale source="Alexa Skills Kit + Google Assistant SDK docs; cross-platform VUI audits">Specs that duplicate platform-owned rules go stale every time the platform changes — and the team owns the maintenance burden. Specs that omit team-owned rules ship platform-default behaviour as if intentional.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the Applies-If preconditions are not met OR any Skip-If disqualifier holds.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory skip leaf">Decision-tree leaves must reference a rule id. The skip leaf needs a real rule so non-applicable inputs route cleanly out instead of producing false-positive verdicts.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
