<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-identification" title="Stakeholder Analysis: Identification, Matrix, and Engagement">
  <summary>Eight stakeholder categories, six-step analysis procedure, influence/impact matrix quadrants, needs/concerns template, and conflict resolution techniques.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Identify Stakeholders">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include a hidden-stakeholders review step covering: legal, infosec, procurement, works council/union, accessibility, and downstream API consumers. Missing a stakeholder is the dominant real-world failure mode.</statement>
      <rationale>Hidden stakeholders discovered after elicitation begins trigger scope changes, re-validation, and delayed sign-offs; finding them at step 1 costs a single conversation. BABOK v3 ch. 3 lists stakeholder identification as a Knowledge Area, not a preliminary task.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Customer — external beneficiary (end users, buyers, partners).</item>
      <item>End User — direct solution users (employees, customers).</item>
      <item>Sponsor — provides resources and authority (executive, budget owner).</item>
      <item>Domain SME — subject matter expert (process owner, specialist, regulator).</item>
      <item>Implementation SME — technical expert (developer, architect, integrator).</item>
      <item>Tester — validates the solution (QA team, UAT participants).</item>
      <item>Regulator — compliance authority (legal, audit, government body).</item>
      <item>Supplier — external provider (vendor, partner, outsourcer).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2-3: Influence/Impact Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map every stakeholder to one of four quadrants and set default engagement cadence by quadrant: Manage Closely (HH) = weekly 1:1, Keep Satisfied (HL) = biweekly summary, Keep Informed (LH) = monthly digest, Monitor (LL) = release-only. Override only with explicit rationale.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholders managed at the wrong cadence either receive information overload (damaging the relationship) or feel ignored (creating resistance); quadrant-driven defaults calibrate engagement without requiring per-stakeholder judgment for every decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the Mitchell-Agle-Wood salience overlay (power × legitimacy × urgency) on top of the matrix for politically sensitive initiatives; flag "definitive" stakeholders (all three) for daily attention.</statement>
      <rationale>The 2x2 matrix collapses multi-dimensional politics into one axis; salience theory adds urgency and legitimacy that explain why some low-title stakeholders have outsized influence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Steps 4-5: Needs, Concerns, and Engagement Plan">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require an evidence: field on every attitude assertion (quote, transcript line, ticket link); without evidence, attitude defaults to "unknown," not "0" (neutral).</statement>
      <rationale>Self-reported attitude is unreliable; people say "supportive" in workshops and undermine in private. Evidence-backed attitude claims are actionable; ungrounded attitude claims are noise that produces wrong engagement strategies.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Triangulate self-reported attitude with at least one behavioral signal (meeting attendance, Slack response time, sponsor escalations, ticket comments) before assigning attitude to any high-influence stakeholder.</statement>
      <rationale>High-influence stakeholders whose actual attitude diverges from stated attitude are the most dangerous source of late-stage resistance; early triangulation enables proactive management.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Conflict Resolution">
    <rule>
      <statement>When two stakeholders have conflicting needs, follow this sequence: understand each position (why, not what) → find common ground → identify trade-offs → escalate to sponsor with options → document decision with rationale.</statement>
      <rationale>Conflicts resolved by position-trading ("you get requirement A, I get requirement B") without understanding underlying interests re-emerge during design and testing. Interest-based resolution produces durable agreements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Facilitated workshop — for groups with multiple conflicting positions.</item>
      <item>One-on-one discussions — for sensitive interpersonal conflicts or political situations.</item>
      <item>Prototype/demo — to clarify misunderstandings caused by abstract requirements.</item>
      <item>Prioritization exercise — to force trade-off choices when all options cannot be delivered.</item>
      <item>Sponsor decision — for conflicts that exceed the BA's authority to resolve.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
