<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="stakeholder-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for stakeholder-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent invents plausible-sounding stakeholders ("VP of Product Excellence") not present in the org chart.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hallucinated stakeholders produce engagement plans with no real recipients; always seed with a real org chart export and reject any name not in the source list unless flagged suggested_to_verify.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent over-classifies all stakeholders as "supportive" (politeness bias).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs are trained on polite discourse and default to positive sentiment; use a 4-way enum (+/0/-/unknown) with unknown as the default and require evidence for + or -.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent conflates stakeholder with persona ("As a Busy Manager persona...").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A stakeholder is a real named human or role with decision power; a persona is a synthesized archetype for design. Conflating them produces engagement plans targeting archetypes, not real people with authority.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent equates influence with seniority — ranks CFO highest influence by default.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Influence flows through indirect networks; the CFO's EA may have more influence on calendar decisions than the CFO. Force the agent to consider gatekeepers, information brokers, and informal leaders, not just org chart level.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent bulk-reclassifies 50 stakeholders in a single run.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Bulk reclassification of attitude fields is reputationally toxic if wrong; cap agent actions to 5 stakeholders per run and require human review on the diff.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
