<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<playbook id="01-playbook" slug="tm-to-fixed-price-contract-conversion-6-weeks" goal="TBD" complexity="deep">
  <intent>From the initial trigger to the closed outcome described in scope, deliver every artefact named in success_criteria without skipping the decision gates between stages.</intent>
  <scope>Engagement is running on time-and-materials. Client requests conversion to fixed-price for
 the next phase. By end of week 6 Daria has: requirements baseline frozen for phase 2, thr
ee-point estimate with risk reserves, defensible commercial proposal, and a signed contrac
t amendment without the team taking a margin haircut.</scope>
  <success-criteria>
    <criterion>Every stage's decision gate is recorded as passed before the next stage starts.</criterion>
    <criterion>All artefacts named in the stage outputs are produced and signed off.</criterion>
    <criterion>A written close-out record exists for archival and post-mortem.</criterion>
  </success-criteria>
  <stages>
    <stage n="1" name="Scope">
      <intent>Define the scope, exit criteria, and the people who must agree on success.</intent>
      <tasks>
        <task>Restate the scope outcome for this engagement in one sentence.</task>
        <task>Identify who owns the scope output and who must approve it.</task>
        <task>Produce the scope artefact in the agreed format.</task>
      </tasks>
      <methodologies>
        <ref slug="elicitation-techniques" />
        <ref slug="communications-management" />
        <ref slug="schedule-development" />
      </methodologies>
      <outputs>
        <output>Scope artefact (written, signed off)</output>
        <output>Updated decision log entry for the scope step</output>
      </outputs>
      <decision-gate>Advance to the next stage when the scope artefact is approved by the named owner; iterate if any blocker remains.</decision-gate>
    </stage>
    <stage n="2" name="Discovery">
      <intent>Gather evidence about the current state, stakeholders, constraints, and prior data.</intent>
      <tasks>
        <task>Restate the discovery outcome for this engagement in one sentence.</task>
        <task>Identify who owns the discovery output and who must approve it.</task>
        <task>Produce the discovery artefact in the agreed format.</task>
      </tasks>
      <methodologies>
        <ref slug="requirements-prioritization" />
        <ref slug="cost-estimation" />
        <ref slug="scope-management" />
      </methodologies>
      <outputs>
        <output>Discovery artefact (written, signed off)</output>
        <output>Updated decision log entry for the discovery step</output>
      </outputs>
      <decision-gate>Advance to the next stage when the discovery artefact is approved by the named owner; iterate if any blocker remains.</decision-gate>
    </stage>
    <stage n="3" name="Plan">
      <intent>Turn discovery output into a written plan with owners, sequence, and risk reserves.</intent>
      <tasks>
        <task>Restate the plan outcome for this engagement in one sentence.</task>
        <task>Identify who owns the plan output and who must approve it.</task>
        <task>Produce the plan artefact in the agreed format.</task>
      </tasks>
      <methodologies>
        <ref slug="requirements-traceability" />
        <ref slug="lessons-learned" />
        <ref slug="stakeholder-engagement" />
      </methodologies>
      <outputs>
        <output>Plan artefact (written, signed off)</output>
        <output>Updated decision log entry for the plan step</output>
      </outputs>
      <decision-gate>Advance to the next stage when the plan artefact is approved by the named owner; iterate if any blocker remains.</decision-gate>
    </stage>
    <stage n="4" name="Execute">
      <intent>Run the plan in order of dependency; ship each output before moving on.</intent>
      <tasks>
        <task>Restate the execute outcome for this engagement in one sentence.</task>
        <task>Identify who owns the execute output and who must approve it.</task>
        <task>Produce the execute artefact in the agreed format.</task>
      </tasks>
      <methodologies>
        <ref slug="solution-assessment" />
        <ref slug="procurement-management" />
        <ref slug="wbs-creation" />
      </methodologies>
      <outputs>
        <output>Execute artefact (written, signed off)</output>
        <output>Updated decision log entry for the execute step</output>
      </outputs>
      <decision-gate>Advance to the next stage when the execute artefact is approved by the named owner; iterate if any blocker remains.</decision-gate>
    </stage>
    <stage n="5" name="Verify">
      <intent>Check the work against the exit criteria with the people who signed off in Scope.</intent>
      <tasks>
        <task>Restate the verify outcome for this engagement in one sentence.</task>
        <task>Identify who owns the verify output and who must approve it.</task>
        <task>Produce the verify artefact in the agreed format.</task>
      </tasks>
      <methodologies>
        <ref slug="acceptance-criteria" />
        <ref slug="quality-management" />
        <ref slug="earned-value-management" />
      </methodologies>
      <outputs>
        <output>Verify artefact (written, signed off)</output>
        <output>Updated decision log entry for the verify step</output>
      </outputs>
      <decision-gate>Advance to the next stage when the verify artefact is approved by the named owner; iterate if any blocker remains.</decision-gate>
    </stage>
    <stage n="6" name="Communicate">
      <intent>Tell every stakeholder what changed, what's next, and what they own.</intent>
      <tasks>
        <task>Restate the communicate outcome for this engagement in one sentence.</task>
        <task>Identify who owns the communicate output and who must approve it.</task>
        <task>Produce the communicate artefact in the agreed format.</task>
      </tasks>
      <methodologies>
        <ref slug="strategy-analysis-current-state" />
        <ref slug="risk-management" />
        <ref slug="raci-matrix" />
      </methodologies>
      <outputs>
        <output>Communicate artefact (written, signed off)</output>
        <output>Updated decision log entry for the communicate step</output>
      </outputs>
      <decision-gate>Advance to the next stage when the communicate artefact is approved by the named owner; iterate if any blocker remains.</decision-gate>
    </stage>
    <stage n="7" name="Close">
      <intent>Capture lessons, archive the artefacts, and trigger the next-step pipeline.</intent>
      <tasks>
        <task>Restate the close outcome for this engagement in one sentence.</task>
        <task>Identify who owns the close output and who must approve it.</task>
        <task>Produce the close artefact in the agreed format.</task>
      </tasks>
      <methodologies>
        <ref slug="change-control" />
        <ref slug="risk-register" />
      </methodologies>
      <outputs>
        <output>Close artefact (written, signed off)</output>
        <output>Updated decision log entry for the close step</output>
      </outputs>
      <decision-gate>Advance to the next stage when the close artefact is approved by the named owner; iterate if any blocker remains.</decision-gate>
    </stage>
  </stages>
  <gaps>
    <gap slug="tm-to-fp-conversion-playbook" expected-tier="pro" />
    <gap slug="vendor-margin-defense-checklist" expected-tier="pro" />
    <gap slug="change-request-rate-card-template" expected-tier="pro" />
  </gaps>
  <extra key="context" value="[solo]" />
  <extra key="token_budget_estimate" value="17500" />
</playbook>
