<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-overview" title="Overview and core principle">
  <summary>Session-first continuous improvement: Phase 0 (session review) ALWAYS runs first to capture patterns and mistakes from the current conversation into append-only memory files. Phases 1-7 are optional extensions for full audit-brainstorm-apply-log-commit-skill cycles.</summary>

  <section title="Core principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Phase 0 (session review) MUST run on every invocation of the workflow, before any optional extension phase. It extracts patterns, mistakes, and decisions from the current conversation and appends them to `.aidocs/memory/{patterns,mistakes,decisions}.md` in the active project.</statement>
      <rationale>Session context evaporates at compaction. Phase 0 is the cheapest, highest-ROI step in the workflow — it costs nothing beyond a re-read of the current conversation and compounds across sessions because the memory files are append-only. Skipping it means hard-won learnings are lost forever.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Phases 1-7 (Investigate, Classify, Brainstorm, User Approval, Apply, Log, Commit, Skill Creation) are OPTIONAL extensions selected by user intent. The orchestrator MUST NOT auto-chain into them when the user only asked for session capture.</statement>
      <rationale>Most invocations end at Phase 0. Auto-extending into audit or apply phases burns tokens, introduces unrequested risk, and contradicts the user's actual intent. The decision tree (`03-decision-tree.xml`) maps user phrasing to the minimal phase set.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Role split">
    <p>The orchestrator decides which phase runs next based on user intent; parallel subagents perform investigation and apply work; the user gates ALL writes through Phase 3.5 approval. No phase mutates the system without explicit `AskUserQuestion` consent — not even CRITICAL-priority findings.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Orchestrator: phase selection, parallelism, user confirmations, memory-file writes for Phase 0.</item>
      <item>Subagents: investigation (Phase 1), brainstorm (Phase 3), apply (Phase 4), each behind one prompt or delegation contract.</item>
      <item>User: mandatory gate at Phase 3.5 for every change before Phase 4 runs.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Persistent output">
    <p>The four memory files at `.aidocs/memory/` are the workflow's durable artifact. They persist across sessions, are append-only (except `session.md`), and use stable identifier prefixes (`PAT-NNN`, `ERR-NNN`, `DEC-NNN`) so individual entries can be cited from later code review or SDD planning.</p>
    <list>
      <item>`patterns.md` — recurring approaches that worked (PAT-NNN entries).</item>
      <item>`mistakes.md` — errors with root cause and fix (ERR-NNN entries).</item>
      <item>`decisions.md` — non-obvious decisions and their rationale (DEC-NNN entries).</item>
      <item>`session.md` — current session state, overwritten each run.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="04-memory-files.xml">Memory file contract: format, append-vs-overwrite rules, when each is written.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Language convention">
    <rule>
      <statement>User-facing strings (AskUserQuestion options at Phase 3.5, commit messages drafted for review) use Ukrainian. Memory-file entries, code edits, log entries, and prompt files use English.</statement>
      <rationale>Memory files are grep-targets across many sessions; English keeps them searchable. User-facing strings stay in the user's working language.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
