<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-decision-tree" title="User intent to phase mapping">
  <summary>Maps the user's invocation phrasing (Ukrainian or English) to the minimal phase set the orchestrator should run. Phase 0 is implicit in every row except pure Commit (Phase 6) and Skill Creation (Phase 7), which act on already-captured state.</summary>

  <section title="Intent map">
    <list>
      <item>(no args) or "що ми зробили?" or "what did we learn?" → Phase 0 only, because session capture is the entire ask.</item>
      <item>"audit X" or "find issues" or "audit my server" → Phase 0 + Phase 1, because the user wants a system scan on top of session capture.</item>
      <item>"what can be improved?" → Phase 0 + Phase 1 + Phase 2, because the user wants both findings and prioritization.</item>
      <item>"brainstorm improvements" → Phase 0 + Phase 3, because the user wants diverge-converge ideation, not a system scan.</item>
      <item>"fix the issues" → Phase 3.5 + Phase 4, because findings already exist and the user is approving apply, but Phase 3.5 still runs to confirm specific options.</item>
      <item>"log what we did" → Phase 0 + Phase 5, because the user wants the session captured and then written to the dated log.</item>
      <item>"commit improvements" → Phase 6 only, because changes already exist on disk and the user just wants them committed.</item>
      <item>"make a skill from this" → Phase 7 only, because the reusable-knowledge bar is being asserted and Phase 0 has already captured the underlying patterns.</item>
      <item>"full improvement cycle" or "full audit and fix" → all phases (0 through 7), because the user explicitly opted into the complete workflow.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Routing rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>The orchestrator MUST select the minimal phase set consistent with the user's phrasing. When intent is ambiguous, ask via `AskUserQuestion` with 2-3 candidate phase sets — never guess upward into Phase 4 or Phase 6.</statement>
      <rationale>Over-running phases burns tokens and risks unauthorized writes. Under-running is recoverable (the user can re-invoke); over-running is not.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Phase 3.5 MUST run before Phase 4 in every flow that includes Phase 4 — including the "fix the issues" shortcut and the "full improvement cycle" path.</statement>
      <rationale>Phase 3.5 is the security boundary; no apply path is exempt. See `decisions.xml` for the rejected alternative.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
