<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-memory-files" title="Memory file contract">
  <summary>The four memory files at `.aidocs/memory/` are the workflow's durable artifact. Three are append-only with stable identifier prefixes; one is overwritten each session. This file defines the format, when each is written, and the identifier rules.</summary>

  <section title="patterns.md">
    <p>Path: `.aidocs/memory/patterns.md`. Mode: append-only. Identifier prefix: `PAT-NNN` (zero-padded 3 digits, never reused).</p>
    <p>Purpose: recurring approaches that worked across one or more sessions. Each entry describes a reusable technique, the context it applies in, and an example reference.</p>
    <p>Written by: Phase 0 (every invocation). Phase 7 may cite a `PAT-NNN` when promoting a pattern to a full methodology folder.</p>
    <p>Format per entry: `## PAT-NNN: &lt;title&gt;` heading, followed by `**Context:**`, `**Approach:**`, `**Example:**` sub-blocks.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="mistakes.md">
    <p>Path: `.aidocs/memory/mistakes.md`. Mode: append-only. Identifier prefix: `ERR-NNN`.</p>
    <p>Purpose: errors with documented root cause and remediation. Entries describe the symptom, the root cause, and the fix that worked, so future sessions recognize the failure mode early.</p>
    <p>Written by: Phase 0 when something broke or a wrong assumption surfaced. Also by Phase 4 when an apply step failed and the recovery path is worth recording.</p>
    <p>Format per entry: `## ERR-NNN: &lt;title&gt;` heading, followed by `**Symptom:**`, `**Root cause:**`, `**Fix:**` sub-blocks.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="decisions.md">
    <p>Path: `.aidocs/memory/decisions.md`. Mode: append-only. Identifier prefix: `DEC-NNN`.</p>
    <p>Purpose: non-obvious decisions the orchestrator or user took during the session, with the alternative considered and the reason for choosing one over the other. Distinct from the workflow-level `decisions.xml`, which captures workflow-shape decisions, not per-session ones.</p>
    <p>Written by: Phase 0 when a decision surfaced in conversation. Phase 4 when an apply path forked and one branch was chosen.</p>
    <p>Format per entry: `## DEC-NNN: &lt;title&gt;` heading, followed by `**Chose:**`, `**Rejected:**`, `**Rationale:**` sub-blocks.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="session.md">
    <p>Path: `.aidocs/memory/session.md`. Mode: overwritten each invocation (NOT append-only).</p>
    <p>Purpose: snapshot of current-session state — what was active, what is in-flight, what is parked. Read at the start of the next session to re-orient quickly.</p>
    <p>Written by: Phase 0 (always). Phase 5 may update specific subsections during the log step.</p>
    <p>Format: free-form sections — `## Active`, `## In-flight`, `## Parked`, `## Next`. No identifier prefix because entries are not stable.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Identifier rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identifier numbers MUST be assigned by reading the highest existing `PAT-`, `ERR-`, or `DEC-` number in the target file and incrementing by one. Numbers are never reused, even after an entry is later corrected or deleted.</statement>
      <rationale>External references (commits, SDD tickets, code review comments) cite specific identifiers. Reuse silently rewrites history. Append-only plus monotonic identifiers makes the memory files a reliable citation target.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Memory-file edits MUST be additive — never delete or rewrite past entries. To correct a stale entry, append a new one and reference the older identifier in the new entry's body.</statement>
      <rationale>Append-only is the property that makes the memory files trustworthy across sessions. Rewriting past entries breaks citations and erases the learning trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
