<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="05-anti-patterns" title="Anti-patterns to avoid">
  <summary>Failure modes observed during improver runs. Each is named, rejected on sight, and paired with the rule it violates.</summary>

  <section title="Approval gate violations">
    <rule>
      <statement>NEVER apply any improvement without first running Phase 3.5 `AskUserQuestion` approval — including findings labelled CRITICAL.</statement>
      <rationale>CRITICAL is a priority signal, not a consent signal. Auto-applying CRITICAL findings is the historical failure mode this workflow exists to prevent. The user is the security boundary and must explicitly authorize each change.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>NEVER present a single option in Phase 3.5 — every change MUST surface 2-3 alternatives with explicit trade-offs.</statement>
      <rationale>A single-option prompt is a rubber-stamp, not a decision. The user cannot reason about trade-offs they cannot see; alternatives force the orchestrator to think through the design space before asking.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Apply-phase smell">
    <rule>
      <statement>NEVER edit a file in Phase 4 without first reading its current state in the same phase run.</statement>
      <rationale>State drifts between sessions. Editing based on a remembered or assumed file body silently overwrites changes made by another agent or another session. Read-before-edit is the cheapest correctness guarantee.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>NEVER restart a production service in Phase 4 without a second `AskUserQuestion` confirmation, even when the original Phase 3.5 approved the config change.</statement>
      <rationale>Phase 3.5 approves the change; restart is a separate, observable side effect with its own blast radius. Folding the two into one consent step has caused unintended downtime in past runs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Commit-phase smell">
    <rule>
      <statement>NEVER bundle multiple orthogonal improvements into one giant commit in Phase 6 — group by category and produce one commit per logical change.</statement>
      <rationale>Granular commits are the project standard (`feedback_granular_commits` memory entry). Bulk commits are unrevertible, hide root causes during bisect, and conflate unrelated risks for the reviewer.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skill-creation smell">
    <rule>
      <statement>NEVER promote a one-off task to a skill in Phase 7 — only knowledge that is reusable across at least two future contexts qualifies.</statement>
      <rationale>The skills directory is a curated knowledge surface. Adding one-off entries dilutes its signal-to-noise and forces every later reader to filter past noise. The reusable-knowledge bar is enforced at Phase 7 entry.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
