<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="solution-assessment">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-core</domain>
    <summary>Evaluate solution's ability to meet business need and deliver value. Five-step framework: define criteria, assess vs requirements, evaluate business value, identify limitations, recommend action.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>solution</tag>
      <tag>assessment</tag>
      <tag>evaluation</tag>
      <tag>bakok</tag>
      <tag>value</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Solution Assessment</title>
    <summary>Evaluates a solution's ability to meet the business need and deliver expected value across four assessment types: design, implementation, deployment, and post-implementation. Structured five-step framework: define criteria → assess vs requirements → evaluate business value → identify limitations → recommend action.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Solutions are built but value is not measured. Without structured assessment, the gap between promised and delivered value remains invisible, lessons are not captured, and expensive rework repeats on the next initiative. BAKOK Solution Evaluation (KA-6) requires a written limitation register and formal accept/reject recommendation even when the solution is "fine."</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Stage-gate of the BAKOK Solution Evaluation knowledge area: "does the solution deliver enterprise value?" against the original business need.</item>
        <item>Design and implementation assessments inside the build phase ("are we still on the right path?").</item>
        <item>Pre go-live deployment readiness review where multiple workstreams must produce one accept/reject row.</item>
        <item>30/90/365-day post-implementation reviews scoring requirements compliance and benefit realization.</item>
        <item>Solution limitations capture for compliance, audit, or vendor-renewal files.</item>
        <item>Lessons-learned input to the next iteration's strategy analysis (current state → future state).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Continuous-discovery pre-PMF work where requirements are still being invented every sprint — "REQ-001 met" is meaningless when REQ-001 was wrong.</item>
        <item>Throwaway prototypes, spikes, internal tools used by a handful of people — a 15-minute retro replaces the whole template.</item>
        <item>Pure SRE/platform tuning (latency, cost, capacity) — use SLOs and error budgets.</item>
        <item>When no baseline exists — without a measured "before," the variance column is vibes; back-fill the baseline first.</item>
        <item>When the assessor reports to the project sponsor whose bonus depends on the result — route to an independent reviewer.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="assessment-types">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Select assessment type before gathering evidence; each type has a different question and artefact.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing assessment types produces evidence that answers the wrong question — testing deployment readiness with post-implementation metrics, or measuring business value during the design phase.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Design Assessment (during design): validate the proposed solution design against requirements.</item>
        <item>Implementation Assessment (during build): verify correct implementation at sprint boundaries.</item>
        <item>Deployment Assessment (at go-live): confirm readiness across QA, training, ops, support, security, compliance workstreams.</item>
        <item>Post-Implementation Assessment (after deployment): measure actual value delivered against the original business case.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="five-step-process">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run assessment as a five-step linear pipeline; do not skip or reorder steps.</statement>
        <rationale>Step 3 (business value evaluation) depends on Step 1 criteria and Step 2 compliance data; skipping or reordering produces variance columns filled with storytelling rather than measurement.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Step 1 — Define criteria: business value, functional, performance, usability, compliance.</item>
        <item>Step 2 — Assess against requirements: compare solution to each requirement, classify as met/partial/not met/deprecated.</item>
        <item>Step 3 — Evaluate business value: measure delivered value against baseline, target, and variance.</item>
        <item>Step 4 — Identify limitations: document gaps with impact and workaround columns.</item>
        <item>Step 5 — Recommend action: accept / accept with conditions / require changes / reject.</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Add "deprecated" as a first-class requirement status alongside met/partial/not met; do not force stale requirements into not-met.</statement>
        <rationale>Forcing every legacy requirement written 9 months before go-live into met/not-met inflates the not-met count and wastes remediation tokens on requirements that were consciously retired.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="assessment-triggers">
      <list>
        <item>Design complete → Design review.</item>
        <item>Sprint complete → Implementation check.</item>
        <item>Before go-live → Deployment readiness (gate: all workstreams ready/conditional/blocked with one evidence item each).</item>
        <item>30 days post go-live → Initial post-implementation assessment.</item>
        <item>90 days post go-live → Full post-implementation assessment.</item>
        <item>Annually → Ongoing value assessment.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="independence-rule">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Route the assessment through someone whose compensation does not depend on the verdict; do not let the project sponsor's team self-assess.</statement>
        <rationale>BAKOK Solution Evaluation explicitly requires independence; assessments conducted by teams whose bonuses depend on the outcome systematically overstate value realization.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="measurement-failures">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Capturing the baseline at assessment time rather than at requirements freeze.</description>
        <reason>The "baseline" silently becomes "yesterday" and variance is zero by construction — the assessment proves nothing and is unfalsifiable.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating requirements compliance as equivalent to value realization: reporting "100% requirements met" without measuring business outcomes.</description>
        <reason>A solution can be 100% requirements-met and 0% value-realized; the report must surface the functional-met vs benefit-realized split explicitly.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Reporting metric variance (e.g., revenue +18%) as caused by the solution without controlling for external factors.</description>
        <reason>Market tailwinds, competitor outages, or compensation-plan changes can produce the same variance. Without a control group or diff-in-diff, confidence must be marked low and external factors flagged.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="scope-and-timing-failures">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running a single 30-day post-launch assessment and treating it as definitive.</description>
        <reason>At 30 days, users are in honeymoon mode; 12-month assessments consistently show lower satisfaction and surfaced friction that the 30-day report misses. One-shot assessments systematically overstate success.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Assessing adoption (usage rate) as a proxy for value delivered.</description>
        <reason>Mandatory rollouts always show high adoption; only paired cycle-time or output metrics reveal whether the adoption was beneficial or destructive.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>User satisfaction surveys that do not reconcile survey respondent count against active-user count.</description>
        <reason>Surveys reach still-active users; n=50 with a 4.2 score can hide 200 silent leavers. Always cross-reference survey n against active user count; reject satisfaction claims where n/active-users is below a documented threshold (e.g., 10%).</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="llm-specific-failures">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Force every requirements compliance row to include an evidence_ref that resolves to a source; drop any row where evidence is missing rather than inventing a value.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs will fill in "actual" values when evidence is missing; fabricated metrics produce false accept/reject verdicts.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Generate the recommendation as a single enum (accept | accept_with_conditions | require_changes | reject) before any prose; prose must be derived from, not instead of, the enum.</statement>
        <rationale>LLM recommendation prose hedges by default ("consider exploring"); forcing an enum first prevents verdict ambiguity.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>At ba-core level, Solution Assessment is a five-step linear pipeline matching the framework (Define Criteria → Assess vs Requirements → Evaluate Value → Identify Limitations → Recommend Actions). Drive it as five short subagent calls, each emitting a structured fragment that the next step consumes; only the Recommend step produces prose. The BA subagent stays the orchestrator and the human signs the cover memo — agents never decide accept/reject alone.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>improver — natural home for cron-driven 30 / 60 / 90-day post-launch re-assessments; reads the prior report, deltas the metrics, and files the next version.</item>
        <item>sdd-execution — converts the Step 5 Recommendations list into SDD remediation tasks, one task per Not Met requirement or Critical issue.</item>
        <item>feature-executor — executes the bounded remediation tasks generated above (bug fixes, missing features, training rollout) under the accept-with-conditions verdict.</item>
        <item>brainstorm — when the verdict is Reject or limitations are systemic, run diverge / converge before committing to a v2 design.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Lock metric definitions in the original business case and re-verify them at assessment time. Once the team knows the success number, the underlying definition will drift.</item>
        <item>Capture the baseline at requirements freeze. If you wait until assessment time, the "baseline" silently becomes "yesterday" and the variance is zero by construction.</item>
        <item>Run assessments at multiple horizons (30 / 90 / 365 days). One-shot 30-day reports systematically overstate success because users are still in honeymoon mode.</item>
        <item>Keep `deprecated` as a first-class requirement status. Forcing every legacy requirement into Met / Not Met inflates the Not Met count and wastes remediation tokens.</item>
        <item>Pull the issues register from the ticketing system over the full review window — never from team memory. Recency bias inflates whatever broke last week.</item>
        <item>Score functional plus value separately. A solution can be 100% requirements-met and 0% value-realized; the report must surface both splits explicitly.</item>
        <item>Control for external factors. Without a control group or diff-in-diff, mark confidence low and flag market, organizational, or technical variables that could explain the variance.</item>
        <item>Reconcile survey sample size against active users. n=50 with a 4.2 score can hide 200 silent leavers; reject satisfaction claims where n/active-users is below documented threshold.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>gh — Pull issues, PRs, release notes that feed the issues register.</item>
        <item>jira-cli (ankitpokhrel) — Pull Jira tickets / epics for the requirements compliance matrix.</item>
        <item>linear-cli — Same for teams on Linear.</item>
        <item>pandoc — Convert the assessment-report Markdown template to PDF / DOCX for sign-off.</item>
        <item>csvkit (csvgrep, csvstat) — Slice survey / ticket exports without spinning up a notebook.</item>
        <item>duckdb — One-binary SQL over CSV / Parquet exports for the variance and adoption math.</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc) — Render the assessment-flow / decision diagrams referenced from the report.</item>
        <item>ruff (project lint gate) — Required for any helper scripts checked in alongside the report.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <list>
        <item>Jira / Confluence (Atlassian, SaaS) — Source of truth for requirements compliance plus the report's home page.</item>
        <item>Linear (SaaS) — Same role for product-led teams.</item>
        <item>GitHub Issues / Projects (SaaS / OSS) — Issues register plus remediation tracking.</item>
        <item>Mixpanel / Amplitude / PostHog (SaaS / OSS) — Adoption, feature usage, funnel metrics for Step 3.</item>
        <item>GA4 plus BigQuery export (SaaS) — Public-traffic value metrics.</item>
        <item>Tableau / Power BI / Metabase (SaaS / OSS) — Render the variance dashboards linked from the report.</item>
        <item>Qualtrics / SurveyMonkey / Typeform (SaaS) — User feedback ratings table; agent must reconcile n vs active users.</item>
        <item>Zendesk / Intercom / Freshdesk (SaaS) — Issues themes via topic clustering of tickets.</item>
        <item>Pendo / WalkMe (SaaS) — Adoption plus in-app NPS for usability score.</item>
        <item>Google Forms plus Sheets API (SaaS) — Lightweight option for internal solutions.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/solution-assessment-report.md" purpose="Full assessment report with requirements compliance, business value, user feedback, and recommendations."/>
      <template path="templates/post-implementation-review.md" purpose="Post-go-live review template covering outcomes, adoption metrics, lessons learned."/>
    </templates>

  </content>
</methodology>
