<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Indie Hacker Tax and Legal Essentials Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Indie Hacker Tax and Legal Essentials application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-mor-vs-direct-decision" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decide MoR (Paddle, Lemon Squeezy, Stripe Tax/Tax handles VAT) vs direct invoicing (you handle VAT) BEFORE first sale. Choice depends on margin tolerance + ops capacity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">MoR adds 5-8% fee but offloads VAT + chargeback compliance; direct keeps margin but you handle VAT MOSS, registrations, returns.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-entity-shape-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick entity shape from: home-country sole-trader, home-country LLC, Estonia OÜ via e-Residency, US LLC for non-residents, UK Ltd. Each has tax-treaty + banking implications.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Wrong entity = repeated structural costs (tax treaty conflicts, banking refusals, double-taxation).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-advisor-engaged-before-first-sale" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Engage a tax advisor familiar with cross-border digital sales BEFORE first sale. Not after.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Retroactive cleanup costs 3-10× advisor-up-front; advisor fees are tiny vs penalties.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-revenue-trigger-thresholds" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document revenue thresholds that trigger registrations: EU VAT (€10k OSS), UK VAT (£90k), US sales-tax nexus (per state, varies), home-country thresholds.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Triggers fire silently; without monitoring, registrations are missed; penalties accrue.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-bank-pii-data-residency" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Banking + payment-processor choice considers data residency + sanctions screening. Wrong bank = frozen account at scale.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mercury, Wise, Revolut Business, local fintech">Banks frequently de-risk cross-border SaaS; pick a bank that explicitly supports it (Mercury, Wise, Revolut Business, local fintech).</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>