<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="templates Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for templates as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Generating all documents in one pass without waiting for review gates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Design errors compound if not caught early. Testing gaps don't surface until implementation. Reviews gate quality; skipping them trades short-term speed for long-term cost.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Task.md files generated without reading design.md; task scopes are mis-sized or misaligned.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Task generation requires design context. Agents without design create tasks that violate architecture or miss dependencies.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Feature folder naming collisions (feature-024-starter-kits) causing silent overwrites.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents don't detect existing folders by default. Always check .aidocs/ before creating new feature folders.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents skip the traceability check: tasks don't reference implementation-plan rows, rows don't reference design decisions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without traceability, executor agents lose context. Always verify that each task.md references the implementation-plan row and design AD.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Token budget estimates in implementation-plan become stale after context is loaded.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Reading 20k-token codebase evaporates budget fast. Add 20k buffer for agents reading large existing code.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents writing multiple files in one turn silently truncate later files when approaching context limits.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generate documents in separate turns or verify file sizes before merging. Monitor agent output for truncation patterns.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
