<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Notion PM Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every Notion PM workspace must enforce. These are HARD rules — convenience does not override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-three-database-schema" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Workspace uses exactly three core databases: Projects (initiatives), Tasks (work items), Sprints (iterations). Relations link Tasks→Projects and Tasks→Sprints bidirectionally; Rollups compute progress without duplicating data.</statement>
      <rationale source="Notion docs + practitioner experience">Flat databases force manual status tracking; relational + rollups compute project progress, sprint velocity, and workload automatically from task data.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-property-cap-20" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each database has ≤20 properties. Archive any property not used in a view, rollup, or automation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Notion docs">Databases with many properties (especially formula-heavy) load in 3-8s and degrade workspace UX. Lean schemas stay fast.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-status-not-select" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use the Status property type (Not Started / In Progress / Complete groups) for task workflow. Select is forbidden for state because it cannot render progress rings in relation views.</statement>
      <rationale source="Notion docs">Status is purpose-built for workflow tracking and enables native progress visualisation Select cannot replicate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-rollups-not-formulas" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Computed aggregates over related rows (count, sum, % complete) use Rollups, never Formulas that iterate prop("relation"). Formulas may post-process a Rollup result but never replace it.</statement>
      <rationale source="Notion docs">Formulas that iterate relations are not supported and degrade perf; Rollups are pre-computed and cached.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-archive-after-90-days" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Done tasks + completed sprints older than 90 days move to an Archive database via linked databases. The live Tasks DB stays under 500 active rows.</statement>
      <rationale source="Notion docs">Databases with 500+ active rows and complex properties load slowly; archiving preserves perf without losing history.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-rate-limit-3-per-sec" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>API integration caps writes at 3 req/sec per token with exponential backoff on 429. Bulk operations batched; status changes >50 require human checkpoint (no native undo).</statement>
      <rationale source="Notion API docs">3 req/sec is the documented per-token limit; silent rate limiting (200 response, queued) leads to stale state. Bulk irreversibility makes the checkpoint mandatory.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies-If hold and no Skip-If trigger applies, walk the procedure end-to-end and run the validator before declaring done.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory run leaf">Decision-tree leaves must reference a rule id. The run leaf maps "preconditions met" to the canonical execution path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the Applies-If preconditions are not met OR any Skip-If disqualifier holds.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory skip leaf">Decision-tree leaves must reference a rule id. The skip leaf needs a real rule so non-applicable inputs route cleanly out instead of producing false-positive verdicts.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
