<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-views-api" title="Notion Views and API Rules">
  <summary>View configuration rules, Notion REST API patterns for agent task management, and automation integration.</summary>

  <section title="View Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create purpose-specific views: Board (sprint execution, grouped by Status, filtered to current sprint), Table (all tasks, sortable), Timeline (roadmap, grouped by Project, date field = Date Range), Calendar (deadlines, filtered to not-Done). Never create a catch-all view showing everything — it loads slowly and has no clear use case.</statement>
      <rationale>Each view should answer one specific question. Views that show all data for all purposes become the default view and reduce the value of purpose-specific filters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use linked databases (not duplicated databases) to show the same data in multiple pages. Linked databases point to the same source — changes propagate automatically. Duplicating databases creates two separate sources of truth.</statement>
      <rationale>Duplicated databases require manual sync. Linked databases always reflect the source state without manual updates.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Notion REST API">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use database_id (UUID format) for all API operations. Property names in API calls must match exactly the display names in the Notion UI — including case and spacing. Store database_ids in .aidocs/memory/ or constitution.md.</statement>
      <rationale>Property name mismatches cause silent failures (the API returns 200 but does not update the property). Case sensitivity is a frequent source of agent errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use databases.query endpoint with filter and sort parameters rather than pages.retrieve for finding tasks. The query endpoint supports AND/OR filter trees and pagination — pages.retrieve only works when you already know the page_id.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents that scan all database pages via pages.retrieve are making N API calls for N tasks. databases.query returns all matching items in one call with server-side filtering.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="javascript"><![CDATA[
// Query tasks in current sprint assigned to specific user
const response = await notion.databases.query({
  database_id: "tasks-db-id",
  filter: {
    and: [
      { property: "Sprint", relation: { contains: "current-sprint-page-id" } },
      { property: "Assignee", people: { contains: "user-id" } },
      { property: "Status", status: { does_not_equal: "Done" } }
    ]
  },
  sorts: [{ property: "Priority", direction: "ascending" }]
});
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Automations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Notion's native automations for simple property-change triggers (set Completion Date when Status = Done, notify on Urgent priority). Use Zapier or Make (n8n) for cross-tool workflows (Notion task created → Slack notification, GitHub PR merged → Notion task status update).</statement>
      <rationale>Notion native automations run within Notion and are simpler to configure. Cross-tool workflows require an external automation platform because Notion cannot call external APIs natively in automation actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/task-template.md">Task page template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/sprint-template.md">Sprint page template with metrics and retrospective</reference>
</text>
