<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Steerco Meeting Playbook Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that distinguish a Steerco that drives decisions from a Steerco that drifts into status read-outs. Verifiable from meeting artifacts (pre-read send time, decision memo timestamps, agenda content).</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-preread-3-days-early" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The pre-read pack (status snapshot, decisions log, ask list, any supporting attachments) MUST land in attendee inboxes a minimum of 3 business days (72h) before the meeting. Same-day pre-reads are FORBIDDEN. If the pack is not ready 3 days out, the meeting MUST be rescheduled, not run.</statement>
      <rationale source="Executive scheduling realities; Bezos 6-pager send-ahead practice">Senior stakeholders read pre-reads in transit, between meetings, or 30 minutes before — not live. Pre-reads sent &lt;72h before are scanned, not absorbed, leading to "let me get back to you" decisions that defer everything to next month. The 72h rule restores attendees' ability to come prepared.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-ask-list-per-meeting" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Steerco MUST include a numbered "Asks" section on the agenda, listing the specific decisions Steerco is being asked to make at this meeting. Each ask MUST be in the form "We ask Steerco to approve / reject / defer X by date Y". Vague asks ("guidance on Z") are FORBIDDEN; rewrite as a specific binary decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-forcing meeting design; client-decision-forcing-scripts pattern">Without explicit asks, the meeting ends with vague nods that no one is bound by. A numbered ask list converts the meeting into a decision instrument — the PM leaves with N approve/reject/defer outcomes, each owned.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-cancel-if-no-decisions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the asks list at T-5 days contains zero substantive decisions, the meeting MUST be cancelled and a written status memo sent instead. Reputational cost of cancelled-with-good-reason is far lower than the credibility cost of a 90-minute status read-out.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meeting-discipline pattern; Death-by-status-review anti-pattern">A Steerco run with no asks teaches attendees that their time is not respected, and the next ask-laden meeting will see lower quorum / lower preparation. Cancelling protects the forum's signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-decision-memo-48h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A decision memo MUST be sent to all attendees within 48 hours of the meeting, containing: (a) each ask + the decision made, (b) the rationale recorded by the convener, (c) the owner + deadline of each follow-up, (d) decisions deferred + the trigger to revisit. Verbal "we'll capture it" is FORBIDDEN as a substitute.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decisions-log discipline; legal admissibility of meeting outcomes">Steerco decisions are referenced months later in scope disputes. Without a written memo dated within 48h, parties remember the meeting differently and the PM cannot enforce the outcome. The memo is the artifact of the meeting; the meeting itself is volatile.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-asks-not-status-focus" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agenda time MUST allocate ≤30% to status snapshot and ≥50% to asks + decisions. The status snapshot is the pre-read's job; in-meeting time on status is wasted because (a) the pack already covered it, (b) attendees who didn't read won't catch up via a verbal recap. A standing 90-min Steerco split: 15-min status snapshot · 50-min asks · 15-min escalations · 10-min next-phase preview.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meeting-time accounting; expensive-attendee opportunity cost">Steerco attendee time is the most expensive minute in the project's hour-economy. Spending it on status is malpractice when the pack covered it. Forcing the time split shifts the meeting from theatre to decision-making.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Steerco agenda — monthly outsource cadence, mid-phase project">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Steerco · Acme Migration · 2026-05-21 · 14:00-15:30
Pre-read sent: 2026-05-18 (T-3 business days)

Agenda
  14:00-14:15  Status snapshot — RAG dashboard (pre-read pp. 1-2)
  14:15-15:05  Asks (3)
     A1. Approve scope addition: SAML 2.0 federation (was deferred from April).
         Recommendation: approve, +$48k, 3-week schedule impact.
     A2. Approve change of UAT exit criteria from 95% pass to 98% pass.
         Recommendation: reject; 95% with risk-based gate is industry norm.
     A3. Defer or approve early go-live of read-only module.
         Recommendation: approve early go-live, owner Client CTO.
  15:05-15:20  Escalations (1) — Vendor SSO library security review delay.
  15:20-15:30  Next-phase preview — Q3 budget envelope.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1, r2, r5 satisfied — pre-read T-3, three numbered asks each in binary form, &lt;30% status / 56% asks.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Steerco that became a status read-out">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Steerco · Acme Migration · 2026-05-21
Pre-read sent: 2026-05-21 morning

Agenda
  Project update from PM (60 min)
  Q&A (20 min)
  AOB (10 min)

Outcome: "We'll regroup next month." No decisions captured. No memo sent.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1, r2, r3, r4, r5 all violated. Pre-read same-day, no ask list, no decisions to justify the meeting (so it should have been cancelled), no memo. Steerco credibility lost over 2-3 cycles of this.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../escalation-decision-template/"/>
    <link path="../client-status-report-multistyle/"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
