<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-tool-profiles" title="PM Tool Selection — Tool Quick-Reference Profiles">
  <summary>Quick-reference profiles for the most common PM tools, covering best-fit context, team size, price range, strengths, and weaknesses.</summary>

  <section title="Engineering-Focused Tools">
    <list>
      <item>Jira Cloud — Best for enterprise + compliance (50+ users, $8-16/user). Strengths: customizable, large ecosystem, JQL power. Weaknesses: complex UI, historically slow performance, expensive at scale.</item>
      <item>Linear — Best for engineering teams (10-100 users, $8-16/user). Strengths: keyboard-first speed, opinionated UX, strong GitHub integration. Weaknesses: less flexible than Jira, smaller ecosystem, newer vendor.</item>
      <item>GitHub Projects v2 — Best for OSS and developer-native teams (any size, $0-21/user). Strengths: integrated with code, GraphQL API, no context-switch. Weaknesses: limited PM features, no time tracking, GraphQL-only.</item>
      <item>GitLab — Best for DevOps teams wanting one platform (10-1000 users, $0-99/user). Strengths: full DevOps loop, self-host option, REST + GraphQL. Weaknesses: complex pricing, Premium-gated WIP/iterations.</item>
      <item>Azure DevOps — Best for Microsoft shops with compliance requirements (50+, $6-52/user). Strengths: enterprise-grade, Azure AD auth, Boards + Pipelines + Plans. Weaknesses: Microsoft-centric, complex onboarding.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="All-In-One and Non-Technical Tools">
    <list>
      <item>ClickUp — Best for all-in-one needs (10-500 users, $7-19/user). Strengths: feature-rich, highly customizable, docs integration. Weaknesses: can be overwhelming, performance concerns at scale, complex permissions.</item>
      <item>Notion — Best for docs + PM combo (5-100, $8-18/user). Strengths: flexible, excellent documentation, AI features. Weaknesses: not PM-focused, API does not expose all UI features, formulas limited.</item>
      <item>Asana — Best for marketing and ops teams (10-500, $11-25/user). Strengths: clean UX, goal tracking, portfolio views. Weaknesses: less dev-focused, expensive at enterprise scale.</item>
      <item>Monday.com — Best for non-technical teams (10-500, $8-20/user). Strengths: visual, flexible, no-code automations. Weaknesses: expensive at scale, PM-lite compared to Jira.</item>
      <item>Trello — Best for simple kanban teams (5-50, $0-17.50/user). Strengths: easy to use, fast onboarding, Power-Ups. Weaknesses: limited scaling, no sprint or EVM features.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Open-Source Self-Hosted Alternatives">
    <list>
      <item>OpenProject — Gantt + WBS native, REST API, self-hostable (https://www.openproject.org)</item>
      <item>Plane — Linear alternative, self-hostable, Python API (https://plane.so)</item>
      <item>Taiga — Scrum/Kanban, REST API, Python backend (https://taiga.io)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent-Friendliness Notes">
    <list>
      <item>Jira Cloud: REST v3 + JQL, mature, rate-limited per tenant — best for complex automations.</item>
      <item>Linear: GraphQL API, webhooks, fast, opinionated schema — best for engineering-heavy agentic workflows.</item>
      <item>ClickUp: REST API exists but quirky pagination and fragile custom field handling — test before committing.</item>
      <item>Notion: API does not expose timeline, formulas, or all UI features — validate agent use case against API docs first.</item>
      <item>GitHub Projects v2: GraphQL only, no REST; requires explicit schema understanding for agent use.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
