<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="pm-tool-selection Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for pm-tool-selection as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Running a POC on a decision already made by leadership.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Theater POCs erode trust when the team recognizes the outcome is predetermined; skip the process or run a genuine evaluation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Switching tools mid-project under deadline pressure.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tool migration cost — lost automations, broken integrations, retrained muscle memory — always exceeds the friction being escaped during an active project.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM confidently asserts vendor features without a citation URL.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs hallucinate vendor features; pricing pages change quarterly without announcement. Gate every feature claim on a live-fetched citation; fail closed if no URL is provided.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent scores mobile app quality at 8/10 without testing the app on a physical device.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Synthetic mobile UX scores are fiction; outsource physical-device testing to a human evaluator or defer the criterion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>ADR-drafting agent consistently favours Linear over alternatives.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Training data bias from developer Twitter skews toward Linear; force the agent to argue the strongest case for the second-place tool before writing the final recommendation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
