<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-workflow" title="PM Tool Selection — Agentic Workflow and Best Practices">
  <summary>Recommended agentic subagents, prompt patterns, AI-agent gotchas, and best practices for tool evaluation automation.</summary>

  <section title="Agentic Evaluation Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Human sign-off is mandatory at three points: requirements sign-off, POC scoring, and final ADR approval — agents must not select the tool unilaterally.</statement>
      <rationale>A multi-year tool commitment is irreversible on the scale of a sprint; decision authority for irreversible choices belongs to humans with full organizational context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>A requirements-gatherer agent runs async interviews, normalizes responses into a MoSCoW matrix, and a vendor-researcher agent pulls live pricing and feature data. A TCO modeler builds the 3-year model. A human reviews all three before the POC begins.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Recommended Subagents">
    <list>
      <item>requirements-gatherer — runs structured interview templates (current_state, workflow_needs, team_context, future_needs), extracts must/should/nice into YAML.</item>
      <item>vendor-researcher — pulls feature matrices, pricing, SOC2/GDPR posture from vendor docs + G2/Capterra; cites source URL per field; flags data older than 90 days.</item>
      <item>tco-modeler — builds 3-year TCO with license, implementation, training, admin, and hidden costs.</item>
      <item>adr-drafter — produces ADR-style decision record with evaluation summary and migration plan.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/fetch-pricing.sh">Script to snapshot vendor pricing pages for diff-review</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Vendor-Research Prompt Pattern">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Forces citation per field; fails if data is stale or vendor-supplied without verification:</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are a vendor-researcher subagent. For each tool in {tools}, fetch:
- Current pricing tiers (per-user, per-month, annual discount)
- SSO/SAML availability per tier
- Native integrations with {required_integrations}
- API rate limits and auth model
Return JSON conforming to schema {pm_tool_profile.json}. Cite source URL per field.
Flag any score where source data is older than 90 days or marked "vendor-supplied".
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM confidently asserts vendor features without a citation URL.</description>
      <reason>LLMs hallucinate vendor features; pricing pages change quarterly without announcement. Gate every feature claim on a live-fetched citation; fail closed if no URL is provided.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent scores mobile app quality at 8/10 without testing the app on a physical device.</description>
      <reason>Synthetic mobile UX scores are fiction; outsource physical-device testing to a human evaluator or defer the criterion.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>ADR-drafting agent consistently favours Linear over alternatives.</description>
      <reason>Training data bias from developer Twitter skews toward Linear; force the agent to argue the strongest case for the second-place tool before writing the final recommendation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <list>
      <item>Pricing pages change quietly; cache + diff weekly — do not trust last month's research in scoring.</item>
      <item>POC scorecard suffers from the agent flattering the user's apparent preference; randomize tool order in prompts.</item>
      <item>Never commit to a multi-year contract from agent output alone; require human sign-off on any annual subscription commitment.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Ask vendors for their churn-back rate (customers who came from a competitor) — this reveals real-world switching satisfaction that G2 star ratings hide.</statement>
      <rationale>Churn-back rate measures the tool's ability to retain customers who evaluated alternatives; it is a stronger signal than aggregate ratings which mix use-case-mismatches with genuine quality issues.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always negotiate annual + multi-year pricing and ask for "engineering discount" or open-source rate — initial quotes are rarely final.</statement>
      <rationale>PM tool vendors routinely discount 20-40% on multi-year commitments negotiated before renewal; the list price is a ceiling, not a floor.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
