<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="card-sorting Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for card-sorting. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use open sort for early exploration when IA structure is uncertain. Use closed sort for validation when structure is proposed and you need to test whether users can place content correctly. Use hybrid when some categories are locked and others are flexible.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Open sort reveals what categories users would naturally create—most generative, least constrained. Closed sort tests whether users accept the categories you proposed—more constraint, more efficiency, but misses novel groupings. Hybrid is for refinement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Open sort requires 15-20 participants. Closed sort requires 30+ participants. These thresholds ensure statistical reliability: patterns emerge at 15+ for open sort; placement percentages stabilize at 30+ for closed sort.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Fewer than 15 participants in open sort produce unreliable similarity matrices where individual outliers dominate. Closed sort with fewer than 30 participants produces percentages that are too noisy for decision-making.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use 30-60 cards written entirely in user language. Remove internal jargon, system terminology, and product-specific acronyms. Each card should be a noun or short noun phrase (e.g., "Upgrade Account" not "Tier Migration").</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Over 60 cards causes cognitive fatigue, degrading sort quality on the final 20%. Jargon tests vocabulary knowledge rather than mental models—a user who groups "SSO" and "Authentication" together may not do so because they are related, but because they do not understand "SSO." Below 30 cards under-represents the content space and produces oversimplified structures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not present cards in alphabetical order. Alphabetical order biases groupings toward alphabetic proximity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Participants unconsciously group alphabetically adjacent items together even when they are conceptually unrelated. Randomize card order before the sort begins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a pilot sort with one internal person (someone who did not design the IA) to catch confusing card wording before the real study.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A single pilot sort surfaces labeling problems that will derail the actual research. Better to catch these before recruiting real participants.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply similarity matrix thresholds to make grouping decisions explicit: above 70% agreement = definite grouping (create category), 40-70% = ambiguous (needs further research or tree testing), below 40% = keep separate. Document the threshold logic in your report.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without thresholds, analysts interpret matrices subjectively, producing inconsistent conclusions. Fixed thresholds make the decision rule explicit and repeatable across analysts and projects.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For open sorts, flag outlier groupings (unusual groupings made by 1-2 participants). Do not discard them—investigate whether they represent an underserved user segment. If 20% of participants share an outlier grouping, it is not noise; it is a segment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Majority-based analysis can miss important minority needs. An outlier shared by 20% of users may be as important as the majority pattern, especially if that 20% represents high-value customers or power users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For open sorts, compute standardization score (consistency of category structures across participants). Low standardization indicates that users do not share a clear mental model; high standardization indicates consensus.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Standardization is a confidence metric. High standardization means the proposed IA is backed by strong consensus; low standardization suggests the topic space may not have a natural structure or that your cards are ambiguous.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always follow open card sorting with tree testing before implementing the proposed IA.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Card sorting reveals how users group content; tree testing validates that users can navigate the resulting structure and find specific items. The two methods answer different questions. Card sort alone produces an IA that feels logical to users but may be hard to navigate; tree test alone validates navigation but does not validate labels. Together they de-risk the implementation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use ambiguous items from card sort (those scoring 40-70% agreement or above) as the focus for tree testing. Test whether users can find those items in the proposed structure, and which category they expect to find them in.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Items with high agreement need no further testing. Items with low agreement are the bets; tree testing on those items determines whether the proposed structure handles them well or needs adjustment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
