<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Card Sorting — 6-Step Process">
  <summary>Structured procedure for running open, closed, or hybrid card sorts to reveal user mental models for content organization.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Goals">
    <rule>
      <statement>State the IA decision the sort will inform before selecting card set or format.</statement>
      <rationale>Card sorting produces data; the decision it must drive determines what questions to ask, how many cards to include, and whether to run open or closed format.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Goal examples: How do users group our content? What labels make sense to users? Does our current navigation match mental models?</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Prepare Cards">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use 30-60 cards written in user language — no internal jargon, no system terminology, representative of the full content set.</statement>
      <rationale>Over 60 cards causes cognitive fatigue that degrades sort quality. Jargon on cards tests vocabulary knowledge rather than mental models. Below 30 cards under-represents the content space.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Choose Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use open sort for early exploration (users create categories); closed sort for validation (30+ participants needed for statistical reliability); hybrid when refining an existing IA.</statement>
      <rationale>Open sort reveals what categories users create naturally; closed sort tests whether users can place content in predefined categories. Using closed sort for exploration misses the labels users would naturally use.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Recruit Participants">
    <rule>
      <statement>Recruit 15-20 participants for open sort; 30+ for closed sort. Match target user profile.</statement>
      <rationale>Open sort patterns emerge at 15+ participants. Closed sort requires 30+ for the placement percentages to be statistically meaningful. Fewer participants produce unreliable similarity matrices.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Conduct Sessions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Give standard instructions without examples of how to group — examples bias grouping decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>If the instructions include a sample grouping ("for example, you might group these together"), participants anchor on that example and produce less authentic mental models.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Open sort: "Please organize these cards into groups that make sense to you. You can create as many groups as you need. When done, give each group a name."</p>
    <p>Closed sort: "Please place each card into one of these categories. If a card doesn't fit anywhere, put it in 'Doesn't Fit'."</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Analyze Results">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use similarity matrix thresholds to determine grouping confidence: above 70% = definite grouping; 40-70% = consider grouping; below 40% = keep separate.</statement>
      <rationale>Without thresholds, analysts interpret matrices subjectively. Fixed thresholds make the decision rule explicit and repeatable across analysts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Agreement rate — how often items were grouped together across participants.</item>
      <item>Category similarity — overlap between user-created and predefined categories.</item>
      <item>Standardization — consistency of category structures across participants (high = clear mental model exists).</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/results-report.md">Results report template with agreement matrix</reference>
  </section>
</text>
