<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Card Sorting — Examples and Analysis">
  <summary>Concrete open and closed sort examples demonstrating result interpretation and decision rules.</summary>

  <section title="Open Sort Example — E-commerce Categories">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Content: e-commerce product categories. Results: 15 of 20 users grouped "Laptops" and "Desktops" together (75% agreement — above 70% threshold, definite grouping). Users named this category "Computers" not "Computing Devices." "Tablets" split: 8 users with computers, 7 with phones (40% each — ambiguous, needs further testing). Decision: Create "Computers" category with that label; run tree test to validate tablet placement.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Closed Sort Example — Category Placement">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Categories: Electronics, Home, Clothing. Results: Smart Watch → Electronics 85% (clear); Fitness Tracker → Electronics 70% (clear); Heated Blanket → Home 55%, Electronics 40% (ambiguous — below 70% in both). Decision: Heated Blanket needs re-categorization research; consider dual-listing or a new category.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Including more than 60 cards in a single sort session.</description>
      <reason>Participants experience cognitive fatigue past 60 cards, producing rushed, lower-quality groupings in the second half of the sort. Split oversized sets into focused sub-sorts by content area.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Not asking participants why they grouped items together during or after in-person sessions.</description>
      <reason>The similarity matrix shows what was grouped, not why. "Why" questions surface label preferences and mental model distinctions that the quantitative data cannot capture.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating outlier groupings as noise to discard.</description>
      <reason>Unusual groupings may represent an underserved user segment's mental model. Investigate before discarding — one outlier grouping that 20% of users share is not noise, it is a segment.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Card Sort to Tree Test Pipeline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always follow open card sorting with tree testing before implementing the proposed IA.</statement>
      <rationale>Card sorting reveals how users group content; it does not validate that users can navigate the resulting structure. Tree testing provides that validation and catches labeling problems that sorting misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Pipeline: Card Sort → proposed structure → Tree Test → refined structure → implement.</p>
  </section>
</text>
