<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="card-sorting Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for card-sorting as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Including more than 60 cards in a single sort session.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Participants experience cognitive fatigue past 60 cards. The groupings made in the final third of the sort are rushed and lower-quality. Split oversized sets into focused sub-sorts by content area.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Not asking participants why they grouped items together during in-person sessions or immediately after remote sessions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The similarity matrix shows what was grouped, not why. "Why" questions reveal label preferences, mental model distinctions, and conceptual overlaps that quantitative data cannot capture. Asking participants "Why did you put these together?" produces the richest insights.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating open card sort results as a final IA. "Users grouped it this way, so we ship this structure."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Card sorting reveals mental models; it does not validate that users can navigate the resulting structure. Tree testing—where users search for specific items in the proposed IA—provides that validation. Always follow card sorting with tree testing before implementation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Using inconsistent card labels across open sort groups. Some cards say "Reports" (internal language) and others say "View Your Performance" (user language).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Inconsistency confuses participants and produces noisier groupings. Label all cards consistently, either all internal or all user-facing (prefer user-facing).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
