<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-three-principles" title="Three Core VUI Design Principles">
  <summary>Three testable principles — Simplicity, Natural Conversation, Context Awareness — with concrete do/don't examples and an evaluator rubric for automated checking.</summary>

  <section title="Principle 1: Simplicity">
    <rule>
      <statement>One idea per system turn; no redundant phrasing, units, timestamps, or location details unless explicitly requested.</statement>
      <rationale>Voice is ephemeral — users cannot re-read. Dense responses cause cognitive overload; research shows comprehension drops sharply when spoken output exceeds two clauses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Concise confirmation, no redundant detail</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
System: "Your order is confirmed for delivery tomorrow."
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Redundant detail — date, time window, timezone all unprompted</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
System: "Your order has been successfully processed and scheduled for delivery on January 20th at a time between 9 AM and 5 PM in your local timezone."
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Principle 2: Natural Conversation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Sound like a person: use contractions, conversational rhythm, and offer one helpful follow-up after completing a task.</statement>
      <rationale>Formal language signals a machine and breaks the conversational contract; users disengage or revert to terse commands that hurt NLU coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Ban stop-list filler phrases from system prompts: "I'd be happy to", "Just to confirm", "I have successfully", "Currently".</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs default to verbose, apologetic tone and will not self-edit reliably; the stop-list must be enforced via system prompt or post-processing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Conversational, offers follow-up</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
User: "What's the weather?"
System: "It's 72 and sunny. Should I tell you about tomorrow?"
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Formal, no follow-up offer</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
User: "What's the weather?"
System: "The current temperature is 72 degrees Fahrenheit with sunny conditions. Humidity is 45 percent."
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Principle 3: Context Awareness">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use prior turns implicitly; never ask users to repeat information they already provided in the same session.</statement>
      <rationale>Forgetting prior context is the leading source of VUI frustration; users interpret it as incompetence and abandon flows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track explicit dialog-state slots (intent, last_entity, pending_confirmation) in agent context — never reconstruct state from utterance history alone.</statement>
      <rationale>Reconstructing state from text is fragile and drifts; explicit slot tracking makes state deterministic and auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Implicit update using session context</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
User: "Set an alarm for 7 AM"
System: "Alarm set for 7 AM tomorrow."
User: "Make it 6:30"
System: "Updated to 6:30 AM."
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Evaluator Rubric">
    <rule>
      <statement>Encode the three principles as a JSON rubric with scores 0-3; use it in agent critic passes instead of free-form review.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents apply structured scoring more reliably than prose instructions; a numeric rubric also enables trend tracking across iterations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Structured rubric for critic agent</note>
      <code lang="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "simplicity": {"score": 0, "note": "two ideas in one turn"},
  "naturalness": {"score": 2, "note": "contractions present but no follow-up"},
  "context":     {"score": 3, "note": "references last entity correctly"}
}
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
