<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Ads Attribution Models Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Ads Attribution Models MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="warehouse-truth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Warehouse MUST be the canonical source of truth. Platforms are inputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Multi-channel attribution literature">Platforms double-count and use different windows; only warehouse can dedup across sources.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="variance-threshold-15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Variance &gt; 15% between platform / GA4 / warehouse MUST trigger investigation before budget decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cross-channel attribution audit Q4 2025">Above 15% indicates pixel misfire, dedup failure, or definition drift; acting on bad data destroys budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="geo-holdout-quarterly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly geo-holdout incrementality test MUST run per major channel. Without it, true incremental lift is unknown.</statement>
      <rationale source="Incrementality testing literature — Wieczorek, Air Force/Google">Attribution models estimate share-of-credit; only incrementality tests measure true lift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="variance-report-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Variance report MUST run weekly with named reviewer. Monthly is too slow to catch pixel drift.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational cadence — marketing analytics">Pixel breakage often surfaces within days; weekly cadence catches it before quarter-end damage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="definition-stability" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conversion definitions (event name, window, dedup key) MUST be frozen quarterly. Mid-quarter changes invalidate comparisons.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal analytics-governance practice">Definition drift mid-quarter generates apparent variance that is actually a definition artifact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
