<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-models" title="Attribution Model Types and Platform Defaults">
  <summary>Defines the six attribution models, explains the cross-platform overlap problem, and provides lookback window guidelines by sales cycle length.</summary>

  <section title="Attribution Models">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select an attribution model based on sales cycle length and available conversion volume, not platform convenience.</statement>
      <rationale>Each model assigns credit differently and will produce different CPA and ROAS numbers for the same spend. Using the wrong model leads to systematically over- or under-investing in channels.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Model comparison for a journey: FB click → Google click → Email click → Purchase</p>
    <list>
      <item>Last-click: FB 0% / Google 0% / Email 100% — conservative, ignores journey</item>
      <item>First-click: FB 100% / Google 0% / Email 0% — awareness focus only</item>
      <item>Linear: FB 33% / Google 33% / Email 33% — equal credit across all touches</item>
      <item>Position-based: FB 40% / Google 20% / Email 40% — weights first and last touch</item>
      <item>Time-decay: FB 10% / Google 30% / Email 60% — more credit to recent touches</item>
      <item>Data-driven: ML-based — requires 50+ conversions/channel/month to train reliably</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Platform Defaults">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document the attribution model and lookback window for every platform in use; never assume defaults are consistent across platforms.</statement>
      <rationale>Each platform uses different defaults: Meta counts 7-day click + 1-day view, Google Ads uses last Google click at 30 days, GA4 uses data-driven at 90 days. Comparing numbers without knowing this is meaningless.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Meta: 7-day click, 1-day view (view-through counted)</item>
      <item>Google Ads: last Google click, 30-day window</item>
      <item>GA4: data-driven, 90-day window</item>
      <item>LinkedIn: 30-day click, 7-day view (view-through counted)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="The Overlap Problem">
    <p>When a user clicks a Meta ad then a Google ad before purchasing, both platforms record the conversion. Platform totals routinely exceed actual sales by 20-40%.</p>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Comparing platform-reported conversions directly across channels to determine which channel is "winning."</description>
      <reason>Platform totals are not deduplicated. A user clicking both Meta and Google appears in both reports as a unique conversion. The comparison is meaningless without a unified view.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use GA4 or a warehouse-deduped view as the single source of truth for cross-channel performance; use platform data only for in-platform optimization.</statement>
      <rationale>GA4 deduplicates across channels using the same user session. Platform data remains useful for optimizing bids and creative within that platform's ecosystem.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Lookback Window Guidelines">
    <list>
      <item>Impulse purchase (under 1 day): 1-day click window</item>
      <item>Short cycle (1-7 days): 7-day click window</item>
      <item>Medium cycle (1-4 weeks): 30-day click window</item>
      <item>Long cycle (1-3 months): 90-day click window</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Match lookback window to actual sales cycle; never use a shorter window to make numbers look better.</statement>
      <rationale>A 7-day window on a 30-day SaaS trial cycle will miss the majority of attributed conversions and undercount channel contribution.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
