<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ads-attribution-models Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ads-attribution-models as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Comparing platform-reported conversions directly across channels to determine which channel is "winning."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Platform totals are not deduplicated. A user clicking both Meta and Google appears in both reports as a unique conversion. The comparison is meaningless without a unified view.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Running an incrementality test for less than 2 weeks or adjusting budgets during the test.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Insufficient runtime produces statistically noisy results. Mid-test budget changes alter the treatment condition and make the holdout comparison invalid.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Trusting platform-reported totals for cross-channel budget decisions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Platform totals are over-counted by 20-40% due to cross-channel overlap. Decisions based on them systematically overspend on channels that appear more efficient than they are.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Using last-click as the sole attribution model for a multi-touch journey.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Last-click assigns zero credit to all upper-funnel touchpoints, leading to systematic under-investment in awareness and consideration channels.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring view-through attribution entirely.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Display and video channels drive brand recall that appears as direct traffic. Excluding view-through undervalues awareness spend.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent explains small variances (under 15%) with elaborate narratives before a minimum-variance threshold is met.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Small variances are noise from lookback window differences, timezone offsets, and sampling. Narratives on noise mislead decision-makers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent presents platform-reported and GA4-modeled numbers side-by-side as comparable values without labeling the model and window for each.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>They use different lookback windows and deduplication logic. An unlabeled table implies comparability where none exists.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent computes a single "today" number using GA4 property timezone and Google Ads account timezone interchangeably.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>GA4 uses property timezone; Google Ads uses account timezone. These can differ by hours and produce off-by-one date errors in daily reports.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent reports data-driven attribution point estimates without confidence intervals or sample-size caveats.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Data-driven models have uncertainty that grows with low conversion volume. Point estimates without CIs create false precision and overconfident recommendations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
