<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="requirements-lifecycle Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for requirements-lifecycle. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Requirements MUST flow through these stages in order (with allowed backward loops): Identify → Analyze → Specify → Validate → Verify → Manage. A requirement cannot reach Implemented until it is Approved; it cannot reach Verified until Implemented. Deferred requirements may return to Proposed in a later iteration.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The stage order enforces that requirements are understood before they are built; skipping Analyze or Validate leads to building the wrong thing or discovering defects too late to fix.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin a canonical state set in a single file (e.g. `requirements/_states.yaml`) and reference it from every prompt and pre-commit hook. Do not rely on LLMs or humans retaining the state list; embed it in validation code.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">State drift is silent; an agent assumes a state that is not in the canonical set and proposes an impossible transition. Making the list a data file eliminates the assumption.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every requirement MUST have these attributes: ID (REQ-XXX format), Name (short title), Description (full text), Status (one of the canonical states), Priority (MoSCoW or numeric), Source (stakeholder/document/discovery method), Owner (person responsible), Version (semver or X.Y), Created (date), Modified (date), Author (who wrote it). Missing attributes block the transition, not warn.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Incomplete metadata destroys traceability. A requirement with no Owner means nobody answers when QA asks "is this still true?"; one with no Source means audit cannot trace it back to a stakeholder decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use semantic versioning (X.Y.Z): Z for wording-only edits (no behavioral change), Y for AC/NFR changes (test cases must be updated), X for scope changes (may trigger re-approval). A requirement at 2.0 is materially different from 1.x — treat it as a new requirement at approval boundaries.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Wording-only bumps pollute version history with noise; scope bumps trigger retesting and re-approval. Conflating the two means developers implement the wrong version and QA skips retesting because "only grammar changed".</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every change to an Approved requirement MUST originate as a Change Request (CR-XXX), not as a direct edit. The CR MUST include: current requirement text, proposed text, reason for change, and an impact analysis identifying all downstream artifacts (design, code, test cases) that must change. A CR is approved, rejected, or deferred by the same stakeholders who approved the original requirement; the approval gates a version bump.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a CR, changes are invisible to QA and design; developers implement the new requirement but testing is against the old version. A CR makes the cost and scope visible; approvers are forced to decide if the change is worth the rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Validation occurs during the Specify and Validate stages, before code starts. Activities: stakeholder walkthrough (do the written requirements make sense?), prototype review (does the visual match the requirement?), acceptance-criteria testability review (can QA write a test?). Verification occurs during Implemented → Verified, after code is ready. Activities: design review (does the design satisfy the requirement?), code inspection (does the code do what the design says?), testing (does the test pass the AC?). Do not mix the activities; validation questions asked after code is live are rework.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Validation-at-build-time (asking QA to validate) means you are asking QA to reject code that is already built. Validation must happen before Approved is reached.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Generate a Requirements Status Log at least once per sprint (or on audit request). The log MUST include: requirement ID, name, current status, priority, owner, version, last modified date. Separately track the counts of each status as a burndown check. Include a detailed section listing orphans (no parent or no child) and a changelog of status transitions since the last log.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A status log is proof that requirements are being managed; without it, an auditor cannot verify progress or see which requirements have stalled in Proposed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every requirement attribute MUST be machine-readable (YAML frontmatter, JSON, or database fields, never free text). Use consistent key names across the organization. Version must be semver. Priority must be one of a closed set (MoSCoW, 1-5 scale, etc.). Status must be one of the canonical states. Tooling (git, pre-commit, CI) must validate frontmatter schema; reject non-compliant requirements at commit time.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Free-text attributes lead to silent errors: "priority: high" vs "priority: HIGH" vs "priority: P1" are all assumed equivalent but tooling cannot parse them. Machine-readable attributes catch these silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
