<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-channel-taxonomy" title="Distribution Channel Research: Channel Taxonomy and Evaluation">
  <summary>Four channel categories with characteristics, a weighted evaluation matrix, and the LTV:CAC viability rule that gates which channels are worth scaling.</summary>

  <section title="Channel Categories">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always research all four channel categories before selecting a primary: organic (SEO, content, social, community, WOM, PLG), paid (search ads, social ads, display, influencer, affiliate, sponsorships), sales-led (outbound, partnerships, conferences, webinars), and viral/network (referral, integrations, embeds, UGC).</statement>
      <rationale>Founders pick channels based on preference, not fit. A channel chosen without reviewing the full taxonomy misses the category where buyers actually concentrate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Organic: 6-12 months to results, low cost, sustainable growth, lower CAC over time</item>
      <item>Paid: immediate results, scalable when proven, high cost, best for fast testing</item>
      <item>Sales-led: high value B2B and complex products, 1-6 months to results, high cost</item>
      <item>Viral/network: best for products with network effects, 1-4 months, low-variable cost</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Channel Evaluation Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each candidate channel on six weighted factors: audience presence (25%), competitors using (15%), cost to test (20%), time to results (15%), scalability (15%), team capability (10%). Prioritize highest-scoring channels for initial investment.</statement>
      <rationale>Weighting audience presence highest prevents the common failure of investing in channels where the target buyer does not exist, regardless of team familiarity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>A channel is viable only when LTV:CAC exceeds 3:1. Model channel economics (CPM → CTR → CPC → conversion rate → CAC) before scaling any channel beyond micro-test budget.</statement>
      <rationale>Channels that feel productive but have LTV:CAC under 3:1 are capital destroyers — they feel like growth while compounding a structural margin problem.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Channel Testing Sequence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow the five-step testing sequence: micro-test ($100-500, 1-2 weeks) → validate signal → scale test ($1-5K, 1 month) → optimize conversion → scale budget. Never jump from micro-test to full scale.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping the scale-test stage bets the marketing budget on a statistically insignificant micro-test; the validate step decides whether to proceed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Portfolio approach by stage: at 0-$10K MRR master 1 channel; at $10-50K MRR add 2-3 channels; at $50K+ MRR diversify. Maintain 80% effort on 1-2 proven channels, 20% on experiments.</statement>
      <rationale>Trying all channels simultaneously dilutes effort below the minimum needed to get accurate signal from any one channel.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>B2B SaaS tool: interviews show 60% discover via Google search, 25% via peer recommendations, 15% via LinkedIn. Strategy: SEO primary (content for "how to [problem]" keywords), LinkedIn secondary (thought leadership + ads), referral tertiary (in-product program). SEO CAC after 6 months: $20; LinkedIn CAC: $150; referral CAC: $30.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Consumer mobile app: 45% from App Store search, 30% from friend recommendation, 25% from Instagram/TikTok. Strategy: ASO primary (free organic installs), viral loops secondary (shareable content), TikTok organic tertiary. Avoids paid channels until virality loop is proven.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
