<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-market-level-process" title="Distribution Channel Research: Market-Level Agentic Process">
  <summary>Four-stage agentic workflow for market-level channel research, confidence-band rules, citation requirements, and the boundary-first gate.</summary>

  <section title="Four-Stage Pipeline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always run the boundary agent first and refuse to proceed until geo + segment + buyer + product category are locked. An unbounded market produces meaningless channel-share denominators.</statement>
      <rationale>Channel-share is a fraction — without a denominator (market boundary) it is undefined. Agents that skip this gate produce plausible-sounding numbers with no anchor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Stage 1 (Boundary agent): lock geo + segment + buyer + category → market-definition spec</item>
      <item>Stage 2 (Channel-share agent): quantify traffic/revenue mix across top 10 incumbents using SimilarWeb + Ahrefs + ad libraries → market-level channel-share table with confidence bands</item>
      <item>Stage 3 (Partner-landscape agent): map every distributor/reseller/marketplace/integration partner with reach, exclusivity, take-rate → partner-landscape table</item>
      <item>Stage 4 (Economics agent): layer benchmark CPC/PMC/CAC on channel-share table, run LTV sensitivity (low/mid/high) → LTV:CAC ranges per channel</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Confidence-Band Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Report channel-share as a range with confidence band tied to N of competitors with available data: HIGH if ≥7 incumbents agree, MED if 4-6, LOW if ≤3. Never output a single percentage without the band.</statement>
      <rationale>SimilarWeb traffic mix is a proxy for channel-share, not a measurement of revenue-share — a single number projects false precision onto an inherently noisy estimate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use revenue- or traffic-weighted aggregation when computing market-level channel-share — never equal-weight across competitors. Weight by SimilarWeb monthly visits as proxy.</statement>
      <rationale>Equal-weight averaging gives micro-competitors the same influence as category leaders, skewing the picture toward the long tail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Report partner take-rates as facts when from public marketplace docs (AWS 3%, Shopify 0-20%, App Store 15-30%) and as [INFERRED] with inference path when from job posts or partner-portal scrapes.</statement>
      <rationale>Private reseller margins (15-40%) are negotiated and only leak via indirect signals; treating inferred rates as facts leads to materially wrong economics models.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Citation Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every number must carry source + URL + capture-date triple. Economic numbers older than 12 months must be marked [UNVERIFIED] rather than cited as current.</statement>
      <rationale>Ad library data and traffic estimates rot in weeks; stale benchmarks in investor decks create credibility risk when scrutinized.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run LTV sensitivity at low/mid/high LTV and output ranges, not point estimates. Reject any single LTV:CAC ratio output as incomplete.</statement>
      <rationale>LTV uncertainty kills market-level LTV:CAC modeling — the right output is a range with sensitivity bands so investors and operators can see the cliff.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include regional splits for multi-geo markets. Never blend global averages — CPC variance across regions can be 3-5x, destroying the strategic recommendation.</statement>
      <rationale>US-centric benchmarks systematically misrepresent APAC and EU markets where CPCs, partner ecosystems, and channel maturity differ fundamentally.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/market-channel-share.py">Aggregate per-competitor traffic mixes into market-level share table with confidence bands</reference>
  <reference path="templates/channel-research-report.md">Full channel research report skeleton</reference>
  <reference path="templates/partner-landscape.md">Partner-landscape table with reach, exclusivity, take-rate, source, capture-date</reference>
</text>
