<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="distribution-channel-research Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for distribution-channel-research as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Trying all channels simultaneously at launch.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Dilutes effort below the minimum needed to get accurate signal from any single channel. Focus on 1-2 initially.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Copying competitor channels without validating fit for the specific product.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Channel fit depends on audience presence, cost structure, and team capability — not on what the market leader does.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring channel economics before scaling — no CAC calculation before increasing budget.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Channels that feel productive but have LTV:CAC under 3:1 destroy capital; economics must be modeled before scaling.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Giving up on a channel after fewer than 4-6 weeks with no optimization.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Organic channels take 3-12 months to mature; premature abandonment produces false negatives that leave viable channels unexplored.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>No attribution tracking set up before running channel tests.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without attribution, test results cannot be attributed to any channel; the data is useless for decision-making.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Channel granularity collapse: "paid social" lumped together as one channel in the market-share table.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"Paid social" is not one channel — Meta Reels, Meta Feed, IG Stories, LinkedIn Sponsored, TikTok In-Feed behave differently. Force per-platform breakdown or the analysis is meaningless for channel selection.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Survivorship in published case studies: "we got to $10M via SEO" stories overweight organic and underweight paid.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Published stories are 1-of-100 — channel-share inference from public stories must be cross-checked with SimilarWeb traffic mix data from the silent majority.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Producing a 7-tier portfolio recommendation ("Phase 1 SEO, Phase 2 paid") in market-research output.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>GTM sequencing is GTM-strategist work, not market research. Stop at channel-share + partner-landscape + economics tables; let the strategist interpret them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents skipping the boundary gate and producing "channel mix for SaaS" without geo or segment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a market boundary the channel-share denominator is undefined and all output is conjecture. Enforce a stop-and-ask gate before any data work.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents fabricating CPC, CPM, take-rate, and traffic-share values without sourced citations.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Number hallucination in channel benchmarks produces investment decisions grounded in fiction. Require source + URL + capture-date for every number and reject answers failing the citation check.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Boundary skipping: agents will happily produce "channel mix for SaaS" without a geo or segment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Enforce a stop-and-ask gate before any data work; without a market boundary the channel-share denominator is undefined and all output is conjecture.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Number hallucination: agents fabricate plausible CPC, CPM, take-rate, and traffic-share values.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require source + URL + capture-date for every number, and reject answers that fail the citation check.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>US-bias: training data overweights US benchmarks; for non-US markets force the agent to source regional data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>For non-US markets force the agent to source regional data (Statista, eMarketer regional, local Ad libraries) rather than defaulting to US benchmarks.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Confidence-band omission: agents collapse channel-share into single percentages.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Explicitly require N + confidence band per row; a single percentage projects false precision onto an inherently noisy estimate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Survivorship lean: agents will overweight famous "we won via SEO" stories.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Prompt for the silent majority (incumbents that never wrote a Medium post) by sampling top-10 by traffic, not top-10 by content output.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Partner-landscape under-reporting: agents miss MSPs, VARs, and SI partners because those rarely have web presence.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require the agent to scrape "Partners / Resellers / Find a partner" pages of each incumbent and capture every named entity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Equal-weight aggregation bug: agents default to averaging across competitors equally.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Explicitly demand traffic- or revenue-weighted aggregation; equal weights give micro-competitors the same influence as category leaders.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-18" severity="medium">
      <description>LTV point-estimate bug: agents output a single LTV:CAC ratio.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require low/mid/high sensitivity or reject the answer; point estimates hide the cliff where unit economics invert.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-19" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale benchmarks: agents quote 2022 CPCs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require capture-date &gt;= last 12 months for any economic number, else mark [UNVERIFIED].</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
