<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="learning-speed-competitive-moat">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-operations</domain>
    <summary>When AI replicates features in weeks, durable advantage is learning velocity: noticing changes, updating beliefs, shipping different answers via versioned beliefs.yaml and agent pipeline.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>competitive-advantage</tag>
      <tag>decision-making</tag>
      <tag>learning-systems</tag>
      <tag>agent-ops</tag>
      <tag>strategy</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>product</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Learning Speed as Competitive Moat</title>
    <summary>When AI lets anyone clone product features in weeks, the durable competitive advantage is how quickly an org notices changes, updates its beliefs, and ships different answers. This is operationalized as a versioned beliefs.yaml updated by a daily/weekly agent pipeline: a signal-collector ingests market, customer, and analytics signals; a classifier tags each signal against current beliefs; a synthesizer diffs the beliefs weekly; a strategy-reviewer proposes roadmap changes. Humans own two gates: kill/keep decisions and any belief change affecting pricing or positioning.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Feature parity is no longer a moat — AI can replicate a UI in days. The real moat is learning velocity: (Signals Noticed × Update Speed × Execution Quality) / Time. Orgs that run weekly strategy reviews instead of quarterly, and that log decisions with predictions and check-back dates, compound their advantage while competitors are still debating last quarter's roadmap. Decision logs graded quarterly on prediction accuracy are the forcing function.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>AI-replicable product surface where feature parity is reachable in weeks (most B2B SaaS, content tools, vertical AI wrappers)</item>
        <item>Org with 3+ teams where signal latency is measured in weeks, not days</item>
        <item>Strategy reviews are quarterly but competitor/customer behavior changes weekly</item>
        <item>Post-PMF stage where the bottleneck is "what do we ship next" not "does anyone want this"</item>
        <item>Board, GTM, or fundraising narrative needs a defensible operational moat beyond a feature list</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF / 1–5 person team — a single founder's speed beats any process; "rituals" become theater</item>
        <item>Truly defensible moats already in place (network effects, regulated licenses, hardware, dataset lock-in) — focus there, not on meta-process</item>
        <item>Markets with 6–12 month sales cycles (defense, medical devices) — weekly updates produce noise</item>
        <item>Teams that will not act on signals — an Insight Repository without a decision owner is a graveyard</item>
        <item>Burned-out teams — adding weekly rituals on top of broken delivery makes velocity worse</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="learning-velocity-formula">
      <p>Learning Velocity = (Signals Noticed × Update Speed × Execution Quality) / Time. Each factor is addressable: signal collection is automated; update speed is increased by weekly reviews instead of quarterly; execution quality is maintained via the belief-update constraint (mutate only on sufficient evidence).</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat beliefs.yaml as code: versioned in git, PR-reviewed, diffable. PR-reviewed belief changes beat Slack-thread consensus.</statement>
        <rationale>Beliefs that live in Notion pages or Slack threads drift without audit trail. A versioned YAML file makes every belief change visible, attributable, and reversible.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="signal-collection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Limit the watchlist: 3–5 competitors, 1 macro trend, 1 customer segment. Broader scope equals noise, not signal.</statement>
        <rationale>AI can ingest thousands of signals per day; without a bounded watchlist the team drowns in volume and stops acting on any of it. Constraint is the design.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Ingest at least one external corpus (product analytics or competitor scrape). A system fed only internal Slack channels measures its own opinion velocity, not the market.</statement>
        <rationale>Confirmation loops where the same channel provides signals and classification are invisible and common. External corpus is the mitigation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="belief-update-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Mutate a belief only if (a) 3 or more independent event_ids agree, or (b) 1 high-severity event directly contradicts the current claim with a cited URL or transcript.</statement>
        <rationale>Single data points are noise; three independent signals from different sources constitute evidence. The threshold prevents recency over-weighting and Sonnet evidence-laundering.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pair every belief with a kill criterion and a check-back date. Beliefs without falsifiers rot into dogma.</statement>
        <rationale>A belief that cannot be falsified is not a belief — it is an assumption. Kill criteria and check-back dates force the team to revisit rather than defend.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Synthesizer generating insights at digest-of-digest-of-digest compression, losing original wording.</description>
        <reason>Re-grounding every synthesizer run on the raw events.ndjson is mandatory. Previous digests anchor on prior framing and lose the original signal over time.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="decision-logging">
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure decisions made per week crossed with decisions reversed within 30 days. High reversal rate indicates a noisy loop; low decision count indicates an inert org.</statement>
        <rationale>Insights captured is a vanity metric. Decision count and decision stability are the actual outputs of a functioning learning system.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run quarterly calibration: grade past predictions against outcomes. Recalibrate confidence weights and prompt scoring rubrics based on accuracy.</statement>
        <rationale>Without calibration, confidence weights become superstition. Calibration is not optional — it is the mechanism that prevents the belief system from drifting from reality.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="weekly-rituals">
      <p>Monday: customer interview insights shared. Wednesday: competitor updates reviewed. Friday: experiment results analyzed and strategy adjustments communicated. Time-box rituals: Monday 30 min digest, Friday 45 min strategy. Drift past those times and people skip.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Default to "kill" on the Friday review for evidence-thin roadmap items. Burden of proof is on keeping, not killing.</statement>
        <rationale>Keeping an item with thin evidence consumes H1 capacity. The asymmetric default (keep requires evidence, kill does not) prevents roadmap accumulation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive this as a daily/weekly belief-update pipeline, not a methodology. A daily collector agent (Haiku) ingests signals from product analytics, customer calls, support tickets, competitor watchlist, market news. A daily classifier (Haiku) tags each signal as evidence-for | evidence-against | new-hypothesis | noise against the current belief registry. A weekly synthesizer (Sonnet) updates a versioned beliefs.yaml, flags any belief whose evidence flipped, and generates a Monday digest. An Opus "strategy-reviewer" agent runs once per week against beliefs.yaml + ongoing experiments + roadmap and proposes which roadmap items to keep, kill, or re-prioritise. Humans own only two checkpoints: kill/keep decisions and any belief change that affects pricing or positioning.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Separate mechanical work (haiku: signal collection, classification, decision logging) from judgment work (opus: strategy review, roadmap pass). Mixing costs 10x and introduces bias.</statement>
        <rationale>Opus applied to classification tasks burns budget without improving quality. Haiku applied to strategy synthesis produces confident-sounding but shallow reasoning. Each model tier has a specific function.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>signal-collector (Haiku, daily): Pulls deltas from analytics (PostHog/Amplitude), CRM (Hubspot/Salesforce), support (Intercom/Zendesk), call transcripts (Gong/Fireflies), competitor watchlist. Emits normalized JSON events to events.ndjson.</item>
        <item>signal-classifier (Haiku/Sonnet, daily): Tags each event against current beliefs.yaml: evidence-for | evidence-against | new-hypothesis | noise. Drops noise.</item>
        <item>belief-updater (Sonnet, weekly): Versioned beliefs.yaml write. Diff-aware: only changes a belief when ≥3 independent events agree, or 1 high-severity contradicting event. Emits a per-belief audit trail.</item>
        <item>weekly-synthesizer (Sonnet, Monday digest): Which beliefs changed, which experiments concluded, which competitor moves matter, recommended discussion topics. Cite event_id per claim.</item>
        <item>strategy-reviewer (Opus, Friday roadmap pass): For each in-flight item, "still bet on this? evidence?". Outputs keep/kill/reframe with named decision owner.</item>
        <item>decision-logger (Haiku, continuous): Records every decision with prediction + check-back date. Quarterly calibration job grades prediction accuracy → feeds back into belief-updater confidence weights.</item>
        <item>faion-research-agent (on demand): Runs market/competitor mode on demand to refresh the signal corpus the collector sees.</item>
        <item>brainstorm (on demand): Diverge/converge on new-hypothesis events before they enter belief registry.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Belief-updater (XML, structured output):</note>
        <code lang="xml"><![CDATA[<role>belief-updater</role>
<current_beliefs>{{ beliefs_yaml }}</current_beliefs>
<new_events>{{ events_jsonl }}</new_events>
<rules>
  Only mutate a belief if (a) >=3 independent event_ids agree, OR
  (b) 1 high-severity event directly contradicts current claim with cited URL/transcript.
  Never invent beliefs. Cite event_id for every change.
</rules>
<output_schema>
  {changed:[{belief_id, before, after, evidence:[event_id], confidence_delta}],
   unchanged_with_pressure:[{belief_id, opposing_evidence:[event_id]}]}
</output_schema>]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Strategy-reviewer (Opus, neutral framing):</note>
        <code lang="xml"><![CDATA[<role>strategy-reviewer</role>
<beliefs>{{ beliefs_yaml }}</beliefs>
<roadmap>{{ roadmap_md }}</roadmap>
<experiments>{{ experiments_yaml }}</experiments>
<deliverable>For each roadmap item: keep|kill|reframe, cited evidence,
decision_owner, check_back_date.</deliverable>
<constraint>Default to "kill" if evidence_for_keeping &lt; 3 cited events
in last 30 days. Never reuse last week's recommendation without re-citing.</constraint>]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Memory rot: belief-updater pulled into context-window compaction loses last week's reasoning.</description>
        <reason>Persist beliefs.yaml and beliefs.history.ndjson outside the LLM and re-inject on every run. Never rely on LLM memory for belief continuity across sessions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Evidence laundering: sonnet rewrites the same event into 3 different "independent" supports for a belief.</description>
        <reason>Dedupe by event_id hash before counting independent signals. Three occurrences of the same event do not count as three independent signals.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Prompt bias: "summarise this week's competitor wins" yields wins. Use neutral framing: "score evidence-based threat 1-5, default 1".</description>
        <reason>Leading prompts pre-load the model to find wins. Neutral framing with default scores prevents confirmation bias.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated event_ids: model invents event_42 that does not exist in events.ndjson.</description>
        <reason>Run a fact-checker pass that looks up every cited id in events.ndjson before publishing. Uncited event_ids are fabrications.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Token blow-up from dumping 10k events directly into Opus weekly.</description>
        <reason>Pre-cluster with haiku, hand 50–100 archetypal events to opus. Full event streams at opus cost is wasteful and counterproductively degrades reasoning quality.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Action-less insight loop: agent surfaces 200 insights per week, no decision_owner, nobody acts.</description>
        <reason>Force schema field decision_owner on every event that reaches the belief-updater. Drop events without an owner rather than surfacing them without action.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-publishing risk: an agent-generated digest claiming a competitor is "in trouble" leaks via Slack screenshot.</description>
        <reason>Add a human review gate before any cross-org distribution. Agents should draft for internal consumption; humans approve before external sharing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Calibration neglect: nobody scores last quarter's predictions, confidence weights become superstition.</description>
        <reason>Quarterly grading job is not optional. It is the feedback loop that prevents belief drift from reality.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations-and-failure-modes">
      <p>Vanity loops: teams measure "insights captured" instead of "decisions changed" — looks great, predicts nothing. Belief inertia: leadership says "weekly review" but never overrides last quarter's roadmap; the ritual exists, the moat does not. Signal drowning: AI dumps thousands of mentions; no signal-to-decision ratio. Without scoring + action owner this becomes worse than human curation. Recency bias: weekly cadence over-weights last 7 days, kills strategic patience on bets that need 90 days to play out. "Learning velocity" is unmeasurable directly — proxies (cycle time, decision count, prediction accuracy) drift; teams game them. Cross-team write-amplification: shared insight repo without curation produces 50 "insights/day" nobody reads. Tooling sprawl: Notion + Slack + Linear + Looker + Zoom transcripts ⇒ no single source of belief; agents lose the thread across contexts.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-tools">
      <p>Productboard: SaaS, Partial REST API. Insight repo + roadmap; rigid taxonomy. Maze: SaaS, yes API. Continuous discovery experiments at scale. Dovetail: SaaS, yes API + AI tags. Customer-research repo; auto-tagging quality varies. Notion AI: SaaS, Limited (no eventing). Cheap belief registry; weak as system of record. Linear: SaaS, yes GraphQL. Strong for decision log + experiment status. Hex / Hex Magic: SaaS, yes API. Notebooks agents can run as jobs. Statsig: SaaS, yes REST. Experimentation + feature flags + warehouse export. Eppo: SaaS, yes REST. Warehouse-native experiment platform. GrowthBook: OSS + SaaS, yes REST + DB. Self-host belief experiments. Pendo / Heap: SaaS, Partial API. Behavioural signal layer. Productlane: SaaS, yes API. Customer-feedback → product loop. Glean: SaaS, yes API. Cross-tool semantic search; "AI-indexed knowledge" layer. Hebbia / Glean Assistant: SaaS, yes agent layer. Enterprise insight surfacing. OpenAI / Anthropic Claude API: SaaS, Native. Belief updater / strategy reviewer brains. Postgres + pgvector: OSS, yes. Belief registry + event store; cheap and ownable.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>posthog API / CLI: Product analytics events, feature flag results — posthog.com/docs/api. amplitude API: Behavioural cohorts, retention deltas — developers.amplitude.com. metabase / cube: SQL-based metric layer agents can query — metabase.com, cube.dev. gong / chorus API: Sales call transcripts, deal signals — app.gong.io/api. fireflies.ai API: Meeting transcripts → searchable corpus — docs.fireflies.ai. intercom / zendesk API: Support tickets, conversation tags — developers.intercom.com. linear / jira API: Decision log, experiment status — developers.linear.app. notion / confluence API: Belief registry storage, audit trail — developers.notion.com. langfuse / helicone: LLM-call observability (your own agents) — langfuse.com. firecrawl / jina reader: Competitor page extraction — firecrawl.dev, r.jina.ai. dbt: Transform raw signals → metric tables — docs.getdbt.com. dagster / prefect / airflow: Schedule the daily/weekly agent loops — dagster.io, prefect.io. git + yamllint: Version beliefs.yaml, diff weekly — trivial. claude (Anthropic SDK): All synthesizer / reviewer agents — docs.anthropic.com.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Treat beliefs.yaml as code: versioned, reviewed, diffable. PR-reviewed belief changes beat Slack-thread consensus. Measure decisions, not insights. Track (decisions made / week) × (decisions reversed within 30 days) — high reversal = noisy loop, low decisions = inert org. Pair every belief with a kill criterion + check-back date. Beliefs without falsifiers rot into dogma. Quarterly calibration: grade past predictions vs outcomes; recalibrate confidence weights and prompt scoring rubrics. Separate "what changed" (Haiku, mechanical) from "what to do" (Opus, judgment). Mixing cost 10x and biases. One belief registry per product line, not per team. Cross-team write access; PM-lead has merge rights. Time-box rituals: Monday 30 min digest, Friday 45 min strategy — drift past that and people skip. Decision logs > meeting notes. A logged decision with prediction + owner + check-back is worth 10 retro pages. Force red-team passes: every belief change must survive a "what would have to be true for this to be wrong?" prompt. Limit watchlist: 3–5 competitors, 1 macro trend, 1 customer segment. Broader scope = noise. Bias to kill on Friday review. Default for evidence-thin items is "kill or reframe", not "keep". Keep the human in the loop on pricing, positioning, hiring — anything irreversible. Agents propose, humans dispose.</p>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/belief_update.py" purpose="Weekly belief-update loop: loads events.ndjson, calls Claude, writes beliefs.yaml"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog/learning-velocity">Reforge — Speed of learning as a moat</link>
      <link href="https://www.producttalk.org">Teresa Torres — Continuous Discovery Habits</link>
      <link href="https://www.producttalk.org/opportunity-solution-tree/">Opportunity-Solution Tree</link>
      <link href="https://www.stratechery.com">Ben Thompson — Aggregation theory and learning-rate moats</link>
      <link href="https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/claude-code/sub-agents">Anthropic Claude Agent SDK</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
