<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-spec-structure" title="Specification Structure v2.0">
  <summary>Section-by-section rules for the full spec v2.0, the two-pass writing process, and the document hierarchy that distinguishes spec from design from implementation plan.</summary>

  <section title="Document Hierarchy">
    <p>The three planning documents answer different questions and must not be conflated:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Specification: WHAT and WHY — requirements, user stories, acceptance criteria.</item>
      <item>Design: HOW — architecture, file structure, API contracts, AD-X decisions.</item>
      <item>Implementation Plan: IN WHAT ORDER — tasks, dependencies, token estimates.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Reject any HOW language from a spec document. If an agent inserts architecture choices or file paths into a spec, move them to design.md.</statement>
      <rationale>HOW language in specs conflates requirements with solutions, blocking the design phase's ability to choose between approaches freely.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Required Sections">
    <rule>
      <statement>A full spec v2.0 must contain all twelve sections in order: Reference Documents, Overview, Problem Statement, User Personas, User Stories, Functional Requirements, Non-Functional Requirements, Acceptance Criteria, Out of Scope, Assumptions and Constraints, Dependencies, Related Features.</statement>
      <rationale>Partial specs cause design-phase debates about unstated requirements. Every missing section represents a gap that will surface during implementation at higher cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every NFR must have a numeric target. "Fast response" is rejected; "&lt; 500ms p95" is accepted. "Secure password storage" is rejected; "bcrypt 12 rounds" is accepted.</statement>
      <rationale>Qualitative NFRs cannot be tested and cannot be cited in design decisions. Numeric targets produce testable quality gates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Status must be "Approved" before the design phase begins. Agents must not auto-proceed from Draft to Approved — this is a human-in-loop gate.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-proceeding skips stakeholder alignment. A design built on a Draft spec produces waste if the spec changes during review.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Two-Pass Writing Process">
    <p>Pass 1 (discovery): Load constitution.md and any related done/ specs. Generate backbone — Problem Statement, User Personas, User Stories, FR skeleton table with placeholder text. Do not write ACs or NFRs yet.</p>
    <p>Pass 2 (formalization): Fill each FR with SMART requirement text (one unambiguous SHALL statement). Add NFR table with numeric targets. Write AC for each Must-priority FR in Given-When-Then. Complete Out of Scope (at least 3 explicit exclusions). Fill Dependencies section.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run Pass 1 and Pass 2 as separate agent invocations. Do not combine them.</statement>
      <rationale>Combined passes cause agents to conflate requirements discovery with requirements writing, producing FRs that are too specific (implementation details) or too vague (missing validation rules).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Traceability Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Traceability must be bidirectional: FR traces to US (forward), AC traces to FR (forward), and AC is validated by FR (back). Orphaned FRs and orphaned ACs are quality gate failures.</statement>
      <rationale>Bidirectional traceability enables mechanical coverage verification: for every Must-priority FR, at least one AC exists and passes, therefore all must-have requirements are satisfied.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
