<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-setup-steps" title="Google Ads Campaign Setup Steps">
  <summary>Step-by-step process for creating a Google Ads Search campaign: conversion tracking, campaign type selection, settings, ad group structure, RSA creation, and extensions.</summary>

  <section title="Conversion Tracking First">
    <rule>
      <statement>Install and verify conversion tracking before creating any campaign that targets a conversion goal.</statement>
      <rationale>Smart Bidding without conversion data wastes ~14 days in learning burning budget. A campaign verified firing conversions starts with useful signal immediately.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Create Google Ads account</item>
      <item>Link to Google Analytics 4</item>
      <item>Create conversion actions (purchase, lead, sign-up, call, install)</item>
      <item>Install Google Tag (gtag.js) or GTM container</item>
      <item>Verify Tag Assistant shows conversions firing before launch</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Campaign Type Selection">
    <list>
      <item>SEARCH: people actively searching — best for high-intent leads, simplest to optimize</item>
      <item>DISPLAY: image ads across websites — brand awareness, retargeting</item>
      <item>SHOPPING: product feed-driven — e-commerce with Merchant Center feed</item>
      <item>VIDEO: YouTube ads — views, awareness, product demos</item>
      <item>PERFORMANCE_MAX: AI cross-channel — requires 30+ conversions/month</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to Search campaign type for new advertisers; it provides direct intent matching and is the easiest to diagnose and optimize.</statement>
      <rationale>Search campaigns match ads to active queries, providing clear signal about intent. Display and PMax require more data and budget to optimize effectively.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Campaign Settings">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always explicitly set target_search_network=False, target_content_network=False, target_partner_search_network=False for Search-only campaigns; the API does not default to Search-only like the UI recommends.</statement>
      <rationale>API-created Search campaigns silently enable Display and Search Partners unless explicitly disabled. This wastes budget on irrelevant placements from day one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Campaign name: [Product]_[Type]_[Goal]_[Date] — enforced via regex</item>
      <item>Networks: Search only (disable Display and Search Partners explicitly)</item>
      <item>Locations: target market specifically (use geoTargetConstants/&lt;id&gt;, not country name strings)</item>
      <item>Languages: match content language</item>
      <item>Bidding: Maximize Conversions (no target CPA) for first 30 conversions</item>
      <item>Budget: minimum $20-50/day; $1/day budget signals a unit error (1,000,000 micros = $1)</item>
      <item>Status: always create as PAUSED; require explicit go-live step</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Ad Group Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>One theme per ad group; 10-20 keywords per group; all keywords in a group must share the same intent and match the ad copy.</statement>
      <rationale>Tightly themed ad groups produce higher Quality Scores because keyword-to-ad relevance improves. Mixing intents dilutes relevance and raises CPC.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Responsive Search Ads">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write at least 3 RSA headlines per ad group with 15 total headlines; include the primary keyword in at least one headline; target Ad Strength of Good or Excellent.</statement>
      <rationale>More headlines give Google more combinations to test, improving CTR over time. Keyword inclusion in headlines raises Quality Score expected CTR component.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Headlines: up to 15, 30 characters each</item>
      <item>Descriptions: up to 4, 90 characters each</item>
      <item>Include: keyword, benefit, social proof, CTA, offer/urgency</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Extensions (Assets)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add sitelinks (4-6), callouts (4-6), and structured snippets at account or campaign level before launch; missing extensions lower ad rank and CTR.</statement>
      <rationale>Extensions expand ad size, increase CTR, and contribute to Quality Score. They are listed as Asset resources in API v12+; using deprecated Extension service resources returns errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
