<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="frameworks Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for frameworks. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick the smallest subset of frameworks that answers the current decision — never run all eight at once. Decision modes: idea, validate, size, position, pivot.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Running all eight frameworks on one idea is framework theater. Agents default to exhaustive execution; the router constraint prevents this and keeps output actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock the ICP in one sentence before any framework runs; reuse that sentence verbatim across all artifacts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Frameworks produce inconsistent outputs when each run re-infers a slightly different ICP. One locked sentence prevents drift and enables downstream SDD agents to ingest artifacts directly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply all 7 Ps systematically, generate 2-3 ideas per P, and tag each idea with its underlying user-pain-id to prevent duplication across Pain/Profession/People cells.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents fill Pain/Profession/People with restatements of the same idea. Requiring a unique user-pain-id per idea forces structural diversity across the seven prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For agent runs, skip "What do you find yourself building for yourself?" — agents cannot honestly answer this and will invent a project. Use the other three questions and pipe in real user history if available.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Paul Graham questions reward introspection, not aggregation. LLMs trained on generic startup content will produce plausible but fabricated answers to introspective prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Validate each Paul Graham answer with 2-3 other people before treating it as a market signal, and check whether solutions already exist.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Personal pain points are necessary but not sufficient for a market. A solution that already exists at reasonable cost means the problem is solved, not an opportunity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score each of five criteria 1-10, require a one-line justification AND a cited source URL for market-size and competition columns before accepting the score.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A 50/50 niche score with zero primary research is worse than no score — it legitimizes guesses. Citations force the agent to ground numbers in real evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply all five validation criteria (frequency, intensity, WTP, search volume, competition) before recommending pursuit; the presence of competitors is a green flag, not a red flag — it confirms the problem exists.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">No competitors usually means no market, not a blue ocean. Absence of search volume means people are not actively looking for a solution. Both are failure signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write the functional JTBD statement first using the "When/I want/So I can" template with a verifiable outcome — reject any outcome phrased as an adjective ("feel empowered") and replace with a measurable verb ("invoice sent in &lt;90s, paid within 14 days").</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">JTBD statements drift into wishful copywriting when outcomes are unmeasurable. Verifiable outcomes anchor product decisions and can be tested in user research.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Triangulate market size with three methods (top-down, bottom-up, competitor-based); do not average if the spread is greater than 2x — report the range and flag the divergence instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Averaging incompatible methods produces false precision. A 2x spread signals that one method's assumptions are wrong; averaging hides the problem and misleads investors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Round aggressively — $8.3B is fake precision, $8B is honest. Use two significant figures maximum for TAM/SAM.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Market sizing compounds errors across four multipliers. Reporting four significant figures implies an accuracy that the underlying data does not support.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap competitor analysis at 5-7 named direct players plus one explicit "long tail" row; tag the rest as "long tail" with an estimated count.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents over-list adjacent products to appear thorough. A table of 20 competitors is less useful than a tight table of 6 with deeper analysis per row.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Check VPC fit against actual user quotes (cite interview ID per row), not assumed pains/gains — agents over-claim fit when both sides of the canvas are invented.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A VPC always "fits" if the agent invented both customer profile and value map. Requiring interview citations per pain-reliever and gain-creator row forces the canvas to be grounded in evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cite a URL with retrieval date on every external number. LLM-only cells are explicitly tagged "estimate".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs hallucinate framework cells fluently. Without a citation requirement the niche matrix becomes confidently wrong. The "estimate" tag signals which numbers need validation before acting on them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require two independent scorers (or two agent runs) for niche scoring; average only if within 2 points on each criterion.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Identical inputs to two agent runs produce 15+ point spread. Two runs with averaged scores are more reliable than one run treated as ground truth.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
