<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework-router" title="Research Framework Router">
  <summary>Decision router that maps the current question to the smallest set of applicable frameworks and defines the artifact pipeline from idea to spec.</summary>

  <section title="Router Logic">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick the smallest subset of frameworks that answers the current decision — never run all eight at once. Decision modes: idea, validate, size, position, pivot.</statement>
      <rationale>Running all eight frameworks on one idea is framework theater. Agents default to exhaustive execution; the router constraint prevents this and keeps output actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>idea mode: 7Ps + Paul Graham questions + niche evaluation</item>
      <item>validate mode: validation criteria + JTBD + problem interviews</item>
      <item>size mode: TAM/SAM/SOM + competitor analysis</item>
      <item>position mode: Value Proposition Canvas + competitor analysis + JTBD</item>
      <item>pivot mode: niche evaluation + TAM/SAM/SOM + Value Proposition Canvas</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the ICP in one sentence before any framework runs; reuse that sentence verbatim across all artifacts.</statement>
      <rationale>Frameworks produce inconsistent outputs when each run re-infers a slightly different ICP. One locked sentence prevents drift and enables downstream SDD agents to ingest artifacts directly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Artifact Pipeline (Idea to Spec)">
    <list>
      <item>1. Discovery: apply 7Ps + Paul Graham in parallel; output idea-candidates.md (10-20 raw ideas)</item>
      <item>2. Triage: score each candidate on the 50-point niche matrix; cull anything below 30</item>
      <item>3. Validation: pick top 3, run validation criteria with primary research (5+ interviews, Google Trends, Reddit)</item>
      <item>4. Jobs: write JTBD statements (functional + emotional + social) for the survivor</item>
      <item>5. Sizing: TAM/SAM/SOM via three-method triangulation; flag spread &gt; 2x; do not average</item>
      <item>6. Competition: fill 6-dimension table (features, pricing, positioning, tech, feedback, GTM)</item>
      <item>7. Positioning: Value Proposition Canvas; check pain-relievers cover top-3 pains</item>
      <item>8. Handoff: write executive-summary.md linking all artifacts; pass to faion-sdd for spec.md</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Citation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cite a URL with retrieval date on every external number. LLM-only cells are explicitly tagged "estimate".</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs hallucinate framework cells fluently. Without a citation requirement the niche matrix becomes confidently wrong. The "estimate" tag signals which numbers need validation before acting on them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require two independent scorers (or two agent runs) for niche scoring; average only if within 2 points on each criterion.</statement>
      <rationale>Identical inputs to two agent runs produce 15+ point spread. Two runs with averaged scores are more reliable than one run treated as ground truth.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Recommended Subagents">
    <list>
      <item>faion-research-agent: orchestrator, 9 modes (ideas, niche, market, competitors, pricing, personas, pains, validate, names)</item>
      <item>faion-market-researcher-agent: owns sizing, competitor table, pricing, trend analysis frameworks</item>
      <item>faion-user-researcher-agent: owns JTBD, VPC customer side, pains, personas, validation interviews</item>
      <item>faion-domain-checker-agent: pairs with positioning output when a name shortlist is generated</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/framework-router.sh">Shell router that prints the framework subset for a given decision mode.</reference>
</text>
