<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-ideation-frameworks" title="7Ps Ideation and Paul Graham Questions">
  <summary>Two complementary idea-generation frameworks: 7Ps systematic ideation and Paul Graham's introspection prompts, with anti-duplication rules for agent use.</summary>

  <section title="7Ps of Ideation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply all 7 Ps systematically, generate 2-3 ideas per P, and tag each idea with its underlying user-pain-id to prevent duplication across Pain/Profession/People cells.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents fill Pain/Profession/People with restatements of the same idea. Requiring a unique user-pain-id per idea forces structural diversity across the seven prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Pain: What frustrates you (or your target user) daily? Focus on problems you personally understand.</item>
      <item>Passion: What do you love doing? Look for intersection with a market need.</item>
      <item>Profession: What is broken in your industry? Look for manual, error-prone, or expensive processes.</item>
      <item>Process: What workflow is inefficient? Code review, billing, scheduling, onboarding.</item>
      <item>Platform: What can be improved on an existing platform? Better Slack integrations, Notion plugins, VS Code extensions.</item>
      <item>People: Who do you know with problems? Freelancers, founders, ops teams, developers.</item>
      <item>Product: What product do you wish existed? What do you hack together repeatedly?</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Intersection of multiple Ps is the highest-signal zone: Pain (meeting coordination is broken) + Passion (developer tooling) + Platform (VS Code) = async standup bot for distributed engineering teams.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Paul Graham Questions">
    <rule>
      <statement>For agent runs, skip "What do you find yourself building for yourself?" — agents cannot honestly answer this and will invent a project. Use the other three questions and pipe in real user history if available.</statement>
      <rationale>Paul Graham questions reward introspection, not aggregation. LLMs trained on generic startup content will produce plausible but fabricated answers to introspective prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>What is tedious but necessary? Look for manual, repetitive tasks that users accept as unavoidable.</item>
      <item>What is surprisingly hard to do? Tasks that seem simple but require expert knowledge or coordination.</item>
      <item>What would you pay for that does not exist? Unmet needs with demonstrated willingness to pay.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate each Paul Graham answer with 2-3 other people before treating it as a market signal, and check whether solutions already exist.</statement>
      <rationale>Personal pain points are necessary but not sufficient for a market. A solution that already exists at reasonable cost means the problem is solved, not an opportunity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
