<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-mining-fundamentals" title="Process Mining Fundamentals: Algorithms, Event Logs, and Mining Types">
  <summary>Discovery algorithm comparison, minimum event-log requirements, and mining question taxonomy (discovery vs conformance vs enhancement).</summary>

  <section title="Mining Question Taxonomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name the mining question type (discovery, conformance, or enhancement) before selecting an algorithm; each produces a different artefact.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents that conflate discovery and conformance produce graphs nobody asked for; naming the question type prevents wasted analysis cycles.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Discovery: reconstruct the actual process model from event data — produces a Petri net or DFG.</item>
      <item>Conformance: compare the discovered model against a normative BPMN/Petri net — produces a fitness/precision score and deviation log.</item>
      <item>Enhancement: enrich an existing model with performance data (cycle time, waiting time, resource load) — produces an annotated model.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Event Log Minimum Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Audit the event log for three minimum columns (case_id, activity, timestamp) and additional quality checks before selecting any tool or algorithm.</statement>
      <rationale>80% of process mining project effort is log preparation; running an algorithm on an unprepared log produces an unsound or unreadable result regardless of tool quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Required columns: case_id (unique per process instance), activity (discrete label), timestamp (datetime, not date-only).</item>
      <item>Minimum scale: &gt;= 200 cases; &lt; 3 activities or &gt; 200 activities — taxonomy problem, not a mining problem.</item>
      <item>Bad timestamp rate: reject if more than 2% of rows have unparseable timestamps.</item>
      <item>Case cardinality: if one case_id spans multiple business processes, split first.</item>
      <item>Activity vocabulary: if free-text comments, define a grouping taxonomy before mining.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Proceeding to algorithm selection with only case_id/activity/timestamp columns validated, skipping timestamp format, case-ID consistency, and vocabulary size checks.</description>
      <reason>Even a structurally valid log fails when timestamps are date-only (no ordering within a day), case IDs cross process boundaries, or activity labels are free-text — each produces a spaghetti DFG or unsound Petri net.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="templates/pm-feasibility-audit.py">Python script auditing a CSV log for mining readiness and recommending an algorithm.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Discovery Algorithm Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select a single named algorithm variant with explicit rationale; reject "use whichever the tool defaults to."</statement>
      <rationale>Alpha Miner cannot handle loops or noise; Heuristic Miner handles noise but loses formal guarantees; Inductive Miner guarantees soundness but trades fitness for precision. The wrong choice on a real-world log wastes a month of debugging.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Activity count &lt; 15 and variant count &lt; 30: Alpha Miner. Variant count &gt; 100 or significant noise: Inductive Miner (infrequent variant). Moderate noise, loop presence: Heuristic Miner.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Running Alpha Miner on a real-world ITSM log with 5,000 cases and 600+ variants — Alpha cannot handle loops or noise, producing an unsound Petri net that is unreadable and invalid.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Disclose the algorithm name and parameters on every mining artefact; downstream readers cannot judge the graph's reliability without them.</statement>
      <rationale>Vendors rebrand standard algorithms; the BA must press for the specific algorithm and its defaults, then record them on the deliverable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Variant Filtering">
    <rule>
      <statement>Filter to top-10 variants by frequency for first review; surface the long tail only after the main flow is understood.</statement>
      <rationale>A real ITSM log with 5,000 cases surfaces 600+ variants; the unfiltered discovery graph is unreadable, creating the "spaghetti DFG presented as success" failure mode.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a node/edge count gate (e.g., abort if more than 40 nodes without explicit override) to prevent unreadable outputs being delivered as complete work.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents do not perceive graph unreadability; they deliver a 600-node SVG and call the task done without a structural quality gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
