<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-automation-assessment" title="Automation Candidate Assessment and Adoption Gate">
  <summary>Automation readiness scoring criteria, RPA vs intelligent automation comparison, and six-criterion adoption gate for deciding whether to proceed with a process-mining initiative.</summary>

  <section title="Automation Candidate Scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score automation candidates on six criteria before selecting a technology; do not target automation based on stakeholder enthusiasm.</statement>
      <rationale>RPA initiatives that skip structured scoring fail at high rates — most failures trace to poor process understanding and incorrect assumption that the process is rule-based.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Volume (high weight): target &gt;= 100 transactions/day.</item>
      <item>Standardization (high weight): rule-based with low exception rate.</item>
      <item>Stability (medium weight): process unchanged for &gt;= 6 months.</item>
      <item>Digital Input (medium weight): structured data available, not image/PDF only.</item>
      <item>Error Rate (medium weight): high manual error frequency indicates automation value.</item>
      <item>ROI Potential (high weight): high labor cost, quick payback period.</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Score each criterion 1-5. Total &gt; 24 of 30: full automation. 18-24: partial automation. 12-18: process improvement first, then re-assess. &lt; 12: not suitable for automation.</note>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/automation-assessment.md">Automation readiness scoring template with ROI estimate skeleton.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="RPA vs Intelligent Automation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Distinguish RPA (rule-based, repetitive, structured data only) from Intelligent Automation (AI-driven decisions, structured and unstructured data, continuous improvement) before tool selection.</statement>
      <rationale>Selecting RPA for variable/complex processes leads to high exception rates and human-in-the-loop bottlenecks that negate automation benefits.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>RPA: task type = rule-based and repetitive; decision making = predefined rules; data = structured only; exceptions = human escalation; learning = none.</item>
      <item>Intelligent Automation: task type = complex and variable; decision making = AI-driven; data = structured + unstructured; exceptions = autonomous handling; learning = continuous improvement.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Adoption Gate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run six adoption criteria before committing to a process-mining initiative; if any criterion produces a no-go, name the single blocker and the cheapest experiment to unblock it.</statement>
      <rationale>Tool procurement and initiative launch on a no-go log or an illiterate stakeholder group wastes budget with no recoverable output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Event-log availability: can the source system export a log with case_id, activity, timestamp?</item>
      <item>Case volume: &gt;= 200 cases minimum; &lt; 200 use SQL.</item>
      <item>Stakeholder literacy: does at least one BA or process owner understand DFG/Petri net outputs?</item>
      <item>Regulatory tolerance: does GDPR/HIPAA/other regulation permit event-log extraction and storage?</item>
      <item>Tooling budget: open-source (pm4py) / mid-market (Apromore) / enterprise (Celonis) — align with ROI estimate.</item>
      <item>Automation downstream dependency: is there an actual automation or redesign plan, or is mining a curiosity exercise?</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Conflating process mining (reconstructing flows from system logs) with task mining (desktop click recording) or with BPM (modeling desired processes).</description>
      <reason>Incorrect categorization leads to wrong tool purchase: Celonis for task-mining needs, or UiPath Task Mining for a conformance-checking goal. The budget is wasted and the initiative fails on deliverable mismatch.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
