<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-design-process" title="Structured Interview Design Process">
  <summary>Six-step process for building a consistent, predictive interview structure: competency definition, question creation, rubric design, interviewer training, consistent execution, and evidence-based debrief.</summary>

  <section title="Why Structure Matters">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the same questions in the same order for every candidate; deviation breaks comparability and introduces interviewer-specific bias.</statement>
      <rationale>Meta-analyses (Schmidt and Hunter, 1998; Structured Interviewing meta-analysis, 2016) show structured interviews have validity twice that of unstructured ones for predicting job performance. Consistency is the mechanism: without it, you are comparing different data points, not different candidates.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Competencies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify 4-6 competencies per role; more than 6 cannot be evaluated in a standard interview loop without diluting each assessment.</statement>
      <rationale>Each competency requires 2-3 questions and meaningful scoring time. With 4-6 competencies across 4-5 interview rounds, each round can own 1-2 competencies without overlap.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Competency Profiles by Level">
      <p>Individual contributor: technical skills, problem-solving, communication, collaboration.</p>
      <p>Manager: leadership, delegation, developing others, strategic thinking.</p>
      <p>Executive: vision, influence, business acumen, change management.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Create Questions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write 2-3 behavioral questions per competency; pair with 1 situational question for roles where candidates may lack direct experience.</statement>
      <rationale>Behavioral questions ("Tell me about a time...") require real past examples. Situational questions ("What would you do if...") are weaker but necessary when the candidate pool includes career-changers or new graduates.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Question Type Selection">
      <p>Behavioral: past performance; preferred for any competency where the candidate should have prior experience. Situational: hypothetical; use for competencies new-to-role candidates cannot yet demonstrate. Technical: skill assessment; architecture, code, or domain-specific knowledge. Motivational: fit and values; use sparingly, not as a substitute for behavioral evidence.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Build Scoring Rubric">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define behavioral anchors for each score on the rating scale before the interview loop begins; anchors must describe observable behaviors, not impressions.</statement>
      <rationale>Without anchors, a "4" means different things to different interviewers. Behavioral anchors ("Identified root cause; implemented a lasting solution visible to the team") produce cross-interviewer score correlation above 0.8 when calibrated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Rating scale: 5 = exceptional (far exceeds expectations), 4 = strong (exceeds), 3 = meets, 2 = developing (below), 1 = insufficient (does not meet).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Steps 4-6: Train, Execute, Debrief">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a calibration session with all interviewers before the first candidate; score a sample response together and discuss divergence.</statement>
      <rationale>Interviewers who have never calibrated together will diverge by 1-2 points on the same evidence. A 30-minute calibration session closes most of that gap before it affects real candidates.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Collect all interviewer scores independently before the debrief meeting; discussing scores first collapses independent signals into one opinion.</statement>
      <rationale>When the first voice in a debrief is strong (hiring manager, senior engineer), subsequent scorers anchor to it regardless of their own evidence. Independent scoring is the primary mechanism for maintaining panel diversity value.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
