<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-scoring" title="Interview Scoring, Behavioral Anchors, and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Rating scale definition, how to write behavioral anchors for each score, common scoring antipatterns, and metrics for evaluating interview process quality.</summary>

  <section title="Rating Scale">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a 1-5 rating scale; avoid 7- or 10-point scales that introduce false precision without additional behavioral anchor resolution.</statement>
      <rationale>A 1-5 scale maps cleanly to behavioral anchors (exceptional / strong / meets / developing / insufficient). Wider scales force interviewers to make distinctions the anchors cannot support, producing noise rather than signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Scale Definitions">
      <p>5 — Exceptional: far exceeds expectations; demonstrates this competency at a level above the role requirements; would be an outlier contributor on the team.</p>
      <p>4 — Strong: exceeds expectations; demonstrates this competency beyond what is minimally required; likely to perform well in the first year without significant ramp.</p>
      <p>3 — Meets: meets expectations; demonstrates this competency at the level the role requires; standard hire.</p>
      <p>2 — Developing: below expectations; demonstrates partial evidence of this competency; would require significant coaching or favorable conditions.</p>
      <p>1 — Insufficient: does not meet requirements; cannot demonstrate this competency; not suitable for this role at this time.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Behavioral Anchors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write behavioral anchors before the interview loop begins, not after scoring; post-hoc anchors are written to justify scores already given.</statement>
      <rationale>Anchors written after scoring rationalize the gut impression rather than defining the evidence standard. Pre-written anchors force the interviewer to look for specific behaviors during the interview, not after.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <note>Problem-Solving anchor example. Score 5: "Solved an ambiguous, cross-functional problem; created a framework or approach now used by others on the team." Score 4: "Identified root cause through systematic analysis; implemented a solution that persisted beyond the immediate situation." Score 3: "Solved a standard problem using a known approach; logical reasoning but did not go beyond the expected path." Score 2: "Needed significant guidance; could describe the problem but struggled to identify a path forward independently." Score 1: "Could not demonstrate problem-solving ability; responses were hypothetical or described team effort without personal contribution."</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Scoring "culture fit" as an unanchored gut impression.</description>
      <reason>Unanchored "culture fit" is the most common vector for affinity bias. Replace with a specific competency ("alignment with operating principles", "collaboration style") that has behavioral anchors like any other.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Asking different questions to different candidates and still using a shared scorecard.</description>
      <reason>A scorecard built for Question A cannot validly assess a candidate who answered Question B. The scores are not comparable, and the process will not withstand an audit.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Discussing candidate impressions in Slack or over lunch before the formal debrief.</description>
      <reason>Informal pre-debrief discussion anchors subsequent scorers to the first opinion shared; it functions as an unstructured debrief with no documentation. Written scores before any discussion is the only protection against anchoring.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Panel of more than 5 interviewers per candidate.</description>
      <reason>Beyond 5 interviewers, candidate fatigue produces declining response quality in later rounds, and scorecard aggregation yields diminishing returns. Incremental signal from round 6+ is noise, not information.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Process Quality Metrics">
    <p>Interview-to-offer rate: target 15-25%; significantly below may indicate over-filtering, above may indicate insufficient rigor. Quality of hire: percentage of hires meeting or exceeding expectations at 1-year review; target above 80%. Interviewer calibration: score correlation across interviewers on the same candidate; target above 80% agreement within 1 point. Candidate experience: post-interview survey score; target above 4.0/5. Time in interview process: total calendar days from first interview to offer; predictable, not necessarily short, is the target.</p>
  </section>
</text>
