<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="structured-interview-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for structured-interview-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Scoring "culture fit" as an unanchored gut impression.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unanchored "culture fit" is the most common vector for affinity bias. Replace with a specific competency ("alignment with operating principles", "collaboration style") that has behavioral anchors like any other.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Asking different questions to different candidates and still using a shared scorecard.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A scorecard built for Question A cannot validly assess a candidate who answered Question B. The scores are not comparable, and the process will not withstand an audit.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Discussing candidate impressions in Slack or over lunch before the formal debrief.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Informal pre-debrief discussion anchors subsequent scorers to the first opinion shared; it functions as an unstructured debrief with no documentation. Written scores before any discussion is the only protection against anchoring.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Panel of more than 5 interviewers per candidate.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Beyond 5 interviewers, candidate fatigue produces declining response quality in later rounds, and scorecard aggregation yields diminishing returns. Incremental signal from round 6+ is noise, not information.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
