<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="devops-platform-policy-finops Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for devops-platform-policy-finops. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All Kubernetes Pods and Deployments on the platform MUST pass the following admission gates enforced via Gatekeeper ConstraintTemplates: (1) required labels — team and app labels mandatory on all pods; (2) resource limits required — all containers must declare CPU and memory limits; (3) non-root execution — runAsNonRoot: true required unless explicitly exempted with a documented justification stored in an exemption ConfigMap. ConstraintTemplates MUST be applied in dry-run mode for 2 weeks before switching to enforce mode to avoid blocking existing workloads.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Resource limits prevent a single pod from starving other pods on the node (noisy neighbor problem). Required labels are the prerequisite for cost allocation by team. Non-root execution is a CIS Kubernetes Benchmark requirement. The 2-week dry-run prevents the constraint from blocking existing legitimate workloads on day one of enforcement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Platform tagging standards MUST require the following tags on all cloud resources created through platform golden paths: team (owning team name), service (service name from catalog), environment (development | staging | production), cost-center (business unit for chargeback). Tags MUST be enforced via Gatekeeper policies (Kubernetes) or AWS Service Control Policies / GCP Organization Policies (cloud resources). Untagged resources MUST generate an alert to the platform team within 24 hours of creation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cost allocation is impossible without consistent tagging. Retroactive tagging campaigns (after 6-12 months of untagged resources) typically achieve 40-60% coverage — the remaining 40% is permanently unattributable. Enforcement at creation time achieves near-100% coverage without manual remediation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per-team cost dashboards MUST be accessible to all team members (not just finance) and MUST update at least daily. Dashboards MUST show: current month spend by team and service, 30-day trend, top 5 cost drivers, and projected month-end spend. Cost data MUST be available in the developer portal (Backstage plugin) so developers see cost impact alongside deployment status.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cost signals only change developer behavior when they are visible at the point of decision. Finance reports delivered monthly do not change provisioning decisions made 3 weeks earlier. Same-day cost visibility in the developer portal is the mechanism that drives the 15-30% cost reduction observed in orgs with mature FinOps practices.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
