<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="White-Label Partnership Design Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every White-Label Partnership Design application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-pricing-2x-direct-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>White-label rate ≥1.5-2× direct rate. Reasoning: client-facing comms, revisions overhead, brand-suppression all add cost.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Industry rule-of-thumb: below 1.5× direct rate, white-label is a net loss after support costs.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-captivity-cap-30-percent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No single primary agency contributes &gt;30% of revenue. Beyond = effectively captive.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Captivity caps protect against single-agency departure = business failure; 30% is the empirically safe ceiling.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-anti-circumvent-clause" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Contract: primary agency commits to no circumvent (going direct to your contractors). You commit to no direct-client poaching.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Trust collapses under circumvention; explicit clause is the only safeguard.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-brand-attribution-policy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Contract clarifies: no brand attribution (white-label) OR limited (e.g., 'powered by' in fine print). Surprise attribution kills the partnership.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Brand-attribution surprise is the #1 white-label dispute; explicit policy prevents.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-quarterly-relationship-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly review with primary agency: workload, quality, revenue share, future projects. Maintains relationship + surfaces friction.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Without review, friction accumulates silently until rupture; quarterly cadence is the safety valve.</rationale>
    </rule>

  
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If all Applies-If preconditions hold and no Skip-If disqualifier is present, execute the full procedure from `04-procedure.xml` and commit the artefact described in `02-output-contract.xml`.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's affirmative leaf; pairs the preconditions with the methodology's commit path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Skip-If condition is present (one-shot, &lt;3 instances/year, regulator override, missing owner), do NOT apply this methodology. Route to the sibling/upstream methodology named in `AGENTS.md` Related section.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's skip leaf; prevents over-application of a heavyweight artefact when the loop conditions do not hold.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>