<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Benefits Realization Rules and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Rules for ownership, baseline discipline, attribution, agentic tracking, and avoiding the common failure modes that make benefit tracking theatre.</summary>

  <section title="Ownership and Baseline">
    <rule>
      <statement>The benefit owner is a named business stakeholder with operational levers post-handover; the PM is never the benefit owner.</statement>
      <rationale>PMs have no authority over adoption, process change, or operational incentives after project close; assigning ownership to the PM creates accountability without power, guaranteeing the benefit is never tracked.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Baseline measurements must be taken before go-live; if the baseline cannot be established, flag it as an open task (baseline=null), not a zero.</statement>
      <rationale>A zero baseline implies the current state is zero, which is rarely true; null + open-task is honest and triggers the measurement activity before launch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Sponsor sign-off on benefit definitions — metric, baseline, target, owner, measurement source — is a project initiation gate; "we'll figure out metrics later" is a known failure mode.</statement>
      <rationale>Benefits defined post-launch are shaped by the actual outcomes observed, not by the investment thesis; they cannot serve as evidence of ROI.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Attribution Discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Declare the attribution method upfront (cohort, before/after with controls, holdout, qualitative); default to "qualitative" rather than fabricating causality from correlation.</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple concurrent initiatives make clean attribution impossible without deliberate experimental design; admitting qualitative attribution is honest. Asserting causality without design is misleading and damages trust when challenged.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents or analysts asserting benefit causality from correlation in post-launch data without a declared attribution method.</description>
      <reason>Attribution hallucination overstates the project's impact, inflates reported ROI, and corrupts future investment decisions by rewarding projects that benefited from coincident market or operational improvements.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Benefits Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>The benefit-author agent must reject any benefit entry that lacks metric + baseline + target + owner + metric_source; null baseline is permitted but must flag an open measurement task.</statement>
      <rationale>Incomplete entries are accepted and abandoned; rejection at authoring time forces the conversation about measurability before resources are committed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>The RAG rubric is deterministic: GREEN if actual &gt;= 90% of expected curve, YELLOW 70-89%, RED below 70%; the reporting agent must not soften RED without an explicit sponsor-override note.</statement>
      <rationale>Narrative agents have a politeness bias toward GREEN; a hard rule removes the soft option and ensures sponsors see accurate status even when it is uncomfortable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/benefits_status.py">Realization % and RAG computation script</reference>
    <reference path="templates/benefits-register.md">Benefits register template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/realization-report.md">Post-launch realization report template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Portfolio Discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Recompute portfolio ROI annually using realized measurement data, not original business-case forecasts; this is the feedback loop that calibrates future investment decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Organizations that compare actuals to forecasts learn to forecast better; those that only use original forecasts systematically over-invest in project types that reliably under-deliver.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
