<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ops-contractor-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>Four-phase framework for managing contractors post-hire: onboard with docs and tools, establish async communication, assign scoped tasks, evaluate monthly using SBI-R feedback.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>contractors</tag>
      <tag>management</tag>
      <tag>operations</tag>
      <tag>feedback</tag>
      <tag>oversight</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Contractor Management and Operational Oversight</title>

    <summary>A four-phase operational framework for managing hired contractors after the contract is signed: onboard with documentation and tool access, establish async communication rhythm (daily/weekly/monthly), assign tasks with explicit scope and examples, and evaluate performance monthly using an SBI-R (Situation-Behavior-Impact-Request) feedback structure.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Contractors fail silently: without a documented onboarding kit, clear quality standards, and structured feedback, quality drifts and scope creeps — but the manager doesn't discover it until a deadline is missed. Front-loading documentation and structured check-ins reduces rework and miscommunication, which is the primary cost driver in contractor engagements.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Onboarding a new contractor: build doc pack, provision tooling, schedule check-in cadence</item>
        <item>Aggregating weekly/monthly status across multiple contractors</item>
        <item>Drafting structured SBI-R feedback from observed work output</item>
        <item>Performance evaluation cycles: synthesize a review from logged tasks and quality signals</item>
        <item>Standardizing communication rhythm for an async, multi-timezone contractor roster</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-hire screening and sourcing — use ops-contractor-basics</item>
        <item>Conflict resolution or termination conversations — human-only; agents can prep facts but not deliver</item>
        <item>Performance issues that may signal worker misclassification — escalate to legal first</item>
        <item>Managing W-2 employees — different feedback frameworks (1:1s, OKRs, comp reviews)</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="onboarding">
      <p>Deliver a complete onboarding document before the contractor starts the first task. The onboarding kit must include: business context, role description, tool list with access, working norms, quality standards with examples, and a communication guide.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Deliver a complete onboarding document before the contractor starts the first task. The onboarding kit must include: business context, role description, tool list with access, working norms, quality standards with examples, and a communication guide.</statement>
        <rationale>Front-loading documentation pays back within the first deliverable cycle. Contractors who understand context produce work that requires fewer revision rounds. Without examples of quality standards, the contractor defaults to their own standards, which may not match yours.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Onboarding checklist: send welcome message, provision tool access, share documentation, assign a first task that is smaller than normal scope (a win builds confidence), schedule first check-in within the first week.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="communication-rhythm">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use async-first communication (Slack threads, Loom) for daily updates and blockers. Reserve synchronous calls for ambiguous problems only. Set explicit response-time expectations in the onboarding document.</statement>
        <rationale>Requiring instant responses creates artificial urgency and degrades contractor autonomy. Async-first respects timezone differences and produces a documented record. Sync calls for ambiguous problems avoid the back-and-forth that inflates async threads.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Communication cadence: daily async updates (Slack, brief), weekly check-in (call or video for planning and review), monthly performance review (structured evaluation with rating rubric).</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not micromanage. Provide goal, context, deliverable, deadline, and reference material. Do not specify process steps unless the contractor requests guidance.</statement>
        <rationale>Micromanagement signals distrust, reduces initiative, and creates employee-classification risk in jurisdictions that weigh behavioral control heavily in contractor tests.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="task-assignment">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every task assignment must include: goal (outcome, not steps), context (why this matters, current baseline), deliverable (specific output format), deadline (realistic date), and reference (example of good work).</statement>
        <rationale>Tasks specified by deliverable rather than process give contractors creative latitude while maintaining outcome accountability. Without context, contractors optimize for effort instead of outcome.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Well-specified task">
        <note>Task: Redesign pricing page. Goal: increase conversions by 20%. Context: current page has 2% conversion, competitors average 4%. Deliverable: Figma design + rationale document. Deadline: Friday, Jan 26. Reference: [link to competitor examples]. This gives outcome, baseline, format, date, and reference — no process specified.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Poorly-specified task">
        <note>Task: "Make the pricing page better." No goal, no baseline, no deliverable format, no deadline, no reference. The contractor will produce whatever "better" means to them.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="feedback-framework">
      <p>Give all feedback using the SBI-R format: Situation (what context), Behavior (what they did), Impact (measurable effect), Request (what to do differently). Log feedback the same week the behavior occurs — SBI loses signal at one-month delay.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Give all feedback using the SBI-R format: Situation (what context), Behavior (what they did), Impact (measurable effect), Request (what to do differently). Log feedback the same week the behavior occurs — SBI loses signal at one-month delay.</statement>
        <rationale>Generic feedback ("the quality was low") does not change behavior because it does not identify the specific action to change. SBI-R connects a specific observable behavior to a measurable outcome, making the causal link actionable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Positive SBI-R feedback">
        <note>Situation: yesterday's blog post. Behavior: you added data visualization and internal links. Impact: increased time-on-page by 40% and shares by 3x. Request: keep using this approach for future posts. Amplifies a specific behavior tied to measured outcomes.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Constructive SBI-R feedback">
        <note>Situation: last week's email campaign. Behavior: subject line was generic ("Newsletter #5"). Impact: open rate dropped to 12% versus usual 25%. Request: use specific, benefit-focused subject lines — see linked examples. Identifies the specific behavior and provides a redirect.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Giving feedback at monthly cadence instead of same-week.</description>
        <reason>Behavioral connection weakens beyond one week. Contractors cannot recall the specific micro-decision that produced the outcome; feedback becomes abstract criticism.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="common-issues-and-roots">
      <p>Root causes and fixes: slow delivery (unclear priorities — set deadlines and rank tasks), quality problems (misaligned expectations — provide examples and explicit standards), communication gaps (timezone mismatch — set overlap hours and async tools), scope creep (undefined boundaries — define deliverables upfront in writing), inconsistent work (no documented process — document standards and create checklists for recurring deliverables).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="evaluation">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run a structured monthly review even when nothing is wrong. Rate the contractor on five areas (quality 1–5, communication 1–5, reliability 1–5, speed 1–5, proactiveness 1–5), document highlights and improvement areas, and make an explicit decision: continue, adjust scope/rate, or end engagement.</statement>
        <rationale>Small frictions surface only when prompted. An informal "things seem fine" assessment misses gradual drift in quality, communication delays, or changes in availability that compound over quarters. An explicit decision prevents engagement inertia.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Maintain a "contractor onboarding kit" repo (Notion or git) that ships intact to every new contractor — versioned, reviewed quarterly.</statement>
        <rationale>A versioned onboarding kit ensures consistency across contractors and reduces ramp-up time. It also forces documentation discipline that prevents institutional knowledge from existing only in the manager's head.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Source README assumes single-PM single-contractor; doesn't cover contractor-managing-contractor or pod structures. SBI feedback framework is helpful as scaffolding but cannot capture nuance of repeated underperformance — human judgment required. Time tracking metrics are vulnerable to gaming; the methodology trusts self-reported hours. No guidance on contractor-to-employee conversion (visa, comp, equity) — out of scope. Cross-cultural feedback norms differ widely; the SBI template reads as US/Western-direct and may need softening for some markets.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM-generated feedback drifts toward mealy-mouthed praise without specific behavior + measurable impact.</description>
        <reason>Agents default to positive framing. Force SBI structure and require at least one concrete behavior + one measurable outcome in every feedback block.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent over-trusts time-tracker self-reports without cross-checking against PR/commit/asset volume.</description>
        <reason>Time tracking is vulnerable to gaming. Before passing hours to evaluation, cross-check reported time against verifiable output volume.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent digests Slack history and flattens sarcasm and friction signals.</description>
        <reason>Any thread with more than 5 back-and-forth messages indicates friction that requires human reading, not summarization.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent auto-paying invoices or auto-approving payment without human review.</description>
        <reason>Cross-border payments on disputed work are hard to claw back. Each invoice requires explicit human approval against the SOW.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent pulling Slack or Notion into LLM context without redaction of customer data.</description>
        <reason>Status threads frequently reference customer names, deal sizes, or support issues. Use a redaction step before any external-API LLM call.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-generated SOW addenda re-introducing default IP/confidentiality clauses that conflict with the master agreement.</description>
        <reason>Always diff any agent-generated addendum against the signed master agreement before sending.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <p>Treat the agent as a contractor ops layer: it ingests Slack/Loom transcripts, time-tracker exports, and PR/asset deliverables, then emits weekly status digests, missed-deadline alerts, and draft feedback notes. The principal reviews and personalizes before sending. Pair with ops-contractor-basics (pre-hire) and ops-legal-basics (contracts, IP assignment). For payment workflows, drive Deel/Wise/Stripe Connect via their REST APIs.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-growth-agent (source README) — owns the management loop; drafts check-in notes, evaluations. /faion — when contractor work is dev-tracked in SDD tasks, sequence and gate task acceptance. improver — quarterly: identify recurring blockers across contractor pool and propose process fixes. General-purpose Claude subagent for SBI feedback drafting: prompt with situation/behavior/impact triples, generate request.</p>

      <p>Prompt pattern: "You have &lt;contractor&gt;'s last 4 weekly check-ins (attached) and the original SOW. Output: (1) trend summary 3 bullets, (2) one risk to flag, (3) draft monthly review using the framework Quality/Communication/Reliability/Speed/Proactiveness, 1-5 + notes. Stay neutral; do not recommend continue/end — that's the human's call."</p>

      <p>Prompt pattern: "Convert this raw observation into SBI-R feedback (max 100 words): '&lt;contractor&gt; shipped pricing-page redesign 2 days late, but the design lifted conv from 2% to 3.4% per Friday A/B test'"</p>

      <p>CLI tools: gh (track contractor PRs, review diffs, gate merges), slack-cli/slack-sdk (pull thread history for status digests), toggl API client (pull time entries by user/project), harvest CLI (pull invoiced hours, project budgets), linear CLI (sync contractor task list, priorities), loom API (pull async-video update transcripts).</p>

      <p>Services: Deel (REST API for contracts, time, milestones, payments; end-to-end agent-drivable), Remote.com (similar to Deel; stronger in EU), Bonsai (solo-friendly: contracts + time + invoicing in one API), Notion (source of truth for SOWs, playbooks, onboarding docs; strong API), Linear (best-in-class API for task assignment + status), Asana (API for project tracking; weaker than Linear for dev work), Slack (API for digests, async standups, alerts), Loom (transcripts via API on paid plan; video content not parseable), Toggl/Harvest/Clockify (all have time-tracking APIs), DocuSign/HelloSign (e-sign new SOW addenda programmatically).</p>

      <p>Token economics: ingesting 4 weeks of Slack history per contractor is multi-100k tokens. Pre-summarize daily, cache, then reduce.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Front-load documentation: a complete onboarding pack pays back within the first deliverable cycle. Define "done" with examples, not adjectives. "Match this past piece" beats "high quality." Use async-first communication (Slack threads + Loom) and reserve sync calls for ambiguous problems only. Run a structured monthly review even when nothing's wrong — small frictions surface only when prompted. Log feedback the same week the behavior happens; SBI loses signal at one-month delay. Treat the contractor like a contractor: avoid setting fixed working hours, providing all tools, or branding them as your team to clients (misclassification flags). Maintain a "contractor onboarding kit" repo (Notion or git) that ships intact to every new contractor — versioned, reviewed quarterly.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/onboarding-doc.md" purpose="Contractor onboarding document: business context, role, tools, working norms, quality standards"/>
      <template path="templates/weekly-checkin.md" purpose="Weekly check-in: completed, in-progress, blockers, next-week focus, hours logged"/>
      <template path="templates/evaluation.md" purpose="Contractor review: 5-area rubric (quality, communication, reliability, speed, proactiveness) + decision"/>
      <template path="templates/slack-digest.py" purpose="Pull contractor Slack thread history for weekly status digests"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.ccl.org/articles/leading-effectively-articles/closing-the-gap-between-intention-and-action-with-sbi/"/>
      <link href="https://www.deel.com/resources/contractor-management"/>
      <link href="https://www.loom.com/blog/async-communication"/>
      <ref slug="ops-contractor-basics"/>
      <ref slug="ops-legal-basics"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
