<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules">
  <rule testable="true">The register tracks at least 6 agency-level risk classes: revenue concentration, key-person, FX/currency, contractor classification, pipeline thinness, regulatory; project-level risks live in a separate register and are not allowed here.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Each row has 8 columns: ID, class, description, likelihood (1-5), impact (1-5), score (L×I), owner (named human), trigger (the observable event that flips it to actioned); rows missing owner or trigger are rejected.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Revenue-concentration row uses the running 90-day rule: any client ≥40% of trailing-90-day revenue is automatically scored ≥15 and added if missing; this row is recomputed every Monday from billing data, not estimated.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Key-person rows must name the bus-factor item (e.g. "only X knows the AWS root creds", "only Y can run the data pipeline") and a remediation owner with a written deadline; "we'll cross-train" without a date is rejected.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Weekly refresh fits in 30 minutes: 5 min to update scores from the dashboard, 15 min to walk the top-5 by score, 10 min to write the action note; if the meeting runs over twice in a row, the register is too big — split it.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Any risk scoring ≥15 (high likelihood × high impact) must have either a mitigation action active this week OR a written decision to accept the risk signed by the founder; silent high-score rows are forbidden.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Archive resolved risks to a "closed" tab with the date and a one-line lesson; do not delete — closed-risk history is the agency's institutional memory and feeds annual planning.</rule>
  <example>Monday 9:00, 6-person agency: PM opens the register. Revenue concentration shows Client A at 47% (auto-bumped to 5×4=20). Key-person row: "Anna sole admin of client portal infra" — owner = founder, trigger = Anna takes >5 working days off without backup. FX row: 60% revenue in USD, EUR costs, score 4×3=12, action = quarterly hedge review. Contractor row: two devs in PL not classified, owner = ops, deadline = end of month. Meeting closes at 9:28 with three actions logged.</example>

  <section title="Self-routing anchors">
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If all Applies-If preconditions hold and no Skip-If disqualifier is present, execute the full procedure from `04-procedure.xml` and commit the artefact described in `02-output-contract.xml`.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's affirmative leaf; pairs the preconditions with the methodology's commit path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Skip-If condition is present (one-shot, &lt;3 instances/year, regulator override, missing owner), do NOT apply this methodology. Route to the sibling/upstream methodology named in `AGENTS.md` Related section.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's skip leaf; prevents over-application of a heavyweight artefact when the loop conditions do not hold.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
