<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="distribution-channel-research">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>market-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Identifies pathways customers use to discover and adopt a product: traffic-source mix across incumbents, partner/reseller/marketplace landscape, and benchmark channel economics with confidence bands.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>distribution-channels</tag>
      <tag>channel-economics</tag>
      <tag>partner-landscape</tag>
      <tag>gtm-research</tag>
      <tag>cac-benchmarks</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Distribution Channel Research</title>
    <summary>Distribution channel research identifies and evaluates the pathways through which customers discover and adopt a product at the market level: traffic-source mix across incumbents, partner/reseller/marketplace landscape, and benchmark channel economics (CPC/CPM/CAC ranges with confidence bands). It answers "how do people in this market actually find and buy products like this?" before committing GTM spend.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>"If you build it, they will come" fails because founders pick channels based on preference rather than where the buyer segment actually lives. Market-level channel-share data (not guesswork) reveals which channels move volume, what the margin stack-up looks like through each path, and which partner types control access to the buyer — information that prevents wasted spend on wrong channels.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Market entry: need to know which channels actually move volume in a target market before committing GTM budget.</item>
        <item>Investor/strategy decks requiring sourced channel-economics slide with market-level CPC/CAC ranges.</item>
        <item>Channel-share studies: quantifying what % of category revenue flows through SEO vs paid vs partner vs direct.</item>
        <item>Partner-landscape mapping for B2B: identifying distributors, resellers, MSPs, and integration partners.</item>
        <item>Refreshing channel benchmarks when numbers in the deck are older than 12 months.</item>
        <item>Pricing/business-model research that depends on channel margin stack-ups.</item>
        <item>Market entry analysis: a client/founder needs to know which channels actually move volume in a target market before committing GTM spend (e.g. "is dental SaaS sold via direct, marketplace, or channel partners in DACH?").</item>
        <item>Investor / strategy decks where the channel-economics slide must show market-level CPC/CAC ranges and partner take-rates with sourced citations, not back-of-envelope guesses.</item>
        <item>Channel-share studies: quantifying what % of category revenue flows through SEO vs paid vs partner vs direct sales across the top 10 incumbents.</item>
        <item>Partner-landscape mapping for B2B: identifying every distributor, reseller, MSP, marketplace, and integration partner that touches the buyer journey, with reach/exclusivity/take-rate per partner.</item>
        <item>Pricing &amp; business-model research that depends on channel margin stack-ups (e.g. SaaS direct 70% gross margin vs. AWS Marketplace listing −3% take vs. reseller −20%).</item>
        <item>Refreshing channel benchmarks when incumbent CPC/CPM/CAC numbers in the deck are &gt;12 months old.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Founder needs creative/copy/test-design help — route to growth-marketer.</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF single-product validation where the question is "does anyone want this" — premature optimization.</item>
        <item>Pure brand campaigns with no recurring channel decision.</item>
        <item>Markets where channel data is structurally unavailable (private niches, NDAs, regulated verticals) — output will be conjecture; stop and flag.</item>
        <item>When the requester has not specified a market boundary (geo + segment + buyer) — denominator is undefined.</item>
        <item>Founder needs creative/copy/test-design help — that is a growth-marketing job, not market research; route to pro/marketing/growth-marketer or the researcher-variant of this methodology.</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF single-product validation where the question is "does anyone want this" — channel research at that stage is premature optimization.</item>
        <item>Pure brand campaigns or one-off launches with no recurring channel decision.</item>
        <item>Markets where channel data is structurally unavailable (private niches, enterprise with NDAs, regulated verticals with no ad libraries) — output will be conjecture; flag and stop.</item>
        <item>When the requester has not specified a market boundary (geo + segment + buyer); without a boundary the channel-share denominator is undefined.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="channel-categories">
      <rule>
        <statement>Always research all four channel categories before selecting a primary: organic (SEO, content, social, community, WOM, PLG), paid (search ads, social ads, display, influencer, affiliate, sponsorships), sales-led (outbound, partnerships, conferences, webinars), and viral/network (referral, integrations, embeds, UGC).</statement>
        <rationale>Founders pick channels based on preference, not fit. A channel chosen without reviewing the full taxonomy misses the category where buyers actually concentrate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Organic: 6-12 months to results, low cost, sustainable growth, lower CAC over time</item>
        <item>Paid: immediate results, scalable when proven, high cost, best for fast testing</item>
        <item>Sales-led: high value B2B and complex products, 1-6 months to results, high cost</item>
        <item>Viral/network: best for products with network effects, 1-4 months, low-variable cost</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="channel-evaluation-matrix">
      <rule>
        <statement>Score each candidate channel on six weighted factors: audience presence (25%), competitors using (15%), cost to test (20%), time to results (15%), scalability (15%), team capability (10%). Prioritize highest-scoring channels for initial investment.</statement>
        <rationale>Weighting audience presence highest prevents the common failure of investing in channels where the target buyer does not exist, regardless of team familiarity.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>A channel is viable only when LTV:CAC exceeds 3:1. Model channel economics (CPM → CTR → CPC → conversion rate → CAC) before scaling any channel beyond micro-test budget.</statement>
        <rationale>Channels that feel productive but have LTV:CAC under 3:1 are capital destroyers — they feel like growth while compounding a structural margin problem.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="channel-testing-sequence">
      <rule>
        <statement>Follow the five-step testing sequence: micro-test ($100-500, 1-2 weeks) → validate signal → scale test ($1-5K, 1 month) → optimize conversion → scale budget. Never jump from micro-test to full scale.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping the scale-test stage bets the marketing budget on a statistically insignificant micro-test; the validate step decides whether to proceed.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Portfolio approach by stage: at 0-$10K MRR master 1 channel; at $10-50K MRR add 2-3 channels; at $50K+ MRR diversify. Maintain 80% effort on 1-2 proven channels, 20% on experiments.</statement>
        <rationale>Trying all channels simultaneously dilutes effort below the minimum needed to get accurate signal from any one channel.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>B2B SaaS tool: interviews show 60% discover via Google search, 25% via peer recommendations, 15% via LinkedIn. Strategy: SEO primary (content for "how to [problem]" keywords), LinkedIn secondary (thought leadership + ads), referral tertiary (in-product program). SEO CAC after 6 months: $20; LinkedIn CAC: $150; referral CAC: $30.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Consumer mobile app: 45% from App Store search, 30% from friend recommendation, 25% from Instagram/TikTok. Strategy: ASO primary (free organic installs), viral loops secondary (shareable content), TikTok organic tertiary. Avoids paid channels until virality loop is proven.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="four-stage-pipeline">
      <rule>
        <statement>Always run the boundary agent first and refuse to proceed until geo + segment + buyer + product category are locked. An unbounded market produces meaningless channel-share denominators.</statement>
        <rationale>Channel-share is a fraction — without a denominator (market boundary) it is undefined. Agents that skip this gate produce plausible-sounding numbers with no anchor.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Stage 1 (Boundary agent): lock geo + segment + buyer + category → market-definition spec</item>
        <item>Stage 2 (Channel-share agent): quantify traffic/revenue mix across top 10 incumbents using SimilarWeb + Ahrefs + ad libraries → market-level channel-share table with confidence bands</item>
        <item>Stage 3 (Partner-landscape agent): map every distributor/reseller/marketplace/integration partner with reach, exclusivity, take-rate → partner-landscape table</item>
        <item>Stage 4 (Economics agent): layer benchmark CPC/PMC/CAC on channel-share table, run LTV sensitivity (low/mid/high) → LTV:CAC ranges per channel</item>
      </list>
      <note>Drive market-level channel research with a 4-stage chain. (1) Boundary agent locks geo + segment + buyer + product category and produces a market-definition spec — refuse to proceed without it. (2) Channel-share agent quantifies traffic/revenue mix across the top 10 incumbents using SimilarWeb + Ahrefs + ad libraries, emits a market-level channel-share table with confidence bands. (3) Partner-landscape agent maps every distributor / reseller / marketplace / integration partner, with reach, exclusivity, and known/inferred take-rate. (4) Economics agent layers benchmark CPC/CPM/CAC on the channel-share table and runs LTV sensitivity (low/mid/high) to produce LTV:CAC ranges per channel.</note>
    </section>

    <section name="confidence-band-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Report channel-share as a range with confidence band tied to N of competitors with available data: HIGH if ≥7 incumbents agree, MED if 4-6, LOW if ≤3. Never output a single percentage without the band.</statement>
        <rationale>SimilarWeb traffic mix is a proxy for channel-share, not a measurement of revenue-share — a single number projects false precision onto an inherently noisy estimate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use revenue- or traffic-weighted aggregation when computing market-level channel-share — never equal-weight across competitors. Weight by SimilarWeb monthly visits as proxy.</statement>
        <rationale>Equal-weight averaging gives micro-competitors the same influence as category leaders, skewing the picture toward the long tail.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Report partner take-rates as facts when from public marketplace docs (AWS 3%, Shopify 0-20%, App Store 15-30%) and as [INFERRED] with inference path when from job posts or partner-portal scrapes.</statement>
        <rationale>Private reseller margins (15-40%) are negotiated and only leak via indirect signals; treating inferred rates as facts leads to materially wrong economics models.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="citation-requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every number must carry source + URL + capture-date triple. Economic numbers older than 12 months must be marked [UNVERIFIED] rather than cited as current.</statement>
        <rationale>Ad library data and traffic estimates rot in weeks; stale benchmarks in investor decks create credibility risk when scrutinized.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run LTV sensitivity at low/mid/high LTV and output ranges, not point estimates. Reject any single LTV:CAC ratio output as incomplete.</statement>
        <rationale>LTV uncertainty kills market-level LTV:CAC modeling — the right output is a range with sensitivity bands so investors and operators can see the cliff.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include regional splits for multi-geo markets. Never blend global averages — CPC variance across regions can be 3-5x, destroying the strategic recommendation.</statement>
        <rationale>US-centric benchmarks systematically misrepresent APAC and EU markets where CPCs, partner ecosystems, and channel maturity differ fundamentally.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Trying all channels simultaneously at launch.</description>
        <reason>Dilutes effort below the minimum needed to get accurate signal from any single channel. Focus on 1-2 initially.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Copying competitor channels without validating fit for the specific product.</description>
        <reason>Channel fit depends on audience presence, cost structure, and team capability — not on what the market leader does.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ignoring channel economics before scaling — no CAC calculation before increasing budget.</description>
        <reason>Channels that feel productive but have LTV:CAC under 3:1 destroy capital; economics must be modeled before scaling.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Giving up on a channel after fewer than 4-6 weeks with no optimization.</description>
        <reason>Organic channels take 3-12 months to mature; premature abandonment produces false negatives that leave viable channels unexplored.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No attribution tracking set up before running channel tests.</description>
        <reason>Without attribution, test results cannot be attributed to any channel; the data is useless for decision-making.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="market-researcher-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Channel granularity collapse: "paid social" lumped together as one channel in the market-share table.</description>
        <reason>"Paid social" is not one channel — Meta Reels, Meta Feed, IG Stories, LinkedIn Sponsored, TikTok In-Feed behave differently. Force per-platform breakdown or the analysis is meaningless for channel selection.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Survivorship in published case studies: "we got to $10M via SEO" stories overweight organic and underweight paid.</description>
        <reason>Published stories are 1-of-100 — channel-share inference from public stories must be cross-checked with SimilarWeb traffic mix data from the silent majority.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Producing a 7-tier portfolio recommendation ("Phase 1 SEO, Phase 2 paid") in market-research output.</description>
        <reason>GTM sequencing is GTM-strategist work, not market research. Stop at channel-share + partner-landscape + economics tables; let the strategist interpret them.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents skipping the boundary gate and producing "channel mix for SaaS" without geo or segment.</description>
        <reason>Without a market boundary the channel-share denominator is undefined and all output is conjecture. Enforce a stop-and-ask gate before any data work.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents fabricating CPC, CPM, take-rate, and traffic-share values without sourced citations.</description>
        <reason>Number hallucination in channel benchmarks produces investment decisions grounded in fiction. Require source + URL + capture-date for every number and reject answers failing the citation check.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Boundary skipping: agents will happily produce "channel mix for SaaS" without a geo or segment.</description>
        <reason>Enforce a stop-and-ask gate before any data work; without a market boundary the channel-share denominator is undefined and all output is conjecture.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Number hallucination: agents fabricate plausible CPC, CPM, take-rate, and traffic-share values.</description>
        <reason>Require source + URL + capture-date for every number, and reject answers that fail the citation check.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>US-bias: training data overweights US benchmarks; for non-US markets force the agent to source regional data.</description>
        <reason>For non-US markets force the agent to source regional data (Statista, eMarketer regional, local Ad libraries) rather than defaulting to US benchmarks.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Confidence-band omission: agents collapse channel-share into single percentages.</description>
        <reason>Explicitly require N + confidence band per row; a single percentage projects false precision onto an inherently noisy estimate.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Survivorship lean: agents will overweight famous "we won via SEO" stories.</description>
        <reason>Prompt for the silent majority (incumbents that never wrote a Medium post) by sampling top-10 by traffic, not top-10 by content output.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Partner-landscape under-reporting: agents miss MSPs, VARs, and SI partners because those rarely have web presence.</description>
        <reason>Require the agent to scrape "Partners / Resellers / Find a partner" pages of each incumbent and capture every named entity.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Equal-weight aggregation bug: agents default to averaging across competitors equally.</description>
        <reason>Explicitly demand traffic- or revenue-weighted aggregation; equal weights give micro-competitors the same influence as category leaders.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LTV point-estimate bug: agents output a single LTV:CAC ratio.</description>
        <reason>Require low/mid/high sensitivity or reject the answer; point estimates hide the cliff where unit economics invert.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Stale benchmarks: agents quote 2022 CPCs.</description>
        <reason>Require capture-date &gt;= last 12 months for any economic number, else mark [UNVERIFIED].</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <list>
        <item>Channel-share denominators are noisy: SimilarWeb traffic mix is a proxy for channel-share, not a measurement of revenue-share; for B2B with 6-month sales cycles the gap is enormous.</item>
        <item>Partner take-rates are rarely public — public marketplace fees (AWS 3%, Shopify 0–20%, App Store 15–30%) are anchors, but private reseller margins (15–40%) are negotiated and leak only via job posts, RFPs, and partner-portal scrapes.</item>
        <item>Ad-library coverage is uneven: Meta + Google have full transparency in EU/Brazil, partial in US; LinkedIn + TikTok ad libraries are shallow; B2B podcast and newsletter sponsorship has no library at all.</item>
        <item>Survivorship in case studies: published "we got to $10M via SEO" stories are 1-of-100 — channel-share inference from public stories overweights organic and underweights paid.</item>
        <item>LTV uncertainty kills market-level LTV:CAC modeling — the right output is a range with sensitivity bands, not a point estimate, and agents that produce point estimates are silently wrong.</item>
        <item>Geographic averaging: blending US + EU + APAC CPC into one number masks 5x regional variance that destroys the strategic recommendation.</item>
        <item>"Channel" is fractal: "paid social" is not one channel — Meta Reels, Meta Feed, IG Stories, LinkedIn Sponsored, LinkedIn InMail behave differently. Pick the right granularity for the market question or the analysis is meaningless.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Lock the market boundary (geo + segment + buyer + category) before any channel work; an unbounded market produces meaningless channel-share.</item>
        <item>Use weighted aggregation when computing market-level channel-share: weight each competitor by revenue or traffic (proxy: SimilarWeb monthly visits) — not equal weights — so micro-competitors do not skew the picture.</item>
        <item>Capture every public channel datapoint with source + URL + capture-date triple; ad libraries and traffic estimates rot in weeks.</item>
        <item>Report channel-share as a range with confidence band (HIGH/MED/LOW) tied to N of competitors with available data, not a single number.</item>
        <item>Always include regional splits for multi-geo markets — global averages hide 3–5x CPC variance that breaks the strategic recommendation.</item>
        <item>For partner take-rates: report public marketplace fees as facts; report reseller / channel-partner margins as [INFERRED] with the inference path (job post wording, RFP leak, partner-portal screenshot).</item>
        <item>Treat channel-share + partner-landscape outputs as dated snapshots, not standing truth — refresh quarterly for active markets, semi-annually for slow markets.</item>
        <item>Use LTV sensitivity (low/mid/high) bands not point estimates — investors and operators need to see the cliff.</item>
        <item>Cross-check ad-library evidence with traffic mix: a competitor with 0% paid in SimilarWeb but 200 active Meta ads is a measurement artifact, not a contradiction — flag it.</item>
        <item>Separate buy-side channels (where the buyer searches) from fulfillment channels (how the product is delivered) — for B2B SaaS sold via AWS Marketplace, the channel-share table needs both rows.</item>
        <item>Avoid the 7-tier portfolio recommendation cliché ("Phase 1 SEO, Phase 2 paid…") in market-research output — that is GTM-strategist work, not market research; stop at the channel-share + partner-landscape + economics tables.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>faion-research-agent (mode competitors) — pulls per-competitor traffic mix, ad creatives, partner mentions, marketplace listings.</item>
        <item>faion-research-agent (mode niche) — produces market boundary + buyer-journey scaffold for stage 1.</item>
        <item>faion-research-agent (mode pricing) — feeds margin / take-rate context for partner-economics math.</item>
        <item>faion-domain-checker-agent — cheap pre-flight when partner / marketplace listings imply microsite domains for verification.</item>
        <item>pro/research/market-researcher/competitor-analysis knowledge — per-competitor channel inference.</item>
        <item>pro/research/market-researcher/market-research-tam-sam-som knowledge — sets the revenue denominator that channel-share is computed against.</item>
        <item>pro/marketing/ppc-manager knowledge — current paid-channel CPC/CPM/CAC benchmarks with regional splits.</item>
        <item>pro/marketing/growth-marketer knowledge — LTV modeling and sensitivity bands.</item>
        <item>pro/marketing/gtm-strategist knowledge — interprets channel-share output for portfolio recommendations.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-pattern">
      <prompt purpose="market-level-channel-research">
        <![CDATA[Role: market-level distribution-channel research subagent (market-researcher).
Inputs: market_boundary={geo, segment, buyer, category},
        incumbents=[top10_domains], LTV_low/mid/high=[$X,$Y,$Z],
        analysis_depth={share|partners|economics|all}.
Tasks:
 1. Verify market boundary is well-defined; if any field is missing, STOP and request it.
 2. For each incumbent: extract traffic-source mix (cite SimilarWeb date),
    paid-ad presence (cite ad-library date), partner/marketplace listings.
 3. Aggregate to market-level channel-share table with confidence bands
    (HIGH if >=7 incumbents agree, MED if 4-6, LOW if <=3).
 4. Map partner landscape: distributors, resellers, marketplaces, integrations.
    For each: reach (S/M/L), exclusivity (Y/N), take-rate (cite or [INFERRED]).
 5. Layer benchmark CPC/CPM/CAC ranges per channel (cite source + date,
    regional split if multi-geo).
 6. Run LTV:CAC at low/mid/high LTV, output ranges not points.
Constraints:
 - Every number cites source + capture date or is flagged [UNVERIFIED].
 - No time estimates; complexity tags only (low/med/high).
 - If <3 incumbents have data, return LOW-confidence and recommend primary research.
Return: markdown matching templates.md sections 1-5.]]>
      </prompt>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/channel-research-report.md" purpose="Channel research report skeleton: discovery, evaluation, economics, competitor channels, testing plan"/>
      <template path="templates/channel-test-report.md" purpose="Per-channel test report: parameters, metrics table, analysis, recommendation"/>
      <template path="templates/market-channel-share.py" purpose="Aggregate per-competitor traffic mixes into market-level share table with confidence bands"/>
      <template path="templates/partner-landscape.md" purpose="Partner-landscape table skeleton with reach, exclusivity, take-rate, source, capture-date columns"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="competitor-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="market-research-tam-sam-som"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
