<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Tax Basics — Framework and Structure">
  <summary>US solopreneur tax framework: tax types, entity selection for SE tax savings, deduction categories, and retirement accounts.</summary>

  <section title="Tax types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set aside approximately 30% of net monthly profit to a dedicated tax-savings account and never spend it on business operations.</statement>
      <rationale>Effective solopreneur tax rates (federal income + self-employment + state) typically reach 30–40% of net profit. Founders who do not separate reserves scramble at quarterly estimate deadlines and face underpayment penalties.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Self-employment tax is 15.3% on 92.35% of net profit (12.4% Social Security on first ~$160K, 2.9% Medicare with no cap, 0.9% additional Medicare above $200K). This is on top of federal and state income tax.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Effective tax rate for $100K net profit: SE tax $14,130 + federal income ~$15,000 + state ~$5,000 = ~$34,000 (34%). Reserving $2,833/month covers this.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Entity selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Evaluate S-Corp election when consistent net profit exceeds $80K. Run the math annually mid-year, not at year-end when election filing windows may have passed.</statement>
      <rationale>S-Corp election allows splitting profit into salary (subject to SE tax) and distributions (not subject to SE tax). At $100K profit with $50K reasonable salary, SE tax savings are ~$7,650/year. Below $80K, the added payroll complexity erodes the benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>$100K LLC (default): $15,300 SE tax. $100K with S-Corp, $50K salary: $7,650 SE tax on salary + $0 on distribution. Net savings: ~$7,650/year.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never recommend an S-Corp salary split below 40% of profit without explicitly flagging IRS "reasonable compensation" risk.</statement>
      <rationale>The IRS can reclassify distributions as salary and assess back SE tax plus penalties if salary is unreasonably low relative to the work performed.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Deductions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use actual-method home office deduction (square footage ratio applied to rent, utilities, internet) only when the space is used exclusively and regularly for business; flag that this method creates depreciation recapture on home sale.</statement>
      <rationale>The simplified method ($5/sq ft, max $1,500) is audit-safer and avoids recapture. Actual method is better only for high-rent situations with large dedicated office space.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Home office: dedicated space required; simplified ($5/sqft, max 300 sqft, max $1,500) or actual (% of home costs)</item>
      <item>Equipment: computer, monitors, phone — deduct via Section 179 in year of purchase or depreciate</item>
      <item>Software: all business-use subscriptions and tools</item>
      <item>Marketing: ads, content creation, design — keep receipts</item>
      <item>Professional services: legal, accounting, consulting — business-related only</item>
      <item>Education: courses, books directly related to the business</item>
      <item>Travel: must have documented business purpose</item>
      <item>Health insurance premiums: self-employed deduction (check spouse employer-plan interaction)</item>
      <item>Retirement contributions: SEP-IRA, Solo 401k — reduce taxable income dollar-for-dollar</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Retirement accounts">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize retirement contributions as a tax planning tool, not just savings: SEP-IRA allows up to ~25% of net SE income (max ~$66K); Solo 401k allows $22.5K employee deferral plus 25% employer contribution.</statement>
      <rationale>At a 24% marginal bracket, a $10K SEP-IRA contribution produces $2,400 in immediate federal tax savings. This is risk-free return that cannot be achieved elsewhere.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>$100K net profit. SEP-IRA contribution ~$18,500. Tax savings at 24%: $4,440. Plus SE tax deduction on half of SE tax adds ~$2,000 more in federal savings.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>HSA (Health Savings Account) requires a high-deductible health plan but provides a triple tax benefit: deduction + tax-free growth + tax-free withdrawal for medical expenses. Use it when eligible.</statement>
      <rationale>2024 limits: $4,150 (individual), $8,300 (family). No other account type has the triple tax benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/tax-reserve-calc.py"/>
    <link path="templates/tax-planning-checklist.md"/>
    <link path="templates/annual-tax-summary.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
