<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Tax Basics — Worked Examples">
  <summary>Two concrete tax-strategy examples: first-year solopreneur with W-2 income and full-time solopreneur at $150K profit.</summary>

  <section title="First-year solopreneur">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Situation: side business, $30K profit, still employed (W-2 income). Strategy: keep sole prop (simple), claim home office at $1,500 simplified, track all expenses, set aside 25% of profit for taxes, no quarterly estimates needed because W-2 withholding covers safe-harbor. Result: taxable SE income ~$28,500, SE tax ~$4,350, income tax at marginal W-2 rate, deductions offset some income.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>When a founder has both W-2 and self-employment income, check whether W-2 withholding satisfies safe-harbor before setting up quarterly estimates.</statement>
      <rationale>Quarterly estimates are only required when expected tax liability exceeds $1,000 after withholding. Over-estimating complexity adds administrative burden without reducing liability.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Full-time solopreneur at scale">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Situation: $150K LLC profit, considering S-Corp. Strategy: elect S-Corp, pay $75K reasonable salary, distribute $75K, max SEP-IRA (~$14K on salary portion), use home-office actual method. Result: SE tax savings ~$7,600, retirement contribution $14K, tax savings from retirement ~$3,360, total optimization ~$11K vs default LLC treatment.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>For S-Corp with SEP-IRA, contribution limit is based on W-2 salary, not total profit. At $75K salary, max SEP-IRA is ~$14K (not the ~$28K that would apply to $150K profit on a sole prop). Verify before projecting retirement savings.</statement>
      <rationale>Many founders over-estimate S-Corp retirement benefits because the base for SEP-IRA switches from net SE income to W-2 wages. This is a common miscalculation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Founder assumes the simplified home-office deduction method and the actual method can both be applied in the same year.</description>
    <reason>Only one method can be used per year. Switching methods annually is allowed but requires full recalculation. Applying both double-deducts.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Agent hardcodes 2024 contribution limits (Solo 401k $22.5K, SEP-IRA $66K, HSA $4,150/$8,300) without flagging the year.</description>
    <reason>Contribution limits are indexed to inflation and change annually. Hardcoded limits produce wrong advice after the tax year changes.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
