<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-overview" title="Overview and core principle">
  <summary>The orchestrator builds a complete AI media publishing pipeline from scratch (Telegram channel + static site + automation) by walking the operator through a structured discovery interview, then scaffolding a project that mirrors the centralized pattern proven across four production outlets: neromedia, pashtelka, longlife, ender.</summary>

  <section title="Core principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every new media outlet MUST conform to the centralized pattern: pipeline code in the outlet repo, scheduling and monitoring delegated to the central media-manager service. The orchestrator never adds cron entries directly to the host machine.</statement>
      <rationale>Outlets drift when each one owns its own scheduler. A central control plane (media-manager) gives a single place to start, stop, monitor, and command outlets through a single Telegram bot. Per-outlet cron leads to silent failures, divergent timing, and double-publish bugs.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>The orchestrator MUST collect ALL discovery interview answers before proposing a format or scaffolding any code.</statement>
      <rationale>Decisions like single-language vs multi-language, automation level, and source mix change the pipeline complexity by an order of magnitude. Proposing early forces re-work; gathering all answers first makes the proposal a one-shot.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Role split">
    <p>Three actors share the work. The orchestrator runs the interview, proposes the plan, and scaffolds the project. The user picks identity, voice, sources, and automation level. The central media-manager owns scheduling (cron), monitoring, and operator commands once the outlet is registered.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Orchestrator: discovery interview, format proposal, project scaffolding, infrastructure setup, registration in media-manager.</item>
      <item>User: media identity, topics, audience, brand voice, source preferences, automation level, technical constraints (domain, hosting, budget).</item>
      <item>Media-manager: cron schedules per outlet, health monitoring, morning briefing, agent commands (/status, /logs, /generate).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Reference outlets">
    <p>Four production implementations the new outlet should mirror:</p>
    <list>
      <item>neromedia-faion-net — AI/tech news, 8 languages, 8 Telegram channels.</item>
      <item>pashtelka-faion-net — Ukrainian diaspora in Portugal, single channel.</item>
      <item>longlife-faion-net — health and longevity, Ukrainian, comic mascot Vita.</item>
      <item>ender-faion-net — Roblox media for kids, Ukrainian plus English, characters EnderFaion and FaionEnder.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Central control plane lives at the media-manager-faion-net project. Templates used by this workflow live in the sibling templates/ folder (relative to this content directory).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Language convention">
    <rule>
      <statement>User-facing strings during the interview and any operator chat live in Ukrainian. Code, prompt files, schemas, commit messages, and CHANGELOG entries live in English.</statement>
      <rationale>Ukrainian for the human keeps the interview natural; English for everything machine-touchable saves roughly 30% of tokens and keeps grep mechanical.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="../templates/">Pipeline, prompt, schema, gatsby, admin, and script templates rendered during scaffolding.</reference>
</text>
