<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-phases" title="The seven phases">
  <summary>The orchestrator runs a fixed seven-phase sequence from intake to a registered, monitored outlet. Phases are invariant; complexity inside each phase is set by the answers collected in phase 1.</summary>

  <section title="Phase 1: Discovery interview">
    <p>Trigger: user asks for a new media outlet, blog, news bot, or content pipeline.</p>
    <p>What it does: walks eight question groups (identity, topic and audience, content strategy, channels, brand voice, sources, automation level, technical constraints) and stores all answers before any proposal.</p>
    <p>Output: a complete answer map covering identity, voice, sources, channels, automation level, technical constraints.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Constraint: ALL eight question groups MUST be asked before proposing format. Partial interviews lead to partial scaffolds.</item>
      <item>Constraint: questions with discrete options use AskUserQuestion; free-text questions are asked plainly.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="03-discovery-interview.xml">Full interview question set.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 2: Propose format">
    <p>Trigger: phase 1 answers complete.</p>
    <p>What it does: maps interview answers to a concrete plan — domain, Telegram channel, language list, daily article counts, complexity level, content type table — and asks the user to confirm before scaffolding.</p>
    <p>Output: an approved proposal block with architecture, content plan, complexity level, and seed scope.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Constraint: proposal MUST name a complexity level (Minimal, Standard, or Full) drawn from content/04-pipeline-complexity.xml.</item>
      <item>Constraint: no scaffolding starts before the user types approval.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 3: Scaffold project">
    <p>Trigger: user approves the proposed format.</p>
    <p>What it does: creates the project folder under workspace/projects/, lays out the canonical directory tree (pipeline/, gatsby/, admin/, scripts/, content/, state/, tests/), renders templates with project-specific values from the interview.</p>
    <p>Output: a project tree with all required files in place, no code yet executed.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Constraint: directory tree MUST match the canonical scaffold (see content/05-scaffold-structure.xml).</item>
      <item>Constraint: prompt templates MUST follow the system / ===SPLIT=== / task convention.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="05-scaffold-structure.xml">Canonical project tree and key patterns.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 4: Setup infrastructure">
    <p>Trigger: scaffold complete.</p>
    <p>What it does: creates the Telegram channel and adds the bot as admin, points DNS via Cloudflare, configures nginx on the host server, builds the Gatsby site, optionally runs the Flask admin panel for review-mode pipelines.</p>
    <p>Output: a publicly reachable site origin, a Telegram channel ready to receive posts, environment variables stored in workspace/.env.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Constraint: Telegram bot tokens and channel IDs MUST live in env vars; never hardcoded in code.</item>
      <item>Constraint: SSL via Cloudflare proxy or Let's Encrypt; never serve plaintext.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 5: Create content">
    <p>Trigger: infrastructure live.</p>
    <p>What it does: runs the pipeline in dry-run to generate ten to twenty seed articles, then a full run to deploy site and publish first posts. Operator inspects site previews, Telegram OG previews, and review-loop output quality.</p>
    <p>Output: seed articles on the site, first Telegram posts with images and captions, a baseline of editorial-plan diversity to tune from.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Constraint: every Telegram post MUST carry an image (no-publish-without-image rule).</item>
      <item>Constraint: review loop MUST run at least one revision cycle on Standard and Full complexity levels.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 6: Register in media-manager">
    <p>Trigger: seed content published successfully.</p>
    <p>What it does: adds an entry to media-manager-faion-net/config/settings.py with cron times and Telegram credentials, updates the landing page metadata, updates media-manager AGENTS.md, updates projects/AGENTS.md.</p>
    <p>Output: the outlet appears in /status output, the morning briefing, and is steerable through @nero_media_manager_bot.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Constraint: cron entries are added ONLY in media-manager settings, never in host crontab.</item>
      <item>Constraint: outlet MUST be reachable through media-manager bot commands before the workflow ends.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 7: Iterate">
    <p>Trigger: outlet registered and running for at least one day.</p>
    <p>What it does: weekly content review, voice-guide tuning, RSS source adjustment, editorial balance tweaks, addition of new content types or languages.</p>
    <p>Output: continuous quality improvements committed back to the outlet repo.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Constraint: changes to voice or sources MUST land as commits, not as ad-hoc shell edits.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
