<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-discovery-interview" title="Discovery interview question set">
  <summary>Eight grouped questions the orchestrator MUST ask before proposing a format. Discrete-option groups use AskUserQuestion; free-text groups are asked plainly. All answers are gathered before any output.</summary>

  <section title="Interview rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>The orchestrator MUST gather answers to ALL eight question groups before proposing any format, scaffold, or architecture.</statement>
      <rationale>Identity, language scope, automation level, and source mix interact non-linearly. Proposing after the third answer locks in a complexity level that will not match later answers, forcing rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Q1: Media identity">
    <p>Single-select. Header: "Media Identity". Question: "What media are you creating?"</p>
    <list>
      <item>News outlet — breaking news, reports, analysis on a topic or region.</item>
      <item>Expert blog — one voice, deep expertise in a niche.</item>
      <item>Community media — for a specific community (diaspora, profession, hobby).</item>
      <item>Brand media — company blog, thought leadership, product updates.</item>
      <item>Digest or curation — curate and summarize from other sources.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Q2: Topic and audience">
    <p>Free text. Ask all four sub-questions in one turn.</p>
    <list>
      <item>What topics do you cover? List three to ten.</item>
      <item>Who is your reader? Age, profession, interests, pain points.</item>
      <item>What languages? Which is primary?</item>
      <item>What region or city if location-specific?</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Q3: Content strategy">
    <p>Multi-select. Header: "Content Types". Question: "What content types do you need?"</p>
    <list>
      <item>Breaking news (300-600 words).</item>
      <item>In-depth materials (600-1500 words).</item>
      <item>Practical guides (800-2000 words).</item>
      <item>Opinion or analysis (600-1200 words).</item>
      <item>Daily digest (compilation).</item>
      <item>Utility alerts (weather, transport, etc.).</item>
    </list>
    <p>Follow-up free-text: how many articles per day, what publishing schedule.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Q4: Channels and platform">
    <p>Multi-select. Header: "Channels". Question: "Where do you publish?"</p>
    <list>
      <item>Telegram channel.</item>
      <item>Website (static site).</item>
      <item>Both Telegram plus website.</item>
      <item>Newsletter (email).</item>
      <item>Social media (Twitter/X, Instagram).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Q5: Brand voice">
    <p>Free text. Ask as one block.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Author name or pseudonym (real-sounding or character).</item>
      <item>Tone: formal, warm, ironic, academic, casual.</item>
      <item>Specific voice rules (for example, explain terms for immigrants).</item>
      <item>Visual style for images: photo, illustration, comic, minimalist.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Q6: Content sources">
    <p>Multi-select. Header: "Sources". Question: "Where does content come from?"</p>
    <list>
      <item>RSS feeds (news sites).</item>
      <item>Web search (Google, SearXNG).</item>
      <item>APIs (weather, transport, government).</item>
      <item>Manual input (editor notes).</item>
      <item>Social media monitoring.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Q7: Automation level">
    <p>Single-select. Header: "Automation". Question: "How automated should it be?"</p>
    <list>
      <item>Full auto-pilot — generate and publish without human review.</item>
      <item>Generate plus review before publish — human approves through admin panel.</item>
      <item>Semi-auto — human writes, AI assists with research and editing.</item>
      <item>Manual with AI tools — human drives, AI helps on demand.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Q8: Technical">
    <p>Free text. Ask as one block.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Domain name (existing or new).</item>
      <item>Hosting server available (faion-net, own server, or need a new one).</item>
      <item>Telegram bot (existing shared bot or create new through @BotFather).</item>
      <item>Budget for APIs (Claude, OpenAI image generation).</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
