<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-pipeline-complexity" title="Pipeline complexity levels">
  <summary>Three discrete complexity levels the proposal phase MUST pick from. The level sets stage count, line-of-code budget, and which features are present (review loops, image generation, multi-language).</summary>

  <section title="Level 1: MINIMAL">
    <p>Five stages, roughly 500 lines of code. Stages: collect, generate, save, deploy, publish_tg.</p>
    <p>When to choose: simple blog, single topic, low volume, single language, no editorial-plan need, no review loop needed.</p>
    <list>
      <item>No editorial plan — topics are picked ad hoc.</item>
      <item>No research agent — generation reads source material directly.</item>
      <item>No review loop — first generation is published.</item>
      <item>Single language only.</item>
      <item>Line budget: about 500 LOC.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Level 2: STANDARD">
    <p>Eight stages, roughly 1200 lines of code. Stages: editorial_plan, collect, research, generate, review_loop, save, deploy, publish_tg.</p>
    <p>When to choose: news outlet, moderate volume, quality matters, single or two languages.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Editorial plan with daily topics.</item>
      <item>Research agent with web search and RSS.</item>
      <item>One to two review cycles before publish.</item>
      <item>Optional image generation per article.</item>
      <item>Line budget: about 1200 LOC.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Level 3: FULL">
    <p>Twelve or more stages, roughly 2500 lines of code. Stages: editorial_plan, plan_review, collect, research, generate, review_loop (cap 3), tg_caption, tg_review, translate (per language), image_gen, save, deploy, verify, publish_tg, digest.</p>
    <p>When to choose: professional media, multi-language, high volume, brand-critical quality bar.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Plan review before generation begins.</item>
      <item>Hard-capped review loop (three cycles maximum).</item>
      <item>Dedicated Telegram caption optimisation with its own review.</item>
      <item>Translation pass per target language.</item>
      <item>Image generation gated by anti-slop checks.</item>
      <item>Site-verify step after deploy.</item>
      <item>Daily digest compilation at the end of the day.</item>
      <item>Line budget: about 2500 LOC.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
