<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="07-anti-patterns" title="Anti-patterns">
  <summary>Named failure modes the orchestrator MUST avoid when running this workflow. Each rule is rejection-on-sight during code review.</summary>

  <section title="Process anti-patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do NOT propose a format or scaffold any code before completing all eight discovery interview question groups.</statement>
      <rationale>Identity, language scope, automation level, and source mix interact non-linearly. Early proposals lock in a complexity level that does not match later answers, forcing rework or producing a half-fitted scaffold.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Do NOT skip the review loop on Standard or Full complexity outlets.</statement>
      <rationale>The review loop is the only mechanism that catches drift between editorial-plan intent and generated text. On Standard and Full pipelines it is load-bearing for quality. Bypassing it produces low-quality posts that erode brand trust and require manual cleanup.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Operations anti-patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do NOT add cron entries directly to the host crontab. Scheduling lives ONLY in media-manager-faion-net/config/settings.py.</statement>
      <rationale>Per-outlet cron creates silent timing drift, bypasses central monitoring, and breaks the single-pane-of-glass invariant. Media-manager is the only authority for cron scheduling, /status reporting, and operator commands.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Do NOT publish a Telegram post without an image.</statement>
      <rationale>Image-less posts collapse the OG preview area in clients, cut engagement, and violate the no-publish-without-image content rule encoded in NERO memory. Image generation is non-optional for any outlet that publishes to Telegram.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Do NOT hardcode bot tokens, channel IDs, or API keys in source files. All secrets live in workspace/.env (mode 600) and are loaded through env vars.</statement>
      <rationale>Hardcoded credentials leak through git history, screenshots, and copy-pastes into LLM contexts. Env-var loading also lets media-manager swap a shared bot for a per-outlet bot without code changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
