<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="workflows">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>Two core PM pipelines: Project Bootstrap (idea → constitution → TASK_000) and MLP Planning (MVP → Most Lovable Product) enforcing required sequencing and artifacts.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>product-management</tag>
      <tag>project-bootstrap</tag>
      <tag>mlp-planning</tag>
      <tag>roadmap</tag>
      <tag>backlog</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Product Manager Workflows</title>
    <summary>Two core PM pipelines: Project Bootstrap (idea → constitution → TASK_000) and MLP Planning (MVP → Most Lovable Product). Bootstrap is interactive and requires explicit user confirmation at Phase 4; MLP runs five `faion-mlp-agent` modes sequentially. Both pipelines treat `.aidocs/features/` as the planning source of truth and Jira/Linear as the execution mirror — never the reverse.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Without a structured bootstrap pipeline, projects start without a constitution, backlog items lack FR/AC numbering, and RICE scores are never assigned. The MLP transition is where "minimum viable" products become products people love — but only when grounded in real competitor evidence and telemetry, not speculation. These workflows enforce the required sequencing and artifacts.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>New project bootstrap where `.aidocs/` is empty and `constitution.md` + `roadmap.md` need authoring before any code task.</item>
        <item>MVP-to-MLP transition after first usable build ships and produces real telemetry.</item>
        <item>Sprint kickoff and review ceremonies where backlog needs grooming, sizing, and tracker sync.</item>
        <item>Release coordination: changelog generation, release-notes draft, GTM handoff.</item>
        <item>Daily PM ritual: backlog re-prioritization, stakeholder digest, blocker surfacing.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>During SDD task execution itself — code tasks belong to `feature-executor`. PM workflow stops at TASK_000.</item>
        <item>One-off feature requests inside an active sprint — log to backlog via tracker API.</item>
        <item>Spec changes after spec freeze — route through change management.</item>
        <item>Solo Phase 1 before anything to prioritize — use `solo/product/product-planning/mvp-scoping` instead.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="bootstrap-pipeline">
      <p>Seven-phase pipeline from idea to TASK_000, with mandatory Phase 4 user confirmation and the output artifact structure under .aidocs/.</p>
      <p>Phase sequence: 1. Vision Brainstorm (Five Whys to real need) → 2. Tech Stack Selection (frontend, backend, database) → 3. MVP Definition (max 3-5 features, cut 50% nice-to-haves) → 4. User Confirmation (MANDATORY — present summary, get explicit approval) → 5. Backlog Creation (feature specs with FR/AC) → 6. Constitution (write project constitution) → 7. TASK_000 (setup task with project goals).</p>
      <p>Bootstrap produces: .aidocs/constitution.md, .aidocs/roadmap.md, .aidocs/features/backlog/{NN}-{feature}/spec.md (max 5 features), .aidocs/features/00-setup/tasks/todo/TASK_000_project_setup.md.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Phase 4 user confirmation cannot be skipped or simulated — the bootstrap pipeline must hard-fail with NEEDS-HUMAN if no explicit approval token is received.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs eager to complete will simulate user approval; bootstrap must detect non-interactive mode and exit rather than invent answers. An unsigned constitution is not a constitution.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Bootstrap must detect non-interactive mode (cron, CI) and exit with FAIL needs-human; do not invent answers.</statement>
        <rationale>The AskUserQuestion step blocks in non-interactive runs; an agent that invents user approval produces a constitution nobody agreed to, corrupting the entire project record.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every spec must have a RICE row (reach/impact/confidence/effort frontmatter) before leaving backlog; reject specs without RICE at grooming time.</statement>
        <rationale>Unscored backlog items cannot be prioritized; RICE without frontmatter is invisible to the rice-reorder script and the sprint kickoff agent.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Agents must refuse to invent features not present in the idea-validation or competitive-analysis inputs.</statement>
        <rationale>MLP hallucination — inventing WOW features without competitor evidence — is the most common failure mode; the PM's job is to make evidence the precondition, not the review step.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>When two PM agents may run concurrently, take a flock on .aidocs/.numbering.lock before assigning the next feature number or task number.</statement>
        <rationale>Concurrent agents assigning {NN} without a lock create numbering collisions that break spec filenames and all downstream references.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="mlp-planning-workflow">
      <p>Five-mode sequential MLP pipeline that transforms a shipped MVP into a Most Lovable Product, with constraints on WOW feature grounding and a cap of 7 WOW items.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run the five faion-mlp-agent modes strictly in sequence: analyze → find-gaps → propose → update → plan. Each mode persists its artifact so a failed run can resume from the last completed mode.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping modes — especially running propose before analyze — produces WOW features ungrounded in competitor evidence, which is the primary MLP failure mode.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Output artifacts: product_docs/mvp-scope-analysis.md (analyze), product_docs/mlp-analysis-report.md (find-gaps), product_docs/mlp-implementation-order.md (plan). Each file is the input to the next mode.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every WOW feature must cite a row in mvp-scope-analysis.md; features with no competitor evidence are labeled "speculative" and placed under "Deferred — needs validation".</statement>
        <rationale>Speculative WOW features not grounded in competitor evidence or customer data are guesses; they belong in the deferred bucket, not the MLP roadmap.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap WOW features at 7; more than 7 and the MLP becomes a v2.0 plan, not an MLP.</statement>
        <rationale>MLP is the minimum set of WOW features that makes users love the product — a superset of MVP but not a full feature rebuild. Empirically, 8+ WOW features require a second release cycle to ship.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run MLP propose only after the MVP ships and produces real telemetry; propose-without-data is the primary failure mode the workflow does not warn about in its README.</statement>
        <rationale>WOW feature selection without usage data is marketing speculation; the propose mode needs to know which MVP features users actually used before proposing enhancements.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>MLP "update" mode rewrites spec files in-place on retry, clobbering FR numbering.</description>
        <reason>Always run git status before and after update mode; agents on retry have been observed overwriting FR-NN.N numbering with duplicates. Use the artifact files as checkpoints, not as editable scratch space.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running the full MLP pipeline from cron when the product is still in MVP phase with no telemetry.</description>
        <reason>MLP propose generates fictional WOW features when there is no usage data; the cron trigger must check for the existence of a telemetry artifact before running.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="numbering-conventions">
      <p>Standard numbering patterns for features, tasks, requirements, and acceptance criteria used across the PM workflow artifacts.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use these exact patterns across all PM workflow artifacts: features as {NN}-{name} (e.g., 01-auth), tasks as TASK_{NNN}_* (e.g., TASK_001_setup), functional requirements as FR-{NN}.{N} (e.g., FR-01.1), acceptance criteria as AC-{NN}.{N} (e.g., AC-01.1).</statement>
        <rationale>Consistent numbering enables cross-referencing between specs, task files, and tracker tickets; inconsistent numbering breaks the rice-reorder script, spec-to-task linking, and MLP update mode's in-place edit logic.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat .aidocs/features/ as the planning source of truth and Jira/Linear as the execution mirror — never the reverse.</statement>
        <rationale>Tracker tickets get deleted, re-numbered, or migrated; the .aidocs/ file tree is under git and has full history. If the tracker is the source of truth, history is lost when tickets are deleted.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>When syncing RICE values to Jira numeric custom fields, coerce explicitly; Jira drops the value silently on type mismatch.</statement>
        <rationale>Jira's REST API does not return an error when a numeric field receives a string value; the value is silently ignored, leaving the field empty in the tracker while appearing correct in the spec frontmatter.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>The daily PM orchestrator produces one digest file (.aidocs/digest/YYYY-MM-DD.md) and sends only the diff vs. yesterday via tg-send, not the full digest.</statement>
        <rationale>Sending the full digest daily creates Telegram noise; the diff is what the PM needs to act on. Full digests are available on demand from the file.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="orchestration-and-cadence">
      <p>Drive the PM cadence as a **daily orchestrator** (cron + on-demand) plus three event-driven flows: **bootstrap**, **sprint**, **release**. The orchestrator wakes, reads `.aidocs/features/`, syncs deltas to the tracker, and emits a digest. Sprint and release flows are explicit `Task` invocations from the user. Never run bootstrap from cron — it is interactive (Phase 4 confirmation is mandatory). For MLP, sequence the five `faion-mlp-agent` modes strictly (`analyze → find-gaps → propose → update → plan`); each mode persists its artefact so a failed run resumes.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>`faion-mvp-scope-analyzer-agent` — Pulls competitor MVP scope; required input for Phase 3 of bootstrap and Phase 1 of MLP.</item>
        <item>`faion-mlp-agent` — Five-mode orchestrator (`analyze`, `find-gaps`, `propose`, `update`, `plan`). Each mode = one Task invocation.</item>
        <item>`faion-research-agent` (mode=ideas/market/competitors) — Feeds bootstrap Phases 1-3 with `.aidocs/product_docs/*.md` artefacts.</item>
        <item>`faion-sdd-executor-agent` (in `agents/`) — Downstream of TASK_000 creation; receives the first executable task.</item>
        <item>`faion-marketing-manager` — Downstream of release flow; consumes `executive-summary.md` plus release-notes draft for GTM.</item>
        <item>`faion-business-analyst` — Required between Phase 5 (backlog) and Phase 6 (constitution) for FR/AC formalisation.</item>
        <item>General-purpose `Task` subagent — Use for backlog grooming + tracker sync when no specialised PM-ops agent is registered.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <prompt purpose="bootstrap-phase-5-backlog">
        <![CDATA[You are the PM orchestrator. Inputs:
  .aidocs/product_docs/idea-validation.md
  .aidocs/product_docs/competitive-analysis.md
For each MVP feature (max 5), create:
  .aidocs/features/backlog/{NN}-{slug}/spec.md
with sections: User Story, FR-NN.N (max 5), AC-NN.N (Given/When/Then),
RICE score, MoSCoW tag. Refuse to invent features not present in inputs.
Return: list of created paths, RICE table, blocking questions.]]>
      </prompt>
      <prompt purpose="sprint-kickoff">
        <![CDATA[mode=sprint-kickoff sprint_id={N}
Steps:
  1. Read .aidocs/features/backlog/, sort by RICE desc
  2. Pull next K features whose sum(effort) <= team_capacity_pd
  3. Move backlog/ → todo/, generate TASK_NNN_*.md per feature
  4. Sync to Jira/Linear via MCP; attach spec.md as description
Output: sprint plan as table, list of skipped features with reason.]]>
      </prompt>
      <prompt purpose="mlp-propose">
        <![CDATA[mode=propose project_path=.
Constraints: every WOW feature must cite a row in mvp-scope-analysis.md.
If no competitor evidence exists for a feature, label it "speculative"
and place under "Deferred — needs validation". Max 7 WOW items.]]>
      </prompt>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations-and-failures">
      <p>**Tracker drift.** Workflow writes to `.aidocs/features/backlog/` but Jira/Linear are the source of truth for many teams. Without a sync subagent, the two diverge within one sprint.</p>
      <p>**No stakeholder loop.** Bootstrap Phase 4 is a single user confirmation; real PM workflows require sign-off from eng lead, design, and exec sponsor. Agent skips this and produces unsigned constitutions.</p>
      <p>**MLP "WOW" generation hallucinates.** `faion-mlp-agent` mode=`propose` invents features without competitor evidence unless explicitly grounded in `mvp-scope-analysis.md`.</p>
      <p>**Numbering collisions.** `{NN}-{feature}` and `TASK_{NNN}` numbering breaks when two parallel agents create features simultaneously — no lock file in current spec.</p>
      <p>**No definition-of-ready / definition-of-done gates.** Tasks land in `todo/` whether or not the spec passes INVEST. Add a validator subagent.</p>
      <p>**Release management absent.** README does not cover release branching, RC tagging, or rollback windows. Use `pro/product/product-manager/release-planning` alongside.</p>
      <p>**Capacity blindness.** RICE Effort assumes a homogeneous team; agent has no model of available developer-days, so prioritisation drift is common.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>gh project — Read/write GitHub Projects v2 fields, issues, PRs — `gh extension install github/gh-projects` · https://cli.github.com/manual/gh_project</p>
      <p>jira-cli (ankitpokhrel) — Headless Jira ops: issue create, transition, JQL search — `go install github.com/ankitpokhrel/jira-cli/cmd/jira@latest`</p>
      <p>linear-cli (community) — Linear teams/issues from terminal — `npm i -g @evangodon/linear-cli`</p>
      <p>shortcut-cli — Shortcut (Clubhouse) story CRUD — `npm i -g shortcut-cli`</p>
      <p>notion-cli (litencatt) — Notion DB read/write for roadmap pages — `brew install litencatt/tap/notion-cli`</p>
      <p>productboard-cli (community) — Productboard feature ingest — https://www.npmjs.com/package/productboard-api</p>
      <p>git-changelog-command-line — Auto-changelog by conventional commits — `npm i -g conventional-changelog-cli`</p>
      <p>release-please (Google) — Release PRs from conventional commits — `npm i -g release-please`</p>
      <p>semver-cli — Validate / bump semver in release flow — `npm i -g semver`</p>
      <p>dust (renamed `dst`) — RICE/MoSCoW spreadsheet via CSV — local Python script</p>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <p>Jira Cloud (SaaS) — Use Atlassian Remote MCP or `jira-cli`; rate limit 100 req/min/user. — Yes — REST + JQL + MCP server</p>
      <p>Linear (SaaS) — Best-in-class API; webhooks for sprint events. — Yes — GraphQL + official MCP</p>
      <p>Shortcut (SaaS) — Story `external_id` field for two-way sync. — Yes — REST</p>
      <p>GitHub Projects v2 (SaaS) — Use `gh` CLI; fields are typed (single-select, iteration). — Yes — GraphQL</p>
      <p>Productboard (SaaS) — Good for feedback ingest; portal not scriptable. — Partial — REST, no MCP</p>
      <p>Aha! (SaaS) — Heavy enterprise; PMs use for portfolio, not sprint. — Partial — REST</p>
      <p>Notion (SaaS) — Roadmap source-of-truth for solo/small teams. — Yes — REST + MCP</p>
      <p>ClickUp (SaaS) — Watch rate limits; many fields are custom. — Yes — REST</p>
      <p>OpenProject (OSS, self-hosted) — Run on faion-net server; Docker compose. — Yes — REST</p>
      <p>Plane (makeplane) (OSS, self-hosted) — Modern Linear-alternative; active dev. — Yes — REST</p>
      <p>Taiga (OSS) — Scrum + Kanban; smaller community. — Yes — REST</p>
      <p>Focalboard (OSS) — Local-only kanban. — Limited — API closed since Mattermost merge</p>
      <p>LaunchDarkly (SaaS) — Feature flag gates for release management. — Yes — REST</p>
      <p>Statsig (SaaS) — Experimentation + flags; PM owns config. — Yes — REST</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Treat `.aidocs/features/` as the planning source of truth and Jira/Linear as the **execution mirror** — never the reverse, or agents lose history when tickets are deleted.</p>
      <p>Lock numbering. When two PM agents may run concurrently, take a flock on `.aidocs/.numbering.lock` before assigning the next `{NN}` or `TASK_{NNN}`.</p>
      <p>Every spec must have a RICE row before it leaves backlog; reject specs without `reach/impact/confidence/effort` frontmatter at grooming time.</p>
      <p>Run MLP propose only after MVP ships and produces real telemetry — propose-without-data is the failure mode README does not warn about.</p>
      <p>Cap WOW features at 7. Empirically, more than that and the MLP becomes a v2.0 plan, not an MLP.</p>
      <p>Daily orchestrator should produce **one** digest file (`.aidocs/digest/YYYY-MM-DD.md`) and `tg-send` only the diff vs yesterday — saves Telegram noise.</p>
      <p>Hold a `release-cut` ceremony agent that creates the release branch, generates changelog, opens the PR, and pings the GTM agent — don't bolt this onto sprint kickoff.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>**Phase 4 confirmation cannot be skipped.** LLMs eager to finish will simulate user approval. Hard-fail the flow if the user-message stream lacks an explicit `approve` token.</p>
      <p>**`AskUserQuestion` blocks in non-interactive runs** (cron, CI). Bootstrap must detect non-interactive mode and exit with `FAIL needs-human` — do not invent answers.</p>
      <p>**Specs are markdown, trackers are typed.** When syncing RICE values to Jira numeric custom fields, coerce explicitly; otherwise Jira drops the value silently.</p>
      <p>**MLP "update" mode rewrites spec files in-place.** Always run `git status` before and after — agents have been observed clobbering FR numbering on retry.</p>
      <p>**Tracker MCP token leakage.** Linear and Jira MCP servers cache OAuth tokens; in a worktree-isolated agent, the token may belong to a different user. Verify `whoami` against the tracker before write ops.</p>
      <p>**Capacity field is unreliable.** Sprint kickoff agent should require explicit `team_capacity_pd` argument from user; never compute from velocity alone (velocity is a trailing indicator and breaks on holiday weeks).</p>
      <p>**Hidden features.** PMs sometimes file features as `epic` in the tracker but as `feature/` in `.aidocs/`. The sync agent must understand both shapes; otherwise epics duplicate.</p>
      <p>**No DoD validator.** Add a `definition-of-done.yaml` per feature and a checker subagent — without it, `done/` collects half-merged work.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="references">
      <p>Reforge — "PM Operating Model" (sprint cadence + ceremonies): https://www.reforge.com/blog</p>
      <p>Marty Cagan — Inspired (Phase 4 confirmation philosophy): SVPG, 2017.</p>
      <p>Atlassian — Jira Cloud REST v3 + JQL: https://developer.atlassian.com/cloud/jira/platform/rest/v3/</p>
      <p>Linear — API + MCP: https://developers.linear.app/</p>
      <p>GitHub Projects v2 GraphQL: https://docs.github.com/en/graphql/reference/objects#projectv2</p>
      <p>release-please (Google): https://github.com/googleapis/release-please</p>
      <p>Companion methodology: `pro/research/researcher/workflows` (research-side state machine)</p>
      <p>Companion methodology: `pro/pm/pm-agile/scrum-ceremonies` (sprint mechanics this workflow drives)</p>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/rice-reorder.sh" purpose="Rank backlog by RICE score, write sorted INDEX.md"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
