<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Competitive Analysis — Examples and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Concrete e-commerce and SaaS examples of finding-to-insight conversion and analysis anti-patterns.</summary>

  <section title="E-commerce Checkout Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Finding: all 5 competitors offer guest checkout. Insight: guest checkout is table stakes — not having it is a competitive disadvantage, not a differentiator. Recommendation category: Must Have. Finding: only 1 competitor shows estimated delivery on the product page (before cart). Insight: opportunity to differentiate by surfacing delivery estimate earlier in the flow than any competitor does. Recommendation category: Could Differentiate.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="SaaS Onboarding Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Competitor comparison: A = 8 onboarding steps, 15 min to value. B = 3 steps, 2 min to value. C = 5 steps, 8 min to value. Competitor B has highest user ratings. Insight: minimal onboarding correlates with highest satisfaction — reducing steps is the primary lever. Recommendation: target 3-4 steps maximum and measure time-to-first-value as the success metric.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Recommendation Prioritization Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a four-tier recommendation structure in every competitive analysis report: Must Have (table stakes), Should Have (parity), Could Differentiate (opportunity), Avoid (observed failure mode).</statement>
      <rationale>Without tiers, all recommendations appear equal and teams debate which to implement first. Tiers pre-empt the debate by making priority explicit from the analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Analysis Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Analyzing only direct competitors and ignoring aspirational examples from other industries.</description>
      <reason>Direct competitors may all share the same blind spot. Aspirational examples expose solutions that the entire competitive set has missed. Some of the most valuable UX innovations come from pattern transfers across industries.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Copying a competitor pattern without understanding why they made that choice.</description>
      <reason>The competitor may have shipped that pattern to fix a specific problem in their system that does not apply to yours. Copying without context imports the constraint along with the solution.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running competitive analysis once and treating the findings as permanent.</description>
      <reason>Competitor products change continuously. Analysis older than 6-12 months describes a market that no longer exists. Schedule regular check-ins: major annually, minor quarterly, triggered when a competitor ships a significant update.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating competitive analysis as a substitute for user research.</description>
      <reason>Competitors' patterns may also be wrong — users tolerate them because there is no better alternative. Validate competitive patterns with your own users before adopting them as design requirements.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
