<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="competitive-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for competitive-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Analyzing only direct competitors and ignoring aspirational examples from other industries.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Direct competitors may all share the same blind spot. Aspirational examples expose solutions that the competitive set has not discovered. Pattern transfers across industries often yield the highest-value insights.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Copying a competitor pattern without understanding why they made that choice.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The competitor may have shipped that pattern to fix a specific problem in their system that does not apply to yours. Copying without understanding context imports constraints along with the solution.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Running competitive analysis once and treating findings as permanent.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Competitor products change continuously. Analysis older than 6-12 months describes a market that no longer exists. Schedule regular check-ins: major annually, minor quarterly, triggered when a competitor ships a significant update.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating competitive analysis as a substitute for user research.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Competitors' patterns may also be wrong. Users tolerate them because there is no better alternative. Validate competitive patterns with your own users before adopting them as design requirements.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Over-interpreting surface patterns without validating causation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Competitors may have implemented a pattern for reasons unrelated to UX (regulatory constraint, technical limitation, legacy code). Surface observation cannot determine causation. Always include human review before committing to a recommendation based on competitor behavior.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
