<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Privacy-Compliant Analytics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Privacy-Compliant Analytics` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="default-deny-not-default-allow" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CMP MUST default to deny for analytics + advertising + functional cookies until explicit consent. Pre-checked consent boxes are forbidden (GDPR Art. 7 + 2024 EDPB guidelines).</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 7; EDPB Cookie Banner Taskforce report 2024">Default-allow is illegal in EU under GDPR; CCPA also penalizes silent opt-in. Default-deny is the only configuration that survives audit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="consent-mode-v2-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Google products (GA4, Ads) MUST use Consent Mode v2 with ad_storage + analytics_storage + ad_user_data + ad_personalization signals. Consent Mode v1 is deprecated.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google Consent Mode v2 docs; March 2024 enforcement">Without v2, Google rejects EEA conversions starting March 2024. Without all four signals, retargeting + modeled conversions break silently.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="gpc-signal-honored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Server MUST honor Global Privacy Control (GPC) header signal as a CCPA opt-out. Ignoring GPC is a documented CCPA violation as of CA Attorney General 2023 enforcement.</statement>
      <rationale source="CCPA enforcement actions 2023-2024; Sephora settlement precedent">GPC is a binding signal under CCPA. Major settlements (Sephora $1.2M) cite GPC ignorance specifically. Detecting + honoring header is mandatory, not optional.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="ip-anonymized-before-storage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Analytics tools MUST anonymize IP (truncate last octet for IPv4, last 80 bits for IPv6) before storage. Raw IP storage requires DPA + lawful basis.</statement>
      <rationale source="GA4 docs anonymizeIp; ICO IP guidance">Raw IP = personal data under GDPR. Tools that ship anonymization by default (GA4, Plausible, Matomo) need it confirmed in config; tools that don&apos;t (custom logging) need pre-storage hashing.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="tag-audit-log-per-release" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every release MUST include a tag-firing audit: list of tags + which consent categories they require + a network-tab proof. New tags without entry are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="GTM audit best-practice; OneTrust deployment guides">Tag drift is the #1 silent compliance break. Without per-release audit, marketing adds a pixel, dev forgets to gate it, regulator finds it on a random visit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
