<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-compliance-rules" title="Compliance Rules and LLM Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Mandatory GDPR UI parity rule, sub-processor DPA requirement, IP anonymization scope limit, and documented LLM agent errors in privacy work.</summary>

  <section title="UI Parity Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>The "Reject all" button must be one click and visually equal to "Accept all" in size, color, and prominence.</statement>
      <rationale>CNIL (France) issued multiple fines in 2022–2024 for consent banners where "Accept all" was a prominent button and "Reject all" required additional clicks or was visually de-emphasized. Equal prominence is a concrete, auditable requirement.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Sub-Processor DPA Requirement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every new analytics pixel, SDK, or session-replay tool must have a signed DPA, a valid data-transfer mechanism (SCCs or EU-US DPF), and an entry in the Records of Processing before it fires.</statement>
      <rationale>Adding an undocumented sub-processor violates GDPR Article 28; the CMP consent banner does not authorize processing by unlisted vendors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>tie the cookie policy table to the live CMP scan output, not a hand-written list — it drifts within weeks</item>
      <item>run Cookiebot or Osano quarterly scan to catch new cookies introduced by code changes</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="IP Anonymization Scope">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not claim that IP anonymization exempts analytics from GDPR processing law — state only that it is one mitigation applied, and document the lawful basis separately.</statement>
      <rationale>ICO and EDPB treat anonymized IP-derived analytics as personal data in many cases; claiming anonymization = no GDPR is a common LLM error that creates compliance risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent LLM Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent claims "GA4 is GDPR-compliant" as a conclusion.</description>
      <reason>This is a marketing claim, not a legal determination. The correct output is the gating mechanism applied (consent gate + Consent Mode v2 + EU region configuration).</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent writes banner copy with highlighted Accept and hidden Reject button.</description>
      <reason>LLMs default to UX patterns optimized for conversion, not consent parity; lock UI parity in the template and do not let the agent restyle.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent claims hashing emails/IDs is sufficient anonymization.</description>
      <reason>Hashing without a rotation policy is reversible; only salted hashing with key rotation can reduce re-identification risk, and even then GDPR may still apply.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent uses Accept-Language or other client-side signal for EU/US/CA region detection.</description>
      <reason>Region detection must use a server-trusted GeoIP signal; client-side headers are user-controlled and not legally reliable for jurisdiction determination.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
