<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="activation-tactics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>growth-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Concrete techniques for increasing signup-to-Aha conversion: progressive onboarding, templates, checklists, empty state design, time-to-value optimization, activation emails, and in-app guidance.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>activation</tag>
      <tag>onboarding</tag>
      <tag>aarrr</tag>
      <tag>experiments</tag>
      <tag>ab-testing</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Activation Tactics &amp; Experiments</title>

    <summary>Concrete techniques for increasing the percentage of new signups that reach the Aha moment: progressive onboarding, templates/presets, activation checklists, empty state redesign, time-to-value reduction, activation emails, and in-app guidance. Each tactic is paired with an experiment template for A/B testing.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Activation is the conversion from signup to experienced value. Most SaaS products lose 60-70% of signups before they activate. Each tactic targets a specific friction or motivation gap in the signup-to-Aha funnel. Users who use templates activate at 65% vs 35% for blank-start users — a measurable, reproducible pattern across multiple products.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Activation rate below target (typically below 30-40% for D7).</item>
        <item>Session recordings show users landing on empty states or quitting during onboarding.</item>
        <item>Time-to-first-value exceeds 5 minutes for a simple use case.</item>
        <item>Email open rates for Day 0 welcome email are high but click-through is low.</item>
        <item>You have an A/B testing framework and want a prioritized experiment backlog.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF: low activation may signal wrong product/audience, not friction — fix the product first.</item>
        <item>Sales-led B2B with human-guided implementations — self-serve activation tactics do not apply.</item>
        <item>When you do not yet track the activation event — instrument first, optimize second.</item>
        <item>Single-session utility tools where "activation" equals "usage" — no onboarding funnel exists.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="progressive-onboarding">
      <rule>
        <statement>Show value before requiring setup; defer configuration to the moment it becomes relevant.</statement>
        <rationale>Front-loaded setup screens increase cognitive load before the user has experienced any value. Show a sample project first, then guide them to create their own.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>5 setup screens → empty product. User quits before seeing any value.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Skip setup → show sample project → guide "try editing this task" → after Aha: "now create your own project".</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="templates-and-presets">
      <rule>
        <statement>Offer 3-5 use-case templates at first login; users who pick a template activate at ~65% vs ~35% for blank-start.</statement>
        <rationale>Templates reduce the blank-page problem and immediately anchor the product to the user's specific use case, accelerating time to value.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="activation-checklist">
      <rule>
        <statement>Show a visible progress checklist (2-5 steps) with a marked activation event; remove it once the user activates.</statement>
        <rationale>Progress visibility triggers the Zeigarnik effect — users feel motivated to complete partial sequences. Expected lift: +10-25% activation rate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/activation-checklist.yaml">YAML config for in-product checklist with activation_event flag</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="empty-state-design">
      <rule>
        <statement>Replace generic empty states with personalized prompts that surface the highest-converting first action.</statement>
        <rationale>An empty state is a decision point: without guidance, the user faces choice paralysis. A personalized CTA with a template shortcut doubles conversion.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="time-to-value-optimization">
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure time from signup to Aha moment; if it exceeds 5 minutes for the core use case, remove steps until it does not.</statement>
        <rationale>Each additional minute increases dropout probability. Remove optional fields, pre-fill defaults, skip to core action. Target: signup to value in under 3 minutes.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="activation-emails">
      <rule>
        <statement>Send a 4-email sequence (Day 0, 1, 3, 7) to users who have not activated; each email has a single CTA linked to the next blocking step.</statement>
        <rationale>Re-engagement emails targeting non-activated users recover 5-10% of them on Day 7. Each email should have one goal — not a product tour.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/email-sequence.md">4-email activation sequence copy templates</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="in-app-guidance">
      <rule>
        <statement>Deploy tooltips at the first visit to each key feature; use coach marks for multi-step processes; use chat prompts only when session recordings show users stuck for 30+ seconds.</statement>
        <rationale>Contextual help shown at the right moment adds guidance without overwhelming the interface. Poorly timed tooltips (shown every visit) are dismissed and create noise.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="experiment-backlog">
      <list>
        <item>Remove signup form fields → target: Signup-to-Step2, expected: +10-20%</item>
        <item>Show templates first → target: Activation rate, expected: +15-30%</item>
        <item>Pre-fill sample data → target: Time to value, expected: -50%</item>
        <item>Add progress checklist → target: Activation rate, expected: +10-25%</item>
        <item>Add welcome video → target: Onboarding completion, expected: +5-15%</item>
        <item>Simplify first action (reduce to 1 step) → target: Step N to Activation, expected: +10-20%</item>
        <item>Add tooltip at key moment → target: Feature discovery, expected: +5-15%</item>
        <item>Send Day 1 re-engagement email → target: D7 activation, expected: +5-10%</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="hypothesis-template">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write every experiment hypothesis as: "If we [change], then [metric] will increase by [X%] because [mechanism]." Fix primary metric, sample size (min 2000/variant), and duration before launch.</statement>
        <rationale>Pre-registration prevents post-hoc metric selection and ensures the test has enough power to detect the expected lift.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[## Experiment: Templates First

### Hypothesis
If we show a template picker as the first screen after signup,
then D7 activation rate will increase by 15%
because templates reduce blank-page friction and anchor the product to the user's use case.

### Variants
- Control: Blank project screen
- Treatment: Template picker (5 options)

### Sample Size
- Users per variant: 2,000
- Duration: 14 days
- Statistical power: 80%

### Metrics
- Primary: Day 7 activation rate
- Secondary: Time to activation, D30 retention

### Decision Criteria
p < 0.05 on primary metric AND 95% CI lower bound > 5% lift]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="experiment-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running the experiment until it looks significant, then stopping.</description>
        <reason>Peeking invalidates the p-value. Commit to sample size or duration before launch; only analyze once that threshold is reached.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Testing 5 changes at once in a single experiment variant.</description>
        <reason>Cannot attribute the effect to any single change, making iteration impossible. Test one variable at a time unless running a full multivariate design.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/activation-checklist.yaml" purpose="YAML config for in-product onboarding checklist with activation event flag."/>
      <template path="templates/email-sequence.md" purpose="4-email activation sequence: Day 0, Day 1, Day 3, Day 7."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="aarrr-pirate-metrics"/>
      <ref slug="ab-testing-basics"/>
      <ref slug="activation-metrics"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
