<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ops-contractor-basics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>Five-step framework for solopreneurs hiring contractors: Identify, Find, Evaluate, Onboard with paid test task, Manage. Always run a paid test task before ongoing engagement.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>contractors</tag>
      <tag>hiring</tag>
      <tag>delegation</tag>
      <tag>solopreneur</tag>
      <tag>freelance</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Contractor Basics for Solopreneurs</title>

    <summary>A five-step framework for solopreneurs hiring their first contractors: Identify (delegation matrix and ROI calc), Find (sourcing channels and job-post template), Evaluate (screening stages, red/green flags), Onboard (paid test task before commitment), Manage (communication norms and tool setup). The core rule: always run a paid test task on a real deliverable before any ongoing engagement; never sign a contract or make a hire autonomously — human approval required at every commitment point.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Solo founders maxed on time stall growth. A $30/hr VA or designer that saves 5+ hours/week produces $15K–$20K/year of effective value at a 3–5x ROI over the founder's own time. The failure modes are hiring too fast without a test task (discovering quality problems after weeks of commitment), or treating contractors like employees (misclassification fines of $1K–$25K per contractor in the US).</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo founder ready to delegate first paid work</item>
        <item>Drafting a job post, paid-test-task brief, or applicant scoring rubric</item>
        <item>Computing ROI of delegation vs DIY before committing budget</item>
        <item>Pre-flight screening: flagging red/green signals in a candidate dossier</item>
        <item>Re-evaluating which tasks are core vs delegate-worthy after a workload spike</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Hiring W-2 employees — misclassification risk; use hr-recruiter knowledge</item>
        <item>Managing an existing contractor relationship — use ops-contractor-management</item>
        <item>Procurement of SaaS vendors or agencies on retainer — different structure (MSA + SOW)</item>
        <item>Hiring in regulated roles (legal, medical, financial advice) — needs licensed-professional checks</item>
        <item>Markets where contractor classification is legally constrained (CA AB5, EU dependent-contractor tests) — escalate to legal counsel first</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="delegation-decision">
      <p>Delegate when: the task is a specialized skill where others perform better, it is time-consuming and repetitive, and the contractor rate is less than 60% of the founder's effective hourly rate.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Delegate when: the task is a specialized skill where others perform better, it is time-consuming and repetitive, and the contractor rate is less than 60% of the founder's effective hourly rate.</statement>
        <rationale>Core competency work (your competitive advantage) stays with the founder. Everything else is a candidate for delegation. The 60% threshold ensures the ROI exceeds overhead and management time.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Positive delegation ROI">
        <note>Founder effective rate $100/hr. Task takes 5 hrs/week. Contractor rate $30/hr at 4 hrs/week. Weekly savings: $500 - $120 = $380. Annual savings: $19,000. Onboarding overhead payback: 2-3 weeks.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="sourcing-and-evaluation">
      <p>Always run a paid test task on a real deliverable before any ongoing engagement. The test task budget is marketing spend, not work owed. Never ask for unpaid sample work.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always run a paid test task on a real deliverable before any ongoing engagement. The test task budget is marketing spend, not work owed. Never ask for unpaid sample work.</statement>
        <rationale>The test task is the only reliable signal of real work quality AND communication style. Portfolios and interviews are necessary but not sufficient filters. Unpaid work filters out quality candidates who have options.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Document the role's quality bar with 2-3 "good output" and "bad output" examples before posting the job. This artifact is harder to produce than the job post but is the highest-leverage filter.</statement>
        <rationale>Without an explicit quality standard, applicant scoring becomes subjective and LLM shortlisting optimizes for surface signals (grammar, buzzwords) rather than output quality.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Red flags: generic application (did not read job post), no relevant samples, poor communication, unrealistic timeline, no questions about the work.</p>
      <p>Green flags: thoughtful application with specific references to the post, relevant portfolio, asks clarifying questions, honest about limitations, quick and clear responses.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="classification-compliance">
      <p>Treat contractors as contractors: they control how they work (not just what they deliver), use their own tools, set their own schedule, and have other clients. Never dictate working hours, mandate specific tools, or require daily standups.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Treat contractors as contractors: they control how they work (not just what they deliver), use their own tools, set their own schedule, and have other clients. Never dictate working hours, mandate specific tools, or require daily standups.</statement>
        <rationale>Misclassifying a contractor as an employee exposes the business to US penalties of $1K-$25K per contractor plus back taxes. CA AB5 and EU dependent-contractor tests apply even more strictly. Each of the listed behaviors is a misclassification indicator.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ui-designer-hire">
      <p>Real-world example: UI design for new product pages. Process: posted on Dribbble and Twitter; received 40 applications; shortlisted 5 with strong portfolios; paid test: redesign one page ($150, real deliverable, could ship); selected best result. Outcome: $75/hr, 10 hrs/month, ongoing relationship, freed 15+ hours/month of founder time.</p>
      <example type="good" title="UI designer hire from portfolio sourcing">
        <note>Need: UI design for new product pages. Process: posted on Dribbble and Twitter; received 40 applications; shortlisted 5 with strong portfolios; paid test: redesign one page ($150, real deliverable, could ship); selected best result. Outcome: $75/hr, 10 hrs/month, ongoing relationship, freed 15+ hours/month of founder time.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="virtual-assistant-hire">
      <p>Virtual assistant hiring: admin, scheduling, email management. Process: posted on Upwork; filtered on reviews and demonstrated experience; 20-minute interview for communication quality; 2-week trial at 10 hours/week; promoted to ongoing. Outcome: $20/hr, 15 hrs/week, handles all admin, saved 20+ hours/week, ROI estimated 10x on investment.</p>
      <example type="good" title="Virtual assistant hire with trial period">
        <note>Need: admin, scheduling, email management. Process: posted on Upwork; filtered on reviews and demonstrated experience; 20-minute interview for communication quality; 2-week trial at 10 hours/week; promoted to ongoing. Outcome: $20/hr, 15 hrs/week, handles all admin, saved 20+ hours/week, ROI estimated 10x on investment.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Founder hires without a paid test task because "the portfolio looked great".</description>
        <reason>Portfolio shows past work on past problems with past clients. The test task reveals how the contractor handles YOUR problems, YOUR feedback, and YOUR communication style. Skipping it is the most common expensive hiring mistake.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent sends a contract or offer letter to a contractor without human approval.</description>
        <reason>Contract signing creates legal obligations. Misclassification flags embedded in the contract language are not reliably detected by LLMs. Mandatory human-in-loop at every commitment point.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent publishes a job post with a specific hourly rate range derived from training data without current market verification.</description>
        <reason>Contractor market rates vary significantly by region, skill, and current demand. Hallucinated rates either deter qualified applicants or attract applicants expecting different compensation. Always WebSearch current rates before publishing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration">
      <p>Use a single-agent loop for sourcing and shortlisting: scrape job posts, parse applicant data, draft outreach messages. Hand off to a human-in-loop checkpoint before any paid commitment (test task, contract sign, first invoice). Pair with ops-contractor-management for the post-hire phase and ops-legal-basics for contractor-agreement boilerplate. The agent's job is reducing screening overhead, not picking the contractor.</p>

      <p>US-centric tax/classification framing (IRS 20-factor test, EIN, W-9). Outside US, agent must localize. Hourly rate tables in source README are illustrative only — agent must verify current market rates by region/skill before using them in a brief. No guidance on equity-as-comp or revenue share — purely cash-rate model. Doesn't cover team-of-contractors coordination — single-contractor framing only. Quality screening relies on portfolio assessment; LLM cannot reliably judge visual design quality without a human reviewer in the loop.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Agent must not send a contract, sign an agreement, or make any payment commitment autonomously. Human approval is required at every commitment point (test task commissioning, contract signing, first invoice approval).</statement>
        <rationale>Misclassification penalties ($1K-$25K per contractor), unenforceable contract terms from training data, and incorrect scope commitments are not LLM-recoverable errors.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>When scoring applicants, output a ranked top-3 for human review and explicitly state "Do NOT recommend a hire — surface candidates for human decision". Never select the contractor.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs over-weight grammatical fluency in applicant summaries. For design and dev roles, portfolio quality (requiring human judgment) matters more than communication polish. The selection is a human call.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Before publishing any job post with a budget range, WebSearch current rates for the specific role and region (e.g. "UI designer Ukraine hourly rate 2025"). Never use hardcoded rate tables from training data.</statement>
        <rationale>Market rates shift significantly by year and region. The illustrative rate tables in the source README are anchors, not current market data.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Applicant screening prompt: "You are reviewing 12 Upwork applications for [role]. For each: extract years of experience, 3 most relevant portfolio links, communication quality (1-5), red flags, green flags. Output JSON array sorted by fit-score. Do NOT recommend a hire — surface a top-3 for human review."</p>

      <p>ROI calculation prompt: "Compute delegation ROI: my hourly value=$X, task takes me Y hrs/week, contractor rate=$Z/hr, contractor takes K hrs to do same task. Return weekly savings, annual savings, payback if onboarding takes M hrs."</p>

      <p>LLM-generated job posts default to vague "rockstar/ninja" copy — agent must extract specific deliverables from the human first or the post won't filter applicants. Agents will hallucinate market rates; always WebSearch current rates by &lt;role&gt; &lt;region&gt; hourly rate 2025 before publishing a budget range. When summarizing applicant pools, LLMs over-weight grammatical fluency — useful for content/copy roles, misleading for design/dev roles where portfolio matters more. Do not let an agent send the offer or sign the contract autonomously; mandatory human-in-loop at the contract stage. Misclassification penalties (US ~$1k-25k per contractor) are not LLM-recoverable mistakes. Agent-drafted contracts that copy clauses from training data may include unenforceable or jurisdiction-mismatched terms. Always run through ops-legal-basics template + human review. Token cost: a 40-applicant Upwork pool review is ~30-60k tokens; batch and cache the rubric, score in chunks of 10. "Treat as contractor not employee" rule — agents must not auto-schedule the contractor's hours, dictate working tools, or set fixed daily standups; that's a misclassification flag.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools: gh (pull contractor work product from PRs they own; review diffs), op (pull contractor credentials from 1Password vault for tool provisioning), wise-cli (programmatic Wise transfers for cross-border contractor pay), stripe (create Stripe Connect Express accounts for contractor payouts), jq (parse Upwork/Toptal API responses, candidate exports).</p>
      <p>Services: Upwork (SaaS, partial agent support via exported CSVs), Toptal (SaaS, no public API; pre-vetted talent), Deel (SaaS with REST API for contractor onboarding, contracts, payments, compliance docs), Remote.com (API for contractor agreements + global payments), Bonsai (API for proposals, contracts, invoices), Wise (REST API for batched contractor payouts), Stripe Connect (programmatic onboarding + payout), HelloSign / Dropbox Sign (API to send contractor agreements for e-signature), DocuSign (mature API, more enterprise-leaning), LinkedIn Recruiter (no agent-grade API for solopreneur tier).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Always run a paid test task before committing to ongoing engagement; budget the test as marketing spend, not as work owed. Tie the test task to a real deliverable you can ship — never throwaway work; respect contractor's time. Force a 24-hour cool-down between shortlist and hire decision; LLM-driven shortlists optimize for surface signal. Document the role's quality bar with 2-3 examples of "good" and "bad" output before posting — this is the hardest artifact to produce and the highest-leverage one. Use platforms with escrow (Upwork) for first engagement with a new contractor; switch to direct payment (Wise/Stripe) only after 2-3 successful cycles. Set explicit timezone overlap requirements in the job post — vague "async friendly" attracts mismatch. Never ask for unpaid sample work; this filters out the contractors you actually want.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/job-post.md" purpose="Job posting boilerplate: role, responsibilities, requirements, compensation, application instructions"/>
      <template path="templates/delegation-roi.py" purpose="ROI calculator: my hourly rate, task hours/week, contractor rate → weekly/annual savings"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.irs.gov/businesses/small-businesses-self-employed/independent-contractor-defined"/>
      <link href="https://www.upwork.com/resources/hiring-guide"/>
      <link href="https://developer.deel.com/"/>
      <link href="https://stripe.com/docs/connect"/>
      <link href="https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/flsa/misclassification"/>
      <ref slug="ops-contractor-management"/>
      <ref slug="ops-legal-basics"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
