<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Blameless Retro — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for facilitating a blameless post-incident retrospective. Each rule has empirical roots in the SRE / incident-response literature and a known violation pattern.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-language-rule-enforcement" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Facilitator interrupts blame language in real-time. Person-as-subject phrases ("Bob deployed without testing") are reframed as system-as-subject ("the deploy pipeline allowed an untested deploy"). The reframe is verbal at the moment, not after the meeting.</statement>
      <rationale source="Etsy DebriefFacilitator's Guide, Sidney Dekker (Field Guide to Understanding Human Error)">Post-meeting language cleanup does not change participant behavior. Real-time reframing teaches the pattern. Without enforcement, "blameless" becomes a stated value the meeting does not actually hold.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-contributing-factors-min-3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The retro MUST identify at least 3 contributing factors. Single-cause "root cause" framing is forbidden — incidents always have multiple contributing factors. If the team converges on one cause, push for "what made that cause go undetected?", "what made the impact bigger than it should have been?", "what made recovery slower?".</statement>
      <rationale source="Sidney Dekker — The Field Guide to Understanding Human Error, John Allspaw's "How Complex Systems Fail" reading">Single-root-cause framing produces single-fix action items that don't transfer learning. Multi-factor analysis surfaces detection gaps, comms gaps, mitigation gaps — all separately fixable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-action-items-owner-and-date" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every action item MUST have a single named owner AND a target date. Action items with "the team will look into" or "TBD" owner are not action items — they are wishes. The retro is incomplete until every action has an owner + date.</statement>
      <rationale source="PagerDuty postmortem doc, GTD methodology">Unowned action items have a completion rate &lt; 15% per organizational research. Owned + dated action items complete at 60-75%. Forcing the assignment at retro time is the cheapest place to make this happen.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-meta-round-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The final agenda block is the META round: "What did we ALMOST learn from this incident but didn't dig into?" The facilitator captures unspoken concerns, hypotheses participants thought but didn't voice, and patterns connecting this incident to others. This block is 10 minutes and is non-skippable even when time pressure exists.</statement>
      <rationale source="Liminal Thinking practice, organizational learning research (Edmondson)">The meta round catches the highest-leverage insights — the things people noticed but didn't say. Without explicit space, these die in the room. Empirically, meta-round captures produce the most cross-incident pattern-recognition improvements.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-retro-record-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The retro record MUST be published to a known location (wiki, repo /postmortems folder) within 48 hours, with all action items + owners + dates visible to a broader audience than the meeting participants. Private / unpublished retros do not produce organizational learning.</statement>
      <rationale source="PagerDuty / Google SRE postmortem-public stance, knowledge-management research">Published records are auditable, searchable, and cite-able. Unpublished retros become tribal knowledge that decays. The 48-hour cap prevents the publication-debt spiral where retros queue indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical example">

    <example type="good" title="Real-time blameless reframe">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Participant: "Bob deployed at 4pm Friday without running the
  integration tests."

Facilitator (interrupting after first sentence):
"Let me reframe: the deploy process allowed a deploy at 4pm Friday
that bypassed integration tests. What in the pipeline made that
bypass possible?"

Result: discussion moves to "the deploy script had a --skip-tests
flag intended for hotfix-only use, but no enforcement of the
hotfix condition" — a concrete systemic factor with a clear fix.

Action items generated:
  - Remove --skip-tests flag, replace with explicit hotfix-mode
    requiring incident-id (owner: alex.k, by 2026-05-30)
  - Add Friday-after-3pm deploy warning prompt (owner: jane.s,
    by 2026-05-27)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1, r3: real-time reframe + named action items with owner and date.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Single-root-cause shutdown">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Facilitator: "What's the root cause?"
Team: "Bob skipped the tests."
Facilitator: "OK, action item: Bob will run tests next time."

Retro duration: 12 min. Action item: 1, named-and-shamed.
Two months later: a different person, same skip-tests path, same
incident class. Original action item: not actionable (training a
person doesn't fix a system).

Repair: enforce r2 + r1. Push for ≥3 contributing factors;
reframe person-as-subject into system-as-subject.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1, r2, r3 violations — the "blame the human" anti-pattern that produces no system learning.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
