<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="tmux-power-user Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for tmux-power-user. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Ctrl+A as the prefix key rather than the default Ctrl+B; it is more ergonomic and consistent with GNU screen muscle memory.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ctrl+B requires moving the left hand off the home row. Ctrl+A is reachable without moving the hand, reducing friction across hundreds of daily prefix-chord invocations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set base-index 1 and pane-base-index 1; the default zero-indexing makes Alt+1 select window 0, which feels counter-intuitive.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">With base-index 1, Alt+1 through Alt+9 map directly to the visual position of windows in the status bar.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always set escape-time to 10ms or less; the default 500ms causes a noticeable delay in vim when pressing Escape.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Vim and other editors rely on fast Escape detection. The default 500ms makes modal editing feel sluggish over SSH.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use | and - for splits; the defaults " and % are not mnemonic. Open splits in the current pane's working directory.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">| visually represents a vertical divider (horizontal split). - represents a horizontal line (vertical split). Both are immediately memorable. Current-path inheritance eliminates the need to cd after each split.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run the status bar script with a 5-second refresh interval; 1-second intervals cause noticeable CPU overhead on low-power VPS instances.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A status bar that refreshes every second calls shell scripts 60 times per minute. At 5 seconds, the overhead drops to 12 calls per minute with no perceptible staleness for CPU/memory metrics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Install TPM before adding any plugin declarations to .tmux.conf; otherwise tmux.conf fails to source and all settings are lost.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">TPM's run directive at the bottom of .tmux.conf initializes all plugins. If the TPM directory does not exist, the run command silently fails and no plugins load.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use tmux-resurrect and tmux-continuum for automatic session persistence. Enable @resurrect-capture-pane-contents so the text visible in each pane is saved and restored.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without pane contents capture, a restored session shows empty panes. With it, the last visible output (logs, process output) is replayed into each pane. Continuum auto-saves every 15 minutes and auto-restores on tmux server start.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Optional: add tmux-yank for system clipboard integration over SSH, but verify xclip or xsel is installed on the remote host first.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">tmux-yank copies to system clipboard (macOS pbcopy, Linux xclip/xsel). Over SSH, this requires xclip or xsel on the remote host.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always use has-session before creating a named session; re-running a session-creation script should attach to the existing session, not fail or create duplicates.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Session scripts are often called from aliases, shell startup, or agents. If the session already exists, recreating it destroys ongoing work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use different prefix keys for local and remote tmux to avoid double-prefix confusion: Ctrl+A locally, Ctrl+B remotely (or vice versa).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">When inside a local tmux session and SSH'd into a remote tmux, every prefix command requires sending the prefix twice (once for local tmux to ignore, once for the remote). Different prefixes eliminate this ambiguity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Control background processes from scripts or agents via tmux send-keys to send commands and capture-pane to inspect pane output programmatically.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">send-keys allows scripts to interact with tmux panes without requiring an interactive terminal. capture-pane enables condition-based automation (check pane output, take action).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
