<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>
  <section name="tpm-plugins">
    <summary>tmux Plugin Manager (TPM) installation, essential plugin configuration, and common pitfalls.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Install TPM before adding any plugin declarations to .tmux.conf; otherwise tmux.conf fails to source and all settings are lost.</statement>
      <rationale>TPM's run directive at the bottom of .tmux.conf initializes all plugins. If the TPM directory does not exist, the run command silently fails and no plugins load.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Install TPM (one-time, before first use)
git clone https://github.com/tmux-plugins/tpm ~/.tmux/plugins/tpm

# In .tmux.conf — declare plugins
set -g @plugin 'tmux-plugins/tpm'
set -g @plugin 'tmux-plugins/tmux-resurrect'
set -g @plugin 'tmux-plugins/tmux-continuum'

# MUST be the last line in .tmux.conf
run '~/.tmux/plugins/tpm/tpm'

# After adding plugins: press prefix + I to install
# To update: prefix + U
      ]]></code>
    </example>

    <section name="essential-plugins">
      <list>
        <item>tmux-resurrect — saves and restores sessions including pane layout, running commands, and vim sessions</item>
        <item>tmux-continuum — auto-saves sessions every 15 minutes; auto-restores on tmux server start</item>
        <item>tmux-yank — copies to system clipboard over SSH (requires xclip/xsel/pbcopy on the client)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="resurrect-continuum">
      <rule>
        <statement>Enable @resurrect-capture-pane-contents so the text visible in each pane is saved and restored, not just the pane structure.</statement>
        <rationale>Without pane contents capture, a restored session shows empty panes. With it, the last visible output (logs, process output) is replayed into each pane.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
set -g @plugin 'tmux-plugins/tmux-resurrect'
set -g @plugin 'tmux-plugins/tmux-continuum'

# Resurrect: save pane content and vim session files
set -g @resurrect-capture-pane-contents 'on'
set -g @resurrect-strategy-vim 'session'

# Continuum: auto-save every 15 min, auto-restore on start
set -g @continuum-restore 'on'
set -g @continuum-save-interval '15'

# Manual save/restore commands (outside of auto):
# prefix + Ctrl+s = save
# prefix + Ctrl+r = restore
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="plugin-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Forgetting prefix + I after adding a new plugin declaration — plugin directories are not created until install is run</item>
        <item>TPM run directive not at the bottom of .tmux.conf — plugins declared after run do not load</item>
        <item>tmux-yank requires xclip or xsel on the remote host for SSH clipboard forwarding to work</item>
        <item>tmux-continuum auto-restore only runs when tmux server starts, not on attach; a running server will not auto-restore</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>
</text>
