<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ia-framework">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Systematically organize, label, and structure navigation systems so users find what they need without the content matching internal org structures.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>information-architecture</tag>
      <tag>navigation</tag>
      <tag>content-organization</tag>
      <tag>findability</tag>
      <tag>taxonomy</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-24</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Information Architecture - Framework</title>
    <summary>Information architecture (IA) is the structural design of shared information environments. It involves organizing, labeling, and creating navigation systems that help users find and understand information. A robust IA framework prevents low findability, user frustration, increased support costs, and poor scalability as content grows.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Without proper IA, users cannot find what they need. Content organization matches the company, not users. Navigation is confusing and inconsistent. Search becomes the only way to find anything. Adding new content breaks existing structure. Different teams organize content differently.</p>
      <p>Optimizing individual touchpoints without seeing the full information landscape creates local maxima: one screen improves while handoffs between sections or channels get worse. Information architecture forces cross-functional visibility into the complete structure and surface friction that no single team owns.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>At the start of a product or site build, before any navigation or page structure is committed to code.</item>
        <item>When users consistently report they cannot find things and analytics confirm high search usage and low direct navigation.</item>
        <item>During a content migration or redesign where the existing structure needs to be evaluated and reorganized.</item>
        <item>When adding a new content type or feature to an existing product — to validate it fits the current IA before creating a one-off page.</item>
        <item>When onboarding stakeholders who need to understand the product's structural logic before contributing content.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>For single-purpose tools with fewer than 10 distinct screens — a simple user flow diagram suffices.</item>
        <item>When the product's navigation is already well-validated by tree testing and usability data — redo IA only when evidence warrants it.</item>
        <item>As the first step in a research process; IA should follow user research (card sorting, interviews), not precede it.</item>
        <item>When the team has no authority over navigation or content organization (e.g., working inside a locked CMS template).</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <how-to>
      <step>Research: Understand the content (content inventory, content types and relationships, growth projections), understand users (user research, mental models, common tasks and goals), and understand business (goals, key content priorities, governance needs).</step>
      <step>Define Strategy: Based on research, determine the primary user tasks, most important content, how users will expect to find things, and how the structure will scale.</step>
      <step>Create Organization Schemes: Select among Topic (by subject matter, for content sites), Task (by user goal, for tool/app UIs), Audience (by user type, for multi-audience sites), Alphabetical (A-Z order, for directories and glossaries), Chronological (by date, for news and blogs), and Geographic (by location, for location-based services).</step>
      <step>Define Taxonomy: Create consistent naming with categories (top-level groups), subcategories (nested groups), tags (cross-cutting labels), and metadata (structured attributes).</step>
      <step>Design Navigation: Design global navigation (appears on every page), local navigation (within a section), contextual navigation (related content links), utility navigation (account, help, settings), footer navigation (secondary links, legal), and breadcrumbs (location in hierarchy).</step>
      <step>Validate: Test with users via card sorting (organization), tree testing (findability), and usability testing (real use).</step>
    </how-to>
    <section name="ia-components">
      <p>Information architecture has four core components:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Organization: How content is grouped into categories and sections, reflecting either subject matter (topic-based), user goals (task-based), or user type (audience-based).</statement>
        <rationale>The organization scheme is the foundation for all downstream navigation design. Choosing the wrong scheme — such as org-chart navigation that matches internal structure instead of user mental models — undermines findability from the start.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Labeling: How content is named in menus, headings, and navigation items. Labels must be plain language that users recognize, not internal jargon.</statement>
        <rationale>Labels are the primary interface between user intent and content. Jargon labels or generic terms like "Resources" and "Solutions" force users to search rather than browse because they cannot predict what is behind each label.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Navigation: How users move through the information space. Navigation types include global (every page), local (within sections), contextual (related items), utility (account, help), and footer (secondary and legal).</statement>
        <rationale>Different navigation types serve different user intents. Mixing all navigation into a single mega-menu or removing navigation types entirely creates cognitive overload and hidden content.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Search: How users query the information space when browsing fails. Search requires metadata (tags, descriptions) to work well and should be complemented by filters and facets.</statement>
        <rationale>Search is a safety net, not a primary navigation method. When users resort to search, it signals that browsing structure is insufficient. Improve structure first; search optimizations are secondary.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="ia-principles">
      <p>Every information architecture should be evaluated against four principles:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Findability: Users can locate what they need through navigation, search, or context without exceeding three clicks or requiring prior knowledge of taxonomy terms.</statement>
        <rationale>Findability is the core promise of IA. If users cannot find content after clicking three times or searching, the IA has failed. Five-level hierarchies and generic labels fail this test.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Understandability: Labels make sense to users without domain expertise. Labels must be tested with representative users, not assumed to be clear.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams working inside a domain lose perspective on what is obvious and what is jargon. First-click testing with target users reveals assumptions about label clarity.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Scalability: The structure accommodates growth in content volume and new content types without requiring wholesale reorganization.</statement>
        <rationale>Taxonomies built for 50 pages of content often break when reaching 500 pages. Anticipate growth and design flexibility — allow new content to fit into existing categories or establish clear criteria for new top-level categories.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Flexibility: Content can live in multiple contexts — appear in more than one category, belong to multiple tags, or be surfaced in different navigation paths depending on user mental model.</statement>
        <rationale>Rigid tree structures force content into a single parent, creating navigation paths that do not match some users' mental models. Faceted navigation and cross-category tagging reduce this friction.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Org chart navigation — using internal reporting structure (Product, Engineering, Sales, Marketing sections) instead of user mental models (Features, Documentation, Community, Support).</description>
        <reason>Org-chart navigation mirrors how the company is structured, not how users think about the product. Users do not know which internal team owns a feature; they search by feature or task.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Too deep hierarchy — more than 3-4 levels in navigation.</description>
        <reason>Beyond 3 levels, users lose context of where they are and retreat to search. Each level adds a decision point and a chance for wrong turns.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Too many choices — more than 7 items per navigation level (Miller's Law).</description>
        <reason>Humans cannot comfortably hold more than 7 items in working memory while making a choice. Above 7 items, navigation becomes a search task in itself.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Jargon labels — using internal terminology (API Keys, Service Tiers, Webhook Integrations) in public navigation without translation.</description>
        <reason>Users working with the product understand jargon through repeated exposure, but first-time visitors and occasional users will not recognize terms. Test labels with people outside your company.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No testing — assumptions about navigation not validated with users.</description>
        <reason>Even experienced designers misjudge label clarity and category groupings. Card sorting and tree testing reveal mismatches; assumptions should not drive IA.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="ia-artifacts">
      <p>IA work produces several deliverables, each serving a specific purpose at different project stages:</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Sitemap (throughout project): A visual hierarchy showing all pages/sections and how they relate. Used for planning, communication, and coverage checks.</statement>
        <rationale>Sitemaps are the lingua franca between stakeholders. A documented sitemap prevents scope creep and ensures all parties see the same structure.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Taxonomy document (early stage): A living reference of all categories, subcategories, tags, and naming conventions. Governs where new content will be placed.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a taxonomy document, teams will interpret categories differently and add conflicting content types. A documented taxonomy prevents inconsistency at scale.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Navigation specification (mid to late stage): Detailed design of global, local, contextual, and utility navigation, including label text, visual hierarchy, and responsive behavior.</statement>
        <rationale>Navigation design bridges IA (what exists and how it relates) from visual design (how it is presented). Specs prevent designers from inventing navigation patterns that contradict the IA.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Page inventory or content table (mid stage): A spreadsheet or database listing every page/feature with URL, owner, template type, priority, and metadata. Used to track coverage and manage updates.</statement>
        <rationale>Large sites drift into unmaintained content. An inventory with an owner column ensures someone is responsible for each page and makes it visible when content is deprecated but not removed.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Wireframes and mockups (late stage): Layout sketches showing how navigation elements appear in context with content, often annotated with interaction notes.</statement>
        <rationale>Wireframes ground the IA in real layout constraints — a 7-item mega-menu might not fit responsively on mobile. Early wireframe review catches infeasible structures.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/information-architecture-101/"/>
      <link href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/information-architecture-for/0596527349/"/>
      <link href="https://www.howtomakesenseofanymess.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.iainstitute.org/"/>
      <link href="https://www.uxbooth.com/articles/complete-beginners-guide-to-information-architecture/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
