<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ops-customer-success-basics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ops-customer-success-basics. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define exactly one north-star success metric per product before building any CS motion. "Active projects per team &gt;= 3" is a success metric. "Customer engagement" is not.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Multiple success metrics create measurement ambiguity and split CS effort. A single north-star forces clarity about what "successful customer" means and makes health scoring objective.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trigger lifecycle touchpoints on product behavior events, not on fixed calendar days. "Day-7 email" sent when a customer has not yet logged in a single time is noise, not success.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Event-triggered outreach reaches customers when they are in a relevant product context. Calendar-triggered outreach reaches customers regardless of state, producing high unsubscribe rates and trained ignoring.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build the knowledge base before building lifecycle email sequences. Emails should link into existing content; each send must not introduce new content that exists only in the email.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Customers who click an email link and find no supporting content lose trust. The knowledge base is the product-side capability; email is the notification layer. Build in that order.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap automated re-engagement outreach at one message per week per account. An at-risk account must not receive more than three automated re-engagements before the sequence pauses and escalates to human review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Re-engagement spam is the fastest way to convert a disengaged customer into a churned customer who also unsubscribes and leaves a negative review. Automation helps at low volume; at high frequency it accelerates the outcome you are trying to prevent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never let an agent issue refunds, plan downgrades, comp credits, or any billing action autonomously. Human approval is required at every billing touchpoint.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Autonomous billing actions are irreversible, create accounting inconsistencies, and may violate subscription terms or payment processor rules. The cost of a single incorrect autonomous credit exceeds any automation efficiency gain.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agent-written upsell prompts must include the customer's current plan in context before generating the prompt. Never offer a plan the customer is already on.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">An upsell email offering the customer's existing plan reads as broken and damages trust. This is a common failure when agent context does not include current subscription state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Auto-generated case studies require explicit customer approval before publication. Never publish without a recorded approval step in the workflow.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Publishing a customer's name, metrics, or story without consent creates privacy violations, potential NDA breaches, and reputational damage. Approval is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When computing sentiment from support tickets or NPS, always include a confidence score. Route confidence below 0.7 to human review. Sarcasm, code-switching, and short responses make LLM sentiment brittle.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A customer who writes "wow, great job" after a billing error is probably being sarcastic. LLMs score this as positive. False-positive health scores mask real churn risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-calibrate health-score thresholds after every significant product release. Rules built on pre-release behavior patterns fire incorrectly after the product changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A health rule that fires when a customer has not used "feature X" becomes incorrect after feature X is removed or renamed. Stale rules produce wrong alerts and wrong suppressions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ground every automated outreach in a specific customer action: "you created project X 3 days ago and haven't returned" is personalized. "We noticed you haven't been active" is generic noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generic empathy trains customers to ignore automated messages. Specific behavioral grounding demonstrates that the system is paying attention and produces higher response rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Customer event logs contain PII (names, email, behavioral patterns, company data). Apply field-level redaction before sending to external LLM APIs. Aggregate summaries only through cloud endpoints.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Product event logs often contain full user identification alongside sensitive behavioral data. Privacy regulations (GDPR, CCPA) restrict sending this data to third-party processors without specific legal basis.</rationale>
    </rule>
      <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
