<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Customer Success Basics — Framework">
  <summary>Five-stage proactive CS framework: Define, Measure, Engage, Enable, Expand — with event-triggered touchpoints and high-touch vs tech-touch segmentation.</summary>

  <section title="Success definition">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define exactly one north-star success metric per product before building any CS motion. "Active projects per team >= 3" is a success metric. "Customer engagement" is not.</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple success metrics create measurement ambiguity and split CS effort. A single north-star forces clarity about what "successful customer" means and makes health scoring objective.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>SaaS tool: success = using core features; metric = feature adoption rate or DAU/seat</item>
      <item>Online course: success = completing content + implementing learnings; metric = completion rate (target 80%+)</item>
      <item>Service: success = achieving stated outcome; metric = results delivered vs promised</item>
      <item>Membership: success = engaging regularly; metric = engagement score (logins, content consumption)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Touchpoint design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Trigger lifecycle touchpoints on product behavior events, not on fixed calendar days. "Day-7 email" sent when a customer has not yet logged in a single time is noise, not success.</statement>
      <rationale>Event-triggered outreach reaches customers when they are in a relevant product context. Calendar-triggered outreach reaches customers regardless of state, producing high unsubscribe rates and trained ignoring.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>New customer: Day 1 welcome → Day 3 check-in (if no key action) → Day 7 progress → Day 14 feature tip → Day 30 success review</item>
      <item>No login for 7 days: re-engagement email with one specific tip tied to their last action</item>
      <item>No login for 14 days: personal outreach from founder/CSM</item>
      <item>Usage approaching plan limit: proactive upgrade offer with value framing</item>
      <item>First success milestone: celebrate + identify next goal + natural expansion conversation</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Segmentation">
    <list>
      <item>Enterprise (high MRR): high-touch — dedicated success manager, QBRs, custom onboarding</item>
      <item>Mid-market: medium-touch — periodic calls + automation</item>
      <item>SMB: low-touch — mostly automated sequences with human escalation triggers</item>
      <item>Self-serve: tech-touch — fully automated, knowledge base, community</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Enablement before outreach">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build the knowledge base before building lifecycle email sequences. Emails should link into existing content; each send must not introduce new content that exists only in the email.</statement>
      <rationale>Customers who click an email link and find no supporting content lose trust. The knowledge base is the product-side capability; email is the notification layer. Build in that order.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/health-score.py"/>
    <link path="templates/cs-playbook.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
