<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="surveys">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Structured data collection from many users through standardized questions that quantify attitudes, preferences, and experiences enabling statistical confidence and tracking changes over time.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>surveys</tag>
      <tag>questionnaires</tag>
      <tag>quantitative-research</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>nps</tag>
      <tag>sus</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Surveys and Questionnaires</title>
    <summary>Structured data collection from many users through standardized questions that quantify attitudes, preferences, and experiences. Four survey types: satisfaction (CSAT, NPS), task-based (SUS, SEQ), preference (A vs B), and exploratory (usage patterns). Standard metrics require exact question wording and order — any deviation invalidates benchmarking against published norms.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Qualitative research (interviews, diary studies) reveals "why" but cannot generalize to the full user base. Surveys provide statistical confidence and enable tracking changes over time. NPS, SUS, and CSAT are industry-standard benchmarks; using the exact published wording lets you compare your product against 10,000+ published scores. Surveys are also the fastest way to triage: which segments are unhappy, which features matter most.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Validating qualitative findings at scale after interviews or diary studies.</item>
        <item>Tracking standardized UX metrics over time: NPS, CSAT, SUS, SEQ, CES — quarterly cohorts vs baseline.</item>
        <item>Post-task micro-surveys (1-2 questions) embedded in product after key flows.</item>
        <item>Segmenting a large user base: screener surveys to recruit participants for deeper qualitative work.</item>
        <item>Quantifying feature value across the full user base.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>"Why" questions — surveys give "what" and "how much"; interviews give "why".</item>
        <item>Sample below 100 — confidence intervals are too wide; do interviews instead.</item>
        <item>Highly emotional or sensitive topics — social desirability bias dominates self-report.</item>
        <item>Concept testing where artifact context matters — closed questions cannot substitute for showing the design.</item>
        <item>When results cannot drive action — running surveys you will ignore burns respondent trust permanently.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="definition">
      <p>Surveys collect structured data from many users through standardized questions. They quantify user attitudes, preferences, and experiences — answering "what" and "how much" at scale, which qualitative methods cannot do efficiently.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="survey-types">
      <list>
        <item>Satisfaction: measure happiness with the product — CSAT, NPS, CES.</item>
        <item>Task-based: post-task feedback after a specific flow — SUS, SEQ.</item>
        <item>Preference: compare options — A vs B choice.</item>
        <item>Exploratory: understand usage patterns and behaviors at scale.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="when-to-use-vs-not">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use surveys to quantify what you already know qualitatively, or to triage at scale. Do not use them to answer "why" questions — that requires interviews.</statement>
        <rationale>Surveys give statistical confidence but no causal explanation. Using a survey to find out why users churn produces a list of surface symptoms, not root causes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not launch a survey with fewer than 100 expected responses. With smaller samples, confidence intervals are too wide to act on.</statement>
        <rationale>A sample of 30 produces a 95% CI of ±18 percentage points on a proportion. That range is wider than most meaningful differences you are trying to detect.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="process-steps">
      <rule>
        <statement>Place demographics at the end, not the start. Begin with low-effort, high-relevance questions to build respondent investment.</statement>
        <rationale>Opening with demographics signals a corporate census rather than a conversation about the respondent's experience. Completion rates drop by 10-15% when demographics lead.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Step 1: define clear research objective — one primary question the survey must answer.</item>
        <item>Step 2: choose question types (multiple choice, rating scale, ranking, open-ended, matrix).</item>
        <item>Step 3: write questions — one concept per question, neutral wording, exhaustive options.</item>
        <item>Step 4: design flow — intro, screening, easy questions, core questions, demographics, thank you.</item>
        <item>Step 5: pilot test with 5-10 representative users before launch; fix confusion and measure completion time.</item>
        <item>Step 6: analyze — compute response rate, run quantitative statistics, code open-ended themes, segment results.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="lock-standard-wording">
      <rule>
        <statement>Never paraphrase the question wording for NPS, SUS, SEQ, or CES. Use the exact published text, scale anchors, and order. Any deviation invalidates comparison against published benchmarks.</statement>
        <rationale>Standardized UX metrics are benchmarkable because thousands of studies use identical wording. A single word change shifts mean scores by 0.3-1.5 points on a 7-point scale — more than most meaningful product changes you are trying to detect.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="net-promoter-score">
      <rule>
        <statement>NPS question: "How likely are you to recommend [product] to a friend or colleague?" on a 0-10 scale. Score = % Promoters (9-10) minus % Detractors (0-6). Passives (7-8) are excluded.</statement>
        <rationale>NPS range is -100 to +100. Industry average is approximately 32. Above 50 is excellent. Below 0 means more detractors than promoters. Segment before interpreting — overall NPS hides divergent cohort experiences.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Report NPS with confidence interval: "NPS = 42 ± 6 (n=200)" gives stakeholders actionable signal. "NPS = 42" alone creates false precision.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="system-usability-scale">
      <rule>
        <statement>SUS uses 10 specific alternating-polarity questions on a 1-5 Likert scale. Score = (sum of odd-item scores - 5) + (25 - sum of even-item scores), multiplied by 2.5. Range: 0-100. Average: 68. Above 80: excellent.</statement>
        <rationale>SUS is the most-validated usability scale with published benchmarks from 500+ studies. The alternating-polarity design prevents straightlining. Using only some of the 10 questions invalidates the score entirely.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="csat">
      <rule>
        <statement>CSAT question: "How satisfied are you with [X]?" on a 1-5 or 1-7 scale. Score = (count of satisfied responses / total responses) x 100.</statement>
        <rationale>CSAT is task-specific and moment-specific — use it immediately after a specific interaction, not as a general product measure. Delayed CSAT measures recency effects, not the target interaction.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="single-ease-question">
      <rule>
        <statement>SEQ question: "Overall, how easy or difficult was this task?" on a 1-7 scale ("Very difficult" to "Very easy"). Administer immediately after each task in usability testing. Published average: 5.5.</statement>
        <rationale>SEQ is a single-item validated scale for measuring per-task ease. It correlates well with multi-item scales and takes 10 seconds to complete. Use it after every task in usability tests to build a per-task ease profile.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="question-types">
      <list>
        <item>Multiple choice: fixed options — best for frequency, category membership. Analysis: percentages.</item>
        <item>Rating scale: measure intensity (1-5, 1-7, 1-10) — best for satisfaction, ease, confidence. Analysis: mean, median.</item>
        <item>Ranking: prioritization among options — best for feature importance. Analysis: weighted order.</item>
        <item>Open-ended: exploration and verbatim voice — best for "what else?" and discovery. Analysis: thematic coding.</item>
        <item>Matrix: multiple items on the same scale — best for feature comparison. Analysis: per-item mean.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Include at least one open-ended question per survey. Quantitative data tells you what; verbatim responses tell you why in users' own language.</statement>
        <rationale>The highest-value product insights in survey data consistently come from open-text fields. NPS score alone tells you little; the "why" open-text reveals the top promoter driver and top detractor complaint.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="bias-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Check every drafted question for four bias types before launch: leading (suggests an answer), double-barreled (two concepts), vague (undefined terms), and loaded (emotive language). Rewrite any question scoring above 0 on any dimension.</statement>
        <rationale>Question wording dominates survey results. Two well-meaning researchers writing the same survey produce statistically different scores. LLM-drafted questions over-use jargon and double-barreled phrasing — expect to rewrite 30% of agent-generated questions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Double-barreled: asks about two concepts in one question — speed and accuracy.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[BAD: "How satisfied are you with the speed and accuracy of search results?"]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Leading: implies a positive sentiment before asking.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[BAD: "How much do you love our new feature?"]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Vague: undefined referent and undefined frequency.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[BAD: "How often do you use it?"]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Clear, single concept, defined terms, neutral wording.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[GOOD: "How often do you use the search feature?"
- Never
- Less than once a week
- 1-3 times per week
- Daily
- Multiple times per day]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="response-rate-factors">
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep surveys under 5 minutes / 10-15 questions for general audiences; under 2 minutes for in-product micro-surveys. Every additional minute of completion time reduces response rate by 5-10%.</statement>
        <rationale>Long surveys have steep dropout that disproportionately removes casual users who engage least. The resulting sample over-represents power users and unhappy users, making the data unrepresentative.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Length: shorter surveys have higher response rates. Aim for under 5 minutes.</item>
        <item>Incentive: increases response rate but may attract non-target respondents on general panels.</item>
        <item>Timing: mid-week (Tuesday-Thursday), mid-day produces highest response rates.</item>
        <item>Mobile-friendly: many respondents complete on phone — test the survey at 390px viewport.</item>
        <item>Clear purpose: explain why the participant should respond and how results will be used.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agents excel at the operational and analytical bookends. Pre-launch: a research agent drafts the survey from objectives, validates against bias heuristics (leading, double-barreled, vague), assembles standardized scales correctly, and runs a pilot-test simulation. Post-launch: an analysis agent computes per-segment statistics, codes open-ended responses with a fixed taxonomy, runs sentiment + theme analysis, generates the report draft. Humans approve the survey before launch and review the analysis before circulating.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-ux-researcher-agent (drafts questions, designs scales, performs synthesis); faion-market-researcher (from pro/research/market-researcher) (sampling design, weighting, statistical confidence); faion-product-manager (translates results into roadmap signals); faion-conversion-optimizer (designs in-product micro-surveys timed to key moments); faion-data-analyst style subagent (segmentation cuts, cross-tabs, longitudinal tracking).</p>
      <p>Prompt pattern for bias check (run on every drafted question): Question: "{q}" Options: {options} Score for: leading (does it suggest an answer?), double-barreled (two concepts?), vague (undefined terms?), loaded (emotive language?), missing options (exhaustive + mutually exclusive?). Output JSON with score 0-3 per dimension and rewrite_suggestion if any score &gt;0.</p>
      <p>Open-ended coding (apply to each response): Response: "{text}" Taxonomy: {fixed_codes} Assign 1-3 codes from taxonomy. If response is off-topic, code as OFFTOPIC. If new theme not in taxonomy, code as NEW with proposed_label. Return JSON.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Self-report ≠ behavior. NPS predicts loyalty weakly; SUS scores don't correlate strongly with measured task success. Question wording dominates results. Two well-meaning researchers writing the same survey produce statistically different scores. Response bias: power users and angry users over-respond; casual users under-respond. Without weighting, signal skews. LLM-coded open-ended responses cluster aggressively, hiding nuanced minority views. Always sample-check coding manually. Long surveys (&gt;5 min) have steep dropoff; the last questions get fewer, lower-quality answers. Standardized metrics (NPS, SUS) require strict question wording and order; "almost-NPS" is not benchmarkable against industry data.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Lock the question wording for any standardized metric (NPS, SUS, SEQ, CES) — change a word and the benchmark comparison is invalid. Pilot every survey with 5-10 representative users before launch; agents can simulate this with synthetic respondents but a real pilot catches genuine confusion. Keep surveys under 5 minutes / 10-15 questions for general audiences; under 2 minutes for in-product micro-surveys. Demographics at the END, not the start. Start with low-effort, high-relevance questions to build investment. Always include at least one open-ended question — the gold for product insight comes from open-text comments, not Likert means. Report confidence intervals, not just point estimates. "NPS = 42 ± 6" tells stakeholders far more than "NPS = 42". Segment before interpreting — overall scores hide divergent experiences (new vs experienced, plan tier, geo). Run the same survey periodically (quarterly) so you can track movement, not just absolute level.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>LLM-drafted questions over-use jargon and double-barreled phrasing. The bias-check pass is mandatory; expect to rewrite ~30% of LLM-generated questions. LLM coding of open-ended responses converges on majority themes and silences outliers. Always look at the OFFTOPIC/NEW buckets manually — that's where surprises live. Sentiment classification on short product feedback ("works fine") is unreliable; require the LLM to extract specific praise/issue rather than a polarity score. Fake-respondent / bot fraud is common on cheap general panels; require attention checks and validate response patterns (straightlining, suspicious speed). Prompt caching: when coding thousands of open-ended responses, cache the taxonomy + few-shot examples as a system prompt; cuts cost ~80%. Don't let an agent autonomously translate standardized scales to other languages — translated SUS/NPS need formal cross-cultural validation, not LLM translation. Cross-tabs over many segments inflate false positives (multiple-comparisons problem). Apply a Bonferroni or FDR correction before reporting any "significant" segment difference. Privacy: survey responses often contain PII in free text. Redact before sending to a third-party LLM, or run coding on a local model for sensitive populations.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="references">
      <p>Sauro, Jeff &amp; Lewis, James — Quantifying the User Experience (definitive UX-stats reference). Tullis, Tom &amp; Albert, Bill — Measuring the User Experience. Oppenheim, A.N. — Questionnaire Design, Interviewing and Attitude Measurement. Nielsen Norman Group — Qualitative Surveys: https://www.nngroup.com/articles/qualitative-surveys/. MeasuringU — UX metrics &amp; NPS guidance: https://measuringu.com/. SUS reference — System Usability Scale: https://www.usability.gov/how-to-and-tools/methods/system-usability-scale.html. Anthropic — Prompt caching: https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/build-with-claude/prompt-caching</p>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/survey-plan.md" purpose="Survey planning template: objective, audience, sample size, questions with types, success metrics"/>
      <template path="templates/standard-survey.md" purpose="Ready-to-use satisfaction + feature + open-ended survey with NPS, usability, and demographic questions"/>
      <template path="templates/nps-segments.py" purpose="NPS calculation with per-segment cut (pandas); includes open-ended coding hook"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
