<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spec-requirements">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd-planning</domain>
    <summary>Translate plain-language feature requests into traceable SMART requirements, user stories, and Given-When-Then acceptance criteria for spec.md authoring.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>sdd</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>specifications</tag>
      <tag>smart</tag>
      <tag>moscow</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Specification Requirements</title>
    <summary>A structured methodology for translating a plain-language feature request into a traceable set of user personas, INVEST-validated user stories, SMART functional and non-functional requirements (FR-X / NFR-X), and Given-When-Then acceptance criteria (AC-X). Every FR must trace to a user story; every Must FR must have at least one AC. Output is a spec.md that the design phase consumes.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Ambiguous requirements are the single largest source of rework in software projects. SMART criteria make each requirement testable (pass/fail); traceability (FR-X → US-X → AC-X) ensures no requirement is implemented without a verification condition. MoSCoW prioritization enforces scope discipline — without it, every requirement becomes "Must" and MVP never ships.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Starting any non-trivial feature estimated to touch more than one system layer</item>
        <item>Stakeholder has described a need in plain language that needs translation into testable requirements</item>
        <item>Feature scope is ambiguous and "Out of Scope" must be made explicit before design begins</item>
        <item>Multiple user personas are affected and their needs conflict or overlap</item>
        <item>Acceptance criteria will drive automated BDD tests (Gherkin/Given-When-Then)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Bug fix with a clear, agreed-upon fix — spec overhead exceeds value</item>
        <item>Purely internal refactor with no user-facing behavior change</item>
        <item>Spike or proof-of-concept — spec assumes known requirements; spikes discover them</item>
        <item>Design is already finalized and requirements are back-filled without intent to use them</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="smart-requirements">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every FR must satisfy all five SMART criteria: Specific (one interpretation only), Measurable (testable pass/fail), Achievable (technically feasible), Relevant (traces to a user story), Time-bound (MoSCoW priority assigned).</statement>
        <rationale>Ambiguous requirements are the largest source of rework. SMART forces precision at authoring time, not during implementation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use "System SHALL" imperative voice for every FR. Never use "should", "can", "may", or "will".</statement>
        <rationale>"SHALL" is unambiguous in requirements engineering and signals a testable mandatory constraint.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Ban ambiguous words: "fast", "good", "easy", "support", "handle". Replace with quantified targets.</statement>
        <rationale>These words cannot be tested — they produce requirements that pass review but fail verification.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Well-formed FR with SMART criteria">
        <note>FR-001: System SHALL validate email format on registration. Validation SHALL reject any input that does not match RFC 5321. Priority: Must. Traces to: US-001.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Ambiguous FR without SMART criteria">
        <note>FR-001: System should handle email validation properly. — not measurable, no trace, no priority.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="moscow-prioritization">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Assign each FR exactly one MoSCoW priority: Must (cannot launch without), Should (important but not critical), Could (nice to have), Won't (explicitly excluded from this release).</statement>
        <rationale>Without explicit prioritization, every requirement defaults to Must and MVP scope explodes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Must requirements must not exceed 60% of total FR count. If they do, re-classify or split the feature.</statement>
        <rationale>Enforcing this ratio preserves the MVP concept and prevents scope creep disguised as priority.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="traceability">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every FR must reference at least one user story (US-X). Every Must FR must reference at least one acceptance criterion (AC-X).</statement>
        <rationale>Traceability ensures every implemented requirement has a business reason and a verification condition.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use sequential identifiers: FR-001, FR-002; US-001; AC-001. Never use section headings as identifiers.</statement>
        <rationale>IDs are stable references across spec, design, and implementation documents. Headings change; IDs should not.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="given-when-then-acceptance-criteria">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Write every AC in Given-When-Then format with specific values, not generic placeholders. "Given user is on registration page" is acceptable; "Given user enters valid data" is not.</statement>
        <rationale>Specific values make ACs directly executable as BDD tests without interpretation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Cover at minimum: happy path, error handling (validation failure), boundary condition, security scenario (unauthorized access or injection). Performance scenario required for any Must NFR.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents and reviewers systematically skip boundary and security scenarios unless coverage is explicitly mandated.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>AC that reuses the same "Then" clause for multiple scenarios: "Then the user sees a message".</description>
        <reason>Non-unique outcomes cannot be individually verified. Each AC must have a distinct, observable result.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="non-functional-requirements">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every NFR must specify a measurement method, not just a target. "Response time SHALL be &lt; 500ms p95, measured server-side under 1000 concurrent users" is complete; "&lt; 500ms" alone is not.</statement>
        <rationale>A target without a measurement method is unverifiable — performance tests cannot be designed without knowing the conditions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="phase-by-phase-checklist">
      <p>A complete spec requires ten phases from brief to approval:</p>
      <section name="phase-1-smart-problem-analysis">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Before writing any requirement, create a Business Value Statement: [WHO] currently cannot [WHAT] because [WHY]. This results in [IMPACT]. By implementing [SOLUTION], we will [BENEFIT].</statement>
          <rationale>Agents and reviewers need the "why" anchor before requirements; without it, Achievable and Relevant criteria cannot be validated.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Specific: identify exactly which persona has which problem</item>
          <item>Measurable: define the success metric (not "feels good" — a number)</item>
          <item>Achievable: confirm technical feasibility before writing the requirement</item>
          <item>Relevant: link to an actual business goal, not a nice-to-have</item>
          <item>Time-bound: assign a MoSCoW priority before moving to user stories</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-2-user-personas">
        <list>
          <item>Create minimum 2 distinct personas (name, role, goal, pain points, context)</item>
          <item>Personas must differ — not duplicates with different names</item>
          <item>Include when/where they use the product (device, environment)</item>
          <item>Personas must be specific enough to make design decisions from</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-3-user-story-mapping">
        <list>
          <item>Identify high-level user activities (e.g., "Manage Account")</item>
          <item>Create backbone: main actions under each activity</item>
          <item>Map walking skeleton: MVP stories under each backbone item</item>
          <item>Map phase-2 stories separately from MVP — show swimlane boundaries</item>
          <item>Verify MVP is independently launchable without phase-2 stories</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-4-user-stories-invest">
        <list>
          <item>Format: "As a [persona], I want [action], so that [benefit]" — never omit the benefit clause</item>
          <item>Independent: can be delivered without requiring another story in the same sprint</item>
          <item>Negotiable: implementation details can be discussed, goal is fixed</item>
          <item>Valuable: delivers measurable user or business value on its own</item>
          <item>Estimable: team can size it — if not, split further</item>
          <item>Small: fits one iteration; if not, split</item>
          <item>Testable: at least one AC can be written for it</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-5-use-cases-complex-features-only">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Write use cases only for multi-step workflows with multiple actors or complex branching. Single-actor, linear flows do not need a use case — a user story with AC is sufficient.</statement>
          <rationale>Use case overhead on simple features adds documentation burden without improving clarity.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Primary actor, preconditions, main flow (numbered), alternative flows (3a, 4a format), postconditions</item>
          <item>Alternative flows must cover validation errors and edge cases</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-6-functional-requirements">
        <list>
          <item>One requirement per FR-X — no compound requirements ("X and Y")</item>
          <item>"System SHALL" imperative; no ambiguous words</item>
          <item>Include validation rules if input constraints exist</item>
          <item>Trace to US-X in the FR body</item>
          <item>Assign MoSCoW priority; Must must not exceed 60% of FR count</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-7-non-functional-requirements">
        <list>
          <item>Performance: response time with percentile and load conditions</item>
          <item>Scalability: concurrent user or throughput ceiling</item>
          <item>Security: auth mechanism, encryption standard, compliance (GDPR, etc.)</item>
          <item>Availability: uptime SLA with RTO/RPO</item>
          <item>Accessibility: WCAG level if user-facing</item>
          <item>Each NFR: specific target + measurement method + priority</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-8-acceptance-criteria">
        <list>
          <item>Given-When-Then with specific values (email "test@example.com", not "valid email")</item>
          <item>AC-001: happy path</item>
          <item>AC-002: validation error</item>
          <item>AC-003: boundary condition</item>
          <item>AC-004: security scenario (unauthorized access)</item>
          <item>AC-005: performance scenario (if Must NFR applies)</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-9-scope-definition">
        <list>
          <item>In Scope: explicit list of what IS included</item>
          <item>Out of Scope: explicit list with reason and timeline for each item</item>
          <item>"Not in this release" without a reason is not sufficient — add "Phase 2", "Never", or "v2.0"</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-10-assumptions-and-constraints">
        <list>
          <item>Document assumptions about user behavior, system state, external services</item>
          <item>Technical constraints: file size limits, API rate limits, browser support</item>
          <item>Business constraints: budget, timeline, integration dependencies</item>
          <item>Validate assumptions with stakeholders before signing off spec</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="concrete-examples">
      <section name="user-persona-example">
        <example type="good" title="Well-formed persona">
          <note>Persona: Freelance Developer "Alex". Role: Solo developer building SaaS products. Goal: Ship MVPs in weeks without managing auth/payments/infra. Pain Points: Too much time on boilerplate. Context: Works from home on macOS, deploys to Vercel, uses GitHub daily.</note>
        </example>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Persona: "Power User" — goal: "use the product effectively".</description>
          <reason>No role, no pain points, no context. Cannot guide any design decision.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
      <section name="user-story-examples">
        <example type="good" title="Well-formed user story">
          <note>US-001: As a freelance developer (Alex), I want to create an account with my email, so that I can save API keys and project settings between sessions. Priority: Must (MVP). INVEST: Independent — no other story required; Testable — AC-001 exists.</note>
        </example>
        <antipattern>
          <description>As a user, I want to log in, so that I can use the site.</description>
          <reason>No persona specificity, no measurable benefit clause. Cannot validate INVEST criteria.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
      <section name="functional-requirement-examples">
        <example type="good" title="Well-formed FR">
          <note>FR-001: System SHALL allow users to register with email and password. Email SHALL match RFC 5321 format. Password SHALL be minimum 8 characters with at least 1 uppercase letter and 1 digit. Traces to: US-001. AC: AC-001, AC-002. Priority: Must.</note>
        </example>
        <antipattern>
          <description>FR-001: System should validate user input properly.</description>
          <reason>"Should" is not mandatory, "properly" is ambiguous, no validation rules, no trace, no AC reference.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
      <section name="non-functional-requirement-examples">
        <example type="good" title="Well-formed NFR">
          <note>NFR-001: Login response time SHALL be less than 500ms at p95, measured server-side (excluding network latency) under a load of 1000 concurrent users. Validation: load test with k6. Priority: Must.</note>
        </example>
        <antipattern>
          <description>NFR-001: System should be fast and responsive.</description>
          <reason>No quantified target, no measurement conditions, not testable.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
      <section name="acceptance-criteria-examples">
        <example type="good" title="Happy path AC">
          <note>AC-001 (Happy Path): Given user is on /register, And email "test@example.com" is not in the system, When user enters email "test@example.com" and password "SecurePass1!", And clicks Register, Then account is created in the database, And user receives a verification email within 30 seconds, And user is redirected to /dashboard.</note>
        </example>
        <example type="good" title="Error handling AC">
          <note>AC-002 (Error): Given user is on /register, When user submits password "weak", Then a validation error "Password must be at least 8 characters with 1 uppercase and 1 digit" is displayed inline, And no account is created.</note>
        </example>
        <antipattern>
          <description>AC-001: When user submits valid data, then the system responds correctly.</description>
          <reason>"Valid data" and "responds correctly" are placeholders. Cannot be executed as an automated test.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
      <section name="scope-definition-examples">
        <example type="good" title="Well-formed out-of-scope">
          <note>Out of Scope: Social login (Google, GitHub) — Phase 2, post-MVP. Reason: OAuth provider complexity. Two-factor authentication — Phase 3. Reason: Added complexity vs. MVP value. SSO/SAML — Not planned. Reason: Enterprise-only requirement, not current market.</note>
        </example>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Out of Scope: Advanced features.</description>
          <reason>Does not name specific features. Scope creep prevention requires explicit item enumeration with reasoning.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
      <section name="common-mistakes">
        <antipattern>
          <description>Writing spec.md after design.md is already complete.</description>
          <reason>Back-filled requirements are never used for design decisions; traceability is fictional, not functional.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Spec over 500 lines.</description>
          <reason>Feature scope is too broad. Split into sub-features; large specs fragment agent context and human review.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>All requirements classified as "Must".</description>
          <reason>Violates 60% Must cap. Forces MVP scope inflation. Re-classify ruthlessly.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-integration-workflow">
      <p>A planning subagent reads a product brief or feature request, extracts personas, writes user stories with INVEST validation, produces FR-X requirements with MoSCoW classification, and generates AC-X acceptance criteria in Given-When-Then format. The output spec.md is reviewed by a human and approved before the design phase starts. The faion-sdd-executor-agent later uses FR-X → AC-X traceability to validate that each implementation task satisfies its requirement.</p>
      <section name="recommended-subagents">
        <list>
          <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — reads spec.md during task execution to verify AC-X criteria are met</item>
          <item>Planning subagent (claude-opus-4-7) — full spec authoring from brief; needs multi-step reasoning for persona+story+AC chain</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="prompt-pattern">
        <example type="good" title="Spec authoring prompt">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Given the following feature brief: {brief}
1. Define 2 user personas (name, role, goal, pain points).
2. Write user stories in "As a [persona], I want [action], so that [benefit]" format.
   Validate each against INVEST criteria — flag any that fail.
3. Write FR-X functional requirements using "System SHALL..." format.
   MoSCoW: Must ≤ 60% of scope. Each FR traces to a user story.
4. Write NFR-X for performance, security, availability.
5. Write AC-X acceptance criteria in Given-When-Then for each Must FR.
   Cover: happy path, error handling, boundary conditions.
6. Define In Scope and Out of Scope sections explicitly.
Output: spec.md following the template in templates.md.]]></code>
        </example>
        <example type="good" title="Traceability review prompt">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Review spec.md. For each FR-X check:
- Does it trace to a user story?
- Is the requirement testable (pass/fail possible)?
- Is there a corresponding AC-X?
Output a traceability matrix: FR-X | US-X | AC-X | Testable | Missing.]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section name="cli-tools">
        <list>
          <item>cucumber — Execute Given-When-Then acceptance criteria as automated tests. Install: gem install cucumber. Docs: https://cucumber.io</item>
          <item>behave — Python BDD framework for AC-X execution. Install: pip install behave. Docs: https://behave.readthedocs.io</item>
          <item>reqif-tool — Import/export requirements in ReqIF standard format. Docs: https://github.com/strictdoc-project/strictdoc</item>
          <item>strictdoc — Requirements management + traceability in Markdown/RST. Install: pip install strictdoc. Docs: https://strictdoc.readthedocs.io</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="services-and-apps">
        <list>
          <item>Linear (SaaS, Agent-friendly) — FR-X as Issues with custom fields; AC-X as checklists. REST + GraphQL API.</item>
          <item>GitHub Issues (SaaS, Agent-friendly) — Lightweight; FR-X as issues with acceptance-criteria label. GraphQL API.</item>
          <item>Notion (SaaS, Agent-friendly) — Good for rich spec docs with linked databases for traceability. REST API.</item>
          <item>Confluence (SaaS, Partial) — Common in enterprise; agents can write via API. REST API.</item>
          <item>Coda (SaaS, Agent-friendly) — Table-based traceability matrices work well. REST API.</item>
          <item>StrictDoc (OSS, Agent-friendly) — Markdown-native requirements with auto-generated traceability. File-based.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Write the Business Value Statement before any requirements — agents and reviewers need the "why" anchor</item>
        <item>Use FR-X IDs from the first line; never use section headings as requirement identifiers</item>
        <item>Every FR must have at least one AC; agent output without AC is incomplete spec</item>
        <item>Out of Scope must list specific features with reasons — "not in this release" without a reason is not sufficient</item>
        <item>Keep spec.md under 500 lines; if larger, the feature scope is too broad — split into sub-features</item>
        <item>Run through the coverage checklist (happy path, error handling, boundaries, security, performance) for every Must FR</item>
        <item>Never start design.md until spec.md has human sign-off — design locked to unsigned spec wastes effort</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Agents omit "Relevant" and "Time-bound" from SMART criteria unless both are explicitly in the prompt</item>
        <item>Given-When-Then output often reuses the same "Then" clause for multiple scenarios — require unique, specific outcomes</item>
        <item>Agents will write acceptance criteria that are not actually testable ("system should feel fast") — require quantitative values for all NFRs</item>
        <item>Security scenarios (injection, auth bypass) are systematically skipped unless the coverage checklist is in the prompt</item>
        <item>Spec-to-design handoff is a human checkpoint; agents must not begin design.md until spec is approved</item>
        <item>Large specs (>300 lines) fragment agent context — pass only relevant FR-X sections to design subagent</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://cucumber.io/docs/bdd/"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/business-analysis-certifications/babok/"/>
      <link href="https://www.agilebusiness.org/page/ProjectFramework_10_MoSCoWPrioritisation"/>
      <link href="https://strictdoc.readthedocs.io"/>
      <link href="https://www.projectsmart.co.uk/brief-history-of-smart-goals.php"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
