<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-antipatterns" title="Consistency and Standards — Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Concrete failure modes: inconsistent terminology, button order reversals, design drift, and platform violations.</summary>

  <section title="Inconsistent Terminology">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using different labels for the same action on different pages: Page 1 shows [Save], Page 2 shows [Submit], Page 3 shows [Done] — all performing the same save operation.</description>
      <reason>Users encountering different labels assume different behavior. "Submit" implies a one-way action; "Save" implies editability. The mismatch creates incorrect expectations and hesitation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Inconsistent Layout">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Button order reversed between screens: Page 1 shows [Cancel] [Save]; Page 2 shows [Save] [Cancel].</description>
      <reason>Users develop muscle memory for button position. Reversing order causes users to click the wrong button by habit, leading to accidental cancellations or confirmations.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Design Drift">
    <antipattern>
      <description>New features are designed without referencing the design system, introducing new button variants, spacing values, or color usage that conflict with established standards.</description>
      <reason>Each exception becomes precedent for the next designer who sees it. Drift compounds: after 6 months, audits find 8 button variants where 2 were defined. Prevention requires design system reference in every feature kickoff.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Platform Convention Violations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using non-standard icons for common actions (hamburger menu as search, magnifying glass as settings) or placing navigation in unexpected positions (bottom nav on desktop, top nav on mobile).</description>
      <reason>Platform conventions represent learned behavior across millions of app interactions. Violating them forces users to explicitly learn your deviation, which most will not do — they will simply fail to find the feature.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="No Design System">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Each page or feature is designed independently without a shared component library or token system.</description>
      <reason>Without a source of truth, consistency degrades in proportion to team size and velocity. At 3 designers and 6-month tenure, the product will have measurably different typography, spacing, and component styling per feature.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Good Examples for Reference">
    <example type="good">
      <note>iOS: Back button always top-left, swipe from edge to go back, pull to refresh, tab bar at bottom. These conventions are so reliable that deviating from any of them generates App Store reviews specifically calling out the inconsistency.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Google products share search pattern, account menu, iconography across Gmail, Drive, Calendar, and Maps — users transfer knowledge between products without relearning.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
