<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="risk-register">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Structured log of threats and opportunities, each scored by probability x impact, assigned response strategy and owner with observable triggers. Every Accept requires contingency.</summary>
    <category>uncertainty</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>risk-register</tag>
      <tag>scoring</tag>
      <tag>contingency</tag>
      <tag>monitoring</tag>
      <tag>opportunities</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="risk-management"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Risk Register</title>

    <summary>A structured log of identified threats and opportunities, each scored by probability x impact (1-25 scale), assigned a response strategy (Avoid/Transfer/Mitigate/Accept for threats; Exploit/Share/Enhance/Accept for opportunities), and owned by a named individual. Every Accept entry requires a contingency plan or amount. The register is a living artefact: reviewed weekly, updated on new signals, closed when risks pass or materialise.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Unmanaged risks derail projects through surprise: scramble mode erodes stakeholder confidence and recovery is reactive. A scored register converts vague worry into trackable work items, forces explicit ownership, and surfaces near-certain high-impact risks before they hit. Risk-driven contingency (sum of probability x cost-exposure per open risk) beats flat 15% reserves because it calibrates to actual exposure.</p>
      <p>Probability and impact are notoriously biased; LLMs anchor on the user's framing and produce overconfident scores. A 5x5 matrix gives a false sense of precision — risk score 12 vs 15 is mostly noise, but it drives prioritisation. "Accept" is over-used by both humans and agents to clear the register without doing real work. Static registers go stale fast; the methodology ages well only with weekly review. Positive risks (opportunities) are routinely dropped; agents focus on threats by default. Triggers and leading indicators are vague; agents need concrete sensors.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Standing up the uncertainty domain at project kickoff</item>
        <item>Weekly risk review cycles (diffing register against issue tracker and schedule)</item>
        <item>Pre-gate and steering-committee snapshots (top-N risks with response status)</item>
        <item>Vendor/supplier onboarding (category=External, contract clauses as triggers)</item>
        <item>Any milestone where "what could kill this?" deserves a written answer</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure-Scrum teams already tracking risks as backlog impediments — duplicate tracking splits attention</item>
        <item>Tasks under 1 week with a single owner — a standup question suffices</item>
        <item>Pre-discovery R&amp;D where uncertainty is the work — use a learning log instead</item>
        <item>Risks already covered by a separate risk system (GDPR, security) — avoid reinventing</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="identification">
      <p>Brainstorm threats and opportunities across four categories: Technical (technology failures, complexity), External (vendor delays, regulation), Organizational (resource loss, priority shifts), Project Management (poor estimates, scope creep). Techniques: team brainstorming, expert interviews, checklist review, historical project analysis.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="probability-scale">
      <list>
        <item>Very Low — rare, less than 10%</item>
        <item>Low — unlikely, 10-30%</item>
        <item>Medium — possible, 30-50%</item>
        <item>High — likely, 50-70%</item>
        <item>Very High — almost certain, greater than 70%</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="impact-scale">
      <list>
        <item>Very Low — less than 5% budget or schedule effect</item>
        <item>Low — 5-10% effect</item>
        <item>Medium — 10-20% effect</item>
        <item>High — 20-40% effect</item>
        <item>Very High — greater than 40% or project failure</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="scoring">
      <p>Risk Score = Probability level (1-5) x Impact level (1-5). Priority: 15-25 = High (immediate action); 8-14 = Medium (monitor closely); 1-7 = Low (periodic review).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="threat-response-strategies">
      <list>
        <item>Avoid — eliminate the threat by changing approach or removing the risky element</item>
        <item>Transfer — shift to a third party via insurance, outsourcing, or contractual clauses</item>
        <item>Mitigate — reduce probability or impact (prototype first, add testing, cross-train)</item>
        <item>Accept — acknowledge and plan contingency; requires contingency_amount or contingency_plan</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="opportunity-response-strategies">
      <list>
        <item>Exploit — ensure the opportunity occurs (assign best resources, accelerate)</item>
        <item>Share — partner with another party to capture the benefit</item>
        <item>Enhance — increase probability or impact (more marketing, better timing)</item>
        <item>Accept — take the benefit if it occurs; no special action required</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ownership-and-monitoring">
      <p>Every risk has exactly one named owner responsible for: monitoring triggers, executing the response if the trigger fires, and updating status. Review weekly: add new risks, update P/I as situation changes, close resolved risks, track response effectiveness. Top-5 risks appear at every steering committee.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="concrete-rules">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every risk must have exactly one named individual as owner; "the team" is not valid.</statement>
        <rationale>Risks without a single owner are observed, not managed. Accountability requires a name.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every trigger must be an observable signal — a metric, log event, or date — not a subjective phrase like "if it gets bad".</statement>
        <rationale>Unobservable triggers cannot be monitored; risks activate without warning.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every Accept strategy entry must include a contingency_amount or contingency_plan field; Accept without contingency is invalid.</statement>
        <rationale>Accept without a contingency is denial dressed as a strategy. When the risk materialises there is no prepared response.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Risk score must equal probability_level x impact_level; stored score must match computed value or the register is invalid.</statement>
        <rationale>Score integrity is required for heatmap accuracy and prioritisation correctness.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Include at least one opportunity (positive risk) for every ten threats; reject registers that contain only threats.</statement>
        <rationale>Sponsor approval rates rise when upside is made visible. LLMs drop opportunities by default.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Calibrate the impact scale with a project-specific reference point (e.g. "High impact = greater than $50k or greater than 1 month delay") before scoring.</statement>
        <rationale>Uncalibrated scales produce inconsistent scores across assessors and over time.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Risk-driven contingency (sum of probability x cost_impact per open risk) must replace flat-percentage reserves for any project with an active risk register.</statement>
        <rationale>Flat reserves systematically over- or under-fund based on risk profile; risk-driven calculation calibrates to actual exposure.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Identifying risks once at kickoff and never updating the register.</description>
        <reason>Static registers go stale within weeks; new risks appear continuously and scored risks change as context evolves.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using "Communication breakdown" as a risk in every register.</description>
        <reason>Generic risks from LLM defaults are not project-specific; they add noise and dilute the register's signal.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Scoring more than 70% of risks as Medium/Medium (3/3).</description>
        <reason>Uniform scores indicate anchoring bias; force a roughly normal distribution across the 5x5 matrix.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="software-project-threat-register">
      <example type="good" title="Five scored threats with response strategies">
        <note>Each has a concrete trigger and named owner role.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| ID   | Risk                        | Cat   | P | I | Score | Strategy | Response                         | Owner  |
|------|-----------------------------|-------|---|---|-------|----------|----------------------------------|--------|
| R-01 | Key developer leaves        | Org   | M | H | 12    | Mitigate | Document code, cross-train       | PM     |
| R-02 | Third-party API deprecated  | Ext   | L | VH| 10    | Accept   | Abstraction layer; monitor feeds | ArchLd |
| R-03 | Scope creep from sponsor    | PM    | H | M | 12    | Avoid    | Change control process enforced  | PM     |
| R-04 | Performance under load      | Tech  | M | M | 9     | Mitigate | Load testing at sprint 3         | QA Ld  |
| R-05 | Budget cut mid-project      | Org   | L | H | 8     | Accept   | Identify optional features list  | PM     |
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="opportunity-register">
      <example type="good" title="Positive risks with Exploit/Enhance strategies">
        <note>Often omitted by default — include at least 1 per 10 threats.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| ID   | Opportunity             | P | I | Score | Strategy | Response                    |
|------|-------------------------|---|---|-------|----------|-----------------------------|
| O-01 | Early delivery possible | M | H | 12    | Enhance  | Fast-track critical path    |
| O-02 | Partnership offer       | L | VH| 10    | Exploit  | Prioritise integration work |
| O-03 | Positive press coverage | M | M | 9     | Share    | Prepare press kit in advance|
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Two-phase. Phase 1: a risk-identifier reads the project context (charter, WBS, stakeholder register, recent incidents) and brainstorms candidate risks in each PMBoK category, with explicit triggers and owners. Phase 2: a risk-scorer assigns probability × impact with rationale and proposes a strategy + response plan. Human review between phases. Weekly the agent diffs telemetry against the register and emits a CHANGES file (new risks, escalations, closures).</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: risk-identifier (define inline) — input: project artefacts; output: candidate risks YAML. risk-scorer (define inline) — input: candidate risks; output: scored risks with strategy + response. risk-monitor (define inline) — input: live register + telemetry feeds; output: CHANGES.md with deltas. faion-brainstorm — for the initial threat/opportunity list when context is thin. faion-sdd-executor — once a mitigation becomes a code task, drives implementation through quality gates.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-pattern">
      <example type="good" title="Structured output schema for risk-scorer">
        <note>Enforces constraints LLMs violate by default.</note>
        <code lang="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "id": "R-XX",
  "title": "...",
  "category": "Technical|External|Organizational|PM",
  "probability": "VL|L|M|H|VH",
  "impact": "VL|L|M|H|VH",
  "score": 12,
  "strategy": "Avoid|Transfer|Mitigate|Accept|Exploit|Share|Enhance",
  "response_plan": "imperative sentence",
  "trigger": "concrete observable signal",
  "owner": "name or UNASSIGNED",
  "is_opportunity": false,
  "contingency_plan": "required if strategy=Accept",
  "rationale": "2 sentences max"
}
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Every risk has exactly one named owner; never "the team".</item>
        <item>Triggers must be observable (metric, log event, date); reject "if it gets bad".</item>
        <item>Calibrate P/I scales with at least one historical reference: e.g. "H impact = &gt; $50k or &gt; 1 month delay".</item>
        <item>Risk-driven contingency: sum (P × I × cost) for open risks; beats flat 15% reserve.</item>
        <item>Weekly review is a ritual, not optional; missed weeks → register goes stale.</item>
        <item>Track top-5 risks at every steering committee; if the same five appear month after month, the responses are not working.</item>
        <item>Capture opportunities (positive risks) — sponsor approval rates rise when you show upside.</item>
        <item>For agile teams, surface high-score risks into the sprint backlog as risk-mitigation stories.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs love brainstorming risks but score them all "Medium / Medium" — force a normal-ish distribution and reject outputs where greater than 70% are M/M.</item>
        <item>"Communication breakdown" appears in 90% of LLM-generated registers — treat as a smell and replace with project-specific risks.</item>
        <item>Agents drop opportunities; require a positive-risk quota.</item>
        <item>Triggers default to "if it happens" — strip and require concrete signals.</item>
        <item>Currency / units missing on impact ("major" with no $ or days); force a quantitative_impact field.</item>
        <item>"Accept" gets used as a junk drawer; require contingency on every Accept.</item>
        <item>LLMs invent risk-management ISO codes; verify any cited standard.</item>
        <item>For very large registers (greater than 50 risks), context windows truncate — chunk by category and stitch.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/risk-register.md" purpose="Register table (ID, description, category, P, I, score, strategy, response, owner, status)"/>
      <template path="templates/risk-card.md" purpose="Single risk deep-dive card with trigger, contingency, and ownership fields"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/validate-register.py" purpose="Validate risk YAML: score integrity, Accept+contingency rule, heatmap output"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards/risk"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards/pmbok"/>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/iso-31000-risk-management.html"/>
      <link href="https://www.coso.org/"/>
      <link href="https://www.risk-doctor.com/"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/mikefarah/yq"/>
      <link href="https://stedolan.github.io/jq/"/>
      <link href="https://pandoc.org/"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/mermaid-js/mermaid-cli"/>
      <ref slug="risk-management"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
