<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Service Blueprint Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules that distinguish a service blueprint from a glossy diagram. A blueprint that fails any rule is a journey map in disguise.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-five-swimlanes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The blueprint MUST contain exactly five swimlanes in this order: (1) Customer Actions, (2) Frontstage Interactions, (3) Line of Visibility, (4) Backstage Actions, (5) Support Processes &amp; Systems. The "Line of Visibility" is a horizontal divider, not a free row; what is BELOW it is invisible to the customer. Missing or merged lanes = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">The line of visibility is the entire point of the blueprint — it isolates "what the user sees" from "what causes the user's experience." Without it, the artefact regresses to a journey map.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-systems-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Support Processes &amp; Systems lane MUST name specific internal systems (e.g. Salesforce, Zendesk, Stripe Billing, Snowflake) per journey step — not generic labels ("CRM", "billing"). Unnamed systems = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Generic labels don't help engineering or ops. Naming the real system surfaces "we need a Zendesk macro" vs "we need a Salesforce integration" — different teams, different work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-failure-point-notation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every observed friction point on the journey lane MUST trace a "failure arrow" downward through the Line of Visibility to the specific backstage step or system that caused it. Friction points without a downward causal trace = REJECT — that's the gap this methodology exists to close.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">"User got frustrated at billing" is useless to ops; "user got frustrated because the Stripe dunning email sends 7 days before the support team gets notified" is fixable. The arrow IS the fix-target.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-moments-of-truth-scored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The blueprint MUST tag ≥ 3 "moments of truth" (high-impact steps that determine satisfaction/churn) with: impact score (1-5), evidence source (interviews / NPS / support tickets / churn analysis), and a hypothesised root cause. Unscored MoTs = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">A flat blueprint suggests all steps matter equally; in reality 3-5 moments dominate. Scoring forces prioritization, which is the only way the blueprint produces a backlog.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-backstage-actor-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every backstage action MUST name the role/team that performs it (Support Agent / Onboarding Specialist / Fulfilment Op / Finance Ops / SRE). "The team does X" = REJECT. Roles can be plural (e.g. "Tier-1 Support") but cannot be company-wide ("we").</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Vague backstage actors hide work; once the role is named you can ask whether that role has the tools/training/SLA to do it well. RACI inputs to design changes follow directly.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example title="Worked friction trace">
      <text>step: "user contacts support about billing discrepancy"  customer_action: opens chat widget  frontstage: support agent receives ticket in Zendesk (T+0)  line_of_visibility: ─────────  backstage_action: agent attempts to verify invoice (T+2min)  support_system: Zendesk macro queries Salesforce; Salesforce DOES NOT carry Stripe invoice line-items → agent must open Stripe dashboard (T+5min)  MoT_score: 5/5 (interview evidence: 6/10 churned users cite this step)  root_cause: Stripe→Salesforce data sync missing; design backlog item: SAL-INVOICE-LINES-IMPORT</text>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../researcher/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../jtbd-switch-interview/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
