<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Outcome-Based Pricing Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every outcome-based price computation must satisfy. These prevent the two failure modes that kill outcome pricing in agency engagements: defensibility under questioning and accepting a too-low price live in the call.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-prospects-own-number" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Outcome value MUST come from the prospect's own estimate (their current revenue baseline, their stated cost, their named churn rate). When the prospect refuses to share a number, the engagement is priced as time-and-materials, not outcome-based. Industry benchmarks are used only as a sanity check on the prospect's number, never as the primary input.</statement>
      <rationale source="Blair Enns Pricing Creativity; observed loss reasons in agency pricing">A price built from industry-benchmark numbers cannot be defended in the call ("we average X% lift across the industry, so your value is Y") because the prospect can always argue they are atypical. A price built from the prospect's own number reframes the conversation: the agency is helping the prospect capture a slice of value the prospect has already conceded exists.</rationale>
      <example type="good" title="Prospect-anchored outcome value">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Discovery quote: "Our cart abandonment is 71%, AOV $87, we get about
12,000 sessions/month. Industry benchmark on cart abandonment is 70%."

Outcome dimension: revenue recovered from reduced cart abandonment.
Baseline (their number): monthly revenue at 29% checkout completion = ~$303k/mo.
Target lift (conservative): 71% → 58% abandonment = ~$135k/mo additional.
Outcome value (annual): ~$1.62M, prospect-stated metrics.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-confidence-honest-not-ego" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Confidence is rated 1-5 based on portfolio evidence: 5 requires ≥ 3 comparable past engagements with outcomes within ±30% of the proposed target; 3 requires 1 comparable engagement; 1 means no portfolio evidence. Confidence cannot be promoted on the strength of conviction; only past delivered outcomes count.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tetlock superforecasting research; calibration in expert estimation">Founders consistently overestimate confidence when they want the deal. A portfolio-anchored rule removes the freedom to do this. Confidence directly multiplies the price: a 2-point confidence over-estimate inflates the asking price by 30-50%, which is the single most common cause of prospects walking from a value-based proposal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-capture-rate-banded-by-context" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capture rate sits in a banded range: 5-10% for speculative outcomes (long horizon, multi-cause attribution), 10-15% for measurable but non-guaranteed (medium horizon, clean attribution), 15-25% for measurable with success-fee or guarantee. The band is selected from the rules, not from optimism. Going above the band requires either a written guarantee with skin-in-the-game or a documented past capture rate at that level.</statement>
      <rationale source="agency pricing benchmarks; consulting margin analysis">Capture-rate is the single biggest lever — moving from 10% to 20% doubles the price. Banding prevents the temptation to push the rate up after the prospect indicates budget headroom. The discipline trades short-term margin for long-term win-rate stability.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-floor-before-call" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Compute the engagement floor BEFORE the sales call. Floor includes: direct delivery cost (engineer-weeks × loaded rate), 25% opportunity-cost premium, and minimum margin (typically 30-40%). The floor is committed-to in writing before the call so the founder cannot drift below it under live negotiation pressure.</statement>
      <rationale source="negotiation research on anchoring; agency win-rate analysis">Live negotiation systematically pushes founders below their actual floor — the desire to close the deal in the room overrides numerical discipline. Pre-committed floors are the single most effective protection against accepting bad deals; the founder simply walks at the floor.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-discount-ladder-with-tradeoffs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define a 3-step discount ladder from asking price down to floor, where each step trades away something concrete: scope, payment terms, exclusivity, success-fee structure. No step is a pure price cut. The ladder is the founder's negotiation script.</statement>
      <rationale source="Voss Never Split the Difference; B2B sales pattern research">A pure-price-cut ladder trains the prospect to keep asking for more cuts. A trade-based ladder reframes each concession as the prospect choosing between price and scope, which puts the decision back on them and stops the cut-cycle.</rationale>
      <example type="good" title="Trade-based discount ladder">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Asking: $48k for 8-week engagement, weekly retros, white-glove handoff.

Step 1: $42k — drop weekly retros, keep biweekly. Save 4 hours of my time.
Step 2: $36k — handoff becomes self-serve docs (no walkthrough). Save 6 hours.
Step 3: $30k (floor) — engagement length stays, but scope drops 2 deliverables;
        any added work is at standard hourly rate. This is my published floor.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Computation formula">
    <list>
      <item>asking_price = prospect_outcome_value * confidence_multiplier * capture_rate</item>
      <item>confidence_multiplier: 5=1.0, 4=0.85, 3=0.70, 2=0.55, 1=0.40</item>
      <item>floor = direct_cost * 1.25 (opportunity premium) * (1 + minimum_margin)</item>
      <item>asking_price MUST be at least 1.6x the floor; if it is below, decline or revise inputs</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
