<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Outcome-Based Pricing Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six failure modes that defeat outcome-based pricing in agency engagements. Each has a detector and a repair.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="high">
      <description>Anchor from thin air — outcome value is derived from generic industry benchmarks without a prospect-stated baseline, so the prospect can argue every assumption away in the call.</description>
      <detector>outcome.prospect_stated_baseline lacks a verbatim quote OR baseline value not present in discovery notes</detector>
      <repair>Defer the proposal. Schedule a 20-minute discovery follow-up to capture the prospect's own baseline (revenue, CAC, churn, traffic). If the prospect refuses to share, drop to time-and-materials pricing — outcome-based is not viable without the prospect's number.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="high">
      <description>Ego confidence — founder rates confidence 4 or 5 because they want the deal, not because of portfolio evidence.</description>
      <detector>confidence.score &gt;= 4 AND portfolio_evidence has fewer than 3 comparable case studies OR comparable case studies' outcomes deviate from the proposed target by &gt; 30%</detector>
      <repair>Force-downgrade confidence to the level supported by evidence. Recompute asking_price; the recomputed price is what the prospect actually deserves. If the new price is below floor × 1.6, decline or re-scope.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="high">
      <description>Capture-rate greed — founder pushes capture rate above the band (e.g. 25% on a speculative outcome with no guarantee) on the theory that the prospect has budget headroom.</description>
      <detector>capture.rate &gt; 0.15 AND capture.band = speculative OR capture.rate &gt; 0.25 unconditionally</detector>
      <repair>Reset capture rate to the band's upper limit. If the founder wants the higher rate, restructure the contract to include a written success-fee or guarantee that justifies it; the capture rate is then defensible.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="high">
      <description>No pre-committed floor — founder enters the call without a written floor, accepts a price below cost-plus-opportunity-premium under live negotiation pressure.</description>
      <detector>floor.committed_value_usd missing OR floor.committed_value_usd timestamp is after the proposal call</detector>
      <repair>Reject the deal. The floor must exist BEFORE the call. Founder runs the floor computation, documents it, and either (a) walks the deal at the post-call price or (b) re-enters negotiation with the floor as the documented walk-away.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Discount ladder collapses to pure price cuts during the call — founder concedes price without trading scope or terms, training the prospect to keep asking.</description>
      <detector>discount_ladder steps contain only a price field, no trade_away field OR the final price is lower than the documented floor</detector>
      <repair>Rehearse the ladder before the call. Each step has a one-line trade-away the founder commits to. If the prospect rejects every trade and demands pure cuts, the founder walks at the floor — the deal terms are signalling a bad-fit customer.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Calibration absent — agency takes 6 outcome-based engagements, never reviews whether the predicted outcome value matched reality.</description>
      <detector>more than 4 closed engagements with no win-loss-calibration entry OR the latest entry is older than 12 months</detector>
      <repair>Quarterly calibration script reads closed deals, compares predicted outcome to actual realised outcome (with the same baseline metric), and flags engagements where the gap exceeds 50%. Engineering leader writes a one-page recalibration note that adjusts the confidence-band and capture-rate rules.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>
      Prospect lines like "your competitor offered 30% capture rate" are negotiation moves, not data. Capture rate is determined by the bands and the engagement structure, not by competitor anchors. The founder either accepts the deal at the disciplined price or declines; matching a competitor's number below the floor is a signal the founder should walk, not match.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>
      Before sending the proposal, the founder reads the pricing memo aloud — outcome value, confidence justification, floor, ladder — and answers a single question: "Can I defend each number on the call without flinching?" If the answer is no, the inputs need revisiting before the call, not during it.
    </p>
  </section>
</text>
