<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Two-Track Podcast Strategy Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Two-Track Podcast Strategy application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-two-tracks-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plan MUST distinguish guest-appearance track (faster ROI) from owned-show track (long-term authority). Conflating them is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">The two tracks have different cadence, prep, and ROI horizons; treating them as one collapses both.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-launch-buffer-three-episodes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Owned show MUST record ≥3 episodes before public launch. Launching with episode 1 only is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Algorithm placement collapses on schedule slips; a 3-episode buffer absorbs the first guest reschedule.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-niche-positioning" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Show MUST have a niche positioning sentence naming audience + topic + angle. Generic 'business podcast' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Discovery algorithms favour niches; generic shows lose to keyword-tight shows.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-guest-prep-doc" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each guest appearance MUST be supported by a prep doc with talking points + plug position + CTA. Improv-only is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Without prep, the plug or CTA gets dropped; the appearance becomes content for the host, not a growth move.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-repurpose-pipeline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every published episode MUST yield ≥3 derivative assets (clip + transcript + post). Single-format publishing is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Audio-only effort produces single-channel reach; repurposing multiplies impressions per recording hour.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
