<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-podcast-strategy Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-podcast-strategy. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default to guest appearances before hosting a show; guest strategy delivers faster ROI with zero equipment investment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Guest appearances reach existing audiences immediately. A single niche podcast appearance can produce 150+ trial signups and 30 paying customers. Hosting requires 12-24 months to deliver equivalent authority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Target podcasts with 50K-500K listeners in your niche; do not pitch 1M+ listener shows as a first step.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Large shows require established credentials and relationships. Mid-tier niche shows have higher booking rates and more targeted audiences for B2B products.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reference one specific recent episode by name in every pitch; a pitch without a named episode signals templating and is ignored.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Personalization is the primary differentiator; hosts receive dozens of generic pitches weekly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lead with audience value, not the guest's credentials; propose 3 specific bullet points the episode will cover.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hosts prioritize audience benefit over guest status; credential-first pitches convert at one-third the rate of audience-value pitches.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Record 3 episodes before publishing any of them; launching without a backlog causes schedule failures that permanently damage algorithm placement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Inconsistency is the single biggest cause of podcast failure. A 3-episode buffer ensures week-1 and week-2 can publish on schedule even if week-3 recording fails.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use a cold open (30-sec teaser from the episode) before the intro music; it hooks listeners before the generic intro can lose them.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Podcast platforms show 30-second previews; a cold open converts at 2x the rate of a music-first intro.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Research the last 5 interviews of every guest before preparing questions; generic biography openers waste the opening 5 minutes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Guests repeat the same origin story on every show; starting with insight-first questions produces more valuable content and higher completion rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Feed agent a transcript after recording to generate show notes, chapter timestamps, tweet thread, and newsletter blurb in one pass.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Post-production content generation from transcript is the highest-leverage agentic workflow for podcasting; it converts 60 minutes of recording into 5 distribution assets.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
