<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-guest-strategy" title="Podcast Guest Appearance Strategy">
  <summary>Finding relevant podcasts, pitching effectively, and converting appearances into leads and customers.</summary>

  <section title="Why Guest First">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to guest appearances before hosting a show; guest strategy delivers faster ROI with zero equipment investment.</statement>
      <rationale>Guest appearances reach existing audiences immediately. A single niche podcast appearance can produce 150+ trial signups and 30 paying customers. Hosting requires 12-24 months to deliver equivalent authority.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Finding Target Podcasts">
    <list>
      <item>Listen Notes API: search by topic, filter by episode count and listener score</item>
      <item>Podmatch / MatchMaker.fm: guest-host matching platforms (manual workflow)</item>
      <item>Competitor research: find where similar founders or experts appear</item>
      <item>Direct cold outreach to smaller niche shows (50K-500K listeners range)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Target podcasts with 50K-500K listeners in your niche; do not pitch 1M+ listener shows as a first step.</statement>
      <rationale>Large shows require established credentials and relationships. Mid-tier niche shows have higher booking rates and more targeted audiences for B2B products.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pitch Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reference one specific recent episode by name in every pitch; a pitch without a named episode signals templating and is ignored.</statement>
      <rationale>Personalization is the primary differentiator; hosts receive dozens of generic pitches weekly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Lead with audience value, not the guest's credentials; propose 3 specific bullet points the episode will cover.</statement>
      <rationale>Hosts prioritize audience benefit over guest status; credential-first pitches convert at one-third the rate of audience-value pitches.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/podcast-pitch.txt">Guest pitch email with personalization slots and 200-word constraint</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Generic pitch with "I'm a huge fan of your show" opener and no episode reference.</description>
      <reason>Signals mass templating; hosts delete immediately. 200-word personalized pitch with specific episode reference outperforms by 3-5x.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Preparing only one topic angle for the pitch.</description>
      <reason>Hosts often prefer a different angle; offering 3 distinct angles increases booking rate significantly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No CTA during the appearance (no mention of where to find more).</description>
      <reason>Listeners who are not directed to a specific action take none; every appearance needs a clear verbal CTA.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Real Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS guest strategy — 6-month outreach campaign</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Approach: Pitched 30 niche podcasts, appeared on 15, shared unique framework each time
Results: 2,500 website visits, 150 trial signups, 30 paying customers ($6K MRR), several partnership leads
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
