<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-hosting-strategy" title="Podcast Hosting Setup, Episode Structure, and Growth">
  <summary>Minimum viable equipment, episode structure, guest interview process, metrics, and agent workflows for hosting a show.</summary>

  <section title="Minimum Viable Setup">
    <rule>
      <statement>Record 3 episodes before publishing any of them; launching without a backlog causes schedule failures that permanently damage algorithm placement.</statement>
      <rationale>Inconsistency is the single biggest cause of podcast failure. A 3-episode buffer ensures week-1 and week-2 can publish on schedule even if week-3 recording fails.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>USB microphone: Audio-Technica ATR2100x ($50-100)</item>
      <item>Recording: Riverside.fm (remote guests) or Audacity (solo)</item>
      <item>Hosting: Transistor ($19/mo) or Buzzsprout — both have REST APIs</item>
      <item>Cover art: Canva (1400x1400px minimum)</item>
      <item>Distribution: submit to Apple Podcasts, Spotify, Google Podcasts via hosting platform RSS</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Episode Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a cold open (30-sec teaser from the episode) before the intro music; it hooks listeners before the generic intro can lose them.</statement>
      <rationale>Podcast platforms show 30-second previews; a cold open converts at 2x the rate of a music-first intro.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/show-intro-script.txt">Reusable show intro with value proposition and episode hook slots</reference>
    <reference path="templates/episode-outline.txt">Interview episode outline with question scaffolding and timestamps</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Guest Interview Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Research the last 5 interviews of every guest before preparing questions; generic biography openers waste the opening 5 minutes.</statement>
      <rationale>Guests repeat the same origin story on every show; starting with insight-first questions produces more valuable content and higher completion rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Prepare 10 questions; use 5-7 in the actual interview</item>
      <item>Share general topics with guest, not exact questions — allows authentic responses</item>
      <item>Test tech 15 min before recording</item>
      <item>High-value question types: "Tell me about when you first realized...", "What's something most people get wrong about...", "What would you do differently if starting today?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Downloads/episode first year: 100+ (good), 1,000+ (great)</item>
      <item>Completion rate: 60% (good), 80%+ (great)</item>
      <item>Guest booking rate: 30% of pitches (good), 50%+ (great)</item>
      <item>Website referrals per episode: 50 (good), 200 (great)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Workflows">
    <rule>
      <statement>Feed agent a transcript after recording to generate show notes, chapter timestamps, tweet thread, and newsletter blurb in one pass.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-production content generation from transcript is the highest-leverage agentic workflow for podcasting; it converts 60 minutes of recording into 5 distribution assets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Episode question generation prompt:</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Generate 10 interview questions for a podcast episode on [TOPIC].
Guest: [NAME], [ROLE], [COMPANY]
Known for: [KEY INSIGHT OR ACCOMPLISHMENT]
Show tone: [CONVERSATIONAL/TECHNICAL/STORYTELLING]
Avoid: generic "what's your background" opener, "what advice would you give" closer.
Include: one contrarian follow-up question per section.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
