<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="security-supply-chain Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for security-supply-chain. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Secret scanning MUST run on every commit via a pre-commit hook (Gitleaks or detect-secrets) AND in CI on the full history (`git fetch --unshallow`). When a secret lands on main, rewrite history with `git filter-repo` and rotate the credential immediately.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Pre-commit catches secrets before they reach the remote. CI with full history catches secrets introduced by force-pushes, merge commits, or squash merges that bypass the hook. Rotation without history rewrite leaves the secret in the public git object store indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use lock files (package-lock.json, poetry.lock, go.sum, Cargo.lock) for all dependency manifests. Commit lock files. Never add lock files to .gitignore.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Lock files pin the exact resolved dependency tree including transitive dependencies, preventing silent upgrades to vulnerable versions during CI installs. Without lock files, `npm install` today and tomorrow may resolve different packages.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>License policy: deny by default; maintain an allowlist of approved licenses (MIT, Apache-2.0, BSD-3-Clause, MPL-2.0). Review and reject GPL-3.0 and AGPL-3.0 for commercial projects unless legal sign-off is explicit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">SCA tools struggle with vendored or unknown-license code; an explicit allowlist forces review rather than silent acceptance of copyleft licenses that can create legal obligations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
