<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-affiliate-marketing">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>Build partner-driven acquisition channels where publishers earn commissions on referrals. Program design, recruitment, enablement, tracking, fraud prevention, and payouts.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>affiliate</tag>
      <tag>partner</tag>
      <tag>commission</tag>
      <tag>referrals</tag>
      <tag>acquisition</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Growth Affiliate Marketing</title>
    <summary>A structured approach to building partner-driven acquisition channels where third-party publishers earn commissions on sales they refer. Covers program design (commission structure, cookie duration, terms), affiliate recruitment, asset library creation, onboarding sequences, performance tracking, fraud prevention, and payout operations.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Linear ad spend produces linear growth; affiliates create leverage — when incentive structure and asset quality align, a small roster of quality partners compounds new customer acquisition without proportional ad budget increases. Commission capped at less than 30% of LTV produces positive unit economics while motivating partners.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Recurring-revenue product (SaaS, subscription, course) with LTV high enough to support 20-40% commissions.</item>
        <item>Digital product with self-serve checkout and clean link/code attribution.</item>
        <item>Niche ICP reachable through 20-50 quality newsletter writers, bloggers, or course creators.</item>
        <item>Checkout is Stripe/Paddle/Lemon Squeezy-compatible (affiliate link or discount-code friendly).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Sub-$30 transactional products with thin margin — payouts + admin overhead exceed return.</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF or volatile pricing — unstable offers burn affiliate relationships.</item>
        <item>Brand-sensitive regulated verticals (finance, medical) — affiliate copy creates compliance risk.</item>
        <item>No asset library exists yet — affiliates without swipes/banners won't promote.</item>
        <item>Marketplace price-comparison products — coupon-site affiliates cannibalize organic conversions.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Affiliate Program Design">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap total commission at less than 30% of 12-month LTV; anything above makes the program net-loss when factoring in platform and admin costs.</statement>
        <rationale>Commission must be sustainable at scale. A 40% payout on a $99 LTV product produces a slow bleed as the affiliate roster grows.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="Model Types">
        <rule>
          <statement>Choose the commission model based on product type: percentage-of-sale for digital subscriptions, flat fee for high-ticket services, recurring (lifetime) for SaaS with high LTV, tiered for motivating top performers.</statement>
          <rationale>Recurring commissions on SaaS align affiliate incentives with retention; flat fees suit high-ticket or services where LTV is predictable but average order value is high.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
      <section name="Key Program Terms">
        <rule>
          <statement>Set cookie duration to 30-90 days; use last-touch attribution by default and document it explicitly in affiliate terms.</statement>
          <rationale>Cookie duration below 30 days loses affiliates who produce delayed conversions from content like blog posts. Attribution model must be declared up front to avoid disputes.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Delay payouts 30-60 days after the sale to cover the refund window; pay outstanding commissions on program termination.</statement>
          <rationale>Paying out before the refund window closes loses money on cancellations. Reliable on-schedule payment is the top factor affiliates use to rate a program.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Set a minimum payout threshold ($50-100) and pay monthly on a fixed schedule.</statement>
          <rationale>Small payouts create processing overhead. A predictable schedule builds trust; erratic payments cause affiliate churn.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
      <section name="Fraud Prevention">
        <rule>
          <statement>Explicitly prohibit brand-keyword PPC bidding, coupon-site listing, spam/unsolicited email, and incentivized traffic in program terms; monitor for violations and enforce termination.</statement>
          <rationale>Coupon-site and brand-keyword affiliates cannibalize cheap organic conversions. Spam traffic violates FTC endorsement rules and can produce chargebacks.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Flag transactions where the same IP records more than 3 sales in 1 hour, click-to-conversion time is under 30 seconds, or referrer is a known coupon domain.</statement>
          <rationale>These patterns indicate click stuffing or transaction injection. Automated fraud sweeps before payout approval prevent irreversible losses.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Two-tier (MLM-style) commission structures where affiliates earn on recruits' sales.</description>
          <reason>Attracts low-quality recruiters; creates FTC compliance risk and tax-form complexity with no proportional lift in quality referrals.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
      <section name="Platform Selection">
        <rule>
          <statement>Backstop cookie-only attribution with promo codes and logged-in-user attribution to recover the 20-40% of conversions lost to iOS 14.5, ITP, and ad-blockers.</statement>
          <rationale>Cookie-only tracking understates affiliate contribution and underpays honest affiliates while overpaying last-click coupon sites that inject themselves after attribution is broken.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="Affiliate Recruitment and Enablement">
      <section name="Affiliate Types">
        <rule>
          <statement>Prioritize niche newsletter writers as first-recruit targets; they typically offer the highest CPM-equivalent ROI versus broad bloggers because their audience trust is higher and topic alignment is tighter.</statement>
          <rationale>Newsletter writers have direct inbox access to a pre-qualified audience. Open rates above 25% with prior sponsored content signal monetization willingness and audience trust.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <p>High-value types in order of typical effort-to-revenue: newsletter writers (low effort, targeted), course creators (low effort, curriculum integration), power users/existing customers (low effort, authentic voice), comparison sites (medium effort, high intent traffic), content bloggers (medium effort, SEO value), agencies recommending to clients (medium effort, B2B).</p>
      </section>
      <section name="Outreach">
        <rule>
          <statement>Personalize outreach with a specific reference to the affiliate's recent content before mentioning the program; generic "partnership opportunity" emails get ignored.</statement>
          <rationale>Affiliates receive mass outreach constantly. A specific reference proves you are a real reader and increases reply rate significantly.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>State the commission structure and average monthly earnings range in the first outreach message; affiliates will not reply to vague "great opportunity" messages.</statement>
          <rationale>Time is the affiliate's constraint. Concrete numbers allow instant triage. "Our top affiliates earn $X/month" backed by real distribution data also sets honest expectations.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
      <section name="Asset Library">
        <rule>
          <statement>Provide at minimum: unique tracking links, banner ads (multiple sizes), email swipe copy, social post copy, demo video, and case studies before recruiting affiliates.</statement>
          <rationale>Affiliates promote what is easy to use. Without assets, even motivated affiliates stall. The asset library quality is the single biggest predictor of activation rate.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Launching the program without an asset library and expecting affiliates to create their own promotional materials.</description>
          <reason>Affiliates abandon programs that require significant creative work; they move to programs that make promotion frictionless.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
      <section name="Onboarding Sequence">
        <rule>
          <statement>Run a structured onboarding sequence: Day 0 welcome + credentials, Day 1 dashboard tutorial, Day 3 best-performing strategies, Day 7 check-in, Day 14 first-sale tips, Day 30 recap.</statement>
          <rationale>80% of affiliates who don't produce a sale in the first 30 days never will. A structured onboarding shortens time-to-first-sale and increases the activation rate above 30%.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Provide a "top 10 starter playbook" covering the highest-converting tactics from existing affiliates so new partners can copy proven approaches immediately.</statement>
          <rationale>New affiliates lack context on what messaging and channels work. Sharing winning tactics reduces experimentation time and aligns affiliate copy with brand standards.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
      <section name="Ongoing Management">
        <rule>
          <statement>Recompute LTV quarterly and adjust commission tiers accordingly; never let affiliates discover a commission cut mid-campaign.</statement>
          <rationale>Affiliates plan promotional calendars around commission rates. Surprise cuts destroy trust and trigger public complaints in affiliate communities.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="Affiliate Tracking Metrics and Real Examples">
      <section name="Key Metrics">
        <rule>
          <statement>Track five program-level metrics weekly: affiliate activation rate (target above 30%), conversion rate (target above 2%), revenue per active affiliate, CAC via affiliates (must stay below 30% of LTV), and fraud rate (target below 1%).</statement>
          <rationale>These five metrics together diagnose whether the program is healthy. Low activation rate means recruitment or onboarding failure; high CAC means commission is too high or traffic quality is low.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <p>Affiliate activation rate = affiliates with 1+ referral / total affiliates. Conversion rate = sales / clicks. CAC via affiliates = total commissions paid / customers acquired. Fraud rate = flagged transactions / total transactions.</p>
      </section>
      <example type="good" title="SaaS Affiliate Program">
        <p>Project management tool. Structure: 30% recurring commission, 60-day cookie, monthly payouts at $50 minimum. Recruited 50 productivity bloggers, 15 joined, 5 became active promoters. Results over 12 months: 200 customers, $60K ARR attributed, $18K commissions paid. Effective affiliate CAC: $90 vs $150 via paid ads — 40% more efficient.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Course Affiliate Program">
        <p>$500 online course. Structure: 40% per sale ($200 flat), 30-day cookie. Targeted newsletter writers in niche, created co-branded landing pages, provided exclusive bonuses. Results: 50 affiliates, 300 sales ($150K revenue), $60K commissions paid — 10x ROI on program management cost.</p>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Inactive affiliate tail: signing up many affiliates without a pruning process.</description>
        <reason>80% of affiliates produce zero sales. An unpruned roster inflates support overhead and dilutes program resources. Healthy programs continually recruit quality partners and prune inactive ones quarterly.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Paying commissions before the refund window closes.</description>
        <reason>Cancellations and chargebacks that arrive after payout are unrecoverable losses. The 30-day holdback is non-negotiable arithmetic, not a courtesy.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <section name="Tools Reference">
        <p>Platform options: Rewardful (Stripe-native SaaS), FirstPromoter (SaaS-focused), PartnerStack (B2B deeper PRM), Lemon Squeezy and Paddle (built-in affiliate for digital products). Fraud detection: pandas for transaction pattern analysis, playwright for brand-keyword PPC monitoring. Payouts: Wise or PayPal Mass-Pay for cross-border.</p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/affiliate-agreement.md" purpose="Key-points affiliate agreement template with commission, rules, termination, liability"/>
      <template path="templates/affiliate-welcome-email.md" purpose="Welcome email with link, dashboard access, quick-start steps, and asset links"/>
      <template path="templates/payout-calc.py" purpose="Monthly payout calculation with refund holdback (30-day window)"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
