<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Decision Log Template Core Rules">
  <summary>The minimum field set and ritual every design decision-log entry must satisfy to prevent re-litigation and survive team turnover.</summary>
  <section title="Required fields per entry">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Each entry carries seven fields: id (sortable, e.g. DEC-2026-05-20-001), date, context (1-2 sentences of triggering problem), options considered (≥2, with one-line tradeoff each), decision (one sentence), owner (named person, not "the team"), and a link to the Figma frame or Storybook story the decision applies to. Entries missing any field are rejected by the linter or review hook.</statement>
      <rationale>Each field corresponds to a question the next reader will ask. Skipping one means the entry will be re-opened within a sprint; "the team decided" without an owner is the single biggest cause of decision reversal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Options considered always include a "do nothing / keep current" option with its tradeoff. Decisions that record only the chosen option are upgraded to include at least one alternative; if no alternative existed, the entry is downgraded to a "constraint" not a "decision".</statement>
      <rationale>The most expensive design mistakes come from decisions that never compared against the null option. Forcing "do nothing" into the comparison catches sunk-cost reasoning early.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Entries are append-only. When a decision is reversed, the original entry stays and a new entry is added that cites the original by id and explains what changed. Editing or deleting a past entry is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>Append-only history is the only way to learn from reversed decisions. Edited or deleted entries erase the why-we-tried-it record that prevents repeating the same mistake.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The log lives in exactly one location (a markdown file in the repo, a Notion DB, an Airtable, or a Figma page — but only one) and is linked from the team's standup template, Figma cover page, and onboarding doc. Multiple parallel logs are merged or one is declared canonical.</statement>
      <rationale>Two logs equal zero logs: nobody trusts either, decisions get logged in whichever feels less effort, search returns half the truth. One canonical location with three pointers in is the cheapest way to keep the log alive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Each entry includes at least one tag from a fixed vocabulary (e.g. "copy", "layout", "interaction", "a11y", "design-system", "scope-cut") so the log can be filtered for handoff or audit. Free-text tagging is forbidden; the vocabulary lives in the log header.</statement>
      <rationale>Free-text tags decay to noise within a month. A small fixed vocabulary makes the log filterable when an onboarding designer or AI agent needs "all a11y decisions for the checkout flow".</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## DEC-2026-05-20-003
- date: 2026-05-20
- tags: [copy, empty-state]
- context: First-run empty state copy reviewed in stakeholder walkthrough.
- options:
  - "Nothing here yet" — neutral, fits 8 languages; no CTA → users sometimes stall.
  - "Add your first item" — directive, drives action; translation length varies ±40%.
  - Do nothing — keep "No data" → tested poorly in last research round.
- decision: "Nothing here yet" + secondary "Add" button below.
- owner: K. Petrenko
- link: figma.com/file/.../?node-id=42
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
2026-05-20 — we agreed to change the empty state copy
]]></code>
      <note>No id, no owner, no options, no link, no tags — will be re-opened by the next reviewer.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
