<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="pytest Mocking — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every python-pytest-mocking application must obey.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-mocker-over-unittest-mock" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use the mocker fixture from pytest-mock. Do not call unittest.mock.patch directly in tests.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">mocker auto-cleans patches after every test; manual patch.start/stop or with-blocks are boilerplate and error-prone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-patch-use-site" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Patch where the function is used, not where it is defined: mocker.patch('apps.orders.services.send_mail') when orders.services does 'from emails.utils import send_mail'.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">Python binds names at import; patching the definition has no effect on the consumer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-autospec-for-signature" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use autospec=True (or create_autospec) so mocks match the real signature. Reject calls with wrong args at test time.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">Without autospec, a mock accepts any args — silent signature drift between code and test.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-asyncmock-for-async" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mock async callables with AsyncMock. Never with MagicMock.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">MagicMock returns a sync value when awaited (warning: coroutine was never awaited); AsyncMock returns a coroutine.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-spy-when-behaviour-matters" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use mocker.spy(obj, 'method') when you want the real implementation to run but also record calls.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">Spy gives observability without changing behaviour — ideal for verifying that production code actually called the dependency.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-never-mock-orm" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not patch Model.objects.* in service tests. Use a real DB fixture with savepoint rollback.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">Mocking the ORM tests the mock, not the code; passes even when querysets are broken.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
