<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-backlog-principles" title="Backlog Health Principles and Structure">
  <summary>DEEP and INVEST principles for backlog quality, four-tier backlog structure, and criteria for a well-formed backlog item.</summary>

  <section title="Backlog Health Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply DEEP to the backlog as a whole: top items Detailed, bottom items Emergent, all items Estimated, all items Prioritized.</statement>
      <rationale>A backlog uniformly detailed at all depths wastes refinement effort on items that will never be built. DEEP matches detail depth to proximity to execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply INVEST to every individual item before marking it Ready: Independent, Negotiable, Valuable, Estimable, Small, Testable.</statement>
      <rationale>Items that fail INVEST block sprint planning — engineers cannot estimate or test them without more work, causing last-minute scope changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Backlog Structure">
    <list>
      <item>Ready (Next Sprint) — Detailed, estimated, acceptance criteria present, no blockers</item>
      <item>Upcoming (1-3 sprints) — Defined, some detail, rough estimate</item>
      <item>Backlog (Future) — Ideas, rough description, not yet refined</item>
      <item>Icebox (Maybe/Later) — Parked, low priority, revisit quarterly</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain 2-4 sprints worth of Ready items, fewer than 100 total items (or grouped), and fewer than 10% stale items.</statement>
      <rationale>These three targets are the minimal health indicators. Below 2 Ready sprints causes planning panic; above 100 ungrouped items means signal is buried in noise; above 10% stale means the backlog is a graveyard.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Backlog Item Quality">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every Ready item must have: clear user value, acceptance criteria (Given/When/Then format), size estimate, priority rank, and documented dependencies or none.</statement>
      <rationale>Items reaching sprint planning without acceptance criteria cause in-sprint scope debates. Given/When/Then forces specificity that "user can do X" does not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Vague item title like "Better search" or "Fix dashboard".</description>
      <reason>Vague titles require a conversation to decode intent. Reformulate as "Add autocomplete to product search" — action-oriented, scoped, estimable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Properly refined backlog item after grooming</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Title: Add autocomplete to product search
As a customer
I want to see suggestions as I type
So that I find products faster

Acceptance Criteria:
- Given 2+ characters typed, when user pauses 300ms, then top 5 suggestions appear
- Given a suggestion is shown, when user clicks it, then product detail page opens
- Given mobile viewport, when autocomplete is active, then keyboard does not obscure results

Estimate: M (3-5 days)
Priority: P2 — high-usage path
]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/backlog-item.md">Backlog item template with full story format, AC, estimate, priority, and links.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
