<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-grooming-process" title="Backlog Grooming and Agent Integration">
  <summary>Five-step grooming process, health targets, agent workflow for automation, and critical rules for human-in-loop control.</summary>

  <section title="Grooming Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Capture — accept items from any source, categorize type (feature/bug/debt/research), defer evaluation</item>
      <item>Step 2: Groom (weekly, 1-2h) — review new items, refine top items, re-prioritize on new learning, archive stale</item>
      <item>Step 3: Prioritize — apply RICE or MoSCoW, re-rank when new information arrives or goals change</item>
      <item>Step 4: Refine top-of-backlog — break into smaller stories, add AC, clarify requirements, estimate, identify deps</item>
      <item>Step 5: Cleanup — delete duplicates, archive items untouched for 6+ months, merge related items</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Archive items untouched for 6+ months AND with no roadmap link. Timestamp alone is not sufficient for stale detection.</statement>
      <rationale>Valid items can be dormant; cross-check with linked customer requests and roadmap before archiving.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/backlog-health-check.md">Health snapshot: counts by status/type, metric table with targets, actions needed.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/grooming-agenda.md">Session template: new item triage, top-of-backlog review, refinement, estimates, cleanup summary.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Agents draft; humans commit. Never grant write-scoped tokens to autonomous agents on live trackers.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent-applied edits to live tickets in front of users is jarring and error-prone. Route through PR-style changeset or staging branch for human review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Triage agent (nightly): classify new items, draft story format, propose priority — outputs draft only</item>
      <item>Health-check agent (weekly): compute counts, age distribution, AC coverage %, stale candidates</item>
      <item>Groomer agent (synchronous, during session): assists refinement of top-20 items under human approval</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM-rewritten user stories that paraphrase the original request.</description>
      <reason>Original requestor wording is signal; agent paraphrasing destroys it. Keep original text under a Raw Request section in every item.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent-generated estimates without team-historical priors.</description>
      <reason>T-shirt sizing without calibration against past delivery is dart-throwing. Bootstrap from last 30 closed items before trusting agent estimates.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-merging "similar" items based on semantic similarity alone.</description>
      <reason>Wrong merges destroy audit trail and lose distinct customer requests. Require 0.9+ similarity score AND human accept before merging.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Priority Limit Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>If more than 20% of the backlog is already P1, refuse to propose new P1 items until the proportion drops.</statement>
      <rationale>P1 inflation means nothing is P1. The label loses its forcing function for sprint ordering.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/backlog-health.sh">Weekly cron: Linear API pull, health report generation, stale candidate extraction.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
