<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Certification Changes Rules and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Rules for generating accurate 2026-aligned study content and avoiding stale-weight agent errors.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Force-feed the 2026 domain weights (33/41/26) in every system prompt that generates PMP study content; never let the agent infer weights from training data.</statement>
    <rationale>LLMs trained before mid-2025 emit the old weights (42/50/8) confidently; explicit injection is the only reliable fix.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Restrict "Business Environment" to PMI vocabulary only; reject AI-generated content that conflates it with SOC, ITIL, or general business strategy terms.</statement>
    <rationale>Business Environment is an ITIL and SOC term with different meanings; cross-pollination produces incorrect exam answers.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Fetch the current PMI ECO PDF before generating any study plan; do not use cached or inferred task lists.</statement>
    <rationale>ECO layout and task lists change each cycle; stale ECO data produces study plans misaligned with the actual exam.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Cite one sustainability reference per generated answer (GPM P5, ISO 21502, or ISO 14001); do not mix standards within a single answer.</statement>
    <rationale>PMI cites multiple sustainability standards with different scopes; mixing produces inconsistent and potentially incorrect guidance.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Distinguish AI as exam content (what candidates must know about AI in PM) from AI used in studying (what tools candidates use); never conflate the two.</statement>
    <rationale>AI-in-PM is now a testable topic; conflation confuses exam preparation with tool usage.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Generating practice questions using "processes" vs "principles" wording when they should reference 2026 ECO task language.</description>
    <reason>Old wording anchors candidates in PMBoK 6 framing; 2026 questions use PMBoK 7/8 outcome-based language.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Practice question banks generated by agents that drift toward old domain percentages when sampling.</description>
    <reason>Without explicit weight constraints, sampling produces 42/50/8 distribution by default; enforce 33/41/26 in the sampler.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Using third-party exam prep content without verifying the publication date aligns with the 2026 ECO update.</description>
    <reason>Pre-2025 content reflects old weights and will mislead candidates for the new exam form.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <reference path="templates/study-plan.md">Weekly study plan template with domain-weighted hour allocation</reference>
</text>
