<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-numbering-conventions" title="Numbering Conventions">
  <summary>Standard numbering patterns for features, tasks, requirements, and acceptance criteria used across the PM workflow artifacts.</summary>

  <section title="Numbering Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use these exact patterns across all PM workflow artifacts: features as {NN}-{name} (e.g., 01-auth), tasks as TASK_{NNN}_* (e.g., TASK_001_setup), functional requirements as FR-{NN}.{N} (e.g., FR-01.1), acceptance criteria as AC-{NN}.{N} (e.g., AC-01.1).</statement>
      <rationale>Consistent numbering enables cross-referencing between specs, task files, and tracker tickets; inconsistent numbering breaks the rice-reorder script, spec-to-task linking, and MLP update mode's in-place edit logic.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Tracker Sync Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat .aidocs/features/ as the planning source of truth and Jira/Linear as the execution mirror — never the reverse.</statement>
      <rationale>Tracker tickets get deleted, re-numbered, or migrated; the .aidocs/ file tree is under git and has full history. If the tracker is the source of truth, history is lost when tickets are deleted.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When syncing RICE values to Jira numeric custom fields, coerce explicitly; Jira drops the value silently on type mismatch.</statement>
      <rationale>Jira's REST API does not return an error when a numeric field receives a string value; the value is silently ignored, leaving the field empty in the tracker while appearing correct in the spec frontmatter.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Daily Orchestrator Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>The daily PM orchestrator produces one digest file (.aidocs/digest/YYYY-MM-DD.md) and sends only the diff vs. yesterday via tg-send, not the full digest.</statement>
      <rationale>Sending the full digest daily creates Telegram noise; the diff is what the PM needs to act on. Full digests are available on demand from the file.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
