<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-headline-angles" title="Headline Angles and Pinning Rules">
  <summary>Ten headline angle categories with examples, keyword inclusion rules, and position pinning guidelines.</summary>

  <section title="Headline Angle Categories">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cover at least 7 of the 10 angle categories across 15 headlines — heavy repetition of a single angle wastes slots and prevents the algorithm from identifying which message resonates.</statement>
      <rationale>Google's RSA system tests combinations; angles that are nearly identical produce statistically indistinguishable results, providing no learning signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Keyword match — "Project Management Software" (exact search term)</item>
      <item>Primary benefit — "Ship Projects 2x Faster"</item>
      <item>Secondary benefit — "Save 10 Hours Per Week"</item>
      <item>Social proof — "Trusted by 10,000+ Teams"</item>
      <item>CTA — "Start Your Free 14-Day Trial"</item>
      <item>Offer/price — "From $9/User/Month"</item>
      <item>Feature — "Real-Time Team Collaboration"</item>
      <item>Differentiator — "No Training Required"</item>
      <item>Urgency/scarcity — "Limited Time: 30% Off"</item>
      <item>Question — "Drowning in Project Chaos?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Keyword Inclusion Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include the primary keyword in at least 2 headlines, placed naturally — do not keyword-stuff or truncate at character limit to fit the keyword.</statement>
      <rationale>Keyword relevance in headlines directly improves Quality Score → lower CPC. Truncated or unnatural keyword placement degrades CTR, negating the Quality Score benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pinning Guidelines">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin a headline to position 1 only when brand or legal compliance requires it to always appear — avoid pinning for performance reasons, as it reduces the combination space available to the algorithm.</statement>
      <rationale>Each pinned position removes a testing slot from the algorithm. Pinning 3 headlines effectively converts the RSA into a fixed ETA, eliminating all adaptive optimization.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
