<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-activation-tactics" title="Activation Friction Reduction and Free Tier Balance">
  <summary>Concrete tactics for reducing activation friction and defining a balanced free tier that gives enough value to reach the Aha moment without removing upgrade incentive.</summary>

  <section title="Signup Friction Reduction">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reduce signup to 3 fields maximum (name, email, password) with instant access. Move any additional qualification fields to a post-activation profile step.</statement>
      <rationale>Each additional field reduces signup completion by 5-10%. 10-field forms fail ~70% of users before they experience any value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never show a blank canvas on first login. Pre-seed with sample data, templates, or a pre-filled demo object. The target "empty state time" before the user sees populated content is under 2 minutes.</statement>
      <rationale>Empty states force users to think before they have context. Pre-seeded content reduces time-to-value and increases Day-0 activation rate by 20-40%.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Progressive Onboarding">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reveal features contextually as users take actions rather than teaching everything upfront. Gate each next capability on completing the previous one.</statement>
      <rationale>Showing all features at once overwhelms users and dilutes focus on the core activation path. Progressive reveal increases feature adoption depth without increasing early drop-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Project management tool: 4-step progressive reveal tied to user actions.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1. Login → Create first task (core value demonstrated)
2. Add 3 tasks → Show task organization options
3. Organize tasks → Show collaboration features
4. Invite teammate → Show advanced reporting/analytics
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Free Tier Balance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design the free tier to give enough value to reach the Aha moment with clear natural upgrade triggers (usage limits, feature gates, user limits) — not so generous that there is no incentive to upgrade, not so restrictive that the user cannot experience value.</statement>
      <rationale>Too-generous free tiers produce low conversion (users never hit limits). Too-restrictive tiers produce high abandonment (users cannot see value before hitting a wall).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Feature gates: basic vs premium features — upgrade trigger is needing advanced functionality.</item>
      <item>Usage limits: 5 projects, 100MB storage — upgrade trigger is hitting capacity at meaningful usage.</item>
      <item>User limits: 1-2 users free vs unlimited team — upgrade trigger is team growth.</item>
      <item>Time limits: 14-day trial of premium features — upgrade trigger is trial expiration with demonstrated value.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
