<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-conversion-and-expansion" title="Upgrade Prompt Rules, Expansion Signals, and Test Ideas">
  <summary>When and how to show upgrade prompts, expansion signal detection, and a structured A/B test idea bank for onboarding, upgrade prompts, and pricing pages.</summary>

  <section title="Upgrade Prompt Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show upgrade prompts at 80% of limit consumption, never at 100%. Cap upgrade prompts to one per session and zero during the first session. Never show during a critical workflow or immediately after a recent dismissal.</statement>
      <rationale>Prompts at 100% arrive too late — the user has already hit a wall and is frustrated. First-session prompts break trust before value is demonstrated. Over-prompting trains users to dismiss all prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>All upgrade copy must: name a comparable customer, quantify the value (hours saved, projects unlocked), name the specific plan, and include two CTAs (primary: upgrade, secondary: see example or learn more). Reject "Get More Features", "Upgrade Now", and "Premium Plan" as CTA text.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic upgrade copy does not connect the user's current need to the plan's value. Named customer + quantified benefit copies convert at 2-3x generic CTA text in A/B tests.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Feature gate message: team exceeds 3-member free limit.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Teams like Acme Corp save 10 hours/week with unlimited member access.
 Your team is ready for [Product] Team plan."
 [Upgrade to Team] [See what's included]
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Generic upgrade prompt — no customer, no value quantification.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"This feature is for Pro users only."
[Upgrade]
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Self-Serve Checkout">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pricing pages must have: 2-4 tiers maximum, a feature comparison table, an annual discount (15-20%), and no "Contact Sales" button for basic or pro tiers. Instant access on upgrade — no approval wait.</statement>
      <rationale>More than 4 tiers introduces choice paralysis. Hiding annual discount reduces LTV. "Contact Sales" on standard tiers is a conversion cliff that routes self-serve users into a sales process they did not want.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Expansion Signals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Monitor team-growth signals (multiple users from same domain, @mentions, external sharing), power-user signals (daily active usage, API usage, integration connections), and upsell-readiness signals (feature gate hits 3+ times, pricing page visits). Route PQL-qualified users to targeted upgrade prompts; do not show expansion prompts to users who have not hit these signals.</statement>
      <rationale>PQL-based prompts sent at behavioral readiness convert at 3-5x prompts sent on time-based schedules alone.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="A/B Test Idea Bank">
    <p>Onboarding tests: number of signup fields (2 vs 3 vs 5); social login vs email-only; interactive walkthrough vs tutorial video; empty state vs pre-filled templates; progress checklist vs progress bar.</p>
    <p>Upgrade prompt tests: prompt timing at 70% vs 80% vs 90% of limit; prompt format (banner vs modal vs sidebar); CTA copy ("Upgrade" vs "Unlock" vs "Get unlimited"); price anchoring (monthly vs annual shown first).</p>
    <p>Pricing page tests: 2 vs 3 vs 4 tiers; annual discount amount (15% vs 20% vs 25%); feature comparison layout (table vs cards); CTA position (top vs bottom vs both); FAQ placement.</p>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/ice-scorer.py">ICE scoring dataclass for ranking tactic backlog</reference>
</text>
