<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="plg-optimization-tactics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for plg-optimization-tactics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs recommend "remove all limits" or "give 30-day trial" — this conflicts with the balanced-tier guidance.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin the system prompt to the specific limit-type matrix in this methodology.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-generated upgrade copy drifts to generic SaaS language ("powerful features", "enterprise-grade").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add a post-filter that scans for these tokens and rewrites them using named customers and quantified value.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents writing directly to a paid Stripe price object or live Appcues flow.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Gate every mutation behind a human-approved PR or ticket.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Free-tier limit changes shipped autonomously by agent with high ICE score.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Free-tier limit changes must be reviewed with finance + retention data — never let an agent ship a limit change autonomously.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>PQL scoring weights reused from last quarter's coefficients without re-fitting.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require the agent to re-fit weights against converted cohorts every quarter.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>"Empty State Time under 2 minutes" target used without server-side data seeding step in the onboarding flow spec.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents producing onboarding flows must explicitly include the seed step or the metric is unreachable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
