<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-pipeline" title="At-Scale Research Assembly Line">
  <summary>The six-stage pipeline for AI-augmented research operations and the platform capabilities that support each stage.</summary>

  <section title="Assembly-line model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure the research pipeline as: recruit → moderate (human or unmoderated) → transcribe → tag → cluster → report → publish. Agents own transcription, tagging, clustering, and report drafting; humans own study design, ethics, interpretation, and stakeholder framing.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing agent and human responsibilities without clear ownership lets errors propagate through all downstream stages silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a research repository (Dovetail, Marvin, EnjoyHQ, Notably) as the single source of truth; have agents push artifacts with stable IDs. Track a decisions-ledger linking tagged insights to shipped product changes — the ratio is the actual ROI of scaling.</statement>
      <rationale>Scaling research without a repository strategy produces archived reports nobody reads; the decisions-ledger proves that insights changed behavior.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a human verifier subagent that samples 10% of agent-tagged segments per study and gates publication on agreement rate of 90% or above.</statement>
      <rationale>AI auto-tagging accuracy varies by domain; sentiment models trained on product reviews mis-tag user-research segments with sarcasm, code-switching, and non-English transcripts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Platform capabilities">
    <p>Platform tiers by team size: small teams benefit from built-in automation and AI analysis in tools like Maze and Sprig; large teams need scalable panels (Userlytics 2M+, UserTesting), collaboration across squads, and adaptable workflows with repository integration.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stratify panels by role, geography, and tenure; report on stratification balance per study. "n=200 random" is a misleading scale claim without stratification disclosure.</statement>
      <rationale>Large panels are not high-quality panels; professional respondents and geographic clustering bias results.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap unmoderated panel reliance at 60-70% of the research mix; complement with moderated and longitudinal studies for depth.</statement>
      <rationale>Unmoderated testing cannot capture motivations, context, or unexpected paths that a moderator would pursue.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Localization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Transcribe in the source language, translate after tagging — never the reverse.</statement>
      <rationale>Translation before tagging loses tag-relevant nuance; code-switching and cultural idioms that carry emotional weight in the original disappear in translation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
