<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="user-research-at-scale Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for user-research-at-scale as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-summarisers compress 30-minute interviews to one paragraph and lose disconfirming evidence.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Compression loses context; require quote retention with timestamps for every claim.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Sentiment models trained on product reviews mis-tag user-research segments (heavy use of past tense, hypothetical framing).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>User-research speech patterns differ fundamentally from product reviews; retrain or use domain-specific sentiment models.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM "synthetic users" used to validate willingness-to-pay or behaviour.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Synthetic users are sycophantic; never use them to validate go/no-go decisions, only to seed prompts and edge cases.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Diarisation errors mis-attribute moderator speech to participants, biasing tag distributions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always verify speaker tags before clustering; diarisation accuracy drops on overlapping speech and accents.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Multi-agent pipelines without idempotency reprocess the same recording when re-run, double-counting tags.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require deduplication keys (recording ID + run ID) before any tagging write.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent pipelines push transcripts to a repository without PII redaction.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>GDPR/CCPA require PII redaction before storage; pair with password-scrubber-agent or equivalent before pushing transcripts to a repo.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>"AI follow-up question" features that ask leading questions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Review generated probes before they ship to participants; leading questions bias responses and violate research ethics.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
