<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-token-structure" title="Design Token Structure and Rules">
  <summary>Three-tier token hierarchy, naming conventions, alias rules, and governance discipline for W3C-compliant design token systems.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Tier Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Establish three tiers before generating any tokens: global (raw primitive values) → semantic (intent aliases) → component (scoped overrides).</statement>
      <rationale>Without the hierarchy, semantic tokens hold raw values and component tokens reference semantics directly — both patterns defeat the "update once, apply everywhere" guarantee.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Semantic tokens must never hold raw values; they must always alias a global token using {global.token.path} reference syntax.</statement>
      <rationale>A semantic token holding a raw hex value must be updated in two places when the brand color changes — defeating the entire purpose of the token layer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="json"><![CDATA[{
  "color": {
    "blue": { "value": "#3B82F6", "type": "color" },
    "primary": { "value": "{color.blue}", "type": "color", "description": "Primary brand color" },
    "feedback": {
      "error": { "value": "{color.red}", "type": "color" }
    }
  },
  "spacing": {
    "xs": { "value": "4px" },
    "sm": { "value": "8px" },
    "md": { "value": "16px" }
  }
}]]></code>
      <note>Global tokens hold raw values; semantic tokens reference globals; naming uses intent, not value.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Semantic token holding a raw hex value: "color.primary": { "value": "#3B82F6" }</description>
      <reason>When the brand color changes, every semantic token holding the raw value must be updated individually. Alias resolution breaks the single-source-of-truth guarantee.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Naming Conventions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name semantic tokens by intent, not by value: use color.feedback.error, not color.red; use spacing.md, not spacing.16.</statement>
      <rationale>The value may change; the intent should not. Intent-based names remain valid across rebrands and theme changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a single naming convention across all tokens in a project — kebab-case is the W3C DTCG default; enforce it in CI via Style Dictionary transforms.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixed conventions (camelCase in some tokens, kebab in others) produce incorrect generated output and make token references unreliable across platforms.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Governance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a single source of truth: either Figma Variables or a tokens JSON file in the repo — never maintain both independently.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a single source, Figma and code diverge within weeks; token-based theming becomes unreliable and designers stop trusting the system.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat breaking token renames (not additions) as a major version bump; communicate them ahead of time to all consuming teams.</statement>
      <rationale>Token renames silently break components in all consuming packages; versioning disciplines prevent surprise failures in downstream design systems.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce semantic-references-global rule in CI: run Style Dictionary build as a validation step and fail the pipeline if any semantic token contains a raw value.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual review of token files does not scale; automated enforcement is the only reliable governance mechanism.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/tokens.json">W3C-compliant token JSON example with global and semantic tiers</reference>
  <reference path="templates/sd.config.js">Style Dictionary config generating CSS variables and JS/TS exports</reference>
</text>
