<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="design-tokens-fundamentals Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for design-tokens-fundamentals as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Semantic token holding a raw hex value: "color.primary": { "value": "#3B82F6" }</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>When the brand color changes, every semantic token holding the raw value must be updated individually. Alias resolution breaks the single-source-of-truth guarantee.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents default to two-tier (global + component) token structures; the semantic tier must be explicitly requested.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without explicit constraints in the prompt, agents collapse the semantic tier and put intent-based token names in the component tier, breaking the hierarchy.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Generated token names often mix conventions (camelCase in some, kebab in others) within a single file.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents follow patterns from training data without enforcing a single convention; specify convention explicitly in the prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents frequently produce semantic tokens that reference raw hex values instead of global token paths.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without schema validation in the prompt, agents copy values instead of creating aliases; validate with jq or Style Dictionary build.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Token generation without a design reference produces arbitrary spacing and color scales.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents cannot invent design values; always provide the actual design values as input.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Token sprawl: agents generate excessively granular tokens (one per component state) that defeat the scalability benefit.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without explicit constraints, agents over-tokenize. Specify maximum number of tokens and minimum reuse count in the prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
