<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Chunking Production Service — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 rules: fail-fast config validation, dispatch by strategy enum, metadata propagation, logged fallback, strategy_used in output.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-fail-fast-config" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ChunkingService MUST validate ChunkingConfig at construction time. If strategy=SEMANTIC and embedding_func is None, raise ValueError immediately, not at chunk() time.</statement>
      <rationale source="Production fail-fast pattern">Mid-batch failures are expensive; configuration errors must surface before the run starts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-strategy-enum-dispatch" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Strategy MUST be a closed enum (FIXED, SENTENCE, PARAGRAPH, SEMANTIC, RECURSIVE, MARKDOWN, HTML, CODE). Free-string strategy values are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Codebase consistency audit">Open strings drift across call sites; closed enum makes dispatch deterministic and refactor-safe.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-metadata-propagation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every emitted chunk MUST carry the caller-supplied document metadata dict merged with the chunker's own metadata. The caller's keys take precedence on conflict.</statement>
      <rationale source="Traceability incident log">Lost source/page/tenant metadata makes hits unattributable; merge policy must be explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-logged-fallback" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The fallback word-split path MUST be reachable only through the exception handler. Every fallback MUST log {source, requested_strategy, exception, traceback} at WARNING level, and emitted chunks MUST carry strategy_used="fallback" with the original requested strategy retained as `requested_strategy`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Batch-pipeline silent-failure post-mortem">Silent fallback hides parse errors; operators cannot distinguish primary from degraded chunks without explicit tagging.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-strategy-used-in-output" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every chunk in the service envelope MUST carry `strategy_used` field (the actual strategy that produced it). For audit, the envelope MUST also carry `requested_strategy`.</statement>
      <rationale source="A/B-comparison + audit-trail requirement">Without strategy_used, A/B analysis cannot attribute quality changes; without requested_strategy, fallback frequency is invisible.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
