<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="pain-point-research">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>user-researcher</domain>
    <summary>5-step process: define scope, mine four source tiers, categorize, score with Pain Intensity Matrix, extract root causes via 5 Whys. Output: ranked pain log, not assumptions.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>research</tag>
      <tag>pain-points</tag>
      <tag>discovery</tag>
      <tag>scoring</tag>
      <tag>user-problems</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Pain Point Research</title>
    <summary>Systematic 5-step process for discovering and prioritizing user pain points: define scope, mine four source tiers (complaints, questions, forums, job boards), categorize by type, score with the Pain Intensity Matrix (frequency × severity × reach × spend × alternatives), then extract root causes via 5 Whys. Output is a ranked pain log, not a list of assumptions.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Finding pain points without a source strategy produces confirmation bias — researchers look where they expect to find what they already believe. The tiered source model forces triangulation across direct complaints (highest signal) through job boards (revealed willingness to pay). The weighted scoring formula surfaces which pains are frequent enough and severe enough to be worth solving, before any solution work begins.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Early-stage discovery when no validated problem yet exists</item>
        <item>Competitor gap analysis: mining negative reviews to find underserved pain</item>
        <item>Content marketing: identifying questions your audience actively asks</item>
        <item>Prioritizing a backlog of improvement ideas by actual user pain vs. assumptions</item>
        <item>Researching a new market niche before committing to build</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>After product-market fit: qualitative pain mining is less useful than quantitative retention analysis</item>
        <item>When a decision needs statistical confidence: pain mining is directional, not significant</item>
        <item>Replacing direct user interviews: forum complaints lack context and nuance</item>
        <item>When the audience is too specialized with no public online presence (e.g., internal enterprise users)</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="define-research-scope">
      <p>Before mining sources, establish clear boundaries on audience, domain, and research depth.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Before mining, define audience, context, domain, and a numeric goal (e.g., 20 pain points in 4 hours) so scope is bounded and progress is measurable.</statement>
        <rationale>Unbounded research produces unfocused lists; a numeric goal forces prioritization of sources and stops the researcher from mining indefinitely without output.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="mine-four-source-tiers">
      <p>Pain signals exist across four tiers, each revealing different aspects of the problem landscape. Mining all four prevents blind spots.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Mine at least 3 source types across all four tiers: Tier 1 (direct complaints: Reddit, Twitter, G2, App Store), Tier 2 (questions: Quora, Stack Overflow, Google PAA), Tier 3 (forums: Slack, Discord, Facebook, Indie Hackers), Tier 4 (job boards: Upwork, Fiverr, LinkedIn Jobs).</statement>
        <rationale>Single-source mining misses the pain landscape; job board queries ("looking for someone to...") reveal pain points users are willing to pay to outsource — the strongest signal outside of direct payment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Tier 1 (direct complaints): Reddit, Twitter, G2, App Store — highest signal, user frustration on record</item>
        <item>Tier 2 (questions): Quora, Stack Overflow, Google People Also Ask — indicate gaps in knowledge or tools</item>
        <item>Tier 3 (forums): Slack communities, Discord, Facebook groups, Indie Hackers — peer conversations, workaround discovery</item>
        <item>Tier 4 (job boards): Upwork, Fiverr, LinkedIn Jobs — revealed willingness to pay to outsource; strongest purchase intent signal</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="categorize-pain-points">
      <p>Before scoring, group pains into categories to reveal systemic patterns. Eight standard categories capture most pain types.</p>

      <p>Eight categories: Time Waste (takes too long), Money Loss (costs more than it should), Complexity (too hard to understand), Integration (tools don't work together), Reliability (doesn't work consistently), Support (can't get help), Process (workflow is broken), Learning (hard to get started). Categorize before scoring to reveal systemic patterns invisible in individual items.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="score-with-pain-intensity-matrix">
      <p>Weighted scoring separates frequent-minor pains from rare-critical pains. The formula reflects early-discovery priorities: frequency and severity matter more than willingness to pay.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Score each pain point using: Score = (Frequency x 0.3) + (Severity x 0.25) + (Reach x 0.2) + (Spend x 0.15) + (Alternatives x 0.1). Scale each dimension 1-5. Priority: &gt;4 critical, 3-4 significant, 2-3 moderate, &lt;2 deprioritize.</statement>
        <rationale>Unweighted pain lists give equal priority to frequent-minor and rare-critical pains; the weighted formula reflects that frequency and severity matter more than willingness to pay in early discovery.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Frequency (30%): How often do users encounter this pain? (1=once a year, 5=daily)</item>
        <item>Severity (25%): How bad is the pain when it happens? (1=minor annoyance, 5=blocks work entirely)</item>
        <item>Reach (20%): What fraction of the audience experiences it? (1=under 10%, 5=over 80%)</item>
        <item>Spend (15%): How much would users pay to solve it? (1=under $10, 5=over $1000)</item>
        <item>Alternatives (10%): How many alternatives or workarounds exist? (1=many, 5=none)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="extract-root-causes-via-5-whys">
      <p>Surface pain often has a different root cause than it appears. The 5 Whys method peels back layers to find the true problem.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>For top-scored pains, run 5 Whys to find the root cause before designing any solution; also use the JTBD format: "When [situation], I want to [action], so I can [outcome]."</statement>
        <rationale>Surface pain often has a different root cause than it appears; solving the symptom leaves the root intact and the user's job undone.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Pain: "I spend 3 hours/week on expense reports." Why 1: Reports are manual. Why 2: No auto-import. Why 3: No OCR integration. Why 4: IT won't approve new tools. Why 5: Process takes 6 months. Root: Organizational friction in tool adoption — not a product problem.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="research-examples">
      <p>Two worked examples of complete pain research outputs for different audiences.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Email Marketers">
        <note>Scope: solo marketers managing newsletters. Top pains by score: Deliverability issues (r/emailmarketing, Reliability, 4.5); Pricing spikes with growth (Reddit, Money, 4.0); Segmentation complexity (G2 reviews, Complexity, 4.2); Confusing analytics (Twitter rants, Complexity, 3.8); Clunky template editing (App reviews, Process, 3.5). Root cause: tools built for big teams, not solopreneurs. Opportunity: simple email tool optimized for under 10K subscribers.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Online Course Creators">
        <note>Scope: first-time course creators. Top pains: Video editing takes forever (Indie Hackers, Time Waste, 4.6); Students don't complete (Twitter, Process, 4.1); Platform fees too high (Reddit, Money, 4.3); Marketing is overwhelming (Facebook groups, Complexity, 4.0); Don't know what to teach (Quora, Learning, 3.9). Root cause: creators are content experts, not tech or marketing experts. Opportunity: done-for-you course launch service.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <p>Six critical errors that undermine pain research validity and actionability.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Surface-level research: reading only post titles, not comments.</description>
        <reason>Titles are clickbait; the pain signal is in the comments where users explain their situation with specificity.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Only one source type.</description>
        <reason>Single-source research is blind to the pain landscape; each tier reveals a different aspect of the problem space.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Not quantifying frequency or severity — treating all pains as equally important.</description>
        <reason>Without scoring, the loudest pain (most vocal users) wins over the most frequent pain (most users affected).</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Ignoring who is complaining; noting only what they complain about.</description>
        <reason>Segment matters: a pain that is severe for freelancers may be irrelevant for enterprise users even if the surface complaint is identical.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Confirmation bias: only documenting expected pain points.</description>
        <reason>Unexpected pains are often the most actionable; filtering them out produces a research report that confirms assumptions rather than challenges them.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-limitations">
      <p>Understanding where LLMs fail in pain research prevents false confidence in automated analysis.</p>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Every quote extracted by an LLM must be verified against the actual source URL before use in any decision; do not trust scores generated without explicit dimension inputs.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs hallucinate forum posts and review quotes; pain scoring is subjective and agent scores should be treated as a starting hypothesis requiring human sanity-check.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Public forum signals are biased toward vocal minority — angry users write; satisfied users are silent</item>
        <item>LLMs hallucinate forum posts and review quotes; every quote must be verified against the actual source URL</item>
        <item>Pain scoring (frequency × severity × reach) is heuristic; a human must sanity-check edge cases</item>
        <item>Reddit and App Store data require scraping or manual collection — no universal API for all sources</item>
        <item>Temporal signal is lost when mining: an old pain may already be solved by a competitor update</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Five techniques that improve research signal and prevent common pitfalls.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Mine at least 3 source types to triangulate (forum complaints + review sites + job boards)</item>
        <item>Record the source URL for every quote — verification is required before any decision</item>
        <item>Group pains into categories before scoring; categorization reveals systemic patterns invisible in individual items</item>
        <item>Use job board queries ("looking for someone to...") to find pain points users are willing to pay to outsource</item>
        <item>Run pain mining monthly for active markets — pain landscape shifts with competitor product updates</item>
        <item>Note who is complaining (segment) as carefully as what they are complaining about</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/pain-log.md" purpose="Structured log with per-pain scoring fields and summary table"/>
      <template path="templates/reddit-mining.md" purpose="Reddit mining report template (posts, quotes, patterns)"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.reddit.com/dev/api/"/>
      <link href="https://praw.readthedocs.io"/>
      <link href="https://www.intercom.com/blog/pain-points/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
