<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Secrets Management: Storage, Access, and Rotation Rules">
  <summary>Storage rules (encrypt at rest, HA), access rules (short-lived creds, no secrets in logs), rotation rules.</summary>

  <section title="Storage Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deploy Vault in a 3–5 node Raft HA cluster across availability zones; enable auto-unseal with cloud KMS (AWS KMS, GCP KMS, or Azure Key Vault) to prevent seal state after node restarts.</statement>
      <rationale>A single-node Vault is a single point of failure for the entire secrets infrastructure. Without auto-unseal, a node restart requires a human to manually unseal with threshold keys — an operational bottleneck during incident response.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable audit logging on all secrets backends and retain logs for compliance periods (minimum 90 days); set alerts on anomalous access patterns (access from new IPs, bulk secret reads).</statement>
      <rationale>Secrets access logs are the primary forensic evidence after a breach. Without them, it is impossible to determine which secrets were accessed, by whom, and when. Many compliance frameworks (SOC2, PCI-DSS) mandate audit logging for credential access.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Access Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never inject secrets at build time (Dockerfile ARG, CI environment variables baked into images); always inject at runtime via environment variables, volume mounts, or secret store SDKs.</statement>
      <rationale>Build-time secrets are captured in image layers and visible in `docker history`. CI-baked secrets appear in artifact metadata. Runtime injection keeps secrets outside the artifact and limits their exposure window to the container's lifetime.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never log secret values; configure Vault audit redaction, ensure application logging frameworks redact `password`, `token`, `secret`, and `key` fields.</statement>
      <rationale>Logs are often stored in less-secure systems (S3, Elasticsearch) accessible by more people than the secrets backend. A single debug log line containing a secret can expose it to everyone with log access.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply least-privilege Vault policies: scope secret paths to the specific namespace and application; deny `sys/*` by default.</statement>
      <rationale>Vault policies use path-based RBAC. A policy granting `secret/data/*` gives access to all secrets for all applications. Scoped paths ensure that a compromised service account can only read its own secrets, not the entire secrets tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Rotation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Automate secret rotation on a schedule (30 days typical for static credentials); use grace periods that keep both old and new credentials valid simultaneously to support zero-downtime rotation.</statement>
      <rationale>Instant rotation without a grace period causes a window where the old credential is invalid but deployed applications have not yet fetched the new one, causing connection failures. Grace periods overlap old and new credentials, allowing rolling restarts to complete before the old credential expires.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable secret scanning in pre-commit hooks (GitLeaks, detect-secrets) and in CI pipelines to detect credential commits before they reach main branch history.</statement>
      <rationale>A secret committed to Git is permanently in the history until a full Git history rewrite, which is destructive and requires all contributors to re-clone. Prevention via pre-commit hooks is far cheaper than remediation after a commit reaches the default branch.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Using Kubernetes Secrets as a secrets management solution by storing base64-encoded credentials directly in manifests committed to Git.</description>
    <reason>Kubernetes Secrets are only base64-encoded, not encrypted. They are readable by anyone with `kubectl get secret` access in the namespace. Committed to Git, they are permanently visible to all repository contributors and in CI logs.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
