<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Product Operations (PM-side) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>PM-side RACI contract with an existing Product Ops function: consumes canonical artefacts, hands off scaled-org ceremonies, never duplicates instrumentation Product Ops owns.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="raci-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The PM-↔-ProductOps boundary MUST be a written RACI per artefact (tracking-plan, OKR cascade, voice-of-customer, launch readiness).</statement>
      <rationale source="Marty Cagan / Melissa Perri — Product Ops literature">Without RACI, both sides build the same dashboard twice OR both wait for the other.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="canonical-store-consumed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When Product Ops maintains a canonical store, the PM MUST consume from it rather than build a parallel one.</statement>
      <rationale source="Productboard / Pendo enterprise patterns">Parallel stores fragment the truth and undermine Product Ops investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="scaled-ceremony-handed-off" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Once a PM-invented ceremony or template gains traction with &gt;=3 PMs, it MUST be handed off to Product Ops for templating and scaling.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Product Ops adoption audits">PM-maintained scaled artefacts produce bus-factor 1.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="instrumentation-not-duplicated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If Product Ops owns instrumentation, the PM MUST NOT add ad-hoc parallel instrumentation. Requests go through Product Ops backlog.</statement>
      <rationale source="Segment / Mixpanel governance patterns">Ad-hoc instrumentation produces orphan events.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="escalation-path-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When PM-↔-ProductOps disagree, the escalation path MUST be named in the contract.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — conflict-escalation patterns">Without a named path, the wrong exec gets dragged in and the relationship sours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — no Product Ops function (use solo); &lt;=2 PM team; consultancy with no recurring surface; recent RACI without org change), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
