<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-product-ops-maturity" title="Product Operations Maturity Model and AI-Native Ops">
  <summary>Covers the 3-level Product Ops maturity model, AI-native capabilities, 2026 market data, and PM-side maturity-gating rules.</summary>

  <section title="Maturity Model">
    <p>Level 1 Tactical: process documentation, tool management, template standardization. Level 2 Strategic: data infrastructure, insights delivery, cross-functional alignment. Level 3 Transformational: AI automation, predictive analytics, automated stakeholder communication.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Before requesting an AI-predictive capacity report from Product Ops, the PM agent checks the documented Product Ops maturity level; if Level 1, refuse the request and propose a Level 1 alternative.</statement>
      <rationale>Requesting Level 3 outputs from a Level 1 function produces either hallucinated predictions or shadow rollups that undermine the function; maturity-gating prevents PM impatience from corrupting the Product Ops contract.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="2026 Market Data">
    <p>96% of organizations have a Product Ops function. 75% of dedicated teams work centralized. 50% report directly to CPO. Top challenge: role clarity and responsibilities. PM Satisfaction tracked by 54% of teams; Collaboration Metrics by 37%; Cycle Time and Decision Quality by others.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Native Product Ops">
    <p>Level 3 AI-native capabilities: automated status updates and reporting, AI-powered roadmap analysis, predictive capacity planning, automated stakeholder communication. These capabilities require a functioning Level 2 data infrastructure first.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Product Ops is evolving from process orchestration to strategic enablement; teams must prove impact through business outcomes, not just efficiency gains.</statement>
      <rationale>PM Satisfaction as a success metric (used by 54% of teams) measures internal customer experience; it is necessary but insufficient — the PM must also track downstream product outcomes that Product Ops enabled.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="PM-Side Rules for Consuming Product Ops">
    <rule>
      <statement>Label every Product Ops output as signal in PM memos, with a fixed header: "Source: Product Ops rollup, freshness timestamp. PM decision pending below."</statement>
      <rationale>Unlabeled Product Ops outputs in PM memos blur the PM/Ops accountability boundary; the label makes the PM's decision-making role explicit and prevents decision laundering.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a quarterly contract audit with faion-improver to detect PM-side shadow rollups, Product Ops automations no PM reads, and dropped hand-offs.</statement>
      <rationale>The PM/Ops boundary drifts silently; a quarterly explicit audit is the only mechanism that surfaces drift before it becomes entrenched as the new operating model.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Name a PM-side consumer for every Product Ops automation; if a rollup has no PM reader, flag it back to Product Ops as their debt — do not silently pretend to use it.</statement>
      <rationale>Unused automations consume Product Ops capacity without producing decisions; naming consumers creates accountability on both sides of the hand-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
