<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-operations Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-operations as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>PM agent getting write token "for convenience" and starting to edit Linear tickets directly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Once an agent has write access and uses it without triggering an error, the habit is established; audit token scopes per agent in CI and refuse new writer tokens without a Product Ops co-sign.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Shadow rollups. PM subagents that read Linear/Jira/Productboard directly (instead of the Product Ops canonical store) produce numbers that diverge from the org-published figures. The PM ships a deck, Product Ops ships a different deck, trust collapses.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always read from the canonical store.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Charter drift. When a PM's own subagent gets good at status packs, the PM is tempted to skip Product Ops. Six months later the org has two parallel rollup systems and no one owns reconciliation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hard rule: PM-side agents read, Product Ops agents write.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Decision laundering. "Product Ops said the feature is at risk, so we killed it" — this offloads accountability from the PM to a function that has no decision rights.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents must label every Product Ops output as signal, never recommendation-to-kill.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Template fragmentation. PM uses brainstorm to design a new spec template, ships it inside their squad, never hands it to Product Ops. Three squads later there are three spec templates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hand-off step is mandatory.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Maturity mismatch. PM asks for AI-driven predictive capacity, Product Ops is at Level 1 (process docs only). The PM-side agent must detect and refuse the request, pointing to the maturity gap, not silently produce a fragile prediction.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Maturity mismatch becomes technical debt when a capability is built on top of immature infrastructure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>OKR-from-Product-Ops trap. Product Ops can roll up OKR progress; it cannot author meaningful OKRs. PMs who ask their subagent to "use Product Ops to write our OKRs" get cargo-culted documents.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>OKRs need strategic context the rollup does not contain; require human sign-off on every PM-authored OKR.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent saying "Product Ops recommends killing feature F-123" — recommendation laundering.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Product Ops provides signal, not recommendations; recommendations without decision authority confuse accountability. Strip "Product Ops recommends" language at the prompt level; only the PM recommends.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>PM posts a "draft" directly into Notion canonical pages because the hand-off queue felt like ceremony.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The queue is the contract, not ceremony; lock the canonical pages at the API level so "drafts" cannot bypass the queue even when the PM considers them harmless.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale rollup as fresh data. PM agent reads rollup-latest.md whose last_updated is 5 days old, presents it in an exec deck.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always read the freshness header and refuse to compose stakeholder content on stale inputs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Cargo-cult OKRs from rollups. LLM sees "feature X regressed by 12%" and proposes an OKR "improve X by 20%."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>OKRs need strategic context the rollup does not contain. Require human sign-off on every PM-authored OKR.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-system ID drift in PM artefacts. PM memo cites "feature 123" ambiguously across Productboard / Jira / Linear IDs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always resolve through the canonical mapping table Product Ops maintains.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy contamination. PM pulls customer interview transcripts into the same context as Product Ops rollups; PII leaks into the metrics store.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Keep PM narrative store and Product Ops metrics store on separate auth domains.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Charter ambiguity coded into prompts. A prompt that says "use Product Ops or just query the data yourself" trains the agent to bypass the function.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Prompts must be unambiguous: read from canonical store, hand off to Product Ops, full stop.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Maturity-skip silence. Agent silently produces a Level 3 predictive output even though Product Ops is at Level 1.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Make the maturity check a hard gate, not a soft warning.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
