<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Churn Basics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Churn Basics` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="report-three-metrics-together" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Churn report MUST simultaneously include customer churn rate, MRR churn rate, and Net Revenue Retention (NRR). Reporting any one metric in isolation is rejected at review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Recurly / OpenView SaaS benchmark reports">Single-metric churn reports hide expansion vs. contraction dynamics; NRR can mask high logo churn behind upsells. Three metrics together prevent narrative cherry-picking.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="separate-voluntary-involuntary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Voluntary churn (active cancel) and involuntary churn (failed payment) MUST be tracked separately. Combined numbers conflate marketing failure with billing failure.</statement>
      <rationale source="Profitwell churn benchmarks 2023-2024">Involuntary churn is a tooling / dunning problem (Recover, Stripe Smart Retries). Voluntary churn is a product / pricing / segment problem. Mixing them sends the team chasing the wrong fix.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="monthly-not-annualized" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Monthly churn MUST be reported as monthly. Annualizing by multiplying by 12 is forbidden — compute compounded annual churn = 1 − (1 − monthly)^12.</statement>
      <rationale source="actuarial / SaaS finance handbook">At 5% monthly, true annual churn is 46%, not 60%. Linear annualization overstates the problem and distorts forecasts, board narratives, and runway projections.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="segment-by-cohort-and-plan" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Churn MUST be segmented by acquisition cohort AND plan tier. Aggregate-only churn rates are forbidden in board / quarterly reports.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tomasz Tunguz cohort analysis posts">Aggregate churn averages aging cohorts with fresh ones and free-tier with enterprise. Cohort × plan grids surface the real failure mode — e.g. month-2 churn on starter plan.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="health-score-leading-indicator" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Health-score must include &gt;= 3 leading indicators (login frequency drop, feature usage delta, support frustration score). Backtest thresholds on historic churners before going live.</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer success operations corpus">Lagging churn rate is too late — the customer has decided. Leading indicators give a 2-4 week intervention window. Without backtesting, false-positive rate is high and CS teams ignore alerts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
