<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Trunk-Based Branch by Abstraction Core Rules" version="2.0.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the trunk-based-branch-by-abstraction methodology. Each pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="five-steps-in-order" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>BbA MUST follow the five steps in order: (1) create Protocol/interface, (2) wrap old implementation, (3) implement new code behind interface, (4) flag-gated swap + validate, (5) remove old + collapse abstraction. Skipping or reordering steps is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Martin Fowler — Branch By Abstraction">Each step is independently shippable. Out-of-order steps leave trunk in a broken or half-migrated state; skipping step 5 leaves permanent indirection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="step-5-ticket-at-step-1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A step-5 cleanup ticket MUST be filed at step-1 merge time, linked to the feature flag. Filing the ticket later is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — abstraction-debt audit">Cleanup tickets filed later are filed never. Agents move on; abstractions calcify into permanent layers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="one-flag-one-task" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each BbA migration MUST use exactly one feature flag named per the project convention (e.g., billing.use_stripe_v2). Reusing an existing flag for a different BbA is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — flag-naming convention">Flag reuse blurs ownership; cleanup becomes ambiguous; rollback affects unrelated paths.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="deletable-old-path" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After step 4 validation, the old implementation MUST be deletable by deleting only the wrapper + concrete class + flag block. If deletion requires editing call sites, the abstraction was not properly introduced.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — BbA postmortem">Step 5 should be mechanical; manual edits to call sites mean the abstraction leaked, and the migration is not safely complete.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-mixed-step-prs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each PR MUST advance exactly one BbA step. Mixing step-2 (wrap old) with step-3 (implement new) in the same PR is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PR size discipline">Step-mixing inflates diff size and makes failures hard to bisect; one-step-per-PR keeps each diff reviewable and revertable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="validate-with-dark-launch" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 4 (flag-gated swap) MUST include at least one dark-launch period (&lt; 1% traffic, full diurnal cycle) before scaling. Direct 100% flip is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Dark-launch best-practices">Dark launch catches data-shape bugs (float precision, ordering, null handling) that pass unit tests but fail on real traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
