<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="design-doc-examples">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd-planning</domain>
    <summary>Worked design doc examples for authentication features, showing AD format with FR traceability tables and file change tables for structural reference when generating design.md.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>design</tag>
      <tag>architecture-decision</tag>
      <tag>examples</tag>
      <tag>authentication</tag>
      <tag>sdd</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Design Document Examples</title>

    <summary>Concrete, worked design document examples for user authentication and related features. Provides a reference AD (Architecture Decision) format with FR traceability tables, file change tables, and component breakdowns that agents use as few-shot structural references when generating or reviewing design.md files.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Abstract templates alone do not calibrate output quality. Agents injected with a correctly structured example produce designs that match the expected AD format, FR coverage table, and file change table. The authentication example also demonstrates the decision-making narrative: alternatives table with explicit rejection reasons, consequences with trade-offs, and traceability to FR/NFR identifiers.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Generating a new design.md for a user-identity or auth-related feature — inject the auth example as few-shot context.</item>
        <item>Reviewing a generated design.md for structural gaps — compare AD format, FR coverage, and file table against the example.</item>
        <item>Onboarding a new design-writing agent that needs a calibration reference before its first real feature.</item>
        <item>Teaching the AD alternatives-and-rejection pattern when an agent produces shallow "alternatives" sections.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Copying example task names, file paths, or technology choices (JWT, bcrypt cost 12) into a real project without checking the constitution — examples encode defaults, not decisions.</item>
        <item>Frontend component hierarchy examples (RegisterForm props) in backend-only or non-React projects.</item>
        <item>Treating example file structures as required layouts rather than illustrative patterns.</item>
        <item>Running examples through automated tooling that expects live code — they are documentation artifacts, not executable code.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="fr-coverage-and-ad-structure">
      <p>Each design.md must include a FR coverage table that maps each requirement to the AD(s) that implement it. This table must be present in every design.md and must be generated last — after all ADs are written — to catch missing coverage.</p>

      <example type="good" title="FR coverage table from the authentication example">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| FR     | Requirement Summary                          | Implemented By    |
|--------|----------------------------------------------|-------------------|
| FR-001 | User registration with email/password        | AD-001, AD-002, AD-003 |
| FR-002 | Email validation required                    | AD-001            |
| FR-003 | Password strength (8+ chars, 1 upper, 1 num) | AD-002            |
| FR-004 | User login with JWT token                    | AD-004            |
| FR-005 | User logout                                  | AD-004            |
| FR-006 | Protected routes middleware                  | AD-004            |
| NFR-001| Response time < 500ms p95                    | AD-005            |
| NFR-002| bcrypt password hashing                      | AD-002            |
| NFR-003| HTTP-only cookies for tokens                 | AD-003            |
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ad-001-email-validation">
      <p>Architecture Decision 001: Email Validation Strategy. Shows full ADR format with Context/Decision/Rationale/Alternatives/Consequences/Traces.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Full ADR for email validation">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### AD-001: Email Validation Strategy

**Context:** Users must provide valid email addresses for account recovery and notifications.

**Decision:** Use Zod schema validation with RFC 5322 format check at API level.

**Rationale:**
- Immediate feedback to user on invalid format
- Prevents invalid data from reaching database
- Zod provides TypeScript type safety

**Alternatives Considered:**
| Alternative | Pros | Cons | Why Rejected |
|-------------|------|------|--------------|
| Database constraint only | Simple | No user feedback until commit | Poor UX |
| External email verification service | Catches typos | Adds latency, cost | Over-engineering for MVP |

**Consequences:**
- Positive: Fast validation, good UX, no external dependencies
- Negative: Will not catch typos in valid-format emails
- Risks: Some valid emails might be rejected by strict RFC 5322

**Traces to:** FR-001, FR-002
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ad-002-password-hashing">
      <p>Architecture Decision 002: Password Hashing. Demonstrates security trade-off reasoning and explicit rejection criteria.</p>

      <example type="good" title="AD for password hashing — note the explicit cost factor and security rationale">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### AD-002: Password Hashing

**Context:** Passwords must be stored securely to prevent breaches.

**Decision:** Use bcrypt with cost factor 12.

**Rationale:**
- Industry standard for password hashing
- Adaptive work factor (can increase as hardware improves)
- Built-in salt generation
- Cost 12 balances security and performance (~300ms hash time)

**Alternatives Considered:**
| Alternative | Pros | Cons | Why Rejected |
|-------------|------|------|--------------|
| SHA-256 | Fast | No salt, vulnerable to rainbow tables | Insecure |
| Argon2 | More secure | Less battle-tested, harder to configure | Over-engineering |
| Cost 10 | Faster | Weaker security | NFR-002 requires strong hashing |

**Consequences:**
- Positive: Strong security, proven algorithm
- Negative: ~300ms latency on registration/login
- Risks: Future hardware may require cost increase

**Traces to:** FR-001, FR-003, NFR-002
]]></code>
      </example>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>When using this example as a reference, verify the bcrypt cost factor against your project's constitution — cost 12 is not a universal default.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents copy bcrypt cost 12 from this example into every project regardless of performance constraints or constitution decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ad-003-token-storage">
      <p>Architecture Decision 003: Token Storage. Demonstrates security trade-off reasoning between XSS/CSRF protection and UX.</p>

      <example type="good" title="AD for JWT storage strategy — demonstrates security trade-off reasoning">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### AD-003: Token Storage

**Context:** JWT tokens need a storage mechanism that balances security and UX.

**Decision:** Store JWT in HTTP-only, SameSite=Strict cookies.

**Rationale:**
- HTTP-only prevents XSS attacks
- SameSite=Strict prevents CSRF attacks
- Cookies sent automatically with requests (better UX)

**Alternatives Considered:**
| Alternative | Pros | Cons | Why Rejected |
|-------------|------|------|--------------|
| localStorage | Simple, works with CORS | Vulnerable to XSS | Security risk |
| sessionStorage | Simple | Lost on tab close | Poor UX |
| In-memory only | Most secure | Lost on refresh | Poor UX |

**Consequences:**
- Positive: Strong security, automatic handling
- Negative: Slightly more complex CORS setup
- Risks: Requires HTTPS in production

**Traces to:** FR-001, FR-004, NFR-003
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ad-004-and-005-jwt-and-pooling">
      <p>Architecture Decisions 004 and 005: JWT vs Session-Based Auth and Database Connection Pooling. Shows stateless authentication scaling and performance considerations.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Remaining ADs — JWT vs session auth and connection pooling">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### AD-004: JWT vs Session-Based Auth

**Context:** Need authentication mechanism for protected routes.

**Decision:** Use JWT with 7-day expiration, no refresh tokens for MVP.

**Rationale:**
- Stateless authentication (no server-side session store)
- Scales horizontally (no shared state)
- Simpler implementation for MVP

**Alternatives Considered:**
| Alternative | Pros | Cons | Why Rejected |
|-------------|------|------|--------------|
| Session-based with Redis | Can revoke instantly | Requires Redis, stateful | More infrastructure |
| JWT with refresh tokens | Better security | Complex flow | Over-engineering for MVP |

**Consequences:**
- Positive: Simple, scalable, no external dependencies
- Negative: Cannot revoke tokens before expiration
- Risks: Compromised token valid for 7 days

**Traces to:** FR-004, FR-005, FR-006

---

### AD-005: Connection Pooling

**Context:** Database queries must meet NFR-001 (< 500ms p95).

**Decision:** Use connection pooling with min=2, max=10 connections.

**Consequences:**
- Positive: Consistent low latency, efficient resource use
- Negative: Slightly more memory usage
- Risks: Must monitor pool exhaustion

**Traces to:** NFR-001
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="file-change-table">
      <p>Every design.md must include a file change table with Action (CREATE/MODIFY/DELETE), File, Description, FR, and AD columns. Missing test files is the most common omission.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Auth feature file change table — observe that test files are explicit entries">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Action | File                              | Description                  | FR     | AD    |
|--------|-----------------------------------|------------------------------|--------|-------|
| CREATE | src/auth/handlers/register.ts    | User registration endpoint   | FR-001 | AD-001, AD-002 |
| CREATE | src/auth/handlers/login.ts       | User login endpoint          | FR-004 | AD-002, AD-004 |
| CREATE | src/auth/handlers/logout.ts      | User logout endpoint         | FR-005 | AD-004 |
| CREATE | src/auth/services/password.ts    | Password hashing/verification| FR-003 | AD-002 |
| CREATE | src/auth/services/jwt.ts         | JWT generation/verification  | FR-004 | AD-003, AD-004 |
| CREATE | src/auth/services/email.ts       | Email validation             | FR-002 | AD-001 |
| CREATE | src/auth/middleware/protect.ts   | JWT auth middleware          | FR-006 | AD-004 |
| CREATE | src/auth/types.ts                | TypeScript interfaces        | FR-001 | -     |
| CREATE | src/auth/index.ts                | Router configuration         | FR-001 | -     |
| CREATE | database/migrations/001_users.sql| User table schema            | FR-001 | -     |
| CREATE | tests/auth/register.test.ts      | Registration tests           | FR-001 | -     |
| CREATE | tests/auth/login.test.ts         | Login tests                  | FR-004 | -     |
| CREATE | tests/auth/middleware.test.ts    | Middleware tests              | FR-006 | -     |
]]></code>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>File change table without test file entries.</description>
        <reason>Agents stop after source files and treat tests as optional. Tests must be explicit CREATE entries or they will not be implemented.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="using-examples-as-few-shot-context">
      <p>Guidelines for injecting examples as structural references in design-generation prompts, including domain filtering and alternative consideration patterns.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Inject the relevant example domain (auth for user-identity features, payment for transactional features) as a structural reference in the design-generation prompt. Never mix domains.</statement>
        <rationale>TypeScript interface examples cause agents to generate TypeScript even in Python projects if example is injected without domain filtering.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Annotate example ADs with why each alternative was rejected, not just what was rejected.</statement>
        <rationale>The rejection reason is where agents learn decision-making. An alternatives table without rejection reasons produces agents that list straw-man options.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Review the generated design against the FR coverage table — every FR-X from spec must appear in at least one AD and one file entry.</statement>
        <rationale>The coverage table is the reconciliation step that catches FRs that slipped through the AD drafting pass.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <p>Common patterns where agents misapply examples by treating them as specifications or reproducing formatting rather than adapting content.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent copies bcrypt cost 12 or JWT 7-day expiry from example into every project.</description>
        <reason>Examples encode defaults, not decisions. Always filter example technology choices through the project constitution.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Alternatives Considered table always has exactly 2-3 rows because example has 2-3 rows.</description>
        <reason>The example count is illustrative. Complex decisions may need 4+ alternatives. Prompt explicitly to consider all real options.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent reproduces directory tree diagrams as ASCII art from file structure examples.</description>
        <reason>Project rules prohibit ASCII art. Use directory tree format (allowed) or a file change table only.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Component hierarchy examples assume React; agent will confuse these with backend component diagrams.</description>
        <reason>Examples demonstrate correct structure but cannot show incorrect structure being caught and fixed. Filter examples by technology stack.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Examples are static snapshots; they don't reflect how a real design evolves through review cycles.</description>
        <reason>Real designs change through feedback. Use examples as calibration points, not final answers.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Examples serve as few-shot prompts for design generation subagents. When invoking a design-writer agent, inject the relevant example (auth for user features, payment for transactional features) as a reference in the prompt. The agent uses the example's AD structure, FR coverage table format, and file change table as a template. A reviewer subagent then compares the generated design against the example's structural completeness using the FR coverage table as a checklist proxy.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Recommended subagent prompt pattern">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Generate design.md for feature: {feature_name}
Spec requirements: {fr_list}
Constitution constraints: {tech_stack}

Use this example as structural reference — match the AD format, FR coverage table,
and file change table exactly. Adapt content, not structure.

EXAMPLE:
{paste relevant sections from design-doc-examples}
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Reviewer subagent checklist">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Review the generated design.md against the structural checklist:
- FR coverage table present and complete?
- Each AD has: Context, Decision, Rationale, Alternatives Considered, Consequences, Traces to?
- File changes table has Action (CREATE/MODIFY/DELETE), File, Description, FR, AD columns?
- Testing strategy covers unit and integration?
- Risks table has Impact, Probability, Mitigation?
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Tools and services for validating and sharing design examples.</p>

      <commands>
        <command name="diff design.md design-reference.md">Compare generated design against example structure</command>
        <command name="grep -c 'AD-'">Count AD entries; complex features should have 3-7 ADs</command>
        <command name="grep 'Traces to'">Verify all ADs have FR traceability links</command>
      </commands>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Keep examples in their own methodology directory — do not inline them in templates or README files that agents load automatically (adds token cost every session)</item>
        <item>Annotate example ADs with why each alternative was rejected, not just what was rejected — this is where agents learn decision-making, not just structure</item>
        <item>Include a "wrong" example alongside each "right" example showing common mistakes (missing Consequences section, no traceability, vague Rationale)</item>
        <item>Version examples when the template format changes — agents referencing stale examples produce outdated structure</item>
        <item>Use the authentication example as a baseline for any user-identity feature; payment example for any transactional feature; do not remix across domains</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/fr-coverage-check.py" purpose="Script to verify every FR-X from spec appears in design's FR coverage table."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://github.com/joelparkerhenderson/architecture-decision-record"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/donnemartin/system-design-primer"/>
      <link href="https://12factor.net/"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/architecture/"/>
      <ref slug="design-doc-structure"/>
      <ref slug="design-doc-writing-process"/>
      <ref slug="writing-implementation-plans"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
