<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="mobile-ux-patterns">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Apply established mobile UI patterns for navigation, forms, loading, and gestures so users can navigate and complete tasks without friction on iOS and Android.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>mobile</tag>
      <tag>patterns</tag>
      <tag>ios</tag>
      <tag>android</tag>
      <tag>design</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>design</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Mobile UX Patterns &amp; Templates</title>
    <summary>Mobile-specific UI patterns for navigation (tab bars, hamburger menus), forms (progressive disclosure, inline validation), interactions (pull-to-refresh, swipe actions, long-press), loading states (skeleton screens), empty states, error recovery, and onboarding. Each pattern includes specifications for iOS and Android with touch targets, animations, and accessibility guidelines.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Mobile apps succeed when they follow platform-specific conventions—users have mental models built on thousands of hours with iOS or Android. Deviating from expected patterns causes friction, abandonment, and negative reviews. Patterns exist because they solve real problems: 44pt touch targets prevent mis-taps, bottom tab bars support one-handed use, soft deletes prevent data loss. Documented patterns prevent reinventing, reduce design review cycles, and give developers confidence the interaction is correct.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing mobile features for iOS or Android that need proven interaction models.</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing mobile app against platform guidelines (Apple HIG, Material Design) before launch.</item>
        <item>Documenting a new mobile pattern for a design system so it is reproducible across teams.</item>
        <item>Evaluating mobile UX debt—mapping deviations from established patterns to prioritize fixes.</item>
        <item>Training engineers on mobile conventions when building native components.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When the product's core differentiator is a custom interaction model (e.g., gesture-first apps)—force-fitting standard patterns may reduce the differentiator.</item>
        <item>Designing for novel form factors (foldables, wearables, AR) where established mobile patterns do not apply.</item>
        <item>As a substitute for testing on real devices with real users—pattern compliance does not equal usability for your specific context.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="navigation-patterns">
      <p>Navigation patterns determine how users discover features and move between sections. Choice of pattern (tab bar, hamburger, drawer) shapes discoverability, one-handed use, and information architecture.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use a bottom tab bar for 3-5 main sections of equal importance where users frequently switch between them. Tab bars MUST show icons and labels (iOS HIG: 49pt height; Material Design: 56dp). Icons MUST be 24-28px with at least 8pt label text. One tab MUST be visually active at all times.</statement>
        <rationale>Bottom tab bars support one-handed use on large phones (thumb reaches 60-70% of screen). Research shows 50% less discovery with hamburger menus versus visible tab bars. Always-visible tabs enable instant access without a menu gesture.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use a hamburger menu for 6 or more navigation items, secondary navigation, or less-frequently-accessed features. Icons MUST be 24x24dp/pt minimum. Menu MUST slide from left, overlay or push content, and close via X button, back gesture, or click-outside.</statement>
        <rationale>Hamburger menus hide navigation behind a gesture, reducing discoverability but conserving screen space. Reserve for secondary or low-frequency sections.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use content tabs (horizontal scrolling tabs) for 2-5 categories within a single section. Tabs MUST have 48dp/pt height with full-width touch targets. Active tab MUST show a 2-3dp underline indicator. Tabs MAY scroll horizontally if more than 5 exist.</statement>
        <rationale>Content tabs allow fast switching within one section (e.g., Feed, Messages, Notifications within a messaging app). Smaller than bottom tabs, appropriate for subcategories.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Bottom tab bar with visible icons and labels">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
┌────────────────────────────┐
│ Content area              │
│                          │
│                          │
├────────────────────────────┤
│ 🏠 Home │ 🔍 Search │ ✖ Add │ 💬 Chat │ 👤 Profile │
│ (49pt tab height)                           │
└────────────────────────────┘
]]></code>
        <note>Each tab is always visible, labeled, and easily tappable. One tab is highlighted as active.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Hamburger menu as primary navigation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
┌────────────────────────────┐
│ ☰ App Name                 │
│                          │
│ Content area              │
│                          │
│                          │
└────────────────────────────┘
]]></code>
        <note>Primary navigation hidden behind hamburger reduces discoverability by 50% versus visible tabs.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="form-patterns">
      <p>Form patterns reduce abandonment and errors by managing cognitive load, providing smart defaults, and showing users exactly where they are in a multi-step flow.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For multi-field forms, use progressive disclosure: show only essential fields on each step. Registration MUST not exceed 5 fields per screen. Steps MUST be visually indicated (e.g., "Step 1 of 3") with a back button available on each step.</statement>
        <rationale>Long forms cause abandonment. Progressive disclosure reduces perceived effort and allows users to exit without losing all input. Nielsen found registration abandonment drops from 75% (15 fields) to 30% (5 fields) with progressive steps.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Input fields MUST use appropriate keyboard types: email input triggers email keyboard, phone input triggers numeric keyboard, text area allows text suggestions. Labels MUST remain visible while the keyboard is open.</statement>
        <rationale>Platform-specific keyboards reduce typing errors and accelerate input. Invisible labels force users to scroll up to see what field they are typing in, causing errors and frustration.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Validation MUST occur on blur (user leaves field), not on keypress. Valid fields MUST show a success indicator (green checkmark). Invalid fields MUST show an error message adjacent to the field with specific guidance (e.g., "Email must include @" not "Invalid input").</statement>
        <rationale>Real-time keypress validation interrupts flow and shows errors before users have finished typing. Blur validation allows natural thinking. Specific error messages reduce correction time.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Apply smart defaults where applicable: country auto-detected from IP, phone number formatted by locale, date field shows a date picker, credit card type auto-detected from card number. Users MUST be able to override any smart default.</statement>
        <rationale>Smart defaults reduce friction without removing user agency. Auto-detection is a courtesy, not a requirement.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Progressive disclosure in registration">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Step 1 of 3: Email
┌──────────────────┐
│ Email            │
│ [            ] ✓ │
│                 │
│ [Back] [Next]    │
└──────────────────┘
(User enters email, form validates on blur, shows checkmark, cannot click Next until valid)
]]></code>
        <note>Each step shows one logical group. Labels visible. Validation on blur prevents interruption.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Long form, no step indication">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Registration Form
┌──────────────────┐
│ Email            │
│ [            ]   │
│ Password         │
│ [            ]   │
│ Name             │
│ [            ]   │
│ Phone            │
│ [            ]   │
│ Address          │
│ [            ]   │
│              [Submit]
└──────────────────┘
(15 fields on one screen, no progress indicator, user abandons)
]]></code>
        <note>No visual progress. Overwhelming field count causes abandonment.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="interaction-patterns">
      <p>Gestures and interactions must be standard, fast, and reversible. Custom gestures confuse users and should only be used when differentiating the product.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pull-to-refresh MUST be implemented for any scrollable list that can have new content. Pull distance MUST be 100-150px with visual feedback (spinner or progress indicator). Refresh MUST complete within 3 seconds on 3G or show a loading skeleton. Cancel if user scrolls back up before refresh completes.</statement>
        <rationale>Pull-to-refresh is a standard iOS and Android gesture. Users expect it in feeds, inboxes, and notification lists. Minimum pull distance prevents accidental refresh during scrolling.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Swipe actions (swipe-left, swipe-right) MUST reveal actions progressively. Full swipe MAY perform an immediate action; partial swipe MUST show action buttons. Destructive actions (delete) revealed by swipe MUST require confirmation or allow undo. Swipe MUST have a clear visual model: preview at 50%, commit at 100%.</statement>
        <rationale>Swipe actions save screen space while maintaining discoverability if buttons appear at partial swipe. Progressive reveal prevents accidental deletion.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Long-press (2+ second hold) MAY open a context menu or activate multi-select mode. On long-press, provide haptic feedback (haptic engine), visual indication (scale or highlight), and a clear exit method (tap elsewhere, Escape). Never hide primary actions behind long-press.</statement>
        <rationale>Long-press is a secondary gesture; primary actions must be visible or one-tap accessible. Haptic feedback signals that something is happening.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Pull-to-refresh with skeleton loading">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
(Pull down 100-150px)
───────────────────────  ← Progress indicator
│ ▓▓▓ Title placeholder  │  (Skeleton while loading)
│ ▓▓ Subtitle           │
│ ▓▓▓▓▓ Content         │
└───────────────────────┘
(Feels faster than spinner, shows layout)
]]></code>
        <note>Skeleton screens reduce perceived load time. Layouts match final content size.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Swipe without preview">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
(Swipe left without visual feedback)
│ Item                  │  → Item deleted immediately
│                      │  (No confirmation, no undo, no preview)
└───────────────────────┘
]]></code>
        <note>Users cannot see what action will result from swiping. Destructive without recovery.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="loading-and-empty-states">
      <p>Users perceive waiting time differently based on feedback. Skeleton screens feel faster than spinners; progressive loading shows visible progress.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For content lists and cards, use skeleton screens (gray placeholder shapes matching final content layout) instead of spinners. Load critical content first (above-the-fold), then defer below-fold content. Skeleton MUST animate at 1-2 second intervals to indicate progress without motion sickness.</statement>
        <rationale>Skeleton screens reduce perceived load time by 20-30% versus spinners (Nielsen research). Users see layout immediately, feel less uncertain. Spinners remain appropriate only for brief operations under 1 second.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Images MUST load lazily below the fold. Pre-fetch the next logical step (next page, next tab) in the background. For truly empty states (first use, user cleared all items, no search results, error), show a friendly message explaining why, a call-to-action for the next step, and optionally an illustration. Do not blame the user ("You have no items") — instead, guide them ("Add your first item").</statement>
        <rationale>Lazy loading and pre-fetching improve perceived speed. Empty state guidance reduces frustration and provides an action instead of a dead end.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Skeleton screen for list loading">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
┌─────────────────────┐
│ ▓▓▓▓▓ (shimmer)     │ ← Loading
│ ▓▓▓  ▓▓▓  ▓▓▓      │
├─────────────────────┤
│ ▓▓▓▓▓               │ ← Each item matches final layout
│ ▓▓▓                │
├─────────────────────┤
│ ▓▓▓▓▓               │
│ ▓▓▓                │
└─────────────────────┘
(User sees content is loading and what layout to expect)
]]></code>
        <note>Skeleton matches content layout exactly. Shimmer animation signals progress without being distracting.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Friendly empty state">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
┌─────────────────────┐
│                     │
│       📭            │
│    No items yet     │
│   [Add your first]  │
│                     │
└─────────────────────┘
]]></code>
        <note>Clear reason, friendly tone, action button, optional icon. User knows what to do next.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="error-and-retry-patterns">
      <p>Errors are inevitable. Recovery must be fast, clear, and not blame users.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Error messages MUST be placed adjacent to the field or action that failed. Message format: [Icon] "What went wrong" [optional reason] [Action button]. Never show error codes ("Error 404") to users—translate to human language ("Page not found"). Message tone must be friendly, never accusatory ("Email must include @" not "You entered an invalid email").</statement>
        <rationale>Proximity reduces scanning time. Human language and friendly tone reduce frustration.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Network errors MUST offer a [Retry] button. Server errors MUST offer [Retry] and [Contact support]. Temporary errors (502) MAY auto-retry with exponential backoff (1s, 2s, 4s) and show a countdown. Permanent errors MUST show a clear message and an alternative path (back to home, try different input).</statement>
        <rationale>Retry buttons give users agency. Auto-retry with countdown prevents thundering herd; countdown shows progress. Alternative paths prevent dead ends.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Contextual error with retry">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
┌──────────────────────┐
│ ⚠ Email must include │
│   an @ symbol        │
│                      │
│ [example@site.com]   │
└──────────────────────┘
(Error message next to field, specific guidance, field still editable)
]]></code>
        <note>User sees exactly what is wrong and how to fix it. Inline, not blocking.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="touch-target-sizing">
      <p>Touch targets that are too small cause mis-taps and frustration. Platform guidelines exist for a reason: ergonomics and error prevention.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Primary buttons and interactive elements MUST be at least 44pt (iOS) or 48dp (Material Design) in both width and height. Spacing between touch targets MUST be at least 8pt minimum (preferably 12pt) to prevent accidental taps of adjacent buttons.</statement>
        <rationale>44-48pt is the minimum thumb-friendly size; research confirms fewer mis-taps and faster completion. Adjacent spacing prevents fat-finger errors.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Text links within paragraphs should be tappable (wrapped in a padded area) rather than line-height only. Minimum link height MUST be 44pt; if height is constrained, increase horizontal padding around the text to meet 44pt clickable area.</statement>
        <rationale>Paragraph text is often 16-18pt; making it fully 44pt tall breaks layout. Padding achieves the touch target without inflating line-height.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="44pt buttons with 8pt spacing">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
┌───────────────────┐
│ [  [Save]  ]  8pt │
│      (44pt)       │
│      [Cancel]     │
│      (44pt)       │
└───────────────────┘
]]></code>
        <note>Buttons are 44pt minimum. 8pt spacing prevents accidental adjacent taps.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Tiny buttons with no spacing">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
┌───────────────────┐
│ [OK] [Cancel]     │  (Both 24pt, touching)
│                   │
│ Users mis-tap constantly
└───────────────────┘
]]></code>
        <note>Buttons too small. Adjacent positioning causes mis-taps.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="thumb-reachability">
      <p>On large phones (6+ inches), users hold the device with one hand. Primary actions must be reachable with thumb.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Primary actions and CTAs MUST be in the bottom 40-50% of the screen (easy zone, reachable with thumb). Avoid placing critical actions at the top center or top corners on large phones. Secondary actions and less-frequent buttons MAY use the harder-to-reach top 30%. Use the Steve Hoober thumb zone model as reference: easy zone covers bottom, hard zone covers top.</statement>
        <rationale>One-handed use is the default on mobile. The Hoober research quantifies thumb reach; placing primary actions in the hard zone increases miss rate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="CTA in easy zone (bottom)">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
(Large phone, one-handed)
┌─────────────────────┐  ← Hard zone (top center, not thumb-reachable)
│ Content area        │
│                    │
│                    │  ← Easy zone (bottom 40%, thumb-reachable)
│  [Primary CTA]     │
└─────────────────────┘
]]></code>
        <note>Primary action at bottom. Thumb reaches without shifting grip.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="orientation-and-responsive">
      <p>Users rotate their devices. Apps must handle both portrait (primary) and landscape (if needed) without losing content or breaking layout.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Apps MUST support portrait orientation (primary). Landscape orientation SHOULD be supported for content consumption (video, reading). Content MUST NOT be lost on rotation; state MUST persist (e.g., form input, scroll position). Use adaptive layouts: on portrait, stack vertically; on landscape, use two-column layout if space allows.</statement>
        <rationale>Rotation is frequent user behavior, especially on tablets. Losing content or form input on rotation causes frustration and abandonment. Adaptive layouts maximize screen real estate in landscape without breaking mobile portrait experience.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Form persists on rotation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Portrait:              Landscape:
┌─────────┐           ┌──────────────────┐
│ Name    │           │ Name   │ Email   │
│ [  ]    │           │ [ ]    │ [ ]     │
│ Email   │    →      │        │         │
│ [  ]    │           │ Phone  │ Address │
│ [Save]  │           │ [ ]    │ [ ]     │
└─────────┘           └──────────────────┘
(All input persists, layout adapts to landscape width)
]]></code>
        <note>No loss of state or data. Layout changes to use landscape width efficiently.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/mobile-design-checklist.md" purpose="Audit checklist for mobile design covering touch targets, thumb reachability, navigation, forms, performance, and accessibility."/>
      <template path="templates/mobile-pattern-template.md" purpose="Template for documenting a new mobile pattern with iOS/Android specs, behavior states, and accessibility guidelines."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/"/>
      <link href="https://m3.material.io/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/mobile-usability/"/>
      <link href="https://mobbin.design/"/>
      <link href="https://www.pttrns.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
