<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Status Report Templates by Audience Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that guarantee each audience gets a report shaped for the way they read. Each rule is verifiable from the PM's audience map and report archive — no subjective judgement required.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-audience-mapped-template" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every stakeholder receiving the weekly status MUST be mapped to ONE of four templates: CEO (3-number + 1-risk, &lt;100 words), PMO (RAG table + plan delta, ≤300 words), Technical Sponsor (scope + blockers + decisions needed, ≤400 words), Internal Leadership (narrative + ask + confidence, ≤500 words). A stakeholder receiving "all of the above" is forbidden — pick one.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stakeholder communication literature; Mike Cohn status reporting patterns">Different roles read for different signals. A CEO will not scroll past the first three lines; a technical sponsor needs the blocker detail the CEO would skip. Merging the four into one report optimises for nobody and is the modal failure mode.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-single-source-spreadsheet" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All four templates MUST be generated from ONE shared spreadsheet / Notion DB (milestone, RAG, owner, due date, blocker note, budget). The PM MUST NOT hand-edit the four reports independently. Generation can be manual copy-paste or scripted, but the source is single.</statement>
      <rationale source="DRY discipline; PM source-of-truth principle">Maintaining four parallel narratives drifts within one cycle: the CEO report says "on track" while the PMO report says AMBER. A single source enforces consistency by construction and cuts production time roughly fourfold.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-ceo-5-line-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The CEO template MUST fit in 5 lines or fewer in a plain-text email body: 1 line state ("On plan", "Slipping", "At risk"), 3 numbers (e.g. progress %, budget %, weeks to next milestone), 1 risk or ask. Attachments allowed but optional. If 5 lines cannot tell the truth, escalate via `escalation-decision-template` instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Executive scanning patterns; Bezos 6-pager inversion">CEOs read inbox previews. The 5-line cap forces the PM to write what fits in the preview pane. The discipline of compressing weekly state to 5 lines is itself a quality check: if the PM can't do it, they don't have a clear picture either.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-rag-before-prose" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The PMO template MUST lead with a RAG (Red / Amber / Green) status table covering all active workstreams BEFORE any narrative. Prose follows the table to explain Amber / Red rows. Green rows get no prose; absence of explanation is the signal of "no news, on track".</statement>
      <rationale source="PMO communication conventions; Prince2 status reporting">PMOs scan RAG dashboards. Narrative buried before the table forces them to extract the dashboard themselves, which they will not do — they will ask the PM in the next stand-up. Leading with RAG saves both parties a meeting.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-separate-technical-from-leadership" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Technical scope, dependency, and architectural decisions MUST appear in the Technical Sponsor template ONLY. The Internal Leadership template MUST translate those into business impact ("Auth migration completed; users now SSO-able with no support tickets") and MUST NOT contain raw technical language or component names.</statement>
      <rationale source="Translation discipline; common cross-functional failure mode">Putting technical detail in the leadership report tells the VP "this PM cannot translate" — eroding the trust the report was meant to build. The split keeps each audience inside its competence band and signals the PM understands theirs.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="CEO template — Week 7 of 12, mid-flight project">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Subject: Acme migration — Week 7 — On plan

State:   On plan.
Numbers: 58% complete · 51% of budget · 5 weeks to UAT.
Risk:    Vendor SSO library on hold pending their security review (no schedule
         impact yet; will impact week 9 if not resolved).
      ]]></code>
      <note>r3 satisfied — 5 lines, 3 numbers, 1 risk. CEO knows in 8 seconds whether to keep scrolling.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="One-size-fits-all report sent to everyone">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Subject: Weekly status

This week we made good progress on multiple workstreams. The team had a great
stand-up on Tuesday where we discussed the Postgres migration in depth, and we
identified that the read-replica lag will need to be addressed in week 9. The
SSO library issue from last week is still pending vendor review...
[continues for 1,400 words covering everything for everyone]
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1, r3, r4, r5 violations. CEO will not read past line 2. PMO won't find the RAG. Sponsor's blocker detail is buried. VP gets raw technical language. Nobody opens this report by week 4.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../../../../pro/pm/project-manager/client-status-report-multistyle/"/>
    <link path="../../../../pro/pm/project-manager/escalation-decision-template/"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
