<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Status Report Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed when applying status-report-templates-by-audience. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>
  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern id="fm-one-size-fits-all" severity="high">
      <symptom>Open-rate of weekly status drops below 30% by week 4; stakeholders ask in standups "what's happening?".</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Practitioner experience">Single 1400-word report sent to every audience; CEO doesn't scroll, PMO can't find RAG, sponsor misses blockers, VP gets jargon.</root-cause>
      <fix>Split into 4 audience-mapped templates from a single source spreadsheet. Reduce CEO copy to 5 lines.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="fm-source-drift" severity="high">
      <symptom>CEO report says "On plan" while PMO report shows AMBER on a workstream; clients lose trust in the PM.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Practitioner experience">Reports were hand-edited independently, no shared source. Each one drifted to a different RAG state.</root-cause>
      <fix>Generate all four from one spreadsheet (or script the generation). Edits go to the source; reports rebuild.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="fm-raw-technical-in-leadership" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Internal VP forwards the report to their boss with the message "I have no idea what this means".</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Practitioner experience">Leadership template copied technical sponsor text instead of translating to business impact.</root-cause>
      <fix>Force leadership template to use business-impact phrases only ("Auth migration completed; users SSO-enabled; no support tickets") with no component names.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="fm-rag-buried-in-prose" severity="medium">
      <symptom>PMO repeatedly asks "what's the RAG this week?" after the report is sent.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Practitioner experience">PMO template led with prose; RAG table was at the bottom or absent.</root-cause>
      <fix>Lead with RAG table in PMO template; Green rows take no prose; Amber/Red get a sentence each.</fix>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
