<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Viral Metrics and K-factor Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Viral Metrics and K-factor` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="k-equals-i-times-c" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Canonical K-factor formula MUST be K = i * c where i = avg invites sent per user, c = invitee-to-active conversion rate. Other formulations (e.g. invite-to-signup) are derivatives and must be labeled.</statement>
      <rationale source="Andrew Chen viral coefficient definition; Sequoia growth math">Mixed definitions across reports yield uncomparable numbers. K = i * c is the canonical formulation; everything else is a labeled variant.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="measure-weekly-not-cumulative" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>K-factor MUST be measured weekly (cohort-based), not as cumulative all-time. Cumulative K averages dead loops with active ones.</statement>
      <rationale source="viral-metrics field manual; Reforge curriculum">Cumulative K hides decay. Weekly cohort K shows whether loop is gaining or losing momentum — actionable signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="decompose-i-and-c-separately" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Report MUST surface i and c separately. Combined K alone hides which leg is the bottleneck.</statement>
      <rationale source="Viral optimization corpus (PayPal, Dropbox postmortems)">K = 0.2 from i=2, c=10% has different fix than K = 0.2 from i=0.5, c=40%. Decomposition tells team which leg to optimize.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="track-viral-cycle-time" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Viral cycle time (mean days from user activation → invite sent → invitee active) MUST be measured. Long cycle times mute compound growth even with high K.</statement>
      <rationale source="Adam Penenberg Viral Loop; cycle-time math">K=0.5 + 7-day cycle = different growth than K=0.5 + 30-day cycle. Cycle time multiplies the loop power; tracking it surfaces the silent bottleneck.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="retention-adjusted-k" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Effective K MUST adjust for retention: K_eff = K * D30_retention. Report both raw K and K_eff. Raw K alone overstates loop value on leaky-bucket products.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brian Balfour growth-loop framework">Raw K on a 15% D30 product is theatre — invitees vanish. K_eff = K * retention shows real compounding. Decision-maker needs both.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
