<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-optimization" title="Improving i and c — Viral Optimization Levers">
  <summary>Tactics to increase invites-per-user (i) and invite conversion rate (c), with common mistakes to avoid.</summary>

  <section title="Increasing i (Invites per User)">
    <list>
      <item>Natural share moments: prompt sharing at the instant of an achievement or result — not on first login</item>
      <item>Referral incentives: reward referrers; double-sided (both parties rewarded) converts better than single-sided</item>
      <item>Multi-channel sharing: email, SMS, copy-link, social — users have channel preferences</item>
      <item>Contact import: allow bulk invite from address book to lower per-invite friction</item>
      <item>Viral content: shareable artifacts (results page, badge, score) that embed product branding</item>
      <item>Team/collaboration features: product that requires others to use inherently drives invites</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Increasing c (Invite Conversion Rate)">
    <list>
      <item>Personal invitation copy: "John invited you to [Product]" vs generic blast — high impact</item>
      <item>Social proof: "5 of your colleagues already use this" — high impact</item>
      <item>Clear value proposition on landing page: one sentence, no jargon</item>
      <item>Low-friction signup: one-click social auth, minimal fields — high impact</item>
      <item>Incentive for invitee: "$10 when you join" — medium impact, verify margin allows it</item>
      <item>Preview of value before signup: show what they will get, not just marketing copy</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Measurement Checklist">
    <list>
      <item>Track: invite_sent event with loop_type and share_channel properties</item>
      <item>Track: invite_clicked, referral_signup, referral_activated events</item>
      <item>Compute i, c, K weekly; flag K drops &gt; 20% week-over-week</item>
      <item>Segment K by acquisition channel and user cohort to find viral power users</item>
      <item>Do not report K computed on fewer than 500 invites — noise dominates at small samples</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Over-incentivizing referrals (50%+ reward to hit K=1).</description>
    <reason>Attracts fraud and low-quality users who joined for the reward. Sets unsustainable cost expectations. K plateaus quickly; agents optimizing reward size erode margin without meaningful K lift.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Using a single invite channel (email only).</description>
    <reason>Users have strong channel preferences. Email-only sharing misses SMS and social invites that convert at 25% vs email's 12-15% in many consumer apps.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Sending generic invite blasts from the product (outbreak/spam virality).</description>
    <reason>Modern email filters and OS protections block automated contact imports. Damages brand NPS and can trigger CAN-SPAM violations.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
