<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Edge-Case Checklist Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Edge-Case Checklist. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-ten-closed-cases" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Checklist is exactly 10 cases: long-text, RTL, slow-network, no-data, error-state, offline, dark-mode, small-screen, a11y-screen-reader, time-zone. Custom additions go in a separate checklist.</statement>
      <rationale source="Closed-taxonomy principle">Open lists become aspirational and get skipped; 10 closed cases stay runnable in &lt;10 minutes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-yes-no-na-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each case is answered YES / NO / N/A with a one-line visual treatment note; vague &apos;maybe&apos; or &apos;partial&apos; answers are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-rule stability">Binary answers force a clear treatment; &apos;partial&apos; hides regret.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-na-requires-reason" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>N/A answers carry a one-line reason (&apos;component is read-only — no RTL input concern&apos;); silent N/A is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Falsifiability principle">Silent N/A erodes the checklist; reasons make N/As auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-handoff-blocked-on-no" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any case with NO answer blocks handoff until either the design is updated to YES or the team explicitly accepts the debt (recorded in design-decision-log).</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-debt convention">Silent NO ships bugs to production; the block + decision-log path makes debt deliberate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-checklist-run-pre-handoff" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Checklist runs BEFORE design-to-dev handoff begins; mid-handoff checklist runs are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Process-discipline convention">Mid-handoff edge cases force rework; pre-handoff catch shifts the cost left.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-edge-case-checklist.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
