<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="design-doc-writing-process Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for design-doc-writing-process. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Read constitution.md, contracts.md, spec.md, and completed done/ designs BEFORE writing any section. Extract tech stack constraints, naming conventions, and existing patterns.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Designs written without constitution context violate tech stack decisions. Designs written without done/ patterns introduce duplicate or conflicting architectural choices.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run codebase research before writing any architecture decision. Invest 20-40k tokens here. Designs skipping Phase 2 conflict with existing patterns.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Naming inconsistencies, duplicate service patterns, and API contracts that conflict with existing routes are all caused by skipping Phase 2.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build the FR coverage table before writing any AD. Every FR-X and NFR-X must map to at least one AD candidate. Gaps found here are cheaper to fix than gaps found after ADs are written.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The traceability matrix is the planning instrument for Phase 4. Without it, ADs are written in isolation and FRs are accidentally omitted.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each AD must include Context, Decision, Rationale (minimum 2 reasons), Alternatives Considered (minimum 2 real alternatives with rejection reasons), Consequences (positive/negative/risks), and Traces to FR-X.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Future agents reading design.md need to understand why a path was NOT taken. Missing Consequences and rejection reasons cause agents to re-open closed decisions during implementation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every file in the implementation must appear in the Files table with Action (CREATE/MODIFY/DELETE), File path, Description, FR, and AD columns. Test files must be explicit entries.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Files not in the table are not implemented. Agents stop after source files and treat tests as optional unless tests are listed explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Data model tables must include a constraints column. Omitting constraints causes migration failures when the executor implements the schema.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Executor agents implement exactly what the table shows. Missing NOT NULL, UNIQUE, or FK constraints are silently omitted from migrations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If contracts.md exists: write "See contracts.md section X" — do not redefine endpoints in design.md. If contracts.md does not exist: document each endpoint with method, path, request/response schema, and all 4xx/5xx error responses.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Two sources of truth for API contracts always drift. Executor agents implement from design.md and produce code that diverges from the actual contract.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write API contracts (Phase 7) only after data models (Phase 6) are finalized. Contracts referencing undefined model fields produce executor tasks with incomplete validation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Data model field types, constraints, and names determine the contract's request/response shapes. Reversing the order produces contracts that do not match the models.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
