<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Long-Game Reddit Marketing Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Long-Game Reddit Marketing application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-lurk-before-post" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Account MUST accumulate ≥30 days of organic comments + ≥100 karma in target subreddits before any promotional post. Direct promo from a new account is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">New-account promo is the #1 ban trigger; mod tools flag it within hours.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-value-to-promo-ratio" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Posting mix MUST be ≥10 value posts per 1 promotional post per subreddit. Higher promo ratios are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Reddit's culture punishes self-promotion above this ratio with shadowbans even if mods don't act.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-read-each-subreddit-rules" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each target subreddit MUST have its rules read and the rule sheet attached to the plan. Cross-posting without rule check is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Per-subreddit rules vary wildly; one violation can lose the account.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-no-link-only-posts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Posts MUST carry standalone value in the body; link-only posts are rejected unless the subreddit explicitly permits them.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Link-only posts read as marketing spam regardless of source.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-account-distinct-from-throwaway" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The brand account MUST be a single named account with profile + history. Throwaways for promo are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Mods cross-check accounts; throwaways tank trust and are removed.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
