<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="PMBoK 7 and 8 Reference Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the ref-pmbok methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="show-formula-and-result" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always show formula AND result when reporting EVM metrics. Never emit only the computed value.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI audit guidance">Audit trails require reproducibility; a bare '$92K EAC' without formula cannot be verified or challenged.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="clamp-zero-denominators" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Clamp EVM denominators to avoid division by zero. When PV or AC is zero, emit null for affected metrics rather than infinity or NaN.</statement>
      <rationale source="Numerical stability practice">LLM arithmetic on near-zero denominators produces nonsense results that look plausible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="name-estimation-technique" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Present estimation accuracy bands as heuristics with ranges, never as guarantees; name the technique alongside the band.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK estimation chapter">Sponsors anchor on the tightest band regardless of technique used; the band is technique-dependent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="one-strategy-per-risk" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pair every risk entry with exactly one response strategy. A risk without a strategy is an observation, not a managed risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK 7 risk domain">Risk registers without strategies are decoration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rag-recalibration" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If more than 50% of projects in a portfolio are amber, the RAG threshold is miscalibrated, not the projects. Recalibrate before acting.</statement>
      <rationale source="Portfolio-management practice">RAG inflation destroys the signal; amber must be rare enough to trigger genuine attention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pin-edition" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin the PMBoK edition in every project charter and in every agent system prompt that generates PM content.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — edition-drift audits">PMBoK 6 is over-represented in training data; without explicit pinning, agents default to 6th edition vocabulary.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>As a standalone methodology to do anything — pair with operational methodologies</item>
      <item>Non-PMI frameworks (PRINCE2, IPMA, ISO 21500) — vocabulary overlaps but differs</item>
      <item>Agile-only environments with no baseline — EVM formulae are meaningless</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
