<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-pmbok7-reference" title="PMBoK 7 Reference Tables">
  <summary>PMBoK 7 eight performance domains, twelve principles, EVM formulae, estimation accuracy bands, risk response strategies, and RAG thresholds.</summary>

  <section title="PMBoK 7 Performance Domains">
    <list>
      <item>Stakeholder — engaging stakeholders; outcome: agreement on objectives and sustained support</item>
      <item>Team — building high-performing teams; outcome: shared ownership and growth</item>
      <item>Development Approach — selecting predictive/agile/hybrid; outcome: right approach for context</item>
      <item>Planning — scope, schedule, cost, resources; outcome: realistic and achievable plans</item>
      <item>Project Work — executing and monitoring; outcome: efficient delivery</item>
      <item>Delivery — value and outcomes; outcome: benefits realised</item>
      <item>Measurement — tracking with metrics; outcome: data-driven decisions</item>
      <item>Uncertainty — risks and complexity; outcome: managed uncertainty</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="PMBoK 7 Twelve Principles">
    <list>
      <item>P-01 Stewardship: act with integrity, be accountable</item>
      <item>P-02 Team: build culture of accountability and respect</item>
      <item>P-03 Stakeholders: engage proactively</item>
      <item>P-04 Value: focus on outcomes, not outputs</item>
      <item>P-05 Systems Thinking: see the whole, understand interdependencies</item>
      <item>P-06 Leadership: inspire, adapt style, enable others</item>
      <item>P-07 Tailoring: adapt processes to context</item>
      <item>P-08 Quality: build quality into processes</item>
      <item>P-09 Complexity: navigate with appropriate strategies</item>
      <item>P-10 Risk: balance risk with reward</item>
      <item>P-11 Adaptability: embrace change, learn from experience</item>
      <item>P-12 Change: enable envisioned future state</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="EVM Quick Reference">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always show formula AND result when reporting EVM metrics. Never emit only the computed value — auditors need the formula to verify the calculation.</statement>
      <rationale>Audit trails require reproducibility. A bare "$92K EAC" without formula cannot be verified or challenged.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Clamp EVM denominators to avoid division by zero. When PV or AC is zero, emit null for the affected metrics rather than infinity or NaN.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM arithmetic on EVM rows with zero or near-zero denominators produces nonsense results that look plausible. Code calculation with explicit guards is required.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>SV (Schedule Variance) = EV - PV; positive = ahead of schedule</item>
      <item>CV (Cost Variance) = EV - AC; positive = under budget</item>
      <item>SPI (Schedule Performance Index) = EV / PV; greater than 1 = ahead</item>
      <item>CPI (Cost Performance Index) = EV / AC; greater than 1 = under budget</item>
      <item>EAC (Estimate at Completion) = BAC / CPI</item>
      <item>ETC (Estimate to Complete) = EAC - AC</item>
      <item>VAC (Variance at Completion) = BAC - EAC</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/evm-calculator.py">EVM calculator with RAG output</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Estimation Accuracy Bands">
    <list>
      <item>Analogous: -50% to +100% — early stages, rough order of magnitude</item>
      <item>Parametric: -10% to +25% — historical data available</item>
      <item>Bottom-up: -5% to +10% — detailed scope defined, most accurate</item>
      <item>Three-point (PERT): variable — risk-aware, useful with high uncertainty</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Present estimation accuracy bands as heuristics with ranges, never as guarantees. An agent that quotes "+/- 10%" without "bottom-up only" misleads sponsors.</statement>
      <rationale>Sponsors anchor on the tightest accuracy band regardless of which technique was used. The technique must be named alongside the band.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Risk Response Strategies">
    <list>
      <item>Threats: Avoid (eliminate), Mitigate (reduce probability/impact), Transfer (shift to third party), Accept (acknowledge and monitor)</item>
      <item>Opportunities: Exploit (ensure occurrence), Enhance (increase probability/impact), Share (partner to capture), Accept (take if occurs)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always pair a risk entry with exactly one response strategy. A risk without a strategy is an observation, not a managed risk.</statement>
      <rationale>Risk registers that lack strategies are decoration. The strategy and owner are what make a risk register actionable in execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="RAG Status">
    <list>
      <item>Green: on track — continue monitoring</item>
      <item>Amber: at risk — corrective action plan required within 48 hours</item>
      <item>Red: off track — escalation required immediately</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>If more than 50% of projects in a portfolio are amber, the RAG threshold is miscalibrated, not the projects. Recalibrate before acting on individual project statuses.</statement>
      <rationale>RAG inflation (everyone is amber) destroys the signal. Amber must be rare enough that it triggers genuine attention.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
