<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-pmbok8-delta" title="PMBoK 8 Changes and Agent Edition Drift">
  <summary>Key changes from PMBoK 7 to PMBoK 8 and the agent failures that occur when training-data edition bias overrides the instructed edition.</summary>

  <section title="PMBoK 8 Core Changes">
    <list>
      <item>Principles: 12 (PMBoK 7) streamlined to 6 (PMBoK 8): Stewardship and Ethics, Collaboration, Value Optimisation, Systems and Complexity, Adaptability, Sustainability</item>
      <item>Performance Domains: 8 (PMBoK 7) reorganised to 7 (PMBoK 8): see seven-performance-domains methodology</item>
      <item>Sustainability: moved from "mentioned" in PMBoK 7 to a core principle in PMBoK 8; requires a measurable proxy (CO2 per release, accessibility audit pass rate)</item>
      <item>AI in PM: no coverage in PMBoK 7; dedicated appendix in PMBoK 8 covering schedule prediction, risk analysis, resource optimisation, status reporting</item>
      <item>Processes: none (fully principle-based in PMBoK 7) to 40 non-prescriptive processes in PMBoK 8</item>
      <item>Quality: integrated throughout all domains in both editions; never a standalone domain</item>
      <item>Communications: merged into Stakeholders domain in PMBoK 8</item>
      <item>Procurement: moved to appendix in PMBoK 8; no longer a standalone domain</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Edition Drift Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin the PMBoK edition in every project charter and in every agent system prompt that generates PM content. Never let an agent assume the edition.</statement>
      <rationale>PMBoK 6 is over-represented in training data. Without explicit pinning, agents default to the 6th edition vocabulary (knowledge areas, process groups) regardless of instruction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent output contains "Integration Management", "Cost Management", or "Communications Management" as domain names.</description>
      <reason>These are PMBoK 6 knowledge area names. In PMBoK 7/8 these are replaced by Governance, Finance, and integrated Stakeholders respectively. Output containing these names must be regenerated with PMBoK 7/8 vocabulary pinned.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent applies EVM metrics to a pure-agile project with no scope or cost baseline.</description>
      <reason>EVM requires a baseline. Without one, SPI and CPI are undefined. Agile metrics (cycle time, flow efficiency, throughput) must be used instead.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>"RAG" used without spelling out Red/Amber/Green on first use in PM contexts.</description>
      <reason>"RAG" is also retrieval-augmented generation. In PM system prompts, abbreviation without disambiguation causes agents to hallucinate RAG retrieval references in status reports.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../seven-performance-domains/content/01-domains.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
