<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Scope-Creep Email Language Pack Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every push-back email must follow so the response is firm without being adversarial and converts creep into change orders instead of absorbed work.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-acknowledge-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The first sentence acknowledges the request as legitimate and useful before any push-back. Replies that open with "this is out of scope" or "we did not agree to" are rejected; rephrase to lead with "this is a useful idea — here is how we can do it cleanly".</statement>
      <rationale source="De-escalation phrasing">Opening with a refusal triggers defensiveness regardless of how the rest of the message reads. Acknowledging first preserves the relationship and lets the substance land; this is purely a phrasing rule, not a substance rule — the answer can still be "no".</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-reframe-as-change-order" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every push-back must explicitly name "this is a change to the agreed scope" and offer a concrete next step (change-order link, rate, calendar slot to scope it). "Sorry, we can't" alone is rejected. The change-order framing turns "no" into "yes, here is how" without absorbing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Yes-and pricing">Bare refusals teach clients to escalate or work around the freelancer. Reframing converts the same conversation into a commercial one with a clear path, which is the only outcome that preserves both relationship and margin.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-no-absorb-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The language pack must NOT contain a default "we'll just include this one" phrasing. The closest allowed phrasing is "we'll log this as goodwill for engagement &lt;id&gt; and review at next checkpoint" — the goodwill must be named, logged, and budget-capped (max 5% of engagement value across the engagement).</statement>
      <rationale source="Compounding-creep avoidance">Absorbing once teaches the client that asking works. The named-goodwill phrasing preserves the option (sometimes worth it) but caps the cumulative absorption and surfaces the pattern at the next checkpoint so the founder can re-price.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-rotate-phrasings" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per-client send-log must track which phrasing has been used with this client. The same exact phrasing must not be sent to the same client twice in a row; if no fresh option exists, the founder edits the phrasing or escalates to a call.</statement>
      <rationale source="Template-fatigue avoidance">Identical phrasing twice tells the client they are talking to a template, not a partner. Rotating preserves the polite-firm effect while keeping the relationship human. The "escalate to a call" fallback covers the case where the founder is out of phrasings — that is itself a signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-log-the-send" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every send logs: engagement_id, scenario_used (one of the 7 indexed scenarios), phrasing_id, client_response (within 7 days: accepted-change-order | declined | silent | counter-proposed), and outcome ($ recovered or absorbed). Unlogged sends are not part of the practice.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practice over event">The pack improves only if its outcomes are tracked. The 7-day response classification surfaces which scenarios consistently convert and which always go silent; the $ outcome closes the loop between phrasing choice and engagement margin.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies-If preconditions fail OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or to no methodology at all).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application of a methodology produces worse artefacts than no methodology at all because downstream consumers trust the schema and act on bad data. The skip-record makes the non-application traceable so future audits can detect drift.</rationale>
    </rule>


  </section>

  <example>
    <description>Indexed phrasing for the "tiny tweak" scenario, with rule-conformance.</description>
    <code language="markdown">
### Scenario: "Tiny tweak" — client asks for an apparently small change that is actually out of scope

**Use as-is, replace [bracketed] parts:**

&gt; Hi [name],
&gt;
&gt; Good catch on [the field change] — that would definitely make [the thing] cleaner.
&gt; (r1 acknowledge)
&gt;
&gt; Looking at our SOW for [engagement-name], this lands outside the [section X] we
&gt; scoped, so I'd want to handle it through a small change order so it doesn't
&gt; squeeze the items we already committed to this sprint.
&gt; (r2 reframe-as-change-order)
&gt;
&gt; Two options:
&gt;   • Quick add to scope: I'll send a 1-line change order at our [rate]; usually
&gt;     ~[N] hours of effort end-to-end.
&gt;   • Defer to phase 2: I'll add it to the v2 backlog with your note attached.
&gt; (r2 concrete next step)
&gt;
&gt; If it helps, happy to jump on 15 minutes tomorrow to pick the path.
&gt; (escalation option per r4)
&gt;
&gt; — [founder]

phrasing_id: tiny-tweak-v1
last_used_with: acme-co (2026-04-12)
last_outcome: accepted-change-order, $480 recovered
    </code>
  </example>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../scope-creep-firewall/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../change-request-impact-rubric/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
