<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="On-Call Handoff Protocol Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of oncall-handoff-protocol enforces. Each rule has a statement, a rationale anchored to industry practice, and a source citation.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every handoff lists active incidents with: status, last action, next step, owner.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Book — On-call">Without an active incidents block, the incoming engineer rediscovers fire-fighting state from scratch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every handoff lists follow-up items with explicit dates / SLAs and an owner.</statement>
      <rationale source="PagerDuty Incident Response 2025">Loose follow-ups become forgotten work and re-emerge as repeat incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Incoming engineer acknowledges receipt in writing before shift hands over.</statement>
      <rationale source="Increment Magazine — On-call issue">Verbal acks evaporate; written ack is the closing artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Even a quiet shift produces a one-line handoff ('no incidents, no follow-ups, no fatigue').</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Book — On-call">Empty handoffs are still data; missing handoffs hide drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Outgoing engineer signals fatigue level (low/medium/high); high fatigue escalates to ops lead, not silent.</statement>
      <rationale source="PagerDuty research on operator burnout 2025">Hidden fatigue compounds across shifts and produces incident-causing oversight.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, skip this methodology and route to the adjacent one referenced in Related.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 skill-authoring conventions">A skip rule keeps the decision tree closed: every branch ends at a real rule id.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>