<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Beta Cohort Communication Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Beta Cohort Communication application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="one-ask-per-send" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every broadcast MUST contain exactly one ask (use the new feature, reply with a use-case, fill a 2-question survey). Multiple asks dilute response rate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Email-marketing research">Email-marketing research — anchors Beta Cohort Communication rule `one-ask-per-send`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="three-message-types" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All communication MUST classify as one of: weekly recap, single-ask survey, milestone announcement. Other shapes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Beta-lifecycle research">Beta-lifecycle research — anchors Beta Cohort Communication rule `three-message-types`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-segment-tags" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cohort messages MUST tag the recipient segment (early-adopter / quiet / lapsed). Untagged sends prevent recovery flows.</statement>
      <rationale source="Lifecycle marketing">Lifecycle marketing — anchors Beta Cohort Communication rule `named-segment-tags`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="reply-sla-72h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Founder MUST reply to cohort questions within 72h. Slower = cohort assumes beta is abandoned.</statement>
      <rationale source="Beta-engagement field reports">Beta-engagement field reports — anchors Beta Cohort Communication rule `reply-sla-72h`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="graduation-message-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cohort MUST receive a graduation message (paid offer or polite sunset) at the charter&apos;s end-date. Skipping = cohort feels orphaned and stops responding.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cohort-graduation practice">Cohort-graduation practice — anchors Beta Cohort Communication rule `graduation-message-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
