<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Beta Cohort Communication Cadence Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Beta Cohort Communication Cadence application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-weekly-broadcast" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send a weekly broadcast: what shipped, what's coming, what we need from you. ≤300 words. Same day + same time each week.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Cohorts decay without cadence; predictability creates the open-the-email habit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-targeted-feedback-90-percent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>≥90% of cohort completes ≥1 targeted feedback (Loom, form, call) per month. Track per-user completion; chase the missing 10%.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Cohorts where most users never give feedback are pre-churn cohorts; targeted ask is the leading indicator.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-graduation-criteria" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define graduation criteria up front: minimum usage, ≥1 feedback session, opted into launch tier. Graduation = beta ends, paid plan begins.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Open-ended betas drift to zombie; explicit graduation creates a natural commercial transition.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-public-credit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Public credit for beta users: changelog mentions, beta-tester badge, early-adopter discount lock-in. Trust is built by visible recognition.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Public credit converts beta cohort into testimonial source + word-of-mouth distribution.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-alumni-program" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post-graduation, beta alumni get: lifetime founder discount, dedicated Slack channel, early access to next features. Alumni become permanent feedback loop.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Beta cohort is the most informed user base; losing them at graduation is wasteful.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>