<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-positioning-and-content" title="Twitter/X Positioning, Content Strategy, and Thread Structure">
  <summary>Positioning formula, content pillar definitions, thread structure, and reply strategy for Twitter/X growth.</summary>

  <section title="Positioning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define your Twitter identity across four elements before posting: topic (what you talk about), angle (what is unique), voice (how you sound), and format (content types).</statement>
      <rationale>Without a clear positioning, followers cannot predict what they will get and have no reason to follow. Positioning creates expectation and repeat engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Bio formula: [What you do] | Building [product] | [Social proof] | [CTA]. Keep under 160 characters.</statement>
      <rationale>The bio is the first conversion surface. Visitors who land on your profile from a reply or mention will decide in 3 seconds whether to follow based on the bio.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pinned tweet should be the best-performing content or a clear offer. Update it when a new high-performer emerges.</statement>
      <rationale>The pinned tweet is the second thing visitors see after the bio. It should demonstrate content quality and provide a CTA.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Thread Structure">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Thread tweet 1 must standalone as a compelling post without reading the rest — it is the main distribution surface. External links reduce reach; put links in the first reply or bio.</statement>
      <rationale>X's algorithm uses tweet 1 engagement (likes, retweets, bookmarks) to decide whether to distribute the rest of the thread. A weak tweet 1 kills the whole thread.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Tweet 1: Hook — problem or bold claim</item>
      <item>Tweet 2: Promise — what they will learn</item>
      <item>Tweets 3-8: Value — the actual content</item>
      <item>Tweet 9: Summary + CTA</item>
      <item>Tweet 10: Follow ask</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Tweet 1 for a build-in-public account: "I went from $0 to $15K MRR in 8 months without paid ads. Here's the exact playbook: [thread emoji]" — specific numbers, promise of value, clear format signal.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Thread hook: "I have 10 tips for growing on Twitter [thread]"</description>
      <reason>Generic number-list hooks are overused. The algorithm sees low engagement on tweet 1 and does not distribute the thread. Use niche-specific, counterintuitive hooks instead.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Reply Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reply to 20-30 accounts larger than you daily using the [React] + [Add value] + [Question or take] formula. Be first or early with a valuable reply.</statement>
      <rationale>Being a consistent, early, thoughtful voice in 3-5 large accounts' comments builds recognition faster than standalone posting because it borrows existing audience attention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Build-in-public posts with real numbers (MRR, user count, specific percentages) outperform vague narrative posts by 2-5x on engagement.</statement>
      <rationale>Specificity signals authenticity and provides concrete value. Audiences can benchmark their own progress against real numbers; they cannot benchmark against vague claims.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/thread-template.md">10-tweet thread structure with hook, promise, value, summary, and CTA slots</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-weekly-content.txt">Agent prompt for 15 tweets + 1 thread + 1 build-in-public update per week</reference>
  </section>
</text>
