<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-growth-metrics" title="Twitter/X Growth Metrics, Conversion, and Failure Modes">
  <summary>KPI targets, conversion tactics, common mistakes, virality triggers, and X API constraints relevant to agents.</summary>

  <section title="KPI Targets">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Track profile visits, follower growth rate, engagement rate, thread views, and newsletter signups from Twitter as primary KPIs.</statement>
      <rationale>Follower count alone is misleading. Profile visits and newsletter signups measure conversion from attention to audience relationship.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Profile visits: 500/week = good, 2K/week = great</item>
      <item>Follower growth: 50/week = good, 200/week = great</item>
      <item>Engagement rate: 2% = good, 5%+ = great</item>
      <item>Thread views: 5K = good, 50K+ = great</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Conversion Tactics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow → Newsletter → Free users → Paid customers. Twitter converts best to email; email converts to customers. Do not try to sell directly from tweets.</statement>
      <rationale>Twitter followers are an attention asset, not a customer list. Email captures that attention in a higher-intent, lower-distraction channel where conversion rates are 5-10x higher.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Pin a tweet with your best offer</item>
      <item>CTA in bio pointing to newsletter or product</item>
      <item>Build in public — show product progress and customer wins</item>
      <item>Limited-time offers for followers in threads</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Inconsistent posting — missing days or weeks.</description>
      <reason>X's algorithm reduces distribution for accounts with erratic cadence. Even one tweet per day maintains algorithm favor; missing multiple days resets momentum.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Only promotional content — no value posts.</description>
      <reason>Promotional-only accounts get unfollowed. The 80% value / 20% promo ratio is minimum; accounts under 1K followers should be 95/5.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Including links in tweet bodies.</description>
      <reason>X significantly reduces distribution of tweets with external links. Links belong in the first reply, pinned tweet, or bio.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent and API Constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>X API Basic tier allows 1,500 posts/month. Track usage if using agent-driven scheduling — bulk generation can exhaust quota and lock out manual posting.</statement>
      <rationale>Quota exhaustion blocks all automated and manual API-authenticated actions. Preserve quota for the highest-value posting windows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/twitter-analytics.py">Parse Twitter Analytics CSV export to compute engagement rate and identify top hook patterns</reference>
  </section>
</text>
