<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-trend-lifecycle" title="Trend Lifecycle and STEEP Analysis">
  <summary>Trend categories, adoption curve stages, entry timing rules, and the STEEP analysis framework.</summary>

  <section title="Trend Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Fad: weeks to months duration; no structural driver; avoid building a business on it</item>
      <item>Trend: 2-5 year window; structural driver exists (technology, demographics, regulation); the solopreneur sweet spot</item>
      <item>Megatrend: decade-scale; high certainty but slow to monetize; entry point is a specific sub-trend within it</item>
      <item>Shift: permanent structural change; treat as the new baseline, not an opportunity in itself</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Adoption Curve Stages and Entry Timing">
    <list>
      <item>Innovators: define the category; too early — no market exists yet, education cost dominates</item>
      <item>Early Adopters: high margins but you educate the market for competitors; viable if you have a distribution advantage</item>
      <item>Early Mainstream (optimal entry): market aware, solutions emerging, growth inflecting — enter here</item>
      <item>Late Mainstream: volume available but commoditization accelerating; viable only with cost or distribution moat</item>
      <item>Decline: shrinking market; enter only if you are serving a niche/legacy segment deliberately</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require a quantitative anchor for any "Early Mainstream" claim: category spend at top 3 players, named buyer logos, or revenue data. Reject the label if only qualitative signals support it.</statement>
      <rationale>"Early Majority" labels are subjective and unfalsifiable without quantitative anchors. The same trend can look "early" or "late" depending on the analyst's framing and the segment chosen.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="STEEP Analysis Framework">
    <list>
      <item>Social: behavior and value shifts (e.g., remote-work normalization, privacy expectations, demographic aging)</item>
      <item>Technology: enabling tech and capability thresholds (e.g., GPT-4 function calling, WebAssembly, CRISPR)</item>
      <item>Economic: financial forces (e.g., interest-rate cycle, labor cost arbitrage, VC dry powder cycles)</item>
      <item>Environmental: sustainability factors and climate risk (e.g., carbon pricing, ESG mandates, supply-chain resilience)</item>
      <item>Political: regulatory landscape and policy pipeline (e.g., EU AI Act, MiCA, GDPR, FTC enforcement trends)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track the regulatory pipeline as a separate axis from STEEP-Political, with explicit stage (proposal / enacted / in-force) and effective date. Proposed rules are not yet constraints; enacted rules with a future effective date are the real driver.</statement>
      <rationale>Regulatory stage confusion is a major agent failure mode. A proposed rule treated as in-force leads to premature product decisions; an enacted rule with a near effective date treated as "proposal" causes compliance misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Trend Strength Scoring">
    <list>
      <item>Growth rate (25%): measured YoY from 3+ independent sources; reject single-source CAGR</item>
      <item>Adoption curve stage (20%): based on quantitative anchor, not label</item>
      <item>Number of well-funded incumbents (15%): proxy for competitive density</item>
      <item>Investment activity (20%): funding velocity and deal count from Crunchbase/PitchBook</item>
      <item>Personal fit + licensing (20%): skills, capital, and regulatory licence requirements</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the personal-fit filter BEFORE presenting a high-scoring trend as an opportunity. A regulated category (broker-dealer, healthcare, gambling) with a strength score of 5/5 is unreachable without the required license.</statement>
      <rationale>A high trend-strength score in a licensed category is worthless without the license. Surfacing unlicensed opportunities wastes planning resources and creates false urgency.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
