<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-macro-regulatory" title="Macro and Regulatory Trend Sources">
  <summary>Primary data sources for macro indicators, regulatory pipelines, and incumbent momentum signals with citation requirements.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Every numeric market-size or CAGR row must carry source URL, publication year, and page number. Reject any row produced from LLM training data without a live citation.</statement>
    <rationale>"The X market is projected to reach $Y by 202Z at A% CAGR" is the highest-confidence/lowest-grounding sentence an LLM produces. Mandatory citation with page numbers is the only practical defense against fabricated analyst statistics.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Macro Indicator Sources">
    <list>
      <item>FRED (St. Louis Fed): US and global macro series — GDP, CPI, employment, interest rates (fred.stlouisfed.org/docs/api/fred)</item>
      <item>World Bank Open Data: country-level development indicators, GNI, governance (data.worldbank.org)</item>
      <item>Eurostat: EU sector, labour, trade data (ec.europa.eu/eurostat, SDMX API)</item>
      <item>OECD.Stat: cross-country macro and tax series (stats.oecd.org, SDMX)</item>
      <item>IMF WEO and IFS: global macro forecasts and financial stability (imf.org/en/Publications/WEO)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Currency- and inflation-normalise all macro numbers. "$10B to $25B by 2030" in nominal dollars at 4% inflation is $20B in real terms — deflate before comparing across reports.</statement>
      <rationale>Nominal-vs-real confusion inflates growth projections and creates strategy plans calibrated to a market size that does not exist in real purchasing power.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Regulatory Pipeline Sources">
    <list>
      <item>EUR-Lex: EU legislation full text and status tracking (eur-lex.europa.eu, CELLAR API)</item>
      <item>US Federal Register: proposed and final rules with full diff (federalregister.gov/developers)</item>
      <item>SEC EDGAR: 10-K and 10-Q filings, risk-factor year-over-year diffs (sec.gov/edgar)</item>
      <item>regulations.gov API: US comment-period dockets</item>
      <item>UK FCA/Companies House: UK rule tracker and corporate filings</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply a two-quarter sanity gap on regulatory shifts. Never pivot the company on a proposed rule; wait for enacted-or-better stage before any resource commitment.</statement>
      <rationale>Proposed rules are withdrawn or substantially modified 30-50% of the time. Building compliance infrastructure or pivoting the product for a proposal that never passes wastes 6-12 months of runway.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Incumbent Momentum Signals">
    <list>
      <item>10-K risk factor diffs year-over-year: new language about a trend signals incumbents fear it — strongest cheap signal available</item>
      <item>Earnings-call transcripts: stage indicator is "we are evaluating" to "we are piloting" to "we are deploying at scale" across sequential calls</item>
      <item>LinkedIn hiring delta by role: hiring PMs for "AI features" or "data platform" signals roadmap direction 6-9 months ahead of product launch</item>
      <item>Crunchbase funding velocity: round size and pace changes for competitors in a category</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require balanced earnings-call sampling: top-3 positive mentions plus top-3 cautionary mentions per call. Do not let the agent surface only bullish quotes.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs default to confirming the briefing document's tone. Mandating cautionary quotes forces the model to surface the risks incumbents acknowledge, not just the opportunities they promote.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
