<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="trend-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for trend-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Entering a trend at peak (mainstream) when competition is already intense</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Late mainstream entry requires a cost or distribution moat that most new entrants lack; the window for margin capture has closed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Chasing every trend without a personal-fit filter</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Trend strength without execution ability produces a business in a growing market that the founder cannot competitively serve.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>No counter-signals in the trend report</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A trend report without cooling indicators is a marketing document, not an analysis. At least 3 counter-signals are mandatory in every final report.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent cites a 2022 Gartner Hype Cycle as "this year's report"</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without WebFetch, the agent uses training-data reports as if they are current. Always check report_publish_date against current_date; reject reports older than 18 months for stage timing claims.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent fabricates CAGR percentages with two decimal places</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Treat any CAGR more precise than the nearest 5% as fabricated unless it has a source URL and page number. Real analyst reports round to one decimal.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent sums incompatible TAMs (AI software, AI services, AI hardware) without noting double-counting</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require segment definitions to be quoted verbatim from each source before any summing; different reports use different definitional boundaries for "AI market."</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent defaults to US sources and misses EU regulatory pipeline leading indicators</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a jurisdictions list in the orchestrator prompt; EU rules often precede US equivalents by 2-4 years and are the actual market-structure driver.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent extrapolates a 2-point trend ("usage-based went 20% to 38%") as a forward projection</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Two data points are insufficient for any projection; require at least 8 quarters of data before publishing a trend line and labeling it as directional.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
