<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-scoring-and-antipatterns" title="Trend Scoring and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Trend strength scoring with required JSON schema, opportunity matrix, common mistakes, and AI-agent gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Opportunity Matrix">
    <p>Two axes: Trend Strength (scored 1-5 per weighted criteria) and Your Ability to Execute (skills + capital + licensing). Optimal entry: high strength + high execution ability. When trend strength is high but execution ability is low, build the missing skills before entering — do not enter anyway and learn on the market's time.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Output Schema (required for every trend report)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every agent-produced trend report must conform to the JSON schema with mandatory source_url, year, and page fields on every numeric row. Reject outputs missing these fields.</statement>
      <rationale>Schema enforcement is the only scalable way to prevent numeric hallucination across quarterly trend reports. Manual review cannot catch fabricated CAGRs at scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="json"><![CDATA[{
  "trend": "AI coding assistants",
  "category": "trend",
  "stage": "early_mainstream",
  "market_size": [{
    "segment": "global developer tooling",
    "tam_usd": 28000000000,
    "cagr_pct": 24.5,
    "year": 2025,
    "source_url": "https://example-analyst.com/report-2025",
    "source_type": "gartner",
    "page": 14,
    "confidence": "med"
  }],
  "macro": [{"indicator": "FEDFUNDS", "value": 5.25, "unit": "%", "yoy_pct": -0.25, "region": "US", "source_url": "https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/FEDFUNDS"}],
  "regulatory": [{"rule_id": "EU-AI-ACT-2024", "jurisdiction": "EU", "stage": "enacted", "effective_date": "2025-08-02", "market_impact": "drag", "source_url": "https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32024R1689"}],
  "score": {"growth": 5, "stage": 4, "concentration": 3, "regulatory_clarity": 3, "macro_tailwind": 4, "fit": 4, "weighted": 3.9},
  "counter_signals": ["Large players (GitHub, OpenAI) have dominant distribution", "Commoditization risk within 18 months"],
  "recommendation": "pursue",
  "next_review": "2025-10-01"
}]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Entering a trend at peak (mainstream) when competition is already intense</description>
      <reason>Late mainstream entry requires a cost or distribution moat that most new entrants lack; the window for margin capture has closed.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Chasing every trend without a personal-fit filter</description>
      <reason>Trend strength without execution ability produces a business in a growing market that the founder cannot competitively serve.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No counter-signals in the trend report</description>
      <reason>A trend report without cooling indicators is a marketing document, not an analysis. At least 3 counter-signals are mandatory in every final report.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent cites a 2022 Gartner Hype Cycle as "this year's report"</description>
      <reason>Without WebFetch, the agent uses training-data reports as if they are current. Always check report_publish_date against current_date; reject reports older than 18 months for stage timing claims.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent fabricates CAGR percentages with two decimal places</description>
      <reason>Treat any CAGR more precise than the nearest 5% as fabricated unless it has a source URL and page number. Real analyst reports round to one decimal.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent sums incompatible TAMs (AI software + AI services + AI hardware) without noting double-counting</description>
      <reason>Require segment definitions to be quoted verbatim from each source before any summing; different reports use different definitional boundaries for "AI market."</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent defaults to US sources and misses EU regulatory pipeline leading indicators</description>
      <reason>Force a jurisdictions list in the orchestrator prompt; EU rules often precede US equivalents by 2-4 years and are the actual market-structure driver.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent extrapolates a 2-point trend ("usage-based went 20% to 38%") as a forward projection</description>
      <reason>Two data points are insufficient for any projection; require at least 8 quarters of data before publishing a trend line and labeling it as directional.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
