<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="task-creation-parallelization Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for task-creation-parallelization as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Task too large: greater than 100k tokens or greater than 4 subtasks in one task file.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Context overflow causes forgotten requirements and inconsistent implementations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Vague acceptance criteria: "registration should work" instead of Given-When-Then with specific values.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents cannot verify completion against vague criteria and produce implementations that pass the agent's interpretation but not the actual requirement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Missing dependency tree: Wave 2+ task has no summaries from Wave 1 dependencies.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each execution agent starts fresh; without explicit patterns from prior waves, naming conventions and error handling diverge.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Tasks sharing a file in the same wave.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Parallel git worktree execution produces merge conflicts when two agents modify the same file simultaneously.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>The Monolith Task: one task for the entire feature.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Exceeds context window; cannot parallelize; progress is invisible; rollback is all-or-nothing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>The Micro-Task: separate tasks for import statement, function signature, function body.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Coordination overhead exceeds implementation time; each task lacks sufficient context to make meaningful decisions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>The Circular Dependency: TASK-001 depends on TASK-002 which depends on TASK-001.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Deadlocks wave execution; fix by extracting the shared dependency into a new Wave 1 task.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>The Missing Context: implementation task with no dependency tree and no related-files section.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent starts fresh without pattern context; produces naming and error handling inconsistent with prior waves.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>The Vague AC: "AC-1: registration should work".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent cannot verify completion; implements to its own interpretation rather than the actual requirement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
