<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Procurement Management Framework Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the procurement-management methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="baseline-included" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always include 'build internally' or 'do nothing' as an explicit row in the evaluation matrix.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK 7 Procurement; field experience">Without a baseline comparison, the decision optimises vendor selection rather than whether to engage one at all.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="contract-type-matches-scope" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select contract type by scope clarity: Fixed Price for well-defined scope; T&amp;M for unclear scope with hard cap + 70% trigger; Cost Plus only for research with full buyer risk acceptance.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-management field experience">Mismatched contract type is the primary cause of cost overruns and disputes; variable scope on fixed-price guarantees conflict.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pre-published-weights" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Publish the scoring rubric and weights before proposals arrive. Retroactive weight changes are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Procurement governance">Pre-published weights force the evaluating team to commit to priorities before they are influenced by vendor positioning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="clause-checklist-pass" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every contract must pass the clause checklist before signing: IP assignment, sub-processor list, DPA (if PII), termination-for-convenience with notice, audit right, SLA with credits, indemnity (incl. AI output IP), warranty period. No 'TBD' clauses.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-law practice">Missing clauses surface as disputes; an undiscovered IP gap locks the buyer into a bad vendor indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="milestone-gated-payments" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tie payments to acceptance of deliverables, not calendar dates. Default Fixed Price split: 25% start, 50% milestone, 25% acceptance.</statement>
      <rationale source="Service-contract field experience">Calendar payments reward timing; milestone-gated payments preserve leverage for final acceptance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="sensitivity-check" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After scoring, re-score with each criterion weight shifted ±10%. If rank order flips, document the rationale or re-evaluate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-analysis literature">A rank that changes under small weight variations means the choice is essentially arbitrary; false precision hides this.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Spot purchases under PO threshold (e.g. under $5K) where formal procurement is overhead</item>
      <item>Highly regulated industries with established central procurement and legal teams — defer to org policy</item>
      <item>SaaS tools the engineering team can self-onboard with monthly billing (security review still needed, but not a full RFP)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
