<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Procurement Process and Contract Types">
  <summary>Six-step procurement process: make-or-buy, SOW definition, contract type selection, vendor sourcing, negotiation, and ongoing management.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Make-or-Buy Decision">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include the "build internally" or "do nothing" option as an explicit row in the evaluation matrix; otherwise procurement becomes a forced choice.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a baseline comparison, the decision optimizes vendor selection rather than whether to engage a vendor at all.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Factors favouring Make: full control needed, internal expertise sufficient, long-term strategic asset. Factors favouring Buy: faster time-to-capability, specialized expertise needed, risk transfer preferred.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Contract Type Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select contract type based on scope clarity and risk allocation: Fixed Price for well-defined scope (vendor bears cost risk); T&amp;M for unclear scope (buyer bears cost risk); Cost Plus for research or highly uncertain work (buyer bears all cost risk).</statement>
      <rationale>Mismatched contract type is the primary cause of cost overruns and disputes; variable scope on a fixed-price contract guarantees conflict.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For T&amp;M contracts, enforce a hard cap and a weekly burn-rate report; trigger a change request at 70% of cap.</statement>
      <rationale>T&amp;M without a cap produces silent budget overruns; the 70% trigger provides time to re-scope or stop before the cap is hit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Mobile app development with clear deliverables (design mockups, working app, source code, App Store approval, 95% crash-free): Fixed Price. Cloud infrastructure setup with evolving requirements: T&amp;M with $15K/mo cap and senior/junior rate card.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Sourcing Methods">
    <p>RFI: gather market info before committing to a procurement. RFP: formal proposals with solutions (use for complex work). RFQ: price quotes for defined work (use when scope is clear). Sole source: direct engagement — requires documented justification.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Publish the scoring rubric with weights before proposals arrive. Retroactive weight changes after seeing proposals are bias laundering.</statement>
      <rationale>Pre-published weights force the evaluating team to commit to priorities before they are influenced by vendor positioning.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Mandatory Contract Clause Checklist">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every contract must include all of the following before signing: IP assignment, sub-processor disclosure, DPA (if PII involved), termination-for-convenience clause with reasonable notice, audit right, SLA with credits, indemnity including AI-output IP, warranty period. Reject any contract missing a clause; do not accept "TBD".</statement>
      <rationale>Missing clauses surface as disputes; an undiscovered IP gap or absent termination clause locks the buyer into a bad vendor indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Ongoing Vendor Management">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tie payments to acceptance of deliverables, not calendar dates. Default structure: 25% at start, 50% at milestone, 25% at completion for Fixed Price.</statement>
      <rationale>Calendar-based payments reward delivery timing, not delivery quality; milestone-gated payments preserve leverage for final acceptance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/sow.md">Statement of Work template</reference>
</text>
