<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-error-categories" title="LLM-Specific Error Categories">
  <summary>Taxonomy of LLM agent failure modes used to classify MIS-NNN entries and select prevention strategies.</summary>

  <section title="Hallucination Errors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag entries with `hallucination-api` when the agent invents a non-existent library method or endpoint. Prevention: include API reference documentation in task context.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs pattern-match from similar APIs and generate syntactically plausible but non-existent calls with full confidence. Type checking and tests are the only reliable catches.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Tag entries with `hallucination-factual` when the agent confidently states a new feature, version, or behavior that does not exist. Prevention: ask for documentation links; treat any unverified "new in X" claim as unverified.</statement>
      <rationale>The 64.5% blind-spot rate in self-correction studies means the agent cannot reliably flag its own factual errors. External verification is required.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Context Errors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag entries with `context-window-loss` when earlier instructions drift out of the effective context. Prevention: break tasks exceeding 300 lines into chunks; include a coding standards summary with each chunk.</statement>
      <rationale>Models become unreliable at 65-80% of advertised context limits. Long conversations cause instruction drift even within the stated window.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Tag entries with `instruction-drift` when requirements specified at session start are not honored mid-task. Prevention: re-inject key constraints every N tool calls or task boundaries.</statement>
      <rationale>Instruction drift is distinct from window loss — the instruction is technically in context but deprioritized by later content.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Implementation Errors">
    <list>
      <item>missing-error-handling: try/catch absent in async flows, silent failures in payment or critical paths</item>
      <item>edge-cases-missed: boundary conditions, empty arrays, null fields not handled</item>
      <item>scope-creep: unrequested features added during implementation</item>
      <item>premature-optimization: performance changes before correctness verified</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Process Errors">
    <list>
      <item>skipped-validation: quality gate bypassed, pre-commit hook skipped</item>
      <item>estimation-underrun: task took 2x+ estimated tokens due to unknown unknowns</item>
      <item>missing-env-var: new config variable not propagated to all environments</item>
      <item>data-migration-no-backup: destructive operation without prior backup</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
