<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-prevention-layers" title="Mistake Prevention Layers">
  <summary>Four-layer defense against recurring mistakes: pre-task warnings, quality gates, CI automation, and multi-model review.</summary>

  <section title="Layer 1: Pre-Task Warning Injection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before executing any task, keyword-search mistakes.md and prepend matching entries as a Warnings section in the task prompt.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents that skip pre-task loading get no benefit from the accumulated mistake corpus. Injection must be explicit and automated, not optional.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[# Load warnings before executing TASK-042 (database migration)
./inject-warnings.sh "database migration schema" | prepend-to-task TASK-042]]></code>
      <note>Keywords match entries by domain, not by full-text similarity. Semantic matching is unreliable in prompts.</note>
    </example>

    <reference path="templates/inject-warnings.sh">Bash script for keyword-based warning injection</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Layer 2: Quality Gates">
    <rule>
      <statement>SDD quality gates L1-L6 are the structural enforcement of lessons from past mistakes. Each gate failure generates a mistake entry.</statement>
      <rationale>Gates create mandatory checkpoints that block progression when known failure conditions are detected, replacing optional checklists.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Layer 3: CI Automation">
    <rule>
      <statement>When a mistake pattern recurs, add an automated CI rule using a file pattern, keyword trigger, or code pattern detector.</statement>
      <rationale>Documentation without enforcement is only awareness. Patterns that survive two documented occurrences require code-level blocking.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[# Prevention rule for destructive migrations (source: MIS-010)
id: PREV_010
trigger:
  type: code_pattern
  pattern: "DROP (TABLE|COLUMN)"
  file_types: ["*.sql", "migrations/*"]
action:
  type: block
  message: "Destructive migration detected. Take backup first. See MIS-010."]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Layer 4: Multi-Model Review">
    <rule>
      <statement>For high-severity mistakes (critical/high), add a cross-validation step where a second agent or model reviews the primary output.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-evaluation has a 64.5% blind-spot rate. A second independent pass catches logical inconsistencies the first model cannot see in its own output.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
