<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Overlay — Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six failure modes for the overlay resolution layer. Each has detector + repair.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="high">
      <description>Silent override: team overrode a security-critical rule (e.g. license veto) and the agent ran with the weaker policy without surfacing the change.</description>
      <detector>Resolution `files` map shows USER/REPO source on a methodology marked `security: critical` in shipped frontmatter AND no acknowledgment in `conflicts`.</detector>
      <repair>Block faion-cli command until operator explicitly acknowledges the override via `faion overlay ack &lt;path&gt;`.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="high">
      <description>Version skew: shipped methodology bumped from v1 to v2 changing schema; team's overlay still v1 content_id.</description>
      <detector>`version_skew: true` AND any file with different content_id triggers schema validation failures.</detector>
      <repair>Surface skew with shipped diff; suggest one of {re-port overlay to v2, pin shipped to v1 for this overlay, drop overlay}.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="high">
      <description>Partial-merge corruption: APPEND on content/*.xml lands new `&lt;rule&gt;` blocks but shipped already has the same rule IDs.</description>
      <detector>Resolved XML contains duplicate `&lt;rule id="..."&gt;` after merge.</detector>
      <repair>Refuse merge; surface ID collision; team must rename their rule IDs (prefix with `team-`).</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Loop in resolver: USER and REPO both reference each other via includes, creating infinite resolution.</description>
      <detector>Resolution stack depth &gt; 8.</detector>
      <repair>Reject. Includes / referrals are forbidden across overlay levels; overlay files must be self-contained.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Maintainer unset: overrides-config.yaml has empty `maintainer:` and the audit log can't attribute changes.</description>
      <detector>`maintainer` empty or "team" placeholder.</detector>
      <repair>Refuse overlay load until config sets a named human (e.g. `maintainer: jane.doe@acme.com`).</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="low">
      <description>Discovery cost: every faion command rescans both overlay directories, adding latency.</description>
      <detector>Resolution time &gt; 200ms for a methodology load.</detector>
      <repair>Cache resolution in `.faion/cache/resolved-overlay.json`, invalidate on file mtime change. Provide `faion overlay invalidate` command.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>
      Overlay files are AUTHORITATIVE content for the agent. They CAN override shipped behaviour by design.
      The agent must trust them after r4 validation passes. There is no injection vector here unless an
      attacker has write access to the team's repo — in which case overlay is the least of the problems.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>
      Overlay changes are real organisational policy changes. Treat them like merging to main:
      reviewed PR, approved by overlay maintainer, audit event published. Operator must NOT
      hand-edit `~/.faion/overrides/` on a colleague's machine. Every overlay change comes through
      the team's overrides repo.
    </p>
  </section>
</text>
