<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="agile-hybrid-approaches">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-agile</domain>
    <summary>Decision framework for Predictive (waterfall), Agile (Scrum/Kanban), or Hybrid delivery based on five factors: requirements clarity, stakeholder availability, risk, team experience, contract.</summary>
    <category>delivery</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>hybrid</tag>
      <tag>waterfall</tag>
      <tag>project-management</tag>
      <tag>delivery-approaches</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Agile and Hybrid Approaches</title>

    <summary>A decision framework for selecting among Predictive (waterfall), Agile (Scrum/Kanban), and Hybrid delivery models based on five project factors: requirements clarity, stakeholder availability, risk tolerance, team experience, and contract type. Hybrid approaches combine elements — e.g., Water-Scrum-Fall, agile execution under predictive governance — when no pure model fits.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Most delivery failures stem from applying the wrong approach: waterfall on high-uncertainty work causes late feedback loops; pure agile on fixed-price contracts masks scope creep. A five-question selection framework with scored thresholds produces a defensible, context-grounded recommendation rather than defaulting to the PM's preferred methodology.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Project kickoff where the right delivery model is genuinely unclear (mixed-experience team, semi-defined scope).</item>
        <item>Fixed-price contracts that need agile execution under predictive governance (Water-Scrum-Fall).</item>
        <item>Regulated environments where parts must be predictive (compliance, validation) and parts agile (UI, integrations).</item>
        <item>Coaching engagements moving from waterfall to agile, where pure-agile from day one would fail change management.</item>
        <item>Solopreneur or small-team work where lightweight Kanban + monthly review is right-sized.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>A team already running stable Scrum or Kanban — switching to hybrid loses cadence without recovering certainty.</item>
        <item>Pure exploration or research where any delivery framework is overhead.</item>
        <item>Teams whose dysfunction is cultural, not methodological — a hybrid won't fix accountability gaps.</item>
        <item>Crisis or incident response — use incident-response runbooks, not a delivery framework selection.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="approach-spectrum">
      <p>Delivery approaches span a continuous spectrum from fully Predictive (requirements fixed early, sequential phases, big-bang delivery) to fully Adaptive (requirements evolve, iterative sprints, incremental delivery). Hybrid picks a point on the spectrum per project phase.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="five-factor-decision-matrix">
      <p>Score each factor as P (Predictive), H (Hybrid), or A (Agile). If 4+ factors score P, choose Predictive. If 4+ score A, choose Agile. Otherwise choose Hybrid.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Prefer Hybrid only when at least two answers point to Predictive AND two point to Agile; otherwise default to the majority signal.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs and humans both default to Hybrid because it sounds safe; the 2+2 threshold prevents false hybrids from sloppy analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="factor-1-requirements-clarity">
        <list>
          <item>P — Clear, stable, fully documented before work starts</item>
          <item>H — Partially known; core stable, details emerging</item>
          <item>A — Unclear, evolving, discovered through feedback</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="factor-2-stakeholder-availability">
        <list>
          <item>P — Limited access; prefer formal scheduled reviews</item>
          <item>H — Regular scheduled meetings achievable</item>
          <item>A — Highly engaged; available for frequent collaboration</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="factor-3-risk-tolerance">
        <list>
          <item>P — Low; must work first time, failure is costly</item>
          <item>H — Medium; can absorb some iteration</item>
          <item>A — High; can experiment and pivot based on feedback</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="factor-4-team-experience">
        <list>
          <item>P — Less experienced; benefits from clear direction</item>
          <item>H — Mixed experience levels</item>
          <item>A — Self-organizing; comfortable with ambiguity</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="factor-5-contract-type">
        <list>
          <item>P — Fixed price, fixed scope</item>
          <item>H — Fixed price, flexible scope (phase gates)</item>
          <item>A — Time and materials or value-based</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="when-each-approach-applies">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pick one approach per project phase, not per ceremony; translate between approaches at explicit, named boundaries.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixed-mode approaches within a single phase produce competing artifacts (burn-down + Gantt) and stakeholder confusion without providing the benefits of either model.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running daily standups alongside Gantt chart updates for the same work.</description>
        <reason>Doubles reporting burden without improving either predictability or agility; the team serves the tools instead of the tools serving the team.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Calling a process "Hybrid" because it uses some agile terminology while keeping all waterfall gates.</description>
        <reason>"Agile in name only" loses the feedback-loop benefit of agile without gaining the predictability of predictive; worst of both worlds.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="three-hybrid-patterns">
      <section name="water-scrum-fall">
        <p>Predictive planning phase → Scrum execution sprints → Predictive deployment phase. Useful for fixed-price contracts with agile development requirements.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Plan phase: fixed scope, contract baseline, WBS</item>
          <item>Build phase: 2-week sprints, weekly demos, backlog refinement</item>
          <item>Deploy phase: fixed test plan, staged rollout, documentation</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="agile-development-with-predictive-governance">
        <p>Sprints for work execution, phase gates for funding and approval decisions. Common in enterprises requiring board approval at each investment stage.</p>
      </section>

      <section name="predictive-core-with-agile-discovery">
        <p>Agile discovery phase identifies and validates requirements, then hands off to waterfall implementation. Useful when requirements are unknown but delivery must be fixed-cost.</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Define "Done" once per phase; hybrid teams sharing a single Definition of Done across agile and predictive phases produce inconsistent quality gates.</statement>
          <rationale>Agile "done" (tested, deployed to staging) differs materially from waterfall "done" (signed off, documented); conflation causes undetected gaps at handoff.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="scrum-reference">
      <section name="scrum-events">
        <list>
          <item>Sprint Planning (2-4 hours): plan sprint work against capacity</item>
          <item>Daily Scrum (15 min): sync, surface blockers</item>
          <item>Sprint Review (1-2 hours): demo to stakeholders, collect feedback</item>
          <item>Sprint Retrospective (1-2 hours): improve process</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="scrum-roles">
        <list>
          <item>Product Owner: what to build, priority, backlog ownership</item>
          <item>Scrum Master: process health, impediment removal</item>
          <item>Developers: how to build, delivery commitment</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="kanban-principles">
      <list>
        <item>Visualize workflow — make work visible on a board</item>
        <item>Limit WIP — cap items in each column to expose bottlenecks</item>
        <item>Manage flow — optimize throughput, not utilization</item>
        <item>Make policies explicit — document column entry/exit criteria</item>
        <item>Continuous improvement — retrospect on flow metrics, not sprint events</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use burn-up over burn-down for hybrid stakeholder reporting; burn-down hides scope additions.</statement>
        <rationale>When scope is added mid-sprint, burn-down charts appear on track while total work grows invisibly; burn-up charts make scope growth explicit.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Dogmatic adherence to one methodology ("We MUST do pure Scrum").</description>
        <reason>No single approach fits all project types; forcing a misfit approach causes ceremony theater without the benefits of either model.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Maintaining both burn-down charts AND traditional Gantt for the same work.</description>
        <reason>Doubles reporting burden without improving visibility; teams serve the tools instead of the tools serving the team.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Discovery → Implementation handoff without an explicit translation boundary.</description>
        <reason>Bakes in a translation tax (agile artifacts → waterfall inputs) that grows larger over time and is difficult to remove once established.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="worked-examples">
      <example type="good" title="Fixed-Price Hybrid Contract">
        <note>Situation: fixed-price contract, $100K, 4 months, scope partially defined.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Phase 1: Discovery (2 weeks) — Agile
- User story workshops to surface real requirements
- Prototype 3 key screens for client validation
- Finalize and baseline scope for contract

Phase 2: Development (10 weeks) — Scrum
- 5 two-week sprints
- Weekly demos to client (fulfills "engagement" clause)
- Backlog refinement mid-sprint

Phase 3: Deployment (2 weeks) — Predictive
- Fixed test plan against acceptance criteria
- Staged rollout (internal → pilot users → all)
- Documentation and handover package

Governance layer (runs throughout):
- Monthly steering committee (predictive cadence)
- Sprint reviews serve as delivery evidence
- Change requests required for scope changes beyond 10%
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Solopreneur Personal Kanban">
        <note>Right-sized for single-person work: minimal ceremony, maximum focus.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
This Week's Focus (WIP: 3 items maximum)
1. [>] Write blog post
2. [>] Update landing page copy
3. [>] Customer discovery call

Waiting (blocked on external)
- Design review from contractor
- API access credentials from partner

Done This Week
- Email newsletter sent
- Invoice sent to client A

Weekly Review (Sunday, 30 min)
- What shipped? What moved to Waiting?
- What's the priority for next week?
- Any waiting items to chase?
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Solo Founder First Hire Integration">
        <note>Structured onboarding plan for founder moving from individual contributor to team lead.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Week 1: Orientation
- Share vision, values, and "why we exist"
- Walk through codebase with commentary
- Explain current processes (written, not verbal)
- Define initial responsibilities explicitly

Weeks 2-4: Gradual Ownership Transfer
- Pair on first 3 tasks
- Review their work thoroughly and explain feedback
- Give direct, kind feedback on process not person
- Discuss what is working and what isn't

Month 2: Independent Ownership
- Assign features end-to-end without pairing
- Reduce review from every PR to spot checks
- Ask them to propose process improvements
- Celebrate first solo ship publicly

Key rule: document everything, assume nothing.
]]></code>
        <rule>
          <statement>For solopreneur use, cap ceremonies at one weekly review unless the team explicitly requests more; agents over-engineer ceremonies by default.</statement>
          <rationale>Ceremony overhead scales poorly for individuals; one weekly review captures the critical "what shipped, what's stuck" signal without adding coordination tax.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A selection agent runs the decision-framework checklist (requirements clarity, customer availability, risk, team experience, contract type) against project inputs and outputs a recommendation with rationale. A scaffolding agent generates the ceremony cadence + artifact set tailored to the chosen approach (sprint plan templates for agile parts, milestone plan for predictive parts). A weekly governance agent reconciles status across approaches into one stakeholder-facing summary.</p>
      <p>Best practices: Pick one approach per phase, not per ceremony. "Discovery is agile, build is agile, deploy is predictive" beats "we do daily standups but also Gantt charts in parallel". Translate between approaches at explicit boundaries: a sprint review at the end of agile build feeds the predictive deploy plan as input artifacts. Burn-up > burn-down for hybrid stakeholder reporting; burn-down hides scope additions. Keep ceremonies minimal: one planning, one daily, one demo, one retro per cycle. Add governance gates as separate, named events. Define "Done" once per phase. Hybrid teams that share a single Definition of Done across modes get sloppy. Calibrate forecasts with Monte Carlo + throughput; deterministic estimates lie. Document the chosen mix as an ADR — future contributors need to know why. For solopreneur use, agents over-engineer ceremonies; cap at one weekly review unless asked.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/sprint-plan.md" purpose="Sprint planning template: goal, capacity table, backlog, dependencies, risks."/>
      <template path="templates/kanban-board.md" purpose="Kanban board template with WIP limits."/>
      <template path="templates/pick_approach.py" purpose="Script: reads a YAML decision file and outputs Predictive/Agile/Hybrid recommendation."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.scrum.org/resources/blog/scrum-and-pmbok"/>
      <link href="https://www.scaledagileframework.com/agile-product-delivery/"/>
      <link href="https://mermaid.js.org/syntax/gantt.html"/>
      <link href="https://squidfunk.github.io/mkdocs-material/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
