<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-conversation-strategy" title="Threads Conversation Strategy and Cross-Platform Synergy">
  <summary>Reply formula, conversation-starter types, cross-platform synergy rules, and what makes content perform on Threads.</summary>

  <section title="Reply-First Growth">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reply to large accounts first — one early, thoughtful reply on a 100K-follower post outperforms five standalone posts for discovery.</statement>
      <rationale>Threads surfaces engaged replies to the original post's audience. Early replies get the most exposure; late replies are buried.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the [Agree/Disagree] + [Add perspective] + [Question] reply formula. Never write "Great point!" as a reply.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic agreement adds no value and signals low-quality engagement. Questions invite the original poster to respond, creating a visible conversation thread.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Reply to a post about shipping fast: "This is so true. I found the same thing when building [X] — the constraint of a hard deadline produced better decisions than open-ended sprints. What made you realize this?"</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Reply: "Great point! So insightful. Totally agree." — No perspective added, no question, no reason for the original poster or their audience to engage further.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Conversation-Starter Post Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post 5+ short punchy posts per day across these types: hot takes, this-or-that, fill-in-blank, experience prompts, and predictions.</statement>
      <rationale>Threads rewards high volume of conversational posts. Each post type generates a different engagement pattern — questions drive replies, hot takes drive quote posts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Hot take: "Unpopular opinion: [bold statement]. Change my mind."</item>
      <item>This or that: "[A] or [B]?" (e.g., "Notion or Obsidian?")</item>
      <item>Fill in blank: "The best [X] is ___"</item>
      <item>Experience: "Raise your hand if you've ever [relatable struggle]"</item>
      <item>Prediction: "In [year], [specific prediction about your niche]"</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not include links in Threads posts. Threads does not render links and promotional posts are heavily suppressed.</statement>
      <rationale>Threads's algorithm suppresses posts that look promotional or are designed to drive traffic off-platform. Use the bio link for all external CTAs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cross-Platform Synergy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cross-promote from Instagram Stories by sharing a specific Threads post with "join the conversation on Threads" — this is the fastest follower import mechanism.</statement>
      <rationale>Instagram followers already trust the account. Directing them to Threads via Stories converts at a much higher rate than organic Threads discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When adapting Twitter/X content for Threads: shorten to 1-3 posts, remove thread numbering, make it conversational, add a genuine question at the end, remove promotional language.</statement>
      <rationale>Twitter content is declarative and formal. Threads culture rewards rough edges, admitted uncertainty, and genuine curiosity. Verbatim cross-posts underperform.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/adapt-twitter-thread.py">Strip tweet numbering and split Twitter thread into Threads-native conversational posts</reference>
  </section>
</text>
