<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-growth-patterns" title="Threads Growth Patterns, Metrics, and Failure Modes">
  <summary>Metrics benchmarks by growth stage, scaling milestones, and the most common Threads growth mistakes.</summary>

  <section title="Metrics Benchmarks">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Track follower growth rate (target 5-10% weekly), replies per post, and profile visits per day as primary Threads KPIs.</statement>
      <rationale>Threads provides almost no exportable analytics. Manual tracking in a spreadsheet is required. These three metrics are observable without API access.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Followers: starting = building, 100+/week = growing, 500+/week = established</item>
      <item>Post views: 100 = starting, 1K = growing, 10K+ = established</item>
      <item>Replies per post: 2-5 = starting, 10-20 = growing, 50+ = established</item>
      <item>Profile visits: 10/day = starting, 50/day = growing, 200+/day = established</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Just cross-posting content from Twitter without adaptation.</description>
      <reason>Twitter content is declarative and polished. Threads culture rewards casual, curious, rough-edged posts. Verbatim cross-posts feel out of place and underperform.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Being too promotional — product pitches in posts.</description>
      <reason>Threads's algorithm heavily penalizes promotional content. The platform norms are 95% value, 5% promo. Any promotional feel reduces distribution.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Posting once a day instead of 5+ posts daily.</description>
      <reason>Threads requires higher post volume than LinkedIn or Twitter because the feed is highly active and content decays quickly. One daily post is not enough for the algorithm.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using a formal or corporate tone.</description>
      <reason>Threads culture is conversational and casual. Corporate language signals inauthenticity and the audience does not engage.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Limitations on Threads">
    <rule>
      <statement>Batch-generate 35+ post drafts per week but post only what feels genuinely on-voice. Volume generation is useful; volume posting without editing is harmful.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent output defaults to polished and authoritative. Threads requires rough edges and genuine curiosity. Always rewrite agent output before posting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>As of 2026, Threads has no official write API. All posting must be done manually by a human. Agent output is drafts only.</statement>
      <rationale>Meta's Threads API (2024) is read-only. Any tool claiming to post to Threads on your behalf is violating ToS and risks account suspension.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
