<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ideation-methods">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>communicator</domain>
    <summary>Structured frameworks for generating and developing ideas systematically: SCAMPER, Mind Mapping, and Starbursting that work solo or in small groups to produce structured idea artifacts.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>ideation</tag>
      <tag>creativity</tag>
      <tag>scamper</tag>
      <tag>mind-mapping</tag>
      <tag>starbursting</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Ideation Methods: SCAMPER, Mind Mapping, and Starbursting</title>
    <summary>Structured frameworks for generating and developing ideas systematically: SCAMPER (apply 7 lenses to an existing product to generate variants), Mind Mapping (visual branching for exploring connections), and Starbursting (5W+H question generation before answering). Unlike group brainstorming techniques, these methods work solo or in small groups and produce structured idea artifacts, not just lists.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Unstructured ideation produces ideas that cluster around the obvious. SCAMPER forces exploration of seven distinct transformation types (Substitute, Combine, Adapt, Modify, Put to other uses, Eliminate, Reverse), systematically breaking cognitive fixation. Starbursting delays solution-jumping by generating questions first — the primary cause of failed product launches is insufficient question-asking before committing to an answer.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Improving or extending an existing product, service, or process (SCAMPER).</item>
        <item>Exploring a complex topic to map its structure and connections (Mind Mapping).</item>
        <item>Starting a new project where unknowns must be surfaced before planning (Starbursting).</item>
        <item>Preparing for a decision by identifying what you don't yet know.</item>
        <item>Risk analysis and pre-mortem exercises.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When speed matters more than coverage — these methods take 30-90 minutes; use quick brainstorming instead.</item>
        <item>When the solution space is already well-defined — apply evaluation frameworks, not ideation ones.</item>
        <item>For emotional or relational issues — structured creativity tools are inappropriate in conflict contexts.</item>
        <item>When the group is too large (greater than 6) — use group brainstorming techniques instead.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="scamper-systematic-creativity">
      <p>SCAMPER applies seven transformation lenses to an existing product or process to systematically generate improvement ideas.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply each SCAMPER lens in sequence, spending 5-10 minutes per lens generating 3-5 ideas — do not evaluate until all seven lenses are complete.</statement>
        <rationale>Premature evaluation blocks exploration. The Eliminate and Reverse lenses produce the most disruptive ideas and are most often skipped when teams run out of time — forcing a fixed time per lens ensures coverage.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Substitute: What materials, people, or processes can we replace?</item>
        <item>Combine: What features, audiences, or ideas can we merge?</item>
        <item>Adapt: What works in a similar industry that we can copy and improve?</item>
        <item>Modify: What can we change in size, shape, color, speed, or frequency?</item>
        <item>Put to other uses: Who else needs this? What other markets exist?</item>
        <item>Eliminate: What is not essential? What rules can we break?</item>
        <item>Reverse/Rearrange: What if we did the opposite? Changed the sequence?</item>
      </list>
      <example type="good" title="Applying SCAMPER to a coffee shop">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Substitute: Plant-based milk default, robot baristas
Combine:    Coffee + coworking, Coffee + laundry
Adapt:      Copy hotel concierge service, airline loyalty program
Modify:     24/7 hours, subscription model, tiny/huge cup sizes
Put to use: Evening wine bar, podcast studio rental
Eliminate:  No cash, no menu (AI recommends), no seating
Reverse:    Customers make own coffee, mobile shop comes to you
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Rushing through all lenses in under 15 minutes total.</description>
        <reason>The disruptive ideas (Eliminate, Reverse) require more cognitive effort and only emerge after the obvious ideas are exhausted. Rushing produces the same ideas brainstorming produces without structure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="mind-mapping">
      <p>Mind Mapping creates a visual representation of a complex topic's structure and connections, radiating from a central node through branches and sub-branches.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Start with a single central topic, radiate main themes as branches, add details as sub-branches, then draw connections between related ideas across different branches.</statement>
        <rationale>The connection-drawing step is the highest-value phase: it surfaces non-obvious relationships between ideas that linear brainstorming misses. Most teams stop at sub-branches and skip connections.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use single words or short phrases per node — never full sentences.</statement>
        <rationale>Full sentences force sequential processing; single words allow the eye to skip and pattern-match across the map, which is how the mind finds connections.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Digital tools: Miro, Mural (collaborative), MindMeister, XMind (dedicated), FigJam, Whimsical.</item>
        <item>Start broad (main branches), then go specific (sub-branches).</item>
        <item>Use different colors for different themes.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="starbursting">
      <p>Starbursting uses the 5W+H framework (Who, What, Where, When, Why, How) to systematically generate questions about an idea before committing to answers.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Before answering any question about a new idea, use Starbursting to generate all six question types (Who, What, Where, When, Why, How) — at least 5 questions per type — then prioritize the top 10 to answer.</statement>
        <rationale>Most failed products result from teams answering the wrong questions early. Starbursting delays solution commitment until the question landscape is mapped, exposing assumptions that would otherwise remain invisible.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Starbursting a new mobile app idea">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
WHO:   Who are the users? Who pays? Who maintains? Who are competitors?
WHAT:  What problem does it solve? What features are essential?
WHERE: Where will users use it? Where is data stored?
WHEN:  When do users need it? When to launch?
WHY:   Why would users choose us? Why now vs. later?
HOW:   How to monetize? How to acquire users? How to measure success?

Priority questions (top 10 to research first):
1. Why would users choose us over [existing alternatives]?
2. How do we acquire the first 100 users?
...
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="combining-methods">
      <p>Ideation methods combine for greater impact: SCAMPER + Mind Map for improving products, Starbursting + Brainstorming for planning new projects.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Combine SCAMPER + Mind Map when improving an existing product: create a mind map of the current product, then apply SCAMPER to each branch.</statement>
        <rationale>The mind map ensures SCAMPER covers all product dimensions (not just the obvious ones); SCAMPER ensures each dimension gets systematic transformation, not just free-form brainstorming.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Combine Starbursting + Brainstorming for new project planning: use Starbursting to generate the question list, then run a brainstorm session per priority question.</statement>
        <rationale>Brainstorming on the wrong question produces well-elaborated wrong answers. Starbursting first ensures the brainstorm is directed at the highest-leverage unknowns.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-integration-guidelines">
      <p>Agents excel at generating SCAMPER ideas, Starbursting questions, and Mind Map structures in batch format, but human review is essential to prevent thin lateral thinking and idea overlap.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>When using agents for SCAMPER: provide a product/service description and request exactly 3-5 ideas per lens with no overlap between lenses. Run a second pass to score ideas by novelty × feasibility.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents can structure SCAMPER output correctly but the "Reverse" and "Put to Other Uses" lenses require more lateral thinking than single-pass LLM generation reliably provides. Scoring by novelty × feasibility filters obvious ideas.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>When using agents for Starbursting: request 5 questions per 5W+H category, then require human re-ranking by decision-criticality (not interestingness to the model).</statement>
        <rationale>Agents generate 30 questions but rank them by what the model finds interesting, not what your project actually needs to know. Human re-ranking by "what happens if we don't know the answer?" surfaces true decision-critical unknowns.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>When using agents for Mind Mapping: request JSON structure (importable to Miro/Obsidian) rather than ASCII art. Specify maximum 6 branches and 4 children per branch to prevent over-complexity.</statement>
        <rationale>Mind Map value comes from spatial layout and visual connections, not node content. JSON preserves structure for import into a visual tool, whereas ASCII art is static and does not invite connection-drawing.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>SCAMPER "Eliminate" lens produces ideas that trivially break the core product ("remove login") — filter before scoring.</item>
        <item>Agents reuse ideas across SCAMPER lenses (e.g., "subscription model" under both Modify and Reverse) — enforce uniqueness in the prompt.</item>
        <item>Starbursting generates 30 questions but LLMs rank them by interestingness to the model, not decision-criticality for the project — human must re-rank by actual stakes.</item>
        <item>Mind Map JSON often has too-flat (all children of center) or too-deep (5+ levels) structures — specify max depth and breadth in the prompt.</item>
        <item>Human checkpoint required: the top-10 Starbursting questions must be reviewed before research or development begins.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/scamper-worksheet.md" purpose="Fill-in worksheet for SCAMPER with slots for 3 ideas per lens and top-3 summary"/>
      <template path="templates/starbursting-worksheet.md" purpose="5W+H question capture sheet with priority-questions section"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
