<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cassandra Wide-Column Modeling Patterns Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules for nosql-cassandra-patterns. Each rule pairs binary check + sourced rationale. Last rule is the terminal skip-this-methodology guard.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="high-cardinality-partition-key" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The partition key MUST have high cardinality (at least thousands of distinct values) and MUST distribute writes evenly across the cluster. Monotonically increasing partition keys (timestamps, auto-increment IDs) MUST be combined with a high-cardinality prefix (sensor_id, user_id, tenant_id) to prevent sequential writes hitting a single token range. Partition size MUST stay under 100 MB and under ~100k rows; validate with nodetool tablehistograms before deploying.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source + faion-net curation">Cassandra places all rows sharing a partition key on the same replica set. A single large partition cannot be split post-creation; it must be re-keyed. Unbounded time-series partitions grow until the node runs out of memory during compaction. Time-bucketing (composite partition key: entity_id + date) caps partition size and keeps it predictable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="table-per-access-pattern" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each distinct query access pattern MUST have a dedicated table (or materialized view) designed for that query. Do NOT add secondary indexes (Cassandra secondary indexes require a full cluster scan on read). Do NOT use ALLOW FILTERING in production queries. When two access patterns need the same data, write to both tables or use a materialized view.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source + faion-net curation">Cassandra's secondary indexes are node-local and require coordinator fan-out to all nodes on read — they perform worse than a full table scan at scale. ALLOW FILTERING is syntactic sugar for "scan every row in every partition that matches the partition key constraints" — it degrades to O(total rows) and blocks coordinator threads.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="lwt-or-counter-as-needed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use lightweight transactions (LWT: INSERT IF NOT EXISTS, UPDATE IF) only when true compare-and-swap semantics are required. LWT uses Paxos internally and has 4x the latency of a regular write; avoid it on hot paths. For counters, use Cassandra counter columns (COUNTER type) rather than read-modify-write. Use conditional writes (ConditionExpression in DynamoDB) anywhere the application logic says "read-then-write".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source + faion-net curation">Cassandra defaults to eventual consistency (ONE or LOCAL_QUORUM tunable). Read-modify-write without LWT has a race condition under concurrent writes: two agents can read the same value and both apply their update, causing lost writes. The COUNTER column type uses server-side delta accumulation to avoid this race.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="partition-size-capped" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each partition MUST stay under ~100 MB / 100k rows; validate with nodetool tablehistograms before production.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source + faion-net curation">Unbounded partitions cause compaction OOM and tombstone storms.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="consistency-explicit-per-query" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Consistency level (ONE / LOCAL_QUORUM / EACH_QUORUM / LWT) MUST be set explicitly on every query, not left to driver defaults.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source + faion-net curation">Defaults vary by driver/version and silently change durability guarantees.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the preconditions in `Applies If` fail or any of the `Skip If` conditions is true, return `skipped` and apply no further rules.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source + faion-net curation">Methodologies are not universal; running them outside their fit-window wastes effort and produces wrong outputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
