<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Focus Groups Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules anchoring the focus-groups methodology, each grounded in a source.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="three-groups-per-segment" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each segment MUST be sampled with &gt;=3 groups before themes are treated as stable; single-group themes MUST NOT ship as recommendations.</statement>
      <rationale source="Focus group methodology literature">Theme stability requires cross-group convergence; single-group themes reflect group-specific dynamics.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="six-to-ten-per-group" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Group size MUST be 6-10 participants (recruit 7-11 to absorb 20% no-show); groups outside this range MUST be flagged.</statement>
      <rationale source="Focus group methodology literature">&lt;6 lacks dynamic; &gt;10 lets quieter participants disappear.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="written-first-then-discussion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each topic MUST start with a 60-second written exercise (individual opinion) before open discussion; opinion-anchoring on the loudest voice is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — focus group moderation audits">Without written-first, dominant participants anchor the group; written-first preserves independent signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="late-concept-reveal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Concept reveal MUST happen in the last 25% of the session, after vocabulary + needs are mapped; early reveal contaminates language data.</statement>
      <rationale source="Focus group methodology literature">Early reveal causes participants to use the concept's vocabulary instead of their own.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="moderator-not-author" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Moderator MUST be a trained facilitator distinct from the product team author; author MAY observe but not moderate.</statement>
      <rationale source="ESOMAR moderation standards">Author bias leaks through leading questions; trained moderators stay neutral.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Skip-If preconditions hold, the methodology MUST be skipped and the caller routed to the linked alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="self">Applying this machinery to the wrong workflow burns tokens without producing a usable artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
