<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Sprint Goal One Liner Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Sprint Goal One Liner Template application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="five-slots-filled" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output sentence MUST fill all five slots: sprint-number, verb, user/system, measurable benefit, surface, out-of-scope. Empty or &apos;?&apos; in any slot rejects the goal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sprint-goal template research">Sprint-goal template research — anchors Sprint Goal One Liner Template rule `five-slots-filled`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="verb-must-be-outcome" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The verb slot MUST express a state change (reduce, enable, ship, eliminate), not a task action (refactor, draft, investigate).</statement>
      <rationale source="Outcome-vs-output discipline">Outcome-vs-output discipline — anchors Sprint Goal One Liner Template rule `verb-must-be-outcome`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="benefit-is-measurable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The &apos;so that&apos; clause MUST contain a number + threshold + window, not adjectives. &apos;Users are happier&apos; fails; &apos;≥65% signup completion on staging cohort within sprint&apos; passes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Goal-Question-Metric">Goal-Question-Metric — anchors Sprint Goal One Liner Template rule `benefit-is-measurable`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="recitable-at-standup" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The full sentence MUST be ≤30 words and pass the recitability test: each team member can paraphrase it without notes by day 2.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cognitive-load research">Cognitive-load research — anchors Sprint Goal One Liner Template rule `recitable-at-standup`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="explicit-out-of-scope" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The deferring clause MUST name a concrete out-of-scope item the team WAS tempted to add. If nothing is being deferred, the sprint is not focused.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scope-discipline practice">Scope-discipline practice — anchors Sprint Goal One Liner Template rule `explicit-out-of-scope`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
