<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Sprint Goal One-Liner Template Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that fix the lexical shape, placement, and lifecycle of the sprint goal sentence.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The sprint goal MUST follow the literal template: `In sprint NN, we will &lt;verb&gt; &lt;user/system change&gt; so that &lt;measurable benefit&gt;, focusing on &lt;surface&gt;, deferring &lt;out-of-scope&gt;`. All five slots MUST be filled. Slot omission fails the planning gate.</statement>
      <rationale>An open template invites the "we'll improve checkout" abstraction. Fixed slots force the PM to name a verb, a benefit, a surface, and an explicit deferral — the four most-missed parts in real-world goals.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The completed sentence MUST be 25 words or fewer (excluding the literal scaffold words "In sprint NN, we will ... so that ... focusing on ... deferring ..."). Longer sentences are split, not allowed.</statement>
      <rationale>Recitability is the function. A goal a team member has to read off a doc is not a goal; it is documentation. 25-word cap is the empirical ceiling for one-breath recitation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The completed sentence MUST be pinned to the team's primary channel as a channel topic or pinned message, and linked from the sprint board description, within 1 working day of planning ending. Both placements are required, not "either-or".</statement>
      <rationale>One placement gets ignored ("the board says..." / "the channel pin says...") depending on each person's tool of choice. Two placements catch both populations and remove any "I didn't see it" excuse.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>At the start of every standup of the sprint, the facilitator MUST read the sprint goal verbatim before any individual updates. Skipping the recitation is forbidden, even on day 2 onwards.</statement>
      <rationale>"We all know it by now" is exactly when drift starts. Daily recitation keeps the goal active in working memory and gives anyone who has lost the thread a free chance to re-orient.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>When the measurable benefit is achieved mid-sprint, the goal MUST be officially retired and replaced by either "stretch / consolidation" framing or a follow-up goal. The team does NOT continue reciting an already-met goal for the remaining days.</statement>
      <rationale>Reciting a met goal trains the team to treat the goal as theatre. Retiring it visibly preserves the signal that the goal is a real artefact tied to real progress.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
In sprint 14, we will ship email-only signup on the web so that signup
completion lifts to ≥65% on staging cohort, focusing on the desktop flow,
deferring mobile and SSO providers.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Five slots filled. 25 words excluding scaffold. Recitable. Pin-ready. Retire-able once measurement crosses 65%.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Goal:
  - Improve signup
  - Fix mobile bugs from last sprint
  - Start exploring SSO
      ]]></code>
      <note>Bullet list instead of a sentence. No verb-led commitment, no measurable benefit, no deferral, three competing focuses. Fails every rule.</note>
    </example>

  </section>
</text>
