<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="card-sorting">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Ask users to organize content topics into groups and label those groups, revealing how users mentally categorize information. Use open sort to discover natural categories, closed sort to validate a proposed structure, or hybrid to refine an existing IA. Requires 15-20 participants for open sort, 30+ for statistically meaningful closed sort results.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>card-sorting</tag>
      <tag>information-architecture</tag>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>user-testing</tag>
      <tag>usability</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Card Sorting</title>

    <summary>Ask users to organize content topics into groups and label those groups, revealing how users mentally categorize information. Use open sort to discover natural categories, closed sort to validate a proposed structure, or hybrid to refine an existing IA. Requires 15-20 participants for open sort, 30+ for statistically meaningful closed sort results.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Navigation structures designed by product teams mirror internal org charts, not user mental models. Card sorting surfaces the vocabulary and groupings real users expect, before the navigation is built. Co-occurrence matrices identify strong clusters (greater than 70% agreement) and problem items that need further investigation.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>You do not know how users think about your content or what labels they expect</item>
        <item>Users cannot find content in the current navigation (high search usage, low direct nav success)</item>
        <item>Designing or redesigning a site/app information architecture from scratch or major overhaul</item>
        <item>Analyzing open-sort exports to compute similarity matrices and candidate IA structure</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Fewer than 10 content items — overhead not justified; use interviews or usability tests instead</item>
        <item>IA already validated through tree testing and live search analytics — re-sorting adds noise</item>
        <item>UI layout or visual hierarchy questions — card sorting answers content organization, not placement</item>
        <item>As a substitute for running the actual study — agents cannot observe real-time hesitation or card-splitting</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="card-sorting-process">
      <p>Six-step process for planning and running card sort studies to inform information architecture decisions.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>State specific research questions before selecting card sort type or preparing cards.</statement>
        <rationale>Goals determine whether to run open (discover categories), closed (validate structure), or hybrid (refine existing IA) sort. Mixing goals in one study produces inconclusive data.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Research questions: How do users group our content? What labels make sense to users? Does our navigation match user mental models?</note>
      </example>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use 30-60 cards with real content labels written in user language, not internal terminology.</statement>
        <rationale>Over 60 cards causes cognitive fatigue. Jargon on cards tests familiarity with internal terminology rather than mental models. Under 10 items does not justify the study overhead.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Recruit 15-20 participants for open sort; 30+ for closed sort statistical validity.</statement>
        <rationale>Below 15 participants, co-occurrence clusters are statistically unstable. Closed sort requires more participants because placement percentages need sufficient N to be meaningful.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Give participants clear, neutral instructions that do not prime any grouping scheme.</statement>
        <rationale>Priming instructions contaminate results. Instructions must state the task without suggesting categories or grouping logic.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Open sort: "Please organize these cards into groups that make sense to you. You can create as many groups as you need. When done, give each group a name."</note>
      </example>

      <rule>
        <statement>Compute co-occurrence rates for all card pairs; apply thresholds: above 70% — group together; 40-70% — borderline; below 40% — keep separate.</statement>
        <rationale>Co-occurrence data reveals which groupings are statistically robust vs. which reflect individual preferences. Outlier cards (below 40% with any partner) indicate content needing redesign, not just recategorization.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="analysis-methods">
      <p>Co-occurrence matrix construction, similarity thresholds, standardization metric, and outlier interpretation rules.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>For each pair of cards, compute the percentage of participants who grouped them together; this is the co-occurrence rate.</statement>
        <rationale>Co-occurrence data reveals statistically robust groupings independent of the category labels participants used, which vary widely between individuals in open sorts.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Apply three-tier thresholds: above 70% co-occurrence — group together in IA; 40-70% — consider grouping, investigate further; below 40% — keep separate or investigate content problem.</statement>
        <rationale>These thresholds are empirically calibrated for 15-20 participant studies. Below 15 participants, all thresholds are statistically meaningless — report sample size prominently when under threshold.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Cards with no co-occurrence above 40% with any partner are outliers — these indicate content that needs redesign (renaming, splitting, or merging), not just recategorization.</statement>
        <rationale>Outlier cards signal that users cannot form a mental model for the content itself, not that the categorization is wrong. Forcing outlier cards into categories produces navigation that feels arbitrary.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Measure standardization (how consistently participants created similar categories) as an overall study quality indicator.</statement>
        <rationale>Low standardization across participants may indicate cards are ambiguous, participants are too heterogeneous, or the content domain has no shared mental model — all of which affect how much weight to give the results.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>High standardization: most users created similar categories — results are reliable, proceed to tree testing</item>
        <item>Low standardization: each user had a unique approach — investigate card label clarity before building IA from this data</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Always run tree testing on the IA structure proposed from card sort results before building; card sorting shows grouping preferences, not findability.</statement>
        <rationale>Card sorting tells you how users group content; it does not tell you whether users can find content in a hierarchical navigation built from those groupings. Tree testing is the validation step.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="examples-and-agentic-workflow">
      <p>Open sort and closed sort examples with real data, common mistakes, and agentic co-occurrence analysis workflow.</p>

      <example type="good">
        <note>E-commerce product categories open sort, 20 participants. Results: 15/20 grouped "Laptops" and "Desktops" together. Participants named this group "Computers" (not "Computing Devices" which was the internal term). "Tablets" split: 8 users with computers, 7 with phones. Insight: Create "Computers" category using user vocabulary; run tree test with Tablets in both locations to determine final placement.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Categories: Electronics, Home, Clothing. Smart Watch: 85% Electronics, 5% Home, 10% Clothing — clear placement. Heated Blanket: 40% Electronics, 55% Home, 5% Clothing — ambiguous, needs further investigation. Fitness Tracker: 70% Electronics, 10% Home, 20% Clothing — acceptable placement with minor ambiguity toward Clothing.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using 80+ cards in a single session.</description>
        <reason>Cognitive fatigue sets in above 60 cards. Participants start grouping quickly without careful consideration, producing lower-quality data. Split into two separate focused studies.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using internal terminology (jargon) on cards.</description>
        <reason>Jargon tests vocabulary familiarity, not mental models. Cards must use user language. If your sitemap says "Resource Hub", the card must say "Guides and Templates".</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Running closed sort without running open sort first.</description>
        <reason>Closed sort can only validate categories you already have. Open sort discovers the categories users actually expect. Running closed sort first bakes in untested assumptions.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <p>Agent receives content inventory (list of page/item names) and generates a card list with jargon replaced by user-friendly language. After study runs, agent receives exported participant groupings as JSON/CSV, computes co-occurrence matrix, identifies strong clusters (above 70%), borderline items (40-70%), and outliers (below 40%). Proposes candidate IA structure. Generates tree test spec as mandatory follow-up.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent produces confident IA recommendations from fewer than 15 participants.</description>
        <reason>Below 15 participants, co-occurrence clusters are statistically unstable. Flag sample size prominently in output and label recommendations as hypotheses requiring validation.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent treats card sort results as final without mandating tree testing.</description>
        <reason>Card sorting shows how users group content; it does not validate that users can find content in a hierarchy built from those groupings. Tree testing is always required before building.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/card-sort-plan.md" purpose="Study plan: objectives, method, participant profile, card list, categories (closed), analysis plan"/>
      <template path="templates/results-report.md" purpose="Results template: category structure, agreement matrix, key insights, IA recommendations"/>
      <template path="templates/cooccurrence.py" purpose="Python script: compute co-occurrence matrix from open sort export; identify strong/weak/outlier clusters"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/card-sorting-definition/"/>
      <link href="https://www.optimalworkshop.com/learn/101s/card-sorting/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/how-to-conduct-a-card-sorting-session"/>
      <link href="https://boxesandarrows.com/card-sorting-a-definitive-guide/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/tree-testing/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
