<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-spec-design" title="OpenAPI Spec Design Rules">
  <summary>Rules for writing OpenAPI 3.1 specifications that serve as contracts for implementation, code generation, and LLM context: schema placement, required fields, versioning, and Spectral linting.</summary>

  <section title="OpenAPI 3.1 Spec Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use OpenAPI 3.1 (not 3.0). Place all reusable schemas in components/schemas and reference them with $ref everywhere. Include example: values in every schema field — Prism mock responses are generated from examples.</statement>
      <rationale>OpenAPI 3.1 aligns with JSON Schema draft 2020-12, enabling richer validation rules. $ref reuse ensures consistency: changing a schema updates it everywhere. Missing examples cause Prism mocks to return empty strings and zero values, making frontend development against the mock useless.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/openapi-skeleton.yaml">OpenAPI 3.1 spec skeleton</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Schema Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark every required field explicitly in the required: array. Use type: ['string', 'null'] (not nullable: true) for optional fields in OpenAPI 3.1. Use format hints (uuid, date-time, email) and validation constraints (minLength, pattern, enum).</statement>
      <rationale>Explicit required arrays and type constraints give LLMs and code generators the information needed to produce correct validation code. nullable: true is OpenAPI 3.0 syntax that is deprecated in 3.1.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
components:
  schemas:
    User:
      type: object
      required: [id, email, created_at]
      properties:
        id:
          type: string
          format: uuid
          example: "123e4567-e89b-12d3-a456-426614174000"
        email:
          type: string
          format: email
          example: "user@example.com"
        display_name:
          type: ['string', 'null']  # Optional, OpenAPI 3.1 style
          maxLength: 100
          example: "Alice"
        created_at:
          type: string
          format: date-time
          example: "2026-01-15T12:00:00Z"
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="API Versioning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use URL path versioning (/v1/, /v2/) for breaking changes. Maintain separate OpenAPI documents per major version. Set info.version with semantic versioning. Mark deprecated endpoints with deprecated: true before removal.</statement>
      <rationale>URL path versioning is visible, cacheable, and easy to test. Separate spec files per major version keep each spec clean and allow tooling to target specific versions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Spectral Linting in CI">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run Spectral linting as a required CI check before any implementation begins. A spec that passes linting is the quality gate for proceeding to mock and implementation phases.</statement>
      <rationale>Spectral catches missing operationIds (which break code generation), missing tags (which break SDK organization), and schema inconsistencies before any code is written.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/spectral-ruleset.yaml">Spectral ruleset configuration</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Spec Drift">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Modifying generated code to deviate from the spec, then not regenerating when the spec changes. The spec and implementation silently diverge.</description>
      <reason>Generated code that diverges from the spec makes the spec a lie. Add a hash of the spec file as a comment in generated files; if the spec changes, the hash mismatch signals that regeneration is required.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
