<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-toolchain" title="API-First Toolchain">
  <summary>The complete API-first workflow: spec → Spectral lint → Prism mock → OpenAPI Generator stubs → schemathesis contract tests. Tool roles and agent prompt patterns for each phase.</summary>

  <section title="Workflow Phases">
    <list>
      <item>DESIGN — Write OpenAPI 3.1 spec (Stoplight Studio, Swagger Editor, or text editor)</item>
      <item>VALIDATE — Spectral lint: spectral lint openapi.yaml --ruleset .spectral.yaml</item>
      <item>MOCK — Prism mock server: prism mock openapi.yaml --port 4010 --dynamic</item>
      <item>IMPLEMENT — Generate stubs: openapi-generator-cli generate -i openapi.yaml -g python-fastapi -o ./generated</item>
      <item>TEST — Contract tests: schemathesis run openapi.yaml --url http://localhost:8000</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Prism Mock Server">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start Prism with --dynamic flag to generate random data from schema constraints when no explicit example is provided. Without --dynamic, missing examples produce empty responses.</statement>
      <rationale>Frontend teams building against the mock need realistic data shapes. --dynamic generates values that match schema types, formats, and constraints even without explicit examples.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Start mock server (lint first)
spectral lint openapi.yaml --ruleset .spectral.yaml
prism mock openapi.yaml --port 4010 --dynamic &
echo "Mock server running at http://localhost:4010"
echo "Docs at http://localhost:4010/__docs"
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Contract Testing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run schemathesis or dredd against the live implementation in CI. When a contract test fails, determine whether the spec or the implementation is correct — never auto-fix the spec to match a buggy implementation.</statement>
      <rationale>Contract tests enforce that the implementation matches its documented contract. Automatically updating the spec to match implementation failures defeats the purpose of the spec as the source of truth.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM Code Generation from Spec">
    <rule>
      <statement>When generating implementation code from spec, pass the full OpenAPI spec as context and instruct the LLM to use operationId values as function names. For APIs with 100+ endpoints, work on one tag group at a time to avoid context window overflow.</statement>
      <rationale>operationId creates a traceable mapping from spec to code. Breaking large specs by tag group keeps the context manageable while maintaining the spec as the grounding source.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Toolchain Quick Reference">
    <list>
      <item>spectral lint — npm install -g @stoplight/spectral-cli</item>
      <item>prism mock — npm install -g @stoplight/prism-cli</item>
      <item>openapi-generator-cli — npm install -g @openapitools/openapi-generator-cli</item>
      <item>schemathesis — pip install schemathesis</item>
      <item>redocly — npm install -g @redocly/cli (bundle, lint, preview)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
