<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="HIPAA BAA Vendor Checklist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules with rationale + source for hipaa-baa-vendor-checklist. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="signed-baa-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every vendor touching PHI MUST have a signed BAA on file before any PHI is shared; the BAA MUST be countersigned and dated.</statement>
      <rationale source="45 CFR 164.504(e) HIPAA BAA">45 CFR 164.504(e) HIPAA BAA — applies to HIPAA BAA Vendor Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="phi-data-flow-mapped" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Checklist MUST include a current data-flow diagram showing every PHI surface the vendor touches; unmapped surfaces block the engagement.</statement>
      <rationale source="HIPAA Security Rule risk analysis">HIPAA Security Rule risk analysis — applies to HIPAA BAA Vendor Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="breach-notification-72h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>BAA MUST require the vendor to notify the covered entity of any PHI breach within 60 calendar days (and contractually narrowed to 72 hours where possible).</statement>
      <rationale source="45 CFR 164.410">45 CFR 164.410 — applies to HIPAA BAA Vendor Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="sub-processor-disclosure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Vendor MUST disclose every sub-processor handling PHI; the covered entity reserves the right to object before a new sub-processor is onboarded.</statement>
      <rationale source="HIPAA + GDPR convergence">HIPAA + GDPR convergence — applies to HIPAA BAA Vendor Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="audit-rights" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>BAA MUST grant the covered entity audit rights with reasonable notice — at least annually or after a security incident.</statement>
      <rationale source="HIPAA Security Rule + best practice">HIPAA Security Rule + best practice — applies to HIPAA BAA Vendor Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="return-or-destroy-clause" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>BAA MUST require return or certified destruction of PHI on contract termination; if infeasible, contractual protections extend post-termination.</statement>
      <rationale source="45 CFR 164.504(e)(2)(ii)(J)">45 CFR 164.504(e)(2)(ii)(J) — applies to HIPAA BAA Vendor Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="encryption-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Vendor MUST encrypt PHI at rest and in transit using NIST-approved algorithms (FIPS 140-2 / 140-3).</statement>
      <rationale source="HIPAA Security Rule + NIST SP 800-111">HIPAA Security Rule + NIST SP 800-111 — applies to HIPAA BAA Vendor Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If no PHI is in scope or HIPAA does not apply to the engagement, return `skipped`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to HIPAA BAA Vendor Checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
