<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ops-annual-planning-templates Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ops-annual-planning-templates. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Fill templates in this order: vision (human only) → strategic priorities (human writes, agent critiques) → annual goals (must have numeric baseline and target) → quarterly breakdown → budget table → not-doing list. Never start with the budget or task list.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Strategy must drive budgets and tasks, not the reverse. Filling budget first anchors the plan to available spend; filling tasks first anchors to current activity. Both undermine strategic clarity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every field an agent cannot ground in provided input data must be left as "[NEEDS HUMAN INPUT: reason]". Agents must not invent metrics, goals, or financials when input data is missing.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Plausible-sounding but invented data in a planning template is more harmful than empty fields. A founder who thinks their CAC is $150 because an LLM generated that number will make wrong budget decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The "Not Doing This Year" section must contain at least 3 concrete items. If a human skips this section, require them to fill it before accepting the plan as complete.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The stop-doing list is the most value-producing section and the most consistently skipped. Without it, the plan adds new priorities on top of existing commitments, which is how founders burn out.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reject any Key Result that: (a) uses activity language ("launch", "build", "ship") instead of outcome language, (b) has no numeric target, or (c) lacks a baseline and measurement source. Require a rewrite before accepting.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Activity KRs measure effort, not impact. A team can ship 5 features and still lose customers. Outcome KRs require the team to think about what "done successfully" looks like from the customer's perspective.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every metric in a filled template must be traceable to a provided input. If the input data does not contain a value, leave the field as "[NEEDS HUMAN INPUT]" with a reason. Do not extrapolate or estimate without labeling estimates as estimates.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Planning templates filled with LLM-generated plausible numbers produce plans that look complete but are grounded in fiction. Founders make real budget and hiring decisions from these plans.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When filling the quarterly review "misses" section, require structural framings ("we under-resourced X" or "we deprioritized Y for Z") rather than external-attribution framings ("market conditions" or "timing was off"). Reject or flag external attribution without structural cause.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Post-hoc rationalization using external causes prevents learning. Structural causes are actionable; market condition causes are not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run the OKR validator (okr-validator.py) on every set of key results before accepting a plan as final. Do not manually review — run the validator and surface all failures before proceeding.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Manual review of OKR quality is inconsistent. The validator applies uniform rules and catches the most common failure modes (activity KRs, missing numbers, missing baselines) mechanically.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Year-in-review documents must not be published or shared externally without explicit founder approval. These artifacts contain financial data, failure modes, and personal reflection that are vulnerability disclosures if released publicly.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Year-in-review posts by founders are often the primary signal competitors use for strategic intelligence. The agent should never auto-publish or share these documents.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
