<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-template-guide" title="Annual Planning Templates — Guide and Fill Rules">
  <summary>Template inventory, fill-order rules, required vs optional sections, and OKR validation criteria.</summary>

  <section title="Template set">
    <list>
      <item>annual-plan.md — full year: vision, theme, 3 goals with metrics, strategic priorities, Q1-Q4 breakdown, budget, not-doing list, review schedule</item>
      <item>quarterly-review.md — results vs goals, wins, misses with root causes, learnings, adjustments, next-quarter focus</item>
      <item>annual-review.md — executive summary, year-by-numbers, accomplishments, challenges, personal reflection</item>
      <item>monthly-plan.md — monthly goal, metrics table, week-by-week breakdown, blockers</item>
      <item>okr-template.md — objective + why it matters + 3 KRs with baseline and target + initiatives</item>
      <item>year-in-review.md — wins with impact, challenges with response, metrics summary, what to do differently</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Fill order and rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Fill templates in this order: vision (human only) → strategic priorities (human writes, agent critiques) → annual goals (must have numeric baseline and target) → quarterly breakdown → budget table → not-doing list. Never start with the budget or task list.</statement>
      <rationale>Strategy must drive budgets and tasks, not the reverse. Filling budget first anchors the plan to available spend; filling tasks first anchors to current activity. Both undermine strategic clarity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every field an agent cannot ground in provided input data must be left as "[NEEDS HUMAN INPUT: reason]". Agents must not invent metrics, goals, or financials when input data is missing.</statement>
      <rationale>Plausible-sounding but invented data in a planning template is more harmful than empty fields. A founder who thinks their CAC is $150 because an LLM generated that number will make wrong budget decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>The "Not Doing This Year" section must contain at least 3 concrete items. If a human skips this section, require them to fill it before accepting the plan as complete.</statement>
      <rationale>The stop-doing list is the most value-producing section and the most consistently skipped. Without it, the plan adds new priorities on top of existing commitments, which is how founders burn out.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="OKR validation criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reject any Key Result that: (a) uses activity language ("launch", "build", "ship") instead of outcome language, (b) has no numeric target, or (c) lacks a baseline and measurement source. Require a rewrite before accepting.</statement>
      <rationale>Activity KRs measure effort, not impact. A team can ship 5 features and still lose customers. Outcome KRs require the team to think about what "done successfully" looks like from the customer's perspective.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>KR: "Launch a referral program by Q2." — This is an activity, not an outcome. It can be done and fail.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>KR: "Increase referral-sourced new customers from 0 to 15/month by end of Q2, measured via Stripe UTM attribution." — Outcome, numeric, baseline, source specified.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/okr-validator.py"/>
    <link path="templates/annual-plan.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
