<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Product Operations Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Product Operations plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="ops-owns-tool-plumbing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Product Ops MUST own roadmap tool, experiment platform, feedback ingestion, and metric warehouse plumbing; PMs MUST NOT be on the on-call rota for these systems.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reforge — Product Operations 2024">PMs maintaining their own tooling drift into ops; the explicit handoff is the only structural defence of discovery time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="weekly-metric-rollup-canonical" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>There MUST be exactly one weekly product-metric rollup (single artefact, single owner, single distribution list); parallel rollups MUST be merged or killed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — product-ops audit 2025-Q4">Parallel rollups produce divergent numbers and stakeholder confusion; canonical rollup is the only stable input to QBRs and strategy memos.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="stakeholder-update-template-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stakeholder updates MUST use the fixed template (north-star metric, weekly delta, top-3 wins, top-3 risks, asks); ad-hoc-shape updates are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Marty Cagan — Empowered (2020)">Variable-shape updates force stakeholders to re-learn each week and degrade signal-to-noise; the fixed template is the contract.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="process-doc-canonical-location" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every product process (intake, prioritisation, release, postmortem) MUST have exactly one canonical doc in .aidocs/process/; duplicates in Notion/Confluence MUST be marked as mirrors and redirect.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — docs convention 2026">Process docs in multiple locations diverge; the canonical-location rule plus mirror policy is the only durable single source.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="automation-before-headcount" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Product Ops MUST attempt to automate a process before requesting headcount; the automation attempt and result MUST be recorded in the request.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reforge — Product Operations 2024">Heading-down-on-headcount-first is the most common cause of Ops bloat; the automation-first rule keeps the function lean.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
