<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Feature Discovery Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Feature Discovery application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="rice-scored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each candidate MUST carry RICE values (Reach / Impact / Confidence / Effort) with numeric inputs and a unit. 'Gut score' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="RICE prioritisation framework">Numeric inputs survive review; gut scores get re-litigated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-three-sources" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Promoting a feature to the top-5 requires ≥3 distinct evidence sources (interviews / tickets / behavioural signals). Single-customer requests are parked.</statement>
      <rationale source="Triangulation discipline">Single-customer requests are anecdotal and inflate the roadmap with low-impact work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-owner-top-5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each top-5 feature names a single owner (handle + role). 'Team' or any placeholder value is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI accountability discipline">Ownerless top features stall; named owners ship.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="parked-revisit-trigger" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each parked feature carries a revisit trigger (measurable threshold or dated event). Open-ended 'maybe later' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice">Without revisit triggers the board accumulates dead candidates that crowd the live ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="capacity-aware-top-five" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Top-5 total Effort MUST fit the next planning cycle's capacity. Overflow forces the lowest-RICE entry to drop or split.</statement>
      <rationale source="Capacity-aware prioritisation">Over-committed roadmaps lie; capacity-bound top-5 ships.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
