<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-sources-and-categorization" title="Feature Signal Sources and Categorization">
  <summary>Four categories of feature signal sources, the Kano model for classifying features, and the Opportunity Scoring formula for identifying high-value gaps.</summary>

  <section title="Signal Sources">
    <list>
      <item>Customer research: interviews, support tickets, feature requests, churn interviews, NPS detractor follow-ups.</item>
      <item>Usage analytics: feature adoption rates, drop-off points, power user behavior, time-in-feature, error rates.</item>
      <item>Competitive analysis: competitor features, competitor gaps, competitor review sentiment, new entrant patterns.</item>
      <item>Market trends: industry reports, technology changes, regulatory changes, adjacent market cross-pollination.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Weight support tickets and feature requests by customer ARR or segment, not by volume; vocal users are not necessarily your most valuable users.</statement>
      <rationale>A free-tier user who requests a feature 10 times has less signal value than a high-ARR customer who mentions it once. Volume-based weighting produces a roadmap optimized for your noisiest, least valuable segment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not add competitor features without understanding the job that feature serves; feature parity copying leads to bloat without retention benefit.</statement>
      <rationale>Competitors build features for their customers, not yours. Copying without understanding the job produces features that fit neither audience.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Kano Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every candidate feature using Kano before scoring; Must-have (threshold), Performance (more is better), Excitement (delight), or Indifferent.</statement>
      <rationale>A Must-have feature that is missing causes dissatisfaction regardless of how many Excitement features are present. Kano prevents the mistake of adding delighters while leaving a basic expectation unmet.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Must-have (Threshold): expected baseline; absence causes dissatisfaction; presence does not impress. Example: login and security.</item>
      <item>Performance (More is better): satisfaction scales linearly with quality. Example: speed, reliability.</item>
      <item>Excitement (Delighter): unexpected feature that generates strong positive response. Example: AI-powered suggestions.</item>
      <item>Indifferent: neither presence nor absence affects satisfaction.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run Kano classification per customer segment, not on the whole user base; the same feature is a Must-have for one segment and Indifferent for another.</statement>
      <rationale>Aggregate Kano surveys hide segment-specific needs. A feature that is Indifferent on average may be critical for your highest-value segment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Opportunity Scoring (ODI)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Calculate Opportunity = Importance + (Importance - Satisfaction) for each outcome; target features where Importance is high and Satisfaction is low.</statement>
      <rationale>The ODI formula surfaces underserved outcomes. High importance with high satisfaction means customers are already served. High importance with low satisfaction is the opportunity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Feature outcome: "View dashboard with just 3 key metrics"
Importance (N=15 interviews): 9/10
Satisfaction with current solution: 4/10
Opportunity = 9 + (9 - 4) = 14 (high priority)

Feature outcome: "Export to CSV"
Importance: 6/10
Satisfaction: 7/10
Opportunity = 6 + (6 - 7) = 5 (low priority)
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
