<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gitlab-cicd Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gitlab-cicd. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use rules: instead of only/except for all conditional job execution.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">only/except is deprecated and cannot combine conditions. rules: supports if/changes/exists combinators and per-rule variable overrides.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use needs: to form a DAG — jobs start when their specific dependencies finish, not after the whole stage finishes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stage-based execution forces serial stage gates. needs: allows test and lint to run in parallel after build, cutting wall-clock time by 30-60%.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep compiled outputs in artifacts, keep dependency folders in cache.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Artifacts are guaranteed delivery between jobs. Cache is best-effort and shared across pipelines. Mixing them causes missing dist/ in deploy jobs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Scope cache keys with a lockfile hash to invalidate when dependencies change.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A stale cache with the wrong package versions causes intermittent test failures that are hard to reproduce.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Parallelize independent jobs using needs: [] or needs: [specific-job] rather than stage ordering.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">With stage ordering, lint waits for all build jobs. With needs: lint can run in parallel with other test jobs as soon as its single dependency finishes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set expire_in on all artifacts. Use 1 day for CI intermediates, longer only for release artifacts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without expiry, artifacts accumulate indefinitely. GitLab default is 30 days which fills storage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include GitLab security templates via include: rather than writing custom SAST/DAST jobs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">GitLab-maintained templates stay updated with new vulnerability signatures. Custom jobs require ongoing maintenance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mark all CI/CD secrets as Protected AND Masked in GitLab variable settings.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Protected limits the variable to protected branches/tags. Masked prevents the value from appearing in job logs. Both are required; neither alone is sufficient.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define environment: name and url on every deploy job, and pair with an on_stop job.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Environments enable deployment tracking, approval workflows, and rollback. Without on_stop, review namespaces accumulate and consume cluster resources.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enable Docker BuildKit and use --cache-from with the latest tag to speed up image builds.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without layer cache reuse, every build starts from scratch. BuildKit parallelizes layer builds and enables cache import/export.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use when: manual for production deployments; use automated sync for staging.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Production requires human gate. Staging should be continuously deployed to catch integration issues early.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
