<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="product-led-growth">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-operations</domain>
    <summary>PLG uses the product itself as the primary acquisition engine: self-serve onboarding, "aha moment" under 5 minutes, usage-gated upgrades, and PQL scoring for sales-assist handoff.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>plg</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>activation</tag>
      <tag>freemium</tag>
      <tag>saas</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>growth</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Product-Led Growth (PLG)</title>
    <summary>PLG uses the product itself as the primary acquisition, activation, and expansion engine: self-serve onboarding, a clearly defined "aha moment" under 5 minutes, usage-gated upgrade triggers, and PQL scoring that hands off to sales-assist at the right moment. The agent workflow instruments the funnel, generates activation hypotheses, ships the smallest in-product change behind a feature flag, and gates experimentation behind SRM check and pre-registered MDE.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Traditional sales-led growth economics break down below ~$25k ACV — the cost per SDR exceeds the contract value. PLG companies achieve higher revenue per employee (Ahrefs reached $40M ARR with 40 people) because the product itself drives the conversion loop. Without instrumentation-first discipline, agents optimise on uninstrumented funnels and hill-climb noise; without a usage-gate in the free tier, there is no upgrade trigger.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>SaaS / dev tools / API products where users can self-onboard without sales (Linear, Vercel, PostHog pattern).</item>
        <item>ACV under ~$25k where sales-led economics break down; freemium → paid conversion is the growth lever.</item>
        <item>Product produces measurable in-app events (signup, activation step, feature use) that can drive PQL scoring.</item>
        <item>Bottom-up motion targeting individual contributors who later expand to teams (Slack, Notion, Figma pattern).</item>
        <item>Existing product with traffic but flat activation — room for funnel instrumentation and onboarding redesign.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Highly regulated, procurement-heavy enterprise sales (defense, banking core) — buyer is not the user.</item>
        <item>Products requiring data integration, on-prem deploy, or contracts before any value can be shown.</item>
        <item>ACV above ~$100k where one closed deal pays for many SDRs; sales-led ROI dominates.</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF: PLG amplifies a working loop; on a broken product it industrialises churn.</item>
        <item>Network products without single-player value — optimising activation has no payoff if the user lands alone.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Core Principles">
      <rule>
        <statement>Build PLG on four principles: self-serve onboarding (users activate without sales intervention), time-to-value optimization ("aha moment" under 5 minutes), product virality (built-in sharing and collaboration), and expansion revenue (upsell through usage, not sales calls).</statement>
        <rationale>PLG companies achieve higher revenue per employee because the product replaces costly sales motion at the SMB/prosumer tier; without all four principles the loop is incomplete — viral without self-serve requires human handoff, expansion without a usage gate requires sales calls.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Key Metrics (2026 Targets)">
      <list>
        <item>Activation Rate: % users completing key value actions — target above 40%</item>
        <item>Time-to-Value (TTV): minutes to "aha moment" — target under 5 minutes</item>
        <item>Product Qualified Leads (PQLs): users showing buying signals — track weekly</item>
        <item>Expansion Revenue Rate: revenue from self-serve upgrades — target above 30% of total</item>
        <item>Net Revenue Retention (NRR): revenue retained plus expansion — target above 120%</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Define activation as the smallest event sequence that predicts D30 retention, then back-test on historical cohorts before locking the metric. Vanity activation rates that don't predict retention drive wrong optimizations.</statement>
        <rationale>Winning variants on activation can cannibalise D30 retention if activation is defined as "completed onboarding tour" rather than "reached core value". The back-test is the safeguard.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="PLG Onboarding Pattern">
      <list>
        <item>SSO/social login — reduce step-one drop-off</item>
        <item>Interactive product tours, not documentation pages</item>
        <item>Progressive feature disclosure — no feature dump on first session</item>
        <item>Contextual tooltips at moment of relevance, not pre-emptive</item>
        <item>Personalized onboarding paths by user segment — 3-tour designs consistently beat 1-tour</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Bake usage limits into the free tier from day one. Without a friction edge, there is no upgrade trigger and expansion revenue stalls.</statement>
        <rationale>The "freemium tax" — free tier consuming infra cost but converting under 2% — is the direct consequence of a free tier with no usage gate. The upgrade trigger must exist in the product design, not in a sales email.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="PLG Evolution (2026)">
      <p>One-size-fits-all freemium is declining. The current pattern: tailored free tiers by user persona, AI-driven onboarding personalization, and hybrid PLG + sales-assist for enterprise segments above the SMB ceiling.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pair PLG with sales-assist above the SMB ceiling — PLG expansion ceilings are real. The strategic question is when to add humans, not whether to add them.</statement>
        <rationale>PQLs surface at the SMB ceiling and stall without a human follow-up motion. Expansion revenue stalls when no sales-assist exists to close team-wide or enterprise contracts.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Instrumentation-First Rule">
      <rule>
        <statement>Instrument the funnel before optimizing. Agents producing variants on uninstrumented funnels hill-climb noise — there is no signal to optimize against.</statement>
        <rationale>PLG optimization is fundamentally an empirical loop; without telemetry, every "improvement" is untestable and every "result" is confirmation bias.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep one north-star metric (activation rate, NRR, or PQL-to-paid) per quarter. Rotate hypotheses, not metrics.</statement>
        <rationale>Changing the north-star metric mid-quarter makes quarter-over-quarter comparison impossible and hides whether interventions are working or just moving a different number.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Experiment Design Rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Gate every experiment behind SRM (sample-ratio mismatch) check and a pre-registered MDE (minimum detectable effect). Enforce minimum exposure of ≥1k users per variant and minimum runtime of ≥7 days before allowing a winner call.</statement>
        <rationale>Both SRM and pre-registered MDE catch the most common "lift" mirages — exposing too few users or running too short produces statistically invalid conclusions that agents will confidently report as wins.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>When optimizing onboarding, default to subtraction before addition. Prompt agents with "subtract first" and a step-count budget. Tour-builder agents tend to add steps; PLG wins usually come from removing friction.</statement>
        <rationale>The cognitive load of each onboarding step adds drop-off risk. The empirical pattern across PLG products is that removing a step typically outperforms adding a better version of the same step.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always require a retention guardrail metric alongside activation. Winning variants on activation that cannibalise D30 retention must be rejected.</statement>
        <rationale>Activation and retention are not always aligned — a highly frictionless onboarding that skips important setup steps can produce activation wins that reverse by day 30.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="PQL Scoring">
      <rule>
        <statement>Define PQL weights from in-product events that predict upgrade intent (workspace_created, second_user_invited, integration_added, limit_warning_seen), not vanity events (logged in, viewed dashboard). Score users as hot (≥12), warm (≥6), cold (below 6).</statement>
        <rationale>PQL scoring based on vanity events produces a scoring system that identifies engaged free users, not users likely to pay. Upgrade-intent events (limit warnings, team invitations) predict conversion; pageviews do not.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Schedule quarterly PQL model recalibration. The event weights an agent ships today decay as the product changes; a static threshold becomes progressively wrong.</statement>
        <rationale>Product changes alter which events predict upgrade intent. A PQL model trained on v1 behavior systematically mis-scores users on v3 behavior without recalibration.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Limitations and Failure Modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running PLG optimization on a pre-PMF product with insufficient retention signal.</description>
        <reason>PLG amplifies a working loop; on a broken product it industrialises churn. Establish product-market fit before instrumenting the PLG funnel.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>AI onboarding personalization attempting to reference user behavior data before any events have been captured (cold start in first 60 seconds).</description>
        <reason>Enforce a "no behavioural reference before event N" rule. Cold-start personalization that references unavailable data produces error messages or hallucinated user attributes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Privacy regimes (GDPR, India DPDP) restricting event tracking that PLG analytics depend on, with consent-mode gaps distorting funnels.</description>
        <reason>Instrument consent-mode handling before running PLG analytics. Funnels measured without accounting for consent gaps systematically under-count users in regulated markets.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Freemium tax": free tier consumes infra cost but converts less than 2% — common when no usage-gated upgrade trigger exists.</description>
        <reason>Without a friction edge in the free tier, there is no upgrade trigger. The business model fails before the funnel optimization begins.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>TTV measured by clicks, not value: vanity activation rates that don't predict retention.</description>
        <reason>Optimizing on the wrong metric produces wrong interventions. Define activation as a retention-predictive event sequence, not a click count.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>One-size onboarding for distinct personas → low activation across all of them; segmentation is the unlock.</description>
        <reason>Personas have different value drivers. Single-tour designs lose to 3-tour designs almost every time.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Sales-assist gap: PQLs surface but no human follow-up motion → expansion revenue stalls at SMB ceiling.</description>
        <reason>PQLs without sales support don't convert to team/enterprise deals. Add sales-assist at the SMB-to-enterprise inflection point.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Safety Rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pricing and packaging changes require human approval. Revenue regression risk from autonomous pricing changes is non-recoverable — never delegate these to an agent without a human approval gate.</statement>
        <rationale>An agent that can autonomously change a pricing tier can inadvertently destroy MRR for an entire customer segment in a single run. The failure mode is irreversible within the billing cycle.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not let agents touch consent or cookie banner logic. One mis-step breaks all downstream PLG telemetry.</statement>
        <rationale>PLG analytics depend entirely on event capture; corrupting the consent layer silently breaks all measurement without an obvious error signal, causing strategy decisions to be made on invalid data.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not let agents autonomously change a stakeholder's engagement level or send communications to external users. These are relationship decisions with political and legal consequences.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated communications to users without human review can violate communication preferences, trigger opt-outs, or send legally sensitive messages without approval.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Failure Modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents over-fitting on small samples: calling a winner with fewer than 1k users per variant or fewer than 7 days of runtime.</description>
        <reason>Enforce the minimum exposure and runtime gates at the agent output layer, not just in the prompt. Agents will call winners on day 2 with 200 users per variant if not blocked.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs inventing metrics ("engagement score 0-100") that have no source event in the analytics schema.</description>
        <reason>Constrain output to a known event vocabulary loaded from the analytics schema. Invented metrics cannot be tracked or validated.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Tour-builder agents adding steps rather than removing them, even when prompted to optimize onboarding.</description>
        <reason>Prompt explicitly with "subtract first" and a step-count budget. Monitor step-count delta as a guardrail metric alongside activation rate.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>PQL scoring drift: static model becomes wrong as the product evolves but continues to be used without recalibration.</description>
        <reason>Schedule quarterly PQL model recalibration as a standing SDD task. Flag if the model has not been recalibrated in 90+ days.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>PLG is an instrumentation-and-iteration loop, which maps cleanly to subagent orchestration. Use a researcher-style agent to inventory the current funnel (events, drop-offs, persona splits), a planner agent to propose an activation hypothesis with one metric to move, and an executor agent to ship the smallest in-product change (tour copy, default state, gate placement). Pair this with faion-sdd-execution so each PLG experiment ships through the same SDD quality gates as code, and use faion-brainstorm for diverging activation hypotheses before converging on the one to test. Keep humans in the loop for pricing/packaging changes — those are not safe to automate.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — drives an activation experiment as an SDD task: spec (hypothesis, metric, guardrail) → design (event schema, variant) → impl → test-plan (SRM check, MDE).</item>
        <item>faion-brainstorm — diverge/converge on activation hypotheses and TTV interventions before committing to a test.</item>
        <item>faion-improver — session loop to audit funnel telemetry, find leak with biggest delta, file improvement task.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools and Services">
      <p>Essential tools for PLG instrumentation and experimentation:</p>
      <list>
        <item>PostHog — Self-host product analytics, funnels, session replay, feature flags, A/B testing. https://posthog.com/docs/api</item>
        <item>GrowthBook — OSS feature flagging + experimentation, Bayesian stats. https://docs.growthbook.io/tools/cli</item>
        <item>Statsig — Feature gates, holdouts, exposure logs, PQL scoring. https://docs.statsig.com/sdks/cli</item>
        <item>Amplitude API — Funnels, cohorts, export raw events for offline PQL scoring. https://www.docs.developers.amplitude.com</item>
        <item>Mixpanel API — Funnels + JQL for custom PQL queries. https://developer.mixpanel.com</item>
        <item>Segment / RudderStack — Event pipeline, ID resolution, downstream fanout. https://www.rudderstack.com/docs/cli</item>
        <item>Stripe CLI — Subscription lifecycle, usage records, webhook listeners for upgrade events. https://docs.stripe.com/stripe-cli</item>
        <item>dbt — Transform raw events → activation/PQL/NRR models in warehouse. https://docs.getdbt.com</item>
        <item>Cube.dev — Semantic layer for PLG metrics (activation, TTV, NRR) shared across stack. https://cube.dev/docs</item>
      </list>
      <p>Service selection:</p>
      <list>
        <item>PostHog (OSS + Cloud) — Best default for agent-driven PLG; replays + flags + experiments in one.</item>
        <item>GrowthBook (OSS + Cloud) — Cleanest experimentation API; pairs with any analytics warehouse.</item>
        <item>Statsig (SaaS) — Strong holdout + sequential testing; PQL scoring built in.</item>
        <item>Amplitude (SaaS) — Rich charts but agent ergonomics worse than PostHog.</item>
        <item>Mixpanel (SaaS) — JQL good for ad-hoc PQL queries; less native experimentation.</item>
        <item>Pendo / Appcues / Userflow (SaaS) — In-app tours; webhooks decent, code-as-source weak — risky for agent edits.</item>
        <item>Frigade (SaaS) — Onboarding flows as code → agent can PR a tour.</item>
        <item>Endgame / Pocus / Correlated (SaaS) — PQL signal layer; feeds reverse ETL into CRM for sales-assist.</item>
        <item>Hightouch / Census (SaaS) — Reverse ETL warehouse → Salesforce/HubSpot for PQL handoff.</item>
        <item>ProfitWell / ChartMogul (SaaS) — NRR, expansion, churn — the financial counterpart to activation metrics.</item>
        <item>Stripe Billing (SaaS) — Usage-based billing, the engine behind expansion revenue.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Define activation as the smallest event sequence that predicts D30 retention; back-test before locking the metric.</item>
        <item>Instrument before you optimise — agents producing variants on uninstrumented funnels will hill-climb noise.</item>
        <item>Keep one north-star metric (activation rate, NRR, or PQL→paid) per quarter; rotate hypotheses, not metrics.</item>
        <item>Gate experimentation behind SRM (sample-ratio mismatch) and pre-registered MDE; both catch most "lift" mirages.</item>
        <item>Bake usage limits into the free tier from day one; without a friction edge there is no upgrade trigger.</item>
        <item>Pair PLG with sales-assist above $X MRR — PLG ceilings are real; the question is when to add humans, not whether.</item>
        <item>Persona-segment onboarding — single-tour designs lose to 3-tour designs almost every time, and AI personalisation works best layered on top of segments.</item>
        <item>Treat copy and defaults as code: PR-reviewed, versioned, behind flags. Lets agents safely contribute.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Prompt Patterns for Agent Workflows">
      <p>PLG Growth Analyst:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a PLG growth analyst. Given this funnel snapshot
(<events JSON>) and persona segment (<segment>), identify the
single largest drop-off where lift > MDE 3pp is plausible in 14d.
Output: hypothesis, metric, guardrail metric, smallest-change variant.
No copy that requires legal review. Return strict JSON.]]></code>
      <p>Onboarding Editor:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are an onboarding editor. Rewrite step <N> tooltip so that
TTV for persona <P> drops below 5 minutes. Constraints: <=14 words,
no marketing language, must reference the action the user just
took. Output 3 variants + rationale per variant.]]></code>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/pql-scorer.py" purpose="PostHog-based PQL scorer: weight in-app events, write pql_score + pql_tier back as person properties"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://posthog.com/handbook">PostHog Handbook — PLG instrumentation patterns</link>
      <link href="https://docs.growthbook.io">GrowthBook docs — experimentation methodology</link>
      <link href="https://productled.com">ProductLed Institute — frameworks and case studies</link>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com">Reforge — Growth Loops and PLG curricula</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
