<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Change Order Mini Contract — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every change-order email must enforce. These are HARD rules — eagerness to keep the client happy cannot override them.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The change order MUST reference the master agreement by name + date + signed-version hash or identifier; an order that does not anchor to a parent is a new agreement, not a change.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-law amendment doctrine (Restatement (Second) §283 + UK Misrepresentation Act)">Unanchored modifications create disputes over which terms (limitation of liability, IP assignment, payment) carry through.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The order MUST contain four explicit deltas: scope_delta (verbatim deliverable text), price_delta (fixed sum OR hourly cap), schedule_delta (new end date or "no change"), and payment_terms_delta (net-N or up-front %); deltas that say "TBD" reject the order.</statement>
      <rationale source="Construction industry AIA G701 change-order standard">Ambiguous deltas are the #1 cause of post-delivery payment disputes; closed fields force the conversation while goodwill is still present.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The order MUST include a single-sentence acceptance clause: "Reply YES to this email to authorize this change order under the terms of the master agreement"; replies of "ok"/"sure"/"go ahead" SHOULD be accepted only when accompanied by a quote of the table.</statement>
      <rationale source="E-SIGN Act (US) 15 USC §7001 + eIDAS Regulation (EU) No 910/2014">A clear assent + intent-to-be-bound is the minimum threshold; ambiguous "ok" creates re-litigation risk later.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Work on the changed scope MUST NOT begin before the signed reply is captured and stored; if the client pressures for parallel work, the freelancer sends a one-line "starting under verbal authorization, please confirm in email today" — verbal-only work is capped at 8 hours.</statement>
      <rationale source="Unauthorised-work doctrine + freelancer-collections research (Freelancers Union annual report)">Verbal authorizations are unenforceable in half of jurisdictions; the 8-hour cap bounds the loss when the client ghosts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The signed change order MUST be stored as an immutable artifact (PDF, email thread, signed document service entry) and referenced in the invoice line item that bills it; invoices that bill a change without referencing its identifier reject themselves.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-trail + collections best practice">Invoices challenged at payment time win on the back of a single referenceable artifact; the link from invoice → order → master is what closes the loop.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Anchored change-order email">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Subject: Change Order CO-002 — Acme Web Portal SOW dated 2026-04-12

Hi Sam,

Per our chat today, here is the change order for the new client-export feature, applying under our master SOW dated 2026-04-12.

| Field | Delta |
|-------|-------|
| Scope | Add CSV export endpoint + UI button on /clients page. |
| Price | +$1,200 flat (fixed). |
| Schedule | New end date 2026-05-29 (+5 business days). |
| Payment | Billed on completion, net-14, same terms as SOW. |

Reply YES to this email to authorize this change order under the terms of the master agreement.

— Alex
]]></code>
      <note>Anchored to SOW, four explicit deltas, single-sentence acceptance, no ambiguity.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Un-anchored change-order chat">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"sure, can add the export thing, will throw it in this week, sort the bill at the end"
]]></code>
      <note>No master reference, no price delta, no schedule delta, no acceptance. The freelancer will eat this scope.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="../scope-creep-prevention-on-hourly/" />
  </see-also>
</text>
