<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="employee-value-proposition Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for employee-value-proposition. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Structure every EVP around exactly five pillars: Compensation, Benefits, Career, Work Environment, and Culture/Purpose. Each pillar must have at least three named proof points before external use.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A pillar without proof points is aspirational copy. Glassdoor reviews immediately expose claims that do not match employee experience, creating recruiter credibility loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Follow the Discover-Define-Deliver-Measure sequence. Do not skip Discover (surveys + exit interviews + competitor analysis) before drafting the EVP statement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">EVP drafted without Discover produces leadership talking points, not what employees actually experience. The gap between aspiration and reality is the leading cause of EVP backlash.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reject any EVP pillar that cannot be backed by at least three named proof points from internal programs, budgets, or data. Replace unsupported claims with UNVERIFIED placeholders for human fill-in.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Aspirational copy without evidence is detectable by candidates within the first 30 days and surfaces as Glassdoor reviews citing "company doesn't match the pitch." This destroys recruiter credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never invent diversity statistics. Use UNVERIFIED placeholders that humans fill from HRIS. Published false diversity metrics are a serious reputation and legal risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">DEI claims without internal data are reputation risk; agents synthesizing from public sources will produce percentages that contradict what employees see daily.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a post-pass stripping generic clichés ("innovative," "passionate," "fast-paced," "world-class") from every EVP draft.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs default to these phrases; they add word count with zero signal and are the most common reason candidates call EVPs "corporate speak."</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies-If preconditions fail OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or to no methodology at all).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application of a methodology produces worse artefacts than no methodology at all because downstream consumers trust the schema and act on bad data. The skip-record makes the non-application traceable so future audits can detect drift.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
