<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="EVP Five-Pillar Framework">
  <summary>The five EVP pillars, Discover-Define-Deliver-Measure process, and Gartner Human Deal evolution.</summary>

  <section title="The five pillars">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure every EVP around exactly five pillars: Compensation, Benefits, Career, Work Environment, and Culture/Purpose. Each pillar must have at least three named proof points before external use.</statement>
      <rationale>A pillar without proof points is aspirational copy. Glassdoor reviews immediately expose claims that do not match employee experience, creating recruiter credibility loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Compensation: base salary, bonuses, equity, perks — total financial rewards.</item>
      <item>Benefits: health, PTO, parental leave, wellness — non-financial rewards.</item>
      <item>Career: promotions, learning budget, mentorship, mobility — growth opportunities.</item>
      <item>Work Environment: flexibility, tools, team culture, office — day-to-day experience.</item>
      <item>Culture/Purpose: mission, values, impact, belonging — why the work matters.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Development process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow the Discover-Define-Deliver-Measure sequence. Do not skip Discover (surveys + exit interviews + competitor analysis) before drafting the EVP statement.</statement>
      <rationale>EVP drafted without Discover produces leadership talking points, not what employees actually experience. The gap between aspiration and reality is the leading cause of EVP backlash.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Discover: employee surveys, exit interviews, candidate feedback, competitor analysis.</item>
      <item>Define: identify unique strengths, prioritize top 3-5 attributes, craft EVP statement, develop pillars.</item>
      <item>Deliver: communicate internally first, integrate into employer brand, train recruiters, embed in candidate experience.</item>
      <item>Measure: track application rate, offer acceptance, referrals, Glassdoor rating, candidate NPS.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Gartner Human Deal evolution">
    <p>Gartner research (2021+) shows the traditional transactional EVP ("what we offer") is evolving toward a Human Deal that addresses emotional needs, not just contractual ones.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Deeper Connections: family and community support so employees feel understood.</item>
      <item>Radical Flexibility: autonomy over when, where, and how work happens.</item>
      <item>Personal Growth: grow as people, not just professionals.</item>
      <item>Holistic Well-being: physical, mental, financial, and social wellness.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/evp-statement.txt">Fill-in-blank EVP statement template.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/evp-discovery-survey.md">Employee survey for pillar discovery.</reference>
</text>
