<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="EVP Examples by Company Type">
  <summary>Three worked EVP examples (tech startup, remote-first, mission-driven) showing statement and pillar breakdown.</summary>

  <section title="Tech startup EVP">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Early-stage B2B SaaS, 50 employees. Wins on impact and growth; competes on equity.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
EVP Statement:
"For ambitious engineers who want to make an outsized impact, TechCo offers
the rare combination of startup ownership with scale-up stability. Build
products used by millions while growing your career faster than at any BigCo."

Pillar 1 — Impact: own features end-to-end, ship weekly
  Proof points: direct Jira ownership per engineer, weekly releases, zero approval layers
Pillar 2 — Growth: engineering ladder, $5K L&D budget
  Proof points: published IC1-IC6 ladder doc, documented L&D policy, 3 internal promotions last year
Pillar 3 — Equity: meaningful options, not tokens
  Proof points: 0.1-0.5% grants at IC3+, standard 4-year/1-year cliff, published strike prices
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Remote-first EVP">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Fully remote, 200 employees across 30 countries. Wins on flexibility and inclusion.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
EVP Statement:
"For professionals who believe great work happens anywhere, RemoteCo provides
true location independence with the connection of a tight-knit team. Work from
Bali or Baltimore — your impact matters, not your timezone."

Pillar 1 — Flexibility: work from anywhere, async-first
  Proof points: no required meeting hours, home-office stipend $2K/year, overlap hours 2h/day max
Pillar 2 — Connection: quarterly meetups, strong culture
  Proof points: 4 team retreats/year, Donut coffee-chat program, Culture Amp score 4.3
Pillar 3 — Inclusion: equal pay globally, diverse team
  Proof points: location-adjusted salary bands published internally, 43% non-US employees
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Mission-driven EVP">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Climate tech company. Wins on purpose and innovation; accepts below-market comp.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
EVP Statement:
"For those who want their work to matter, ClimateCo offers the rare chance to
build technology that directly fights climate change. Join scientists and
engineers who chose impact over increments."

Pillar 1 — Purpose: direct climate impact
  Proof points: 12 MtCO2e avoided (verifiable, published), B-Corp certified, mission KPIs shared quarterly
Pillar 2 — Innovation: cutting-edge clean tech
  Proof points: 3 patents filed 2024, $2M R&D budget, 6 PhDs on team
Pillar 3 — Community: work with passionate people
  Proof points: Glassdoor 4.6, eNPS +52, avg tenure 3.1 years (above sector median)
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
