<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules-and-gotchas" title="EVP Agent Rules and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Proof-point gate, common EVP antipatterns, and agent-specific failure modes including DEI and localization risks.</summary>

  <section title="The proof-point gate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reject any EVP pillar that cannot be backed by at least three named proof points from internal programs, budgets, or data. Replace unsupported claims with UNVERIFIED placeholders for human fill-in.</statement>
      <rationale>Aspirational copy without evidence is detectable by candidates within the first 30 days and surfaces as Glassdoor reviews citing "company doesn't match the pitch." This destroys recruiter credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Generic claims: "innovative culture," "great people," "make a difference."</description>
      <reason>Every employer says this. Generic claims provide zero differentiation and signal that the EVP was written without employee research.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>One-size-fits-all messaging across all role families.</description>
      <reason>Engineers care primarily about technical growth; sales reps care about uncapped earnings; ops cares about process and stability. A single message under-converts all three.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Never updating the EVP after initial launch.</description>
      <reason>EVP becomes stale as benefits, culture, and leadership change. An EVP that no longer matches reality is worse than no EVP — it creates disappointed hires who become Glassdoor detractors.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent-specific failure modes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never invent diversity statistics. Use UNVERIFIED placeholders that humans fill from HRIS. Published false diversity metrics are a serious reputation and legal risk.</statement>
      <rationale>DEI claims without internal data are reputation risk; agents synthesizing from public sources will produce percentages that contradict what employees see daily.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a post-pass stripping generic clichés ("innovative," "passionate," "fast-paced," "world-class") from every EVP draft.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs default to these phrases; they add word count with zero signal and are the most common reason candidates call EVPs "corporate speak."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Direct translation of a US-centric EVP to EU/LATAM markets without localization (e.g., equity framing in countries where options are taxed at grant).</description>
      <reason>Localization failures produce legally inaccurate or culturally tone-deaf offers that candidates reject at higher rates than generic ones.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/evp-competitive-analysis.md">Competitor EVP comparison table and positioning map.</reference>
</text>
