<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="cognitive-inclusion-design">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>Design patterns for ADHD, autism, dyslexia, anxiety: auto-save, progress, predictable navigation, plain language, dyslexia fonts, reduced motion, non-blaming errors. Serves 15-20% of population.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>cognitive-accessibility</tag>
      <tag>neurodiversity</tag>
      <tag>adhd</tag>
      <tag>autism</tag>
      <tag>dyslexia</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Cognitive Inclusion Design</title>
    <summary>Design patterns for cognitive accessibility: ADHD, autism, dyslexia, anxiety, learning disabilities (15-20% of population). Auto-save, progress indicators, predictable navigation, plain language, dyslexia-friendly typography, reduced-motion defaults, non-blaming errors, sensory-friendly modes.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>WCAG 2.1 addressed cognitive accessibility only thinly; WCAG 2.2 added 3.2.6 Consistent Help, 3.3.7 Redundant Entry, and 3.3.8 Accessible Authentication as direct cognitive accommodations. The remaining gap is large: form abandonment, cognitive overload in dashboards, and anxiety from blame-language errors affect millions of users with ADHD, autism, dyslexia, or anxiety who do not appear in standard AT usage statistics. EU EAA now expects WCAG 2.2 AA plus applicable cognitive guidance for covered product categories.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing or auditing forms, dashboards, learning tools, government services, or healthcare apps used by a non-expert public.</item>
        <item>Reducing form abandonment or support load on complex multi-step flows.</item>
        <item>Auditing copy, error messages, and microcopy for plain language and non-blaming tone.</item>
        <item>Working in EU (EAA) where WCAG 2.2 AA + cognitive guidance is expected.</item>
        <item>Accommodating neurodiverse employees in internal tools (HR platforms, intranets).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure visual/motor a11y audit — use `a11y-testing` and `wcag-22-compliance`.</item>
        <item>Performance-driven, expert-only tooling (CLI dashboards for SREs) — minimalism trumps scaffolding.</item>
        <item>Marketing landing pages where brand voice is intentionally playful — idioms acceptable in moderation.</item>
        <item>Game design where challenge is the point — apply selectively (settings menu, onboarding only).</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="adhd-friendly-design">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Auto-save all form progress every 15-30 seconds and display an explicit "All changes saved" indicator — never rely on browser memory or session state.</statement>
        <rationale>ADHD users are frequently interrupted or switch tasks mid-flow. Lost progress from distraction is the leading cause of task abandonment for this group. Auto-save to server storage (not localStorage) prevents data loss on shared devices.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Show step-and-total progress indicator on multi-step tasks (e.g., "Step 2 of 5").</item>
        <item>Provide "Save and continue later" with email magic link on any form longer than 3 steps.</item>
        <item>Respect prefers-reduced-motion: disable auto-playing animations, make carousels pauseable, offer static alternatives.</item>
        <item>Focus mode: hide non-essential UI elements and reduce notifications on demand.</item>
        <item>Remember scroll position on return to in-progress items.</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-save data to localStorage without scoping to authenticated session.</description>
        <reason>Shared devices expose draft data to other users. Scope auto-save to the authenticated user's server-side session.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="autism-friendly-design">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use only literal language in UI copy — no idioms, no metaphors, no ambiguous phrases. Pair every icon with a text label.</statement>
        <rationale>Autistic users often process language literally. Icons without labels are ambiguous for autism and aphasia users. Idiomatic error messages ("Something went wrong") convey no actionable information.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad" title="Idioms and ambiguous language">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Piece of cake!" (ambiguous success message)
"Click here" (where is here?)
"Think outside the box" (non-literal instruction)
"Something went wrong" (no actionable guidance)
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Literal, clear language">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Your file was saved."
"Submit your application"
"Consider alternative solutions"
"Your payment failed. Please check your card number and try again."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <list>
        <item>Consistent button and navigation placement across all pages — same action always in the same position.</item>
        <item>No unexpected popups or auto-redirects without user confirmation.</item>
        <item>Clear visual boundaries between sections (defined borders, whitespace).</item>
        <item>Show a "You will leave this page" warning before external links or session changes.</item>
        <item>Sensory-friendly color palettes: muted, no harsh color combinations; provide high-contrast mode as opt-in.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="dyslexia-friendly-design">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use left-aligned, sans-serif body text at minimum 16px with at least 1.5 line-height, 0.12em letter-spacing, and no justified alignment.</statement>
        <rationale>Justified text creates variable word spacing ("rivers") that disrupts tracking for dyslexic readers. Ragged right edges and extra spacing reduce word reversal errors and improve reading speed.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Dyslexia-friendly typography">
        <code lang="css"><![CDATA[
/* Dyslexia-friendly typography */
body {
  font-family: Arial, Verdana, sans-serif; /* clean sans-serif */
  font-size: 16px;
  line-height: 1.5;
  letter-spacing: 0.12em;
  word-spacing: 0.16em;
  text-align: left; /* never justify */
}

p {
  max-width: 70ch; /* optimal line length */
  margin-bottom: 2em;
}
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <list>
        <item>Avoid serif and decorative fonts for body text.</item>
        <item>OpenDyslexic font as opt-in (not forced — preference varies; some studies show no universal benefit).</item>
        <item>High contrast: black on white or cream/beige; never gray-on-gray.</item>
        <item>Text-to-speech: built-in read-aloud with synchronized text highlighting and adjustable speed.</item>
        <item>Never use color alone as the only indicator of meaning.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="anxiety-friendly-design">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use inline validation with positive confirmation — never wait until form submit to reveal all errors at once, and never use blaming language in error messages.</statement>
        <rationale>Submit-time error dumps overwhelm anxious users. Blame-language ("You entered an invalid value") triggers avoidance. Immediate, calm, actionable feedback reduces cognitive load and builds trust.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad" title="Blame-language and delayed feedback">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"You failed to enter a valid email address."
"Error: Invalid input detected."
"Your session has expired. All data lost."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Calm, actionable feedback">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Please enter a valid email, for example: name@example.com"
"Your draft was saved. You can continue later."
"Your password is strong."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <list>
        <item>Provide undo functionality and confirmation before any destructive action.</item>
        <item>Show progress and completion indicators ("You're almost done! Step 4 of 5").</item>
        <item>Include obvious "Cancel" or "Go back" buttons — no dead ends or traps.</item>
        <item>Breadcrumb navigation so users always know where they are and how to go back.</item>
        <item>Avoid overcrowding choices — chunk options into groups of 5-7 maximum.</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Over-apologetic copy: "We're so sorry this happened!" on every error.</description>
        <reason>Excessive apology language is itself anxiety-inducing for many users; aim for calm, neutral, factual tone.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="learning-disability-support">
      <list>
        <item>Multi-modal content: text + images + video; audio alternatives to reading; visual diagrams for concepts.</item>
        <item>Scaffolding: break complex tasks into numbered simple steps; provide worked examples and templates.</item>
        <item>Flexible pacing: no time limits on learning; unlimited task repetition; progress saved automatically.</item>
        <item>Hints and tips available on demand without cluttering the main UI.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="implementation-checklist">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Test readability with textstat (Flesch >= 60) and vale (Microsoft Writing Style) in CI; test copy with alex for insensitive or blame language.</statement>
        <rationale>Manual copy review is inconsistent; automated gates catch most instances of jargon, over-complexity, and blaming language before they reach production.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <checklist>
        <check>Content: heading hierarchy; short paragraphs (3-4 sentences max); bullet points for lists; visual breaks; plain language.</check>
        <check>Interaction: predictable navigation; consistent patterns; auto-save; undo/redo; confirmation for destructive actions.</check>
        <check>Visual: adequate spacing; readable fonts (16px minimum); high contrast; color not sole indicator; reduced-motion option; visible focus.</check>
        <check>Timing: no time limits or adjustable; timeout warnings; auto-save prevents data loss; pauseable media.</check>
        <check>Feedback: non-blaming error messages; positive reinforcement; progress indicators; loading states; success confirmations.</check>
      </checklist>
    </section>

    <section name="testing-with-neurodiverse-users">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Include at least one moderated testing session with neurodiverse participants (ADHD, autism, dyslexia, anxiety) per major release; automated tools cannot substitute for real cognitive usability testing.</statement>
        <rationale>Cognitive inclusion cannot be fully verified by code analysis. Flesch scores miss domain jargon. "Sensory-friendly" palette choices vary by individual. Real user testing reveals the actual burden.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Test metrics: task completion rate, error rate, time on task, user confidence, stress (self-reported).</item>
        <item>Recruiting: Fable, UserTesting with neurodiverse screener filters, community organizations.</item>
        <item>Dyslexia font swap (OpenDyslexic) must be opt-in — offer as a user preference, not as the default.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Default to `prefers-reduced-motion: reduce` for any non-essential animation; only animate on explicit user opt-in.</item>
        <item>Auto-save every 15-30 s with explicit "All changes saved" indicator; never rely on browser memory.</item>
        <item>Inline validation > submit-time validation for cognitive load (immediate feedback reduces anxiety).</item>
        <item>Allow "save and continue later" with email magic link on every form > 3 steps.</item>
        <item>Provide a "simple mode" toggle that hides non-essential UI for users who get overwhelmed.</item>
        <item>Pair iconography with text labels — icons alone are ambiguous for autism / aphasia users.</item>
        <item>Use predictable layouts (same nav location, same primary action position) across pages.</item>
        <item>Test copy with `vale` + `alex` in pre-commit; CI gate with `textstat` Flesch ≥ 60.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>The following tools help enforce cognitive inclusion standards programmatically:</p>
      <list>
        <item>`textstat` (Python) — Flesch, Gunning Fog, Dale-Chall readability metrics; `pip install textstat`.</item>
        <item>`vale` (any language) — Linter for plain-language rules; supports Microsoft and write-good styles; https://vale.sh.</item>
        <item>`alex` (JavaScript) — Catches insensitive/blame language; `npm i -g alex`.</item>
        <item>`write-good` (JavaScript) — English prose linter; `npm i -g write-good`.</item>
        <item>`eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y` — Catches some cognitive-related issues (autoplay, focus); `npm i -D eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y`.</item>
        <item>Playwright `page.emulateMedia({reducedMotion:'reduce'})` — Test prefers-reduced-motion behavior.</item>
        <item>Microsoft Immersive Reader (SaaS) — Drop-in read-aloud + dyslexia formatting.</item>
        <item>Fable (SaaS) — Recruits neurodiverse testers; irreplaceable for real usability testing.</item>
        <item>UserTesting + neurodiverse screeners (SaaS) — Filter users by ADHD, dyslexia, autism.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-caveats">
      <p>Cognitive inclusion has real constraints and trade-offs that agents should understand:</p>
      <list>
        <item>WCAG 2.1 covered cognitive only thinly; WCAG 2.2 added some coverage but cognitive remains under-specified.</item>
        <item>"Plain language" is subjective — Flesch/Flesch-Kincaid scores miss domain jargon unique to industries like healthcare or finance.</item>
        <item>Auto-save can leak draft data to other users on shared devices — always scope to authenticated sessions.</item>
        <item>"OpenDyslexic" / "Comic Sans" claims are weakly evidenced; some studies show no benefit, some show preference. Offer choice rather than imposing.</item>
        <item>Sensory-friendly palettes can clash with brand identity; needs design-system buy-in and stakeholder agreement.</item>
        <item>LLMs default to verbose, hedging copy ("might want to consider", "perhaps could") — explicit instruction needed for direct, plain language.</item>
        <item>Agent-rewritten error messages may strip technical detail needed for support — keep error codes for support, soften user-facing message only.</item>
        <item>"Reduced motion" detection in CSS `@media` doesn't catch JS-driven animations (GSAP, Lottie) — agent must check JS too.</item>
        <item>Agents tend to over-add ARIA live regions for "feedback" — too many announcements overwhelm screen-reader users.</item>
        <item>Auto-save naively serialized to localStorage may leak data on shared devices — scope to authenticated session.</item>
        <item>Do not let the agent "translate" copy across locales for cognitive load — Flesch only works for English; per-language metrics needed (LIX for Swedish, Kandel-Moles for Spanish, etc.).</item>
        <item>Empathy-claims drift: an agent may add "We're so sorry!" — over-apologetic copy is itself anxiety-inducing for many users; aim for calm-neutral.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agents are strong at: copy rewrites (plain language, non-blaming tone), error-message audits, form-flow analysis (counting steps, fields, time-on-task estimates), checklist conformance, generating predictable interaction patterns. Agents are weak at: real cognitive testing (need humans with relevant disabilities), judging "sensory-friendly" palettes, validating reduced-motion alternatives feel right. Use agent for first pass, then schedule moderated user testing with neurodiverse panel (Fable, UserTesting + recruit).</p>
      <list>
        <item>Recommended subagents: `faion-sdd-executor-agent` — track each cognitive criterion as a task with completion evidence (screenshot, copy snippet).</item>
        <item>Plain-language rewriter subagent — rewrite UI copy to ≤Grade 8, non-blaming, no idioms, check Flesch ≥ 60.</item>
        <item>Form-flow analyzer subagent — given a form spec, count fields, identify time pressure, suggest chunking + auto-save.</item>
        <item>See also: `accessibility-first-design`, `vui-accessibility-inclusivity`.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/readability-gate.py" purpose="Python CI script failing the build if Flesch reading ease falls below 60 for any UI string."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/cognitive/"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/coga-usable/"/>
      <link href="https://webaim.org/articles/cognitive/"/>
      <link href="https://www.bdadyslexia.org.uk/advice/employers/creating-a-dyslexia-friendly-workplace/dyslexia-friendly-style-guide"/>
      <link href="https://www.gov.uk/guidance/content-design"/>
      <link href="https://www.microsoft.com/design/inclusive/"/>
      <link href="https://www.plainlanguage.gov"/>
      <ref slug="accessibility-first-design"/>
      <ref slug="vui-accessibility-inclusivity"/>
      <ref slug="a11y-testing"/>
      <ref slug="wcag-22-compliance"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
