<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Email Marketing for Solo Operators Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Email Marketing for Solo Operators application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-organic-list-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lists MUST be built from opt-in signups only; purchased or scraped lists are rejected. Complaint rate above 0.1% triggers sanctions.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Cold lists destroy sender reputation across all future sends and are never recoverable cheaply.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-welcome-within-5min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Welcome email MUST fire within 5 minutes of signup, addressed by first name when captured.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Open rate on welcome is 50-86% — highest of any send; delay collapses it.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-segmentation-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every send beyond the welcome MUST be segmented by ≥1 axis (engagement, source, or behaviour). Broadcast-to-all is rejected after 100 subscribers.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Unsegmented blasts depress engagement metrics and accelerate inbox-tab demotion.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-one-cta-per-email" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each email MUST carry exactly one primary CTA. Multi-CTA emails are rejected — they halve click-through rate.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Decision fatigue collapses CTR; one ask outperforms three asks combined.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-deliverability-monitoring" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Bounce rate MUST stay &lt;2% and complaint rate &lt;0.1%. Quarterly list-hygiene sweep removes &gt;180-day inactives.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">ESP reputation collapses fast once thresholds are breached; recovery takes weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
