<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-list-building" title="Email List Building, Welcome Sequence, and Segmentation">
  <summary>Lead magnet types, opt-in form best practices, 5-email welcome sequence structure, and segmentation criteria.</summary>

  <section title="List Building Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never purchase or rent email lists; spam complaints above 0.1% trigger Google/Yahoo bulk sender sanctions that are difficult to reverse.</statement>
      <rationale>Purchased lists have high complaint rates because recipients did not opt in. ISP blacklisting from complaint spikes can render the sending domain unusable for months.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a lead magnet before asking for an email address; organic list growth without a lead magnet is near-zero on most platforms.</statement>
      <rationale>The default "subscribe to my newsletter" CTA converts at 0.1-0.5%; a specific lead magnet converts at 3-10%. The lead magnet is the primary driver of list growth.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Lead Magnet Types">
    <list>
      <item>Checklist: high conversion, easy consumption (e.g., "10-Point SEO Checklist")</item>
      <item>Template: high conversion, immediate value (e.g., "Email Swipe File")</item>
      <item>Guide/eBook: medium conversion, deep knowledge (e.g., "Complete Guide to X")</item>
      <item>Mini-course: medium conversion, nurtures relationship (e.g., "5-Day Email Course")</item>
      <item>Tool/Calculator: high conversion, interactive utility (e.g., "ROI Calculator")</item>
      <item>Webinar: high-intent, live event (converts best when topic is urgent)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Opt-in Form Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a single email field (no name, no phone) for maximum conversion; each additional field reduces opt-ins by 20-30%.</statement>
      <rationale>Friction on the sign-up form is the primary cause of low list growth rates; removing the name field alone typically lifts conversion 15-25%.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Above-the-fold placement converts at 2-3x sidebar placement</item>
      <item>Clear value proposition in the headline: what they get, not "subscribe"</item>
      <item>Privacy assurance below the form ("No spam. Unsubscribe anytime.")</item>
      <item>Exit-intent popup: use sparingly, only with high-value lead magnet</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Welcome Sequence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Automate a 5-email welcome sequence triggered immediately on signup; the first 7 days after opt-in is the highest engagement window.</statement>
      <rationale>New subscribers have peak curiosity on sign-up day. Brands that send nothing for the first week lose 40-60% of potential engagement before the first broadcast.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Day 0: Deliver lead magnet + brief self-introduction</item>
      <item>Day 1: Share your story and philosophy; build connection</item>
      <item>Day 3: Best content piece (top blog post, resource, case study)</item>
      <item>Day 5: Social proof or case study from a customer</item>
      <item>Day 7: Soft pitch — mention the product, no hard sell</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/welcome-sequence.txt">5-email welcome sequence with subject lines and body scaffolding</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Segmentation">
    <list>
      <item>By engagement: Active (opened last 30 days), Engaged (last 90), Inactive (90+ days), VIP (high engagement + purchasers)</item>
      <item>By lead source: different messaging per acquisition channel</item>
      <item>By purchase history: upsell relevant products to buyers</item>
      <item>By interests: targeted content per declared interest</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
