<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Difficult Conversations Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding difficult-conversations. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="fact-vs-story-separated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The script MUST separate observable facts (FACT field) from the author's interpretation (STORY field). Mixing them is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Patterson et al. — Crucial Conversations">Stories drive feelings; conflating them prevents the listener from engaging with reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="safety-signals-monitored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The script MUST include a 'safety check' cue (watch for silence: sarcasm/withdrawal; or violence: cutting off/labelling). When triggered, pause content and restore safety first.</statement>
      <rationale source="Patterson et al. — Crucial Conversations">Content cannot land while the other person is in fight-or-flight; safety restoration must precede content.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="state-60s-opening" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A STATE opening MUST fit in 3-5 sentences (under 60s spoken). Anything longer reads as monologue.</statement>
      <rationale source="Patterson et al. — Crucial Conversations">Long openings destroy the safety being built; brevity invites response.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="desc-for-async-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DESC format MUST be used only in async/written contexts (Slack, email). Reading DESC aloud as a script is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bower &amp; Bower — Asserting Yourself">DESC is calibrated for async delivery; spoken aloud it sounds prepared and clinical.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="wwwf-close" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every conversation MUST close with WHO does WHAT by WHEN + follow-up date. Vague commitment ('we'll do better') is forbidden as the close.</statement>
      <rationale source="Patterson et al. — Crucial Conversations">Without specific accountability both parties leave with different interpretations; follow-up date closes the loop.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
