<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cross-Tool Migration Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Cross-Tool Migration. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="six-phase-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every migration MUST pass through the six phases in order: discover, field-map, dry-run, cutover, verify, decommission. Phase skip is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion tool-migration audit 2025">Skipped phases (esp. dry-run) cause week-of cutover failures that cannot be rolled back.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="field-map-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Field map MUST be an explicit YAML artefact declaring source-field → target-field with type-coercion notes. Implicit defaults are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian Cloud Migration docs">Implicit field mapping produces silent data loss; explicit YAML is reviewable and diff-able.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="identity-merge-via-sso" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>User identity merge MUST go through SSO (Entra/Okta/Google) mapping. Email-only matching is forbidden when SSO is available.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft Learn — Identity migration">Email-only matching breaks on email changes, aliases, and merged accounts; SSO mapping is canonical.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="rollback-gate-pre-cutover" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cutover phase MUST have a documented rollback gate with a hard deadline. If verify fails before the deadline, rollback executes automatically.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI — IT migration governance">Without a pre-committed rollback, teams paper over verify failures and run on a broken system for weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="decommission-only-after-verify" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Source tool MUST NOT be decommissioned until verify phase passes with 100% issue parity and 30-day read-only soak.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — migration playbook">Premature decommissioning destroys the only rollback path; 30-day soak surfaces edge cases the dry-run missed.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Cross-Tool Migration fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Cross-Tool Migration outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
