<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="team-development">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-agile</domain>
    <summary>Framework for building high-performing teams using Tuckman's stages with team charter, skills matrix, and retrospective templates. Adapts PM style per stage using tracked metrics.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>team-development</tag>
      <tag>tuckman</tag>
      <tag>team-performance</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>leadership</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Team Development</title>

    <summary>A framework for building high-performing project teams using Tuckman's stages (Forming → Storming → Norming → Performing → Adjourning) as the diagnostic backbone, paired with three artifact types: team charter, skills matrix, and retrospective template. The PM adapts leadership style per stage and uses tracked metrics (PR attribution, contribution distribution) to move the team through stages deliberately.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Talented individuals do not automatically become a high-performing team. Without structured facilitation through Storming — the most common stuck point — conflict freezes velocity for months. Tuckman's model gives a shared language for diagnosing team health and a stage-specific action menu, reducing guesswork in leadership decisions.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Onboarding a new hire or contractor and wanting to map them onto Tuckman stages.</item>
        <item>Sprint retro reveals interpersonal conflict (Storming) and PM needs structured mediation steps.</item>
        <item>Solo founder hiring first 1–3 people and needing a written charter, skills matrix, and integration plan.</item>
        <item>Tracking a team's progression so leadership knows when to push autonomy vs. provide direction.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>One-off async working groups disbanding in a week — Tuckman overhead exceeds value.</item>
        <item>Pure individual-contributor work with no inter-dependency.</item>
        <item>Highly transactional vendor relationships — Tuckman assumes a sustained team.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="stage-model">
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-run the Tuckman stage assessment after every team-composition change (hire, departure, reorg) — not on a calendar schedule.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams regress to Forming or Storming when key members change; calendar-based assessment misses the regression window where intervention has the highest return.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="forming">
      <p>Polite, cautious, high dependency on the PM for direction. Members focus on defining their role rather than executing work.</p>
      <list>
        <item>PM actions: provide explicit direction, clarify roles and responsibilities, set working agreements in writing</item>
        <item>Evidence signals: members ask permission for small decisions, few spontaneous collaborations, low conflict but also low velocity</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="storming">
      <p>Conflict, competition, and frustration surface. This is the highest-risk stage — teams can stay here for months without structured facilitation.</p>
      <list>
        <item>PM actions: facilitate structured discussion, mediate (meet separately first), focus conversation on shared goals not positions, document agreed decisions</item>
        <item>Evidence signals: heated retros, PR review comments with sharp tone, recurring same argument, velocity drop, attendance issues</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Document Storming-stage decisions in writing immediately; unrecorded verbal resolutions get re-litigated within two sprints.</statement>
        <rationale>Heated decisions feel resolved in the moment but lack shared memory; written record prevents the "we never agreed to that" pattern.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="norming">
      <p>Trust building, cooperation, shared processes forming. Team starts solving problems without PM involvement.</p>
      <list>
        <item>PM actions: delegate, support, encourage cross-team ownership, step back from day-to-day mediation</item>
        <item>Evidence signals: team resolves issues in standup without escalation, PR reviews are constructive, velocity stabilizes</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="performing">
      <p>High productivity, autonomy, self-organizing. PM focuses on removing systemic obstacles, not directing work.</p>
      <list>
        <item>PM actions: empower decisions, remove organizational blockers, protect from external interruptions, provide strategic context</item>
        <item>Evidence signals: team ships without PM in daily loop, retros produce non-trivial improvements, velocity at or above target</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="adjourning">
      <p>Project closure or team restructuring. Focus on knowledge capture and individual transition.</p>
      <list>
        <item>PM actions: celebrate accomplishments, facilitate knowledge transfer, document lessons learned, support individual transitions</item>
        <item>Evidence signals: project marked complete or team restructuring announced</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="trust-building">
      <list>
        <item>Regular 1-on-1s with explicit agenda (block 30 min weekly per direct report)</item>
        <item>Psychological safety — teams must be able to raise concerns without punishment</item>
        <item>Transparent communication — share context behind decisions, not just decisions</item>
        <item>Team-building activities tailored to team size and remote/in-person split</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep the team charter short (one screen) and treat it as a living document; review every 8-10 weeks or after any team-composition change.</statement>
        <rationale>Long charters are not read; short ones are consulted at conflicts. Staleness destroys trust in the document and by extension in the agreements it captures.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="skill-development">
      <list>
        <item>Skills matrix: rate each skill 1 (beginner) to 4 (expert); pair every "1" cell with a named owner and a quarterly improvement target</item>
        <item>Pair programming and cross-training for knowledge transfer across sole-owner skills</item>
        <item>Mentoring programs — internal, with explicit goals and check-in cadence</item>
        <item>Training opportunities — budget per-person per quarter, not per-year</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Skills-matrix scores must be evidence-backed (PRs, incidents, code reviews); self-reported scores without evidence drift toward inflation.</statement>
        <rationale>Inflated matrices mask critical knowledge gaps that surface at the worst moment — when the sole expert is unavailable during an incident.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="process-improvement">
      <list>
        <item>Retrospectives: every sprint; action items must have owner + due date + verification method in next retro</item>
        <item>Process experiments: time-boxed (one sprint), measured, documented as ADR if adopted</item>
        <item>Tool optimization: quarterly review; only add tooling that removes friction, not adds ceremony</item>
        <item>Workload balancing: use contribution data (git shortlog, PR review counts) to surface imbalances</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Retro action items without an owner and verification method are not action items — they are wishes.</statement>
        <rationale>Unowned actions do not get done; unverified actions get closed as done regardless of outcome; both undermine retro trust over time.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using Tuckman stage labels as an excuse for inaction ("we're just Storming, it will pass").</description>
        <reason>Storming does not self-resolve without facilitation; teams that skip active mediation can stay in Storming for months and lose key contributors.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Applying Tuckman to distributed async-only teams without adjustment.</description>
        <reason>The model assumes synchronous dynamics; async teams show attenuated stage signals and require additional indicators (response lag, async thread sentiment).</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping team building because "there's no time."</description>
        <reason>Dysfunction deferred costs more time than investment avoided; unresolved Storming can freeze a team for months.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>One-size-fits-all management style across all team members.</description>
        <reason>Different Tuckman stages and different experience levels require different leadership approaches; uniform style over-manages high performers and under-supports strugglers.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Blaming individuals for systemic failures.</description>
        <reason>Individual blame destroys psychological safety and repeats the failure; root cause is almost always process, tooling, or system design.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="worked-examples">
      <example type="good" title="Navigating Storming Stage">
        <note>Situation: two developers in architectural disagreement that is slowing the team and heating meetings.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Symptoms observed:
- Developer A and Developer B argue about microservice vs. monolith in every planning meeting
- Retrospective atmosphere is tense; others are silent
- Sprint velocity dropped 30% over 3 sprints
- Both devs are updating architecture docs independently

PM actions (in order):
1. Meet individually with A and B — understand each person's technical concern and personal stake
2. Facilitate a structured session with explicit ground rules: one speaker, no interruptions, timer
3. Frame the discussion as "what does the system need?" not "who is right?"
4. Document the agreed-upon architectural decision as an ADR within 24 hours
5. Share ADR with full team; name the decision-maker if no consensus

Week 3 follow-up:
- Both devs cite ADR in code reviews instead of re-litigating
- Retro tone returns to constructive
- Velocity recovers to baseline
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Solo-to-Team Transition">
        <note>Situation: solo founder hiring first team member; no existing process documentation.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Before hire arrives:
- Write down every implicit process (deployment, code review, naming conventions)
- Create a "how we work" document (2 pages max)
- Set up repo access, Slack, 1password, and dev environment guide

Week 1: Orientation
- Walk through codebase together; explain architectural decisions
- Shadow founder for 2 days: observe how decisions get made
- Define initial responsibilities in writing

Weeks 2-4: Gradual Ownership
- Pair on first 3 features; founder drives, new hire navigates
- Swap: new hire drives, founder reviews + explains
- Give feedback within 24 hours of PR submission
- Weekly 1-on-1: what's unclear? what would help?

Month 2: Independence
- Assign a feature with clear acceptance criteria; no pairing
- Check in at midpoint, not daily
- Ask new hire to document one process they think is unclear
- Celebrate first solo ship in team channel

Key: document everything before hire arrives; verbal-only onboarding creates dependency on the founder and slows the transition to independence.
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Skills Matrix Update from Git Data">
        <note>Use git history to provide evidence-backed initial scores for a skills matrix.</note>
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Infer expertise per directory from git contribution history (last 180 days)
since="180 days ago"
for dir in $(git ls-tree -d --name-only HEAD); do
  echo "## $dir"
  git log --since="$since" --pretty=format:'%an' -- "$dir" \
    | sort | uniq -c | sort -rn | head -5
  echo
done
]]></code>
        <note>Use output as starting evidence; do not auto-populate scores without human review.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Use Claude subagents to keep the artifacts (charter, skills matrix, retro doc) under version control and refreshed each sprint. The PM agent generates draft deltas; the human PM/EM owns merging. Treat each Tuckman transition as a trigger event that re-runs the matrix and charter check.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-pm-agent — drafts charter, retro template, action items from sprint logs</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — turns retro action items into SDD tasks under .aidocs/</item>
        <item>General-purpose Claude subagent — synthesises 1-on-1 notes into a Tuckman-stage diagnosis</item>
      </list>

      <p>Prompt pattern examples:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are reading 6 weeks of standup notes + 2 retros for team X.
Classify the team's current Tuckman stage with 3 specific quotes
as evidence. Output 5 PM actions targeted to that stage only.
]]></code>

      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Update the skills matrix in <path>. New input: <PR review patterns,
who reviewed what, who got stuck>. Bump scores only with at least
one cited PR or incident. Flag gaps where one person is sole owner.
]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs over-pattern-match Tuckman labels without evidence.</description>
        <reason>Require evidence quotes in the diagnosis prompt to avoid false classifications.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Letting an agent auto-publish a retro without human review.</description>
        <reason>Humans must redact attribution and tone before sharing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents writing 1-on-1 notes verbatim into shared docs.</description>
        <reason>Privacy boundary violation; separate personal feedback from team-level insights.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents generating a generic charter instead of citing team incidents.</description>
        <reason>Force them to cite the team's actual incidents and patterns to ground the charter in reality.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Skills-matrix scoring by an agent without evidence backing.</description>
        <reason>Must be tied to PRs, incidents, or code reviews; hallucinated scores hide critical gaps.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>Tools and services for team-development workflows:</p>
      <list>
        <item>gh — Pull PR review counts to inform skills matrix (brew install gh)</item>
        <item>git shortlog -sne --since='90 days' — Contribution distribution per teammate (git built-in)</item>
        <item>tokei / scc — Code ownership by directory, proxy for expertise (cargo install tokei)</item>
        <item>git-fame — Per-author line/commit attribution (gem install git_fame)</item>
      </list>
      <p>Services &amp; apps:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Linear — SaaS, agent-friendly REST/GraphQL, cycle reviews map to Tuckman cadence</item>
        <item>Jira — SaaS, agent-friendly REST API, sprint retros + team velocity in one place</item>
        <item>Pulse / Officevibe — SaaS, limited agent support, pulse surveys feed psychological-safety metric</item>
        <item>15Five — SaaS, limited agent support, 1-on-1 notes input for stage diagnosis</item>
        <item>Glean / GitDuck — SaaS, limited agent support, pair-programming evidence for skills matrix</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Run a Tuckman self-assessment with the team after every team-composition change (hire, departure, reorg) — not on a calendar.</item>
        <item>Keep the charter short (one screen). Living document. Review every 8–10 weeks.</item>
        <item>Skills matrix: pair every "1" cell with a named owner who will move it to "2" within a quarter.</item>
        <item>Retro action items must have an owner + due date + a way to verify in next retro. No anonymous TODOs.</item>
        <item>Document Storming-stage decisions in writing — heated discussions get re-litigated unless captured.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/team-charter.md" purpose="Team charter: mission, members, working agreements, meeting cadence, success metrics"/>
      <template path="templates/skills-matrix.md" purpose="Skills matrix template with 1–4 scale and gap-action column"/>
      <template path="templates/retro.md" purpose="Retrospective template: went well / didn't go well / ideas / action items with owner+due"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://rework.withgoogle.com/"/>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuckman%27s_stages_of_group_development"/>
      <ref slug="pm-framework-focus-areas"/>
      <ref slug="reporting-basics"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
