<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="OKR Cascade Multi-Squad Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every multi-squad OKR cascade must enforce. These are HARD rules: founders or squad leads cannot override without explicit retro entry.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-max-three-objectives" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Max 3 Objectives at the company level. Max 3 Objectives per squad. Max 5 Key Results per Objective. If you have more, you have not prioritized.</statement>
      <rationale source="Wodtke, Radical Focus (2nd ed. 2021), ch. 4">Three is the upper bound for human working memory across a quarter. Wodtke's case studies show teams with 4+ Os score 0.4 avg vs 0.7 for teams with 1-2 Os. The cascade collapses if company has 7 Os because squads inherit fan-out exceeding their capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-single-threaded-ownership" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every company-level KR maps to exactly ONE accountable squad. Other squads can be contributors, but only one squad's name appears as Owner. Use RACI Owner column — no shared O.</statement>
      <rationale source="Doerr, Measure What Matters (2018), ch. 8; Amazon STO ('single-threaded owner') model">Shared ownership produces the diffusion of responsibility documented by Latane &amp; Darley. If two squads own "lift activation rate to 35%", neither owns it, both blame the other at quarter-end. Single-threaded ownership forces the trade-off conversation up-front.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-dependency-edges-declared" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every squad OKR document must declare an "Inbound" and "Outbound" dependency list. Inbound = "we need X from squad Y by week N." Outbound = "squad Z needs X from us by week N." Edges that exist in one direction but not the other are bugs — fail the cascade review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Conway's Law applied to OKRs (Sosa, Eppinger, Rowles, 2004 - design structure matrix)">Hidden dependencies surface at week 8 as missed quarters. Declaring them in week 1 (a) forces the conversation in cascade week, (b) lets PMs sequence work, (c) makes the dependency graph a living artifact, not a quarter-end excuse.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-confidence-vote-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Friday each squad records a confidence-vote per KR on a 0.0-1.0 scale ("how confident are we we'll hit ≥0.7 by quarter-end?"). Drop &gt; 0.2 in a week triggers an escalation conversation Monday — no exception.</statement>
      <rationale source="Wodtke, Radical Focus, ch. 7 (Confidence Tracker)">Wodtke's confidence-tracker pattern is the canonical leading indicator. Teams that vote weekly catch 80% of misses by week 6; teams that only check at quarter-end catch zero. The 0.2-drop trigger is calibrated from Wodtke case studies.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-retro-before-next-cascade" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Next quarter's company OKR set may not be drafted until previous quarter's per-KR scores (0.0-1.0) are recorded AND a written retro names ≥3 process changes for next cascade. Quarter-end scoring without retro = blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="Doerr WMM ch. 11; LinkedIn quarterly OKR retro practice">Without forced retro, the same drift repeats. The 3-change minimum prevents "looks fine to me" rubber-stamping. Score recording forces the team to confront 0.3 KRs honestly instead of redefining success at quarter-end.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Company KR → single-squad ownership">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Company O1: Become the default tool for solo founders post-launch.
  KR1.1: Activation rate (signup → first published artifact) 18% → 35%
    Owner: Squad-Onboarding   (single owner)
    Contributors: Squad-Pricing, Squad-Platform
  KR1.2: Net new MRR from organic +$12k → +$28k
    Owner: Squad-Growth
    Contributors: Squad-Content

Squad-Onboarding then cascades KR1.1 into:
  - "Reduce signup→first-publish median time 14d → 3d" (measurable)
  - "Cut signup form fields from 9 to 3" (directional, lever)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2: KR1.1 has one Owner; r3 emerges naturally: Squad-Pricing knows it owes onboarding pricing-page changes by week 4.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Shared ownership, no dependency declaration">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
KR1.1: Activation rate 18% → 35%
  Owners: Squad-Onboarding AND Squad-Platform AND Squad-Growth

Problem: violates r2 (three Owners = no Owner) and r3 (no Inbound/Outbound
list anywhere). At week 8 Squad-Onboarding blames Squad-Platform for not
shipping the new event-tracking pipeline; Platform points at Growth.
Quarter-end score: 0.3, all three teams' fault.
Repair: assign one Owner. Other two appear in Inbound list with a date.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2 + r3 violation pattern that recurs every quarter without enforcement.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
