<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-board-setup" title="Trello Board Setup Rules">
  <summary>Rules for Trello board structure, WIP limits, label system, and card anatomy.</summary>

  <section title="Board Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use 5–7 lists maximum. Encode WIP limits directly in list names: "In Progress (WIP: 3)". WIP is enforced by Butler rule or human review — Trello does not block card moves automatically.</statement>
      <rationale>More than 7 lists create cognitive overhead. Named WIP limits make violations visible without requiring a Power-Up.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Board lists in order: Backlog → Ready for Dev → In Development (WIP: 3) → Code Review (WIP: 2) → QA Testing (WIP: 2) → Done. Archive done cards at sprint end — do not delete them (preserves velocity history).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Label System">
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit labels to 8–12 maximum. Assign labels by type (Feature, Bug, Tech Debt, Docs), priority (P0-Critical, P1-High, P2-Medium, P3-Low), and status modifiers (Blocked, Quick Win). Apply one type label per card — not Feature AND Bug simultaneously.</statement>
      <rationale>Label bloat makes filtering unreliable. Agents producing cards without a fixed label set create arbitrary new labels that break board filters.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Card Anatomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every card must have: a clear action-oriented title, a description using the card template (user story, AC, technical notes, DoD checklist), at least one type label, a due date if committed for the current sprint, and an assignee.</statement>
      <rationale>Unstructured card descriptions cannot be reliably parsed by agents. Templates at card creation enforce consistent structure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Custom Fields Power-Up for story points (number), sprint (dropdown), and component (dropdown). These fields are readable/writable via the Trello REST API custom fields endpoint — use them instead of embedding data in card titles.</statement>
      <rationale>Data in card titles cannot be queried or aggregated via the API. Custom fields are structured and filterable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Sprint Operations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Archive the Done list at sprint end — do not delete cards. Create a new Done list for the next sprint. This preserves card history for velocity calculations via the API.</statement>
      <rationale>Deleted cards cannot be retrieved for historical metrics. Archived cards are queryable via the Trello API archive endpoint.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/card-feature.md">Feature card template with user story, AC, technical notes, DoD</reference>
  <reference path="templates/card-bug.md">Bug card template with steps to reproduce, severity, environment</reference>
</text>
