<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Trello Kanban Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every Trello kanban board must enforce. These are HARD rules — convenience does not override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-lists-7-max-wip-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Board has 5-7 lists. WIP limit encoded in list name ("In Progress (WIP: 3)"). Trello does not block moves — Butler rule or human review enforces the limit.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience + kanban literature">More than 7 lists creates cognitive overhead; named WIP makes violations visible without a paid Power-Up.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-labels-12-max-closed-list" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>≤12 labels in a fixed taxonomy: type (Feature, Bug, Tech Debt, Docs), priority (P0-P3), status modifier (Blocked, Quick Win). One type label per card; new labels go through a PR-like change request.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Label bloat breaks filters; agents inventing labels destroy board hygiene fast.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-custom-fields-not-titles" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Story points, sprint, component live in custom fields (queryable via API). Encoding "[5pt] Add OAuth" in the title is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Trello API docs">Custom fields are queryable + filterable; title strings are not. Agents that parse titles for data are fragile.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-archive-do-not-delete" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Done cards are archived (closed=true) at sprint end, never deleted. Archived cards remain accessible via the API for velocity reconstruction.</statement>
      <rationale source="Trello API docs">Deleted cards cannot be retrieved; archived ones are first-class for historical reporting.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-cached-ids-no-name-lookup-per-write" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agents cache board / list / label IDs once per session in memory or in constitution.md. Writes use IDs, never name-to-ID lookups on every call.</statement>
      <rationale source="Trello API docs">Name lookups waste rate-limit budget; cached IDs cut request count and survive name changes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-rate-limit-100-per-10s" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>API writes capped at 100 requests / 10s / token. Bulk operations batch sequentially with backoff; parallel agents must coordinate. 429 responses MUST be handled explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Trello API docs">Unhandled 429 = silent data loss; the documented limit is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies-If hold and no Skip-If trigger applies, walk the procedure end-to-end and run the validator before declaring done.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory run leaf">Decision-tree leaves must reference a rule id. The run leaf maps "preconditions met" to the canonical execution path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the Applies-If preconditions are not met OR any Skip-If disqualifier holds.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory skip leaf">Decision-tree leaves must reference a rule id. The skip leaf needs a real rule so non-applicable inputs route cleanly out instead of producing false-positive verdicts.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
