<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-folder-shape" title="project-spec/ folder shape">
  <summary>The required directory tree for project-spec/. Each subfolder is a routing node with its own AGENTS.md and CLAUDE.md, never a bulk dump.</summary>

  <section title="Top-level shape">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>project-spec/ MUST be a directory containing both flat reference files and routing subdirectories — never a single .md file.</statement>
      <rationale>One file collapses under its own weight past ~500 lines; agents load the whole thing per query. Subfolders let routing be selective.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>project-spec/AGENTS.md — entry routing doc; lists each subdir + flat file with one-line purpose.</item>
      <item>project-spec/CLAUDE.md — single line: `@AGENTS.md`.</item>
      <item>project-spec/mission.md — what this project IS, who it is for, what success looks like.</item>
      <item>project-spec/glossary.md — domain vocabulary. Every term that appears in code or UI lives here.</item>
      <item>project-spec/business-rules.md — invariants the system enforces. Each rule has an id and lists the code path that enforces it.</item>
      <item>project-spec/data-model.md — canonical entity list + relationships. Source of truth above the ORM.</item>
      <item>project-spec/auth.md — actors, roles, permissions, session model.</item>
      <item>project-spec/deploy.md — hosts, services, deploy scripts. Where each surface runs.</item>
      <item>project-spec/config-secrets.md — env-var inventory. Each var has source (1Password / env / file) and consumer.</item>
      <item>project-spec/non-functional.md — performance, availability, security, accessibility targets.</item>
      <item>project-spec/observability.md — logs, metrics, traces. What is emitted, where it lands, alert thresholds.</item>
      <item>project-spec/invariants.md — system-wide invariants beyond business-rules (e.g. "every API response is JSON; no HTML errors").</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Required subdirectories">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Each subdirectory MUST contain its own AGENTS.md + CLAUDE.md routing pair before any content file is added.</statement>
      <rationale>Per-module coverage rule (workspace convention). Skipping the routing doc forces bulk-load and erases the selective-read benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>project-spec/domain/ — per-aggregate or per-bounded-context detail. Each subdir under domain/ is one aggregate.</item>
      <item>project-spec/api/ — public contracts (REST endpoints, GraphQL schema, CLI commands). Per-surface subdirs.</item>
      <item>project-spec/integrations/ — third-party systems we depend on. One file per integration: contract, failure mode, retry policy.</item>
      <item>project-spec/decisions/ — ADR-style records. One file per decision, append-only.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>A single 1500-line project-spec.md at the project root.</description>
    <reason>Agents pull the whole file for any query; humans cannot diff per-section changes; merge conflicts cascade.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Subdirectory without AGENTS.md / CLAUDE.md.</description>
    <reason>Forces an agent reading project-spec/ to ls every subdir blind; defeats the routing convention.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-rebuild-test.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-location-decision.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
