<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-metric-catalog" title="PLG Core Metric Catalog">
  <summary>Core PLG metrics with formulas, benchmarks, ownership rules, and the anti-pattern of NRR-only tracking.</summary>

  <section title="Ownership Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign one owner per metric. Define the activation event as ONE event, in ONE table, fired in ONE place.</statement>
      <rationale>Without an owner, metric definitions drift and the dashboard becomes folklore. Cross-source UNION aggregations for activation always break when schemas evolve. A single-source activation event is the prerequisite for reliable funnel analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the metric catalog version-controlled (dbt + Git). Pair every dashboard tile with a runbook line: "if this metric moves, who acts and how."</statement>
      <rationale>Dashboards that change metric definitions silently are net-negative — they create false confidence. Without a runbook, teams review the metric but take no action, which is the same as not measuring it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Core Metrics with Benchmarks">
    <list>
      <item>Sign-up to Activation: activated / signups — benchmark 40-60%.</item>
      <item>Free to Paid Conversion: paid / free users — benchmark 2-5% (freemium), 10-25% (trial).</item>
      <item>Time to Value (TTV): median time from signup to aha moment — target under 5 minutes.</item>
      <item>Natural Rate of Growth: (organic + viral) / total signups — target above 50%.</item>
      <item>PQL to Customer: customers / PQLs — benchmark 15-30%.</item>
      <item>Expansion MRR: expansion MRR / total MRR — target above 30%.</item>
      <item>Net Revenue Retention: (MRR + expansion - churn) / MRR — target above 120%.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="NRR vs Gross Dollar Retention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always track both NRR and gross dollar retention (GDR). Never report NRR alone.</statement>
      <rationale>NRR above 100% can conceal logo churn: expansion revenue from remaining accounts masks a shrinking customer base. GDR reveals the erosion that NRR hides.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="TTV Segmentation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track TTV segmented by cohort, acquisition source, user segment (SMB vs Enterprise), and onboarding path — never as a single global median.</statement>
      <rationale>Global TTV median hides large variance between segments. An Enterprise-heavy cohort with 30-minute TTV and an SMB cohort with 2-minute TTV produce a misleading median that drives wrong optimization decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/dashboard.md">Monthly PLG dashboard template</reference>
</text>
