<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-pql-scoring" title="PQL Scoring and Cohort Analysis">
  <summary>PQL signal weights, scoring thresholds, cohort discipline rules, and agent failure modes for PLG analytics.</summary>

  <section title="PQL Scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Calibrate PQL score thresholds against actual close rates monthly. Adjust before sales workload drifts.</statement>
      <rationale>PQL scores drift as the product evolves. Weights that predicted conversion 2 quarters ago may now route the wrong users to sales, wasting sales capacity on low-intent users and missing high-intent users who changed behavior.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>High-weight signals (3 pts each): 100+ actions/week; invited 5+ members; attempted gated feature.</item>
      <item>Medium-weight signals (2 pts each): 10+ hours/month; 3+ integrations connected; exported or shared data.</item>
      <item>Score thresholds: below 6 = nurture; 6-8 = automated upgrade prompt; 9+ = sales outreach.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>When an agent proposes PQL weights, require it to report sample size and confidence band. Reject proposals based on samples under 200 converters + 200 churned trials.</statement>
      <rationale>PQL weight proposals based on small samples overfit. An agent reporting weights without sample size and confidence is producing a plausible-but-unvalidated scoring model that will misroute sales motion.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cohort Discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cohort every metric. Minimum: M0, M1, M3, M6 retention columns per signup month.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-number metrics hide the truth. Cohort tables reveal whether recent cohorts are better or worse than historical ones, which is the leading indicator of product-market fit changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Cohort tables displayed in dashboards with no action attached per cohort.</description>
      <reason>Retention diagnosis without root-cause analysis and an assigned experiment is theater. Each underperforming cohort needs a hypothesis and a next sprint action, not just a colored cell.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent proposes SQL aggregations on event tables without including a test query against a known sample.</description>
      <reason>LLMs produce plausible-but-wrong SQL: UNION over UNION ALL, missed deduplication on user_id, off-by-one in window functions. Always require the agent to output both the SQL and a validation query.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent summarizes cohort retention as "retention improved" when M3 dropped 2 percentage points.</description>
      <reason>LLMs rephrase directional changes to sound positive. Demand verbatim numbers in cohort summaries; no rounding, no rephrasing of direction.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Sending per-user event data (including emails, IPs, names) to an external LLM for analysis.</description>
      <reason>Per-user event data must be aggregated before sending to any external model. Sanitize PII before any LLM call that processes analytics data.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent conflates "activation" with "onboarding completion" in cohort summaries.</description>
      <reason>Activation (reaching the aha moment) and onboarding completion (finishing the setup wizard) are different events with different causal relationships to retention. Confusion between them invalidates the analysis. Inject the glossary into every analytics prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/pql-score.py">PQL scoring function with signal weights and band classification</reference>
</text>
