<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="plg-metrics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for plg-metrics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Cohort tables displayed in dashboards with no action attached per cohort.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Retention diagnosis without root-cause analysis and an assigned experiment is theater. Each underperforming cohort needs a hypothesis and a next sprint action, not just a colored cell.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent proposes SQL aggregations on event tables without including a test query against a known sample.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs produce plausible-but-wrong SQL: UNION over UNION ALL, missed deduplication on user_id, off-by-one in window functions. Always require the agent to output both the SQL and a validation query.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent summarizes cohort retention as "retention improved" when M3 dropped 2 percentage points.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs rephrase directional changes to sound positive. Demand verbatim numbers in cohort summaries; no rounding, no rephrasing of direction.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Sending per-user event data (including emails, IPs, names) to an external LLM for analysis.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Per-user event data must be aggregated before sending to any external model. Sanitize PII before any LLM call that processes analytics data.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent conflates "activation" with "onboarding completion" in cohort summaries.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Activation (reaching the aha moment) and onboarding completion (finishing the setup wizard) are different events with different causal relationships to retention. Confusion between them invalidates the analysis. Inject the glossary into every analytics prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs propose plausible-but-wrong SQL aggregations on event tables (UNION over UNION ALL, missed deduplication).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always require the agent to output the SQL and a test query against a known sample.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>PQL weight proposals based on small samples overfit.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force the agent to report sample size and confidence band. Reject proposals with sample under 200 converters + 200 churned trials.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Cohort summaries paraphrased by the agent often invert direction ("retention improved" when M3 dropped 2pp).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Demand verbatim numbers, no rounding, no directional paraphrase.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Anomaly detection without a baseline is hallucination.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Provide last 8 weeks of values as context for any "anomaly" claim.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy: per-user event data sent to an external LLM without aggregation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Per-user event data must be aggregated before sending to any external model. Sanitize emails, names, IPs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents conflate "activation" with "onboarding completion".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a glossary into the prompt and reject if the agent uses the terms interchangeably.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Quarterly strategy outputs (freemium vs trial) shipped directly from agent recommendation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>These are decision-grade outputs. Never ship the agent's recommendation without a human PM/CFO review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
