<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-seo-fundamentals">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>seo-manager</domain>
    <summary>Three-pillar SEO framework: Technical (crawlability), On-Page (content intent), Off-Page (backlinks). Covers audits, content optimization, link building, and growth metrics.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>seo</tag>
      <tag>organic-search</tag>
      <tag>technical-seo</tag>
      <tag>on-page-seo</tag>
      <tag>link-building</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>SEO Fundamentals</title>
    <summary>The three-pillar SEO framework — Technical (crawlability), On-Page (content and intent match), Off-Page (backlinks and trust) — covering audit checklists, content optimization by search intent, link building strategy overview, keyword research approach, and key metrics for organic growth.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>53% of all website traffic comes from organic search. Without SEO, content is invisible regardless of quality. Most SEO failures trace to one missing pillar: a technically broken site that can't be indexed, content that mismatches search intent, or zero external authority signals. Understanding all three pillars prevents wasted effort on the wrong layer.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Starting SEO from scratch on a new project</item>
        <item>Diagnosing why a site gets no organic traffic despite publishing content</item>
        <item>Setting up a monthly SEO reporting framework</item>
        <item>Creating an SEO content brief for a target keyword</item>
        <item>Identifying which pillar (technical/on-page/off-page) is the current bottleneck</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When you need deep technical SEO implementation detail — use seo-basics</item>
        <item>When you need advanced link building tactics — use growth-seo-link-building</item>
        <item>For AI search optimization (AEO) — use technical-seo-for-ai or zero-click-search-adaptation</item>
        <item>When PPC is the channel, not organic — use ppc-manager</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="technical-seo">
      <rule>
        <statement>Fix technical SEO blockers before investing in content or link building — a site that cannot be crawled and indexed ranks for nothing regardless of content quality.</statement>
        <rationale>Technical issues (blocked robots.txt, noindex tags, crawl errors) create a ceiling that content and backlinks cannot overcome. The order of operations matters: Technical first, On-Page second, Off-Page third.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Audit crawlability: robots.txt allows important pages (test in Search Console); indexability: key pages appear in site:domain.com search; performance: Core Web Vitals pass (LCP, INP, CLS); mobile: passes Google Mobile-Friendly Test; HTTPS: SSL certificate installed, no mixed content; structure: XML sitemap exists and submitted to Search Console; canonicalization: no duplicate content, correct canonical tags.</statement>
        <rationale>Each of these technical factors is a potential ceiling on ranking performance. A single critical issue (e.g., robots.txt blocking all pages) prevents indexing entirely.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>robots.txt with "Disallow: /" blocking all crawling</description>
        <reason>This is the single most common technical SEO disaster — frequently introduced during development and left deployed. Results in zero indexed pages. Always verify robots.txt before and after any site launch.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="on-page-seo">
      <rule>
        <statement>Match search intent before optimizing for keywords — content that mismatches what the searcher wants will not rank regardless of keyword density.</statement>
        <rationale>Google's ranking objective is user satisfaction, not keyword matching. Informational intent queries need guides/explainers; commercial intent needs comparisons/reviews; transactional intent needs product pages. Intent mismatch causes high bounce rates that signal low quality.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Optimize on-page elements: Title tag: primary keyword + benefit, under 60 characters; Meta description: compelling summary, 120-160 characters; URL: short, keyword-rich, hyphen-separated; H1: single H1 containing primary keyword; Content: covers topic completely, beats competitors in depth; Internal links: link to related pages with descriptive anchor text; External links: cite authoritative sources (signals trustworthiness); Schema markup: Article, Organization, FAQ as appropriate.</statement>
        <rationale>These elements collectively signal to Google what the page is about and demonstrate authority and relevance to the user.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="off-page-seo">
      <rule>
        <statement>Prioritize link quality over quantity: one link from a DR 60 relevant site outweighs 50 links from DR 20 irrelevant directories.</statement>
        <rationale>Google's link quality assessment considers domain authority, relevance, anchor text naturalness, and link placement. High-volume low-quality link building can trigger algorithmic or manual penalties.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Build links through: Guest posting on relevant, high-authority publications; Resource link building: resource pages in your niche; HARO / journalist queries: inbound high-authority links; Digital PR and original research: links from media coverage. Avoid: buying links, link farms, excessive reciprocal linking.</statement>
        <rationale>Quality link sources build domain authority and topical relevance. Low-quality tactics risk algorithmic penalties and waste time.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="search-intent-and-content">
      <rule>
        <statement>Identify search intent before writing content — create the format that matches what the searcher expects to find.</statement>
        <rationale>A page targeting "best project management tools" that is structured as a how-to guide (not a comparison) will rank poorly even with perfect keyword optimization, because the format mismatches the informational + commercial intent behind the query.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Classify intent: Informational: how-to guides, explainers, definitions ("what is RAG"); Commercial investigation: comparisons, reviews, "best X" lists; Transactional: product pages, pricing pages, sign-up flows; Navigational: brand-specific searches — optimize for brand terms.</statement>
        <rationale>Each intent type requires a different content format and positioning. Format mismatch is a primary cause of low rankings despite good keyword optimization.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Cover the topic completely — include all subtopics and related questions that top-ranking competitors cover, plus at least one angle they do not.</statement>
        <rationale>Google's ranking assesses comprehensiveness relative to competing pages. A page missing sections that all competitors include will be ranked lower as less authoritative on the topic.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Analyze top 3 SERP results: word count, sections covered, questions answered. Extract "People Also Ask" questions and answer them in the article. Cover edge cases and advanced scenarios that thin content ignores. Add unique value: original research, first-hand experience, contrarian angle.</statement>
        <rationale>Competitive analysis and comprehensiveness are direct ranking factors. Unique value differentiates your page and builds links/shares.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Update outdated content with new information and change the "last updated" date — do not publish duplicate new articles when a refresh would serve the same purpose.</statement>
        <rationale>Google rewards freshness for queries where recency matters. A refreshed authoritative article with existing backlinks outperforms a new article with no backlinks targeting the same keyword.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Keyword stuffing — repeating the target keyword unnaturally throughout the content</description>
        <reason>Google penalizes keyword stuffing as a spam signal. Semantic search understands topical relevance without keyword repetition; natural language performs better.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Targeting high-volume keywords without assessing difficulty</description>
        <reason>New or low-authority sites cannot rank for competitive head terms. Starting with long-tail keywords (lower volume, lower difficulty) builds authority that eventually enables ranking for head terms.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Expecting SEO results within weeks</description>
        <reason>New content takes 3-6 months to rank; authority building takes 12+ months. Abandoning SEO due to no visible results at 30 days is the most common reason SEO investments fail.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="key-metrics">
      <rule>
        <statement>Track these metrics monthly: Organic traffic: growing month-over-month; Keywords in top 10: increasing count; Domain authority: growing over 6-12 month horizon; Core Web Vitals: all green in Search Console; Click-through rate: above 3% for organic listings.</statement>
        <rationale>These metrics indicate whether SEO efforts are working across all three pillars. Stagnation in any metric signals a bottleneck to investigate.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/seo-content-brief.md" purpose="SEO content brief: keyword data, SERP analysis, content requirements, on-page elements"/>
      <template path="templates/monthly-seo-report.md" purpose="Monthly SEO report template with traffic, keyword movement, backlinks, actions"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
