<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-service-selection" title="Azure Compute: Service Selection Rules">
  <summary>Decision rules for VM vs VMSS vs AKS vs Container Apps vs App Service with trade-off rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Service Decision Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose VMs only for legacy applications requiring specific OS versions, custom kernel modules, or licensing tied to VM instances.</statement>
      <rationale>VMs provide full OS control but require the most operational overhead (patching, scaling, HA configuration). Every other scenario maps to a higher abstraction tier with less burden.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use VMSS Flexible orchestration (not Uniform) for all new scale-out workloads; Uniform mode is being deprecated.</statement>
      <rationale>Flexible orchestration supports standard VM APIs, mixed instance types, and max zone-spreading. Uniform mode uses a separate scale set VM API surface that Microsoft is retiring.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose AKS for containerized workloads that require Kubernetes features: custom operators, advanced scheduling, multi-tenancy, or complex networking.</statement>
      <rationale>AKS gives full Kubernetes API access with a free managed control plane (99.95% SLA). Teams without K8s expertise should evaluate Container Apps first — AKS operational overhead is significant.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Container Apps for event-driven microservices that benefit from scale-to-zero; use AKS when you need control plane access, custom operators, or ARM64 nodes.</statement>
      <rationale>Container Apps is built on Kubernetes (Dapr + KEDA + Envoy) but hides all K8s complexity. It does not support Windows containers or ARM64 as of 2026. AKS supports both.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use App Service for web applications and APIs with predictable traffic where slot-based blue-green deployments are sufficient; prefer Container Apps for event-driven or variable-load services.</statement>
      <rationale>App Service deployment slots enable zero-downtime swaps with auto-swap for CD pipelines. Container Apps is better for bursty workloads because it can scale to zero, eliminating idle compute cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="VM Series Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select B-series VMs for workloads with variable CPU usage (CI agents, dev environments, low-traffic web servers); use D-series for balanced production workloads.</statement>
      <rationale>B-series accumulates CPU credits during idle periods and uses them during bursts — ideal when average utilization is below 20%. D-series provides consistent CPU without burst limits, suitable for production APIs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable Availability Zones for all production VMs and VMSS (99.99% SLA); Availability Sets provide only 99.95% SLA and do not protect against zone failures.</statement>
      <rationale>Availability Zones place VMs in physically separate datacenters within a region. A zone failure (rare but documented) takes down all VMs in that zone. Zone-redundant deployments survive such events.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="App Service Tier Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Standard tier or higher for production App Service plans; Free and Basic tiers lack autoscale, custom domains with TLS, and deployment slots.</statement>
      <rationale>Standard is the minimum viable tier for production: it includes 5 deployment slots, VNet integration, autoscale, and custom domain TLS. Premium adds more scale-out capacity and improved performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <note>Decision matrix mapping workload characteristics to Azure compute service.</note>
    <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Workload characteristics → Recommended service:

Legacy app, custom OS, specific kernel    → VM (D-series, Availability Zones)
Stateless web tier, predictable scale     → VMSS Flexible + App Gateway
Containerized, K8s features needed       → AKS
Event-driven, scale-to-zero, Linux only  → Container Apps (Consumption plan)
Web API, simple CD, slot swaps           → App Service (Standard+)
ML/GPU batch inference                   → AKS + GPU node pool (N-series)
Interruptible batch workloads            → VMSS Spot or AKS Spot node pool
]]></code>
  </example>
</text>
