<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-container-apps" title="Azure Compute: Container Apps Rules">
  <summary>Scale-to-zero rules, KEDA scalers, Dapr integration, revision traffic splitting patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Scaling Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set `min_replicas: 0` for batch and background workloads to enable scale-to-zero; set `min_replicas: 1` or higher for latency-sensitive APIs to avoid cold-start latency on first request.</statement>
      <rationale>Scale-to-zero eliminates idle compute cost. However, a cold start from zero replicas adds 1–5 seconds latency depending on image size. APIs with SLA requirements on first-request latency must maintain at least one warm replica.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure KEDA scale rules for event-driven sources (Azure Service Bus, Storage Queue, Event Hub) to scale containers based on queue depth rather than CPU/memory metrics.</statement>
      <rationale>CPU/memory-based scaling reacts to load after it has already arrived. Queue-depth scaling is proactive: containers are provisioned as messages accumulate, before processing falls behind.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Revisions and Traffic Splitting">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use `revision_mode: Multiple` with named revision labels to implement blue-green or canary deployments via traffic weight splitting — never delete the old revision before verifying the new one is healthy.</statement>
      <rationale>Traffic splitting in Multiple mode allows incremental rollout (e.g., 10% → 50% → 100%) and instant rollback by shifting 100% traffic back to the previous revision. Single revision mode requires a full cutover with no gradual validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Dapr Integration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable Dapr sidecar for service-to-service communication and state management in microservices — use Dapr component scopes to limit which containers can access each component.</statement>
      <rationale>Dapr component scopes enforce least-privilege: a payment service can access the payments state store but not the orders state store, even though both run in the same environment. Without scopes, any app can read/write any Dapr component.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <list>
      <item>No Windows container support — use AKS or App Service for Windows workloads.</item>
      <item>No ARM64 support as of 2026 — use AKS with ARM64 node pools if needed.</item>
      <item>Consumption plan has a 4 vCPU / 8 GiB per replica limit — use Dedicated plan for memory-heavy containers.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <note>Container App with HTTP scaling, Dapr enabled, and Key Vault secret reference.</note>
    <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# Bicep-equivalent ARM properties for reference
properties:
  template:
    containers:
      - name: api
        image: myregistry.azurecr.io/api:v2
        resources:
          cpu: 0.5
          memory: 1Gi
        env:
          - name: DB_PASSWORD
            secretRef: db-password
    scale:
      minReplicas: 1
      maxReplicas: 20
      rules:
        - name: http-scaling
          http:
            metadata:
              concurrentRequests: "100"
  dapr:
    enabled: true
    appId: api
    appPort: 8080
    appProtocol: http
  secrets:
    - name: db-password
      keyVaultUrl: https://my-vault.vault.azure.net/secrets/db-password
      identity: /subscriptions/.../userAssignedIdentities/api-identity
]]></code>
  </example>
</text>
