<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="azure-compute Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for azure-compute as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>VMSS Uniform mode in old Terraform that still defaults to Uniform.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force Flexible orchestration on every new VMSS.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>AKS Pod Identity is deprecated in favor of Workload Identity (OIDC + federated credentials). Agents still scaffold Pod Identity from old blog posts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Update to Workload Identity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>KEDA add-on must be enabled AFTER Workload Identity on AKS — wrong order leaves KEDA without an identity, scalers fail silently.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Enable OIDC issuer and Workload Identity before KEDA.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Container Apps: no Windows containers, no ARM64, no privileged containers. Agents reach for --privileged and the deploy fails late.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Check limitations before provisioning.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Container Apps revisions: setting min-replicas: 0 triggers cold starts (5-30s on first request).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>For latency-sensitive APIs use min-replicas: 1 and accept the cost.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>App Service slot swap WITHOUT warmup → first requests after swap hit cold workers and 5xx.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always configure WEBSITE_SWAP_WARMUP_PING_PATH + WEBSITE_SWAP_WARMUP_PING_STATUSES.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>VM/VMSS Spot evictions: 30-second notice via Scheduled Events; agents forget to wire the metadata endpoint and lose work mid-task.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Implement Scheduled Events handler.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>AKS Cluster Autoscaler vs. Karpenter (now AKS Node Auto-Provisioning preview) — agents mix recommendations, end up with neither truly enabled.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pick one and configure it properly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Quotas (vCPU per region, public IPs, NIC count) bite at scale. New subscriptions have absurdly low defaults; agents file ARM templates that hit quota mid-deploy and leave half-created resources.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Check quotas with az vm list-usage before deploying.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents pick a region by name without checking SKU availability — Standard_D4ds_v5 exists in westeurope but not in swedencentral Spot.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a az vm list-skus -l &lt;region&gt; check before generating IaC.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Quota limits cause partial deploys: agents apply, hit a vCPU quota, leave half-created NICs / disks.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always run az deployment group what-if AND check az vm list-usage first.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>"Subscription" vs. "tenant" vs. "management group" confusion → agents create resources in the wrong subscription.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Bind subscription ID via az account set --subscription at the very top of any script and assert via az account show.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Service principal vs. managed identity: agents default to creating a SP because samples do; SP secrets expire and rotate poorly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Prefer Managed Identity / Workload Identity; only use SP for cross-tenant edge cases.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Soft-delete on Key Vault / Storage: agents terraform destroy and the next apply fails because the name is reserved for 7-90 days.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use --purge or rename — and document the choice.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Costs creep silently: agents add a Premium SSD + GRS Storage + always-on App Service Plan; no one notices for a billing cycle.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Wire cost projection into the PR check.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
