<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="aws-ec2-provisioning Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for aws-ec2-provisioning. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All EC2 instances MUST require IMDSv2 (HttpTokens=required, HttpPutResponseHopLimit=2) and use encrypted gp3 EBS root volumes. No instance MUST be launched with a key pair if SSM Session Manager is available — attach an IAM instance profile with AmazonSSMManagedInstanceCore instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">IMDSv1 is vulnerable to SSRF credential theft. Encrypted EBS is free on gp3 and mandated by PCI-DSS, SOC 2, and HIPAA. SSM Session Manager provides audited access without managing SSH keys or opening port 22.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Create a launch template for every ASG. The template MUST encode: ImageId, InstanceType, IamInstanceProfile, MetadataOptions (IMDSv2), BlockDeviceMappings (gp3 encrypted), and SecurityGroupIds. Never hardcode UserData credentials — reference Secrets Manager or SSM Parameter Store from within the instance instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Launch templates make ASG instance refresh zero-downtime and reproducible. Hardcoded credentials in UserData appear in the EC2 console and CloudTrail logs in plaintext.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Auto Scaling Groups MUST use health-check type ELB (not EC2) when a load balancer target group is attached, spread across at least 2 Availability Zones, and apply a target tracking scaling policy on ASGAverageCPUUtilization at 70%. Use instance refresh with min_healthy_percentage=75 for zero-downtime AMI rollouts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">EC2 health checks only detect OS-level failures; ELB health checks detect application-level failures. CPU target tracking at 70% leaves headroom for traffic spikes while preventing over-provisioning. Instance refresh eliminates manual draining and re-registration during AMI updates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Create one security group per application tier (ALB, app, database). App tier ingress MUST reference the ALB security group ID, database tier ingress MUST reference the app security group ID — never use CIDR blocks for inter-tier traffic. Add descriptions to every rule. Restrict SSH/RDP to specific IP ranges; never allow 0.0.0.0/0 on port 22 or 3389.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Security-group-to-security-group references automatically track instance IP changes without rule updates. CIDR-based rules drift as subnets expand. Descriptions are required for audit trails and are enforced by some compliance frameworks.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
