<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Competitive Analysis (UX) — 6-Step Process">
  <summary>Structured procedure for examining competitor products across predefined criteria and converting observations into prioritized design recommendations.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Scope and Select Competitors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select 3-5 direct competitors, 2-3 indirect competitors, and 1-2 aspirational examples. Cap total at 8 to maintain analysis depth.</statement>
      <rationale>More than 8 competitors degrades analysis depth — breadth replaces insight. Aspirational examples from adjacent industries expose solutions that direct competitors have not discovered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Competitor types: Direct (same problem, same user — e.g. Uber vs Lyft). Indirect (same problem, different approach — e.g. Uber vs public transit). Partial (overlapping features). Aspirational (best-in-class to learn from, not a competitor).</p>
    <reference path="templates/analysis-plan.md">Analysis plan skeleton with competitor list and criteria</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Define Evaluation Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Establish evaluation criteria before examining any competitor product — criteria derived after examination are biased toward what was observed.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc criteria selection produces confirmation bias — analysts unconsciously weight criteria where their preferred design performs well. Pre-defined criteria are neutral.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Dimensions to consider: features (what can users do), user flows (how users accomplish goals), UI patterns (design conventions used), information architecture (content organization), content and tone, accessibility compliance.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Gather Data by Actually Using Products">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create real accounts and complete full user flows rather than reviewing screenshots or marketing pages.</statement>
      <rationale>Screenshots reveal visual design only. Friction, error states, loading behavior, and onboarding quality are only visible through direct use. Surface-level review misses the most actionable findings.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Data collection: use on both desktop and mobile, complete key user flows end-to-end, document edge cases, contact support, test accessibility.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Document Findings Consistently">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the same documentation structure for every competitor — annotated screenshots, flow steps, strengths, weaknesses, and opportunities. Inconsistent documentation prevents comparison.</statement>
      <rationale>Inconsistent notes cannot be compared across competitors. A structured template forces coverage of the same criteria for all products.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/competitor-profile.md">Per-competitor profile template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/feature-matrix.md">Feature comparison matrix</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Analyze for Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>After documenting all competitors, identify: what everyone does (baseline expectation), what nobody does (opportunity gap), what top performers do distinctively (best practice), and what common problems exist (anti-patterns to avoid).</statement>
      <rationale>Pattern analysis across competitors is where individual observations become strategic insight. Analyzing one competitor at a time produces a list of features, not a competitive landscape.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Generate Prioritized Recommendations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Categorize every recommendation into Must Have (table stakes), Should Have (competitive parity), Could Differentiate (opportunity), or Avoid (observed failure mode).</statement>
      <rationale>Flat recommendation lists produce debate. Four-tier categorization produces a prioritization decision: Must Have items are blockers; Avoid items are negative signals; differentiation opportunities are the most valuable output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/summary-report.md">Executive summary report template</reference>
  </section>
</text>
