<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="business-process-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-modeling</domain>
    <summary>5-stage analysis cycle for understanding how work flows through an organization, from current-state documentation to future-state design, with metrics-backed process improvement.</summary>
    <category>modeling</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>business-process</tag>
      <tag>bpmn</tag>
      <tag>process-improvement</tag>
      <tag>workflow</tag>
      <tag>automation</tag>
    </tags>
    <applies-to>both</applies-to>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="use-case-modeling"/>
      <ref slug="acceptance-criteria"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Business Process Analysis</title>

    <summary>5-stage analysis cycle for understanding how work actually flows through an organization: identify processes → document current state (with source citations) → analyze (value/time/cost tables) → design future state (diff table, not prose) → validate with stakeholders. Output artifacts are process-documentation.md and process-analysis.md; BPMN XML stored in version control alongside them.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Processes exist only in people's heads; different people execute them differently; inefficiencies are hidden in workarounds. BPA produces a numbers-backed case for change (NVA-minutes × frequency) before automation or system redesign, preventing the "paving the cowpath" failure where a manual mess is automated at scale. Pre-automation discovery is the highest-leverage use: model the as-is so the n8n workflow or backend service eliminates waste, not replicates it.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Raw process evidence exists (SOP docs, Slack threads, ticket histories, support transcripts) and a normalized model is needed before redesign.</item>
        <item>A cross-team workflow shows symptoms of waste: rework loops, long approval queues, dual data entry.</item>
        <item>Pre-automation discovery: before writing an n8n workflow, RPA bot, or backend service replacing a manual process.</item>
        <item>Pre-spec stage of a BA-heavy SDD feature: BPA output becomes input to requirements-documentation and acceptance-criteria.</item>
        <item>Compliance / audit prep where regulators expect a documented process map with controls and exception handling.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Greenfield product where no current process exists — use use-case-modeling or user-story-mapping instead.</item>
        <item>One-off troubleshooting of a single broken instance — use 5-whys / fishbone root-cause tools.</item>
        <item>Tactical UI tweaks where the "process" is one click.</item>
        <item>Highly creative / knowledge-work flows (R&D, design, writing) where steps are non-deterministic.</item>
        <item>Team is already mid-redesign and stakeholders have agreed on future state — re-modelling as-is delays delivery.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="stage-2-document-current-state">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every row in the Process Steps table must cite a source span (file + line, ticket ID, or transcript timestamp). Rows with no citation are marked "unverified" and blocked from analysis.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs smooth over messy interviews into tidy linear diagrams; workarounds (the actual value) get edited out. Source citations make every step falsifiable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Emit a Contradictions section listing any step mentioned differently by two or more sources, verbatim. Do not smooth over contradictions — they are the most valuable signal.</statement>
        <rationale>Contradictions between sources reveal workarounds, tribal knowledge, and undocumented exceptions. Smoothing them produces a map of the ideal process, not the actual one.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every step must have an actor column. Steps with a blank actor are rejected by the documentation agent. Single-pool diagrams that lose handoffs between actors are also rejected.</statement>
        <rationale>Handoffs between actors are where delays, errors, and miscommunication occur. Losing actor attribution makes the process map unanalyzable for bottleneck detection.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run password-scrubber-agent on all raw evidence (SOP docs, Slack exports, ticket histories) before feeding to any other agent. SOPs and tickets routinely contain credentials, customer data, and internal URLs.</statement>
        <rationale>PII and credentials in raw evidence files get embedded in process documentation and spread to wider audiences. Scrubbing at ingestion prevents a class of security incidents.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="stage-3-analyze">
      <rule>
        <statement>VA/BN/NVA rubric: VA = customer would pay for this step; BN = required by law/policy/system but no customer value; NVA = waiting, rework, transport, duplicate data entry. Pin 3 examples per category in the prompt to prevent drift between runs.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a fixed rubric, VA/BN/NVA labels swing with prompt wording. Two runs on the same step list disagree in 20-30% of rows. Pinned examples anchor classification.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>For cycle time and error rate: use only numbers cited in the source documents. If absent, write "Data not available". Never estimate. Never fill table cells with confidence-qualified guesses.</statement>
        <rationale>Hallucinated metrics are worse than missing metrics because they anchor decisions to fabricated baselines. "Data not available" triggers a data-collection action; a guess does not.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Rank improvement opportunities by NVA-minutes × frequency (not by NVA-minutes alone). End the analysis with a Top-3 candidates for elimination block ordered by this composite score.</statement>
        <rationale>A 10-minute NVA step that runs 1000 times a day beats a 2-hour NVA step that runs once per quarter. Frequency-weighting changes the prioritization in real workflows.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="stage-4-design-future-state">
      <rule>
        <statement>Express future-state changes as a diff table, not prose: columns are step, current actor, future actor, current system, future system, change type (eliminate/automate/simplify/integrate/parallelize), and risk. Prose descriptions are not actionable and cannot be assigned to an engineer.</statement>
        <rationale>Future-state prose produces "auto-approve orders under $1000" without specifying which system changes or which engineer owns it. The diff table forces specificity on every axis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap improvement proposals at 5, ranked by effort/benefit scores. More than 5 proposals without prioritization is a shopping list, not a recommendation.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs default to "automate" for everything. A 30-improvement list without ranking forces the BA to prioritize what the agent should have prioritized. Eliminate/simplify (cheaper wins) get under-recommended.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="stage-5-validate">
      <rule>
        <statement>Stage 5 requires human-in-the-loop sign-off from the process owner. The agent prepares a review packet (current-state doc, analysis, future-state diff); a human approves or sends back. Never auto-advance past stage 4 in headless mode.</statement>
        <rationale>Future-state process changes affect real people and systems. Auto-advancing without sign-off produces redesigns that do not account for political, contractual, or operational constraints the agent cannot discover from documents.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <rule>
        <statement>Persist a _bpa-state.json file in the feature's .aidocs directory tracking completed stages and artifact paths. Each agent invocation reads this file to determine which stage to run next. Do not re-run completed stages unless explicitly reset.</statement>
        <rationale>Long BPA sessions span multiple days. Without a state file, a resumed session re-runs early stages and overwrites verified artifacts with less-grounded re-analyses.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Stage 2 and 3 agents are evidence-bound: they receive paths to raw evidence files and must cite them. Stage 4 (design) is generative and receives only the verified stage-3 analysis. Never feed raw evidence to the stage-4 agent directly.</statement>
        <rationale>Feeding raw evidence to the design agent allows it to re-interpret the as-is analysis and drift from the verified findings. The verified analysis is the authoritative input for design.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Stage 2 dispatch: "Read evidence files: [paths]. Build the as-is model for '[process-name]'. For every step row, cite the source line/file in the Notes column. If a step is mentioned by only one source, mark it 'single-source — verify'. Do NOT smooth over contradictions; emit a ## Contradictions section."</statement>
        <rationale>The citation and contradiction requirements are the most important constraints in stage 2. Without them, the agent produces a plausible-sounding but unverifiable process map.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Stage 3 dispatch: "Input: process-documentation.md. Produce process-analysis.md. VA/BN/NVA rubric: [pin examples]. Cycle time and error rate: cite source line or write 'Data not available'. End with Top-3 candidates for elimination ranked by NVA-minutes × frequency."</statement>
        <rationale>The rubric pinning, the data-source requirement, and the frequency-weighted ranking are the three constraints that prevent the most common stage-3 failures.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>When event logs (Jira exports, Zendesk ticket histories, GitHub commit logs) are available, run discover_dfg.py to produce a directly-follows graph before stage 2. Compare the discovered DFG against the manually-built process map. Discrepancies equal workarounds that were not mentioned in interviews.</statement>
        <rationale>Process mining discovers the actual execution sequence from log data without bias from what stakeholders say should happen. Discrepancies between the DFG and the interview-based map are the highest-value finding in any BPA engagement.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-failure-modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ideal-vs-actual gap: LLMs amplify "documenting the ideal" by smoothing messy interviews into tidy linear diagrams.</description>
        <reason>Workarounds (the actual value) get edited out. Force verbatim quotes for anomalies; never paraphrase exceptions.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No native BPMN renderer: Methodology shows arrow-art but produces no machine-readable artifact.</description>
        <reason>Without BPMN 2.0 XML you cannot diff, validate, or feed downstream tools (Camunda, Signavio).</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Value-classification subjectivity: VA/BN/NVA labels swing with prompt wording; runs disagree in 20-30% of rows.</description>
        <reason>Needs a fixed rubric with examples or human review.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Metrics fabrication: "Cycle time" and "error rate" tables invite hallucinated numbers when no data source supplied.</description>
        <reason>Hard rule: blank or "Data not available" if source absent.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Single-pool bias: LLMs collapse multi-actor swimlanes (typical for B2B processes) into linear flows.</description>
        <reason>Needs extra prompting to maintain handoffs. Force swimlane requirement.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Future-state hand-waving: "Auto-approve orders &lt; $1000" is easy to write, hard to scope.</description>
        <reason>Without an explicit "what changes in which system" column, future-state diagrams are unactionable.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Improvement pattern overuse: LLMs default to "automate" for everything.</description>
        <reason>Eliminate/simplify (cheaper, faster wins) get under-recommended.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Not for event-driven systems: BPMN sequence flows model deterministic step-by-step work.</description>
        <reason>Event-heavy async systems (queues, webhooks, sagas) need event storming or BPMN choreography, not basic process flows.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-advanced-workflow">
      <p>Run as a 5-stage state machine, one stage per subagent invocation, persisting artifacts between stages. Stage 1 (identify) and stage 2 (document) are evidence-bound — supply raw inputs and require citation. Stage 3 (analyze) is computational — emit tables, not narrative. Stage 4 (design future) is generative — score each change against effort/benefit. Stage 5 (validate) is human-in-the-loop — prepare review packet for human approval.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-ba-agent — Orchestrator. Owns the 5-stage state machine and writes process-documentation.md / process-analysis.md.</item>
        <item>faion-software-architect — Consumes future-state model and produces system-level design.</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — Downstream: turns approved future-state into spec → design → tasks.</item>
        <item>faion-research-agent — Upstream when no SOP exists: mine industry reference processes (APQC PCF, eTOM).</item>
        <item>General-purpose Task subagent — Pass pm4py + event log CSV; returns discovered DFG/BPMN.</item>
        <item>password-scrubber-agent — Run on raw transcripts/logs before any other agent; SOPs contain credentials.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Stage 2 dispatch: "Read evidence files: [paths]. Build the as-is model for '[process-name]'. For every step row, cite the source line/file in the Notes column. If a step is mentioned by only one source, mark it 'single-source — verify'. Do NOT smooth over contradictions; emit a ## Contradictions section."</statement>
        <rationale>The citation and contradiction requirements are the most important constraints in stage 2.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Stage 3 dispatch: "Input: process-documentation.md. Produce process-analysis.md. VA/BN/NVA rubric: [pin examples]. Cycle time and error rate: cite source line or write 'Data not available'. End with Top-3 candidates for elimination ranked by NVA-minutes × frequency."</statement>
        <rationale>The rubric pinning, the data-source requirement, and the frequency-weighted ranking prevent the most common stage-3 failures.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Process mining and BPMN tools:</p>
      <list>
        <item>pm4py — Discover BPMN/DFG from event logs, conformance check. (pip install pm4py)</item>
        <item>bpmn-js / bpmn-to-image — Render BPMN XML to SVG/PNG for review packets. (npm i -g bpmn-to-image)</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc) — Quick flowcharts when full BPMN is overkill. (npm i -g @mermaid-js/mermaid-cli)</item>
        <item>graphviz (dot) — Render DFG output from pm4py. (apt install graphviz)</item>
        <item>pandas — Event log cleanup, throughput analysis, value-add roll-ups. (pip install pandas)</item>
        <item>python-docx / pdfplumber — Extract steps from existing SOP Word/PDF docs. (pip install python-docx pdfplumber)</item>
        <item>whisper / whisper.cpp — Transcribe stakeholder interviews into evidence text.</item>
        <item>jq — Slice JSON event logs from APIs (Jira, Zendesk, GitHub). (apt install jq)</item>
        <item>csvkit (csvgrep, csvstat) — Inspect raw event logs before feeding to pm4py. (pip install csvkit)</item>
      </list>

      <p>BPMN modeling and execution platforms:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Camunda 8 / Camunda Modeler — OSS + SaaS. Open-standard BPMN 2.0; agents can deploy and query running instances.</item>
        <item>Signavio (SAP) — SaaS. Enterprise-grade; expensive but deep value-stream analytics.</item>
        <item>Bizagi Modeler — SaaS + free desktop. Good free modeler; weak API.</item>
        <item>Lucidchart — SaaS. Easy collaboration; export BPMN XML for downstream tooling.</item>
        <item>draw.io / diagrams.net — OSS, free SaaS. Cheap rendering; no execution semantics.</item>
        <item>Celonis — SaaS (process mining). Industry leader for log-based discovery; pricey.</item>
        <item>ProcessGold (UiPath Process Mining) — SaaS. Tied to UiPath RPA stack.</item>
        <item>Apromore — OSS + SaaS. Open process mining; pairs well with pm4py.</item>
        <item>Disco (Fluxicon) — Desktop. Strong DFG generator for one-off analyses.</item>
        <item>n8n (this workspace) — OSS, self-hosted. Implement future-state automation.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Event log sources for process discovery:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Jira / Linear / Asana — Event logs for ticket-driven processes.</item>
        <item>Zendesk / Intercom — Event logs for support processes.</item>
        <item>Salesforce Flow + Event Monitoring — Event logs for sales/service processes.</item>
        <item>GitHub / GitLab — Event logs for engineering/release processes.</item>
        <item>Zapier / Make — Quick automation of NVA steps without backend changes.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Demand evidence per step: Every row of the Process Steps table must cite a source span (file + line, ticket ID, timestamp). No citation → row marked unverified, blocked from analysis.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Separate the happy path from exceptions: Force two diagrams — one nominal flow + one exception map keyed by trigger event.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Quantify before redesigning: Future-state has no value if current-state metrics missing. If data unavailable, run a 2-week sample first.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>VA/BN/NVA rubric pinned in the prompt: Without it, classifications drift. Pin examples (3 per category) and require agent to compare each step.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Frequency-weight the improvements: A 10-min NVA step running 1000×/day beats a 2-hour NVA step running once/quarter. Rank by nva_minutes × frequency.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Walk the process physically: When evidence is mostly transcripts, schedule a Gemba-walk with screen recording; transcribe with whisper and re-run stage 2.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Diff future-vs-current as a table, not prose: Columns are step | current actor | future actor | current system | future system | change type | risk. Forces specificity.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Validate against process mining: If event logs available, run pm4py DFG discovery and compare to manually-built BPMN. Discrepancies = missed workarounds.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep BPMN in source control: Store BPMN XML alongside process-documentation.md so diffs are reviewable in PRs.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Hand off via spec, not diagram: Output that matters downstream is requirements-documentation.md derived from future-state — diagrams are review aids.</statement>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Linear-flow bias: LLMs collapse parallel branches into sequential steps.</description>
        <reason>Pre-prompt: "Identify all gateways (XOR/OR/AND); never default to linear flow."</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Lost actors: Single-pool diagrams lose handoffs.</description>
        <reason>Force swimlane requirement: every step must have an actor column; if blank → reject.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated systems: Agent invents "ERP" or "CRM" generically.</description>
        <reason>Constrain: "Use only system names that appear verbatim in the evidence."</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Soft metrics: Agent fills cycle-time with "30 min (estimated)".</description>
        <reason>Hard-block: "If metric not directly cited, write Data not available."</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>VA/BN/NVA drift between runs: Same input, different labels on re-run.</description>
        <reason>Mitigate with fixed rubric + temperature 0 + determinism check (run twice, compare).</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Future-state shopping list: Agent emits 30 improvements with no prioritization.</description>
        <reason>Cap at 5 + require effort/benefit scores.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Workaround erasure: "we email Jane because system broken" rewritten as "data transferred to Jane".</description>
        <reason>Force verbatim quotes for anomalies; agent must not paraphrase exceptions.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>PII / credential leak: SOPs and tickets contain customer data, API keys, internal URLs.</description>
        <reason>Run password-scrubber-agent on raw evidence before passing to any LLM tool.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>BPMN dialect mismatch: Output looks like BPMN but fails 2.0 XML validation.</description>
        <reason>Always validate with pm4py.write_bpmn() or bpmn-validate before archiving.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Loop-mining false positives: pm4py discovers loops where real process has retries on transient errors.</description>
        <reason>Filter event logs by terminal states before mining.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Token blow-up at synthesis: 200-step retail process exceeds context.</description>
        <reason>Chunk by sub-process (one BPMN call activity per chunk) and stitch in orchestrator pass.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Cron-mode interactivity: Validate stage requires humans but runs headless.</description>
        <reason>Freeze at stage 4 and emit review packet — never auto-advance without approval.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Documenting the ideal process: agent smooths over interview transcripts into a tidy linear diagram. Workarounds disappear.</description>
        <reason>Workarounds are the actual process. They carry the real value and the real waste. Verbatim quotes for any anomaly; the agent is forbidden from paraphrasing them as normal steps.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated metrics: cycle-time cells filled with "30 min (estimated)" when no data source is supplied.</description>
        <reason>Estimated metrics anchor decisions to fabricated baselines. Hard-block: "Data not available" if not directly cited in the evidence.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Single-pool bias: LLMs collapse parallel branches into sequential steps and lose multi-actor swimlanes.</description>
        <reason>Handoffs between actors are where bottlenecks occur. Pre-prompt: "Identify all gateways (XOR/OR/AND); never default to a linear flow. Every step must have an actor column."</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Future-state shopping list: agent emits 30 improvements with no prioritization or effort scores.</description>
        <reason>Cap at 5 improvements; require effort/benefit scores ranked by NVA×frequency. A list without ranking forces BA work the agent should have done.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Workaround erasure: "we email Jane because the system is broken" rewritten as "data is transferred to the systems team".</description>
        <reason>The workaround is the finding. Force verbatim quotes for any anomaly. The agent must not paraphrase exceptions into normal-looking steps.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>BPMN output that looks like valid XML but fails Camunda/pm4py validation on import.</description>
        <reason>Always validate BPMN 2.0 XML with pm4py.write_bpmn() or bpmn-validate before archiving. Invalid BPMN cannot be executed, diffed, or imported into downstream tools.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated system names: agent invents "ERP" or "CRM" generically when evidence mentions specific systems.</description>
        <reason>Constrain: "Use only system names that appear verbatim in the evidence." Generic names make the process map non-actionable for system-specific redesign.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/process-documentation.md" purpose="Current-state doc template with overview, actors, inputs/outputs, process steps table with citation column, business rules, and metrics."/>
      <template path="templates/process-analysis.md" purpose="Analysis template with value classification table, pain points, bottlenecks, and improvement opportunities ranked by NVA×frequency."/>
      <template path="templates/discover_dfg.py" purpose="Event-log to directly-follows graph via pm4py; outputs dfg.svg and per-activity stats.csv."/>
      <template path="templates/bpa-state.json" purpose="Workflow state file for resumable 5-stage pipeline: tracks completed stages and artifact paths."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_process_modeling"/>
      <link href="https://www.bpmn.org/"/>
      <link href="https://pm4py.fit.fraunhofer.de/"/>
      <ref slug="use-case-modeling"/>
      <ref slug="acceptance-criteria"/>
      <ref slug="specification-writing"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
