<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="hybrid-delivery Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for hybrid-delivery. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select the delivery approach by component risk profile, not by organizational preference or trend. High uncertainty + frequent change → agile; clear requirements + fixed scope → predictive; mixed characteristics → hybrid; continuous deployment needed → agile + DevOps.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Method dogma ("we do agile here") applied without fit analysis produces cargo-cult implementations. The framework must reflect actual project characteristics, not team culture preferences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Draw the boundary in writing inside a program charter or program.yaml: name explicitly which deliverables are predictive (contracts, regulatory submissions, hardware BOMs, charters) and which are agile (software increments, user research, UX iterations).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Boundary ambiguity is the dominant hybrid failure mode. An undocumented boundary turns into a status theatre where teams argue about which method applies to any given decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define exactly one translation table per program: epic ↔ deliverable, story-points ↔ effort, velocity ↔ run rate. Use it for every steering report; never invent new mappings mid-program.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a fixed translation table, steering-committee reporting is inconsistent across presentations. Finance, PMO, and dev teams read the same data with incompatible vocabulary, leading to false alignment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use at most two tools with explicit sync; three or more tools is a smell requiring immediate consolidation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each additional tool adds a sync gap. Agents waste tokens reconciling disagreements between tools; humans lose trust in all data sources when tools disagree.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Match gate frequency to risk profile: monthly for regulated programs, quarterly for steady-state, never weekly (weekly gates are status meetings with a governance label).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Over-gating the agile arm throttles delivery frequency without commensurate risk reduction. Under-gating the predictive arm creates unbounded risk accumulation. Calibrate gates to actual decision needs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints are mandatory at: boundary changes, gate decisions, re-baselining, cadence changes, vendor escalations.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These are structural decisions affecting multiple teams or organizational commitments and must be human-owned.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
