<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-antipatterns" title="Hybrid Delivery — Six Failure Modes">
  <summary>The six most common hybrid delivery failure modes with concrete descriptions and root-cause explanations.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Boundary ambiguity — hybrid is declared but the line between agile-here and predictive-there is never written down.</description>
      <reason>Every governance decision becomes a negotiation over which method applies. Teams default to the method that benefits them locally, creating incoherence at the program level.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Dual definitions of done — agile arm calls a story "done" when it passes sprint review; predictive arm calls a deliverable "done" when a document is signed. No translation layer exists.</description>
      <reason>Steering-committee status reports are incoherent. A sprint's "80% done" and a milestone's "waiting for signature" cannot be meaningfully combined without a defined mapping.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Tool sprawl — backlog in Jira, Gantt in MS Project, deliverables in SharePoint, risks in Excel. No canonical source of truth.</description>
      <reason>Each tool sync gap creates an opportunity for data to diverge. Agents and PMs spend more time reconciling tool disagreements than managing project risk.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Governance drift — predictive arm enforces a stage gate; agile arm flies through it silently. Or agile gets gated to a quarterly cadence and loses all iteration value.</description>
      <reason>Gate frequency must match actual risk profile. Over-gating agile destroys delivery speed without risk benefit; under-gating predictive work accumulates unbounded risk.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Political compromise disguised as method — hybrid is adopted because PMO wants control and teams want autonomy, not because project characteristics require it.</description>
      <reason>Method choice must follow project fit. When hybrid is a political settlement, neither side commits to the other's discipline, producing incoherent execution with the overhead of both methods.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>EVM applied to the agile arm — SPI and CPI computed from story points multiplied by an hourly rate.</description>
      <reason>Story points are a relative sizing unit, not a labour cost measure. EVM on agile produces SPI/CPI numbers that look precise but measure nothing real. Report agile metrics in agile units; apply EVM only to the predictive arm.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
