<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="hybrid-delivery Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for hybrid-delivery as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Boundary ambiguity — hybrid is declared but the line between agile-here and predictive-there is never written down.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every governance decision becomes a negotiation over which method applies. Teams default to the method that benefits them locally, creating incoherence at the program level.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Dual definitions of done — agile arm calls a story "done" when it passes sprint review; predictive arm calls a deliverable "done" when a document is signed. No translation layer exists.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Steering-committee status reports are incoherent. A sprint's "80% done" and a milestone's "waiting for signature" cannot be meaningfully combined without a defined mapping.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Tool sprawl — backlog in Jira, Gantt in MS Project, deliverables in SharePoint, risks in Excel. No canonical source of truth.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each tool sync gap creates an opportunity for data to diverge. Agents and PMs spend more time reconciling tool disagreements than managing project risk.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Governance drift — predictive arm enforces a stage gate; agile arm flies through it silently. Or agile gets gated to a quarterly cadence and loses all iteration value.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Gate frequency must match actual risk profile. Over-gating agile destroys delivery speed without risk benefit; under-gating predictive work accumulates unbounded risk.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Political compromise disguised as method — hybrid is adopted because PMO wants control and teams want autonomy, not because project characteristics require it.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Method choice must follow project fit. When hybrid is a political settlement, neither side commits to the other's discipline, producing incoherent execution with the overhead of both methods.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>EVM applied to the agile arm — SPI and CPI computed from story points multiplied by an hourly rate.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Story points are a relative sizing unit, not a labour cost measure. EVM on agile produces SPI/CPI numbers that look precise but measure nothing real. Report agile metrics in agile units; apply EVM only to the predictive arm.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents over-summarize hybrid programs as "behind" because they conflate vocabulary; force agile metrics in agile units, predictive metrics in predictive units.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Conflation of vocabulary leads to false rollup conclusions that miss real risks in one arm while over-focusing on the other.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs auto-translate epics into "deliverables" and lose information (acceptance criteria collapse to one line). Keep both views; never destroy detail.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Detail loss breaks traceability and makes it impossible to recover original requirements when the inevitably questions arise later.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Date arithmetic is unreliable across calendar conventions (work days vs. calendar days, fiscal vs. ISO weeks). Hard-code the convention in the prompt; have a tool, not the LLM, compute deltas.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLM date math is a known failure mode; systematic errors in burn calculations cascade to wrong gate-readiness assessments.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Stage-gate "go / no-go" must never be auto-emitted — flag readiness only, leave the call to the sponsor.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Gate decisions are inherently human / sponsor decisions; auto-emission removes accountability and trains stakeholders to ignore readiness assessments.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>EVM on agile arm is a trap: agents will compute SPI/CPI from story points × hourly rate. Refuse unless the conversion is explicitly accepted by finance.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Story points × hourly rate is not earned value; this violates EVM principles and produces misleading financial reports.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-tool sync drift: if Jira and MS Project disagree, pin the system of record per field in `program.yaml`.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a pinned source-of-truth per field, agents have no deterministic way to decide which value is correct during reconciliation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Vocabulary leakage: predictive uses "milestone, deliverable, baseline"; agile uses "increment, story, velocity". Force terminology per audience.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mixing vocabularies in reports confuses steering-committee members and masks real misalignment between arms.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Bulk gate-pack generation is a leak risk — packs pull from confidential decks/screenshots. Run `password-scrubber-agent` and manual review before sharing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Gate packs aggregate sensitive data; automated generation without scrubbing frequently leaks credentials, financial data, or strategic information.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Long-context drift: program graphs &gt;50 epics blow context. Page by milestone or workstream and operate on slices.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Operating on massive program graphs depletes context windows and leads to loss of fidelity in agent analysis.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
