<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="project-closure">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Formal termination process for a project: obtain written deliverable acceptance, release resources, close contracts, capture lessons learned, archive documents, and transition to operations.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>project-closure</tag>
      <tag>project-completion</tag>
      <tag>deliverable-acceptance</tag>
      <tag>lessons-learned</tag>
      <tag>handover</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Project Closure</title>

    <summary>Formal termination process for a project: obtain written deliverable acceptance, release resources, close contracts, capture lessons learned, archive documents, and transition to operations. Without a closure event, projects fade without official acceptance, resources stay allocated to finished work, and knowledge walks out with the team.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Informal endings leave ambiguous completion status, open vendor contracts (ongoing costs, liabilities), unarchived documentation, and no knowledge transfer. Formal closure enforces a hard boundary that unlocks people for new work, triggers financial reconciliation, and seeds future projects with lessons. Get acceptance in writing — verbal "looks good" does not hold at invoice time.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>End of any contracted or fixed-bid engagement requiring formal acceptance.</item>
        <item>Cancelled or descoped projects (closure must capture salvage value and lessons).</item>
        <item>Phase-gated programs at major milestone transitions (Phase 1 → Phase 2 closure).</item>
        <item>Internal projects transitioning from build to operate (handover to ops/support).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Continuous-flow or product teams — no closure event; only release boundaries.</item>
        <item>Solo throwaway prototypes — a DONE.md line is enough.</item>
        <item>Projects still in execution; premature closure loses incomplete deliverables.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="step-1-verify-deliverable-acceptance">
      <p>Obtain written acceptance for every deliverable before declaring closure; verbal confirmation does not hold at invoice time.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Obtain written acceptance for every deliverable before declaring closure; verbal confirmation does not hold at invoice time.</statement>
        <rationale>Ambiguous acceptance is the most common source of post-project invoice disputes and scope creep into "maintenance" work that was never bought.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>For each deliverable, confirm: all requirements met, testing complete, documentation delivered, sign-off obtained in writing.</p>
      <reference path="templates/acceptance-form.md">Per-deliverable acceptance form with criteria table and signature block.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="step-2-administrative-closure">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Process all financial, resource, and contract closure actions within the closure window; do not leave open POs or un-released team members.</statement>
        <rationale>Open contracts accumulate charges. Resources "stuck" on finished projects block new assignments and frustrate individuals.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Financial: final invoices, close POs, return unused budget, reconcile costs.</item>
        <item>Resource: release team members, return equipment, revoke access/permissions, notify resource managers.</item>
        <item>Contract: final vendor payments, warranty/support handover, termination letters, archive agreements.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="step-3-lessons-learned">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run the lessons-learned session before the team disperses, not after; memory and candor both degrade within days.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-dispersal sessions yield low attendance and sanitized data. Lessons captured in flight are richer and more actionable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Document what worked and what did not; store in the organizational knowledge base. Capture both successes and failures — teams that log only failures stop contributing honestly.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="step-4-archive-project-documents">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Archive documents into named categories (planning, execution, technical, contracts, closure) with a manifest so they can be found in 12 months.</statement>
        <rationale>Unstructured "shared drive" archives are unfindable; without a manifest, future auditors and PMs have no entry point.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <reference path="templates/closeout-archive.sh">Shell script to bundle the archive with per-category folders and SHA-256 manifest.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="step-5-write-final-project-report">
      <p>Document project completion covering: executive summary, deliverables, schedule/budget/scope/quality performance, key accomplishments, challenges and resolutions, lessons-learned summary, transition information, and acknowledgments.</p>
      <reference path="templates/final-report.md">Final report skeleton with all required sections.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="step-6-transition-to-operations">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Hand operations a working runbook on day -7, not day 0; shadow week lets them surface gaps before you are gone.</statement>
        <rationale>Day-0 handovers leave the ops team inheriting an unsupportable system with no one to ask questions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Handover items: system access, documentation, support tickets, monitoring, L1/L2/L3 contacts, escalation matrix, scheduled maintenance.</p>
      <reference path="templates/handover-doc.md">Operations handover template covering all required sections.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="step-7-celebrate-and-recognize">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Celebrate visibly and name individual contributions; do not cut this step under schedule pressure.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping recognition is the leading cause of post-project demoralization, increasing attrition risk on the next engagement.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="closure-types">
      <list>
        <item>Normal — objectives met: full closure process.</item>
        <item>Early (success) — objectives met ahead of schedule: accelerated closure.</item>
        <item>Early (cancelled) — stopped before completion: document reasons, recover value.</item>
        <item>Integration — absorbed into operations: transition-focused closure.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="examples-and-antipatterns">
      <example type="good" title="Customer Portal v2.0 normal closure">
        <note>6 months, $150k: final UAT sign-off obtained from business sponsor; production confirmed stable after 2-week soak; support team trained; documentation handed over; final cost $147,500 (under budget); 5 lessons captured; team celebration lunch held; final report distributed; project marked closed in system.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Cancelled Mobile App Prototype closure">
        <note>Strategic pivot, 30% complete: documented work completed and reasons; lessons learned on prototyping approach; recovered reusable design assets; released resources to other projects; negotiated early vendor contract termination; archived all documentation; final report with cancellation rationale — value recovered even from incomplete work.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No formal acceptance — assuming silence means approved.</description>
        <reason>Closure without written acceptance leaves deliverable status ambiguous; six months later this becomes an invoice dispute with no documentation to support the PM's position.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Resources not released — people stuck on "finished" projects.</description>
        <reason>Trapped resources block new work and signal to team members that their time is not valued, increasing turnover risk.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Contracts left open — ongoing vendor charges accumulate.</description>
        <reason>Open POs continue to accrue costs and legal liabilities long after work stopped; finance discovers this in quarterly audits, not daily operations.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No lessons captured — knowledge walks out the door with the team.</description>
        <reason>Without documented lessons, the next project repeats the same mistakes. Institutional knowledge is the only free input to future project success.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No celebration — team feels unappreciated after sustained effort.</description>
        <reason>Skipping recognition signals that delivery is expected but not valued, the leading cultural factor in team attrition after project completion.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A subagent excels at the closure-administration grind: assemble the closure checklist from project artefacts, generate the deliverable acceptance form pre-filled per item, draft the final report from status reports + change register + EVM, package documents into a structured archive (with a MANIFEST.json), and produce a per-stakeholder closure communication. Humans drive acceptance signoffs, lessons-learned facilitation, and recognition. Run the agent at the end of execution, then again 30 days post-go-live for benefits-tracking handoff.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-pm-agent — owns closure checklist; drafts final report and handover doc. sdd-execution quality gate — verifies acceptance criteria are met against the original specs. improver agent (skill) — facilitates lessons-learned and writes follow-up actions. faion-communicator — drafts per-audience closure communications (sponsor, team, ops).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Run lessons-learned BEFORE the team disperses, not after; resentment fades but so does memory.</item>
        <item>Get acceptance signoff in writing per deliverable — verbal "looks good" never holds up at invoice time.</item>
        <item>Capture both successes and failures; teams that only log failures stop contributing honestly.</item>
        <item>Hand operations a working runbook on day -7, not day 0; let them break it during shadow week.</item>
        <item>Schedule a 30-day and 90-day post-closure review to catch latent defects and benefits drift.</item>
        <item>Celebrate visibly — sponsor email, team lunch, named recognition; budget it before kickoff.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs draft glowing closure reports by default; explicitly require "challenges" and "what failed" sections with cited examples.</item>
        <item>Agent-extracted metrics from inconsistent status reports drift; require source row references for every number.</item>
        <item>Do not let the agent draft acceptance signoffs as if signed; the form must be human-signed (digital signature ok).</item>
        <item>Lessons-learned summaries by LLMs sound generic; have the agent group quotes verbatim before paraphrasing.</item>
        <item>Token budget: closure reports across a multi-month project exceed context — chunk by phase, then synthesize.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoints: (1) acceptance signoffs, (2) ops-team review of handover, (3) sponsor signoff on final report, (4) archival manifest verification.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <reference path="templates/closure-checklist.md">Signed-off checklist covering all seven closure areas.</reference>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/closure-checklist.md" purpose="Signed-off checklist covering acceptance, admin, resource release, knowledge, transition, and communication."/>
      <template path="templates/acceptance-form.md" purpose="Per-deliverable acceptance form with criteria table, outstanding items, and signature block."/>
      <template path="templates/handover-doc.md" purpose="Operations handover template: system overview, docs index, support tiers, known issues, monitoring, scheduled maintenance."/>
      <template path="templates/final-report.md" purpose="Final project report skeleton: executive summary, deliverables, schedule/budget/scope/quality performance, lessons, transition info."/>
      <template path="templates/closeout-archive.sh" purpose="Shell script to bundle project archive with per-category folders and SHA-256 manifest."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="lessons-learned"/>
      <ref slug="change-control"/>
      <ref slug="earned-value-management"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide">PMI PMBOK Guide 7th ed., Delivery Performance Domain — Project Closure.</link>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/69089">ISO 21500:2021 — Guidance on project management.</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
