<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-input-and-visual" title="Multiple Input Modalities and Visual Accessibility in XR">
  <summary>Input modality requirements for spatial interfaces (gaze, voice, head tracking, controller, hand gestures) and visual accessibility patterns for blind and low-vision users.</summary>

  <section title="Multiple Input Modalities">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide all input modalities simultaneously (gaze + voice + controller + hand gesture) — never require users to switch modality mid-task, and never make any single modality the only path to complete an action.</statement>
      <rationale>W3C XAUR requires multiple input alternatives. Gaze requires eye-tracking hardware (Vision Pro yes; Quest 2 no); voice degrades in noisy environments; controller excludes users with limited arm mobility. Only providing all options simultaneously guarantees coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Interaction   | Touch/Controller  | Voice              | Gaze+Dwell
Select object | Tap / trigger     | "Select [name]"    | Look for 1.5s
Move object   | Drag / joystick   | "Move to [loc]"    | Dwell + direction
Open menu     | Button press      | "Show menu"        | Look at menu icon
Cancel        | B button / back   | "Cancel"           | Look away
      ]]></code>
    </example>

    <section title="Gaze Input">
      <list>
        <item>Dwell time: 1-2 seconds; show visual countdown ring on gaze target.</item>
        <item>Confirmation before any irreversible action — cancel by looking away.</item>
        <item>Gaze requires eye-tracking hardware; check platform capability at runtime before enabling.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Voice Control">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every spatial interaction must have a named voice-command alternative; publish a visible command list in-world.</statement>
        <rationale>Voice commands must be discoverable; if users cannot find the command vocabulary, voice is not actually an accessible path. On-device ASR keeps response latency under 500ms — cloud LLM calls violate this threshold.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Voice command response must feel &lt;500ms — use on-device ASR, not cloud LLM round-trip.</item>
        <item>Provide error recovery: "I didn't understand. Say 'Help' to see available commands."</item>
        <item>Test with diverse accents; generated grammars miss accent variants.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Head Tracking">
      <list>
        <item>Nod to confirm, shake to cancel, tilt to scroll — always provide a voice or controller alternative.</item>
        <item>Limit head-tracking interactions: neck strain risk with sustained use.</item>
        <item>Allow sensitivity adjustment in accessibility settings.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Visual Accessibility">
    <section title="Blind Users — Spatial Audio Navigation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Attach directional audio beacons to spatial landmarks (entrance, exit, key interactive objects) with distinct timbres so blind users can navigate by sound.</statement>
        <rationale>Without spatial audio wayfinding, blind users have no equivalent to visual scanning. Distinct timbres per object type allow users to build a mental map of the environment.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Directional audio cues: volume indicates distance, stereo panning indicates direction.</item>
        <item>AI-powered object descriptions: announce objects in view, describe spatial relationships, read text encountered, warn of obstacles.</item>
        <item>Haptic feedback: vibration for object proximity, different patterns for object types.</item>
        <item>Screen reader integration (where platform supports it): announce spatial UI elements, navigate menus with voice.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Low Vision Users">
      <list>
        <item>High contrast mode in 3D space — adjustable contrast for AR/VR overlays.</item>
        <item>Large text in spatial UI — adjustable size and distance from user.</item>
        <item>Color-blind safe palettes for all spatial indicators.</item>
        <item>Edge highlighting for interactive objects.</item>
        <item>Zoom functionality within the XR environment.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>
</text>
