<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-seated-mode-and-comfort" title="Seated Mode, Hearing Accessibility, Cognitive Load, and Comfort Settings">
  <summary>Seated mode implementation for wheelchair users, 3D caption design for deaf users, cognitive load reduction, and comfort/safety settings for motion sensitivity.</summary>

  <section title="Seated Mode">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to seated mode and teleportation-only locomotion; promote standing and smooth locomotion as opt-in settings, not the other way around.</statement>
      <rationale>Wheelchair users, users with limited mobility, and vestibular-sensitive users are excluded by default room-scale and smooth-locomotion experiences. Opt-in seated mode signals they are an afterthought; opt-in standing mode does not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Seated mode adjustments:
  - Lower UI elements to eye level when seated (~1.2m from floor)
  - Closer interaction distances (arm's length from seated position)
  - Reduce vertical range: height -30 to +20 degrees from eye level
  - All controls within horizontal reach zone (+-90 degrees from center)

Locomotion defaults:
  - Teleportation-only (point and click to move)
  - No room-scale movement required
  - No standing up, overhead reaches, or floor interactions
  - Virtual joystick and voice commands as alternatives
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <list>
      <item>Never require room-scale movement, standing, reaching above 1.8m or below 0.5m, or 360-degree rotation.</item>
      <item>Snap-turn default: 30 degrees per step; adjustable from 15 to 90 degrees.</item>
      <item>Seated-mode preset values are platform-specific — do not transfer Vision Pro values directly to Quest 3 or HoloLens.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/xr-scene-audit.py">Python script auditing scene manifest for seated compatibility and other XAUR requirements</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Hearing Accessibility">
    <rule>
      <statement>3D captions must always face the user, include speaker identification, note sound direction (e.g., "[footsteps, behind-left]"), maintain a constant ~1.5m distance, and have a clear background.</statement>
      <rationale>Static caption placement in XR fails as users turn their heads. Caption text that reads "footsteps" without direction information provides no spatial context to deaf users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Captions at constant ~1.5m distance from user, always facing camera (billboard render mode).</item>
      <item>Include: speech content, speaker identification, significant non-speech sounds, directional cues.</item>
      <item>Adjustable caption size and position in user settings.</item>
      <item>Haptic feedback for important sounds: vibration intensity matches volume, patterns distinguish sound types.</item>
      <item>Visual flash indicators for alerts and alarms (non-flicker: max 3 flashes per second).</item>
      <item>Leverage platform captions first: visionOS 2+ Live Captions, Meta Horizon OS Live Captions.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Adding focus highlight animations for accessibility without checking for flicker/strobe risk.</description>
      <reason>More than 3 flashes per second can trigger photosensitive seizures. All animated focus highlights must be checked against the 3-flash threshold.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Cognitive Load and Comfort">
    <list>
      <item>Simplified UI mode: hide non-essential elements on demand.</item>
      <item>Consistent button placement and gesture vocabulary across scenes.</item>
      <item>Tutorial reminders and on-screen hints available on demand.</item>
      <item>No time pressure in any core interaction path.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add vignette during all locomotion and expose a user-adjustable intensity slider; never remove motion sickness mitigations to "improve immersion".</statement>
      <rationale>Vestibular disorders affect ~35% of adults over 40. Smooth locomotion without vignette is a leading cause of simulator sickness that ends XR sessions. Always opt-out, never opt-in for comfort mitigations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Motion sickness: teleportation default; vignette on movement; fixed reference frame available; adjustable movement speed.</item>
      <item>Visual comfort: brightness and contrast adjustment; reduced particle effects option; field-of-view adjustment; disable motion blur.</item>
      <item>Break reminders: suggest break every 20-30 minutes; health and safety warnings on launch; fatigue warnings after sustained use.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
