<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-intervention-playbook" title="Early Intervention Signals and Save Offers">
  <summary>Signal-to-action table for detecting at-risk users before cancellation, re-engagement email structure, and save-offer design at the cancellation flow.</summary>

  <section title="Signal-to-Action Table">
    <list>
      <item>no login 7 days → automated re-engagement email</item>
      <item>no login 14 days → personal email from a named team member</item>
      <item>feature usage &lt;20% of baseline → "did you know?" feature tip email</item>
      <item>negative support ticket → manager follow-up within 24h</item>
      <item>cancel attempt → save offer page</item>
      <item>payment failure → dunning sequence tied to specific decline code</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tier the response by churn reason: price objections get a discount, value objections get a CSM call, feature gaps get a roadmap link — never a flat 50% off for all segments.</statement>
      <rationale>Reason-matched interventions preserve margin and avoid training the entire cohort to use cancellation as a discount lever.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Save Offer Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap save-offer eligibility at once per 12 months per user and track repeat-savers; users who accept a save offer and cancel again within 90 days are negative-LTV.</statement>
      <rationale>Unlimited save offers convert initially then crater NRR as repeat-savers extract discounts without genuine re-engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>price objection → 50% off for 2 months</item>
      <item>time objection → account pause for 30 days</item>
      <item>feature gap → free upgrade to next tier for 1 month</item>
      <item>competitor move → acknowledge and offer a success-call to address the specific gap</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents inventing save offers exceeding 50% discount or extending trials beyond 30 days without hard constraints.</description>
      <reason>LLMs will generate generous offers unless constrained; unconstrained offers destroy unit economics and the agent cannot see margin data.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Dunning Sequences">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tie dunning email copy to the specific Stripe decline code (insufficient_funds vs lost_card vs do_not_honor); generic "update card" loses recoverable involuntary churn.</statement>
      <rationale>Different decline codes have different recovery rates and appropriate CTAs; a "lost card" decline needs a new card link, not a "try again" button.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
