<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-win-back" title="Win-Back Campaign Timing and Structure">
  <summary>Win-back campaign cadence, email structure per timing window, holdout requirement, and success metrics for recovering churned users.</summary>

  <section title="Win-Back Timing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Send win-back campaigns at 30 days and 90 days after churn; skip the 7-day send — at 7 days the user rarely churned for a product reason and the timing feels aggressive.</statement>
      <rationale>30-day win-backs let the product add improvements to highlight; 90-day win-backs address users who may have tried a competitor and found gaps. 7-day win-backs have lower accept rates and higher unsubscribe rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Day 30: "What has changed" — highlight fixes and features added since they left</item>
      <item>Day 90: "Major update" — if significant product change occurred, use a deeper offer</item>
      <item>Day 180+: typically not worth the send unless a major repositioning has occurred</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Email Structure">
    <list>
      <item>reference the specific feature they requested or issue they had (from exit survey or support data)</item>
      <item>list concrete changes made since they left</item>
      <item>offer: 30% off first resubscription month at Day 30, free month at Day 90</item>
      <item>CTA: single button to reactivate, not a link to a pricing page</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never quote customer text or claim the agent "knows" what the user said — feed only structured signals (exit survey category, ticket sentiment score, last feature used) and prohibit quoting free-text the agent has not seen.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs hallucinate "user mentioned X" from structured data; this destroys trust when the customer reads the email.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Holdout and Measurement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a 10% no-treatment holdout on every win-back campaign; without it you cannot distinguish offer-caused reactivation from natural reversion.</statement>
      <rationale>Some churned users reactivate on their own within 90 days; attributing their return to the campaign inflates win-back ROI and causes over-investment in a tactic that may not be driving the return.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>primary metric: reactivation rate (campaign arm vs holdout arm)</item>
      <item>secondary: D30 retention of reactivated users vs organic D30</item>
      <item>cost metric: discount cost per genuinely incremental reactivation</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="GDPR / Suppression">
    <rule>
      <statement>Check suppression-list status before drafting any win-back send; never send to GDPR-deleted users, and read suppression status before drafting, not after.</statement>
      <rationale>Win-backs to suppression-listed users leak PII, violate GDPR right-to-be-forgotten, and trigger ICO/DPC complaints.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
