<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-cash-flow-and-runway" title="Cash Flow Projection and Runway Calculation">
  <summary>3-month and 12-month cash flow tables, runway formula, safety targets by stage, and agent injection requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Cash Flow Projection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build the 12-month forecast bottom-up from known customer count and ARPU — not top-down from desired revenue.</statement>
      <rationale>Top-down forecasts start from a wish number and work backward. Bottom-up forecasts start from real customer data and produce grounded projections that identify actual growth gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always inject real numbers as context before asking the agent to build projections. Agents will hallucinate specific financial figures if not given actual data.</statement>
      <rationale>Financial hallucinations in projections are silent failures — the output looks plausible but is based on fabricated inputs. Real data must be provided explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Agent prompt: "MRR = $8,500, monthly expenses = $4,200, cash balance = $22,000. Build a 3-month cash flow table. Flag if runway drops below 3 months." This gives the agent real numbers to work with.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Runway Formula">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Runway (months) = Cash on hand / Monthly burn rate. Minimum safe runway by stage: pre-revenue = 12+ months, early revenue = 6+ months, growing = 3+ months, profitable = 3+ months (emergency fund).</statement>
      <rationale>Runway is the primary financial safety metric. Below 3 months, a single bad month becomes an existential threat. The emergency fund (3x monthly expenses, separate account) is the profitable-stage equivalent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/stripe-runway.py">Pull MRR from Stripe API and calculate runway with warning at 3-month threshold</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Scenario Planning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run two scenarios each quarter: base case (flat growth) and stress case (20% revenue drop). Stress case sets minimum acceptable runway and spend floor.</statement>
      <rationale>A base-case-only plan has no resilience mechanism. The stress case forces identification of which expenses are cuttable and which are fixed, before the crisis occurs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track CAC and LTV monthly alongside P&amp;L. A healthy margin with deteriorating LTV:CAC ratio signals future cash flow risk even when current numbers look good.</statement>
      <rationale>LTV:CAC deterioration predicts future revenue decline before it appears in the P&amp;L. Catching it early allows course correction.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
