<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="User Interview Process and Question Design">
  <summary>Interview types, recruitment criteria, question design principles, and synthesis techniques.</summary>

  <section title="Interview Types">
    <p>
      Exploratory (45-60 min) — understand the problem space and user needs.
      Generative (30-45 min) — generate ideas about possible solutions.
      Evaluative (30-45 min) — test concepts or early-stage designs.
      Contextual (60-90 min) — observe users in their actual environment.
    </p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Write research questions (what you need to learn) before writing interview questions (what you will ask).</statement>
      <rationale>Starting with interview questions produces survey-like guides; starting with research objectives produces guides that follow the user's answers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Recruitment Criteria">
    <p>5-8 participants per distinct user segment is the practical threshold for theme saturation. Recruit from: customer database, user panels, social media, professional recruiters. Mix demographics; include both current users and prospects.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Question Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use open-ended questions that ask about past behavior, not hypothetical future behavior.</statement>
      <rationale>Hypothetical questions ("would you use...") produce aspirational answers, not behavioral evidence. Past behavior predicts actual usage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>"Tell me about the last time you [did X]." — anchors to a specific real experience with retrievable detail.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"Would you use a feature that does Y?" — hypothetical; users say yes to be helpful, not because they would actually use it.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>"Walk me through your typical process for [task]." — generates behavioral context the designer can act on.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"Don't you think the app is too complicated?" — leading; suggests the answer and biases the response.</note>
    </example>
    <p>Probing follow-ups: "Why do you think that happened?", "Can you give me a specific example?", "Tell me more about that."</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Synthesis Techniques">
    <p>Affinity mapping: write each observation on a separate note, group similar notes, name each group, identify patterns across groups.</p>
    <p>Insight statement format: "[User type] needs [need] because [motivation/reason]. Currently, [pain point/gap]."</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate "what users said" from "what we infer" in every insight statement.</statement>
      <rationale>Collapsing observation and inference produces insights that sound like research findings but are actually interpretations; stakeholders cannot challenge what they cannot see the evidence for.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/interview-guide.md">Full interview guide template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/session-notes.md">Per-session observation notes template</reference>
</text>
