<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="User Interview Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Neutrality principles, facilitation rules, synthesis quality requirements, and agent limitations.</summary>

  <section title="Facilitation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Listen more than talk; the interviewer's words should be fewer than 20% of the session transcript.</statement>
      <rationale>Talking more than the participant signals that the interviewer is not genuinely curious, closing down disclosure and producing thin data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not react positively or negatively to answers; stay neutral throughout.</statement>
      <rationale>Positive reactions (nodding, "great!") bias subsequent answers toward what the interviewer appeared to reward; neutrality preserves honest disclosure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Record sessions (with consent) even when taking notes.</statement>
      <rationale>Notes miss quote-level detail; transcripts enable the evidence-backed synthesis that makes findings credible to stakeholders.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Synthesis Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always provide verbatim source material when asking the agent to "find examples" or extract quotes.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent will hallucinate plausible-sounding quotes if not given actual transcript text; synthesis must be grounded in provided source.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Insight statements synthesized by agent must be validated against source notes by the researcher before sharing with stakeholders.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent may introduce framing bias when rewriting observations into insights; researcher validation is the quality gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Sanitize transcripts (replace participant names with IDs) before passing to external LLM APIs.</statement>
      <rationale>Interview transcripts often contain PII; participant privacy must be protected under applicable regulations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Poor recruitment — interviewing participants who do not match the target user profile.</description>
      <reason>Insights from the wrong users produce design decisions that serve a population that does not exist or will not use the product.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Not probing — accepting surface-level answers without follow-up.</description>
      <reason>First answers are often rehearsed or socially acceptable; the real insight lives in the follow-up ("why is that?", "can you give me an example?").</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No analysis — collecting data without synthesizing it into insights and sharing with the team.</description>
      <reason>Unanalyzed interview data has zero design impact; synthesis is not optional.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/transcribe-sessions.sh">Batch-transcribe recordings with OpenAI Whisper</reference>
</text>
