<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="user-interviews Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for user-interviews as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Poor recruitment — interviewing participants who do not match the target user profile.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Insights from the wrong users produce design decisions that serve a population that does not exist or will not use the product.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Not probing — accepting surface-level answers without follow-up.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>First answers are often rehearsed or socially acceptable; the real insight lives in the follow-up ("why is that?", "can you give me an example?").</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>No analysis — collecting data without synthesizing it into insights and sharing with the team.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unanalyzed interview data has zero design impact; synthesis is not optional.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Using agent-generated interview guides without neutrality review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent-generated guides tend toward closed or mildly leading questions when product context is provided. Require explicit review for question neutrality before use.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Expecting agents to conduct interviews themselves.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent cannot replicate a human facilitator's rapport, body language reading, or real-time probing judgment. Interviews must be human-facilitated.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Relying on agent synthesis without validation against source notes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Human-in-loop checkpoint: insight statements must be validated against source notes by the researcher before being shared with stakeholders or used for design decisions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Asking agent to "find examples" without providing verbatim transcript text.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent may hallucinate quotes if asked to "find examples" without being given the actual transcript text. Always provide verbatim source material.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Passing unredacted transcripts to external LLM APIs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Privacy: interview transcripts often contain PII. Ensure transcripts are sanitized (participant names replaced with IDs) before passing to external LLM APIs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
