<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-webinar-delivery">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>content-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Webinar execution: engagement tactics (polls, energy, camera), time-limited offer during Q&amp;A, 5-email follow-up sequence. Repurpose recording into 10+ assets.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>webinar</tag>
      <tag>delivery</tag>
      <tag>engagement</tag>
      <tag>conversion</tag>
      <tag>email-followup</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>growth</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Webinar Delivery and Follow-up</title>

    <summary>The execution half of webinars: deliver an engaging live session (polls every 10 minutes, energy higher than normal, camera-at-eye level), convert attendees via a time-limited offer during Q&amp;A, then run a 5-email follow-up sequence over 5 days. Repurpose the recording into 10+ assets (blog post, YouTube, podcast, social clips, quote graphics).</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Most webinars convert below 3% because hosts treat them as one-way presentations and send a single "replay available" email. The mechanism: live engagement tactics (polls, exercises) hold attention and create reciprocity; a scarcity-framed offer during Q&amp;A converts while intent is highest; the 5-email sequence converts late-deciders who need one more nudge; repurposing multiplies the content ROI 10x from a single production effort.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Running a live educational webinar with a product offer at the end.</item>
        <item>Post-webinar follow-up sequence is not set up or is a single email.</item>
        <item>Webinar recordings are sitting unused — need a repurposing workflow.</item>
        <item>Show-up rate is above 30% but conversion is below 5%.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Webinar is not recorded — repurposing workflow requires recording.</item>
        <item>Product offer is not ready — do not run a conversion sequence without a concrete offer and deadline.</item>
        <item>Audience is too small (fewer than 20 registrants) — low absolute conversion numbers make optimization difficult.</item>
        <item>Demo/product webinar for enterprise sales — different format (discovery + qualification), not conversion webinar.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="live-delivery-tactics">
      <p>Pre-go-live technical checklist; engagement techniques timed across the session; presentation energy and camera rules; CTA delivery script structure.</p>

      <section name="pre-go-live-checklist">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Test audio, video, screenshare, and backup plan 30 minutes before going live. Close all notifications and non-essential apps. Have a co-host who can take over if technical issues occur.</statement>
          <rationale>Technical issues in the first 5 minutes lose 20–30% of attendees permanently. Recovery from a bad start is impossible; prevention is the only strategy.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="engagement-techniques-by-timing">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Trigger engagement touchpoints at: start (poll about audience situation), every 10 minutes (question to audience), midpoint (interactive exercise), end (final poll or survey). Never go more than 10 minutes without audience interaction.</statement>
          <rationale>Passive audiences disengage within 7–10 minutes. Each interaction resets attention and generates reciprocity. Polls also provide data that can be referenced throughout the session, making the content feel personalized to the room.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="presentation-delivery-rules">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Deliver energy 30% higher than feels natural. Look directly at the camera lens, not the screen. Stand if possible. The camera flattens expression — what feels like normal energy looks flat on screen.</statement>
          <rationale>Video compression and the screen medium reduce perceived energy by approximately 30%. A presenter who feels "energetic" appears "neutral" on camera. Forced overcorrection reads as natural.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="cta-delivery-script">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Deliver the offer during Q&amp;A, not before. Frame with: audience qualifier, offer description, deadline, objection handling, explicit next step.</statement>
          <rationale>Delivering the CTA too early (before value is established) signals the webinar was just a sales pitch. During Q&amp;A, trust and interest are at peak. The explicit next step must be a single click, not a multi-step hunt through the website.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <example type="good" title="CTA script structure for webinar-only offer">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"For those of you who want to [desired outcome]..."
[Show offer slide: what they get, price, deadline]
"This offer is only available until [specific date and time]."
"If you're on the fence, [handle one main objection]."
"Click the link in the chat to [exact action]."
          ]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="post-webinar-follow-up">
      <p>5-email follow-up structure with timing and subject purpose; conversion metrics benchmarks; common delivery and follow-up mistakes.</p>

      <section name="five-email-sequence-structure">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Send 5 emails over 5 days: immediate (replay + offer), Day 1 (key takeaways + offer), Day 2 (case study + testimonial), Day 3 (FAQ + deadline reminder), Day 5 (deadline extension if used). Each email must carry the offer with a deadline.</statement>
          <rationale>Most conversions happen on Day 1–3 but a meaningful portion (15–25%) come from Day 3–5 when urgency of the deadline becomes real. A single "replay available" email leaves this conversion window unused.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <reference path="templates/follow-up-email-1.txt">Immediate email: replay link, slides, offer CTA.</reference>
        <reference path="templates/follow-up-email-2.txt">Day 1 email: key takeaways, bonus resources, offer.</reference>
        <reference path="templates/follow-up-email-3.txt">Day 2 email: case study, testimonial, deadline.</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="metrics-benchmarks">
        <list>
          <item>Show-up rate: good 40%, great 60%+. Below 30% means registration-to-event delay is too long or reminder sequence is weak.</item>
          <item>Watch time: good 60% of duration, great 80%+. Below 50% means delivery is losing audience — audit first 15 minutes.</item>
          <item>Conversion (attendees to buyers): good 5%, great 15%+. Below 2% means offer mismatch or weak CTA delivery.</item>
          <item>Email open rate (follow-up sequence): good 30%, great 50%+.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="common-delivery-mistakes">
        <antipattern>
          <description>Spending more than 20% of the webinar on the pitch or offer presentation.</description>
          <reason>Audiences register for the educational content. Sensing a bait-and-switch causes early dropoff. The 80/20 rule (80% value, 20% pitch) is the maximum promotional tolerance for a live audience.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Sending only a "replay available" email and no follow-up sequence.</description>
          <reason>Single-email post-webinar follow-up typically converts 1–2% of attendees. The 5-email sequence converts 5–15% by serving different buyer readiness stages on different days.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>No deadline on the offer.</description>
          <reason>Without urgency, "I'll think about it" means "never". A concrete deadline (72 hours, specific date) converts fence-sitters by making inaction costly.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="webinar-content-repurposing">
      <p>10-asset repurposing workflow from a single 60-minute recording; tools for each step; sequencing to maximize output efficiency.</p>

      <section name="repurposing-principle">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Repurpose every webinar into at least 5 assets before publishing or discarding the recording. A 60-minute webinar contains enough raw material for 10+ distinct content pieces.</statement>
          <rationale>A single live webinar production effort (preparation, promotion, delivery) costs significant time. Without repurposing, 90% of the production value is consumed once and discarded. Each repurposed asset reaches a different audience segment or platform.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="ten-asset-workflow">
        <list>
          <item>Transcribe — use Otter.ai or Descript. This unlocks all text-based repurposing.</item>
          <item>Blog post — edit the transcript of the best 15-minute section into a standalone article. Add images.</item>
          <item>YouTube video — upload full recording with chapter timestamps. Title as a search query (not webinar name).</item>
          <item>Podcast episode — export audio-only version. Add intro/outro. Submit to podcast hosting.</item>
          <item>Social clips — cut 3–5 highlight clips of 60–90 seconds for LinkedIn, Instagram, Twitter.</item>
          <item>Infographic — visual summary of the 5 key takeaways. Use Canva.</item>
          <item>Email series — each key point becomes one email in a nurture sequence.</item>
          <item>Slide deck — share slides on SlideShare with alt text for each slide.</item>
          <item>Quote graphics — extract 3–5 memorable quotes as image posts for social.</item>
          <item>LinkedIn article — expanded version of a specific section, tailored for professional audience.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="sequencing">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Transcribe first (Day 0), extract clips (Day 1), create blog post and YouTube upload (Day 2–3), release remaining assets spread over 2–4 weeks.</statement>
          <rationale>Spreading repurposed assets over weeks creates a content drip from a single production event. Releasing everything at once dilutes distribution attention and looks like spam to followers.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Most conversions happen on Day 1–3 but a meaningful portion (15–25%) come from Day 3–5 when urgency of the deadline becomes real.</item>
        <item>The 80/20 rule (80% value, 20% pitch) is the maximum promotional tolerance for a live audience.</item>
        <item>Single-email post-webinar follow-up typically converts 1–2% of attendees while the 5-email sequence converts 5–15%.</item>
        <item>A concrete deadline (72 hours, specific date) converts fence-sitters by making inaction costly.</item>
        <item>A 60-minute webinar production effort, without repurposing, has 90% of the production value consumed once and discarded.</item>
        <item>Spreading repurposed assets over weeks creates a content drip from a single production event.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/follow-up-email-1.txt" purpose="Immediate post-webinar email: replay link, slides, offer CTA"/>
      <template path="templates/follow-up-email-2.txt" purpose="Day 1 email: key takeaways, bonus resources, offer reminder"/>
      <template path="templates/follow-up-email-3.txt" purpose="Day 2 email: case study + testimonial, deadline reminder"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="growth-webinar-planning"/>
      <ref slug="growth-email-marketing"/>
      <ref slug="growth-content-marketing"/>
      <link href="https://descript.com">Descript — transcription + clip extraction</link>
      <link href="https://otter.ai">Otter.ai — transcription service</link>
      <link href="https://www.youtube.com">YouTube — video hosting and distribution</link>
      <link href="https://www.linkedin.com">LinkedIn — professional content platform</link>
      <link href="https://www.canva.com">Canva — design tool for infographics</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
