<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-semantic-layer" title="Semantic Token Layer and Mode Structure">
  <summary>Three-tier naming, mode matrix structure, alias rules, and contrast pair co-location requirement for token systems that support theming.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Tier Naming">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use three tiers exactly — primitive, semantic, component — and ensure component tokens reference semantic tokens, never primitives.</statement>
      <rationale>Component-to-primitive coupling means every primitive rename requires touching component definitions; the semantic layer is the decoupling boundary.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Primitive: `color.blue.500 = #3B82F6` — raw value, no design intent.</item>
      <item>Semantic: `color.action.primary → {color.blue.500}` — purpose-based alias.</item>
      <item>Component: `button.primary.bg → {color.action.primary}` — exception only, must have `$description`.</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Semantic alias with mode values in Figma Variables format</note>
      <code lang="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "collections": {
    "Colors": {
      "modes": ["Light", "Dark"],
      "aliases": {
        "color.surface.primary": {
          "values": {
            "Light": "#FFFFFF",
            "Dark": "#1A1A1A"
          }
        },
        "color.text.primary": {
          "values": {
            "Light": "#1A1A1A",
            "Dark": "#FFFFFF"
          }
        }
      }
    }
  }
}
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Mode Matrix Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every alias must have a value in every declared mode; missing values cause silent fallbacks that ship wrong colors.</statement>
      <rationale>A mode with a missing alias resolves to undefined behavior; different platforms handle undefined differently, making the regression unpredictable and hard to reproduce.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Reserve one mode per axis as the explicit default; document inheritance rules so consumers of unset modes fall back deterministically.</statement>
      <rationale>Implicit inheritance from an undocumented default causes surprise regressions when the default mode is renamed or reordered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Bound mode combinations by design decision, not by combinatorial exhaustion; mode explosion (4 color × 3 density × 5 brands = 60 configs) kills maintainability.</statement>
      <rationale>Each supported configuration requires validation; unchecked mode growth creates an exponential testing burden that makes additions prohibitively expensive.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Contrast Pair Co-location">
    <rule>
      <statement>Co-locate contrast partner pairs in the token spec (e.g., `text.on-surface-primary` declares its surface partner); validation requires both halves.</statement>
      <rationale>WCAG contrast must be verified as a pair, not per token; without co-location the validator cannot determine which text color applies to which surface color in each mode.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate runtime CSS custom properties at build time, not at app boot; boot-time JS theming causes flicker and hurts Core Web Vitals.</statement>
      <rationale>CSS custom properties set at boot add a render-blocking JS execution step before first paint; build-time generation eliminates this entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Per-platform deltas (iOS 14px button padding) expressed as inline overrides on a shared token (`"ios": "14px"`).</description>
      <reason>Inline platform overrides are invisible to designers in Figma and to linters; use separate platform-prefixed tokens instead.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
