<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="semantic-tokens-and-modes Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for semantic-tokens-and-modes as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Per-platform deltas (iOS 14px button padding) expressed as inline overrides on a shared token (`"ios": "14px"`)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Inline platform overrides are invisible to designers in Figma and to linters; use separate platform-prefixed tokens instead.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM invents token names from a closed enumeration without pinning to the manifest.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin the agent to a closed enumeration loaded from the project manifest; reject outputs with identifiers not present in the manifest.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Color math regressions are silent: agent emits `oklch()` values that look fine but fail contrast in dark mode.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always run the mode-validator post-generation; visual inspection is insufficient for contrast in wide-gamut color spaces.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Figma Variables REST API uses `tempId` for newly-created variables; agent reuses a stale ID in a dependent operation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Capture and reuse `tempId` values within the same API call batch; stale IDs create dangling references that are silent until the file is reloaded.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent reorders Style Dictionary transforms while "cleaning up" the config.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Style Dictionary transforms run in declared order; reordering silently changes platform output. Lock the order in the agent's tooling spec.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent auto-promotes primitives to semantic layer without human review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Semantic naming is the one step that adds real human meaning; an auto-promoted name like `color.blue-500-alias` is worse than no semantic layer.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
