<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-gke-cloudrun" title="GKE and Cloud Run Best Practices">
  <summary>GKE Autopilot vs Standard decision, node pool patterns, Cloud Run configuration, and Spot VM usage.</summary>

  <section title="GKE Mode Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use GKE Autopilot for new workloads unless they require GPU, privileged containers, custom node configs, or Windows nodes — Autopilot covers 80%+ of use cases with less operational overhead.</statement>
      <rationale>Autopilot manages node provisioning, OS patching, and kubelet config. Standard mode requires manual node pool sizing, OS upgrades, and kubelet tuning. The operational difference is 20-40 hours/month for a team managing Standard clusters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Autopilot: pay-per-pod resources, automatic node provisioning, no OS patching, no node pool management</item>
      <item>Standard: GPU workloads, privileged containers, custom machine types, Windows containers</item>
      <item>Hybrid (2025): Standard cluster with Autopilot workload profiles — for teams migrating</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Cost Optimization with Spot VMs">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Spot VMs for batch jobs, CI/CD runners, and non-critical background workers — they save 60-91% over on-demand with the only trade-off being preemption.</statement>
      <rationale>Spot VMs are reclaimed by GCP with a 30-second notice when capacity is needed. This is acceptable for stateless batch workloads that can be retried. The cost savings make CI/CD on GKE economically viable vs managed CI services.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# Node pool for batch/CI workloads
node_pools:
  - name: spot-batch
    machine_type: n2-standard-8
    spot: true
    taints:
      - key: workload
        value: batch
        effect: NoSchedule
    autoscaling:
      min_node_count: 0
      max_node_count: 20
]]></code>
      <note>Use tolerations in batch job pods to schedule onto spot nodes. Non-batch pods without the toleration automatically land on on-demand nodes.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Cloud Run Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set min-instances to 0 for cost-sensitive services and to 1+ for latency-sensitive services — cold starts on Cloud Run take 200ms-2s depending on image size.</statement>
      <rationale>min-instances=0 means the service sleeps when idle, saving cost but adding cold start latency on first request. min-instances=1 keeps one warm instance, adding ~$5-20/month but eliminating cold starts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set concurrency to 80-100 for typical web apps; lower (1-10) for CPU-intensive or stateful per-request work.</statement>
      <rationale>Cloud Run bills per-CPU-second. High concurrency means fewer instances needed for the same throughput. But CPU-bound or stateful workloads need isolation per request or they contend for CPU within the instance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Blue-green deploy with gradual traffic shift
gcloud run deploy my-service \
  --image=gcr.io/project/app:v2 \
  --no-traffic \
  --tag=green

# Validate green tag directly
curl https://green---my-service-xxx.run.app/healthz

# Gradual rollout: 10% to new version
gcloud run services update-traffic my-service \
  --to-tags=green=10,latest=90

# Full cutover
gcloud run services update-traffic my-service \
  --to-latest
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
