<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="vui-market-context Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for vui-market-context as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs hallucinate market numbers fluently and confidently; agents cite stats without checking sources.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Knowledge cutoff bias drives agents to cite 2023-2024 stats. Always require grounding in fetched sources with dates.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Aggregator sites (Statista, eMarketer) quote each other in loops; agents cite secondary sources without tracing to primary surveys.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Secondary citations are unreliable chains. Trace to the primary survey (e.g., Edison Research, Statista's underlying methodology) before citing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents extrapolate trends ("at this rate, 100% by 2030") and include extrapolations in decks without flagging them as speculative.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Trend extrapolation is a classic red flag. Remove it or mark clearly as speculation, not data.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent-generated numbers enter investor decks or contracts without human researcher review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Numbers drive high-stakes decisions. Agent output without human review is a liability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating Siri and Bixby as "developer-accessible" platforms when in reality access is heavily gated and shrinking.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The platform table must reflect current developer reality, not past accessibility. Siri and Bixby are nearly closed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
