<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="modern-ba-framework">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-core</domain>
    <summary>Select one primary BA reference framework (BABOK v3, BA Standard 2025, IREB CPRE, PMI-PBA, BCS Diploma, SAFe BA, Agile Extension to BABOK v2, SWEBOK v4) for an engagement before producing any artifact. Score candidates on regulatory fit, team maturity, vocabulary overlap, tooling support, and agile friendliness. Persist the decision as ba-framework-decision.md with a vocabulary glossary.</summary>
    <category>framework</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>ba-framework</tag>
      <tag>babok</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>selection</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Modern BA Framework</title>

    <summary>Select one primary BA reference framework (BABOK v3, BA Standard 2025, IREB CPRE, PMI-PBA, BCS Diploma, SAFe BA, Agile Extension to BABOK v2, SWEBOK v4) for an engagement before producing any artifact. Score candidates on regulatory fit, team maturity, vocabulary overlap, tooling support, and agile friendliness. Persist the decision as ba-framework-decision.md with a vocabulary glossary. This selection is upstream of all routing decisions — pick the rulebook before picking the plays.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>LLMs default to BABOK because it is the most tokenized BA reference in training data. Without a structured selection step, non-IIBA shops (IREB, PMI, BCS) never get the appropriate framework, terminology skew accumulates across artifacts, and regulated programs fail audit because deliverable vocabulary does not match the contracted standard.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Onboarding a BA or agent into an unfamiliar org where the "BA standard" is unclear or contested</item>
        <item>Procurement or RFP responses naming a specific standard — deliverable vocabulary must match exactly</item>
        <item>Regulated industries (pharma GxP, banking BCBS 239, automotive ASPICE) where requirements artifacts are auditable</item>
        <item>Multi-vendor programs where each vendor uses a different BA dialect — normalize to one canonical vocabulary</item>
        <item>Hybrid agile/waterfall portfolios requiring a documented bridge between BABOK and Scrum/SAFe ceremonies</item>
        <item>Building an internal BA competency matrix or training curriculum anchored to a published syllabus</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Team already has a working BA practice with a known reference — re-selection is rework theatre</item>
        <item>Solo founder or 1-2 person product — continuous discovery + plain user stories beats any framework overhead</item>
        <item>Pure UX or growth work — use ux-researcher and conversion-optimizer methodologies</item>
        <item>One-shot tactical analysis (single ticket clarification) — overhead not justified</item>
        <item>Org explicitly anti-IIBA — pick Agile Extension or skip to product-discovery methodologies</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="candidate-frameworks">
      <rule>
        <statement>Maintain awareness of eight candidate BA reference frameworks: BABOK v3 (IIBA, 2015), BA Standard 2025 (IIBA), IREB CPRE (Foundation + Advanced), PMI-PBA / Business Analysis for Practitioners, BCS Diploma in Business Analysis, SAFe Business Analyst, Agile Extension to BABOK v2 (IIBA), and SWEBOK v4 KA: Software Requirements (IEEE).</statement>
        <rationale>Each framework has distinct strengths: BABOK is most comprehensive with 6 knowledge areas and dominates regulated/enterprise contexts; BA Standard 2025 modernizes BABOK with agile/hybrid/transformational org context; IREB CPRE is engineering-grade and strong in automotive (ASPICE), aerospace, medical; PMI-PBA bridges doc/waterfall with PMBOK alignment; BCS is practitioner-focused, common in UK public sector; SAFe maps BA competencies to SAFe roles for scaled agile; Agile Extension bridges BABOK KAs to Scrum/SAFe ceremonies; SWEBOK is engineering-centric for software-only programs.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>BABOK v3 (IIBA, 2015) — most comprehensive; 6 knowledge areas; dominant in regulated and enterprise contexts; ECBA/CCBA/CBAP certs</item>
        <item>BA Standard 2025 (IIBA) — modernizes BABOK v3 with agile, hybrid, and transformational org context; SFIA v9 integration; replaces some BABOK guidance</item>
        <item>IREB CPRE (Foundation + Advanced) — engineering-grade requirements; strong in automotive (ASPICE), aerospace, medical; CPRE-FL/AL certs</item>
        <item>PMI-PBA / Business Analysis for Practitioners — bridging doc/waterfall; PMBOK-aligned; PMI-PBA cert</item>
        <item>BCS Diploma in Business Analysis — practitioner-focused; common in UK public sector; certificate ladder</item>
        <item>SAFe Business Analyst — maps BA competencies to SAFe roles; best for scaled agile (LeSS, PI planning); not audit-grade</item>
        <item>Agile Extension to BABOK v2 (IIBA) — bridge from BABOK KAs to Scrum/SAFe ceremonies; pairs with BABOK v3</item>
        <item>SWEBOK v4 KA: Software Requirements (IEEE) — engineering-centric; most useful for software-only programs; no certs</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="selection-scoring-criteria">
      <rule>
        <statement>Score each candidate on six dimensions before selecting: regulatory_fit, team_maturity_fit, vocabulary_overlap_with_existing, tooling_support, certification_availability, agile_friendliness. Let regulatory_fit veto agile-friendly choices in regulated settings.</statement>
        <rationale>Without structured scoring, LLMs default to BABOK regardless of context; explicit scoring surfaces IREB in automotive and PMI-PBA in hybrid-portfolio orgs.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Pick ONE primary framework and at most two extension frameworks. Two co-equal primaries always produce vocabulary thrash and audit ambiguity.</statement>
        <rationale>Common failure: BABOK v3 + Agile Extension treated as equal primaries; extensions supplement, they do not co-govern.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Cache PDFs of BABOK v3, BA Standard 2025, IREB CPRE-FL/AL, and PMI-PBA as a local fact-source; require the agent to cite from the cache, not from training data.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents confabulate clause numbers, KA boundaries, and version dates; a pinned cache is the only defense.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="framework-table-limitations">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating the "Modern Application" tables as procedures.</description>
        <reason>The tables are descriptive (e.g., "AI/ML literacy" under Analytical Thinking); they have no inputs, outputs, or acceptance tests. Agents that treat them as instructions produce hand-wavy plans.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using certification tier (ECBA, CCBA, CBAP) as a capability proxy.</description>
        <reason>Certs measure exam pass rate, not analyst quality with LLM tools, RAG, or evals; treat the cert ladder as procurement signaling, not skill assurance.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Applying SAFe BA framework in regulated industries (pharma, automotive, aerospace).</description>
        <reason>SAFe BA is not audit-grade; ASPICE, IEC 62304, DO-178C auditors require IREB or BABOK-aligned artifact vocabulary.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="vocabulary-glossary-requirement">
      <rule>
        <statement>Before producing any artifact, build a vocabulary glossary mapping chosen-framework terms to org existing terms and to sibling methodology slugs; persist as glossary.md next to ba-framework-decision.md.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a shared glossary, downstream artifacts in different hands redefine terms silently, breaking traceability across the program.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="selector-prompt-pattern">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a selector subagent with structured candidate scoring before selecting a framework; inputs include industry, regulation_set[], team_size, delivery_model, contract_clauses[], existing_standards[], stakeholder_count, and audit_required (bool).</statement>
        <rationale>Explicit scoring prevents LLM default-to-BABOK bias and forces consideration of IREB, PMI-PBA, BCS alternatives based on context.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Framework selector prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Inputs: industry, regulation_set[], team_size, delivery_model,
        contract_clauses[], existing_standards[],
        stakeholder_count, audit_required (bool).
Candidates: BABOK_v3, BA_Standard_2025, IREB_CPRE, PMI_PBA,
            BCS_Diploma, SAFe_BA, Agile_Extension_BABOK_v2, SWEBOK_v4_Reqs.
Score each on: regulatory_fit, team_maturity_fit, vocab_overlap_with_existing,
               tooling_support, certification_availability, agile_friendliness.
Pick ONE primary + up to 2 extensions.
Produce vocabulary glossary (BA term -> chosen-framework term -> methodology slug).
Emit ba-framework-decision.md. Halt for human sign-off.
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="audit-prompt-pattern">
      <example type="good" title="Post-delivery conformance audit prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Inputs: ba-framework-decision.md, list of produced artifacts in .aidocs/<feature>/.
For each mandatory deliverable in chosen framework, check presence + quality.
Emit framework-conformance.md with PASS/FAIL per artifact and remediation.
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>faion-brainstorm — divergence pass across all 8 candidate frameworks before converging; forces the agent off its default-BABOK prior</item>
        <item>faion-feature-executor — after selection, executes routing planner using chosen framework vocabulary as context on every step</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — wraps BA artifacts inside SDD spec.md / design.md / test-plan.md so the framework choice survives into delivery</item>
        <item>faion-improver — periodic audit comparing produced artifacts vs chosen framework required deliverables; flags drift</item>
        <item>General Task subagent — one per candidate framework, summarizes mandatory artifacts and audit hooks for the selector converge step</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM defaults to BABOK because it dominates training data.</description>
        <reason>Force structured candidate scoring on all 8 frameworks; without it, IREB, PMI-PBA, and BCS are never selected regardless of context fit.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent confabulates clause numbers, KA boundaries, and IIBA version dates.</description>
        <reason>Pin a local fact-source (cached BABOK ToC + IREB CPRE syllabi) and require citations to it; reject any structural claim not present in the cached files.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent auto-proceeds from selection to routing without a human checkpoint.</description>
        <reason>The human-in-the-loop checkpoint between selection and routing is the only place a real BA can correct the framework bias introduced by training data; auto-execution removes this control.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Certification recommendations are IIBA-only, creating vendor bias.</description>
        <reason>Cross-reference IREB, PMI-PBA, BCS, and Scrum.org product-owner tracks before presenting to the user; single-vendor cert lists mislead procurement.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent edits the framework README tables to "modernize" them on each run.</description>
        <reason>Confine edits to agent-integration.md and .aidocs/&lt;feature&gt;/; churning git history on the README tables destroys stable reference content.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="mandatory-human-checkpoints">
      <list>
        <item>Between selection and routing — human BA or PO corrects framework bias before any artifact is produced</item>
        <item>At vocabulary glossary sign-off — confirms terms align with org language before downstream artifacts use them</item>
        <item>Re-run trigger: regulation set change, contract change, primary delivery model change, or M&amp;A integration</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ba-framework-select.sh" purpose="Scaffold a ba-framework-decision.json for a feature with all scoring fields"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/standards-and-resources/babok/"/>
      <link href="https://www.ireb.org/en/downloads"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards"/>
      <link href="https://www.bcs.org/qualifications-and-certifications/certifications-for-business/business-analysis/"/>
      <link href="https://www.computer.org/education/bodies-of-knowledge/software-engineering"/>
      <link href="https://scaledagileframework.com"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
