<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="release-planning">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Six-step process for deciding what goes into each release, when it ships, and how it is communicated. Covers release types, readiness checklists, rollback requirements, and communication plans.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>release-planning</tag>
      <tag>release-management</tag>
      <tag>versioning</tag>
      <tag>rollback</tag>
      <tag>release-notes</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Release Planning</title>
    <summary>A six-step process for deciding what goes into each release, when it ships, and how it is communicated. Covers release-type taxonomy (major/minor/patch/hotfix), readiness checklists, rollback requirements, and audience-specific communication plans. The concrete rule: every release needs a goal statement, a rollback plan, and a communication plan before code touches production.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Releases without structure are chaotic, missed, or anticlimactic — features are ready but not shipped, or shipped without communication, or broken in production with no rollback path. A structured approach prevents the three most common failure modes: scope creep into a release, skipping staging, and going dark to customers.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Planning what to include in an upcoming version (major, minor, patch, or hotfix).</item>
        <item>Coordinating release timing across engineering, support, and marketing.</item>
        <item>Writing release notes for an existing set of changes.</item>
        <item>Setting up a repeatable release cadence for a solo or small-team product.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Continuous deployment with feature flags — individual flag decisions replace release bundling.</item>
        <item>Pre-launch, pre-user products — no communication audience yet, use task lists instead.</item>
        <item>Emergency hotfixes under time pressure — use the hotfix checklist only, not the full plan.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="release-types">
      <p>Major releases are quarterly, cover large features and breaking changes, and carry high risk. Minor releases are monthly, add new features and improvements, and carry medium risk. Patch releases are weekly or as needed, fix bugs and security issues, and carry low risk. Hotfixes are immediate, address critical production issues, and carry very low risk.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="step-1-define-release-goal">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every release must have a stated outcome for users, a success metric, and an optional theme. Template: "Release [Version]. Goal: [Primary outcome]. Success Metric: [How we measure]. Theme: [Optional narrative]."</statement>
        <rationale>Without a goal, a release is just a list of changes. The goal connects the release to product strategy and makes post-release retrospectives meaningful.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-2-select-release-contents">
      <rule>
        <statement>Include: completed features at definition of done, related bug fixes, documentation updates, configuration changes. Exclude: half-finished features, unrelated bug fixes (next release), scope creep added after freeze.</statement>
        <rationale>Half-finished features create technical debt and confuse users. Scope creep added after freeze is the top cause of delayed and broken releases.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-3-assess-release-readiness">
      <rule>
        <statement>All seven readiness items must pass before deployment: code complete, tests passing, documentation updated, migrations tested, rollback plan exists, support team briefed, release notes written.</statement>
        <rationale>Missing any one item creates a predictable class of post-release incidents. Rollback plan especially: without it, every incident response starts with a debate instead of an action.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-4-plan-communication">
      <rule>
        <statement>Identify all audiences (internal team, support, sales, customers, partners) and prepare each asset: release notes, blog post or changelog, customer email, social media, in-app notifications. Announce every release — even small patches.</statement>
        <rationale>Silent releases frustrate customers who noticed a change and can't find context. Support volume spikes when communication is missing.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-5-execute-release">
      <rule>
        <statement>Execute in order: final staging test, maintenance window announcement if needed, production deploy, deployment verification, metrics monitoring, public release announcement.</statement>
        <rationale>Order matters. Announcing before verifying deployment creates a second announcement ("actually it's delayed") that erodes trust.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-6-post-release">
      <rule>
        <statement>Monitor for 24 hours post-release. Gather user feedback. Run a retrospective. Update the roadmap based on what you learned.</statement>
        <rationale>Issues spike in the first 24 hours. Early monitoring contains blast radius. The retrospective closes the learning loop that makes future releases better.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Shipping on Fridays.</description>
        <reason>Weekend incidents have slower response. Engineering and support have reduced coverage. A Monday–Wednesday release window keeps the full team available for the critical 24-hour monitoring window.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No rollback plan.</description>
        <reason>Every release should have a one-click or one-command rollback path. Without it, incident response time multiplies and pressure leads to poor decisions under stress.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Last-minute feature additions after the feature freeze.</description>
        <reason>Late additions skip testing and break the readiness checklist. Institute a 24–48 hour feature freeze before every release.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping communication because the release is "just a patch".</description>
        <reason>Users and support staff notice changes regardless of size. Silent releases generate confused support tickets. Always publish a changelog entry.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping staging deployment.</description>
        <reason>Staging catches integration issues that unit tests miss. A staging deploy is mandatory for any release that touches data migrations or third-party integrations.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No monitoring after release.</description>
        <reason>Error rates, latency, and conversion metrics can degrade subtly after a release. Watch metrics for at least 24 hours before declaring success.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Monster releases bundling months of features.</description>
        <reason>Large releases have higher risk, harder rollbacks, and diluted communication impact. Smaller, more frequent releases reduce blast radius and keep users engaged with steady progress.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="example-saas-monthly-release">
      <example type="good">
        <note>v2.4.0 — Goal: enable team collaboration. Contents: real-time collaboration feature, comments on tasks, 15 bug fixes.</note>
        <note>Timeline: Monday feature freeze and testing, Wednesday staging deploy and final QA, Thursday 2pm production deploy, Thursday customer email and blog post.</note>
        <note>Success metric: team features used by 20% of active users within the first week.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="example-solo-patch-release">
      <example type="good">
        <note>v1.2.3 — Goal: fix critical payment processing bug. Contents: payment fix, 2 minor UI bugs.</note>
        <note>Timeline: same-day deploy, quick changelog update, email to affected customers only.</note>
        <note>Success metric: zero payment failures post-deploy.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/release-plan.md" purpose="Full release plan: metadata, goal, contents, dependencies, risks, rollback plan, communication plan, timeline"/>
      <template path="templates/release-notes.md" purpose="Release notes template: highlights, new features, improvements, bug fixes, breaking changes"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
