<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="release-planning">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Six-step process to decide what ships, when, and how it is announced. Goal, contents, readiness, communication, execution, post-release.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>release-planning</tag>
      <tag>release-management</tag>
      <tag>versioning</tag>
      <tag>rollback</tag>
      <tag>release-notes</tag>
      <tag>semver</tag>
      <tag>changelog</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
    <applies-to>both</applies-to>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Release Planning</title>
    <summary>Six-step process for deciding what goes into each release, when it ships, and how it is communicated. Covers release-type taxonomy (major/minor/patch/hotfix per SemVer 2.0), readiness checklists, rollback requirements, and audience-specific communication plans. Concrete rule: every release needs a goal statement, a one-command rollback plan, and a communication plan before code touches production.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Releases without structure fail in three predictable ways: scope creep slips into the bundle and breaks freeze, staging is skipped and integration bugs hit production, communication is missing and users notice silent changes that drown support. A structured release plan turns each shipment into a small, reversible, observable event with a known audience.</p>
      <p>This methodology aligns with SemVer 2.0 (MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH), Keep a Changelog 1.1.0, and DORA's four key metrics — deployment frequency, lead time for changes, change failure rate, time to restore service — which together correlate with elite engineering performance.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Planning what to include in an upcoming version (major, minor, patch, or hotfix).</item>
        <item>Coordinating release timing across engineering, support, and marketing for a SaaS or library.</item>
        <item>Writing release notes for an existing set of merged changes that have not yet shipped.</item>
        <item>Setting up a repeatable release cadence for a solo founder or small team.</item>
        <item>Triggers: tag matches `v*`, CHANGELOG `[Unreleased]` is non-empty, milestone closes, customer-visible breaking change is queued.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Continuous deployment with feature flags — individual flag rollouts replace release bundling.</item>
        <item>Pre-launch products with no users — use a task list, not a release plan.</item>
        <item>Emergency hotfixes under time pressure — jump straight to the hotfix subset (steps 3, 5, 6 only).</item>
        <item>Internal-only refactors with no observable surface area — push through the regular CI/CD pipeline.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="release-types">
      <p>Release type drives cadence, risk posture, and announcement scope. Use SemVer 2.0 numbering: MAJOR for breaking, MINOR for features, PATCH for fixes. Hotfix is a PATCH bumped out-of-cadence to address a production incident.</p>
      <list>
        <item>major (vX.0.0) — quarterly or yearly. Breaking API changes, large features. Risk: high. Requires migration guide, deprecation notice ≥ one MINOR before, and beta period.</item>
        <item>minor (v0.Y.0) — monthly or biweekly. Backward-compatible features. Risk: medium. Requires release notes and customer email.</item>
        <item>patch (v0.0.Z) — weekly or as fixes accumulate. Bug fixes and security patches only. Risk: low. Requires changelog entry only.</item>
        <item>hotfix (v0.0.Z+1) — within hours. Critical production fix. Risk: very low if scope is limited to the single bug. Requires post-incident review.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <how-to>
      <step>Step 1 — Define release goal. Write a single-sentence outcome the release delivers, a measurable success metric, and an optional theme. This is the title and abstract of every other artifact.</step>
      <step>Step 2 — Select release contents. List all merge-ready changes; cut anything that is not at definition of done; freeze the list. Anything added after this point requires either an explicit re-freeze or a slot in the next release.</step>
      <step>Step 3 — Assess readiness. Run the seven-item readiness checklist below. If any item fails, the release does not ship.</step>
      <step>Step 4 — Plan communication. For each audience write the asset they receive (release notes, blog, email, in-app banner, social post, status page).</step>
      <step>Step 5 — Execute. Follow the deploy ordering: final staging test → maintenance window notice (if needed) → production deploy → smoke verification → monitor metrics 30 minutes → public announcement.</step>
      <step>Step 6 — Post-release. Watch error rates, latency, and key conversion metrics for 24 hours. Collect feedback. Run a 30-minute retrospective. Update roadmap.</step>
    </how-to>

    <section name="step-1-define-release-goal">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every release MUST have a stated user outcome, one success metric, and a target version. Use template: "Release vX.Y.Z. Goal: [outcome]. Metric: [how measured, target, deadline]. Theme: [optional narrative]."</statement>
        <rationale>Without a goal, a release is just a list of changes. The goal connects the release to product strategy and makes the post-release retrospective meaningful. The metric forces the team to define success before shipping, not after.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-2-select-release-contents">
      <rule>
        <statement>Include only: (a) features at definition of done with passing tests and updated docs, (b) bug fixes related to the release theme or marked release-critical, (c) documentation and configuration updates that ship with the code. Exclude: half-finished features, unrelated bug fixes, scope creep added after freeze, vendored dependency upgrades not validated in staging.</statement>
        <rationale>Half-finished features create technical debt and confuse users. Scope creep after freeze is the top empirical cause of delayed and broken releases — DORA reports correlate freeze discipline with low change-failure rate.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-3-assess-release-readiness">
      <rule>
        <statement>All seven readiness items MUST pass before deployment. Treat the checklist as a gate, not a guideline.</statement>
        <rationale>Missing any one item creates a predictable class of post-release incident. The rollback plan especially: without it every incident response begins with a debate instead of an action.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <checklist>
        <check>Code complete: all PRs targeting this release are merged to the release branch and CI is green.</check>
        <check>Tests passing: unit + integration + e2e on the release branch within the last 24 hours.</check>
        <check>Documentation updated: README, API docs, CHANGELOG `[Unreleased]` has all entries, migration notes for breaking changes.</check>
        <check>Migrations tested: schema migrations applied and rolled back successfully against a copy of production.</check>
        <check>Rollback plan exists: a one-command revert path is written, owned, and tested in staging.</check>
        <check>Support team briefed: known issues, FAQ, and triage runbook delivered to support 24 hours before deploy.</check>
        <check>Release notes written: customer-facing notes drafted in the audience's voice and reviewed by one other person.</check>
      </checklist>
    </section>

    <section name="step-4-plan-communication">
      <rule>
        <statement>Identify every audience (internal eng, support, sales, customers, partners, ecosystem) and ship a matching asset for each: release notes, blog/changelog, customer email, social post, in-app notification, status page entry. Announce every release, including patches.</statement>
        <rationale>Silent releases generate confused support tickets from users who noticed a change and cannot find context. The marginal cost of a one-line changelog entry is far smaller than the support volume it prevents.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <checklist>
        <check>Release notes (technical) at templates/release-notes.md.</check>
        <check>Customer email drafted and queued in the marketing tool.</check>
        <check>Blog post or changelog page published on release day.</check>
        <check>Social post (X / LinkedIn) scheduled for one hour after deploy verification.</check>
        <check>In-app banner copy and date set in the feature-flag or CMS.</check>
        <check>Support macro updated with the new feature talk-track.</check>
        <check>Status page incident pre-drafted in case of rollback (kept private until needed).</check>
      </checklist>
    </section>

    <section name="step-5-execute-release">
      <rule>
        <statement>Execute strictly in order: final staging test → maintenance window announcement (if applicable) → production deploy → smoke verification → 30-minute metric watch → public release announcement. Do not announce before verifying. Do not deploy on Friday or the day before a public holiday.</statement>
        <rationale>Order matters because a wrong-order release creates a second corrective announcement ("actually it is delayed") that erodes trust. Friday deploys multiply incident response time because weekend on-call has reduced coverage.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-6-post-release">
      <rule>
        <statement>Monitor for 24 hours. Compare error rate, p95 latency, and the release's primary success metric against the prior 7-day baseline. Hold a 30-minute retrospective within 72 hours. Update roadmap and backlog with what was learned.</statement>
        <rationale>Issues spike in the first 24 hours; early monitoring contains blast radius. Retrospectives close the learning loop that improves the next release. DORA's mean-time-to-restore metric improves directly with disciplined post-release monitoring.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="commands">
      <p>Reference commands an autonomous agent can run when planning, cutting, and verifying a release. Adapt to the project's actual tooling; the names below assume git, GitHub CLI, and a Node/Python toolchain.</p>
      <commands>
        <command name="version-bump-patch">npm version patch -m "chore: release v%s"</command>
        <command name="version-bump-minor">npm version minor -m "chore: release v%s"</command>
        <command name="version-bump-major">npm version major -m "chore: release v%s"</command>
        <command name="python-version-bump">python -m bumpversion patch</command>
        <command name="diff-since-last-tag">git log $(git describe --tags --abbrev=0)..HEAD --oneline</command>
        <command name="list-merged-prs">gh pr list --base main --state merged --search "merged:&gt;$(git log -1 --format=%aI $(git describe --tags --abbrev=0))"</command>
        <command name="cut-release-branch">git checkout -b release/v$VERSION main</command>
        <command name="tag-release">git tag -a v$VERSION -m "release v$VERSION" &amp;&amp; git push origin v$VERSION</command>
        <command name="generate-release-notes">gh release create v$VERSION --generate-notes --draft --target main</command>
        <command name="publish-release">gh release edit v$VERSION --draft=false</command>
        <command name="rollback-tag">git revert --no-commit v$VERSION..HEAD &amp;&amp; git commit -m "revert: roll back v$VERSION"</command>
        <command name="rollback-deploy">kubectl rollout undo deployment/$APP --to-revision=$PREV</command>
        <command name="staging-smoke">curl -fsS https://staging.example.com/healthz &amp;&amp; npm run test:e2e -- --baseUrl=https://staging.example.com</command>
        <command name="prod-smoke">curl -fsS https://example.com/healthz &amp;&amp; curl -fsS https://example.com/api/version | jq -e ".version == \"$VERSION\""</command>
        <command name="watch-error-rate">while sleep 60; do curl -s "$METRICS/api/v1/query?query=rate(http_requests_total{status=~\"5..\"}[5m])"; done</command>
      </commands>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-templates">
      <prompt purpose="Draft a release plan from a CHANGELOG and milestone state."><![CDATA[
You are preparing release vX.Y.Z. Inputs:
- CHANGELOG.md [Unreleased] section.
- Open milestone "vX.Y.Z" with N closed issues.
- Current branch state and last tag.

Produce a release plan with these sections:
1. Goal (one sentence outcome).
2. Success metric (number, target, deadline).
3. Contents: features, fixes, docs, breaking changes (each links to PR/issue).
4. Dependencies and risks.
5. Rollback plan (one-command path that has been tested in staging).
6. Communication plan: release notes, email, blog, social, in-app, status page.
7. Timeline: freeze date, staging deploy, production deploy window, monitor window.

Hard constraints:
- Use SemVer 2.0 numbering and explain MAJOR/MINOR/PATCH choice.
- No Friday production deploys.
- Mark every breaking change with a migration note.
- Output Markdown, no time estimates ("after step X" instead of "in 2h").
]]></prompt>
      <prompt purpose="Generate customer-facing release notes from a technical PR list."><![CDATA[
You are writing customer-facing release notes for vX.Y.Z. Input: list of merged PRs with title, body, and labels.

Output a Markdown document with sections in this order:
- Highlights (1-3 bullets, plain language, value-focused).
- New features (group by area; include screenshots/links if linked in PRs).
- Improvements.
- Bug fixes (one-line each).
- Breaking changes (each: what changed, why, migration steps, deprecation timeline).
- Security (CVE IDs if applicable).
- Acknowledgements (external contributors).

Style:
- Active voice, second person ("you can now").
- No internal jargon; expand acronyms on first use.
- Link every change to its PR or issue.
- Lead with user-visible value, not implementation detail.
]]></prompt>
      <prompt purpose="Run the readiness gate as an automated check."><![CDATA[
You are the release readiness gate for vX.Y.Z. For each of the seven items below, return PASS or FAIL with a one-sentence justification grounded in the linked artifact. If any item is FAIL, refuse the release.

Items:
1. Code complete — all milestone PRs merged, CI green.
2. Tests passing — unit + integration + e2e green within last 24h.
3. Docs updated — README, API ref, CHANGELOG [Unreleased] -> [vX.Y.Z], migration notes.
4. Migrations tested — applied + rolled back on prod-shape DB.
5. Rollback plan — one-command path documented and dry-run-validated.
6. Support briefed — runbook delivered ≥24h before deploy.
7. Release notes — customer-facing draft reviewed by one peer.

Output: Markdown table | Item | Status | Evidence link | Notes |.
Final line: READINESS=PASS or READINESS=FAIL.
]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="changelog-template">
      <p>Follow Keep a Changelog 1.1.0. Maintain CHANGELOG.md at repo root. On each release, rename `[Unreleased]` to `[vX.Y.Z] - YYYY-MM-DD` and create a fresh empty `[Unreleased]` block above it.</p>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Changelog
All notable changes to this project will be documented in this file.
The format is based on Keep a Changelog 1.1.0 and this project adheres to SemVer 2.0.

## [Unreleased]
### Added
### Changed
### Deprecated
### Removed
### Fixed
### Security

## [1.4.0] - 2026-05-15
### Added
- Real-time collaboration on tasks (#412).
### Fixed
- Fix payment retry loop on 402 (#420).

[Unreleased]: https://github.com/org/repo/compare/v1.4.0...HEAD
[1.4.0]: https://github.com/org/repo/compare/v1.3.0...v1.4.0
]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="rollback-plan-template">
      <p>Every release ships with a written rollback plan. Store at `docs/releases/vX.Y.Z-rollback.md` and dry-run it on staging before approving the release.</p>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Rollback Plan v1.4.0

## Trigger conditions
- 5xx rate > 1% sustained 5 minutes.
- p95 latency > 2x baseline sustained 10 minutes.
- Critical user-reported regression (data loss, payment failure).

## Owner
- Primary: @alice (on-call until +24h post-deploy).
- Backup: @bob.

## Procedure (target time-to-restore: < 10 minutes)
1. Announce in #incidents: "rolling back v1.4.0".
2. Run: `kubectl rollout undo deployment/api --to-revision=$PREV`.
3. Verify smoke: `curl -fsS https://example.com/healthz`.
4. Confirm error rate < 0.1% for 5 minutes.
5. Run: `git revert --no-commit v1.4.0..HEAD && git commit -m "revert: v1.4.0"`.
6. Update status page: incident resolved.
7. Post-mortem within 48h.

## Data migration reversal
- v1.4.0 migration `0042_add_team_table` is forward-only.
- Data written by new code is compatible with v1.3.x readers (validated in staging).
- If reversal is required, run `python manage.py migrate app 0041` then redeploy v1.3.x.
]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Shipping on Fridays.</description>
        <reason>Weekend on-call has reduced coverage and slower mean-time-to-restore. A Monday-Wednesday production window keeps the full team available for the critical 24-hour monitoring period.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No rollback plan.</description>
        <reason>Every release must have a one-command rollback path that has been dry-run on staging. Without it, incident response time multiplies and pressure leads to poor decisions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Last-minute feature additions after the freeze.</description>
        <reason>Late additions skip the readiness checklist and break the test baseline. Enforce a 24-48 hour code freeze before every release; later changes go to the next release.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping communication because the release is "just a patch".</description>
        <reason>Users and support staff notice changes regardless of size. Silent releases generate confused tickets. Always publish at least a CHANGELOG entry and an in-app changelog link.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping staging deployment.</description>
        <reason>Staging catches integration issues that unit tests miss. Mandatory for any release touching data migrations, third-party integrations, or infrastructure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No monitoring after release.</description>
        <reason>Error rate, latency, and conversion metrics can degrade subtly after a release. Watch for at least 24 hours before declaring success and updating the status page.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Monster releases bundling months of features.</description>
        <reason>Large releases have higher risk, harder rollbacks, and diluted communication impact. Smaller, more frequent releases reduce blast radius and keep users engaged with steady visible progress.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Announcing before verifying production deploy.</description>
        <reason>A premature announcement followed by a delay or rollback erodes trust faster than any feature can rebuild it. Verify smoke + 30 minutes of clean metrics before publishing the announcement.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="example-saas-monthly-release">
      <example type="good" title="v2.4.0 — team collaboration release">
        <note>Goal: enable team collaboration. Metric: 20% of active users use a team feature within 7 days of release.</note>
        <note>Contents: real-time collaboration, comments on tasks, 15 fixes. SemVer: MINOR (additive features only).</note>
        <note>Timeline: Mon freeze + regression run, Wed staging deploy + final QA, Thu 14:00 UTC production deploy, Thu 15:00 UTC announcement (after 30-min metric watch).</note>
        <note>Rollback: `kubectl rollout undo deployment/api`, owner on-call until Fri 14:00 UTC.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="example-solo-patch-release">
      <example type="good" title="v1.2.3 — payment hotfix">
        <note>Goal: fix critical payment processing bug. Metric: zero payment failures with the new code path for 24h.</note>
        <note>Contents: payment fix, 2 minor UI bugs. SemVer: PATCH.</note>
        <note>Timeline: same-day staging smoke at 11:00, deploy at 13:00, monitor until 14:00, changelog + email to affected customers only.</note>
        <note>Rollback: revert PR #218 + redeploy previous tag; tested on staging at 10:30.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="example-bad-friday-release">
      <example type="bad" title="Friday 17:00 deploy with no rollback plan">
        <note>v3.0.0 (MAJOR) shipped 17:00 Friday with breaking auth change.</note>
        <note>Bug discovered 18:30; on-call solo engineer; rollback plan undocumented.</note>
        <note>Restore-time 4h; 23% of weekend logins failed; trust hit visible in churn for two weeks.</note>
        <note>Lessons: enforce no-Friday rule, mandate documented + dry-run-tested rollback for every MAJOR.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <verify>
      <step>Run: `git tag -l "v$VERSION"` returns the tag and `git push --tags` succeeded.</step>
      <step>Run: `gh release view v$VERSION --json isDraft,publishedAt` shows `isDraft=false` and a non-null timestamp.</step>
      <step>Run: `curl -fsS https://example.com/api/version | jq -e ".version == \"$VERSION\""` returns 0.</step>
      <step>Confirm CHANGELOG has `[vX.Y.Z] - YYYY-MM-DD` block populated and `[Unreleased]` reset to empty headers.</step>
      <step>Confirm error rate (5xx) for the new version is &lt; 0.1% sustained over 30 minutes after deploy.</step>
      <step>Confirm p95 latency is within 1.2x of the 7-day baseline 30 minutes after deploy.</step>
      <step>Confirm release notes are published, customer email sent, in-app banner live.</step>
      <step>Schedule and complete the 30-minute retrospective within 72 hours; capture three actions in the next-release backlog.</step>
      <step>Verify DORA metrics for this release: deploy frequency unchanged or up, lead-time-for-change recorded, change-failure-rate marked false (or true with linked incident), MTTR recorded if any incident occurred.</step>
    </verify>

    <section name="success-criteria">
      <list>
        <item>Goal sentence, success metric, and SemVer-correct version are written before any deploy command runs.</item>
        <item>All seven readiness checks pass; readiness gate prompt returns READINESS=PASS.</item>
        <item>Rollback plan is written, owned, and dry-run-validated on staging.</item>
        <item>Each identified audience received its asset on or before deploy.</item>
        <item>24-hour monitoring window completed; error rate and latency within thresholds.</item>
        <item>Retrospective held; learnings captured in roadmap or backlog.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/release-plan.md" purpose="Full release plan: metadata, goal, contents, dependencies, risks, rollback plan, communication plan, timeline."/>
      <template path="templates/release-notes.md" purpose="Release notes template: highlights, new features, improvements, bug fixes, breaking changes, security."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://semver.org/spec/v2.0.0.html">SemVer 2.0.0 specification</link>
      <link href="https://keepachangelog.com/en/1.1.0/">Keep a Changelog 1.1.0</link>
      <link href="https://dora.dev/">DORA core metrics</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
