<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gha-security-hardening Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gha-security-hardening. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every uses: reference MUST be pinned to a full 40-character SHA commit hash, not a tag or branch. Add the version number as a comment: uses: actions/checkout@b4ffde65f46336ab88eb53be808477a3936bae11 # v4.1.1</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tags are mutable. A supply-chain attack replaces the tag on the upstream repo and every downstream workflow runs malicious code on the next trigger. SHA is immutable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set permissions: at the job level (not workflow level) with only the scopes the job needs. Start with contents: read and add scopes incrementally. Never set permissions: write-all.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Workflow-level permissions apply to every job. A test job that only reads code should never have packages: write or deployments: write. Job-level scope limits the blast radius of a compromised step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All cloud authentication MUST use OIDC. Add id-token: write permission, configure the provider's trust policy to accept the GH OIDC issuer, and use the provider's official configure-credentials action.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Long-lived cloud credentials stored as repo secrets persist until manually rotated. An OIDC token is valid for 15 minutes and is scoped to the specific workflow run; a leaked token is useless after the run completes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>NEVER use pull_request_target to get secrets for fork PRs. Use pull_request with minimal token scopes. If fork PRs genuinely need secrets, deploy to a sandbox environment protected by required reviewers and check out only the base ref, never the PR head.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">pull_request_target runs in the target repo context with all its secrets. A PR with malicious workflow changes can exfiltrate every secret on the first trigger. This is the most common critical GHA vulnerability pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Avoid ${{ github.event.* }} interpolation directly in run: shell commands. Assign to an env: variable and reference the env var with $VARNAME to prevent shell injection.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A PR title like "; rm -rf /" interpolated directly into run: echo "${{ github.event.pull_request.title }}" executes as a shell command. env: variables are passed safely without shell evaluation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Self-hosted runners MUST use specific labels (e.g., runs-on: [self-hosted, repo-name, ephemeral]) and MUST be ephemeral (Actions Runner Controller on K8s, not long-lived VMs). Public repos MUST NOT use self-hosted runners for PR workflows.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">runs-on: self-hosted without labels targets any available runner. A fork PR can run on a privileged runner with access to internal network resources. Ephemeral ARC runners are isolated per job.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
