<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GitHub Actions — Security Hardening Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules including a `skip-this-methodology` rule. Each pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="sha-pin-third-party-actions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Third-party actions MUST be pinned to a specific commit SHA, never a tag. `uses: actions/checkout@v4` is rejected; `uses: actions/checkout@&lt;sha&gt;` is required.</statement>
      <rationale source="Supply chain integrity">Tags are mutable; a compromised tag = compromised workflow. SHA pinning is the only audit-friendly form.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="oidc-not-static-keys" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cloud authentication MUST use OIDC with a trust policy scoped to the repo + branch + workflow. Long-lived access keys in secrets are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Short-lived credentials">Static keys leak; OIDC issues per-run tokens with scoped trust, eliminating the leak class.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="scoped-token-permissions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>`permissions:` block MUST be declared at job or workflow scope with explicit minimum scopes. Implicit default (write-all) is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Least privilege">Default GITHUB_TOKEN has broad write; scoping it caps blast radius if a step is compromised.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-pull-request-target-with-checkout-pr" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>`pull_request_target` workflows MUST NOT check out the PR branch and execute its code with secrets. The combination is the most common GHA supply-chain exploit class.</statement>
      <rationale source="GHA security advisory">The pattern lets a PR from a fork execute arbitrary code with repo secrets — historically exploited multiple times.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="actionlint-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Repository MUST run `actionlint` (or equivalent) as a required check on workflow file changes. Manual review alone is insufficient.</statement>
      <rationale source="Static analysis">actionlint catches expression-injection, missing permissions, and other patterns that humans miss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip when (a) repo internal-only with no external PRs AND no secrets in workflows AND no cloud-auth; OR (b) prototype repo with no production path.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scope guard">Below threshold the overhead exceeds risk; above threshold the methodology is non-optional.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
