<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-metrics" title="EVM Core Metrics and Formulas">
  <summary>The complete EVM metric set: base measurements (PV, EV, AC), variance and performance indices (SV, CV, SPI, CPI), and forecasts (EAC, ETC, VAC, TCPI).</summary>

  <section title="Base Measurements">
    <p>Three numbers are measured at each reporting period:</p>
    <list>
      <item>PV (Planned Value) = BAC x % planned complete. How much work should be done by now per the baseline.</item>
      <item>EV (Earned Value) = BAC x % actually complete. How much value has been earned by work actually done.</item>
      <item>AC (Actual Cost) = money spent to date. How much has been paid for work done so far.</item>
      <item>BAC (Budget at Completion) = total approved budget for the project.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure EV using objective earning rules (0/100, 50/50, milestone-weighted, or percent-complete with DoD gate) defined per work package at baseline; never accept self-reported percentages without objective evidence.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-reported percent complete inflates EV and produces optimistic SPI/CPI; objective earning rules tie EV to observable events (test pass, milestone date, accepted deliverable).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Variance and Performance Indices">
    <list>
      <item>SV (Schedule Variance) = EV - PV. Positive = ahead of schedule; negative = behind.</item>
      <item>CV (Cost Variance) = EV - AC. Positive = under budget; negative = over budget.</item>
      <item>SPI (Schedule Performance Index) = EV / PV. Greater than 1 = ahead; less than 1 = behind.</item>
      <item>CPI (Cost Performance Index) = EV / AC. Greater than 1 = under budget; less than 1 = over budget.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Report SPI, CPI, and EAC as the minimum three numbers in every sponsor update; do not bury them in narrative prose.</statement>
      <rationale>Sponsors making go/no-go decisions need indices, not adjectives. "Slightly behind" carries no actionable information; SPI=0.80 says the team is delivering 80 cents of value per dollar of planned work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Month 3: PV=$50k, EV=$40k, AC=$55k. SV=-$10k (behind), CV=-$15k (over), SPI=0.80, CPI=0.73. Sponsor escalation triggered at CPI below 0.85.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Forecast Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>EAC (Estimate at Completion) = BAC / CPI. Predicted final cost if current efficiency continues.</item>
      <item>ETC (Estimate to Complete) = EAC - AC. Additional cost needed to finish.</item>
      <item>VAC (Variance at Completion) = BAC - EAC. Expected final surplus (positive) or overrun (negative).</item>
      <item>TCPI (To-Complete Performance Index) = (BAC - EV) / (BAC - AC). Required efficiency on remaining work to finish on budget.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>When TCPI exceeds 1.10, treat this as an escalation trigger; sustained CPI improvement of this magnitude is rarely achieved in practice.</statement>
      <rationale>Research on defense programs (Fleming &amp; Koppelman) shows CPI rarely improves more than 10% from its value at 20% project completion; TCPI above 1.10 is aspirational, not a plan.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Produce at least three EAC scenarios: CPI-only (most likely if trend continues), CPI x SPI (both indices persist), and bottom-up ETC; report which scenario the team endorses and why.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-number EAC forecasts hide uncertainty; three scenarios make assumptions explicit and prevent anchoring on the most optimistic estimate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
