<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="EVM Step-by-Step Process">
  <summary>Four steps to implement EVM: establish the time-phased baseline, measure progress with objective earning rules, compute indices deterministically, and forecast completion with multiple scenarios.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Establish Baseline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build the PV curve by distributing BAC across the project timeline per the WBS work packages; the curve must reflect actual planned expenditure, not a straight line.</statement>
      <rationale>A linear PV curve produces misleading SV/SPI in phases with front-loaded or back-loaded work; the S-curve shape reflects real resource allocation and gives accurate schedule performance signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Define BAC (total approved budget) per work package and in total.</item>
      <item>Assign an earning rule to each work package: 0/100 (short tasks), 50/50 (multi-period tasks), milestone-weighted, or percent-complete (long tasks with clear DoD).</item>
      <item>Build the time-phased PV curve by distributing work-package budgets across planned periods.</item>
      <item>Lock the baseline in version control; tag as baseline-v1.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Measure Progress">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post an EV event only when the work package passes its acceptance criterion (Definition of Done); partial credit on deliverables that are not yet accepted is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>EV posted before DoD acceptance inflates performance indices and hides real schedule risk; unaccepted deliverables often require rework that consumes additional AC without new EV.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>At each period end: assess actual completion status for each work package per its earning rule.</item>
      <item>Calculate EV = sum of (work-package budget x earned fraction) for all packages.</item>
      <item>Record AC from the accounting system; never estimate AC from invoices alone.</item>
      <item>Compute SV, CV, SPI, CPI from the period's PV, EV, AC.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Compute and Report">
    <rule>
      <statement>Force all EVM computation through a deterministic script or tool; the LLM narrates and contextualizes the output but does not compute the numbers.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs round inconsistently, conflate SV (currency) with schedule slip (time), and introduce GREEN-washing when prompted to summarize. Deterministic computation eliminates these errors at source.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/evm_calc.py">Deterministic EVM index calculator from YAML inputs</reference>
    <reference path="templates/evm-report.md">EVM dashboard template with RAG status</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Rebaselining Discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Rebaseline only when a formally approved scope change alters the project; never rebaseline to hide variance — preserve the original baseline alongside the new one for audit.</statement>
      <rationale>Rebaselining to make RAG green is EVM fraud; it destroys the performance history and makes future forecasts meaningless. Sponsors and auditors must see the original vs. revised baseline side by side.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Rebaselining monthly to maintain a "green" dashboard after each rough period.</description>
      <reason>Each rebaseline resets the indices to 1.0, erasing the evidence of chronic underperformance. Cumulative drift becomes invisible, and the final overrun surprises everyone.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
