<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules" title="EVM Rules and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Rules for late-project accuracy, risk linkage, and agentic EVM workflow; anti-patterns that destroy EVM credibility.</summary>

  <section title="Late-Project Accuracy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use SPI(t) (time-based Schedule Performance Index) alongside classic SPI for late-stage reporting; classic SPI converges to 1.0 as PV approaches BAC regardless of actual schedule status.</statement>
      <rationale>In the final 20% of a project, PV and BAC are nearly equal; SV and SPI lose discrimination and can show "on schedule" for a project that will be weeks late. SPI(t) = ES / AT remains meaningful throughout.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Triangulate index-based EAC against a bottom-up ETC at least quarterly; pure CPI-based forecasts drift over long durations.</statement>
      <rationale>Index-based forecasts assume the current efficiency persists unchanged; a bottom-up re-estimate incorporates changed scope, team, or technical complexity that the indices cannot see.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Risk Linkage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tie every RED index (SPI &lt; 0.85 or CPI &lt; 0.85) to at least one open risk in the risk register with an explicit action plan; an unexplained RED is an audit finding.</statement>
      <rationale>Red performance without a linked risk and response plan is noise; linking to the register forces the team to decide: accept, mitigate, transfer, or escalate — and documents the decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When a risk closes, verify that the associated performance indices improve in the next period; if they do not, the root cause was misdiagnosed.</statement>
      <rationale>Closing risks without verifying performance impact creates a false sense of recovery; unverified closures leave real causes unaddressed.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic EVM Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>The EVM narrative agent receives typed numeric inputs and emits a RAG verdict by rule (GREEN: SPI &gt;= 0.95 and CPI &gt;= 0.95; RED: SPI &lt; 0.85 or CPI &lt; 0.85; YELLOW: otherwise); it must not soften RED without an explicit sponsor-override field.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a hard RAG rule, narrative agents anchor toward "improving" language even for persistent red indices, which misleads sponsors and delays interventions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Letting the LLM compute EVM numbers from narrative inputs (e.g., "we spent about $55k and are roughly 40% done").</description>
      <reason>Narrative inputs introduce ambiguity; LLMs round inconsistently and may interpolate missing values. Only typed numeric inputs from the accounting system and objective DoD assessments are valid.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Reporting only one EAC scenario in the sponsor update.</description>
      <reason>A single EAC anchors expectations on the most likely (or most optimistic) case; three scenarios expose the range of risk and prevent overconfidence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
