<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Lead Magnet for Solo Consultancy Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Lead Magnet for Solo Consultancy MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="filters-not-collects" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Magnet MUST filter to qualified buyers; vanity-volume (signups / week) is a forbidden primary metric.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — solo-consultancy audit Q1 2026">Solo consultants sell time, not seats; a 10k-signup list with 0 fits is net-negative for the operator.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="one-narrow-promise" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Magnet MUST make exactly one narrow promise (one outcome, one ICP, one situation). Multi-promise magnets MUST be split.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford, Sales Pitch (2023)">Single-promise magnets convert 3-5x better and pre-qualify in copy alone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="filtering-format-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Format MUST be one of: niche audit checklist, opinionated benchmark report, code snippet pack, calculator. Generic eBooks / top-N posts are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo consultancy benchmarks Q4 2025">These four formats encode the consultant's opinion / data / mechanic; generic formats encode nothing and rank against larger publishers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every claim, benchmark number, and screenshot MUST cite source (URL, transcript_id, dashboard snapshot) inline.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice for marketing assets">Unsourced benchmarks are why generic lead magnets fail trust audits; sourcing IS the moat.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="follow-up-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Magnet MUST ship with a 7-day follow-up sequence (&gt;=3 emails) wired to the same audience. Standalone magnets are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Email pipeline cohort analysis 2025">Conversion happens in days 2-7, not on download; a magnet without follow-up forfeits 80% of attributable revenue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ship-week-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>First version MUST ship within 5 working days. Methodology MUST be skipped if scope blows past that.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo-build heuristic — Tiago Forte, Building a Second Brain">Solo-consultant magnets that miss the week-cap signal misfit format; cut scope, do not extend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
