<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-anchor-types" title="Spatial Panel Anchor Types">
  <summary>Four anchor types for spatial UI panels, each with distinct use cases, ergonomic constraints, and platform-specific behavior.</summary>

  <section title="Anchor Type Definitions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign every panel exactly one anchor type before prototyping; do not defer anchoring to implementation.</statement>
      <rationale>Anchor type determines interaction model, platform API, and ergonomic constraints. Changing it late requires redesigning transitions and input mappings.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>World-locked panels must remain fixed in physical space; use for reference content that the user returns to across movement.</statement>
      <rationale>World-locked panels feel grounded and reduce cognitive load for information the user consults repeatedly (maps, documentation, dashboards).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Head-locked panels must be reserved for transient notifications only; never use head-locked for primary navigation.</statement>
      <rationale>Head-locked content follows gaze constantly, causing visual fatigue and disorientation within minutes. Transient use (under 5 seconds) is the only safe pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Body-locked panels are the default for menus and tools used while moving; anchor to torso forward direction, not head orientation.</statement>
      <rationale>Body-locked UI stays accessible without constant arm raising and does not drift with head turns, making it comfortable for extended use.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Hand-attached UI must cover no more than two high-frequency actions (e.g., mode toggle, undo); do not build a full toolbar on the hand.</statement>
      <rationale>A hand that becomes a toolbar is always occupied. More than two actions causes the user to search the hand surface, breaking flow.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Ergonomic Constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place world-locked and body-locked panels at 0.5-2 m distance and within 30° eccentricity from forward gaze.</statement>
      <rationale>Outside this envelope, users must rotate their head or lean, causing fatigue. The 30° eccentricity limit aligns with comfortable reading range without head movement.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Set the minimum touch target size to 4 cm in spatial UI; smaller targets are unreachable with reliable pinch or ray accuracy.</statement>
      <rationale>Unlike touchscreen where a fingertip anchors the touch, spatial interaction uses ray casting or hand tracking with inherent jitter; 4 cm is the empirical floor.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Hand-attached panels must be placed 0.25-0.5 m from the user's eye point; outside this range hand tracking loses precision.</statement>
      <rationale>Hand tracking cameras have a working volume; panels outside it produce tracking dropout and unreachable targets.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Platform Notes">
    <p>visionOS, Meta Horizon OS, and Android XR have diverging anchor vocabularies. Platform-to-anchor mapping:</p>
    <list>
      <item>visionOS: windows (world/body), volumes (world), immersive spaces (full environment)</item>
      <item>Horizon OS: panels (world/body/hand), surfaces (world snap)</item>
      <item>Android XR: spatial panels (world/body), AR anchors (world via ARCore)</item>
      <item>HoloLens/MRTK3: slate (world), follow (body), tag-along (head-locked lite)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>When targeting multiple XR platforms, define anchoring in platform-agnostic terms (world/head/body/hand) and map to platform APIs separately.</statement>
      <rationale>Platform-specific anchor names differ enough to cause translation errors if mixed in design documents.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-window-management.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-comfort-and-gotchas.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/panel-classifier-prompt.txt"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
