<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-window-management" title="Spatial Window Management Rules">
  <summary>Rules for multi-window layout, snapping, grouping, docking, and spatial memory in XR environments.</summary>

  <section title="Window Management Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Support at minimum: snap to surfaces, group related windows, minimize to dock, and spatial memory (restore to last position).</statement>
      <rationale>Users who place windows deliberately form spatial memory; losing positions on app restart breaks the mental model and forces repetitive layout work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Persist spatial memory per-user across sessions, not per-app-launch; store anchor positions in platform world-anchor APIs.</statement>
      <rationale>Per-launch spatial memory resets positions on every cold start, eliminating the ergonomic benefit of allowing users to arrange their workspace.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a "recenter" gesture or voice command that returns body-locked UI to the comfortable default position.</statement>
      <rationale>Users physically drift during extended sessions. Body-locked content that started centered drifts relative to the user's new forward direction; recenter corrects this without requiring the user to close and reopen panels.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Animate panel summon and dismiss with a spatial origin anchor (from the body or hand that invoked it); do not use instant pop-in.</statement>
      <rationale>Instant appearance without a spatial origin disorients users — the panel seems to appear from nowhere. Animating from a source provides spatial context.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Multi-Window Layout">
    <rule>
      <statement>Consult platform manifests for window count and GPU memory limits before allowing users to open more than 3 simultaneous panels.</statement>
      <rationale>Quest and Android XR impose OS-level limits on concurrent window count and GPU memory; exceeding them causes crashes or degraded rendering that the app cannot recover from gracefully.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Group logically related windows (e.g., inspector + canvas) so they can be moved and dismissed together.</statement>
      <rationale>Independent movement of tightly coupled panels breaks layout coherence and forces users to reorganize relationships repeatedly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Head-locked primary navigation — a persistent menu that follows gaze at all times.</description>
      <reason>Causes visual fatigue within minutes; blocks the view of world content; violates Apple visionOS and Meta Horizon OS design guidelines explicitly.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Placing any UI closer than 0.5 m from the user's eye point.</description>
      <reason>Content within 0.5 m is in the vergence-accommodation conflict zone; eyes cannot focus comfortably and the user experiences eye strain within seconds.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Requiring constant arm raising to interact with world-locked UI above eye level.</description>
      <reason>Gorilla arm fatigue sets in after 30-60 seconds of raised-arm interaction; UI above the horizontal midline must be transient or reachable by gaze+pinch, not by reaching up.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/comfort-check.ts">TypeScript comfort checker for distance, eccentricity, and size constraints</reference>
</text>
