<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-comfort-and-gotchas" title="Comfort Rules and AI-Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Ergonomic comfort envelope rules, depth-as-hierarchy guidance, and AI-agent-specific failure modes for spatial UI authoring.</summary>

  <section title="Comfort and Depth Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use depth as a secondary hierarchy signal after color and typography, not as a primary one.</statement>
      <rationale>Many users have reduced stereo acuity (including a significant fraction with amblyopia or monocular vision); depth-first hierarchy excludes them and fails gracefully only if color/typography carry the signal too.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Test panel placement with at least 5 users including short and tall participants; ergonomic defaults assume a 50th-percentile adult standing.</statement>
      <rationale>A 160 cm user and a 195 cm user experience very different comfort envelopes for the same world-locked panel. Seated users have additional constraints on forward reach and upward gaze.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Always verify input modality availability before proposing gaze+pinch, voice, or hand-tracking combinations.</statement>
      <rationale>Voice and gaze are hardware-gated on some Quest variants; controller-only configurations on HoloLens change the entire interaction model. Proposing unsupported modalities produces a build that fails on the target device.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin SDK versions explicitly in every prompt when generating visionOS or Quest code; require the agent to cite API references.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs frequently emit deprecated APIs (e.g., OVRPlugin calls renamed in 2024+). Without version pinning, generated code compiles against documentation, not the installed SDK.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Declare coordinate system assumptions explicitly in every code generation prompt: visionOS (Y-up, right-handed, meters), Unity (Y-up, left-handed, meters), Unreal (Z-up, cm).</statement>
      <rationale>Converting at the wrong layer breaks panel placement in ways that are not obvious until runtime; agents must not assume a coordinate system.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Require USDZ/USD scene mutations to be validated via usdcat before accepting agent output.</statement>
      <rationale>USD authoring is finicky; agents produce syntactically plausible but semantically broken scenes that fail to load silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility Gaps">
    <p>Spatial UI accessibility (color blindness, low vision, motor impairments, vestibular sensitivity) is under-served by the methodology. Agents must escalate to the accessibility-specialist methodology in parallel when designing for diverse users.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag any spatial UI specification that does not address vestibular sensitivity; provide a reduced-motion mode for all animated panel transitions.</statement>
      <rationale>Spatial animations (panel summon, recenter, fly-in) trigger vestibular discomfort in users with motion sensitivity, a common condition that is easy to mitigate with a preference toggle.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/comfort-check.ts">TypeScript function flagging panels outside ergonomic envelope</reference>
</text>
