<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="project-closure">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Formal 7-step process to end a project with signed acceptance, closed contracts, lessons learned, archived docs, final report, operations handover, and team recognition.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>project-closure</tag>
      <tag>handover</tag>
      <tag>lessons-learned</tag>
      <tag>acceptance</tag>
      <tag>project-management</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Project Closure</title>

    <summary>A formal 7-step process to end a project: verify deliverable acceptance with signed artefacts, close financial and contract obligations, conduct lessons learned before the team disperses, archive all documentation, produce a final report, hand over to operations, and recognise the team. Closure applies equally to normal completion, cancelled projects, and phase-end gates in multi-phase programmes. Every checklist item is a record with status, owner, and evidence — not a checkbox that an agent can self-certify.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Projects without formal closure leave resources allocated to "finished" work, contracts accruing costs, access permissions open, and institutional knowledge lost when teams scatter. The most-skipped phase is the most expensive omission: a missed handover creates operational incidents; a missed lessons-learned session means the next project repeats the same errors.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Project objectives met and final deliverables accepted (normal closure).</item>
        <item>Project cancelled mid-flight — still close formally to recover value, release resources, capture lessons.</item>
        <item>Phase-end of a multi-phase programme before the next phase receives funding.</item>
        <item>Agency engagement final invoice and warranty handover.</item>
        <item>Absorption of a legacy project into BAU operations.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Project still has open scope, unresolved issues, or unsigned acceptance — resolve those first.</item>
        <item>Operational or run-rate work with no defined endpoint — use service transition documents instead.</item>
        <item>Long-tail support work after handover — that is operations, not project closure.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="step-1-verify-deliverable-acceptance">
      <p>Obtain written sign-off from the accepting authority for every deliverable before declaring the project closed. Silence does not equal acceptance.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Obtain written sign-off from the accepting authority for every deliverable before declaring the project closed. Silence does not equal acceptance.</statement>
        <rationale>Ambiguous completion status creates re-opened projects, warranty disputes, and resource limbo. A signed artefact is the only auditable evidence of acceptance.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Acceptance criteria must be observable and agreed before closure starts — they cannot be written retrospectively to match the delivered output.</statement>
        <rationale>Retrospective criteria are subjective and always pass; they destroy the value of the gate.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-2-administrative-closure">
      <p>Complete financial, resource, and contract closure activities to release allocated capital and permissions.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Financial: process final invoices, close purchase orders, return unused budget, reconcile final costs (flag delayed net-60 vendor invoices as pending — do not auto-zero).</item>
        <item>Resource: release team members, return equipment, revoke access permissions, notify resource managers.</item>
        <item>Contract: send termination letters, archive agreements, complete warranty/support handover.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Sequence access revocation after operations handover acknowledgement — never revoke before the receiving team confirms readiness.</statement>
        <rationale>Premature access revocation during handover breaks ongoing operations and is harder to reverse than to delay.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-3-lessons-learned">
      <p>Capture lessons and root causes while the team is still available and memories are fresh.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Conduct the lessons learned session before the team disperses, not after. Schedule it at project kickoff as a fixed deliverable.</statement>
        <rationale>Memories fade within days and teams scatter to new projects within hours of a delivery. A lesson-learned session two weeks post-close captures platitudes, not facts.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Store lessons in a queryable format (structured YAML or database), not in a slide deck. Each lesson: what happened, root cause, recommendation, project context.</statement>
        <rationale>Slide decks are never searched; structured lessons are findable by project type, risk category, or team name.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="steps-4-7-archive-report-transition-recognise">
      <p>Finalize and hand over project artefacts, produce the final report, transition operations, and recognize team contributions.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Archive project documents in a structure that matches future search intent: Planning, Execution, Technical, Contracts, Closure. Tag with project type and key outcomes.</statement>
        <rationale>Unstructured archives are effectively deleted — nobody finds them. Structure by intended reuse, not by creation order.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Decommission infrastructure in stages: read-only first, then revoke writes, then deprovision. Default to 30-day soft-delete before hard deletion.</statement>
        <rationale>Staged decommission allows recovery if handover is incomplete. Hard-deletion of cloud resources without a hold period risks irreversible data loss.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Include a team recognition event. Budget it from kickoff as a project line item, not as an afterthought when budgets are exhausted.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping recognition damages future engagement and signals that completion is the PM's success, not the team's.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="closure-types">
      <p>Four closure variants apply to different project end-states:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Normal — objectives met, full closure process applies.</item>
        <item>Early (success) — objectives met ahead of schedule, accelerated closure with same gate sequence.</item>
        <item>Early (cancelled) — document completed work percentage, recover reusable assets, record cancellation rationale formally to prevent same idea resurfacing without learning.</item>
        <item>Integration — project absorbed into operations, transition-focused closure with extra emphasis on runbooks, monitoring handover, and CMDB updates.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>For cancelled projects, document the cancellation rationale in a signed document with the sponsor's name. An informal "we changed direction" leaves the next team without context.</statement>
        <rationale>Cancelled project rationale is the most frequently lost institutional knowledge; it reappears as the same initiative 18 months later with the same failure mode.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <p>Common failure modes when agents conduct closure independently:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent marks closure complete based on issue-tracker "Done" state alone.</description>
        <reason>Done status is self-reported by the team. Acceptance requires a signed artefact from the accepting authority — a different party with independent verification.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent generates lessons learned from ticket history and meeting minutes without human contribution.</description>
        <reason>Agent-generated lessons are pattern-matched platitudes from training data, not project-specific facts. Require quoted contributions attributed to named participants.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent sets final cost to zero because no open invoices appear in the system.</description>
        <reason>Net-60 vendor invoices arrive after project close. Final cost must be flagged as "pending invoices" until the invoice window closes, not auto-zeroed.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent publishes the closure packet without access control.</description>
        <reason>Closure packets contain salaries, vendor rates, and customer data. Restrict access before agents publish or distribute.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow-and-recommended-agents">
      <p>A subagent walks the closure checklist, audits current state of contracts, costs, accesses, and documentation, and produces a closure packet (final report, lessons summary, handover document, archive index). The agent never marks closure complete — it produces the artefacts and a checklist that the PM and sponsor sign off. Treat closure as data: each checklist item is a YAML record with status, owner, evidence link. Tie closure into the SDD lifecycle: feature folder moves in-progress/ → done/ only after closure tasks are green. Pair with Lessons Learned methodology for retrospective facilitation.</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-pm-agent — drives checklist, drafts final report.</item>
        <item>faion-improver — runs lessons-learned facilitation prompts; mines patterns across closures.</item>
        <item>faion-business-analyst — verifies every requirement traces to an accepted deliverable.</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — moves SDD feature folder to done/ after closure pass.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Prompt pattern: inputs include charter.md, scope_baseline.md, schedule_baseline.csv, budget_baseline.csv, current_status.md, deliverables.yaml, contracts.yaml, accesses.yaml. Output: closure_packet/ containing final_report.md, acceptance_log.md, handover.md, archive_index.md, closure_checklist.yaml. Each checklist item includes: id, name, status (pending|done|na), owner, evidence_url, blocker.</p>
      <p>Audit closure_checklist.yaml against today's state: report items where status=done but no evidence_url, or pending with no blocker reason. Output: critical-path open items only.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Command-line tools for closure automation:</p>
      <list>
        <item>gh, glab, jira-cli — Close issues, archive milestones, export ticket history.</item>
        <item>az devops, ado-rest — Close iterations and work items in ADO.</item>
        <item>git archive / git bundle — Archive code repository state at closure.</item>
        <item>pandoc — Render final report → DOCX/PDF for sponsor sign-off.</item>
        <item>aws s3 sync / gsutil rsync / azcopy — Move artefacts to long-term cold storage.</item>
        <item>op (1Password CLI) — Revoke project-scoped credentials.</item>
        <item>terraform destroy — Decommission temporary infra cleanly.</item>
        <item>docusign-cli — Collect electronic acceptance signatures.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Services and SaaS platforms with agent-friendly APIs for closure:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Atlassian Confluence (SaaS, REST API) — Archive page tree; mark space read-only.</item>
        <item>Notion (SaaS, REST API) — Project DB, change status to "Closed".</item>
        <item>DocuSign / Adobe Sign (SaaS, REST API) — Acceptance form signatures.</item>
        <item>ServiceNow (SaaS, Table API) — Operations handover ticket; CMDB updates.</item>
        <item>Jira / ADO / GitHub Projects (SaaS, REST/GraphQL) — Close epics, archive boards.</item>
        <item>1Password (SaaS, op CLI) — Revoke project vault access.</item>
        <item>AWS / GCP / Azure (SaaS, provider CLIs) — Decommission infra; budget alerts.</item>
        <item>Sharepoint / Google Drive (SaaS, Graph / Drive API) — Archive document library, set retention.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Schedule closure at kickoff: it's a deliverable, not an afterthought.</item>
        <item>Acceptance criteria must be observable and signed before closure starts; ambiguous "looks good" causes drift.</item>
        <item>Run lessons-learned before the team disperses; afterwards memories fade and the room scatters.</item>
        <item>Decommission infrastructure in stages: first read-only, then revoke writes, then deprovision; reverts are easier early.</item>
        <item>Archive code with a tagged release named closure-&lt;project&gt; for forensic recovery.</item>
        <item>Recover salvageable assets (designs, components, datasets) into a reusable library before deletion.</item>
        <item>Celebrate. Skipping recognition damages future engagement; budget a small line item from kickoff.</item>
        <item>For cancelled projects, document cancellation rationale formally — it prevents the same idea resurfacing without learning.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/closure-checklist.md" purpose="Complete closure checklist with all required items grouped by category"/>
      <template path="templates/deliverable-acceptance.md" purpose="Deliverable acceptance form with criteria table and signature block"/>
      <template path="templates/handover.md" purpose="Operations handover document: system overview, docs, support contacts, known issues"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="templates/closure-audit.py" purpose="Python auditor: validates closure_checklist.yaml completeness and evidence links"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards/foundational/PMBOK"/>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/75939"/>
      <link href="https://www.axelos.com/certifications/prince2"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
