<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Context-Switch Protocol — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every solo founder day must enforce. These are HARD rules — fascinating Twitter, urgent-seeming DMs, and curiosity cannot override them.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The day MUST run three named modes — Builder, Operator, Inbox — in fixed order. Builder ALWAYS comes first; Inbox NEVER comes before Builder.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cal Newport Deep Work + Mark/Gloria Cost of Interrupted Work research (CHI 2008)">Inbox-first wrecks the morning attentional window; the order is the entire mechanism.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Inside a Builder block, ALL notification channels MUST be silenced at OS level: no Slack badge, no email pull, no Stripe SMS, no Twitter glance. Phone is in another room or face-down on do-not-disturb.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mark et al., Switch! Reading Email and IM — recovery time = 23 min per interruption">A single notification check inside a Builder block costs ~23 minutes of recovery; the silence rule is the cheapest possible protection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each block MUST end with a 5-minute handoff note answering three questions: "what was open?", "what is the next decision?", "what must the next mode remember?". Block transitions without the note are violations.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cognitive offloading + handoff-quality research">Re-loading mental state at the start of a block costs 10–20 minutes; the note costs 5 and recovers the rest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>"Urgent" items discovered inside a Builder block MUST be written to the next Operator block's inbox; they cannot trigger an inline switch unless they fit the documented incident-override list (P0 outage, charge dispute, security incident).</statement>
      <rationale source="Eisenhower-matrix / urgency-import distinction + customer-perception research">Most "urgent" customer messages are not urgent on a 4-hour latency; an explicit override list keeps the founder honest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The protocol MUST be reviewed weekly: count of block violations + count of urgency-override invocations. A trend of ≥3 violations/week for 2 consecutive weeks triggers a structural fix (lengthen Operator block, hire support, scope cut), not a willpower attempt.</statement>
      <rationale source="Systems-thinking discipline (Deming / Senge) — behaviour problems are usually system problems">Repeat violations are signals that the block sizing is wrong, not that the founder is weak.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Anchored day">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
date: 2026-05-20
blocks:
  - mode: builder
    window: 09:00-12:00
    notifications: silenced
    handoff_note: |
      Open: checkout-retry logic, branch fix/retry-422.
      Next decision: choose exponential vs fixed backoff (lean exp).
      Operator must: remember new env var STRIPE_RETRY_MAX=5.
  - mode: operator
    window: 13:00-15:00
    handoff_note: |
      Open: 2 customer DMs replied; refund #482 issued.
      Next decision: write up the data-export FAQ (parked).
      Builder must: nothing pending.
  - mode: inbox
    window: 15:00-16:00
violations_today: 0
]]></code>
      <note>Order respected, notifications off, handoff notes present, no violations.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Un-anchored day">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Woke up, checked Twitter, replied to two DMs, opened email, saw a bug report, tried to code but kept checking Slack. Half-finished by 7pm."
]]></code>
      <note>Inbox-first, no silence, no handoff, no review. The classic solo-founder day-pattern that produces 8 hours of motion and 90 minutes of progress.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="../solo-burnout-tripwires/" />
    <link path="../../sdd/daily-ship-rubric/" />
  </see-also>
</text>
