<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="API Gateway Patterns &amp; Technology Selection Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every api-gateway-patterns application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use simple routing when the architecture has a direct mapping between client requests and backend services with minimal transformation needed and a single client type or uniform client needs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Simple routing avoids operational overhead of BFF or aggregation patterns. Adding patterns prematurely creates maintenance burden without benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use BFF when different clients have vastly different data needs, mobile needs optimized payloads, third-party integrations require different contracts, or different security requirements exist per client type.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A single gateway serving all clients tends to accumulate client-specific logic and becomes a bottleneck; BFF pushes that complexity to per-client surfaces owned by the teams that know those clients.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use aggregation when reducing client-side complexity is a primary goal, when minimizing network round trips matters (mobile, low-bandwidth), or when creating composite API views from independently deployed services.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without aggregation, clients make N parallel requests; mobile clients on slow links feel latency multiplied by the number of services. Aggregation at the gateway trades gateway complexity for client simplicity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use edge+mesh when services require mutual TLS between them, when fine-grained traffic management between services is needed, or when a zero-trust security model is required. Do NOT use a service mesh for a simple two-tier app — the operational overhead is substantial.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The mesh handles east-west (service-to-service) while the gateway handles north-south (client-to-gateway). Combining them avoids duplicating concerns at both layers.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-document-alternatives" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every gateway selection MUST document at least one rejected alternative with a one-sentence reason. Selections without rejected alternatives are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="ATAM rejection-rationale; ADR best practice">Without rejected alternatives the ADR is decision laundering and provides no audit value.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-23 chunk-00 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
