<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Decompose business goals into product outcomes, leading indicators, and falsifiable experiments. Confidence levels, not dates. Audience-specific roadmap artifacts.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>roadmap</tag>
      <tag>outcome-decomposition</tag>
      <tag>business-goals</tag>
      <tag>product-strategy</tag>
      <tag>stakeholder-communication</tag>
      <tag>confidence-levels</tag>
      <tag>experiments</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <applies-to>both</applies-to>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
    <requires>
      <ref slug="outcome-based-roadmaps"/>
      <ref slug="roadmap-design"/>
    </requires>
    <related>
      <ref slug="okr-setting"/>
      <ref slug="product-discovery"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Outcome-Based Roadmaps (Advanced)</title>

    <summary>Advanced outcome roadmapping closes the gap between high-level business goals and the product experiments that move them. The autonomous-agent skill: take a stated business goal (e.g. "increase revenue 20%") and produce (a) a four-layer decomposition tree (Business Goal → Product Outcome → Leading Indicator → Experiment), (b) pre-registered success criteria for every experiment, (c) confidence labels (High / Medium / Low / Exploring) instead of dates, and (d) four audience-tailored roadmap artifacts (customer, board, engineering, sales) emitted from a single source of truth. Use this methodology whenever stakeholders demand specific features and dates while the team must own metric outcomes — the most common pressure scenario for product teams in 2026.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Stakeholders who receive feature timelines will always hold the team to dates. Stakeholders who receive outcome metrics accept a range of solutions and hold the team to results instead. The shift from "feature owner" to "outcome architect" is the most critical PM skill evolution for 2026, driven by board-level expectation that product teams own revenue and profitability metrics, not just delivery velocity. Autonomous coding agents preparing roadmap artifacts must therefore enforce two invariants: (1) every roadmap item links upward to a measurable business goal through an explicit causal chain, and (2) every artifact is rendered for the audience that will consume it, never as a single document.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Trigger A — Stakeholder pressure: a board member, sales lead, or customer demands "what features ship in Q2 with dates" while the team has agreed to outcome ownership. Run this methodology to convert the demand into an outcome conversation.</item>
        <item>Trigger B — OKR decomposition: the company has just published a quarterly or annual OKR (e.g. "increase ARR 20%") and the product team must translate it into experiments that could plausibly move it.</item>
        <item>Trigger C — Quarterly roadmap presentation: roadmap is due in N days for multiple audiences (board, customers, engineering, sales). Run this methodology to emit four artifacts from one source.</item>
        <item>Trigger D — Roadmap drift: features ship on schedule but business metrics do not move. Run this methodology to rebuild the roadmap around outcomes and force-rank by leading-indicator impact.</item>
        <item>Trigger E — After basic roadmap-design has been adopted but the team has not yet introduced outcome decomposition, leading indicators, or audience segmentation.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF where there are no product outcomes to track yet — too early for decomposition. Use product-discovery and continuous-discovery instead.</item>
        <item>Compliance, regulatory, or operational work where the outcome is dictated by an external party, not hypothesized.</item>
        <item>Teams without any analytics instrumentation — outcome roadmaps require measurable leading indicators. Instrument first, then return.</item>
        <item>One-off internal tools or migrations where the success criterion is binary completion, not a metric movement.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <how-to>
      <p>Follow these eight steps in order. Each step has an explicit input, output, and verification check the agent can perform before moving on.</p>

      <step>1. Capture the business goal verbatim. Input: the goal as stated by the executive or board (e.g. "increase revenue 20% by EOY 2026"). Output: a single sentence with a metric, current value, target value, and deadline horizon. Verification: ask "is this falsifiable on a date?" — if no, refine until yes.</step>
      <step>2. Generate two to four candidate product outcomes that, if achieved, would plausibly move the business goal. Each outcome must have a metric, current value, target value, and a one-sentence causal hypothesis ("reducing churn from 8% to 5% increases revenue because retained users compound LTV"). Verification: each outcome metric exists in the analytics system today.</step>
      <step>3. For every product outcome, define exactly one leading indicator that moves earlier than the outcome itself. The leading indicator must be a metric the team can read weekly, not just at quarter-end. Verification: the leading indicator has a known correlation or mechanism with the outcome — write it in one line.</step>
      <step>4. For every product outcome, list two to four candidate experiments. Each experiment must have a name, a hypothesis ("if we do X, Y% of users will Z"), and pre-registered success criteria. Verification: success criteria are written before any experiment starts; for samples ≥ 1000 use statistical significance at p&lt;0.05; for smaller samples use a practical-significance threshold (e.g. "TTV drops from 3 days to 1 day in cohort N").</step>
      <step>5. Assign a confidence label to every experiment and to the parent outcome: High, Medium, Low, or Exploring. Replace any date with a confidence label plus the conditions that would promote it ("High confidence for Q2 if discovery completes by end of March"). Verification: zero hard dates appear in the artifact except for the business-goal deadline horizon.</step>
      <step>6. Emit four audience-specific artifacts from the decomposition tree: customer, board, engineering, sales. Use the audience-specific rules in the section below to filter and reformat. Verification: each artifact contains only the fields permitted for its audience.</step>
      <step>7. Stress-test the tree against the four pressure techniques (confidence levels, options framing, lead with data, why-before-what). Verification: simulate a stakeholder asking "when will feature X ship?" and confirm the tree produces a confidence-plus-condition answer, not a date.</step>
      <step>8. Persist the source-of-truth tree as a single Markdown file (use templates/outcome-decomposition.md). Verification: regenerating any audience artifact from the tree produces an identical document — the tree is the only authority.</step>
    </how-to>

    <checklist>
      <check>Business goal stated as one sentence with metric, current value, target value, and deadline horizon.</check>
      <check>Each product outcome has metric, current value, target value, and a written causal hypothesis.</check>
      <check>Each product outcome has exactly one leading indicator with a one-line causal mechanism.</check>
      <check>Each experiment has a name, hypothesis, and pre-registered success criteria.</check>
      <check>Experiments with sample ≥ 1000 specify statistical significance at p&lt;0.05.</check>
      <check>Experiments with sample &lt; 1000 specify a practical-significance threshold.</check>
      <check>Every experiment and outcome carries a confidence label (High / Medium / Low / Exploring).</check>
      <check>No hard dates appear except the business-goal deadline horizon.</check>
      <check>Four audience artifacts (customer, board, engineering, sales) are emitted from one source tree.</check>
      <check>Customer artifact uses theme-based abstractions and horizon labels (e.g. "H1 2026"), not dates.</check>
      <check>Board artifact leads with outcome metrics and quarterly targets, no feature lists.</check>
      <check>Engineering artifact includes outcome targets, confidence levels, sprint-level Now detail, and options for Next.</check>
      <check>Sales artifact leads with problem-solution framing and confidence signals; only High-confidence items appear when deals close within 90 days.</check>
      <check>Source-of-truth tree is a single file; audience artifacts are derived, never authored independently.</check>
    </checklist>

    <section name="outcome-decomposition">
      <p>Rules for decomposing a business goal into product outcomes, leading indicators, and experiments — the core PM skill that connects roadmap items to measurable business impact. An autonomous agent must produce this tree before drafting any audience artifact.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Decompose business goals in this chain: Business Goal → Product Outcome → Leading Indicator → Experiment. Each layer must be causally plausible, not just correlated, and the agent must write the mechanism in one sentence per edge.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping layers produces roadmaps where features connect loosely to goals. The chain forces the team to articulate the mechanism: "If we improve onboarding (product outcome), TTV drops (leading indicator), which should reduce churn (business goal)."</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Define success criteria for each experiment before running it. For samples with 1000+ users require statistical significance at p&lt;0.05; for smaller samples require a practical-significance threshold expressed as an absolute or relative metric movement.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-hoc success criteria are subject to confirmation bias. Pre-defined criteria make the experiment falsifiable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Reject any roadmap item whose link to a leading indicator is "we believe it helps." Force a written causal mechanism or drop the item.</statement>
        <rationale>Belief without mechanism is the source of feature factories. Every kept item must answer "what changes in user behavior, and how does that move the metric?"</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Example: Business Goal Decomposition">
        <note>Business goal "increase revenue 20%" decomposed into two product outcomes, each with leading indicators and pre-registered experiments. This is the canonical shape an autonomous agent should produce.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Business Goal: Increase revenue 20% by EOY 2026
  Current: $4.0M ARR | Target: $4.8M ARR | Horizon: H2 2026

  Product Outcome 1: Reduce churn from 8% to 5%
    Causal hypothesis: retained users compound LTV → ARR up
    Leading Indicator: NPS improvement (proxy for retention intent)
      Current 32 → Target 45, read weekly on cohort surveys
    Experiments:
      - Onboarding redesign
        Hypothesis: reduces activation time by 40%
        Success: TTV 3d → 1d, p<0.05, sample ≥ 1200 (High confidence)
      - Re-engagement email sequence
        Hypothesis: 15% win-back rate on dormant 30d cohort
        Success: ≥12% reactivation in 14d window (Medium confidence)

  Product Outcome 2: Increase activation rate from 25% to 40%
    Causal hypothesis: more activated users → more paid conversions
    Leading Indicator: Time-to-value (TTV) reduction
      Current 3d → Target 1d, read weekly on new-user cohorts
    Experiments:
      - Guided tour for new users (Medium)
      - Personalized feature suggestions by role (Exploring)
    Success Criteria: TTV from 3 days to 1 day, measured on cohorts
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Antipattern: Feature roadmap pretending to be outcome roadmap">
        <note>Common failure: the team labels columns "Outcome" but fills them with feature names. There is no metric, no leading indicator, no hypothesis. An autonomous agent must reject this shape and demand the four-layer tree.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Outcome: Better onboarding         <-- not an outcome, no metric
  - Redesign signup flow
  - Add welcome email
  - Build tutorial widget          <-- features, no hypothesis, no success criteria
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <p>The PM Role Shift:</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Present yourself as "architect of impact," not "owner of the roadmap." The roadmap is the artifact; the outcome is the job.</statement>
        <rationale>PMs who identify as roadmap owners defend features. PMs who identify as outcome architects drop features that are not moving the metric and replace them — which is the right behavior.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="audience-segmentation">
      <p>Stakeholder communication matrix showing what each audience needs from a roadmap artifact and why the same document cannot serve all audiences. The agent emits four artifacts from the single decomposition tree.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Create separate roadmap artifacts for each audience from one source. Never share the same document with all stakeholders.</statement>
        <rationale>Engineering needs sprint-level detail and dependencies. Customers need capability descriptions without implementation specifics. The board needs outcome metrics with quarterly targets. Sales needs problem-solution framing with a confidence signal. One document that serves all serves none.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>External / customer-facing roadmaps: use theme-based abstractions, no specific dates — use "H1 2026" or "Coming Soon" horizon labels instead.</statement>
        <rationale>Specific dates become contractual commitments in customers' minds. Abstracted horizons communicate direction without creating support escalations when dates slip.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Board / executive roadmaps: lead with outcome metrics and quarterly targets. Include confidence levels. Do not include feature lists — executives need to know if the product will hit the business goal, not which features ship in Q2.</statement>
        <rationale>Boards are accountable for business outcomes. A feature list answer to a business goal question signals misalignment between product and strategy.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Engineering roadmaps: include outcome targets, confidence levels, sprint-level detail for Now, and options (not THE solution) for Next. Dependencies and blockers must be explicit.</statement>
        <rationale>Engineers who understand the outcome can propose better solutions. Options framing ("we have three approaches to this outcome") produces better technical decisions than feature mandates.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Sales roadmaps: lead with the problem being solved, then the solution. Include a confidence signal ("confident", "exploring"). Only include items you can commit to when deals close within 90 days.</statement>
        <rationale>Sales uses roadmaps to close deals. Uncommitted items that end up on sales decks create product commitments the team cannot honor.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="managing-roadmap-pressure">
      <p>Four techniques for responding to stakeholder pressure for specific features or dates while maintaining an outcome-based orientation. The agent should rehearse all four against a hypothetical "when does X ship?" question before sharing any artifact.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Confidence Levels Instead of Commitments. Replace date commitments with confidence levels (High / Medium / Low / Exploring). When pressed for dates, provide a confidence level plus the conditions that would promote it to "high."</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholders accept uncertainty more readily when it is named and bounded. "High confidence for Q2 if discovery completes by end of March" is more credible than a date that will slip silently.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Options Framing. Present options, not THE solution: "We have three approaches to achieving this outcome. Here are the trade-offs." Then ask the stakeholder to choose based on priorities.</statement>
        <rationale>Options framing positions the PM as a strategic partner, not a feature factory. Stakeholders who choose an option own the trade-off — they are less likely to escalate when the deprioritized option is not built.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Lead with Data. When presenting a priority order, lead with the data and outcome before the "what." "Churn is our top metric risk this quarter; here is why we are prioritizing retention over new features."</statement>
        <rationale>Feature arguments are subjective; metric arguments are objective. Data-led framing shifts the conversation from "I want X" to "will X move the metric?"</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Show the Why Before the What. Structure every roadmap presentation: outcome we are targeting → evidence it matters → options we considered → what we chose and why → confidence level. Never start with the feature list.</statement>
        <rationale>Starting with the feature list invites feature negotiation. Starting with the outcome invites metric discussion. The latter produces better decisions faster.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-prompts">
      <p>Reusable LLM prompts an autonomous agent can run to generate or audit each layer of the tree. Each prompt expects the prior layer as input and returns a structured fragment.</p>

      <prompt purpose="Decompose a business goal into product outcomes">
<![CDATA[
You are an outcome architect. Given the business goal below, propose 2-4 product
outcomes that, if achieved, would plausibly move it.

Business goal: {{business_goal}}
Current value: {{current_value}}
Target value: {{target_value}}
Horizon: {{horizon}}

For each product outcome return JSON with fields:
  - name (string)
  - metric (string, must be measurable in current analytics)
  - current_value (number or string)
  - target_value (number or string)
  - causal_hypothesis (one sentence linking the outcome to the goal mechanism)

Constraints:
  - Each outcome metric must be different from the business goal metric.
  - Reject any outcome where the causal mechanism is "we believe it helps."
]]>
      </prompt>

      <prompt purpose="Generate leading indicator and experiments for one outcome">
<![CDATA[
Given this product outcome, return:
  1. exactly one leading indicator (metric readable weekly, with current/target
     and a one-line mechanism linking it to the outcome).
  2. 2-4 candidate experiments. For each experiment include:
       name, hypothesis (if X then Y% of users Z),
       sample_size_estimate, success_criteria, confidence
       (High | Medium | Low | Exploring).

Outcome: {{outcome_json}}

Rules:
  - Sample >= 1000 must specify statistical significance at p<0.05.
  - Sample <  1000 must specify a practical-significance threshold
    (absolute or relative metric movement).
  - Success criteria are pre-registered and falsifiable.
  - At most one experiment may carry High confidence.
]]>
      </prompt>

      <prompt purpose="Render audience artifact from the source tree">
<![CDATA[
Render the decomposition tree below as a roadmap artifact for audience
{{audience}} (one of: customer, board, engineering, sales).

Tree: {{tree_markdown}}

Audience filters:
  - customer:    theme-based abstractions, horizon labels only
                 (no exact dates), no implementation details.
  - board:       outcome metrics + quarterly targets + confidence;
                 no feature list.
  - engineering: outcome targets, confidence, sprint-level Now,
                 options for Next, explicit dependencies.
  - sales:       problem-solution framing, confidence signal,
                 only High-confidence items committable in 90 days.

Output as Markdown. Include only fields permitted for the audience.
]]>
      </prompt>

      <prompt purpose="Pressure simulation — when will feature X ship?">
<![CDATA[
A stakeholder asks: "When will {{feature_name}} ship?"

Using only the decomposition tree below, return an answer that:
  - Names the parent outcome and leading indicator.
  - States a confidence level instead of a date.
  - Lists the conditions that would promote confidence to High.
  - Offers options if the stakeholder wants to accelerate.

Tree: {{tree_markdown}}

Forbidden: hard dates, "soon," "next quarter probably."
]]>
      </prompt>
    </section>

    <verify>
      <step>Run the structural checklist (above). Every check must be ticked before sharing any artifact.</step>
      <step>Self-audit query: paste the decomposition tree to an LLM with the prompt "find every roadmap item whose link to a leading indicator is asserted but not mechanistically explained." Fix every flagged item.</step>
      <step>Pressure simulation: ask "when will [feature X] ship?" against each audience artifact. The answer must contain a confidence label and promotion conditions, never a hard date (except the business-goal horizon).</step>
      <step>Source-of-truth check: regenerate one audience artifact from the tree using the rendering prompt; diff against the saved artifact. Any non-formatting drift means the artifact was edited out-of-band — discard and regenerate.</step>
      <step>Validate the methodology XML itself with the repository validator before committing changes:</step>
    </verify>

    <commands>
      <command name="validate-methodology">python3 scripts/validate-methodology-xml.py skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced/methodology.xml</command>
      <command name="validate-all-knowledge">python3 scripts/validate-methodology-xml.py --all</command>
    </commands>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/outcome-decomposition.md" purpose="Outcome decomposition tree: business goal → product outcomes → leading indicators → experiments. Single source of truth from which the four audience artifacts are rendered."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="outcome-based-roadmaps"/>
      <ref slug="okr-setting"/>
      <ref slug="roadmap-design"/>
      <ref slug="product-discovery"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
