<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="KPI Drift Alarm Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules with rationale + source for kpi-drift-alarm-template. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="baseline-rolling-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each KPI MUST have a rolling baseline of at least 4 cycles; baselines shorter than 4 cycles are auto-rejected as noisy.</statement>
      <rationale source="Statistical drift research">Statistical drift research — applies to KPI Drift Alarm Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="threshold-explicit-direction" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deviation threshold MUST specify direction (above / below / either); thresholds without direction are forbidden because drift can be benign or malignant per direction.</statement>
      <rationale source="KPI design practice">KPI design practice — applies to KPI Drift Alarm Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="two-class-alarm" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Alarms MUST be two-class: warning (1 sigma deviation) + critical (2 sigma deviation); single-class alarms produce alarm fatigue.</statement>
      <rationale source="Site reliability engineering">Site reliability engineering — applies to KPI Drift Alarm Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="suppression-after-fire" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After firing, an alarm is suppressed for a defined window (default 1 cycle) to avoid storm; suppression window MUST be configured per KPI.</statement>
      <rationale source="Alert storm prevention">Alert storm prevention — applies to KPI Drift Alarm Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="escalation-after-repeat" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the same alarm fires for 3 consecutive cycles, escalation routes it to a named owner; silent re-firing is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Escalation-discipline practice">Escalation-discipline practice — applies to KPI Drift Alarm Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="alarm-includes-data-link" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every alarm message MUST include a deep link to the underlying chart / query; alarms without data context are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Alert quality practice">Alert quality practice — applies to KPI Drift Alarm Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="post-resolution-log" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every fired alarm MUST be closed with a written resolution (root cause, action taken); open alarms older than 1 cycle escalate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Incident-management practice">Incident-management practice — applies to KPI Drift Alarm Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If KPI history is shorter than 4 cycles or no on-call coverage exists, return `skipped`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to KPI Drift Alarm Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
