<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Product-Led Growth (PLG) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Product-Led Growth (PLG) plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="aha-moment-under-five-minutes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The product MUST deliver its aha moment within 5 minutes of first sign-in; activation flows exceeding the cap MUST be redesigned or fail PLG readiness review.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenView — Product Benchmarks 2024">Median first-session length on freemium SaaS is 6 minutes; aha after 5 minutes drops activation by half per minute.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pql-scoring-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every PLG product MUST score Product-Qualified Leads on real usage signals (workspace count, integration count, invited collaborators, depth events); intent signals alone MUST NOT qualify.</statement>
      <rationale source="Wes Bush — Product-Led Growth (2019)">Intent-only signals (email opens, demo requests) are MQL noise; PQL must reflect actual product engagement to predict expansion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-mandatory-sales-call-for-paid-conversion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Self-serve paid tiers MUST be reachable without a mandatory sales call; sales-assist is offered, not gated.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenView PLG playbook">Mandatory sales gates kill self-serve velocity; PLG funnels require frictionless paid conversion with optional sales-assist for high-value accounts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="in-product-upgrade-triggers" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Upgrade prompts MUST fire on hitting a usage limit (not on calendar cadence); calendar-driven upgrade emails are forbidden for PLG accounts.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenView — PLG benchmarks 2024">Calendar prompts are spam; limit-hit prompts are contextual and convert 4-7x higher per OpenView benchmarks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="freemium-has-real-job-to-be-done" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The free tier MUST be sufficient to complete at least one core job-to-be-done end-to-end; freemium that crippleware-blocks the core JTBD MUST be redesigned.</statement>
      <rationale source="Wes Bush — Product-Led Growth (2019)">Crippleware freemium trains users that the product cannot do the job; the JTBD-complete free tier is the engine of word-of-mouth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
