<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-plg-principles" title="Product-Led Growth: Core Principles and Metrics">
  <summary>Four PLG core principles, 2026 target metrics (activation rate, TTV, PQL, expansion revenue rate, NRR), and the PLG evolution toward hybrid PLG + sales-assist for enterprise.</summary>

  <section title="Core Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build PLG on four principles: self-serve onboarding (users activate without sales intervention), time-to-value optimization ("aha moment" under 5 minutes), product virality (built-in sharing and collaboration), and expansion revenue (upsell through usage, not sales calls).</statement>
      <rationale>PLG companies achieve higher revenue per employee because the product replaces costly sales motion at the SMB/prosumer tier; without all four principles the loop is incomplete — viral without self-serve requires human handoff, expansion without a usage gate requires sales calls.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Metrics (2026 Targets)">
    <list>
      <item>Activation Rate: % users completing key value actions — target above 40%</item>
      <item>Time-to-Value (TTV): minutes to "aha moment" — target under 5 minutes</item>
      <item>Product Qualified Leads (PQLs): users showing buying signals — track weekly</item>
      <item>Expansion Revenue Rate: revenue from self-serve upgrades — target above 30% of total</item>
      <item>Net Revenue Retention (NRR): revenue retained plus expansion — target above 120%</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define activation as the smallest event sequence that predicts D30 retention, then back-test on historical cohorts before locking the metric. Vanity activation rates that do not predict retention drive wrong optimizations.</statement>
      <rationale>Winning variants on activation can cannibalise D30 retention if activation is defined as "completed onboarding tour" rather than "reached core value". The back-test is the safeguard.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="PLG Onboarding Pattern">
    <list>
      <item>SSO/social login — reduce step-one drop-off</item>
      <item>Interactive product tours, not documentation pages</item>
      <item>Progressive feature disclosure — no feature dump on first session</item>
      <item>Contextual tooltips at moment of relevance, not pre-emptive</item>
      <item>Personalized onboarding paths by user segment — 3-tour designs consistently beat 1-tour</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Bake usage limits into the free tier from day one. Without a friction edge, there is no upgrade trigger and expansion revenue stalls.</statement>
      <rationale>The "freemium tax" — free tier consuming infra cost but converting under 2% — is the direct consequence of a free tier with no usage gate. The upgrade trigger must exist in the product design, not in a sales email.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="PLG Evolution (2026)">
    <p>One-size-fits-all freemium is declining. The current pattern: tailored free tiers by user persona, AI-driven onboarding personalization, and hybrid PLG + sales-assist for enterprise segments above the SMB ceiling.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair PLG with sales-assist above the SMB ceiling — PLG expansion ceilings are real. The strategic question is when to add humans, not whether to add them.</statement>
      <rationale>PQLs surface at the SMB ceiling and stall without a human follow-up motion. Expansion revenue stalls when no sales-assist exists to close team-wide or enterprise contracts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
