<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-led-growth Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-led-growth as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Running PLG optimization on a pre-PMF product with insufficient retention signal.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PLG amplifies a working loop; on a broken product it industrialises churn. Establish product-market fit before instrumenting the PLG funnel.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>AI onboarding personalization attempting to reference user behavior data before any events have been captured (cold start in first 60 seconds).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Enforce a "no behavioural reference before event N" rule. Cold-start personalization that references unavailable data produces error messages or hallucinated user attributes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy regimes (GDPR, India DPDP) restricting event tracking that PLG analytics depend on, with consent-mode gaps distorting funnels.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Instrument consent-mode handling before running PLG analytics. Funnels measured without accounting for consent gaps systematically under-count users in regulated markets.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>"Freemium tax": free tier consumes infra cost but converts less than 2% — common when no usage-gated upgrade trigger exists.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a friction edge in the free tier, there is no upgrade trigger. The business model fails before the funnel optimization begins.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>TTV measured by clicks, not value: vanity activation rates that don't predict retention.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Optimizing on the wrong metric produces wrong interventions. Define activation as a retention-predictive event sequence, not a click count.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>One-size onboarding for distinct personas → low activation across all of them; segmentation is the unlock.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Personas have different value drivers. Single-tour designs lose to 3-tour designs almost every time.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Sales-assist gap: PQLs surface but no human follow-up motion → expansion revenue stalls at SMB ceiling.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PQLs without sales support don't convert to team/enterprise deals. Add sales-assist at the SMB-to-enterprise inflection point.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents over-fitting on small samples: calling a winner with fewer than 1k users per variant or fewer than 7 days of runtime.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Enforce the minimum exposure and runtime gates at the agent output layer, not just in the prompt. Agents will call winners on day 2 with 200 users per variant if not blocked.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs inventing metrics ("engagement score 0-100") that have no source event in the analytics schema.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Constrain output to a known event vocabulary loaded from the analytics schema. Invented metrics cannot be tracked or validated.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Tour-builder agents adding steps rather than removing them, even when prompted to optimize onboarding.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Prompt explicitly with "subtract first" and a step-count budget. Monitor step-count delta as a guardrail metric alongside activation rate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>PQL scoring drift: static model becomes wrong as the product evolves but continues to be used without recalibration.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Schedule quarterly PQL model recalibration as a standing SDD task. Flag if the model has not been recalibrated in 90+ days.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
