<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-project-structure" title="GitHub Projects Structure and Configuration">
  <summary>Project types, custom field setup, view configuration, and milestone integration for GitHub Projects v2.</summary>

  <section title="Project Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use GitHub Projects v2 (not classic) for all new projects; use organization-level projects for multi-repo work.</statement>
      <rationale>Projects v2 supports custom fields, iterations, cross-repo items, and table/board/roadmap views. Classic projects are limited to simple kanban with no custom fields.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Organization project: pulls issues from repo-A and repo-B into one board; each item carries a Repository field for filtering.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Fields">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define these standard custom fields at project creation: Status (single_select), Priority (P0–P3), Estimate (number), Sprint (iteration, 2-week duration), Team (single_select), Release (single_select).</statement>
      <rationale>Fields defined upfront give agents a stable schema; adding fields mid-project requires backfilling existing items.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/project-config.yaml">Project custom fields and views configuration</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Views Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create three standard views: Table (all issues, sort by Priority), Board (sprint filter, group by Status), Roadmap (group by Release, month zoom).</statement>
      <rationale>Table for triage, Board for sprint execution, Roadmap for stakeholder communication — three views cover 90% of PM needs without proliferating custom views.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Board view filter: sprint:@current — shows only current iteration items; WIP limits set per Status column.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Milestone Integration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use milestones for release-scoped work; use iteration fields for sprint-scoped work — do not conflate them.</statement>
      <rationale>Milestones track what ships in a release (v1.0, v1.1); iterations track what the team works on in a sprint. Mixing them makes both metrics inaccurate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Link PRs to issues with "Fixes #123" in the PR description to trigger auto-close and built-in workflow progression.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-close on merge fires the built-in "Item closed → Done" workflow without agent or manual intervention.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
