<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-automation" title="GitHub Projects Automation and Issue Templates">
  <summary>Built-in workflows, GitHub Actions automation, issue YAML templates, and GraphQL API patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Built-in Workflows">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable all five built-in workflows first before writing GitHub Actions: item added (→ Backlog), item reopened (→ Todo), item closed (→ Done), PR merged (→ Done), code review requested (→ In Review).</statement>
      <rationale>Built-in workflows are zero-maintenance; GitHub Actions should only be added for logic that built-in workflows cannot express.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="GitHub Actions Automation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a dedicated GitHub App (not personal access tokens) for Actions-driven project automation; request permissions: projects:write, issues:write, pull-requests:write explicitly in workflow YAML.</statement>
      <rationale>Personal tokens expire and are tied to individual accounts; GitHub Apps rotate automatically and do not break on person departure. Workflows without explicit permissions fail with 403 silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store the project node ID (PVT_* format) in a repository variable or secret — it never changes, unlike the human-readable project number.</statement>
      <rationale>GraphQL mutations require the node ID; the human-readable number is only used in URLs. Using the wrong identifier causes silent mutation failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/workflow-project-automation.yaml">GitHub Actions workflow for project automation</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Issue Templates">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use YAML issue templates (not Markdown) with required fields for problem statement and priority; add projects: ["myorg/1"] to auto-add issues to the project on creation.</statement>
      <rationale>YAML templates enforce required fields at creation time; Markdown templates allow empty submissions. Auto-adding to project on creation ensures no issues are missed in triage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/issue-feature.yaml">GitHub issue YAML template for feature requests</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="GraphQL API">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always resolve issue numbers to ProjectV2Item node IDs before any mutation; implement cursor-based pagination with pageInfo.hasNextPage for all item queries.</statement>
      <rationale>The ProjectV2Item node ID differs from the issue number; passing the wrong ID to a mutation fails silently. Queries without pagination silently return only the first 100 items.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/graphql-query-items.graphql">GraphQL query to fetch project items with field values</reference>
  </section>
</text>
