<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="competitor-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>market-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Systematic competitor study via SWOT-grid + market-share + portfolio scorecard. Produces board-ready artifacts: share in 5% buckets, per-SWOT-cell citation URLs, strategic-group maps.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>competitor-analysis</tag>
      <tag>swot</tag>
      <tag>market-share</tag>
      <tag>portfolio-scorecard</tag>
      <tag>strategic-group</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Competitor Analysis</title>
    <summary>Competitor analysis is the systematic study of businesses competing for the same customers, structured as a SWOT-grid + market-share estimation + portfolio scorecard workflow. The market-researcher variant produces defensible board-ready artifacts — share in 5% buckets, per-SWOT-cell citation URLs, strategic-group maps with pre-committed axes — rather than feature-level positioning advice.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Without a structured framework, teams either ignore competitors or obsess over them without evidence. SWOT cells fabricated from brand familiarity rather than sourced observations lead to false confidence in competitive position. Forcing one citation URL per SWOT cell, rounding share to 5% buckets, and running a devil's-advocate pass eliminates the most common failure modes and produces artifacts that hold up in investor due diligence.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Annual strategy review: scoring 8-15 named competitors on a SWOT grid as input to a board or strategy deck.</item>
        <item>Market-share estimation: producing defensible "X holds ~N% of category Y" claims from public proxies.</item>
        <item>Portfolio benchmarking: comparing a product line against 3-7 incumbents on a fixed quarterly scorecard.</item>
        <item>M&amp;A or partnership shortlist: ranking acquisition targets by SWOT fit and relative strategic-group position.</item>
        <item>Investor due diligence: evidence-backed competitor matrix for a Series A/B deck.</item>
        <item>Win-loss debrief input: cross-referencing lost deals with competitor SWOT.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-feature spec or pricing-page rewrite — use the researcher variant; SWOT/share is overkill.</item>
        <item>Pre-MVP idea triage with no named competitors — use idea-generation-methods or niche-evaluation first.</item>
        <item>Real-time competitive monitoring — SWOT is a snapshot; use Klue/Crayon for live tracking.</item>
        <item>Regulated/enterprise-only categories where market share is locked behind Gartner/IDC reports — agents will fabricate share numbers; buy the report.</item>
        <item>Hyperlocal markets (single city, single B2B niche under 50 buyers) — public proxies do not exist.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="five-step-framework">
      <rule>
        <statement>Identify competitors across three types: direct (same product, same audience), indirect (different product, same problem), and future (emerging or could pivot). Target 5-10 direct, 3-5 indirect, 2-3 future.</statement>
        <rationale>Missing indirect competitors means missing the actual churn cause — substitutes (spreadsheets, email, "do nothing") are what users fall back to, not rival SaaS products.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Google "[problem] solution" and "alternatives to [known competitor]"</item>
        <item>Product Hunt: search by category</item>
        <item>G2/Capterra: browse category leaders</item>
        <item>Reddit: "What do you use for [problem]?" threads</item>
        <item>Ask target customers directly what they use and what they tried before</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Plot competitors on a positioning matrix (x: feature breadth, y: price) and find empty quadrants or underserved positions. The goal is to identify whitespace, not to place competitors accurately for its own sake.</statement>
        <rationale>A matrix without a whitespace conclusion is a visualization exercise — the output must be an actionable positioning recommendation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Analyze each competitor across eight dimensions: product (features, gaps), pricing (model, tiers), positioning (target, message), technology (stack, integrations), traction (users, revenue estimate), team (size, funding), marketing (channels, content, ads), weaknesses (bad reviews, gaps).</statement>
        <rationale>Shallow analysis (name + pricing only) leaves differentiation opportunities invisible. All eight dimensions are required for a complete competitive profile.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Classify gaps into five types: feature gap (they don't have it), quality gap (they do it poorly), audience gap (they don't serve this segment), price gap (too expensive for some), experience gap (UX/onboarding is painful). Prioritize gaps where multiple competitors share the same weakness.</statement>
        <rationale>Acting on a gap that only one competitor misses may be intentional (unprofitable to build); gaps missed by all competitors with evidence of demand are the real opportunities.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Write a differentiation statement in the format: "For [target audience] who [need/problem], [Product] is a [category] that [key benefit]. Unlike [competitors], we [key differentiator]." One statement, specific and testable.</statement>
        <rationale>A vague differentiation statement ("better UX") cannot guide product or marketing decisions; specificity forces clarity about what the differentiator actually is.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>For solo freelancers who need simple project tracking, TaskLite is a project management tool that focuses on single-person workflows. Unlike Asana or Monday, we have no team features, just personal productivity.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Email marketing tool gap: all tools price by subscriber count; solopreneurs hit paywalls early; no tool focuses on under-1000 subscribers. Opportunity: generous free tier (5000 subscribers), solo-focused features, no team complexity.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="swot-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Require one citation URL per SWOT cell. Reject any cell whose evidence is the agent's prior knowledge rather than a fetched URL (review quote, metric, job posting).</statement>
        <rationale>This single rule eliminates ~80% of LLM SWOT slop. "Strong brand" as a strength with no citation is a tautology, not an observation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Define Opportunities as external trends the competitor could ride. Define Threats as external trends that hurt us if the competitor rides them. Reject any cell that collapses O and T into the same bucket.</statement>
        <rationale>Most LLM-generated SWOTs list "AI disruption" as both O and T. The distinction between "trend for them" and "threat to us" is where the strategic value lives.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a devil's-advocate pass after every synthesis: from the top competitor's perspective, rebuild our SWOT. List the 3 threats they would target us with first.</statement>
        <rationale>Self-comparison bias causes agents to under-weight competitor strengths against us; a forced adversarial perspective surfaces the threats most likely to be missed.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="share-estimation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Round all share estimates to 5% buckets and always print "(est.)". Reject any number with a decimal. If share is under 5%, print "long tail".</statement>
        <rationale>Traffic + employees + reviews are correlated, not independent proxies. Agents stack them and report false precision (23.4%). Rounding to 5% buckets is the minimum honest representation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Triangulate share with at least two proxies (traffic + employees, or downloads + revenue). One proxy alone is a guess, not an estimate.</statement>
        <rationale>SimilarWeb traffic share and LinkedIn headcount both have significant noise; two uncorrelated proxies pointing in the same direction provide meaningfully more confidence than one.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run market-research-tam-sam-som first to get the TAM denominator. Never quote a share percentage without naming the denominator and its source.</statement>
        <rationale>Share is a fraction — "X has 30% market share" with no denominator is meaningless marketing language, not analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>For private companies pre-Series-B with no Crunchbase/SEC filing data, write TBD for numeric fields rather than inventing ARR or headcount.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents invent plausible ARR for private startups. A TBD that flags the data gap is more useful than a fabricated number that propagates into strategy decks.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="portfolio-scorecard">
      <rule>
        <statement>Lock the scorecard schema (competitor YAML + scorecard column headers) in git before the first run. Quarterly re-runs must use the same dimensions. Reject any run that adds new columns.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents invent new columns to "improve" the scorecard each quarter. Column drift makes quarter-over-quarter diffs meaningless — the delta is the strategy story.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag every estimate with confidence level: high = official source, med = proxy-triangulated, low = single proxy or inferred. Do not strip confidence tags in synthesis.</statement>
        <rationale>A board-ready competitive matrix with invisible confidence levels buries the distinction between a market-data-sourced number and an inference.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="worked-examples">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Note-taking app analysis: Direct competitors (Notion, Obsidian, Roam Research), indirect (Apple Notes, Google Docs), future (AI writing tools). Findings: Notion strength=all-in-one, weakness=slow+complex; Obsidian strength=local-first+plugins, weakness=steep learning; Roam strength=backlinks, weakness=expensive+dated UI. Positioning: "For busy professionals who want fast, simple notes with linking. Unlike Notion, we're single-purpose and lightning fast. Unlike Obsidian, we work great out of the box."</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Email marketing gap discovery: all tools price by subscriber count; solopreneurs hit paywalls early; no tool focuses on under-1000 subscribers. Gap validated by review mining (50+ feature requests in Mailchimp community). Opportunity: generous free tier (5000 subscribers), solo-focused features, no team complexity.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Only analyzing direct competitors while ignoring indirect and future competitors.</description>
        <reason>Indirect competitors (substitutes, "do nothing") are the actual churn cause — they do not appear in "top 5 CRM alternatives" searches but account for most of the market's status quo.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Surface-level analysis (name + pricing only) without digging into reviews, pricing pages, and features.</description>
        <reason>Feature gaps and quality gaps that create differentiation opportunities are invisible at surface level; they require review mining and hands-on product evaluation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Copying competitor features rather than finding gaps to differentiate.</description>
        <reason>Feature parity is a race to the bottom; differentiation lives in the gaps the competitor chose not to fill.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>One-time analysis without setting up ongoing monitoring.</description>
        <reason>A SWOT snapshot decays in 3-6 months; without a re-run cadence, decisions made from it become stale anchors.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated funding/ARR: agent invents plausible figures like "$12.3M Series A" without Crunchbase/PitchBook access.</description>
        <reason>Hard rule: if API key absent, write TBD and audit the output for any $N not in the source CSV before publishing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>SWOT tautology: agent writes "strong brand" because the company is famous, without a cited evidence URL.</description>
        <reason>Reject any S/W cell whose evidence is the agent's prior knowledge rather than a fetched URL. One citation per cell is non-negotiable.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Context overflow on 10+ competitors: agent tries to pass raw scrapes into a single synthesis prompt.</description>
        <reason>Do not pass raw scrapes into synthesis. SWOT each competitor to YAML first, then synthesize from the YAMLs only — this fits in context and produces cleaner output.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Strategic-group axis-shopping: agent picks axes post-hoc that maximise visual separation.</description>
        <reason>Pin axes in the prompt before running (e.g., price vs. feature breadth with named exemplars for each pole). If data does not separate on pre-committed axes, that is the finding.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Recency bias: SWOT skews to last-90-days news, missing structural threats from the prior 3 years.</description>
        <reason>Force a 3-year retrospective scan ("structural threats since 2023") as a separate sub-task before synthesis.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <list>
        <item>Share estimation is proxy-stacked: traffic (SimilarWeb) + employees (LinkedIn) + reviews (G2) are correlated, not independent. Agents stack them and report false precision (23.4%). Round to 5% buckets and label "estimated".</item>
        <item>SWOT becomes a tautology: agents list "strong brand" as a strength because the company is well-known. Force every S/W/O/T to cite an external observation (a review quote, a metric, a job posting), not a vibe.</item>
        <item>Opportunities/Threats collapse into the same bucket: an LLM treats "AI disruption" as both. Mitigation: define O = external trend the competitor could ride; T = external trend that hurts us if they ride it.</item>
        <item>Portfolio benchmarking drifts: dimensions chosen in Q1 are not the dimensions that mattered in Q4. Lock the scorecard schema in version control.</item>
        <item>Public-data ceiling for private companies: pre-Series-B startups have no reliable share signal; agents will invent ARR. Hard-rule: "if not in Crunchbase or SEC filing, mark TBD".</item>
        <item>Strategic-group maps are 2D: the agent will pick the two axes that maximise visual separation, not the two that matter to buyers. Pre-commit to axes (e.g. price vs. feature breadth) before running.</item>
        <item>SWOT recency bias: weights the last 90 days of news heavily. Force a 3-year retrospective scan to catch structural threats.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive this with the faion-research-agent in mode: competitors as orchestrator, but configured with the market-researcher profile (SWOT + share + portfolio outputs, not differentiation statement). Pipeline runs in three serial phases with intra-phase parallelism: (1) seed + classify competitors into strategic groups (single agent call), (2) per-competitor SWOT + share-proxy collection fanned out as N parallel Task calls so each runs in its own context window, (3) synthesis — cross-competitor portfolio scorecard, strategic-group map, share table — in a final orchestrator pass with a devil's-advocate review sub-task. Output to .aidocs/product_docs/competitive-analysis.md plus a structured _competitors.yml for re-runs and diffing.</p>
      <prompt purpose="orchestrator-market-researcher-profile">
        <![CDATA[
Task(
  subagent_type="faion-research-agent (mode: competitors)",
  prompt="Profile: market-researcher. Build SWOT + market-share + portfolio
  scorecard for category {category}. Seed competitors: {seed_list}.
  Required outputs: (1) SWOT per competitor with cited evidence per quadrant,
  (2) market-share table in 5% buckets with proxy sources, (3) strategic-group
  map (axes: {axis_x}, {axis_y}) — DO NOT pick axes yourself, (4) portfolio
  scorecard vs. our product on dimensions: price_index, feature_count, nps_proxy,
  growth_proxy. Mark all numbers (est.). Reject any SWOT cell without an
  external citation. Output to .aidocs/product_docs/competitive-analysis.md
  and version the seed list to .aidocs/product_docs/_competitors.yml."
)
        ]]>
      </prompt>
      <prompt purpose="per-competitor-swot-fanout">
        <![CDATA[
Task(
  subagent_type="general-purpose",  # sonnet
  prompt="Build SWOT for {competitor}. Sources: G2 reviews (last 90d, both
  5-star and 1-star), HN/Reddit threads, last 4 quarterly LinkedIn employee
  counts, Crunchbase, last 3 changelog/blog posts. Each S/W/O/T cell MUST
  cite a URL + a 1-line evidence quote. Reject 'strong brand' / 'good UX'
  unless backed by a review quote. Threats must be external (market trend,
  regulation, big-tech entry) — not internal weaknesses re-labelled.
  Return YAML matching the SWOT schema in templates.md."
)
        ]]>
      </prompt>
      <prompt purpose="devils-advocate-pass">
        <![CDATA[
Task(
  subagent_type="general-purpose",  # opus
  prompt="Read competitive-analysis.md. From {top_competitor}'s perspective,
  rebuild OUR SWOT. List the 3 threats they would target us with first.
  Flag any quadrant where our self-rated strength is their rated weakness."
)
        ]]>
      </prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Lock the scorecard schema (_competitors.yml + scorecard column headers) in git before the first run; quarterly re-runs must use the same dimensions or the diff is meaningless.</item>
        <item>Round share to 5% buckets and always print "(est.)"; precision beyond that is fake. If share &lt; 5%, print "long tail".</item>
        <item>Force one citation URL per SWOT cell. Reject the cell otherwise. This single rule eliminates ~80% of LLM SWOT slop.</item>
        <item>Separate Opportunities (external trends competitor can ride) from Threats (external trends that hurt us if competitor rides them). Most LLM-generated SWOTs collapse these.</item>
        <item>Run the devil's-advocate pass on every synthesis. Self-comparison bias makes agents under-weight competitor strengths against you.</item>
        <item>Use a denominator before quoting share. Run mode: market (TAM/SAM/SOM) first; share is a fraction, not a count.</item>
        <item>Triangulate share with at least two proxies (traffic + employees, or downloads + revenue). One proxy = guess.</item>
        <item>Cap "future competitors" at 2-3 with a concrete signal. "Big tech could enter" is not a signal; a job posting, beta launch, or acquisition is.</item>
        <item>Pre-commit the strategic-group axes. Do not let the agent pick the axes that maximise visual separation.</item>
        <item>Diff quarterly with csvjoin/git diff on the scorecard; the deltas are the strategy story, not the absolute values.</item>
        <item>Tag every estimate with confidence (high = official source, med = proxy-triangulated, low = single proxy or inferred). Strip nothing in synthesis.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated funding / ARR: without paid Crunchbase/PitchBook access the agent invents plausible figures.</description>
        <reason>Hard rule: "if API key absent, write TBD" and audit the output for any $N not in the source CSV.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>SWOT tautology: agent writes "strong brand" because the brand is famous. Reject any S/W cell whose evidence is the agent's prior knowledge rather than a fetched URL.</description>
        <reason>One citation per cell is non-negotiable.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Share-precision overconfidence: agent reports 23.4%. Force-round to 5% buckets in the prompt and reject any number with a decimal.</description>
        <reason>Traffic + employees + reviews are correlated proxies, not independent measurements.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Strategic-group axis-shopping: agent picks axes post-hoc to make the picture clean.</description>
        <reason>Pin axes in the prompt; if the data does not separate, that is the finding.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Context overflow on 10+ competitors: do not pass raw scrapes into synthesis.</description>
        <reason>SWOT each competitor to YAML first, then synthesise from the YAMLs only.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Recency bias: SWOT skews to last-90-days news.</description>
        <reason>Force a 3-year retrospective scan ("structural threats since 2023") as a separate sub-task.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Portfolio scorecard column drift: agent invents new columns each quarter to "improve" the scorecard.</description>
        <reason>Lock the schema and reject extra columns.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>TAM-less share: agent reports "X has 30% market share" without naming the denominator.</description>
        <reason>Every share % must be paired with a TAM source.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints skipped: sign off on seed list + strategic-group axes before SWOT runs, review per-competitor SWOT YAMLs for cited-URL discipline, approve the share-bucket table and TAM denominator before it lands in board materials, accept or reject devil's-advocate findings before the executive summary.</description>
        <reason>Each checkpoint catches a different class of failure that automated validation cannot surface.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/competitor-report.md" purpose="Full competitor analysis report: market overview, competitor map, detailed analysis, positioning matrix, gap analysis, differentiation, monitoring plan"/>
      <template path="templates/competitor-snapshot.md" purpose="Quick one-page competitor snapshot with strengths, weaknesses, opportunity"/>
      <template path="templates/market-share-proxy.sh" purpose="Bash script assembling SimilarWeb + Crunchbase + GitHub share-estimation proxies into a quarterly CSV"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://docs.similarweb.com">SimilarWeb API</link>
      <link href="https://data.crunchbase.com/docs">Crunchbase API</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
