<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="product" count="112" version="3.0" generated="2026-05-25">
  <description>L2 index of methodologies in the product domain. The retriever reads this after picking product from L1 domains.xml. Entries list slug + tier + summary; open the leaf meta.json / content/*.xml for full payload.</description>
  <methodology slug="30-day-post-launch-review-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/30-day-post-launch-review-template">
    <summary>Produces a 30-day post-launch review report (funnel snapshot + pre-launch-hypotheses outcome + ≥3 ranked next-bets) so the launch window stops being a moment and becomes a learning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ac-quality-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/ac-quality-rubric">
    <summary>Score each acceptance criterion against a 5-axis rubric (testable / atomic / observable / unambiguous / negative-cases) and reject any AC scoring &lt;4/5 before engineering starts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agent-builder-community-rituals" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/agent-builder-community-rituals">
    <summary>Produces a calendar of weekly / biweekly / monthly rituals (office hours, eval-sharing, prompt-swap) plus per-ritual artefact templates and a 90-day retention metric, so isolated agent-builders become a learning community instead of a dying meetup.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agent-pricing-and-unit-economics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/agent-pricing-and-unit-economics">
    <summary>Produces per-task COGS + gross-margin + pricing-model recommendation (seat / task / outcome) for LLM-agent products targeting $5-100K MRR, so token-cost variance does not bankrupt the team on a heavy user.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-ai-product-development" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/agentic-ai-product-development">
    <summary>Produces an agentic-AI product spec (MVI, not MVP) — machine-verifiable goal state + enumerated autonomous actions + escalation-first design + behavioural-regression hook — so 40% of agentic pilots stop dying on the way to production.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-ai-product-development-product-ops" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/agentic-ai-product-development-product-ops">
    <summary>Produces an ops-readiness package for an autonomous agentic AI product — machine-verifiable goal predicate + budgeted autonomous actions + pre-launch escalation runbook + agentic-ops dashboard + behavioural-regression hook — so the agent can safely take traffic in production.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/agents">
    <summary>Two Claude subagents for product scoping — faion-mvp-scope-analyzer-agent (competitor-grounded MVP scope) and faion-mlp-agent (5-mode MLP pipeline analyze→find-gaps→propose→update→plan) — with hard human-checkpoint and VCS-clean preconditions on autonomous spec edits.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-de-risking" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/ai-feature-de-risking">
    <summary>Produces a pre-registered AI-feature de-risking pipeline (frozen eval set + kill-criteria + statistical reporting + judge recalibration + bounded cost) so AI features stop shipping without measurable value.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-native-product-development" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/ai-native-product-development">
    <summary>Produces an AI-native product strategy where AI is the delivery mechanism — pinned model versions, scored build-vs-buy, EU AI Act risk classification, inference-cost as first-class metric, and human-refines wired as a captured product feature.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-native-product-development-product-ops" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/ai-native-product-development-product-ops">
    <summary>Restructures product discovery, delivery, and ops around AI as a first-class material — eval-driven specs, prompt versioning, guardrail review, and dual-loop telemetry (model + product).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-product-success-metrics-catalog" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/ai-product-success-metrics-catalog">
    <summary>Produces an AI-product success-metrics catalog (deflection rate, intervention rate, hallucination rate, time-to-correction, retention-on-AI-features) so AI-native PMs stop measuring chatbots with the same KPIs as form-fills.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="annual-roadmap-vs-quarterly-okr-stitch" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/annual-roadmap-vs-quarterly-okr-stitch">
    <summary>Stitches an annual roadmap into a quarterly OKR cascade so the year's bet and the quarter's KRs stay coupled; output is a stitch spec with traceability matrix.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="anti-roadmap-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/anti-roadmap-template">
    <summary>Quarterly 'what we will NOT ship' list \u2014 explicit deferred / declined / killed items with rationale and revisit triggers, paired with the roadmap to absorb stakeholder pressure.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="audience-driven-pivot-decision" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/audience-driven-pivot-decision">
    <summary>Decision-record framework for pivoting the product while keeping the audience \u2014 distinct from zero-to-one repivots; gated by audience-asset checks and a single-product kill criterion.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backlog-hygiene-cron-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/backlog-hygiene-cron-checklist">
    <summary>Weekly 15-minute backlog-grooming checklist for a solo PM: stale-item sweep, duplicate merge, priority re-rank, top-10 surfaced, no-list refreshed.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backlog-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/backlog-management">
    <summary>Produces a DEEP-compliant backlog config (Ready / Upcoming / Backlog / Icebox buckets + type-tagged items + INVEST-compliant Ready entries + weekly grooming cadence).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backlog-management-product-ops" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/backlog-management-product-ops">
    <summary>Maintain a single-source backlog with weekly grooming, age caps per state, and a refusal-to-publish guardrail when the backlog exceeds the team's capacity by ≥3×.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="beta-charter-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/beta-charter-template">
    <summary>Pre-launch beta charter pinning cohort size, success metric, duration, exit criteria, and graduation conditions \u2014 signed by founder + first beta user.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="beta-cohort-communication" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/beta-cohort-communication">
    <summary>Weekly broadcast + targeted-feedback flow keeping beta cohorts engaged from recruit through graduation \u2014 pinned cadence, three message types, single ask per send.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="build-or-waitlist-decision-tree" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/build-or-waitlist-decision-tree">
    <summary>Per-feature decision: build immediately, waitlist (validate via smoke page first), or decline \u2014 gated by stated demand, capacity, strategic fit, kill-criterion presence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="churn-cohort-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/churn-cohort-analysis">
    <summary>Cohort isolation by activation status, leading-indicator detection, save-flow design — the dedicated playbook product-analytics generalities don't provide.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cohort-based-mini-course-launch" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/cohort-based-mini-course-launch">
    <summary>Cohort sizing + calendar + Maven/Podia/Circle ops + course-as-lead-magnet for a $99-$499 \u00d7 20-seat indie monetization sprint.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="continuous-discovery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/continuous-discovery">
    <summary>Produces a continuous-discovery config (weekly user-touchpoint cadence + opportunity-solution-tree + assumption-test queue + decision log) so discovery stops being a quarterly event.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="continuous-discovery-product-planning" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/continuous-discovery-product-planning">
    <summary>Maintain a weekly customer-touch habit (interview / survey / observation) feeding a continuously updated assumption tree so discovery is a rhythm, not a project.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="customer-journey-bottleneck-attack" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/customer-journey-bottleneck-attack">
    <summary>Customer Journey Bottleneck Attack: codified product practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/Run a quarterly journey-bottleneck attack' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="demo-hypothesis-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/demo-hypothesis-template">
    <summary>One-page demo-hypothesis spec: forces every customer demo to declare what hypothesis it tests, success metric, falsification signal, follow-up gate \u2014 so demos stop being feature parades.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-debt-audit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/design-debt-audit">
    <summary>Design Debt Audit delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Journey-map-driven attack: from friction map to ranked design-backlog' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Recurring audit of accumulated UX shortcuts, deprecated patterns, a</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-debt-vs-design-bet" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/design-debt-vs-design-bet">
    <summary>Per-design-task classifier: design-debt (pay-down work, must-fix, known UX bug) vs design-bet (forward-looking, hypothesis-driven, may fail) \u2014 output is a decision-record with budget envelope per class.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-ops-foundations" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/design-ops-foundations">
    <summary>Rituals, tooling stack, design-team capacity model for the missing 'design-ops' sibling of marketing-ops and dev-ops.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-partner-cadence-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/design-partner-cadence-playbook">
    <summary>Design Partner Cadence Playbook delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Customer demo / sneak-peek session' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Pro/geek-tier B2B PMs need a methodology for running an ongoing design-partner cohort (c</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-partner-program-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/design-partner-program-template">
    <summary>Design Partner Program Template delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Freelance-to-SaaS transition (6-month side build)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: How to convert past freelance clients into paid design partners with disc</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-system-drift-audit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/design-system-drift-audit">
    <summary>Design System Drift Audit delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Design-system-as-code lifecycle: tokens → Storybook → Figma library → PR → governance' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: AI-generated layouts and unsupervised PRs c</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="discovery-cadence-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/discovery-cadence-design">
    <summary>Designs the interview slot, OST refresh cycle, and assumption-test pipeline for a specific team — the act continuous-discovery-habits assumes already happened.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="discovery-research-handoff-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/discovery-research-handoff-template">
    <summary>One-page discovery handoff bundling problem statement, persona, JTBD, evidence quotes, success metric \u2014 the canonical artefact PMs hand to design + engineering after discovery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="distribution-first-ideation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/distribution-first-ideation">
    <summary>Pre-build ideation discipline: validate the audience + channel BEFORE the product \u2014 smoke page, waitlist conversion, channel-fit test produce a go/no-go decision-record.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-flag-rollout-decision" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/feature-flag-rollout-decision">
    <summary>Feature Flag Rollout Decision delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Validate an AI feature before it consumes a quarter' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Release-planning covers release cadence; nothing covers the decision tree</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-prioritization-moscow" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/feature-prioritization-moscow">
    <summary>Produces a MoSCoW prioritisation config (Must / Should / Could / Won't buckets with explicit caps + cycle-bound scope + a single tiebreaker rule).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-prioritization-rice" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/feature-prioritization-rice">
    <summary>Produces a RICE-scored backlog config (Reach × Impact × Confidence ÷ Effort with named units + confidence-floor + evidence citations) so prioritisation stops being a gut-vote ritual.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-prioritization-rice-product-ops" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/feature-prioritization-rice-product-ops">
    <summary>Score features by Reach × Impact × Confidence ÷ Effort; rank by descending RICE; refuse to commit anything with confidence &lt;50% or effort &gt;team-week without a spike.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-sunset-and-deprecation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/feature-sunset-and-deprecation">
    <summary>Feature Sunset And Deprecation delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Validate an AI feature before it consumes a quarter' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Product-lifecycle and technical-debt-management touch this but no method</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feedback-loop-customer-reply-templates" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/feedback-loop-customer-reply-templates">
    <summary>Customer-reply templates closing the feedback loop: acknowledge, route, follow-up \u2014 each ticket emerges with a tagged outcome (build / waitlist / decline / bug) and a customer-facing reply.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feedback-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/feedback-management">
    <summary>Capture user feedback through a single inbound channel, triage daily, classify by theme + severity, close the loop with the user, and feed verified themes into the roadmap.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="founder-dependency-audit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/founder-dependency-audit">
    <summary>Scores every revenue line, account, credential, and client relationship by 'breaks if founder steps away 4 weeks' to produce a ranked dependency register and remediation plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-to-saas-time-box" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/freelancer-to-saas-time-box">
    <summary>Pins an explicit weekly time-box + boundary contract that protects SaaS build slots from client work; produces a 90-day commitment spec with abort criteria.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="friction-to-backlog" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/friction-to-backlog">
    <summary>Converts journey-map friction nodes into prioritised backlog tickets \u2014 each ticket carries the friction-id, expected metric impact, evidence count, owner \u2014 closing the loop from mapping to delivery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gdpr-for-solo-saas" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/gdpr-for-solo-saas">
    <summary>Pragmatic GDPR posture for a one-person SaaS: scope the obligations that actually apply, ship the minimal data-protection set, name when to lawyer up \u2014 not the same content as enterprise GDPR.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="indie-portfolio-scorecard" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/indie-portfolio-scorecard">
    <summary>Single scorecard view across multiple indie products: MRR, growth %, support load, founder hours/week, joy score \u2014 used to decide which products to grow, maintain, kill.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="indie-postmortem-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/indie-postmortem-template">
    <summary>Run a blameless solo-founder postmortem after a launch / outage / project-end: timeline, contributing factors, blast radius, lessons, and ≤3 follow-up actions — capped at 30 min.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kano-prioritization" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/kano-prioritization">
    <summary>Kano-based classifier separating must-haves, performance features, delighters, indifferent, reverse features \u2014 produces a categorised feature list with survey-grounded categories.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kill-criteria-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/kill-criteria-template">
    <summary>Produces a one-page kill-criteria artefact (pre-registered MRR/traffic/joy/runway thresholds + calendared review) so portfolio rotation stays disciplined and zombie bets are sunset on schedule.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kill-or-keep-criteria" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/kill-or-keep-criteria">
    <summary>Produces a checklist that scores a side-project against MRR-floor / traffic-floor / joy-floor / opportunity-cost thresholds and outputs a binary kill-or-keep decision with cited evidence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kpi-tree-construction" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/kpi-tree-construction">
    <summary>Decomposes an NSM into a navigable tree where every leaf has owner, formula, cadence and evidence link; output is a validated KPI tree spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="launch-comms-kit-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/launch-comms-kit-template">
    <summary>Produces a launch comms kit spec (one tweet thread + one PH copy + one mailing-list draft + one HN show-post + one changelog entry) sharing a single positioning sentence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="launch-tier-decision-frame" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/launch-tier-decision-frame">
    <summary>Produces a decision-record selecting one launch tier (soft / friend-circle / PH-day / HN+PH+podcast blitz) based on readiness + funnel-fit + retreat-cost.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="maintain-mode-sops-solo" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/maintain-mode-sops-solo">
    <summary>Produces a maintain-mode SOP spec (weekly check + monthly tax + quarterly review + on-call rule) for a solo-owned product moving from build-mode to maintain-mode.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="metric-deviation-hypothesis-framework" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/metric-deviation-hypothesis-framework">
    <summary>Produces a hypothesis report (named metric + named deviation + ≥3 ranked causes + ranked next-checks) so a metric anomaly stops being folklore and becomes a falsifiable next step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="micro-mvp-cut-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/micro-mvp-cut-rubric">
    <summary>Run a 5-question cut rubric to slice an MVP scope down to ≤5 dev-days while preserving the riskiest assumption test.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="micro-mvps" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/micro-mvps">
    <summary>Produces a micro-MVP spec (single-hypothesis + ≤7-day build + manual back-end allowed + measurable signup-or-pay gate) so a one-week test ships instead of becoming a small MVP.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="micro-mvps-product-planning" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/micro-mvps-product-planning">
    <summary>Ship a Micro-MVP (≤5 dev-days, 1 risk tested, 1 segment, hard kill threshold) per cycle to learn-or-die rather than build-and-hope.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="minimum-product-frameworks" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/minimum-product-frameworks">
    <summary>Pick one of four minimum-product frames (MVP / MLP / MMP / MMR) for the current goal, document the trade-off, and run the matching planning methodology.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mlp-planning" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/mlp-planning">
    <summary>Plan a Minimum Lovable Product: one 'wow' moment, ≥1 thoughtful UX detail, real polish on the critical path, but everything else stays MVP-level.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-product-portfolio-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/multi-product-portfolio-management">
    <summary>Produces a portfolio config (per-product mode tag + weekly time-budget + capital allocation + cross-product kill rule) for a solopreneur running ≥3 products.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mvp-instrumentation-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/mvp-instrumentation-checklist">
    <summary>Produces a checklist proving an MVP ships with ≥1 acquisition event + ≥1 activation event + ≥1 retention event + ≥1 revenue event wired BEFORE first user touches it.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mvp-scoping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/mvp-scoping">
    <summary>Produces an MVP scope spec (named-AHA-moment + ≤4-week build + must-have user journey + explicit cut list + readiness checklist) so the MVP ships viable, not maximal.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mvp-scoping-product-planning" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/mvp-scoping-product-planning">
    <summary>Scope an MVP that tests one riskiest assumption with ≤2 weeks build, ≥10 segment users, and explicit kill / success thresholds — defends scope against feature creep.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="north-star-metric-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/north-star-metric-design">
    <summary>Designs a single North Star Metric: candidate generation, leading-vs-lagging classification, formula + cadence + owner; output is an NSM spec ready for KPI-tree cascade.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="north-star-vs-okr-confidence-calibration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/north-star-vs-okr-confidence-calibration">
    <summary>Produces a weekly confidence-calibration report mapping current OKR progress against NSM target with explicit risks; output is a forecast report with named owners and intervention triggers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="okr-setting" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/okr-setting">
    <summary>Produces an OKR config (≤3 objectives + 2-4 measurable KRs each + quarter boundary + check-in cadence + named owners) so quarter goals stop being a list of features.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="okr-setting-product-planning" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/okr-setting-product-planning">
    <summary>Set quarterly OKRs: 1-3 objectives, 3 key results each, leading not lagging where possible, with a confidence band and weekly check-in cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="outcome-based-roadmaps" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/outcome-based-roadmaps">
    <summary>Produces an outcome-based roadmap spec (≤3 outcomes per quarter + opportunities → solutions → confidence + No-Date-Promises rule + reviewer cadence).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced">
    <summary>Produces an advanced outcome-roadmap spec (multi-quarter outcome chains + dependency edges + confidence-decay model + portfolio-level swim lanes) for teams beyond single-quarter horizons.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="owner-handover-sop-kit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/owner-handover-sop-kit">
    <summary>Generates a structured SOP kit (credentials, runbooks, financials, contracts, escalation) so an agency or product line can be handed to a new owner; output is a handover spec with completeness score.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pivot-vs-quit-decision-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/pivot-vs-quit-decision-template">
    <summary>Pins a decision record comparing pivot-to-v2 versus full shutdown using product signals, runway, founder energy, and customer pull; output is a signed decision-record artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pmf-rubric-for-solos" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/pmf-rubric-for-solos">
    <summary>Scores a solo-founder product on six PMF dimensions (very-disappointed %, retention curve, organic pull, willingness-to-pay, founder-confidence, runway-fit) and outputs a PMF rubric report with verdict.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="portfolio-sunset-decision-frame" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/portfolio-sunset-decision-frame">
    <summary>Frames a sunset decision for one product in a multi-product portfolio using revenue, maintenance cost, strategic fit, and exit cost; output is a signed decision-record with owner and date.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="portfolio-triage-indie" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/portfolio-triage-indie">
    <summary>Produces a versioned triage report (per-product verdict + evidence + next-action) so a weekly portfolio metric scan stops being folklore and becomes a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="post-launch-72h-watch-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/post-launch-72h-watch-runbook">
    <summary>Defines the 72-hour post-launch watch: signal thresholds, on-call rotation, escalation triggers, rollback gates; output is a runbook spec with named owner per signal.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prd-via-ai-without-losing-why" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/prd-via-ai-without-losing-why">
    <summary>Pins a PRD authoring procedure that uses AI for drafting but locks the 'why' (customer evidence, business outcome, anti-goals) before any LLM expansion; output is a PRD spec with citation chain.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pricing-experiment-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/pricing-experiment-design">
    <summary>Designs a live pricing experiment (van Westendorp on traffic, grandfathering, cohort A/B legality, price-sensitivity flags); output is a pricing-experiment design spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pricing-experiment-log" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/pricing-experiment-log">
    <summary>Produces a versioned pricing experiment log (hypothesis → toggle → window → result → decision per flip) so price changes stop being folklore and become a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pricing-experiment-spec-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/pricing-experiment-spec-template">
    <summary>Pinned spec template (hypothesis -&gt; result) for pricing experiments with owner, evidence anchors, and ship/abort gates; output is a per-experiment spec instance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-analytics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/product-analytics">
    <summary>Stand up a minimum-viable analytics setup: NSM + 3-5 leading + 1 health metric, tracking plan, dashboard, and a weekly review tying numbers to product decisions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-discovery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/product-discovery">
    <summary>Run a discovery cycle that maps assumptions across four risk types (Value/Usability/Feasibility/Business-Viability), designs cheap falsifiable experiments with explicit kill thresholds, and emits a go/pivot/kill spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-launch" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/product-launch">
    <summary>Run an outcome-driven product launch: stage-gated checklist, audience-segment cadence, on-launch monitors, and a 14-day post-launch review that decides scale/hold/rollback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-lifecycle" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/product-lifecycle">
    <summary>Place the product in one of five lifecycle stages (idea / launch / growth / maturity / decline) and apply the stage-specific playbook so the operating model matches reality.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="productized-service-canvas" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/productized-service-canvas">
    <summary>One-page canvas that converts a bespoke recurring service into a fixed-outcome, fixed-price, fixed-timeline offer with explicit scope-in/scope-out and a repeatable SOP.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="productized-service-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/productized-service-design">
    <summary>Designs the full productized-service offer (SOP, deliverables, pricing model, guarantees, refund policy, escalation); output is a service design spec ready for launch.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="productized-service-launch" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/productized-service-launch">
    <summary>Pins the launch playbook for a productized service (pricing page, outbound list, beta cohort, payment link, ship gates); output is a launch playbook spec with metrics targets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="qbr-deck-template-services" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/qbr-deck-template-services">
    <summary>Pinned QBR deck template for the micro-agency founder: fixed shape, named owner, evidence anchors, outcome review — turning quarterly retainer reviews into a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rfc-lite-pm-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/rfc-lite-pm-template">
    <summary>Opinionated short RFC-lite template (problem → evidence → scope → open questions) that engineering will actually read; produces a versioned, owner-signed feature brief with evidence anchors and an outcome-review date.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rice-for-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/rice-for-design">
    <summary>RICE adapted for the design backlog: reach=affected user segment, impact=usability lift, confidence=evidence weight, effort=design+dev — emits a ranked design backlog scoped to the friction map.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rice-for-one-person-cheatsheet" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/rice-for-one-person-cheatsheet">
    <summary>RICE reweighted for solo SaaS: Reach in absolute small-number users (80 is signal), Effort in dev-days for one person, Confidence collapsed to 3 levels, and WIP-1 framing — the top of the list is the ONLY bet of the week.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="roadmap-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/roadmap-design">
    <summary>Design an outcome-based roadmap with Now/Next/Later horizons, explicit confidence per item, and quarterly review cadence so the roadmap becomes a steering tool instead of a wishlist.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="roadmap-drift-detection-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/roadmap-drift-detection-checklist">
    <summary>Monthly checklist that catches roadmap drift before the quarter ends: tagged-vs-untagged work ratio, outcome-orphan tickets, stale candidate solutions, and confidence label decay — emits a drift report with action items.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="segment-aware-design-system" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/segment-aware-design-system">
    <summary>Defines a design system where tokens, components, and copy variants are partitioned by user segment so a single codebase serves multiple audiences without forking.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-bug-triage-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/solo-bug-triage-rubric">
    <summary>5-question rubric mapping a bug to one of three queues (drop-everything / next-sprint / accept) within 5 minutes; named owner, retest threshold, and a decay rule for accepted bugs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-go-no-go-criteria" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/solo-go-no-go-criteria">
    <summary>Pre-ship go / hold / no-op gate with five concrete questions (build-quality, scope-vs-promise, comms-ready, rollback-tested, success-metric-instrumented) — produces a signed go/no-go record before any release.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-kpi-dashboard-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/solo-kpi-dashboard-template">
    <summary>5-KPI solo SaaS dashboard (signups, activation, paid conversion, churn, revenue) on one screen with weekly cadence, dashboard URL, and a Sunday review ritual that drives the WIP-1 bet.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-saas-legal-docs-pack" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/solo-saas-legal-docs-pack">
    <summary>Minimum five legal documents (ToS, Privacy, Cookie, Refund, DPA) sourced from Stripe / Iubenda / Termly / Vanta with billing-activation gates that block ship until live.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spec-writing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/spec-writing">
    <summary>Write a one-pager spec containing problem / users / goals / non-goals / requirements / acceptance criteria / open questions, ready for an engineer to start without follow-up calls.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-memo-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/strategy-memo-template">
    <summary>Produces a 2-page strategy memo (vision, bets, non-bets, success metrics) that replaces 40-slide decks for annual product strategy refresh.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="subscription-lifecycle-edge-cases" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/subscription-lifecycle-edge-cases">
    <summary>Wires the 8 subscription edge cases (trial-to-paid, upgrade, downgrade, proration, failed renewal, cancel-then-resubscribe, EU VAT, refunds) into a single tested runbook with Stripe webhook coverage and dunning policy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sunset-failed-product-playbook" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/sunset-failed-product-playbook">
    <summary>End-to-end sunset playbook: refund policy, customer migration plan, domain reuse / archive, asset salvage, public retro — shutters a failing product gracefully and reclaims learning + leverage for the next bet.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sunset-vs-fold-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/sunset-vs-fold-framework">
    <summary>Decision framework for whether to sunset a product (kill cleanly) vs fold it (merge capability into another) when discontinuing a line of business.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="support-tool-pm-triage-spec" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/support-tool-pm-triage-spec">
    <summary>Opinionated Intercom / Pylon / Zendesk triage spec: 5 tag categories, escalation rules, weekly digest format, named owner — converts support inbox into a defensible PM signal feed.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="technical-debt-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/technical-debt-management">
    <summary>Maintain a debt register, budget 10-20% of capacity for debt work per sprint, prioritise by interest rate (cost-of-living-with × likelihood-of-incident), and refuse zero-debt sprints.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-story-mapping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/user-story-mapping">
    <summary>Build a user story map (backbone of activities → user tasks → stories), slice the map into MVP / Release-1 / Release-2 horizontally so scope decisions are visible and shippable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vanity-metrics-audit" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/vanity-metrics-audit">
    <summary>Audits an exec dashboard against the 'vanity vs leading vs lagging' test, marks vanity metrics for retirement, supplies a stakeholder script for political defence, and emits a refactored KPI tree.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vendor-evaluation-scorecard" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/vendor-evaluation-scorecard">
    <summary>Scorecard rubric for choosing AI vendors (LLM, vector DB, eval, observability) across quality, cost, lock-in, security, and SLA — produces a comparable score + decision artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="weekly-pm-async-broadcast-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/weekly-pm-async-broadcast-template">
    <summary>Pins a Monday async PM update format (problem/decision/next-step + named owner) so weekly broadcasts decay into a reviewable artefact, not a Slack scroll.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="what-you-dont-know-about-launch-pre-mortem" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/what-you-dont-know-about-launch-pre-mortem">
    <summary>Walk a solo SaaS launch through every category of unknown-unknown before pressing GO — produces a checklisted pre-mortem report with named owners and revisit triggers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="win-loss-quarterly-pm-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/product/win-loss-quarterly-pm-template">
    <summary>Quarterly synthesis stitching CRM data, win-loss interviews, and competitive notes into the integrated artefact PMs own.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
