<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="product" count="75">
  <methodology slug="agent-builder-community-rituals" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/agent-builder-community-rituals">
    <summary>Codifies the weekly/biweekly/monthly rituals (office hours, eval-sharing, prompt-swap) that turn isolated LLM-agent developers into a learning community.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-product-success-metrics-catalog" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/ai-product-success-metrics-catalog">
    <summary>Ai Product Success Metrics Catalog: codified product-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/AI-native product introduction' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="annual-roadmap-vs-quarterly-okr-stitch" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/annual-roadmap-vs-quarterly-okr-stitch">
    <summary>An explicit stitching methodology that decomposes annual product bets into quarterly OKR cascades so the year's bet and the quarter's KRs stay coupled across all four quarters.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="anti-roadmap-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/anti-roadmap-template">
    <summary>Anti Roadmap Template: codified product-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/Quarter planning + OKR cascade' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="audience-driven-pivot-decision" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/audience-driven-pivot-decision">
    <summary>When MRR stalls and the product fails, pivot the product while keeping the audience — a scoped decision distinct from zero-to-one repivots.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backlog-hygiene-cron-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/backlog-hygiene-cron-checklist">
    <summary>Backlog Hygiene Cron Checklist: codified product-management practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/Backlog grooming + prioritization session' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="beta-charter-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/beta-charter-template">
    <summary>Beta Charter Template: codified product-management practice that turns the recurring 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Pre-launch beta program' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="beta-cohort-communication" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/beta-cohort-communication">
    <summary>Templated weekly/biweekly broadcast + targeted-feedback flow to keep beta cohorts engaged from recruit through graduation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="build-or-waitlist-decision-tree" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/build-or-waitlist-decision-tree">
    <summary>Build or Waitlist Decision Tree: codified product-management practice that turns the recurring 'p1-solo-saas-builder/New feature scoping session (per-feature, on demand)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="churn-cohort-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/churn-cohort-analysis">
    <summary>Cohort isolation by activation status, leading-indicator detection, save-flow design — the dedicated playbook product-analytics generalities don't provide.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cohort-based-mini-course-launch" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/cohort-based-mini-course-launch">
    <summary>Cohort sizing, calendar, Maven/Podia/Circle ops, and course-as-lead-magnet for a $99-$499 × 20-seat indie monetization sprint.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="customer-journey-bottleneck-attack" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/customer-journey-bottleneck-attack">
    <summary>Customer Journey Bottleneck Attack: codified product practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/Run a quarterly journey-bottleneck attack' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="demo-hypothesis-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/demo-hypothesis-template">
    <summary>Single-page template that forces every customer demo to declare what hypothesis the demo tests, so demos stop being feature parades.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-debt-audit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/design-debt-audit">
    <summary>Design Debt Audit delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Journey-map-driven attack: from friction map to ranked design-backlog' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Recurring audit of accumulated UX shortcuts, deprecated patterns, a</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-debt-vs-design-bet" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/design-debt-vs-design-bet">
    <summary>Design Debt Vs Design Bet delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Journey-map-driven attack: from friction map to ranked design-backlog' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Designers need a discipline for distinguishing pay-down wor</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-ops-foundations" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/design-ops-foundations">
    <summary>Rituals, tooling stack, design-team capacity model for the missing 'design-ops' sibling of marketing-ops and dev-ops.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-partner-cadence-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/design-partner-cadence-playbook">
    <summary>Design Partner Cadence Playbook delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Customer demo / sneak-peek session' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Pro/geek-tier B2B PMs need a methodology for running an ongoing design-partner cohort (c</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-partner-program-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/design-partner-program-template">
    <summary>Design Partner Program Template delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Freelance-to-SaaS transition (6-month side build)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: How to convert past freelance clients into paid design partners with disc</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-system-drift-audit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/design-system-drift-audit">
    <summary>Design System Drift Audit delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Design-system-as-code lifecycle: tokens → Storybook → Figma library → PR → governance' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: AI-generated layouts and unsupervised PRs c</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="discovery-cadence-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/discovery-cadence-design">
    <summary>Designs the interview slot, OST refresh cycle, and assumption-test pipeline for a specific team — the act continuous-discovery-habits assumes already happened.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="discovery-research-handoff-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/discovery-research-handoff-template">
    <summary>One-page handoff artefact that bundles problem, persona, JTBD, evidence, and success metric — the canonical bridge PMs hand to design and engineering after discovery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="distribution-first-ideation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/distribution-first-ideation">
    <summary>Distribution First Ideation delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Distribution-First Idea Validation (audience before product)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: All existing discovery/MVP methodologies (continuous-discovery, mv</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-flag-rollout-decision" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/feature-flag-rollout-decision">
    <summary>Feature Flag Rollout Decision delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Validate an AI feature before it consumes a quarter' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Release-planning covers release cadence; nothing covers the decision tree</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-sunset-and-deprecation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/feature-sunset-and-deprecation">
    <summary>Feature Sunset And Deprecation delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Validate an AI feature before it consumes a quarter' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Product-lifecycle and technical-debt-management touch this but no method</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feedback-loop-customer-reply-templates" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/feedback-loop-customer-reply-templates">
    <summary>Feedback Loop Customer Reply Templates delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Customer feedback triage from Intercom/Pylon' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Feedback-management methodologies cover collection + prioritization but</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="founder-dependency-audit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/founder-dependency-audit">
    <summary>Founder Dependency Audit — testable methodology for product-discovery, roadmap, lifecycle. Standalone diagnostic methodology: score every revenue line, account, credential, and client relationship by 'breaks if founder steps away for 4 weeks.' Useful for exit prep AND for sustainable operations even with no exit intent. Currently scattered across nothing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-to-saas-time-box" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/freelancer-to-saas-time-box">
    <summary>Freelancer To Saas Time Box — testable methodology for product-discovery, roadmap, lifecycle. Most freelance-to-SaaS attempts die because client work eats the side build. Need an explicit time-box + boundary methodology to protect the SaaS slot.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="friction-to-backlog" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/friction-to-backlog">
    <summary>Friction To Backlog — testable methodology for product-discovery, roadmap, lifecycle. Converting journey-map friction nodes into prioritised tickets is the actual leverage point of mapping; corpus stops at the artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gdpr-for-solo-saas" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/gdpr-for-solo-saas">
    <summary>Gdpr For Solo Saas — testable methodology for product-discovery, roadmap, lifecycle. Pragmatic GDPR scope for a one-person SaaS: which obligations actually apply, what minimal posture looks like, when to lawyer up. Not the same content as 'GDPR for enterprises'. Missing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="indie-portfolio-scorecard" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/indie-portfolio-scorecard">
    <summary>Indie Portfolio Scorecard — testable methodology for product-discovery, roadmap, lifecycle. Multi-product indies need a single scorecard view: MRR per product, growth %, support load, hours/wk, joy. faion's product-lifecycle is too enterprise. A purpose-built scorecard methodology is the missing keystone.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kano-prioritization" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/kano-prioritization">
    <summary>Kano Prioritization — testable methodology for product-discovery, roadmap, lifecycle. Faion has MoSCoW and RICE but no Kano. Kano is essential for distinguishing must-have basics from delighters and for spotting reverse features that actively annoy users. PMs in P6 need this when leadership demands 'wow' features that data shows are indifferent.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kill-criteria-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/kill-criteria-template">
    <summary>Pre-commit explicit kill thresholds (MRR, signup velocity, joy score, runway) per indie bet so portfolio rotation stays disciplined and zombie products are sunset on schedule.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kill-or-keep-criteria" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/kill-or-keep-criteria">
    <summary>Kill Or Keep Criteria — testable methodology for product-discovery, roadmap, lifecycle. Sunsetting a side-project is taboo / underdocumented. Need a clear kill-or-keep checklist (MRR floor, traffic floor, joy floor, opportunity-cost).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kpi-tree-construction" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/kpi-tree-construction">
    <summary>Kpi Tree Construction — testable methodology for product-discovery, roadmap, lifecycle. No methodology in faion shows how to decompose an NSM into a navigable tree where each leaf has an owner, formula, and weekly cadence. Critical for OKR cascade and for ejecting vanity metrics.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="launch-comms-kit-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/launch-comms-kit-template">
    <summary>Launch Comms Kit Template — testable methodology for product-discovery, roadmap, lifecycle. product-launch methodology covers strategy; the actual launch-day artifacts (changelog, in-app banner copy, support FAQ) have no shared scaffold.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="launch-tier-decision-frame" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/launch-tier-decision-frame">
    <summary>Launch Tier Decision Frame — testable methodology for product-discovery, roadmap, lifecycle. product-launch is monolithic; PMs need a frame to decide silent / standard / flagship launch given audience + risk.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="maintain-mode-sops-solo" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/maintain-mode-sops-solo">
    <summary>Maintain Mode Sops Solo: codified product practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Multi-product portfolio rotation: ship N small bets per year' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="metric-deviation-hypothesis-framework" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/metric-deviation-hypothesis-framework">
    <summary>Metric Deviation Hypothesis Framework: codified product practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/Weekly product metrics review' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-product-portfolio-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/multi-product-portfolio-management">
    <summary>Time-slicing, kill criteria, and shared-audience leverage for indie hackers running 3-7 micro-products on $19/mo budget.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mvp-instrumentation-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/mvp-instrumentation-checklist">
    <summary>Mvp Instrumentation Checklist: codified product practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/Discovery to shipped MVP' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="north-star-metric-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/north-star-metric-design">
    <summary>North Star Metric Design: codified product practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/Build a defensible KPI tree from a fuzzy company OKR' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="north-star-vs-okr-confidence-calibration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/north-star-vs-okr-confidence-calibration">
    <summary>North Star Vs Okr Confidence Calibration: codified product practice that turns the recurring 'role-product-manager/Weekly product metrics review' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="owner-handover-sop-kit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/owner-handover-sop-kit">
    <summary>Owner Handover Sop Kit: codified product practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Prep the agency for acquisition (or graceful walk-away)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pivot-vs-quit-decision-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/pivot-vs-quit-decision-template">
    <summary>Pivot Vs Quit Decision Template: codified product practice that turns the recurring 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Pivot from failed v1 to v2' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pmf-rubric-for-solos" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/pmf-rubric-for-solos">
    <summary>Pmf Rubric For Solos: codified product practice that turns the recurring 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Product/Market Fit hunt (post-MVP, pre-traction)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="portfolio-sunset-decision-frame" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/portfolio-sunset-decision-frame">
    <summary>Portfolio Sunset Decision Frame — pinned decision-frame for the product manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so annual product strategy refresh stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="portfolio-triage-indie" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/portfolio-triage-indie">
    <summary>Portfolio Triage Indie — pinned method for the indie hacker: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so weekly portfolio metric scan stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="post-launch-72h-watch-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/post-launch-72h-watch-runbook">
    <summary>Post Launch 72h Watch Runbook — pinned runbook for the product manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so launch pr sign-off + coordination stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prd-via-ai-without-losing-why" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/prd-via-ai-without-losing-why">
    <summary>Prd Via AI Without Losing Why — pinned method for the product manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so validate an ai feature before it consumes a quarter stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pricing-experiment-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/pricing-experiment-design">
    <summary>Live pricing experiments (van Westendorp on production traffic, grandfathering policy, cohort-segmented A/B legality, price-sensitivity flags).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pricing-experiment-log" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/pricing-experiment-log">
    <summary>Pricing Experiment Log — pinned log for the indie hacker: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so pricing experiment toggle stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pricing-experiment-spec-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/pricing-experiment-spec-template">
    <summary>Pricing Experiment Spec Template — pinned template for the product manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so pricing experiment, hypothesis to result stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="productized-service-canvas" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/productized-service-canvas">
    <summary>One-page canvas for productizing a recurring service into a fixed-outcome, fixed-price, fixed-timeline offer with explicit scope-in/scope-out and a repeatable SOP.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="productized-service-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/productized-service-design">
    <summary>Productized Service Design — pinned method for the micro-agency founder: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so productize one service from custom to fixed stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="productized-service-launch" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/productized-service-launch">
    <summary>Productized Service Launch — pinned method for the technical freelancer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so productize a recurring engagement into a fixed-scope offer stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="qbr-deck-template-services" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/qbr-deck-template-services">
    <summary>QBR Deck Template Services — pinned template for the micro-agency founder: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so quarter-end retention review (qbr cycle, 4 weeks) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rfc-lite-pm-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/rfc-lite-pm-template">
    <summary>RFC Lite PM Template — pinned template for the product manager: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so feature brief (rfc-lite) writing session stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rice-for-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/rice-for-design">
    <summary>Rice For Design — pinned method for the UX/UI designer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so journey-map-driven attack: from friction map to ranked design-backlog stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rice-for-one-person-cheatsheet" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/rice-for-one-person-cheatsheet">
    <summary>RICE adjusted for the solo SaaS builder: Reach baselined to a small absolute user count, Effort in dev-days not dev-weeks, Confidence forced to three discrete levels, and a WIP-1 framing that forces a single bet per Sunday roadmap ritual instead of a ranked stack of parallel work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="roadmap-drift-detection-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/roadmap-drift-detection-checklist">
    <summary>Roadmap Drift Detection Checklist: a weekly PM-side diagnostic that scores roadmap-vs-actual drift before it silently erodes credibility.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="segment-aware-design-system" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/segment-aware-design-system">
    <summary>Tier-aware experiences: same design system expressing different states (locked, preview, full) across free/paid or B2C/B2B segments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-bug-triage-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/solo-bug-triage-rubric">
    <summary>P0/P1/P2 + impact-reach scoring scaled for an ARR-honest solo founder — separates "fix now" from "fix never" in under 60 seconds per bug.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-go-no-go-criteria" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/solo-go-no-go-criteria">
    <summary>Pre-written kill/go rubric the solo founder commits to before validation begins — verdict at decision time follows the rubric, not the founder's attachment to the idea.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-kpi-dashboard-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/solo-kpi-dashboard-template">
    <summary>Concrete dashboard spec — metrics, queries, tools, refresh cadence — for a $0–50k ARR solo SaaS to run a 30-minute Friday pulse without a BI engineer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-saas-legal-docs-pack" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/solo-saas-legal-docs-pack">
    <summary>Minimum viable legal-doc pack — ToS, Privacy, refund policy, cookie banner, DPA — a solo SaaS needs in place before charging the first customer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-memo-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/strategy-memo-template">
    <summary>Produces a 2-page strategy memo (vision, bets, non-bets, success metrics) that replaces 40-slide decks for annual product strategy refresh.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="subscription-lifecycle-edge-cases" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/subscription-lifecycle-edge-cases">
    <summary>Subscription Lifecycle Edge Cases: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Pre-launch hardening: vibe-coded MVP → safe-to-bill production'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sunset-failed-product-playbook" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/sunset-failed-product-playbook">
    <summary>Refund policy, customer migration, domain reuse, asset salvage, public retro — how to shut down a failing product gracefully.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sunset-vs-fold-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/sunset-vs-fold-framework">
    <summary>Sunset Vs Fold Framework: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p3-technical-freelancer/Freelance-to-SaaS transition (6-month side build)'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="support-tool-pm-triage-spec" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/support-tool-pm-triage-spec">
    <summary>Support Tool Pm Triage Spec: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-product-manager/Customer feedback triage from Intercom/Pylon'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vanity-metrics-audit" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/vanity-metrics-audit">
    <summary>Vanity Metrics Audit: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-product-manager/Build a defensible KPI tree from a fuzzy company OKR'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vendor-evaluation-scorecard" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/product/vendor-evaluation-scorecard">
    <summary>Recurring atomic-task scorecard for new SaaS tool, observability platform, AI provider evaluation — the buyer-side complement of gtm-* pages.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="weekly-pm-async-broadcast-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/weekly-pm-async-broadcast-template">
    <summary>Weekly Pm Async Broadcast Template: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-product-manager/Monday roadmap pulse review'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="what-you-dont-know-about-launch-pre-mortem" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/what-you-dont-know-about-launch-pre-mortem">
    <summary>What You Dont Know About Launch Pre Mortem: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Pre-launch hardening: vibe-coded MVP → safe-to-bill production'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="win-loss-quarterly-pm-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/product/win-loss-quarterly-pm-template">
    <summary>Quarterly synthesis stitching CRM data + interviews + competitive notes — the integrated artefact P6 PMs own.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
