<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Azure DevOps Boards Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Azure DevOps Boards methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="process-template-immutable-after-create" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Process template (Basic / Agile / Scrum / CMMI) MUST be chosen before any work items exist; switching after work items exist requires a documented migration plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft docs (Azure DevOps process templates)">the template defines work-item types, states, and fields; post-hoc switches lose data and silently re-shape reports.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="area-and-iteration-paths-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Area paths reflect ownership (team or component) and iteration paths reflect time (release/sprint); mixing them in a single dimension is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft docs">mixed area+iteration paths break the standard reports and stop the boards from filtering correctly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="wiql-queries-versioned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shared queries MUST be stored under a versioned folder (e.g. /Shared Queries/v2/active-bugs) with a date suffix; ad-hoc edits to shared queries are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Azure DevOps platform audits">shared-query drift silently changes every dashboard that consumes the query.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="board-column-maps-to-state" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every board column MUST map to exactly one work-item state; columns mapped to multiple states or empty mappings are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft docs">mismatched columns cause cards to teleport between columns when the underlying state changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="swimlanes-for-classification-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Swimlanes SHOULD represent classification (e.g. risk tier, customer segment), NOT additional workflow state; using swimlanes to model state is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Azure DevOps audits">swimlanes that encode state collide with column-to-state mapping and confuse the team.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="permissions-least-privilege" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Project Administrators group MUST be limited to &lt;=3 people; team-leads use Contributor + scoped Stakeholder access for outside reviewers.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft security guidance">broad Project Administrator membership is the #1 cause of accidental process-template overwrites.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
