<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="product-operations">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>When a Product Ops function exists, the PM is a consumer and partner. PM-side agents read from the canonical store and author narrative artifacts; Product Ops agents own system-of-record writes.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>product-operations</tag>
      <tag>product-manager</tag>
      <tag>raci</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
      <tag>hand-off</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>product-ops-partnership</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Product Operations (PM-side)</title>
    <summary>When a Product Ops function exists, the PM is a consumer and partner — not its operator. PM-side agents are pure readers of the canonical store (Linear/Jira/Productboard rollups) and authors of narrative artifacts (specs, decision memos, discovery memos). Hand-offs are explicit: PM drafts land in a Product Ops queue (PR, Slack thread, Notion draft) where the Product Ops agent applies the write. The PM never bypasses that queue.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>96% of organizations now have a Product Ops function; 50% report to CPO. PMs who run parallel rollups in their own subagents produce numbers that diverge from org-published figures — trust collapses when two decks contradict each other in the same meeting. The hard rule: PM-side agents read, Product Ops agents write.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>PM onboarding into an org with an existing Product Ops function — needs explicit RACI between own subagents and Product Ops automations.</item>
        <item>Multiple PMs requesting inconsistent artifacts — route through the Product Ops canonical store.</item>
        <item>Preparing a board/exec/portfolio review — consume Product Ops outputs instead of re-deriving.</item>
        <item>PM proposes a new ceremony or template — hand off the converged output to Product Ops to ship org-wide.</item>
        <item>PM receives a Product Ops insight and needs to convert it into a discovery or kill decision.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solopreneur / single-PM team with no Product Ops function — use solo-tier skills directly.</item>
        <item>Product Ops charter is undefined — drive brainstorm on the charter first.</item>
        <item>Strategic decisions (pricing, positioning, kill/scale, hiring) — the PM owns these, not Product Ops.</item>
        <item>Customer-facing comms (release notes, interviews, positioning copy) — PM owns the content.</item>
        <item>First 30 days of a new product where the workflow is unstable.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Core Boundary Rule">
      <rule>
        <statement>PM-side agents are pure readers of the canonical store and authors of narrative artifacts (specs, discovery memos, decision logs); Product Ops agents own system-of-record writes.</statement>
        <rationale>PMs who run parallel rollups in their own subagents produce numbers that diverge from org-published figures; when two decks contradict in the same meeting, trust in both collapses.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Issue PM-side agents read-only tokens for Linear/Jira/Productboard; enforce the boundary at the auth layer, not by prompt instructions.</statement>
        <rationale>Prompt instructions saying "do not write to Jira" are overridden by agents with write tokens; token-scoped access is the only reliable contract.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>PM-side brainstorms produce proposals; the publish step lives in Product Ops. Hand off, do not write directly.</statement>
        <rationale>Template fragmentation — 3 squads with 3 spec templates — happens when PMs publish unilaterally; the hand-off queue is what makes templates converge org-wide.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="RACI Table">
      <p>PM owns (R, A): author spec/discovery memo/decision log, define a KPI, decide continue/pivot/kill. Product Ops owns (R, A): run weekly portfolio rollup, set roadmap entry status in Productboard, ship a new template org-wide, schedule a release, distribute stakeholder packs. PM is C on Product Ops activities; Product Ops is C on PM-authored content.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Canonical Store Protocol">
      <rule>
        <statement>PM memos cite the canonical store by URL (e.g., /ops-store/rollup-2026-04-21.md), not by "I queried Linear and found..." — makes hand-offs auditable and kills shadow rollups at the document layer.</statement>
        <rationale>URL-cited sources can be verified; paraphrased queries cannot. Shadow rollups are invisible when they look like primary analysis; URL-citation makes the source explicit.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>If a Product Ops rollup is older than 48 hours, stop and request a refresh — do not substitute a fresh scrape from Linear/Jira.</statement>
        <rationale>Stale rollups used in exec decks create a presentation with out-of-date numbers; presenting stale data as current is worse than presenting no data at all.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Maturity Model">
      <p>Level 1 Tactical: process documentation, tool management, template standardization. Level 2 Strategic: data infrastructure, insights delivery, cross-functional alignment. Level 3 Transformational: AI automation, predictive analytics, automated stakeholder communication.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Before requesting an AI-predictive capacity report from Product Ops, the PM agent checks the documented Product Ops maturity level; if Level 1, refuse the request and propose a Level 1 alternative.</statement>
        <rationale>Requesting Level 3 outputs from a Level 1 function produces either hallucinated predictions or shadow rollups that undermine the function; maturity-gating prevents PM impatience from corrupting the Product Ops contract.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="2026 Market Data">
      <p>96% of organizations have a Product Ops function. 75% of dedicated teams work centralized. 50% report directly to CPO. Top challenge: role clarity and responsibilities. PM Satisfaction tracked by 54% of teams; Collaboration Metrics by 37%; Cycle Time and Decision Quality by others.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-Native Product Ops">
      <p>Level 3 AI-native capabilities: automated status updates and reporting, AI-powered roadmap analysis, predictive capacity planning, automated stakeholder communication. These capabilities require a functioning Level 2 data infrastructure first.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Product Ops is evolving from process orchestration to strategic enablement; teams must prove impact through business outcomes, not just efficiency gains.</statement>
        <rationale>PM Satisfaction as a success metric (used by 54% of teams) measures internal customer experience; it is necessary but insufficient — the PM must also track downstream product outcomes that Product Ops enabled.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="PM-Side Rules for Consuming Product Ops">
      <rule>
        <statement>Label every Product Ops output as signal in PM memos, with a fixed header: "Source: Product Ops rollup, freshness timestamp. PM decision pending below."</statement>
        <rationale>Unlabeled Product Ops outputs in PM memos blur the PM/Ops accountability boundary; the label makes the PM's decision-making role explicit and prevents decision laundering.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a quarterly contract audit with improver to detect PM-side shadow rollups, Product Ops automations no PM reads, and dropped hand-offs.</statement>
        <rationale>The PM/Ops boundary drifts silently; a quarterly explicit audit is the only mechanism that surfaces drift before it becomes entrenched as the new operating model.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Name a PM-side consumer for every Product Ops automation; if a rollup has no PM reader, flag it back to Product Ops as their debt — do not silently pretend to use it.</statement>
        <rationale>Unused automations consume Product Ops capacity without producing decisions; naming consumers creates accountability on both sides of the hand-off.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>PM agent getting write token "for convenience" and starting to edit Linear tickets directly.</description>
        <reason>Once an agent has write access and uses it without triggering an error, the habit is established; audit token scopes per agent in CI and refuse new writer tokens without a Product Ops co-sign.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Shadow rollups. PM subagents that read Linear/Jira/Productboard directly (instead of the Product Ops canonical store) produce numbers that diverge from the org-published figures. The PM ships a deck, Product Ops ships a different deck, trust collapses.</description>
        <reason>Always read from the canonical store.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Charter drift. When a PM's own subagent gets good at status packs, the PM is tempted to skip Product Ops. Six months later the org has two parallel rollup systems and no one owns reconciliation.</description>
        <reason>Hard rule: PM-side agents read, Product Ops agents write.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Decision laundering. "Product Ops said the feature is at risk, so we killed it" — this offloads accountability from the PM to a function that has no decision rights.</description>
        <reason>Agents must label every Product Ops output as signal, never recommendation-to-kill.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Template fragmentation. PM uses brainstorm to design a new spec template, ships it inside their squad, never hands it to Product Ops. Three squads later there are three spec templates.</description>
        <reason>Hand-off step is mandatory.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Maturity mismatch. PM asks for AI-driven predictive capacity, Product Ops is at Level 1 (process docs only). The PM-side agent must detect and refuse the request, pointing to the maturity gap, not silently produce a fragile prediction.</description>
        <reason>Maturity mismatch becomes technical debt when a capability is built on top of immature infrastructure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>OKR-from-Product-Ops trap. Product Ops can roll up OKR progress; it cannot author meaningful OKRs. PMs who ask their subagent to "use Product Ops to write our OKRs" get cargo-culted documents.</description>
        <reason>OKRs need strategic context the rollup does not contain; require human sign-off on every PM-authored OKR.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent saying "Product Ops recommends killing feature F-123" — recommendation laundering.</description>
        <reason>Product Ops provides signal, not recommendations; recommendations without decision authority confuse accountability. Strip "Product Ops recommends" language at the prompt level; only the PM recommends.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>PM posts a "draft" directly into Notion canonical pages because the hand-off queue felt like ceremony.</description>
        <reason>The queue is the contract, not ceremony; lock the canonical pages at the API level so "drafts" cannot bypass the queue even when the PM considers them harmless.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Stale rollup as fresh data. PM agent reads rollup-latest.md whose last_updated is 5 days old, presents it in an exec deck.</description>
        <reason>Always read the freshness header and refuse to compose stakeholder content on stale inputs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Cargo-cult OKRs from rollups. LLM sees "feature X regressed by 12%" and proposes an OKR "improve X by 20%."</description>
        <reason>OKRs need strategic context the rollup does not contain. Require human sign-off on every PM-authored OKR.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Cross-system ID drift in PM artefacts. PM memo cites "feature 123" ambiguously across Productboard / Jira / Linear IDs.</description>
        <reason>Always resolve through the canonical mapping table Product Ops maintains.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Privacy contamination. PM pulls customer interview transcripts into the same context as Product Ops rollups; PII leaks into the metrics store.</description>
        <reason>Keep PM narrative store and Product Ops metrics store on separate auth domains.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Charter ambiguity coded into prompts. A prompt that says "use Product Ops or just query the data yourself" trains the agent to bypass the function.</description>
        <reason>Prompts must be unambiguous: read from canonical store, hand off to Product Ops, full stop.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Maturity-skip silence. Agent silently produces a Level 3 predictive output even though Product Ops is at Level 1.</description>
        <reason>Make the maturity check a hard gate, not a soft warning.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>Model the PM and Product Ops as two distinct agent surfaces with a contract between them. Product Ops owns the canonical store (Postgres / Notion DB / dbt model) and the write-back automations. The PM's subagents are pure readers of that store plus authors of narrative artefacts (specs, discovery memos, decision logs). Hand-offs are explicit: a PM-side draft that needs to land in a system-of-record is posted to a Product Ops queue (GitHub PR, Slack thread, Notion draft DB) where the Product Ops agent applies the write. The PM never bypasses that queue. Inside this repo the boundary maps cleanly to faion-product-manager (PM domain agent, this skill) consuming outputs from a faion-product-ops orchestrator described in the sibling methodology, with brainstorm and faion-sdd as PM downstream tools.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Recommended Subagents">
      <p>faion-product-manager — Owner of this skill. Reads the Product Ops canonical store; produces specs, decision memos, prioritisation tables; never writes to Linear / Jira / Productboard directly.</p>
      <p>faion-product-ops (sibling, pro/product/product-operations/) — Sole authority for canonical-store reads and system-of-record writes. PM agents call it as a service, not a peer.</p>
      <p>brainstorm — PM uses diverge-converge cycles for new ceremonies, templates, KPI definitions. Output is a converged proposal, handed to Product Ops to ship org-wide. Never publishes unilaterally.</p>
      <p>faion-research-agent — When a Product Ops insight ("KPI dropped 12%") needs causal investigation that is out of scope for Product Ops itself (competitor moves, market shifts), the PM delegates to research.</p>
      <p>faion-sdd / feature-executor — Downstream of a PM decision: when the PM accepts a Product Ops "missing spec" warning, the PM (not Product Ops) spawns the SDD task to author it.</p>
      <p>improver — Quarterly: PM runs improver over the PM/ProductOps contract to detect drift (PM-side shadow rollups, Product Ops automations no PM reads, dropped hand-offs).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Prompt Patterns">
      <p>PM weekly review (read-only consumption of Product Ops outputs): Read /ops-store/rollup-latest.md and /ops-store/portfolio-heatmap.json (produced by faion-product-ops). Do not query Linear/Jira/Productboard directly. For each at-risk feature in my portfolio, produce: 1) PM call (continue/pivot/kill), 2) discovery gap, 3) decision owner. If the rollup is older than 48h, stop and request a Product Ops refresh — do not substitute a fresh scrape.</p>
      <p>PM proposes a new artefact (hand-off into Product Ops): I want a new "experiment readiness" template. Run brainstorm in diverge-converge mode (3 angles, 1 converge). Output a single draft to proposals/experiment-readiness.md. Then post to the Product Ops intake queue (Slack #product-ops-intake) with subject "template proposal" and stop. Do not commit to /templates/ — that is Product Ops's write.</p>
      <p>PM responding to a Product Ops signal (signal vs decision separation): Product Ops flagged feature F-123 as at-risk (slip > 5d, 2 blocked dependencies). Treat this as signal, not recommendation. Pull the spec, the last 3 customer interviews, and the metric. Produce a one-page PM decision memo (continue/pivot/kill) with rationale. Tag the memo @pm-handle; do not change feature state in Productboard.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <p>Read-only credentials for PM agents. Issue Linear/Jira/Productboard tokens with read scope only. The contract is enforced by the auth layer, not by prompt instructions.</p>
      <p>Reference the canonical store by URL, not by query. PM memos cite /ops-store/rollup-2026-04-21.md, not "I queried Linear and found...". Makes hand-offs auditable and kills shadow rollups at the document layer.</p>
      <p>Label every Product Ops output as signal. PM-side templates have a fixed header: "Source: Product Ops rollup, freshness timestamp. PM decision pending below."</p>
      <p>Hand-off, do not write. PM-side brainstorms produce proposals; the publish step lives in Product Ops. This is the single most important rule and the easiest to break.</p>
      <p>Quarterly contract audit. Run improver against PM-side flows with the explicit question: "Where am I querying system-of-record directly? Where is Product Ops authoring narrative I should own?"</p>
      <p>Maturity-gate PM asks. Before requesting an AI-predictive capacity report from Product Ops, the PM agent checks the documented Product Ops maturity level; if Level 1, refuse the request and propose a Level 1 alternative.</p>
      <p>Distinguish narrative from numbers. PM owns prose (specs, memos, positioning); Product Ops owns numbers (KPIs, rollups, capacity). Composition lives in PM artefacts; origination of either lives nowhere else.</p>
      <p>Name a PM-side consumer for every Product Ops automation. If a rollup has no PM reader, it is Product Ops's debt — flag it back, do not silently pretend to use it.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools and Services">
      <p>The PM-side tooling deliberately overlaps minimally with Product Ops's write-side stack. PM agents read; they should not need write CLIs at all.</p>
      <p>notion-cli / @notionhq/client (read-only token): Read canonical store and Product Ops rollups. Postgres psql (read-only role): Query the dbt-modelled metrics layer Product Ops publishes. gh: Read roadmap PRs, comment on Product Ops template proposals. slack-cli (read scope): Subscribe to #product-ops-rollups, post hand-off requests. mermaid-cli (mmdc): Render decision-tree / dependency diagrams in PM memos. pandoc: Convert PM markdown memos to PDF / docx for stakeholder packs. jq / yq: Parse Product Ops JSON/YAML outputs in PM scripts.</p>
      <p>Services: Notion (canonical store, RO) — PM reads Product Ops DBs; never edits structure. Linear — Read-only token for PM agents; writes via Product Ops. Jira Cloud — Reads only; ticket creation through Product Ops. Productboard — Source-of-truth for features; PM consumes the rolled-up view. PostHog / Amplitude / Mixpanel — PM reads pre-modelled metrics, not raw events. dbt Cloud / Lightdash / Metabase — The contract surface: PM dashboards live here. Slack — Hand-off channel + digest distribution. Loom / Granola / Otter — PM artefacts (interview clips, meeting recaps) — outside Product Ops scope. Confluence / Notion (narrative) — Specs, decision logs, discovery memos — owned by PM, not Product Ops. n8n — Workspace runs an n8n instance; PM uses it for personal flows that do not touch system-of-record.</p>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/pm-ops-contract-check.sh" purpose="Block PM-side write attempts to system-of-record owned by Product Ops"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.productoperations.com"/>
      <link href="https://www.productboard.com/research/state-of-product-ops/"/>
      <link href="https://www.svpg.com/product-ops/"/>
      <link href="https://www.mindtheproduct.com/tag/product-ops/"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/product-ops"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
