<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-risk-categories" title="Market Risk Categories and Scoring">
  <summary>Five market-risk sub-categories with scoring rules and the citation-enforcement requirement.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Every risk row must cite a paragraph or table from an existing market research file (market-research.md, competitive-analysis.md, pricing-research.md, trend-analysis.md, niche-evaluation.md). No row may cite general knowledge.</statement>
    <rationale>Uncited risk rows are opinion, not analysis. Citation enforcement makes the register auditable, prevents stale scores, and forces re-run when source documents change.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Risk Sub-Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Demand: market too small, poor timing, no validated wedge (note: score against the validated wedge, not the TAM)</item>
      <item>Competition: incumbent copies feature, well-funded rival enters, adjacent player pivots in (include not-yet-entered threats)</item>
      <item>Pricing: split into four sub-rows — commoditization, price war, anchor mismatch, willingness-to-pay collapse</item>
      <item>Trend: technology obsolescence, regulatory shift, macro headwind reversing the adoption curve</item>
      <item>Channel: single-channel dependence (auto High-prob when one channel exceeds 40% of pipeline)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Probability x Impact Scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score probability and impact independently on H/M/L (3/2/1), multiply for Risk Score (1-9). Force at least 2 rows at H/H (score 9) and at least 2 rows at L/L (score 1) — reject balanced-looking registers where every row is M/M.</statement>
      <rationale>Symmetric scoring (all Med/Med) is the most common agent bias; forcing distribution prevents false balance and surfaces real exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>High probability: more than 50% chance in the planning horizon</item>
      <item>Medium probability: 20-50% chance</item>
      <item>Low probability: below 20% chance</item>
      <item>High impact: existential threat to the segment or pricing model</item>
      <item>Medium impact: major setback requiring significant resource reallocation</item>
      <item>Low impact: minor inconvenience, resolved within one sprint</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Response Strategies">
    <list>
      <item>Avoid: eliminate the risk entirely (high prob + high impact); typically means not entering a segment or not adopting a channel</item>
      <item>Mitigate: reduce probability or impact (medium risks); requires concrete actions with named owners</item>
      <item>Transfer: shift to insurance, contracts, or SLAs (low probability, high impact)</item>
      <item>Accept: document and monitor (low risks)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every High-priority row with exactly one of: kill-decision criterion, pivot criterion, or budget reallocation criterion. A risk row without a connected action is decoration.</statement>
      <rationale>Risk registers that document threats without decision criteria are never acted on; the action criterion turns a log into a decision trigger.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Trigger Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Trigger metrics must be observable in the company's existing dashboard. "ARPU drops below $X for 2 consecutive months" works; "market sentiment shifts" does not.</statement>
      <rationale>Unobservable triggers are never fired; the contingency plan is never activated; the risk register provides false security.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
