<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process-and-antipatterns" title="Risk Assessment Process and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Five-step market-risk assessment process, pre-mortem technique, and AI-agent gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Five-Step Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Enumerate risks: run the enumeration agent against market-research.md, competitive-analysis.md, pricing-research.md; require minimum 2 risks per sub-category (demand, competition, pricing, trend, channel)</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Red-team pre-mortem: run a market-specific pre-mortem with 3 failure branches (segment did not materialize, competitor won, price elasticity broke the model)</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Score with citations: apply prob x impact; every cell must cite a specific paragraph or table from the source files; reject rows without citations</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Human review: owner accepts or rejects each row and assigns a trigger metric already visible in the company dashboard</item>
      <item>Step 5 — Persist and schedule: save as market-risk-register.md; re-run enumeration and pre-mortem passes monthly or on any commit to source research files</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/risk-register.md">Risk register template with high/medium/low priority tables and contingency format</reference>
    <reference path="templates/pre-mortem.md">Pre-mortem facilitation template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/market-risk-lint.sh">Citation-enforcement linter for risk register rows</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Pre-Mortem Technique">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the pre-mortem with 3 distinct agent personas (skeptical customer, well-funded competitor, regulator or platform owner) rather than a single agent pass. Consolidate outputs; do not average them.</statement>
      <rationale>A solo agent run produces a single failure narrative that confirms the briefing document's tone. Multiple adversarial personas surface independent failure paths that the enumeration pass misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Demand risk scored against TAM rather than the validated wedge</description>
      <reason>A large TAM with no validated entry wedge is the highest-loss failure mode; anchoring on TAM produces artificially low demand-risk scores.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Pricing risk collapsed into one row instead of four sub-rows</description>
      <reason>Aggregating four distinct failure modes (commoditization, price war, anchor mismatch, WTP collapse) into one row averages them and hides the real exposure.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Channel-dependence risk scored Medium when one channel exceeds 40% of pipeline</description>
      <reason>Any single channel above 40% should be auto-scored High probability unless 3+ years of stable retention evidence exists.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Risk register updated only at project kick-off</description>
      <reason>Stale registers are worse than none; they create false security. Re-run at minimum monthly and on every commit to source research files.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent quotes multi-billion-dollar TAM and scores demand risk Low</description>
      <reason>Force the prompt to score against the validated wedge (named buyer segment, confirmed problem, pipeline evidence), not the TAM ceiling.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent uses stale competitor lists from training data</description>
      <reason>Require the agent to re-read competitive-analysis.md and verify competitor domains via faion-domain-checker-agent before citing any competitive risk row.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent mitigation language defaults to "diversify channels", "monitor competitors", "iterate pricing"</description>
      <reason>Ban these phrases; require action verb + named owner + measurable trigger + budget cap. Vague mitigations are never executed.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent ships "Avoid" response on market risk autonomously (e.g., killing a segment)</description>
      <reason>Avoid-strategy responses mean killing a segment, geo, or pricing tier — never let an agent execute this unattended. Hard human-in-the-loop gate required.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Risk IDs change every agent run (R1..Rn renumbered)</description>
      <reason>Use a stable hash of the risk statement or instruct the agent to diff-merge against the existing register; changing IDs break longitudinal tracking.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
