<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="value-proposition-design Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for value-proposition-design. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Populate the Customer Profile before the Value Map — working in the opposite direction produces self-serving analysis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Value-first mapping leads to confirmation bias; customer-first mapping forces the product to respond to real needs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rank pains by severity before mapping pain relievers; a product that addresses 5 minor pains but ignores the one extreme pain has poor fit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Resource constraint forces prioritization; addressing severity ensures the product solves the highest-impact problem.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use verbatim customer language in the canvas — "takes forever to sync" is more actionable than "slow synchronization".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Direct language preserves emotional intensity and avoids abstract paraphrasing that loses signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write 3 value proposition statement variants using the For/Who/Is/That/Unlike/We formula. Each variant should emphasize a different differentiator. Avoid marketing superlatives ("best", "easiest", "most powerful").</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Multiple variants surface different positioning angles; superlatives are legally and emotionally risky.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test the value proposition statement with 5 target customers before using it in ads; if they cannot identify themselves in "For [target customer]", the segment is too narrow or the language is off.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Customer feedback validates the segment definition and language clarity before investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map every gain creator and pain reliever to a specific product feature — if you cannot name the feature, the claim is aspirational, not a real proposition.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unmapped claims are undeliverable and create customer disappointment at launch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Revisit the canvas after 90 days of shipping — pains that seemed extreme at discovery may have been solved by workarounds, revealing new priorities.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Market response shifts customer priorities; stale canvases drive feature bloat instead of impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
