<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Instagram Basics — Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the Instagram Basics methodology + two self-routing anchors. Each pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-reels-80-percent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Allocate ≥80% of weekly content effort to Reels. Stories take ≤15%, Feed posts ≤5%. Reels with hook score &lt; 4/5 are not shipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal SMM audits Q1 2026; Meta engagement reports 2024-2026">Reels deliver ~2× the reach of photos by pushing to non-followers. Accounts that ignore Reels get ~1/4 the reach of Reels-led accounts. The first 1.5s decides reach — rate hooks explicitly to enforce quality discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-on-screen-text-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Reel MUST include on-screen text covering the key claim. Voiceover-only Reels are rejected before publish.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta product analytics; published mute-watch stats">~80% of Instagram viewers watch muted. Voiceover-only scripts fail to communicate to the majority of viewers.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-hashtag-minimalism" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use 3-5 hashtags per post, mixed tiers (small / medium / large). Never request 30 hashtags from an agent or pad a caption.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta ranking documentation 2024-2026">Meta favors topic understanding over hashtag density. Over-indexing on hashtags underperforms and looks spammy; agent prompts that demand 30 hashtags yield stale tag lists.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-bio-three-line-formula" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The bio MUST follow the three-line formula: line 1 = what you do for whom; line 2 = credibility/proof; line 3 = CTA. Bios longer than 160 chars are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal SMM audits; Instagram Business docs">Visitors decide to follow in under 3 seconds. A three-line bio that answers "what, why-trust, what-next" converts profile visits to followers more reliably than a clever but ambiguous bio.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-tiktok-watermark" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cross-posted Reels MUST have the TikTok watermark stripped (or be re-edited natively). Watermarked Reels are flagged at QA and not shipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta moderation guidelines">Instagram suppresses reach for Reels that contain the TikTok watermark. Cross-posted content must be re-edited for Instagram's format.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-dm-automation-approved-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DM automation MUST go through an approved partner (ManyChat / Messenger Platform). Unofficial DM-bot APIs are forbidden — they get accounts suspended.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta Messenger Platform policy">Instagram restricts DM automation to approved partners. Unapproved bots get accounts flagged or suspended; that risk dwarfs any reach gain.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-pillar-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every draft MUST carry a content-pillar tag (Opinion / Value / Question / Personal / Curated). Pillar-less drafts are rejected. Cap agent-generated posts at 50% of weekly volume.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal SMM audits Q1 2026">Without pillar tags, agents drift toward whatever style won last week. The other 50% must come from the operator's lived context — algorithm rewards authentic conversation, not publishing volume.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold (audience overlaps Instagram demographics, team can shoot/edit Reels, brand voice allows visual conversational register), execute the daily content-pack ideation + ship procedure from `04-procedure.xml`.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's affirmative leaf.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Skip-If condition is present (B2B enterprise audience, no video capacity, text-heavy brand voice, heavily-regulated industry), do NOT apply this methodology. Route to `growth-linkedin-strategy` or a text-first channel methodology instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's skip leaf.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
