<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-profile" title="Instagram Profile, Reels, and Hashtag Strategy">
  <summary>Profile optimization rules, Reels-first format priorities, Stories strategy, and hashtag minimalism rules.</summary>

  <section title="Profile Optimization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure the Instagram bio as: line 1 = what you do for whom; line 2 = credibility/proof; line 3 = CTA.</statement>
      <rationale>Visitors decide to follow in under 3 seconds. A three-line bio that answers "what is this account, why should I trust it, and what do I do next" converts profile visits to followers more reliably than a clever but ambiguous bio.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Username: searchable and memorable (e.g., @yourproduct or @founder.name).</item>
      <item>Display name: include a keyword (e.g., "Mike | SaaS Growth").</item>
      <item>Profile photo: face clearly visible, bright, consistent with other platforms.</item>
      <item>Highlights: About, Products/Services, Testimonials, FAQ, Free Resources.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Reels-First Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Allocate 80% of content effort to Reels; write the hook separately and only ship Reels with hook score 4+/5.</statement>
      <rationale>Reels deliver 2x the reach of photos by pushing to non-followers. The first 1.5 seconds determine algorithmic reach — a weak hook wastes the production effort. Rating hooks explicitly forces quality discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include on-screen text in Reels; never rely on voiceover-only scripts.</statement>
      <rationale>80% of Instagram viewers watch muted. Scripts that put all content in voiceover fail to communicate to the majority of viewers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Optimal Reels length: 7-15 seconds for virality; 30-60 seconds for educational depth.</item>
      <item>Hook: first 1-2 seconds critical.</item>
      <item>Hashtags: 3-5 relevant (not 30).</item>
      <item>Caption: add context and CTA.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Stories Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post Stories daily; pair every Reel with a Story re-share within 24 hours.</statement>
      <rationale>Stories maintain relationship with existing followers while Reels reach new ones. Algorithm rewards accounts that use multiple formats consistently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Hashtag Minimalism">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use 3-5 hashtags per post (mixed small/medium/large tiers). Never request 30 hashtags from an agent.</statement>
      <rationale>Meta now favors topic understanding over hashtag density. Over-indexing on hashtags underperforms and can look spammy. Agent prompts that request 30 hashtags produce stale, low-quality tag lists.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using TikTok-watermarked Reels on Instagram.</description>
      <reason>Instagram suppresses reach for Reels that contain the TikTok watermark. Cross-posted content must have the watermark stripped and ideally be re-edited for Instagram's format.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/reel-script.txt">Reels script template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/bio-template.txt">Bio formula</reference>
</text>
