<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-content-creation" title="Instagram Content Creation and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Caption rules, carousel structure, DM automation constraints, and agent-specific failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Caption Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Caption hook must appear in the first line (before "more"); sweet spot length 150-200 characters; always include CTA.</statement>
      <rationale>Instagram truncates captions after the first line in the feed view. A hook in the first line pulls viewers to expand. Captions over 2,200 characters are permitted but rarely read in full.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce a max-words-per-slide constraint for carousel scripts; reject slide 1 with more than 10 words.</statement>
      <rationale>Carousel slides with 30+ words on slide 1 fail because viewers swipe before reading. Large, readable text on a simple visual stops the scroll.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="DM Automation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Only use approved ManyChat flows for DM automation. Never use unofficial APIs to auto-send DMs at scale.</statement>
      <rationale>Instagram restricts DM automation to approved partners (Messenger Platform). Unapproved bots get accounts flagged or suspended. Agents must never send DMs via unofficial APIs regardless of scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM-generated captions with heavy exclamation marks and emojis.</description>
      <reason>LLMs default to enthusiastic, emoji-heavy Instagram captions. This reads as inauthentic and degrades brand credibility. Explicitly prohibit exclamation marks and emojis (or set a strict per-post limit) in every prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent picks trending hashtags from training data.</description>
      <reason>Hashtag trends change weekly. Training-data hashtag suggestions are stale. Fetch current top hashtags via a research subagent or manual lookup before generating content.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>All Reel scripts follow listicle structure ("3 tips for X").</description>
      <reason>LLMs default to listicle format. Overuse of listicles reduces content variety and engagement. Force narrative or transformation arcs periodically to avoid audience fatigue.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent recommends "trending audio" without an external lookup.</description>
      <reason>The model cannot know current trending audio on Instagram — it has no real-time data. Require an external lookup before the agent recommends audio choices.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/carousel-template.txt">10-slide carousel narrative structure</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-reels.txt">Reels script generation prompt</reference>
</text>
