<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="instagram-basics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for instagram-basics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using TikTok-watermarked Reels on Instagram.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Instagram suppresses reach for Reels that contain the TikTok watermark. Cross-posted content must have the watermark stripped and ideally be re-edited for Instagram's format.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM-generated captions with heavy exclamation marks and emojis.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs default to enthusiastic, emoji-heavy Instagram captions. This reads as inauthentic and degrades brand credibility. Explicitly prohibit exclamation marks and emojis (or set a strict per-post limit) in every prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent picks trending hashtags from training data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hashtag trends change weekly. Training-data hashtag suggestions are stale. Fetch current top hashtags via a research subagent or manual lookup before generating content.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>All Reel scripts follow listicle structure ("3 tips for X").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs default to listicle format. Overuse of listicles reduces content variety and engagement. Force narrative or transformation arcs periodically to avoid audience fatigue.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent recommends "trending audio" without an external lookup.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The model cannot know current trending audio on Instagram — it has no real-time data. Require an external lookup before the agent recommends audio choices.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
