<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-crucial-conversations" title="Crucial Conversations framework: safety, stories, and preparation">
  <summary>A conversation is crucial when stakes are high, opinions differ, and emotions run strong. The first four skills — Start with Heart, Learn to Look, Make it Safe, Master My Stories — are preparation and safety work that must precede any content exchange.</summary>

  <section title="Skill 1: Start with Heart">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before starting a crucial conversation, answer four questions: What do I want for me? For them? For the relationship? For the organization? Behave as if you truly want all four outcomes simultaneously.</statement>
      <rationale>Hidden agendas (wanting to win, wanting to punish) produce scripts that are technically correct but destroy safety. The other person detects misalignment between words and intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Reject the "Fool's Choice" framing — "Either I speak up and damage the relationship, OR I stay silent and the problem continues." Both honesty and respect are achievable simultaneously.</statement>
      <rationale>The Fool's Choice is a cognitive distortion that prevents creative solutions. Accepting it makes avoidance feel justified.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skill 2: Learn to Look — safety signals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Watch for silence signals (masking with sarcasm, avoiding the topic, withdrawing) and violence signals (controlling the conversation, labeling, personal attacks). When either appears, pause content and restore safety before continuing.</statement>
      <rationale>Safety violations are the most reliable predictor of a conversation going off the rails. Content cannot land when the other person is in fight-or-flight mode.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Silence: sarcasm, changing subject, one-word answers, shutting down</item>
      <item>Violence: cutting off, overstating, labeling ("you're being defensive"), personal criticism</item>
      <item>Physical: arms crossed, looking away, raised voice, tears, flushed face</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Skill 3: Make it Safe">
    <rule>
      <statement>Restore safety with Mutual Purpose (show you care about their goals), Mutual Respect (show you value them), Contrasting (clarify what you are NOT saying), or Apology (when genuinely appropriate).</statement>
      <rationale>Safety is not the absence of disagreement — it is the belief that you can express yourself without being attacked or dismissed. Restoring it requires explicit action, not just tonal adjustment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Mutual Purpose: "I want to find a solution that works for both of us."</item>
      <item>Contrasting: "I'm not saying you're incompetent. I am saying this specific approach has caused problems."</item>
      <item>Apology: "I'm sorry I didn't raise this sooner. That wasn't fair to you."</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Skill 4: Master My Stories">
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate the observable fact, the story you told about it, and the feeling that story produced. Challenge victim stories ("They don't respect me") by reframing as ownership stories ("I haven't clearly communicated my needs").</statement>
      <rationale>Stories drive feelings, and feelings drive actions. Changing the story changes the emotional state and opens different behavioral options.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
FACT: "You submitted the report on Thursday."
STORY: "You don't care about deadlines." (interpretation — not fact)
FEELING: "I'm frustrated."

Reframe: "You may have had constraints I don't know about." (ownership story)
New feeling: "I'm curious about what happened."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <list>
      <item>Victim story: "They don't respect me" → Ownership: "I haven't clearly communicated my needs"</item>
      <item>Victim story: "They're incompetent" → Ownership: "They might have constraints I don't know"</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
