<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-state-desc" title="STATE, AMPP, DESC, and WWWF: sharing and closing">
  <summary>STATE structures the opening (Share facts → Tell story → Ask their path → Talk tentatively → Encourage testing); AMPP structures listening; DESC is for written boundary-setting; WWWF closes with specific commitments.</summary>

  <section title="Skill 5: STATE My Path">
    <rule>
      <statement>Open with observable facts (not interpretations), share your tentative story, then immediately invite the other person's perspective. The opening must be deliverable in under 60 seconds — 3-5 sentences maximum.</statement>
      <rationale>Openings longer than 60 seconds read as monologues. "Talk tentatively" ("I might be missing something") is not weakness — it is the signal that invites the other party to contribute.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
S: "The last three milestones were delivered 2-3 days late." (Share facts — observable)
T: "I'm starting to worry about whether we'll hit the launch date." (Tell story — tentative)
A: "Can you help me understand what's happening?" (Ask for their path)
T: "I might be missing context." (Talk tentatively)
E: "I'm open to hearing I'm wrong about this." (Encourage testing)
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ending the STATE opening with a rhetorical question ("You see that this is a problem, right?") instead of a genuine inquiry.</description>
      <reason>Rhetorical questions destroy the safety that the rest of STATE was building. The other person reads them as a trap.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Skill 6: AMPP — exploring others' paths">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use AMPP to understand the other person's perspective: Ask (open questions), Mirror (reflect emotions back), Paraphrase (restate content), Prime (guess their feeling if they seem stuck).</statement>
      <rationale>AMPP prevents the common failure of preparing your rebuttal while the other person is still speaking. Genuine listening requires structured attention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Ask: "What's your view?" — open the door</item>
      <item>Mirror: "You seem frustrated about this." — reflect what you observe</item>
      <item>Paraphrase: "So you're saying the timeline was unrealistic from the start?" — confirm</item>
      <item>Prime: "Are you worried about how this will affect your team's workload?" — guess if stuck</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="DESC — written boundary-setting">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use DESC for written communication (Slack, email) when a live conversation is not possible or to follow up after one. Never read DESC aloud in a meeting as a script.</statement>
      <rationale>DESC is calibrated for written async delivery. Read aloud, it sounds prepared and clinical — destroying the rapport required for a live difficult conversation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
D (Describe): "When I receive Slack messages at 10pm expecting an immediate response..."
E (Express): "I feel stressed and unable to disconnect from work..."
S (Specify): "I would like us to agree that non-urgent messages can wait until morning..."
C (Consequences): "This would help me be more focused during work hours.
If it continues, I'll need to turn off notifications entirely."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-desc-script.txt">Prompt for generating a DESC script</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Skill 7: WWWF — move to action">
    <rule>
      <statement>End every difficult conversation with WHO does WHAT by WHEN and a scheduled follow-up date. Vague commitment ("we'll do better") is not an agreement.</statement>
      <rationale>Without specific accountability, both parties leave with different interpretations of what was agreed. Follow-up date closes the loop and signals the issue is being tracked.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/wwwf-tracker.md">WWWF commitment tracker</reference>
    <reference path="templates/preparation-checklist.md">Pre-conversation preparation checklist</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-state-script.txt">Prompt for generating a STATE opening script</reference>
  </section>
</text>
