<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Small Team Comms Rhythm Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that keep a 2-3 person team aligned without adopting scrum ceremonies or formal comms-management overhead.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The team MUST have exactly three rituals and no more: async daily pulse (text), weekly live sync (≤30 min), monthly direction check (≤45 min); adding a fourth recurring meeting is a graduation signal, not an enhancement.</statement>
      <rationale>The corpus is designed for scrum or formal PM patterns; both fail at 2-3 people because the overhead exceeds the value. A three-ritual cap is the empirically converged minimum that prevents both drift (too little) and ceremony tax (too much) at this team size.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[Daily pulse  : Slack thread, end-of-day, 3 lines (did / next / blocked)
Weekly sync  : 30 min video, Monday, agenda set by Friday
Monthly check: 45 min video, last week of month, direction + roadmap]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The founder MUST NOT be the only person reporting in any ritual; every participant produces their own pulse / status — even the founder is one voice among 2-3, not the moderator.</statement>
      <rationale>When the founder runs comms as broadcasts, the second person stops bringing surfacing-worthy issues forward and the rhythm becomes a status-theatre for the founder's benefit. Equal voice is the load-bearing cultural element of the small-team variant.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The daily pulse MUST be async (text, threaded) and time-bounded so it never replaces working hours; standups-on-Zoom are explicitly forbidden at this team size.</statement>
      <rationale>Daily live standups cost 10-15 minutes plus context-switch cost; for a 2-3 person team that is 30-45 person-minutes/day burned on a ritual that serves a 10-person team. Async pulses give the same surfacing without the schedule fragmentation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The weekly sync MUST be ≤30 minutes wall-clock with a written agenda published at least 24 hours in advance; meetings without an agenda are postponed or cancelled.</statement>
      <rationale>30 minutes forces ruthless prioritisation; 24-hour agenda lead gives each participant time to think (instead of reacting in the meeting), which is the only way a 2-person sync produces decisions instead of restating-the-week.</rationale>
      <example type="bad">
        <description>Weekly sync runs 60-90 min, agenda decided live, founder talks for 70% of it.</description>
        <reason>Indistinguishable from a status broadcast; second person disengages by week 4; useful information stops flowing back to the founder.</reason>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>When the team grows to 4 or more people, this methodology MUST be retired and the team MUST adopt a different comms framework (formal PM plan, scrum-lite, etc.) within the next monthly check; ad-hoc continuation past 3 is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>The rhythm relies on every voice being equal and meetings staying ≤30 min — both break at 4+ people. An explicit graduation trigger prevents the team from limping along on rituals that no longer fit, which is the empirically most common pre-failure pattern in growing micro-agencies.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
