<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Retention Strategies Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Retention Strategies` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="one-loop-not-four" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick ONE primary retention loop matching product&apos;s natural use; optionally ONE secondary. Stacking 3+ loops simultaneously splits attention + dilutes mechanic clarity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reforge retention loops curriculum; product casework">Each loop consumes UX surface + cognitive load. 3+ loops = none feels primary; users disengage from all. One sharp loop &gt; four mediocre ones.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="match-loop-to-product-nature" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Loop archetype MUST match product&apos;s natural use (content product → content loop; social product → network loop). Forcing wrong-shape loop is the #1 retention mistake.</statement>
      <rationale source="Casey Winters / Reforge product-loop framework">Forcing a viral loop on a single-player productivity tool produces nothing. Match: content app → publishing loop; social → friend-graph loop; workflow → habit/streak; marketplace → buyer-seller loop.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="mechanic-tested-before-rollout" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Engagement mechanics (streaks, achievements, variable rewards) MUST run as a 4-6 week A/B test on a cohort before global rollout. Untested mechanics often reduce retention by triggering quit-impulses.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nir Eyal hook model; A/B test postmortems">Mechanics that look good in mockups can backfire — streak break = user quits forever. A/B test catches the inversion before it touches whole base.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="re-engagement-window-30-90" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-engagement campaigns MUST run within 30-90 days of last active. Beyond 90 days, conversion drops &gt; 70%.</statement>
      <rationale source="Iterable / Customer.io re-engagement benchmarks">Recency matters. After 90 days the user is a cold lead, not a re-engagement target. Resources better spent on net-new acquisition.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="variable-reward-not-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When using reward mechanics, MUST use variable-ratio schedule (random reward size / timing) not fixed. Fixed rewards extinct after habit forms.</statement>
      <rationale source="Skinner variable-ratio research; Duolingo retention case study">Fixed rewards become predictable + ignored after habituation. Variable schedule sustains engagement long-term — same psychological mechanism as slot machines (with the ethical hedge).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
