<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="persona-building">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>user-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Five-step evidence-anchored process creating customer archetypes from interviews. Clusters by goals/frustrations/behaviors with citation IDs, validates recognition, refreshes quarterly.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>personas</tag>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>archetypes</tag>
      <tag>product-strategy</tag>
      <tag>customer-insights</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Persona Building</title>
    <summary>A five-step process for creating semi-fictional customer archetypes grounded in real interview data: gather data from at least 10 interviews, cluster utterances by goals/frustrations/behaviours, define at most one primary and one negative persona, validate against real cohort behaviour, and refresh quarterly. Every claim must cite a source interview ID — no invented demographics.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Teams without research-grounded personas default to "everyone is our customer," producing weak positioning, features built for nobody, and messaging that resonates with no one. Fictional personas (stock photos, made-up details) are worse than none: they justify wrong decisions with false confidence. Evidence-anchored personas give product, marketing, and sales a shared archetype that can be falsified and updated.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>After running 10+ customer interviews and the team needs a shared archetype to anchor product/marketing/sales decisions.</item>
        <item>A pivot or new market entry where the prior persona is stale.</item>
        <item>Pre-launch positioning to align messaging across landing page, ads, and onboarding.</item>
        <item>Internal alignment when product and sales describe customers in incompatible terms.</item>
        <item>Annual or post-pivot review of an existing persona library.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before any real research — fictional personas are worse than none.</item>
        <item>Where the audience is well-understood from quantitative data alone (analytics, CRM cohorts) and segments, not personas, are needed.</item>
        <item>For one-off campaigns where a single value-prop test is cheaper.</item>
        <item>For B2B enterprise sales with named accounts — ICPs and buyer maps outperform personas there.</item>
        <item>When team capacity is so small that the persona will not be referenced again.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Data requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run at least 10 customer interviews before creating any persona; fewer interviews produce stereotypes, not archetypes.</statement>
        <rationale>Below 10 interviews, pattern confidence is too low to distinguish signal from individual variation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply a no-demographics-first rule: write goals and frustrations before any demographic detail.</statement>
        <rationale>Demographics trigger stereotype completion in both humans and LLMs; goals and frustrations derived first stay grounded in interview evidence.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every bullet in every persona must cite the supporting interview IDs. Never invent demographic detail not present in the transcripts.</statement>
        <rationale>Hallucinated quotes and invented demographics are the most damaging failure mode — they justify wrong decisions with false specificity.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Clustering dimensions">
      <p>Cluster utterances across four dimensions: Goals (what they want to achieve), Frustrations (what blocks them), Behaviours (how they work and buy), Information Sources (where they learn and get influenced). Each cluster needs a one-sentence pattern, supporting interview IDs, and three verbatim quotes.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Propose at most one primary persona and one negative persona (who NOT to target) per research round without explicit approval to add more.</statement>
        <rationale>Multiple personas at pre-traction stage dilute focus; negative personas are consistently skipped and are as valuable as positive ones for positioning.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Validation and refresh">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pair the persona doc with one paragraph titled "How we would notice this persona is wrong" — a falsification clause.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a falsification clause, personas accumulate institutional momentum and survive past their useful life.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Refresh cycle: minor update quarterly (interview signals, support ticket categories); major rebuild on pivots or new markets.</statement>
        <rationale>Personas frozen at year-one data keep echoing in year-three decisions against a different reality.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Show the draft persona to actual customers and ask if they recognize themselves; measure recognition rate before using for decisions.</statement>
        <rationale>Recognition testing is the fastest validation that the archetype maps to reality rather than to the research team's assumptions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Distribution">
      <rule>
        <statement>Distribute the persona where decisions are made: PM Notion, marketing brief template, sales playbook. A persona-only document gathers dust.</statement>
        <rationale>Personas only change behaviour when they are embedded in the artifacts people already use for decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Worked examples">
      <example type="good" title="Newsletter Nate persona">
        <note>Persona: Newsletter Nate (SaaS for freelance writers). Based on 14 interviews.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[## Newsletter Nate

Who: 34-year-old freelance writer running a paid newsletter with 2,000 subscribers ($4K/month from writing).

Goals: Grow subscriber base to 10,000; reduce time on operations; launch a course.

Frustrations: Email platform is expensive at scale (INT-003, INT-007, INT-011);
no easy way to sell digital products (INT-002, INT-009); analytics are confusing (INT-005).

Quote (INT-007): "I'm a writer, not a tech person. I just want it to work."

Buying trigger: Switches when current tool fails or pricing surprise hits at a growth milestone.

Falsification: If >30% of new signups are NOT running a paid newsletter, this persona is wrong.]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Agency Amy persona">
        <note>Persona: Agency Amy (project management for agencies). Based on 11 interviews.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[## Agency Amy

Who: 38-year-old agency owner, 5-person design agency, $500K annual revenue.

Goals: Stop projects going over budget (INT-001, INT-006); improve client communication (INT-004);
scale without adding overhead (INT-008, INT-010).

Frustrations: Team uses 6 different tools (INT-001, INT-003, INT-008);
clients don't understand project status (INT-004, INT-006).

Quote (INT-003): "I need my team aligned without micromanaging."

Buying trigger: Current tool failure causes a client escalation or budget overrun.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="Antipatterns and failure modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Persona with stock photo, alliterative name, and invented demographics not drawn from interviews.</description>
        <reason>Polished presentation signals quality but predicts nothing; invented detail justifies wrong decisions with false confidence.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Creating 5 or more personas before reaching traction.</description>
        <reason>Multiple personas at pre-traction stage fragment focus; start with one primary and expand only after traction confirms segment boundaries.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Persona updated annually or never.</description>
        <reason>Personas frozen at founding data echo year-one assumptions in year-three decisions; require quarterly minor refresh and post-pivot major rebuild.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No negative persona defined.</description>
        <reason>Without defining who not to target, teams waste acquisition budget on high-churn, high-support-cost, price-sensitive users that fit no sustainable segment.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <p>LLM-generated personas trend toward stereotypes ("Marketing Mary, 35, lives in Brooklyn, drinks oat milk") that look polished but predict nothing. Persona-quote synthesis can drift into invented language; require quotes pulled verbatim from transcripts with source IDs. Demographic tropes overshadow goals/frustrations when models are not constrained.</p>
      <p>Mixing market-research sources (industry reports) with first-party interviews dilutes the persona; keep sources tagged separately. Agents may "rebuild" personas every refresh and lose institutional history; require a versioned diff, not a rewrite. For B2B, agents conflate buyer with user; force the agent to declare the role explicitly per persona.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic workflow and integration">
      <p>Use agents to extract patterns from interview transcripts, support tickets, and sales-call notes; cluster utterances by goals, frustrations, behaviours; produce candidate personas the team validates. Keep validation human (recognition tests with real customers); agents draft and refresh, humans ratify and prioritise. Pair persona output with the explicit data sources behind every claim — no claim without a citation back to interview ID, ticket ID, or analytics segment.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: A persona-builder subagent drives interview-pattern extraction and template fill. Use faion-brainstorm to diverge on candidate persona names and headlines, converge on memorable yet specific options. A pattern-clusterer subagent takes JSON-tagged interview snippets and clusters by goals/frustrations/behaviours, emitting affinity tables. A validator subagent compares persona predictions ("they would buy if X") against actual cohort behaviour from analytics.</p>
      <example type="good" title="Persona extraction prompt pattern">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Given the attached 14 interview transcripts (INT-001..014), cluster utterances about Goals, Frustrations, Buying Behaviour, and Information Sources. Propose at most 2 primary personas and 1 negative persona. For every bullet in each persona, cite the supporting interview IDs. Never invent demographic detail not present in the transcripts.]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Persona validation prompt pattern">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Validate the proposed primary persona against analytics cohort cohort_id=42 (CSV attached). For each behavioural claim, mark Confirmed / Contradicted / No-data.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="Tools and services">
      <p>CLI tools for persona building: Whisper or WhisperX for transcribing interview audio. AssemblyAI or Deepgram for hosted transcription with diarisation. Dovetail, Marvin, or Notably API for pulling tagged interviews. Notion or Airtable API for persona repo CRUD. gpt-researcher (OSS) for literature scan of industry archetypes. Hugging Face bertopic for topic clustering on transcripts. Posthog or Amplitude APIs for behavioural validation against cohorts. Anthropic or OpenAI SDKs for pattern extraction calls. Streamlit for quick persona viewer for stakeholders.</p>
      <p>Services and applications: Dovetail provides tagged-evidence source for personas with REST and AI support. Marvin and EnjoyHQ offer repo with AI summarisation (REST). Notably is AI-native with persona templates built-in. Otter.ai and Fireflies.ai support sales-call transcription source (REST). Gong and Chorus provide sales-call goldmine for B2B personas (REST). Zendesk and Intercom enable support-ticket pattern source (REST). Posthog (SaaS or OSS) provides behavioural cohorts to validate (REST). Reddit and Discord (with consent) serve as lifestyle and language-pattern sources. UserPersona.dev, Personas.app, Xtensio, and HubSpot Make My Persona have light tools for solos but weak API surfaces.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Best practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Hold a "no demographics first" rule: write goals and frustrations before any demographic detail.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include a negative persona; teams shipping to "everyone" lose more than they gain.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Limit to one primary persona until $10K MRR (or equivalent traction signal); later add at most three.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Capture each persona's "buying trigger" verbatim — the phrase that made the actual buyer say yes.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pair the persona doc with one paragraph titled "How we'd notice this persona is wrong" — falsification clause.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Refresh cycle: minor every quarter (interview signals, support ticket categories), major on pivots or new markets.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Avoid stock photos; if the team insists on imagery, use illustrations or anonymised composite photos.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Distribute the persona where decisions are made (PM Notion, marketing brief template, sales playbook) — a personas-only doc gathers dust.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Constrain agent output with "no name unless drawn from interview frequency" or pre-approved list.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every quote must carry a source ID and the agent must refuse without one.</statement>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/persona-full.md" purpose="Full persona template with demographics, goals, frustrations, buying behaviour"/>
      <template path="templates/persona-lean.md" purpose="Lean 6-field persona for rapid iteration"/>
      <template path="templates/persona-negative.md" purpose="Negative persona template (who NOT to target)"/>
      <template path="templates/build-persona.py" purpose="Anthropic SDK script: transcript clustering and persona JSON generation with citation IDs"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/persona/"/>
      <link href="https://dovetail.com/templates/persona/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
