<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Terraform Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Terraform methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-provider-pinning" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>providers + terraform versions MUST be pinned (= operator) in versions.tf. Major-version bumps go via PR with diff + plan attached.</statement>
      <rationale source="HashiCorp Terraform docs — version pinning">Unpinned providers cause silent behaviour drift between runs; pinning makes plans reproducible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-remote-state-with-locking" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>State MUST live in a remote backend with locking (S3 + DynamoDB, TF Cloud, GCS + Cloud Storage lock). Local state forbidden for shared environments.</statement>
      <rationale source="Terraform docs — Backends">Local state corrupts on concurrent edits; locking prevents two engineers applying simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-plan-review-apply-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply MUST run only via CI after a reviewed PR with plan attached. No terraform apply from engineer laptops in shared envs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Terraform Cloud workflows">Laptop applies skip review, leave no audit trail, and routinely diverge from main.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-modules-over-copy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Repeated patterns (VPC, ECS service, RDS) MUST be modules with semver versioning, sourced from a private registry or git tag. Inline copy-paste of 200+ HCL lines is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="terraform-aws-modules pattern">Copy-paste forks drift; modules let one fix propagate to N consumers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-no-secrets-in-state" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sensitive values MUST come from external sources (Vault / Secrets Manager / SOPS) and be marked sensitive = true. Plaintext secrets in .tfvars or state are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Terraform state security">State files leak via S3 misconfig, backups, console access; secrets in state are public secrets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-drift-detection-scheduled" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A weekly CI job MUST run terraform plan against every environment and surface drift (non-zero diff with no PR open). Drift triggers a triage ticket.</statement>
      <rationale source="drift-classification-taxonomy">Drift accumulates silently — manual console fixes, vendor automation, expired resources. Weekly plan surfaces drift before disaster.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
