<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="terraform Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for terraform. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Split configuration into main.tf, variables.tf, outputs.tf, versions.tf, providers.tf, locals.tf, and data.tf.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each file has a single responsibility; reviewers and tools know where to look for each element type.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin required_version with a minimum bound (e.g., &gt;= 1.6.0) and pin provider versions with ~&gt; constraints. Commit .terraform.lock.hcl.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unpinned versions cause silent upgrades that break apply; lock file ensures deterministic runs across machines and CI.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every variable must have a description. Mark sensitive values with sensitive = true. Add validation blocks for constrained inputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sensitive flag redacts values from plan output and state display. Validation provides clear error messages earlier than resource creation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use locals to compute derived values and naming prefixes. Never repeat the same expression in multiple resources.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">DRY locals prevent inconsistent naming and make bulk renames a one-line change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mark outputs that contain secrets as sensitive = true. Provide descriptions for all outputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sensitive outputs are redacted in CI logs and terraform output commands.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prefer for_each over count for resources that may be updated mid-lifecycle to avoid index-based drift.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">count uses numeric indexes; removing item[1] of 3 forces destroy/recreate of item[2]. for_each uses stable keys.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use merge(local.common_tags, { Name = "..." }) to combine tag maps consistently across all resources.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Avoids duplicating the common_tags map in every resource block.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use remote backend with encryption enabled. For AWS: S3 bucket with SSE-KMS, versioning, public access blocked, and DynamoDB table for locking.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Local state cannot be shared across team members or CI/CD. S3 versioning enables state recovery. DynamoDB locking prevents concurrent apply corruption.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Isolate state per environment (envs/dev/, envs/prod/) and per component (network/, compute/). Never share a single state file across environments.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Shared state means a broken dev apply can corrupt prod state. Isolation contains blast radius.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use moved blocks in HCL for resource renames, not terraform state mv. Verify with plan showing no changes after the move.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">moved blocks are version-controlled and self-documenting. terraform state mv is a one-off command that leaves no trace in code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each module has single responsibility. Required files: main.tf, variables.tf, outputs.tf, versions.tf. Never configure providers inside modules.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Provider configuration in modules prevents caller from controlling the provider version/region, making modules inflexible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All module inputs must have descriptions. Add validation rules for constrained inputs. Provide sensible defaults for optional variables.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without descriptions, callers cannot understand what a variable does. Validation surfaces errors at plan time, not at the resource API level.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never store secrets in Terraform code, tfvars files, or state. Reference secrets via data sources (AWS Secrets Manager, Vault).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">State files are stored in S3 and may be logged in CI. Secrets in code are committed to version control. External secret managers provide rotation and audit trails.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use IAM roles, not users. Apply least-privilege: no wildcard actions except read-only describe calls. Add resource-level conditions where available.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Roles use temporary credentials. Wildcard actions grant more permissions than required; resource conditions restrict to tagged/named resources.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>In CI: run terraform fmt -check, terraform validate, and security scanning (tfsec/checkov) before plan. Save plan as artifact; apply only from protected branch using the saved plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">fmt -check catches formatting drift early. Saved plan ensures apply uses exactly the reviewed plan, preventing race conditions if code changes between plan and apply.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
