<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-state-and-modules" title="Terraform State and Modules">
  <summary>Remote backend configuration, state management commands, and module structure and design principles.</summary>

  <section title="Remote Backend">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use remote backend with encryption enabled. For AWS: S3 bucket with SSE-KMS, versioning, public access blocked, and DynamoDB table for locking.</statement>
      <rationale>Local state cannot be shared across team members or CI/CD. S3 versioning enables state recovery. DynamoDB locking prevents concurrent apply corruption.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/backend.tf">S3 backend with DynamoDB locking template</reference>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="hcl"><![CDATA[
terraform {
  backend "s3" {
    bucket         = "company-terraform-state"
    key            = "project/env/terraform.tfstate"
    region         = "us-east-1"
    encrypt        = true
    dynamodb_table = "terraform-locks"
  }
}
]]></code>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Isolate state per environment (envs/dev/, envs/prod/) and per component (network/, compute/). Never share a single state file across environments.</statement>
      <rationale>Shared state means a broken dev apply can corrupt prod state. Isolation contains blast radius.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="State Commands">
    <list>
      <item>terraform state list — list all resources</item>
      <item>terraform state show &lt;resource&gt; — show resource details</item>
      <item>terraform state mv &lt;old&gt; &lt;new&gt; — rename without destroy</item>
      <item>terraform state rm &lt;resource&gt; — remove from state without destroying</item>
      <item>terraform import &lt;resource&gt; &lt;id&gt; — import existing resource</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use moved blocks in HCL for resource renames, not terraform state mv. Verify with plan showing no changes after the move.</statement>
      <rationale>moved blocks are version-controlled and self-documenting. terraform state mv is a one-off command that leaves no trace in code.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Module Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each module has single responsibility. Required files: main.tf, variables.tf, outputs.tf, versions.tf. Never configure providers inside modules.</statement>
      <rationale>Provider configuration in modules prevents caller from controlling the provider version/region, making modules inflexible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>All module inputs must have descriptions. Add validation rules for constrained inputs. Provide sensible defaults for optional variables.</statement>
      <rationale>Without descriptions, callers cannot understand what a variable does. Validation surfaces errors at plan time, not at the resource API level.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="hcl"><![CDATA[
# Good module call with version constraint
module "vpc" {
  source  = "terraform-aws-modules/vpc/aws"
  version = "~> 5.0"

  name = "${local.name_prefix}-vpc"
  cidr = var.vpc_cidr

  enable_nat_gateway = true
  single_nat_gateway = var.environment != "prod"

  tags = local.common_tags
}
]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using workspaces to separate production from development.</description>
      <reason>Workspaces share backend config and are not suitable for prod isolation. Use separate directories with separate state files instead.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
