<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Bug Triage Rubric — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every solo triage pass must enforce. These are HARD rules — sympathy for a vocal reporter cannot override them.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each bug MUST be labelled with severity ∈ {P0, P1, P2} using the solo ladder: P0 = paying customer cannot use core flow; P1 = paying customer experiences degraded core flow OR ≥10% of total users blocked on a non-core flow; P2 = everything else.</statement>
      <rationale source="Revenue-honest prioritisation (Levels.fyi / Indie Hackers founder surveys)">A team-grade ladder over-elevates non-paying noise and starves the work that protects MRR; the solo ladder makes the trade-off explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reach MUST be captured as a concrete count ("3 paying customers, 47 free users") not a verbal estimate ("a few users"); unknown reach is treated as P2 until measured.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anchored estimation / RICE prioritisation discipline">Verbal estimates inflate by 3–5x under emotional pressure; the count is non-negotiable to keep triage honest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>P0 bugs MUST be fixed before any feature work resumes; P1 bugs MUST be scheduled within the current week; P2 bugs MUST be either scheduled within 90 days OR killed with a one-line `wontfix` rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="WIP-limit + backlog-hygiene practice">Backlogs that grow without expiry rot into unactionable noise and erode trust in the tracker as a planning tool.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every triage decision MUST record: severity, reach_count (paying + free split), assigned_week_iso OR `wontfix`, and a one-line rationale; bugs without all four fields are blocked from leaving triage.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-audit discipline">Solo founders re-debate the same bug repeatedly when the rationale is missing; the four-field record kills repeat-debate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Friday triage block MUST be capped at 60 minutes; if the queue is not cleared in 60 minutes, the unprocessed bugs default to P2 and stay in the backlog — the founder does not extend the block.</statement>
      <rationale source="Parkinson's-Law guard / focus-discipline ops">Triage that runs long crowds out building; the cap is what makes the practice sustainable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Anchored triage entry">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
bug_id: BUG-482
title: "Export-to-CSV fails for orgs with > 5k rows"
severity: P1
reach:
  paying: 4
  free: 11
assigned_week_iso: 2026-W21
rationale: "4 paying orgs blocked on a paid-only feature; in-week fix protects renewal."
]]></code>
      <note>Clear severity per the ladder, concrete reach with split, scheduled, rationale.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Un-anchored triage entry">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Export thing is broken for some people, P1 I guess, fix soon."
]]></code>
      <note>No reach, no split, no week, no rationale — guaranteed to be re-debated next Friday.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="../kill-or-keep-criteria/" />
  </see-also>
</text>
