<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Content Refresh SOP — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that every refresh decision and execution must enforce. These guard against the most common failure mode: cosmetic rewrites that re-trigger Google's "substantial update" signal without actually improving the page.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-decay-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Classify a URL as decaying ONLY when at least two of these three signals are true over the last 90 days: clicks dropped &gt;30% vs prior 90 days, avg position dropped &gt;3 ranks, OR engaged-session rate fell &gt;20%. One signal alone is noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="Animalz Content Decay study (2021), Ahrefs decay analysis">Single-signal triggers fire on seasonality (impressions wobble), SERP feature changes (position fluctuates), and tracker drift. Two signals correlated within the same window correctly flag actual decay 87% of the time in the Animalz dataset.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-intent-shift-kill" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before refresh, fetch the live top-3 SERP results for the target keyword. If &gt;=2 of the top-3 are a different content format (e.g., your post is long-form, top-3 are now tools / videos / interactive maps), recommend KILL not refresh.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SERP feature analyses, ahrefs/semrush format-shift studies">Intent shift kills refresh ROI. Once SERP rewards a tool, prose cannot win even if rewritten. Common in finance ("calculator" intent), DIY ("step-by-step video"), local ("map pack"). Kill = noindex + 301 to closest related asset OR rebuild as the new format.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-last-updated-honest" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Update the visible "Last updated" date AND the schema dateModified field ONLY when refresh changed at least one of: primary claim, primary data point, top-of-page intro paragraph, or H1. Cosmetic edits (typo, image swap, link freshen) do NOT justify a date bump.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google Search Quality Rater Guidelines section 4.6.1, Marie Haynes 2023 case studies">Dishonest date-bumping is a quality-rater flag and pattern-matched algorithmically post-Aug-2023 "Helpful Content Update". Sites caught bumping dates without substantive changes have lost 30-70% organic traffic in subsequent updates.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-evidence-before-prose" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Replace or add primary evidence (stat, study citation, named expert quote, screenshot, dated data) BEFORE rewriting any prose. If no new evidence is available, the refresh is downgraded to "leave" — do not ship.</statement>
      <rationale source="E-E-A-T 2023 update, Google SQRG section 3.1">Refresh ROI comes from new evidence, not prettier sentences. LLM-only prose polish triggers AI-content classifiers without raising quality. Evidence-first ensures each refresh is provably valuable to the reader.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-redirect-disambiguation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When KILLing a URL: 301 to the closest topical sibling IF a sibling exists with overlapping intent AND ranking authority. Otherwise return 410 Gone. NEVER noindex-leave-orphan — orphans accumulate crawl budget loss and quality-signal dilution.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google Webmaster guidelines, Search Off the Record podcast Aug-2022 episode on 410 vs 404">Orphan noindex pages are the #3 cause of crawl budget waste in enterprise SEO audits. 410 is a strong signal to deindex fast; 301 preserves equity when sibling intent matches. Choose deliberately — the wrong choice costs equity OR slows deindex.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Two-signal decay triggers refresh">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
URL: /guide/saas-pricing-strategy (published 2023-02, last touched 2023-08)
GSC 90d:    clicks 412 -> 198 (-52%)     [signal 1: drop > 30%]
Rank:       avg pos 4.2 -> 8.7 (+4.5)    [signal 2: drop > 3 ranks]
GA4 90d:    engaged% 64% -> 61%          [no signal]

Decision: REFRESH (2 signals present)
Action:   apply 9-step checklist; primary evidence to replace = 2023
          pricing benchmark stat (now stale); add 2025 SaaS pricing
          benchmark report citation.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1: two-signal threshold, not one-signal trigger.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Cosmetic refresh with dishonest date">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
URL: /guide/best-crm-2024
Action taken: ran prose through GPT to "freshen language", swapped
              hero image, updated schema dateModified to today.
Primary claim:  unchanged ("HubSpot is best for SMBs")
Evidence:       unchanged (2023 G2 ranking)
Result:         caught in next HCU update, -45% organic traffic.

Repair: revert dateModified to actual date of last substantive edit.
        Refresh-or-kill: requires new evidence OR kill. Pick one.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r3 + r4 violation: date dishonesty plus prose-only refresh.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
