<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ops-churn-prevention">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>growth-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Churn prevention is an operational playbook for reducing involuntary and voluntary cancellations through three phases: early intervention, save offers, and win-back campaigns matched to churn-reason segment.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>churn</tag>
      <tag>retention</tag>
      <tag>lifecycle-marketing</tag>
      <tag>saas</tag>
      <tag>customer-retention</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>retention</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Churn Prevention</title>

    <summary>Churn prevention is an operational playbook for reducing involuntary and voluntary cancellations through three phases: early intervention (re-engagement before the user decides to leave), save offers (at the cancellation flow), and win-back campaigns (after churn). Each phase uses tiered actions matched to churn-reason segment, not a generic discount. Agent role: score health, draft segmented copy, stage campaigns — humans approve send.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Unchecked churn compounds: a 7% monthly churn destroys ~57% of ARR per year. Intervention ROI is highest before the cancellation decision is made; save offers and win-backs are progressively more expensive. Reason-matched playbooks outperform generic discounts and avoid training customers to threaten cancellation for extraction.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Monthly churn is at or above 3% on a paid SaaS or subscription product.</item>
        <item>Churn analysis (ops-churn-basics) is done: root causes segmented by reason (price / value / feature gap / involuntary).</item>
        <item>Engagement events (login, feature use) and payment events are tracked and accessible.</item>
        <item>A lifecycle email tool (Customer.io, Intercom, Braze) is owned and writable.</item>
        <item>Cancellation flow is in your product (you can ship a save-offer page, dunning UI).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>B2C apps with no recurring revenue and no contact channel — there is nobody to save.</item>
        <item>Pre-product-market-fit: churn is a symptom of weak value, not weak retention ops.</item>
        <item>Enterprise contracts with manual renewal — handled by AE/CS humans, not this playbook.</item>
        <item>Free tier with zero LTV — saving free users wastes intervention budget.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="early-intervention-signals">
      <rule>
        <statement>Tier the response by churn reason: price objections get a discount, value objections get a CSM call, feature gaps get a roadmap link — never a flat 50% off for all segments.</statement>
        <rationale>Reason-matched interventions preserve margin and avoid training the entire cohort to use cancellation as a discount lever.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Implement signal-to-action triggers: no login 7 days → automated re-engagement email, no login 14 days → personal email from a named team member, feature usage below 20% of baseline → feature tip email, negative support ticket → manager follow-up within 24h, cancel attempt → save offer page, payment failure → dunning sequence tied to specific decline code.</statement>
        <rationale>Actionable signals caught early are cheaper to address than responding after the cancellation request is already made.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="save-offer-design">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap save-offer eligibility at once per 12 months per user and track repeat-savers; users who accept a save offer and cancel again within 90 days are negative-LTV.</statement>
        <rationale>Unlimited save offers convert initially then crater NRR as repeat-savers extract discounts without genuine re-engagement.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Hard-code offer ladder in the prompt template; the agent must select from the ladder and reject any request outside it.</statement>
        <rationale>Without hard constraints LLMs generate offers that sound reasonable but violate margin floors (e.g. "60% off lifetime" appears in generated output without guardrails).</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>price objection → 50% off for 2 months</item>
        <item>time objection → account pause for 30 days</item>
        <item>feature gap → free upgrade to next tier for 1 month</item>
        <item>competitor move → acknowledge and offer a success-call to address the specific gap</item>
      </list>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents inventing save offers exceeding 50% discount or extending trials beyond 30 days without hard constraints.</description>
        <reason>LLMs will generate generous offers unless constrained; unconstrained offers destroy unit economics and the agent cannot see margin data.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="dunning-sequences">
      <rule>
        <statement>Tie dunning email copy to the specific Stripe decline code (insufficient_funds vs lost_card vs do_not_honor); generic "update card" loses recoverable involuntary churn.</statement>
        <rationale>Different decline codes have different recovery rates and appropriate CTAs; a "lost card" decline needs a new card link, not a "try again" button.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="win-back-campaigns">
      <rule>
        <statement>Send win-back campaigns at 30 days and 90 days after churn; skip the 7-day send — at 7 days the user rarely churned for a product reason and the timing feels aggressive.</statement>
        <rationale>30-day win-backs let the product add improvements to highlight; 90-day win-backs address users who may have tried a competitor and found gaps. 7-day win-backs have lower accept rates and higher unsubscribe rates.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Never quote customer text or claim the agent "knows" what the user said — feed only structured signals (exit survey category, ticket sentiment score, last feature used) and prohibit quoting free-text the agent has not seen.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs hallucinate "user mentioned X" from structured data; this destroys trust when the customer reads the email.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Run a 10% no-treatment holdout on every win-back campaign; without it you cannot distinguish offer-caused reactivation from natural reversion.</statement>
        <rationale>Some churned users reactivate on their own within 90 days; attributing their return to the campaign inflates win-back ROI and causes over-investment in a tactic that may not be driving the return.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Check suppression-list status before drafting any win-back send; never send to GDPR-deleted users, and read suppression status before drafting, not after.</statement>
        <rationale>Win-backs to suppression-listed users leak PII, violate GDPR right-to-be-forgotten, and trigger ICO/DPC complaints.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Day 30: "What has changed" — highlight fixes and features added since they left</item>
        <item>Day 90: "Major update" — if significant product change occurred, use a deeper offer</item>
        <item>Day 180+: typically not worth the send unless a major repositioning has occurred</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-workflow-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep the churn-prevention agent in draft-only mode — it stages campaigns to the lifecycle tool's draft status; humans approve creative and offer economics before any send.</statement>
        <rationale>Email send is a one-way action; a batch mistake to the wrong segment cannot be undone. The agent lacks access to brand guidelines, legal review, and margin data needed to finalize offers autonomously.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Classify churn reason from structured signals only (exit survey category, ticket sentiment score, feature-usage drop); do not classify from free-text without human spot-checks.</statement>
        <rationale>Free-text reason classification by LLMs has systematic errors — "too expensive" is frequently mislabeled as "missing feature" — causing intervention budget to be spent on the wrong playbook.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Retrain the health-score model monthly and after any major product change; a model trained on Q1 data misclassifies Q3 cohorts after feature launches.</statement>
        <rationale>Health-score drift produces false-low or false-high risk classifications, wasting intervention budget on healthy users and missing genuinely at-risk ones.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Maximum discount: 50% off, maximum 2 months. Maximum trial extension: 30 days. No overlapping campaigns for the same user. Eligibility: once per 12 months per user.</statement>
        <rationale>These hard constraints prevent LLM generation of economically destructive offers and ensure the intervention budget is focused and repeatable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>agent output: csv with [user_id, playbook_id, subject, body, suggested_offer]</item>
        <item>human review: verify offer is within approved ladder, no suppression violations, correct segment</item>
        <item>send: triggered by human action in the lifecycle tool, not by agent</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="health-score-baseline">
      <reference path="templates/health-score.sql">Weekly health-score snapshot SQL: login frequency, feature breadth, support sentiment, tenure components (each capped at 25 points)</reference>

      <p>Health score SQL baseline uses four components: login frequency in the last 7 days (up to 25 points), feature breadth in the last 30 days (up to 25 points), support ticket sentiment in the last 60 days (25 points scaled to sentiment), and tenure since signup (up to 25 points scaled by days/30). Total score ranges from 0–100.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/churn-prevention-playbook.md" purpose="Early-warning triggers, save offers, win-back campaigns table"/>
      <template path="templates/health-score.sql" purpose="Weekly health-score snapshot SQL (login, feature, support, tenure)"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://sixteenventures.com/customer-success-strategy"/>
      <link href="https://churnkey.co/playbooks"/>
      <link href="https://stripe.com/docs/billing/revenue-recovery"/>
      <link href="https://brianbalfour.com/essays/retention-engagement-growth"/>
      <link href="https://www.forentrepreneurs.com/saas-metrics-2/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
