<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-implementation" title="Backup Implementation Patterns">
  <summary>Concrete implementation patterns for PostgreSQL PITR, Restic, Velero, and automated verification.</summary>

  <section title="PostgreSQL Point-in-Time Recovery">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure WAL archiving in addition to base backups to enable point-in-time recovery; base backups alone only restore to backup completion time.</statement>
      <rationale>A database corrupted at 14:30 with a base backup from 02:00 and 12 hours of WAL archives can be restored to 14:29 — 1 minute of data loss. Without WAL, the loss is 12.5 hours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# postgresql.conf settings for WAL archiving
archive_mode = on
archive_command = 'aws s3 cp %p s3://backup-bucket/wal/%f'
archive_timeout = 300   # archive WAL at most every 5 minutes

# Base backup (streaming WAL during backup)
pg_basebackup \
  -h localhost -U replication \
  -D /backup/base_$(date +%Y%m%d_%H%M%S) \
  -Ft -z -P -X stream --checkpoint=fast
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Restic File Backup">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always run restic check after backup to verify repository integrity; silent corruption is the failure mode Restic is designed to detect.</statement>
      <rationale>Restic uses content-addressed storage with SHA-256 hashes. check verifies all data blobs are present and uncorrupted. Omitting it defeats the integrity guarantee.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
export RESTIC_REPOSITORY="s3:s3.amazonaws.com/backup-bucket/restic"
export RESTIC_PASSWORD_FILE="/etc/restic/password"

restic backup /var/www /etc /home \
  --exclude="*.log" --exclude="node_modules" \
  --tag production --tag "$(hostname)"

restic forget \
  --keep-daily 7 --keep-weekly 4 --keep-monthly 12 \
  --prune

restic check   # mandatory — verify integrity
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Velero Kubernetes Backup">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use defaultVolumesToFsBackup: true in Velero schedules for PVCs without snapshot support; use volume snapshots for supported storage classes.</statement>
      <rationale>File system backup (Restic/Kopia) works on any PVC but is slower. Volume snapshots are faster but require CSI driver support. Omitting both means PVC data is not backed up.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: velero.io/v1
kind: Schedule
metadata:
  name: daily-backup
  namespace: velero
spec:
  schedule: "0 2 * * *"
  template:
    includedNamespaces: [production, staging]
    excludedResources: [events, events.events.k8s.io]
    ttl: 720h             # 30-day retention
    snapshotVolumes: true
    defaultVolumesToFsBackup: true
]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/velero-schedule.yaml">Full Velero schedule with storage location</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Automated Backup Verification">
    <rule>
      <statement>Automate restore verification after every backup job — restore to an isolated environment, check table counts and recent data, push a success metric to Prometheus.</statement>
      <rationale>The 0 in 3-2-1-1-0 is not aspirational — it requires a concrete verification step. Manual restore tests happen rarely or never. Automation makes verification continuous.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Alert when backup age exceeds 1.5x the scheduled interval — a 36-hour-old backup from a daily job indicates missed runs.</statement>
      <rationale>Backup jobs fail silently (exit 0 on partial failure, disk full, network timeout). Age-based alerting catches these without requiring job-level monitoring hooks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/verify-backup.sh">Automated PostgreSQL restore verification script with alerting</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prometheus-alerts.yaml">Prometheus rules for backup age, failure, and size anomaly</reference>
  </section>
</text>
