<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Experimentation at Scale Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Experimentation at Scale plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="pre-registration-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every experiment MUST pre-register hypothesis, primary metric, MDE, sample-size target, and guardrail metrics before traffic is allocated; post-hoc metric selection is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kohavi, Tang, Xu — Trustworthy Online Controlled Experiments (2020)">Post-hoc metric picking is p-hacking; pre-registration is the only structural gate against it at scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="srm-check-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every experiment MUST run a Sample Ratio Mismatch (SRM) chi-square check before reading results; SRM-failing experiments MUST be discarded, not patched.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kohavi et al. — SRM at Microsoft (2018)">SRM failure means traffic allocation is broken; any 'lift' read off an SRM-failing experiment is an artefact, not an effect.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="guardrails-block-shipping" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Guardrail metrics (latency, error-rate, revenue per session) MUST be defined per surface and MUST block shipping when degraded by more than the pre-registered threshold.</statement>
      <rationale source="Booking.com experimentation playbook">Without guardrails, primary-metric wins ship while collateral damage (slower pages, broken flows) goes undetected.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="learning-extraction-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every concluded experiment MUST produce a one-page learning artefact (hypothesis, result, decision, follow-ups); experiments without a learning page MUST be re-opened.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft ExP team — Experimentation Lessons (2023)">Without an extraction step, organisations run thousands of experiments and accumulate zero institutional memory; the playbook becomes the read-only result dashboard.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="min-sample-size-enforced" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Experiments MUST run to the pre-registered sample size; early-stopping for 'looks significant' is forbidden unless a sequential test (mSPRT, group-sequential) was pre-registered.</statement>
      <rationale source="Johari et al. — Peeking at A/B Tests (2017)">Peeking inflates false-positive rate above the nominal alpha; the only safe early stop is a pre-registered sequential design.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
