<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-shape" title="The two-H2 shape">
  <summary>plan.md has exactly two top-level sections: `## Design` and `## Execution Plan`. Both are mandatory when the feature warrants plan.md at all.</summary>

  <section title="## Design">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The `## Design` section MUST cover: package layout for this feature, API contracts that are FEATURE-scoped (not in project-spec), data schemas, sequencing constraints.</statement>
      <rationale>System-wide contracts live in project-spec/. Feature-scoped contracts that exist only for this slice live here so they do not pollute the spec until they survive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Package / module layout — which dirs the feature creates or modifies.</item>
      <item>API contracts new to this feature — request/response shape, status codes, errors.</item>
      <item>Schemas — DB tables, JSON shapes, message-queue payloads.</item>
      <item>Sequencing — any ordering constraint (must run after migration X, must precede deploy of Y).</item>
      <item>Trade-offs considered — one paragraph per non-obvious decision.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="## Execution Plan">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The `## Execution Plan` section MUST contain: wave map, task table with IDs, dependency graph, risk register.</statement>
      <rationale>The plan is what gets executed; without IDs and dependencies the executor cannot parallelise or resume.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Wave map — which tasks can run in parallel, which must serialize.</item>
      <item>Task table — `T0N` id, one-line description, dependencies, token estimate.</item>
      <item>Risks — known unknowns with mitigation.</item>
      <item>Rollback — how to undo this feature if it must be reverted.</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Execution Plan

### Waves
- Wave A (serial): T01 → T02 (T02 needs T01 migration).
- Wave B (parallel): T03, T04, T05 (independent surfaces).
- Wave C (serial): T06 (integration test against T03-T05).

### Tasks
| ID  | Description                     | Deps    | Est. tokens |
|-----|---------------------------------|---------|-------------|
| T01 | Migration: add `verified_at`    | —       | ~3k         |
| T02 | Serializer: expose `verified`   | T01     | ~2k         |
| T03 | Email service: send verify mail | —       | ~5k         |
...
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Splitting plan.md back into separate `design.md` and `implementation-plan.md` files because "they grew long".</description>
    <reason>Length is not the failure mode — drift between the two is. If long, split internally by sub-section, never by file.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-when-to-skip.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-rationale.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
