<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Journey Mapping Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every journey-mapping application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-eight-components" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The map MUST include all eight components: persona, stages, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points, opportunities. Omitting any one is a schema violation.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — Journey Mapping 101">Omitting emotions produces an action log, not a journey map. Omitting opportunities produces a complaint document, not a design input. All eight together force the artefact to drive action.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-evidence-citation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every map cell MUST cite a research artefact id (interview ID, support ticket ID, analytics event id) OR carry the literal value "no data". Ungrounded prose is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — Emotional Journey Map">Ungrounded cells are team assumptions masquerading as research findings. Forcing citations turns gaps into research priorities rather than invention prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-scope-one-persona" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One persona and one journey per map; explicit start and end points named in the scope field. Combining personas is a schema violation.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — Journey Mapping 101">Combining personas hides differences and produces a map that represents neither accurately. Undefined endpoints produce maps with no clear resolution.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-user-perspective-stages" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stages MUST be named from the user's perspective (Discovering, Evaluating, Deciding), not the company's pipeline (Lead, Opportunity, Closed). 4-8 stages per map.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — Journey Mapping 101">Company pipeline names refocus the map on operations instead of experience. The 4-8 stage range keeps the map readable while preserving granularity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-emotional-arc-variance" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Emotional values MUST come from research evidence (quotes, sentiment, observed behaviour). Sharp dips MUST be preserved — smoothed arcs are a violation. Agents are explicitly prompted for variance, not average sentiment.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — Emotional Journey Map; LLM behaviour empirical">LLMs and humans both smooth emotional arcs. Real journeys have sharp dips at friction points — that is where redesign effort is justified. Smoothing hides the actionable signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-future-state-label" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Future-state maps MUST carry an explicit type marker "Future State — Design Hypothesis (not validated with users)". Mixing future-state speculation into a current-state map is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — Journey Mapping 101">Future-state maps generated from team imagination create false consensus that a designed experience matches user needs. The label keeps the distinction visible on the artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
