<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="code-review-cycle Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for code-review-cycle. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use AI pre-screening (Level 1) on every PR before human review; use AI co-review (Level 2) for complex changes; use AI validation (Level 3) after human approval for safety-critical code.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Level 1 cleans up noise before human review, reducing review fatigue. Level 2 augments humans with explanations and pattern references. Level 3 provides final safety net. All three require human oversight — AI review without human review increases change failure rates 30%.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use a different model for review than the model that generated the code.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The model that wrote the code has systematic blind spots for its own output. A separate review model catches different failure modes and provides genuine checks-and-balances.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat AI review findings as suggestions for humans to consider, not hard gates.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI reviewers miss: business logic (no domain understanding), security implications (flags patterns, misses context), architecture decisions (no system-wide view), edge cases (misses what it has not seen), performance at scale (does not know load patterns).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The review cycle is not complete until patterns.md is updated with learnings from the review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Post-merge reflexion is the most frequently skipped step. If skipped, the same issues recur in subsequent tasks because they never enter the project's pattern memory.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every SDD task must pass two explicit quality checkpoints before marking done: self-review and PR review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Checkpoints make quality gates explicit and verifiable, preventing the "it works on my machine" failure mode common in AI-assisted development.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After every PR merge, run a reflexion step: record what review patterns caught issues and what AI missed that humans found.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Reflexion (Shinn et al., 2023) demonstrates that verbal reinforcement from retained review examples measurably improves agent reliability on subsequent similar code. Skipping reflexion means each task starts with zero learning from prior reviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
