<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-workflow" title="Review Workflow and SDD Integration">
  <summary>Step-by-step review pipeline, SDD task completion checkpoints, reflexion learning loop integration, and best practices for authors, reviewers, and teams.</summary>

  <section title="Review Pipeline">
    <p>The full review pipeline after task execution:</p>
    <list>
      <item>1. Task completion → self-review (author + AI assist)</item>
      <item>2. PR creation with AI pre-review (Level 1 pass)</item>
      <item>3. Automated CI/CD checks (lint, tests, security scan)</item>
      <item>4. AI co-review pass (CodeRabbit, Copilot, etc.)</item>
      <item>5. Human review (peer/senior) with AI explanations available</item>
      <item>6. Iterations addressing BLOCK findings</item>
      <item>7. Approval + merge</item>
      <item>8. Reflexion learning (update patterns.md and mistakes.md)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>The review cycle is not complete until patterns.md is updated with learnings from the review.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-merge reflexion is the most frequently skipped step. If skipped, the same issues recur in subsequent tasks because they never enter the project's pattern memory.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="SDD Task Completion Checkpoints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every SDD task must pass two explicit quality checkpoints before marking done: self-review and PR review.</statement>
      <rationale>Checkpoints make quality gates explicit and verifiable, preventing the "it works on my machine" failure mode common in AI-assisted development.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
task_completion:
  self_review:
    - "All acceptance criteria met"
    - "AI review passed (no critical issues)"
    - "Tests added and passing"
  pr_review:
    - "Design doc alignment verified"
    - "Traceability links correct"
    - "No SDD deviations (or documented)"
      ]]></code>
      <note>These checkpoints are embedded in the task file, not left as implicit expectations.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Reflexion Learning Loop">
    <rule>
      <statement>After every PR merge, run a reflexion step: record what review patterns caught issues and what AI missed that humans found.</statement>
      <rationale>Reflexion (Shinn et al., 2023) demonstrates that verbal reinforcement from retained review examples measurably improves agent reliability on subsequent similar code. Skipping reflexion means each task starts with zero learning from prior reviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
reflexion:
  patterns_learned:
    - "What review patterns caught issues?"
    - "What did AI miss that humans caught?"
  improvements:
    - "Update AI rules for missed issues?"
    - "Add to self-review checklist?"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <list>
      <item>Authors: self-review with AI first before pushing; keep PRs small; mark AI-generated code for extra scrutiny</item>
      <item>Reviewers: review AI suggestions before deep dive; focus on what AI misses (business logic, architecture); do not rubber-stamp AI approvals</item>
      <item>Teams: configure AI to team-specific standards (custom ruff/eslint); track false positive rate quarterly; tune if rate exceeds 20%</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/prompt-review.txt">Prompts for AI pre-screen and independent review</reference>
</text>
