<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-adr-format" title="ADR Nygard Format and Lifecycle">
  <summary>The Nygard ADR format (Context/Decision/Alternatives/Consequences), status lifecycle, authoring best practices, and antipatterns to reject.</summary>

  <section title="Nygard Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every ADR must contain five sections: Context (situation and forces), Decision (active voice "We will..."), Alternatives Considered (at least 2 with pros, cons, and rejection reason), Consequences (positive, negative, neutral), Related Decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing the Alternatives section is the most common quality failure. Without alternatives, the ADR does not explain why other options were rejected — new team members will re-open the decision without knowing what was already considered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/adr-template.md">Nygard ADR skeleton with all required sections and field descriptions.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Status Lifecycle">
    <rule>
      <statement>All new ADRs are written with status "Proposed". A human must change it to "Accepted" before the ADR is considered active. Agents must not self-approve ADRs.</statement>
      <rationale>"Proposed" is a human-in-loop gate. Self-approving skips the review step where affected teams can object or add constraints. An ADR that bypasses review may conflict with decisions in other parts of the system.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When superseding an existing ADR, create a new ADR and update the old one's status to "Superseded by ADR-NNN". Never edit an Accepted ADR's content — immutability is the convention.</statement>
      <rationale>Editing Accepted ADRs destroys the historical record. The original decision context is valuable even after the decision is superseded — it explains why the earlier choice made sense at the time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Proposed: under discussion, gathering feedback.</item>
      <item>Accepted: approved, active decision.</item>
      <item>Deprecated: no longer relevant, kept for history.</item>
      <item>Superseded: replaced by a newer ADR (link required).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Authoring Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write in active voice: "We will use PostgreSQL" not "PostgreSQL was chosen". Keep each ADR under 400 words. If it is longer, the decision scope is too broad — split it.</statement>
      <rationale>Passive voice obscures agency and makes the decision seem inevitable rather than chosen. Length over 400 words typically means the ADR contains implementation details that belong in design.md.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store ADRs in docs/adr/NNN-title.md in the same repository as the code. Number sequentially from 001. Never reuse a number even if an ADR is deleted.</statement>
      <rationale>Co-location with code gives agents file-system access to ADRs during code generation and review. Sequential numbering creates a stable citation scheme (AD-X references in design.md and tasks).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>ADR used as a design guide: detailed implementation instructions in the Decision section.</description>
      <reason>ADRs document the choice, not the implementation. Implementation details belong in design.md. An ADR with implementation details will become stale as the implementation evolves.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Missing Alternatives section or alternatives stated as "Option A and Option B were considered."</description>
      <reason>Without pros, cons, and rejection reasons per alternative, the ADR does not prevent re-opening the debate. Alternatives must include why each was rejected.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>ADRs stored only in a wiki (Confluence, Notion) separate from the codebase.</description>
      <reason>Agents cannot access wiki content via file system during code generation. Orphaned ADRs drift out of sync with the actual implementation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
