<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="architecture-decision-records Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for architecture-decision-records. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every ADR must contain five sections: Context (situation and forces), Decision (active voice "We will..."), Alternatives Considered (at least 2 with pros, cons, and rejection reason), Consequences (positive, negative, neutral), Related Decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Missing the Alternatives section is the most common quality failure. Without alternatives, the ADR does not explain why other options were rejected — new team members will re-open the decision without knowing what was already considered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All new ADRs are written with status "Proposed". A human must change it to "Accepted" before the ADR is considered active. Agents must not self-approve ADRs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">"Proposed" is a human-in-loop gate. Self-approving skips the review step where affected teams can object or add constraints. An ADR that bypasses review may conflict with decisions in other parts of the system.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When superseding an existing ADR, create a new ADR and update the old one's status to "Superseded by ADR-NNN". Never edit an Accepted ADR's content — immutability is the convention.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Editing Accepted ADRs destroys the historical record. The original decision context is valuable even after the decision is superseded — it explains why the earlier choice made sense at the time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write in active voice: "We will use PostgreSQL" not "PostgreSQL was chosen". Keep each ADR under 400 words. If it is longer, the decision scope is too broad — split it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Passive voice obscures agency and makes the decision seem inevitable rather than chosen. Length over 400 words typically means the ADR contains implementation details that belong in design.md.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store ADRs in docs/adr/NNN-title.md in the same repository as the code. Number sequentially from 001. Never reuse a number even if an ADR is deleted.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Co-location with code gives agents file-system access to ADRs during code generation and review. Sequential numbering creates a stable citation scheme (AD-X references in design.md and tasks).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before writing an ADR, the agent must read docs/adr/ to find the next sequential number, then read the relevant feature spec.md and design.md to source Context, Decision, and Consequences. Do not invent consequences not grounded in these documents.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Invented consequences are the second most common quality failure after missing alternatives. Consequences must be traceable to real design tradeoffs, not generic technology wisdom.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After writing, set status to "Proposed" and stop. The agent must not proceed to Accepted without human review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Human sign-off is the primary quality gate for ADRs. Agents that self-approve skip the review where affected teams identify conflicts with other architectural constraints.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run ADR compliance review at major version bumps and after significant refactors. Mark obsolete decisions as "Deprecated" — do not leave orphaned Accepted ADRs that no longer reflect the codebase.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Orphaned Accepted ADRs mislead agents and new team members. An ADR that says "We will use PostgreSQL" when the project now uses MongoDB is worse than no ADR.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
