<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="architecture-decision-records Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for architecture-decision-records as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>ADR used as a design guide: detailed implementation instructions in the Decision section.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>ADRs document the choice, not the implementation. Implementation details belong in design.md. An ADR with implementation details will become stale as the implementation evolves.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Missing Alternatives section or alternatives stated as "Option A and Option B were considered."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without pros, cons, and rejection reasons per alternative, the ADR does not prevent re-opening the debate. Alternatives must include why each was rejected.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>ADRs stored only in a wiki (Confluence, Notion) separate from the codebase.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents cannot access wiki content via file system during code generation. Orphaned ADRs drift out of sync with the actual implementation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents fabricating alternatives in the Alternatives Considered section without grounding in real context.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hallucinated alternatives undermine the credibility of the entire ADR. Always supply spec.md and design.md as input when asking an agent to write alternatives.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Consequences section copied from the Decision section with different wording.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Consequences must describe downstream effects, not restate the decision. Require distinct, actionable consequence bullets in the prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Passing all 50+ ADR files to an agent instead of just the index list.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Full ADR history consumes 20-40k tokens. Pass only the index (NNN | Title | Status) and load individual ADRs on demand when their content is needed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
