<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Continuous Discovery Habits Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Weekly customer-discovery cadence where the Product Trio (PM, Design, Tech) maintains an Opportunity Solution Tree with verbatim-quote provenance and agent-assisted triage / coding / synthesis.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="opportunity-from-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every roadmap item MUST link to one OST opportunity, and that opportunity MUST cite ≥1 verbatim quote with participant_id + interview_date. Solution-shaped opportunities ('build X') are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Teresa Torres — Continuous Discovery Habits (2021)">Solution-shaped opportunities collapse the need/answer distinction; quote provenance keeps the tree grounded in past behaviour.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="weekly-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>PM MUST conduct ≥1 customer interview per calendar week; sampling diversity (segment, recency, plan-tier, churn-status) is enforced before each round.</statement>
      <rationale source="Continuous Discovery Habits — keystone habit">Weekly cadence is the keystone habit; diversity prevents power-user bias and surfaces undersampled segments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="one-outcome-per-tree" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One outcome per OST per quarter. Two outcomes in scope → build two trees and surface the cross-tree dependency explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Teresa Torres essays">Merged outcomes create metric ambiguity and untestable assumptions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="verbatim-provenance" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every opportunity links to ≥1 quote_id with participant + date. Synthesis agents consume full transcripts and verbatim quotes, never paraphrases.</statement>
      <rationale source="OST methodology — quote-level evidence">Paraphrased evidence is lossy and drifts the OST toward solution-shaped opportunities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="prune-or-park" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Opportunities with no new evidence in 60 days get parked; archive at 180 days. Tree health beats tree completeness.</statement>
      <rationale source="Product Talk pruning rituals">Unmaintained opportunities decay into dumping-ground noise and make the tree unusable past 200 nodes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="trio-prep-24h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock the Trio to one meeting per week and ship a trio-prep doc 24h before. Without prep, the meeting collapses to a status update.</statement>
      <rationale source="Marty Cagan — Inspired (Product Trio cadence)">Prep shifts the meeting from 'what to talk about' to 'which three opportunities are ready for the next solution test'.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — discovery already covered by customer-development or jobs-to-be-done; B2B &lt; 20 logos with 12-month sales cycle; mature growth-stage where experimentation-at-scale is primary), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
