<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="continuous-discovery-habits Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for continuous-discovery-habits. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every roadmap item MUST link to one OST opportunity. That opportunity MUST have verbatim quotes with participant ID + interview date from at least one past-behavior interview. Opportunities phrased as "build X" or "add X" are rejected; they belong as candidate solutions under a real opportunity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Solution-shaped opportunities collapse the distinction between need and proposed answer. Without this separation, the team builds features without validating the underlying problem exists or is worth solving.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The PM MUST conduct at least one customer interview per week, minimum. Interview subjects MUST be sampled across segment, recency, and plan-tier to avoid over-sampling the same power-users. Sampling diversity checks MUST happen pre-interview; agents must enforce diversity (segment, recency, churn-status, plan-tier) before each round.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Weekly interviews as a keystone habit create organizational memory and prevent feature-list drift. Diverse sampling prevents over-indexing on vocal minorities and surfaces unmet needs in undersampled segments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One outcome per OST per quarter. If two outcomes are in scope, build two trees and contend with the cross-tree dependency explicitly — do not merge.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Merged outcomes create metric ambiguity and make assumption testing untestable. Separate trees let teams focus on falsifiable, time-bounded outcomes without strategic hedging.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quote-level provenance is non-negotiable: every opportunity links to &gt;=1 quote_id with participant + date. The interview transcript is source of truth; never let synthesis agents reason from summaries (lossy). Feed full transcripts with quote-level IDs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Paraphrased evidence is lossy and drifts the OST toward solution-shaped "opportunities." Verbatim quotes with participant IDs let the trio re-listen, re-interpret, and link to other evidence months later.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Park ruthlessly — opportunities with no new evidence in 60 days get parked; archive at 180 days. Tree health beats tree completeness.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unmaintained opportunities become technical debt. Parking forces the trio to regularly ask "is this still a real customer need?" and prevents the OST from becoming a dumping ground.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock the trio to ONE meeting per week and ship the trio-prep doc 24h before. Without prep, the meeting becomes a status update.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A prepared trio meeting is focused, decision-driven, and respects time. Prep shifts the meeting from "what should we talk about?" to "here are three opportunities ready for the next solution test."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pair every opportunity with one assumption test type per dimension (desirability, viability, feasibility, usability, ethical). Cheap to enumerate, expensive to skip and learn later.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Assumption tests make the solution-to-opportunity link testable before investing engineering. Pre-registered tests prevent the team from shipping unvalidated solutions and convert roadmaps from "opinions in priority order" to "falsifiable hypotheses."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a calibration interview round monthly: PM listens-only to a CS or sales call, codes it, and compares to interview-coder output. If divergence &gt; 25%, retune the coder prompt.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Interview-coder agents will paraphrase quotes and conflate preferences with past-behavior evidence. Monthly calibration catches drift early and keeps the agent prompt aligned to the team's coding standards.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Anonymize PII at coding time, not at synthesis time. Once it's in the corpus, it's leaked. Discovery-delivery percentage is a contract with engineering, not a PM aspiration. If 15% gets eaten weekly, escalate or shrink scope; do not silently absorb it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">PII scrubbing requires a local gating step before agent coding to prevent accidental exposure to remote LLMs. Discovery-delivery commitment is meaningless without enforcement; silently absorbing discovery work trains teams to skip the practice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Feedback-triage (haiku): Daily at 8am. Input: Support tickets, NPS verbatims, sales-call notes. Output: Top-N opportunity-candidates (JSON) ranked by frequency × outcome-relevance. Route high-signal items to PM's review queue; low-signal items to a separate "consider later" archive.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cheap models for collection and triage. Haiku can categorize at high volume with minimal latency, surfacing patterns that humans would miss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interview-prep (sonnet): Pre-interview. Input: Current OST, opportunity gap, last 4 transcripts. Output: Research questions, screener, anti-leading-question rewrites. Force questions about specific recent instances ("tell me about the last time you..."), never future predictions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sonnet for structured authoring. Interview prep keeps the PM grounded in past-behavior anchoring and prevents the interview from drifting into aspirational "would you use" territory.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interview-coder (sonnet): Post-interview. Input: Transcript (text or audio→text). Output: Coded quotes, snapshot of "story", behavioral evidence flags. Force verbatim copy of the source span and a separate paraphrase field; downstream agents must consume verbatim only. Label every quote as past_behavior | preference | speculation; synthesizer must filter to past_behavior only for opportunity creation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Interview-coder will paraphrase quotes, breaking provenance. Forcing verbatim + paraphrase lets downstream agents stay grounded in evidence. Behavior labels prevent the OST from drifting into preference-only opportunities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>OST-synthesizer (opus): Weekly. Input: All coded quotes since last run, current OST. Output: Proposed tree-diff (add/move/dedup nodes), evidence linkage. Force a JSON-patch (RFC 6902) or YAML-diff format; reject full-tree outputs. Require N&gt;=5 quotes from &gt;=3 participants before emitting a theme; never manufacture cross-cutting themes from N=2 unrelated quotes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opus for synthesis where cross-corpus reasoning happens. Forcing diffs prevents drift and keeps PMs in control. Requiring N&gt;=5 prevents hallucination of patterns from thin evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assumption-tester (sonnet): On opportunity-promotion. Input: Solution + key assumptions. Output: List of assumption-test designs (Type-1: desirability/viability/feasibility/usability/ethical).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Structured enumeration of assumptions prevents teams from shipping unvalidated solutions. Sonnet is strong at structured task decomposition.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trio-prep (sonnet): Pre-trio meeting. Input: OST, recent quotes, capacity allocation. Output: 1-page agenda; 3 opportunities ready for "next solution to test". Constrain output to specific recommendations + tradeoffs; reject hedging boilerplate like "depends on team capacity".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sonnet for structured writing. Prep constraints keep the meeting focused and decision-driven.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r16" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Weekly-readout (sonnet): Friday. Input: All week artifacts. Output: weekly-discovery.md + roadmap-input.md. Roadmap-input is a delta artifact, never a rewrite. Quarterly mapper emits "promote / demote / hold / drop" recommendations versus current Now/Next/Later.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Weekly readouts build organizational memory. Delta artifacts keep PMs in control of major roadmap shifts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r17" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Roadmap-mapper (opus): Quarterly. Input: Full OST, outcome history, capacity. Output: Now/Next/Later updates as deltas to existing roadmap. Force it to use rolling-90d evidence count, not raw recency, to prevent bias toward last week's interviews.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opus for synthesis. Quarterly mapping locks in roadmap direction driven by evidence, not opinion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r18" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Archive-pruner (sonnet): Monthly. Input: OST nodes with no edits in 90d. Output: Archive proposals; PM approves. Set OST token budget: cap ost-synthesizer at 120k tokens per run (full OST + 1 week of transcripts). If over, archive first; never expand context.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Monthly pruning keeps the tree navigable. Token budgets prevent runaway costs on synthesis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r19" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All agent integration happens through files in `.aidocs/product_docs/discovery/`. No in-app SaaS state without an export step. This keeps the OST portable and queryable.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">File-based state lets agents version-control the tree, run diffs, and keep everything queryable via simple grep/yaml parsing. SaaS-only state becomes a black box the moment the tool changes pricing or API.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r20" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Feedback ingest sources (support tickets, NPS, sales calls, app-store reviews) MUST be mapped to the OST via standardized fields: source, date, user_id, segment, verbatim. Never ingest raw data without annotation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Annotated ingest lets agents weight by segment and avoid false-positive clustering from identical generic complaints across different sources.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
