<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-ost-framework" title="OST Framework and Weekly Discovery Cadence">
  <summary>Defines the Opportunity Solution Tree structure, weekly cadence, interview best practices, discovery-delivery capacity allocation, and OST maintenance rules.</summary>

  <section title="OST Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every opportunity must express an unmet customer need, pain, or desire in the customer's own words — reject any opportunity phrased as "build X" or "add X feature".</statement>
      <rationale>Solution-shaped opportunities contaminate the tree with implementation choices before the need is validated; they belong as solutions under a real opportunity, not as opportunities themselves.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every opportunity must link to at least one verbatim quote with participant-id and interview-date; opportunities without evidence are not opportunities, they are hypotheses.</statement>
      <rationale>Quote-level provenance is the only defense against the OST becoming fiction; without it, the tree reflects PM assumptions, not customer evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain one OST per outcome per quarter; if two outcomes are in scope, build two separate trees and handle cross-tree dependencies explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale>Merging two outcomes into one tree produces an OST with no single measurable north star; every feature can claim to serve "one of the outcomes" and nothing gets ruthlessly prioritized.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Weekly Discovery Cadence">
    <p>Monday: review customer feedback queue. Tuesday: run customer interview (30 min keystone habit). Wednesday: analyze interview + behavioral data. Thursday: team sync to share insights. Friday: plan next week's discovery.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Talk to customers weekly as a keystone habit — even one interview per week compounds into 50 data points per year that no monthly research sprint can replicate.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams that do monthly discovery bursts miss signal between bursts and struggle to connect interview themes to specific product changes; weekly cadence creates a running evidence stream.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Focus every interview on past behavior, not future predictions; ask about specific recent instances ("tell me about the last time you..."), never about hypothetical preferences.</statement>
      <rationale>Future predictions are aspirational and systematically optimistic; past behavior is what the product must actually support.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Before each interview round, run a sampling-diversity check: segment, recency, plan-tier, churn-status. Reject the prep if the last 4 interviews are within one slice.</statement>
      <rationale>PMs systematically over-sample the same 5 power users; segment diversity is required to prevent the OST from reflecting one persona's experience as universal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Discovery-Delivery Balance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Allocate discovery capacity at 15-20% as a contract with engineering, not a PM aspiration; if 15% gets eaten weekly, escalate or shrink scope.</statement>
      <rationale>Discovery done only by the PM while engineers stay at 100% delivery collapses the Product Trio to PM-only; continuous discovery as a team practice requires engineering participation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="OST Maintenance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Park opportunities with no new evidence in 60 days; archive at 180 days. Tree health beats tree completeness.</statement>
      <rationale>By month 6, uncurated OSTs accumulate 200+ nodes and become unusable; ruthless parking is the only way to keep the tree actionable for the trio.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running a quarterly archive-or-promote ritual only — opportunities are never pruned between quarters.</description>
      <reason>Infrequent pruning allows the tree to bloat to the point where trio meetings spend most time navigating the tree rather than making decisions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="templates/ost.yaml">OST schema: outcome, opportunities with evidence, solutions, assumption tests</reference>
  </section>
</text>
