<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="continuous-discovery-habits Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for continuous-discovery-habits as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>"Weekly interview" degrades to "weekly chat with the loudest customer" — PMs over-sample the same 5 power users.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents must enforce sampling diversity (segment, recency, churn-status, plan-tier) before each round. Without this, the OST reflects power-user preferences, not market-wide patterns.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>OST grows monotonically; without pruning, it becomes a dumping ground. By month 6 most trees have 200+ nodes and become unusable.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Need a quarterly archive-or-promote ritual. Monthly pruning keeps the tree navigable and forces teams to drop invalidated hypotheses.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Opportunities get conflated with solutions ("opportunity: build dashboard"). Must reject solution-shaped opportunities; they belong as branches under a real opportunity.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Solution-shaped opportunities collapse the distinction between need and proposed answer, preventing the team from validating the underlying problem.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Discovery-delivery balance (15–20% capacity) is fictional in most teams — engineers stay at 100% delivery, PM does discovery alone, trio collapses to PM-only.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Discovery-delivery percentage is a contract with engineering, not a PM aspiration. If 15% gets eaten weekly, escalate or shrink scope; do not silently absorb it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Outcome metric ambiguity — many PMs pick activation/retention proxies that the team can't actually move in a quarter. Agent-driven OST inherits the bad outcome and produces noise.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin the outcome_id. New wording = new outcome = new tree. Outcome metrics must be directly movable by the team in a quarter, not proxy metrics that conflate causation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Past-behavior interviews still surface aspirational answers when the prompt is loose; LLM transcript-coding amplifies this, mistaking interviewer leading questions for customer signal.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Interview-prep must produce questions about specific recent instances ("tell me about the last time you..."), never future predictions. Coder must label every quote as past_behavior | preference | speculation; synthesizer must filter to past_behavior only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Synthesis collapses when interview corpora cross &gt; 100 transcripts without theming — naive embedding-based clustering returns shallow themes ("users want speed"). Hierarchical theming (axial coding) is needed.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require N&gt;=5 quotes from &gt;=3 participants before emitting a theme. Do not manufacture cross-cutting themes from N=2 unrelated quotes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Tree visualization tools (Miro/FigJam) become the bottleneck — a YAML/JSON tree-as-code is more agent-friendly but humans don't love it.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin OST as YAML; use mermaid-cli or graphviz to render SVG for stakeholder meetings. Agents are fast on code; don't force them to manipulate design tools.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Memory creep across weeks: agents fed last-week's "decisions" treat them as immutable, blocking re-litigation. Always include a revisited_ok: true flag in the prompt for opportunities older than 30 days.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Opportunities should be revisitable; otherwise the team locks in bad assumptions. Explicit revisit flags let teams re-negotiate old decisions when new evidence arrives.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Calendar contention: agents auto-book interviews into PM's deep-work blocks; require a "discovery zone" calendar block as the only legal slot.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Interview scheduling must respect PM's focus time. A "discovery zone" block signals availability and prevents agent-driven interview scheduling from disrupting the week.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Customer recordings often contain SSN, contract terms, internal company info. Run a PII scrubber pre-coding; never feed raw recordings to a remote LLM without redaction.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PII scrubbing is a mandatory gating step before agent ingestion. Compliance and privacy require local redaction before any remote processing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
