<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-design-rules" title="Accessibility-First Design — Thresholds and Rules">
  <summary>Concrete, testable thresholds for color contrast, touch targets, motion, focus states, and semantic structure that must be resolved at design time.</summary>

  <section title="Color and Contrast">
    <rule>
      <statement>Body text must meet a 4.5:1 contrast ratio against its background (WCAG AA). Large text (18pt+ or 14pt bold) requires 3:1. UI components and focus indicators require 3:1.</statement>
      <rationale>Contrast ratios below these thresholds make text unreadable for low-vision users and in high-ambient-light environments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use color as the sole indicator of meaning (e.g., red = error). Always pair color with a text label, icon, or pattern.</statement>
      <rationale>Approximately 8% of males have color vision deficiency; color-only signals are invisible to them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Test designs with a color blindness simulator (e.g., Stark plugin) for deuteranopia, protanopia, and achromatopsia before developer handoff.</statement>
      <rationale>Simulation catches color-only patterns that pass contrast ratio checks but still fail color-blind users.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Touch Targets and Spacing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Touch targets must be at minimum 24×24px (WCAG 2.2 AA). Use 44×44px as the production target; 48×48dp for Material Design contexts.</statement>
      <rationale>Targets below 24px are consistently missed by users with motor impairments and elderly users with reduced dexterity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain at least 8px spacing between adjacent interactive elements to prevent mis-taps.</statement>
      <rationale>Dense interactive element layouts produce high error rates for users with tremors or limited fine motor control.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Focus and Keyboard Navigation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design visible focus indicators for every interactive element with a minimum 3:1 contrast ratio against adjacent colors. Never remove the default browser focus ring without a replacement.</statement>
      <rationale>Keyboard-only users and switch control users navigate entirely via focus indicators; invisible focus makes the interface unusable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Plan and annotate the keyboard focus order in design specs. Logical tab order must follow reading order; modal dialogs must trap focus while open and return focus to the trigger on close.</statement>
      <rationale>An unspecified focus order results in developer-guessed tab sequences that are often illogical or inaccessible.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Motion and Time Limits">
    <rule>
      <statement>All animations must be pausable and must respect the prefers-reduced-motion media query. No auto-playing video with sound. No flashing content above 3 flashes per second.</statement>
      <rationale>Motion triggers vestibular disorders in some users; flashing above 3 Hz can induce photosensitive seizures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Remove time limits from interactive flows, or make them adjustable and extendable with at least 20 seconds warning.</statement>
      <rationale>Fixed time limits exclude slow readers, users with cognitive disabilities, and screen reader users who process content sequentially.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Semantic Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Specify heading levels (H1 → H2 → H3) in design annotations. Never skip a heading level. Every page must have exactly one H1.</statement>
      <rationale>Screen reader users navigate by heading; a broken hierarchy makes content structure incomprehensible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>All form inputs must have visible labels connected via for/id. Placeholder text is not a label substitute — it disappears on input and has insufficient contrast.</statement>
      <rationale>Placeholder-only labels fail blind users who cannot see the placeholder and sighted users once they start typing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include in design handoff: heading levels, image alt text, link text (no "click here"), focus order, ARIA labels for custom components, error message copy, loading state announcements.</statement>
      <rationale>Developers cannot infer accessibility semantics from visual designs; explicit annotation is required for correct implementation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
