<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-patterns" title="Accessibility-First Design — Common Patterns">
  <summary>Concrete implementation patterns for accessible forms, modal dialogs, navigation landmarks, buttons vs links, and progressive enhancement.</summary>

  <section title="Semantic HTML vs Div Soup">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="html"><![CDATA[
<nav aria-label="Main navigation">
  <ul>
    <li><a href="/">Home</a></li>
    <li><a href="/about">About</a></li>
  </ul>
</nav>
<main>
  <article>
    <h1>Main Title</h1>
    <section>
      <h2>Section Title</h2>
      <p>Content here...</p>
    </section>
  </article>
</main>
<aside aria-label="Related content">
  <h2>Related Articles</h2>
</aside>
      ]]></code>
      <note>Native landmark elements (nav, main, aside, footer) give screen readers free navigation without extra ARIA.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using only div and span with CSS classes for all layout and interactive elements.</description>
      <reason>Screen readers receive no semantic information; keyboard navigation and assistive technology integrations break entirely.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Forms">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every input must have a visible label connected via for/id. Use aria-describedby for helper text. Mark required fields with both an asterisk and aria-required. Group related inputs with fieldset + legend.</statement>
      <rationale>Screen readers announce labels on focus; without a programmatic label the field is announced only by type ("edit blank"), giving no context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Error messages must use aria-invalid="true" on the input and role="alert" on the error text so screen readers announce errors without requiring the user to navigate to them.</statement>
      <rationale>Sighted users see inline errors visually; blind users only discover errors if they are programmatically announced.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="html"><![CDATA[
<label for="email">Email address <span aria-hidden="true">*</span></label>
<input id="email" type="email" aria-required="true"
       aria-describedby="email-hint email-error" aria-invalid="true">
<p id="email-hint">We'll only use this to send your receipt.</p>
<p id="email-error" role="alert">Enter a valid email address.</p>
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Modal Dialogs">
    <rule>
      <statement>When a modal opens: move focus to the first interactive element inside it, trap Tab/Shift+Tab within it, close on Escape key, and return focus to the trigger element on close.</statement>
      <rationale>Without focus trapping, keyboard users tab out of the modal into an obscured background; without Escape support they cannot exit without a mouse.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark background content with aria-hidden="true" when a modal is open so screen readers do not read background content.</statement>
      <rationale>Without aria-hidden, screen reader users can navigate the background page while the modal is open, causing confusion.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Buttons vs Links">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use button for actions that do not change the URL (submit, toggle, open modal, delete). Use anchor (a) for navigation to a new page or section. Never style one as the other without role correction.</statement>
      <rationale>Screen readers and voice control software identify interactive elements by role; a div styled as a button is not keyboard-reachable and not announced as a button.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip Links">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place a "Skip to main content" link as the first focusable element on every page. It may be visually hidden until focused.</statement>
      <rationale>Keyboard users and screen reader users must Tab through all navigation on every page load without a skip link — a severe usability barrier on navigation-heavy pages.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Progressive Enhancement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build in layers: (1) semantic HTML providing core functionality, (2) CSS for visual presentation, (3) JavaScript for enhanced interactions. Core functionality must work without JavaScript.</statement>
      <rationale>JS-only interfaces break for users on low-bandwidth connections, corporate environments that block JS, and assistive technologies that execute JS inconsistently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Mobile Checklist">
    <list>
      <item>Touch targets at minimum 44x44px on all interactive elements</item>
      <item>No user-scalable=no in viewport meta — pinch zoom must be enabled</item>
      <item>Text resizes to 200% without horizontal scroll (WCAG 1.4.4)</item>
      <item>Forms compatible with platform autofill (correct input type and autocomplete attributes)</item>
      <item>Both portrait and landscape orientation supported</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
