<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-conversion-optimization">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>conversion-optimizer</domain>
    <summary>Research-driven cycle for improving conversion rates: measure drop-offs, form hypotheses, run A/B tests to statistical significance, implement winners, document learnings.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>cro</tag>
      <tag>conversion-rate-optimization</tag>
      <tag>a-b-testing</tag>
      <tag>research</tag>
      <tag>funnel-optimization</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>cro</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Conversion Rate Optimization (CRO)</title>

    <summary>A research-driven cycle for systematically improving conversion rates across web funnels: measure where users drop off, research why, form testable hypotheses, run A/B tests to statistical significance (95%+, 100+ conversions/variant, 2+ weeks), implement winners, and document learnings in a reusable library. A 1% → 2% lift doubles effective marketing spend.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Traffic without conversion is wasted acquisition budget. CRO applies scientific method to UX decisions: hypothesis + controlled test + significance gate + learning library. Without the gate, early-stop false positives corrupt the program. Without the library, the same mistakes repeat. The PIE framework (Potential × Importance × Ease) ensures effort goes to high-traffic, high-impact pages first.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Established traffic (≥5k unique visitors/page/month) with under-converting funnels.</item>
        <item>Starting or running a structured A/B testing program.</item>
        <item>Redesigning forms, pricing pages, checkout, or onboarding where research-driven hypotheses outperform opinion.</item>
        <item>Quarterly CRO program reviews: wins, losses, learnings, next-cycle backlog.</item>
        <item>Multi-page funnel diagnosis using heatmaps + session recordings + exit surveys together.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Low-traffic pages (under ~5k uniques/month) — statistical significance is unreachable; use qualitative research instead.</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF startups — optimizing the wrong funnel; nail message-market fit first.</item>
        <item>Stable, mature funnels with sub-1% lift potential — resources better spent on acquisition or new product.</item>
        <item>Major redesigns — run user research and prototype testing, not A/B tests.</item>
        <item>Compliance-heavy flows (KYC, medical) where CRO levers conflict with required disclosures.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="cro-cycle">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Follow the research-before-testing rule: run heatmaps, session recordings, and 5+ user interviews before writing a single A/B test hypothesis.</statement>
        <rationale>Random changes produce random results. Research anchors hypotheses to real user friction, which lifts win rate from ~30% to ~50% per test.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use the PIE framework to prioritize: score each opportunity on Potential (impact headroom), Importance (traffic volume), and Ease (implementation cost), then divide by 3. Test highest-scoring opportunities first.</statement>
        <rationale>High-traffic pages with large drop-offs and low-effort fixes return value fastest; PIE prevents teams from polishing low-traffic pages.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="funnel-stage-benchmarks">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Establish baseline metrics per funnel stage before starting any CRO work: landing page bounce rate target below 50%, signup form completion above 30%, pricing CTA click rate above 5%, checkout completion above 60%, visitor-to-customer 1-5%.</statement>
        <rationale>Without baselines, test results have no reference frame and post-test "lift" claims are unverifiable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Track drop-offs with funnel visualization tools (GA4, Mixpanel). Identify the single biggest leak first; fixing downstream leaks while the top leaks are open wastes budget.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="hypothesis-formation">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every test hypothesis must follow this template: "We believe that [change] will cause [effect] because [rationale]. We will measure this by [metric] and consider it successful if [target]."</statement>
        <rationale>Pre-registration prevents post-hoc rationalization. Hypotheses without explicit success criteria inflate false-positive rates.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Common CRO levers: clarity (simpler headlines), value prop (better benefit framing), trust (logos, testimonials), urgency (limited offers), friction reduction (fewer form fields), risk reversal (money-back guarantees).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ab-test-requirements">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not declare a winner until: 100+ conversions per variant, 2+ weeks of runtime covering weekly cycles, and 95%+ statistical significance. Never peek at results before the minimum sample is reached.</statement>
        <rationale>Stopping early at ~80% confidence inflates the false-positive rate from 5% to ~30%, polluting the learning library with phantom wins.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run a 30-day holdback cell (95% rollout + 5% control) after shipping winners to monitor novelty regression.</statement>
        <rationale>Winners often regress 30+ days post-launch; holdback cells catch regressions before they fully erode the gain.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep traffic assignment user-id-hashed, not session-based, and monitor for test pollution: bot traffic, consent-banner disruption, and cross-test contamination before calling results.</statement>
        <rationale>Session-based assignment allows the same user to see both variants; bot traffic and consent banners silently inflate or deflate exposure counts.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="learning-library">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Document every test result — winner, loser, or inconclusive — with: name, date, hypothesis, change, metric result, lift percentage, what generalizes, what does not, and next test idea.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams that maintain a learning library double their annual win rate by avoiding repeated experiments and building on prior knowledge.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="worked-examples">
      <example type="good" title="Signup form: 15% → 27% completion (+45% lift)">
        <p>Research: heatmaps showed hesitation at password field; session recordings showed confusion about requirements; exit surveys cited "too many fields". Hypothesis: reducing to email-only signup (set password later) will increase form completion because it removes the most-cited friction point. Result: 45% lift, no negative impact on activation.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Pricing page: 2% → 3.3% trial conversion over two sequential tests">
        <p>Research: users wanted easy plan comparison; FAQ questions revealed feature confusion; mobile layout was broken. Three tests: (1) comparison table — no impact; (2) FAQ section added — +15%; (3) mobile redesign — +20% on mobile segment. All three run to full significance; mobile segmented separately from desktop.</p>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Stopping tests early when results look good at 80% confidence.</description>
        <reason>At 80% confidence the false-positive rate is ~30%, not 5%. "We have a winner" declared on day 4 pollutes the learning library with phantom gains.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using heatmaps as the only research source before forming hypotheses.</description>
        <reason>Heatmaps reveal where users click but not why they leave. Pair with session recordings and exit surveys to triangulate intent; heatmap-only hypotheses have a lower win rate.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Copying "best practice" changes from industry case studies without local research.</description>
        <reason>Urgency timers and social-proof-above-fold tactics fail to replicate without local data confirming the same friction exists in your specific audience.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running a major redesign as an A/B test.</description>
        <reason>Multivariate changes cannot isolate which element caused any measured effect; use user research and prototype testing instead.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No learning library entry after a test concludes — win or loss.</description>
        <reason>Without documentation, teams re-run the same failed tests and lose accumulated institutional knowledge. The library is the primary long-term asset of a CRO program.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/cro-audit.md" purpose="CRO audit template: funnel analysis table, research findings, PIE backlog, recommended tests."/>
      <template path="templates/ab-test-brief.md" purpose="A/B test brief: hypothesis, variants, metrics, sample size, implementation checklist."/>
      <template path="templates/sample-size.py" purpose="Binary metric sample-size calculator: two-sided, 95% confidence, 80% power."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="funnel-basics-framework"/>
      <ref slug="funnel-tactics-basics"/>
      <ref slug="growth-free-trial-optimization"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
