<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Methodologies Summary (Product Manager) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Routing rubric matching observable PM-task signals (artifact, time horizon, decision shape) to the right methodology under pro/product/product-manager/.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="rubric-deterministic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Routing MUST be deterministic given the three signals (artifact, horizon, decision_shape). Two agents with the same inputs MUST pick the same methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — routing audit">Non-deterministic routing erodes trust and produces inconsistent outputs across runs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="artifact-type-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The first routing dimension is the requested artifact (spec / roadmap / OKR / experiment / readout / pricing decision). Artifact shape eliminates most candidates immediately.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — PM-task taxonomy">Most PM tasks are artifact-driven; routing on artifact first prunes the search space cheaply.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="horizon-second" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Time horizon (this-week / this-sprint / this-quarter / annual) is the second dimension. Mismatched horizon is the most common mis-routing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — mis-routing post-mortems">Quarterly methodologies applied weekly produce noise; weekly methodologies stretched to annual collapse.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="decision-shape-third" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision shape (binary / ranked / cascade / framework-pick / report) breaks any remaining tie.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — routing audit">Decision shape captures the operator's mental model of 'what answer do I want'; the rubric must mirror that.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="fallback-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When no methodology fits cleanly, the rubric MUST name `methodologies-summary` as the fallback (this methodology) rather than guessing a near-match.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — failure-mode audit">Silent guessing routes ambiguous tasks to plausibly-relevant methodologies that produce wrong outputs; named fallback is honest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — task already tagged with a methodology slug; agent inside another methodology's procedure; non-PM-domain task), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
