<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-conversions-utm" title="Conversion Configuration and UTM Standards">
  <summary>Conversion designation in GA4 and ad platforms, UTM parameter schema, naming conventions, and Consent Mode v2 requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Conversion Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement Consent Mode v2 from day one even outside the EEA; retrofitting it later requires a migration and risks 30-50% conversion loss in reports during the transition.</statement>
      <rationale>Consent Mode v2 became mandatory in the EEA in March 2024. Sites outside EEA will need to add it when expanding. Installing it at launch eliminates a future migration and ensures modeled conversion data flows correctly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>GA4 Admin → Events → mark key events as conversions</item>
      <item>Set conversion value for revenue-generating events</item>
      <item>Import GA4 conversion actions into Google Ads (Tools → Conversions → Import from GA4)</item>
      <item>Set attribution window per conversion type (match to sales cycle)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="UTM Parameters">
    <rule>
      <statement>Standardize UTM naming in code as exported constants; never rely on humans typing utm_source values manually — typos produce fragmented source/medium data that cannot be cleaned retroactively.</statement>
      <rationale>A constant export (`UTM_SOURCES = {"google": "google", "meta": "meta"}`) prevents "Google", "google", "goog" all appearing as separate sources. Fragmented data corrupts channel attribution permanently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>utm_source: traffic origin (google, meta, linkedin, twitter, email, affiliate) — lowercase only</item>
      <item>utm_medium: marketing channel type (cpc, paid_social, email, organic_social, referral)</item>
      <item>utm_campaign: format [initiative]_[description]_[date] e.g. launch_spring_sale_2026q1</item>
      <item>utm_content: ad variation format [type]_[description]_[version] e.g. video_testimonial_v2</item>
      <item>utm_term: keyword for paid search</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using spaces or uppercase letters in UTM values.</description>
      <reason>Spaces get encoded as %20 or + differently across browsers and tools. Mixed case creates separate entries in GA4 reports. Both produce reporting fragmentation that requires manual cleanup.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Consent Mode v2">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set analytics_storage and ad_storage to "denied" by default before the consent banner renders; only upgrade to "granted" after explicit user consent is recorded.</statement>
      <rationale>Collecting analytics data before consent is recorded violates GDPR in the EEA and is increasingly enforced. Denied-by-default is the only approach that survives a regulatory audit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Hash all PII (email, phone) via SHA-256 on lowercase-trimmed values before sending to ad pixels; use server-side tagging to prevent raw PII from reaching client-side code.</statement>
      <rationale>Ad platforms require hashed PII for enhanced matching. Sending raw PII violates GDPR and ad platform terms. Skipping normalization (lowercase + trim) produces near-zero match rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
