<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Value Stream Management — Framework and Metrics">
  <summary>VSM principles from the Flow Framework, DORA four-tuple, VSM + DORA combination pattern, and the implementation sequence.</summary>

  <section title="Value Stream Mapping Fundamentals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map from "user filed request" to "user received value" — not from "ticket created" to "merged"; customer-visible time is the only honest measurement boundary.</statement>
      <rationale>Internal pipeline metrics (commit-to-deploy) can look elite while the customer waits weeks for spec, design, and compliance stages that precede the first commit. Only customer-anchored boundaries reveal actual value flow.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>VSM originated from lean manufacturing; Mik Kersten (Project to Product, 2018) adapted it to software with the Flow Framework. It identifies bottlenecks outside the software team — the stages that DevOps automation cannot reach.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Flow Metrics (Kersten / Flow Framework)">
    <list>
      <item>Lead Time: time from accepting work to customer handoff — end-to-end flow. The primary metric.</item>
      <item>Cycle Time: time within a single process stage — process efficiency. Used to locate the constraint.</item>
      <item>Throughput: items completed per time period — delivery rate.</item>
      <item>WIP: work items in progress simultaneously — per Little's Law, WIP = Throughput × Cycle Time.</item>
      <item>%C/A (Complete and Accurate): percentage received by downstream stage without rework needed — quality of handoffs.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Split flow data by work type (feature, defect, risk, debt) — single-number flow metrics hide trade-offs.</statement>
      <rationale>A team shipping 100% defect work has high throughput but zero feature delivery; aggregating disguises this. Mik Kersten's four-type split is the minimum granularity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="DORA Four-Tuple">
    <list>
      <item>Deployment Frequency: how often code deploys to production. Elite = multiple per day.</item>
      <item>Change Lead Time: commit to production time. Elite = under 1 hour.</item>
      <item>Change Failure Rate: percentage of deployments causing a failure. Elite = under 5%.</item>
      <item>Mean Time to Recovery (MTTR): time to restore service after failure. Elite = under 1 hour.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never optimize one DORA metric in isolation — always pair DF with CFR; high DF + high CFR is a negative trade-off.</statement>
      <rationale>Deployment frequency can be gamed by deploying trivial changes; the constraint is value delivery per deploy, not deploys per day in isolation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not publish "Elite DORA" status without trend context — the label is meaningless and will be gamed by teams optimizing for the scorecard.</statement>
      <rationale>DORA levels were designed as benchmarks for improvement, not badges. Publishing static levels without trend data invites Goodhart's Law to destroy the signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Implementation Sequence">
    <list>
      <item>1. Instrument: connect Jira/Linear, GitHub, deploy logs, PagerDuty, Zendesk via ID links — commit timestamps are the foundation.</item>
      <item>2. Map: trace one work item end-to-end; identify the stages; measure Lead Time and Cycle Time per stage.</item>
      <item>3. Measure DORA: daily collection on git + deploy logs.</item>
      <item>4. Identify constraint: apply Little's Law; highest WIP × Cycle Time stage is the system bottleneck (Theory of Constraints).</item>
      <item>5. Experiment: run one targeted experiment on the constraint; measure its effect on Lead Time.</item>
      <item>6. Monitor: quarterly VSM refresh; refresh the map; do not assume the stream stays static.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>VSM workshop that produces a poster but no telemetry instrumentation.</description>
      <reason>Without instrumentation, the VSM map decays into fiction within months as the stream evolves. Map and metric collection must happen simultaneously.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
