<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-tools-and-references" title="Value Stream Management — Tools, Services, and References">
  <summary>CLI tools, SaaS services, best practices, and key references for VSM instrumentation and DORA measurement.</summary>

  <section title="CLI Tools">
    <list>
      <item>four-keys (Google) — DORA pipeline reference implementation (https://github.com/dora-team/fourkeys)</item>
      <item>gh api — GitHub deployments + PR timestamps for DORA collection</item>
      <item>jq — stream join JSON across tools; essential for cross-tool ID linking (https://jqlang.github.io/jq/)</item>
      <item>git log --pretty — cycle time inputs from commit timestamps (core git)</item>
      <item>pagerduty-cli — MTTR data from incident logs (https://github.com/martindstone/pagerduty-cli)</item>
      <item>glab api — GitLab deployment events, MR timestamps</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Services">
    <list>
      <item>LinearB — engineering metrics, GitHub-native, REST API; good for mid-size orgs (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Plandek — Flow + DORA dashboards, REST API; supports multiple source integrations (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Jellyfish — engineering benchmarking, REST API; strong on team-level analysis (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Faros AI — DORA + Flow with open data layer; can self-host (SaaS/OSS).</item>
      <item>Apache DevLake — self-host DORA + Flow with plugin architecture for all major tools (OSS).</item>
      <item>Tasktop / Planview Viz — enterprise VSM platform; requires license; REST API partial (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Code Climate Velocity — cycle time, PR throughput; GitHub-centric (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Allstacks — forecasting from flow data; REST API (SaaS).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Visualize flow with cumulative flow diagram (CFD), not bar charts — CFD reveals stage starvation and WIP accumulation that bar charts hide.</statement>
      <rationale>Bar charts show throughput at a point in time; CFDs show the rate of item entry and exit per stage, making bottleneck dynamics visible as widening bands.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Little's Law (WIP = Throughput × Cycle Time) as a sanity check on agent-collected data — large deviations indicate instrumentation errors.</statement>
      <rationale>Little's Law holds for any stable system; if agent-collected WIP, throughput, and cycle time do not satisfy it, there is a data collection bug, not an anomaly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When AI tooling lifts throughput, watch Change Failure Rate and rework rate — productivity that creates incidents is disguised debt.</statement>
      <rationale>The AI productivity paradox: AI-generated code that deploys fast but fails in production increases MTTR and CFR, erasing the DF gain. Track the full four-tuple together.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="References">
    <list>
      <item>Mik Kersten, "Project to Product" (2018) — Flow Framework foundational text</item>
      <item>Forsgren, Humble, Kim, "Accelerate" (2018) — DORA research and four-tuple</item>
      <item>Goldratt, "The Goal" (1984) — Theory of Constraints</item>
      <item>Google Cloud DORA report 2024 — https://cloud.google.com/devops/state-of-devops</item>
      <item>Apache DevLake — https://devlake.apache.org</item>
      <item>Sibling methodologies: earned-value-management/, agile-ceremonies-setup/, pm-tool-selection/, schedule-development/</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
