<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="django-quality-queries Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for Django ORM query optimisation. Each rule names a concrete observable and the centralised location where the fix lives (selectors, not views).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-select-related" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every QuerySet that will be iterated MUST declare `select_related(...)` for every ForeignKey / OneToOneField accessed in the loop body BEFORE the iteration. The call belongs in selector / manager methods (centralised), not in views. Target: list endpoints ≤ 5 queries, detail endpoints ≤ 10 queries.</statement>
      <rationale source="Django docs https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/stable/ref/models/querysets/#select-related">select_related issues a single SQL JOIN — same query, zero extra round trips. Centralising in selectors means every caller (views, admin, Celery) inherits the optimisation. Hard targets give code review a concrete pass/fail.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-prefetch-related" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every QuerySet that traverses ManyToMany / reverse-FK / GenericForeignKey MUST use `prefetch_related(...)`. When the related queryset needs filtering, annotation, or its own select_related, use `Prefetch(...)` with `to_attr=` to expose a stable attribute. Never filter the prefetched relation in Python after iteration.</statement>
      <rationale source="Django docs https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/stable/ref/models/querysets/#prefetch-related">prefetch_related issues exactly 2 queries regardless of result-set size (1 for parents, 1 for children). Python-side filtering after a prefetch re-issues queries and silently undoes the optimisation; Prefetch(queryset=...) pushes the filter into SQL.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-bulk-ops" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Batch writes MUST use `bulk_create(objs, batch_size=500)`, `QuerySet.update(...)`, or `F()` expressions. Never iterate model instances calling `.save()` for counter increments or batch creates. F() expressions are evaluated server-side and are race-safe under concurrent writes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Django docs https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/stable/ref/models/querysets/#bulk-create">bulk_create executes one multi-row INSERT for O(1) queries vs O(N) per-row INSERTs. QuerySet.update issues a single UPDATE … WHERE. F() avoids read-modify-write races: under concurrent decrement two requests reading the same stock value both write back stock-1 instead of stock-2.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-indexes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Add `models.Index(fields=[...])` for every field appearing in: (a) `.filter()` clauses on hot paths, (b) `.order_by()` on tables with > 10k rows, (c) ForeignKey fields not covered by Django's auto-index. Add composite indexes for the most common multi-field filter+sort pattern (e.g. `["is_active", "-created_at"]`). Verify with `EXPLAIN ANALYZE` in development.</statement>
      <rationale source="PostgreSQL EXPLAIN docs + Django Index reference https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/stable/ref/models/indexes/">Sequential scan on an unindexed field is O(rows); B-tree index lookup is O(log N). On a 100k-row table the ratio is ≈10,000x. Composite indexes match real query shapes; single-column indexes cannot service combined filter+sort efficiently.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-assertnumqueries" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every hot endpoint (list view, dashboard, high-traffic API) MUST have a `with self.assertNumQueries(N):` (or `django_assert_num_queries`) regression test that locks the exact query count. Enable nplusone middleware in test settings with `NPLUSONE_RAISE=True`. Profile new views with Django Debug Toolbar before merging.</statement>
      <rationale source="Django testing docs https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/stable/topics/testing/tools/#django.test.TransactionTestCase.assertNumQueries">assertNumQueries is a zero-cost regression lock: a future commit that reintroduces N+1 fails CI immediately. Without it, N+1 regressions become visible only under load testing or production incident, after engineering cost has already been paid.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
