<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="brainstorming-ideation">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>communicator</domain>
    <summary>Agentic ideation pipeline: generation → semantic dedup → cluster-and-score; emits a scored shortlist for human review, not a facilitated session.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>brainstorming</tag>
      <tag>ideation</tag>
      <tag>agentic-pipeline</tag>
      <tag>scoring</tag>
      <tag>semantic-dedup</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="brainstorming-techniques"/>
      <ref slug="ideation-methods"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Brainstorming Ideation (Agentic Pipeline)</title>

    <summary>Brainstorming-ideation covers using brainstorming techniques as a generative input for automated pipelines — where the output is a scored shortlist, not a facilitated group session. The agent receives a problem statement, runs a structured generation pass (Classic, Reverse, or Brainwriting-simulated), deduplicates semantically, clusters by theme, and scores against an impact/effort rubric. For facilitated group sessions, see brainstorming-techniques/ which covers the human-facilitation angle.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Agent-generated idea lists plateau in novelty around 30-40 ideas without persona switching or domain constraint injection. The critical failure points are: (1) mixing generation and evaluation in the same prompt — causes premature convergence; (2) using the generating agent to also score ideas — circular bias toward first-pass outputs; (3) semantic clustering silently merging two distinct viable ideas — human review at the cluster stage is mandatory before scoring.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Product feature generation: given a persona + pain point, produce candidate features to evaluate against backlog</item>
        <item>Content ideation: bulk-generating article topics, campaign angles, or ad copy variants for human selection</item>
        <item>Risk surfacing: Reverse Brainstorming to enumerate failure modes before a launch or deployment</item>
        <item>Feeding a scored shortlist into a downstream pipeline (Linear backlog, Notion idea database)</item>
        <item>Feeding an ideation pipeline where the output is a scored shortlist, not a facilitated group session</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When human group dynamic is the point (team alignment, buy-in, psychological safety) — agentic bulk generation skips the relational work</item>
        <item>When the problem is too narrow for divergent thinking; use direct prompting or SCAMPER instead</item>
        <item>When ideas require domain-expert validation that an LLM cannot reliably provide (medical, legal, engineering safety)</item>
        <item>When you need the dot-voting or scoring to be done by the same agent that generated the ideas — circular bias invalidates the prioritization</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Three-pass pipeline: diverge (generation only, no evaluation), semantic dedup, cluster-and-score. Each pass is a separate prompt or function call — never combined in one.</p>

      <p>Agent receives a problem statement, a target idea count, and an optional technique flag (classic / reverse / brainwriting-simulated). It runs a generation pass with enforced formatting (one idea per line, no justification), then a dedup pass (semantic similarity), then a cluster-and-score pass. Output is a scored shortlist (top 5-10) with cluster labels, ready for human review. The human selects finalists and the agent generates one-line implementation notes per finalist.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-brainstorm — purpose-built for structured diverge/converge; use when full multi-round review is needed. General Claude Opus call — for raw generative passes where creativity &gt; structure.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="pass-1-diverge">
      <rule>
        <statement>Send the generation prompt with only the problem statement and constraints. Do NOT include scoring criteria, evaluation language, or ranking instructions. The output must be a numbered list with no justification text.</statement>
        <rationale>Including evaluation language in the generation prompt causes premature convergence — the model self-censors and produces fewer, safer ideas than an unconstrained generation pass.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Seed the generation pass with persona injection to force diverse viewpoints: "Generate from the perspective of a skeptic, an optimist, a first-time user, and an engineer." This produces more diverse output than an anonymous generation pass.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent-generated ideas plateau in novelty around 30-40 without persona switching. Training data bias causes clustering around the most common solutions in the domain.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/prompt-diverge.txt"/>
    </section>

    <section name="pass-2-semantic-dedup">
      <rule>
        <statement>Remove near-duplicate ideas before clustering using semantic similarity (cosine similarity threshold 0.82 with sentence-transformers). Do not rely on exact string matching — paraphrased duplicates survive it.</statement>
        <rationale>Duplicate ideas inflate cluster size and give false confidence in idea frequency. A cluster with 8 ideas that are all paraphrases of one idea is not 8 independent signals.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/semantic-dedup.py"/>
    </section>

    <section name="pass-3-cluster-and-score">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cluster deduplicated ideas into 5-7 semantic themes in a separate pass. Score each cluster on Impact (3x weight) and Feasibility (2x weight). Return a scored shortlist of top 5-10 clusters for human review.</statement>
        <rationale>Scoring before clustering produces per-idea scores that ignore the compound value of a theme. Scoring after clustering evaluates the best implementation of each direction.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Require human review of cluster boundaries before finalizing scores. The clustering pass can silently merge two distinct viable approaches that share domain vocabulary.</statement>
        <rationale>Semantic clustering by cosine similarity groups by surface word overlap, not conceptual distinctiveness. Two approaches can share words while being strategically opposed.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="reverse-brainstorm-variant">
      <rule>
        <statement>For risk surfacing: invert the problem ("How would we make X fail?"), generate negative ideas, then reverse each into a positive mitigation. Run as two sequential passes — inversion then reversal — not combined.</statement>
        <rationale>Groups generate more honest and specific negative ideas than positive ones, especially when they are politically constrained from criticizing directly.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/prompt-reverse.txt"/>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <prompt purpose="diverge-pass"><![CDATA[
Generate <N> distinct ideas for: <PROBLEM_STATEMENT>.
Constraints: <CONSTRAINTS if any>.
Format: numbered list only. No explanations. No duplicates.
      ]]></prompt>
      <prompt purpose="reverse-brainstorm"><![CDATA[
List <N> ways to make <PROBLEM_AREA> as bad as possible.
Be specific. Format: numbered list only.
Then reverse each item into a solution in a second numbered list.
      ]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="circular-scoring-bias">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using the same agent that generated the ideas to also dot-vote or rank them.</description>
        <reason>The generating agent has higher confidence in ideas it produced with higher certainty in the first pass. Self-scoring compounds this into a self-reinforcing ranking with no independent judgment.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <rule>
        <statement>Scoring must be done by a separate agent or human. The generating agent provides the list; a fresh agent or human applies the scoring rubric.</statement>
        <rationale>Separation of generation and evaluation is the most important architectural rule in agentic brainstorming pipelines.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="premature-convergence">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Including evaluation language ("good idea because...", "this works better than option B") in the generation prompt.</description>
        <reason>The model self-censors and produces fewer, safer ideas. The generation pass becomes a mixed pass that produces a filtered list masquerading as a brainstorm.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <rule>
        <statement>Generation prompt must contain only: problem statement, constraints, format instructions, and quantity target. No evaluation language.</statement>
        <rationale>Strict format enforcement (numbered list only, no explanations) prevents evaluation language from contaminating output even when the model defaults to justification.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="semantic-clustering-failures">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Accepting cluster assignments without human review, particularly when two conceptually distinct approaches share domain vocabulary.</description>
        <reason>Cosine similarity clusters by word overlap. "Automate onboarding email sequence" and "Automate onboarding task assignment" may cluster together despite being architecturally different solutions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="positional-bias-in-large-lists">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Passing a list of 50+ ideas to a scoring prompt in a single call.</description>
        <reason>Ideas in positions 1-15 receive systematically higher scores than identical ideas in positions 35-50 due to positional bias in LLM attention. The first batch is not comparable to the last batch.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <rule>
        <statement>Chunk idea lists into batches of 25 for scoring. Score each batch against the rubric independently, then compare top-scored ideas across batches in a final pass.</statement>
        <rationale>Chunking equalizes positional treatment. Cross-batch comparison in the final pass is a manageable 25-item set with no positional artifact.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <list>
        <item>jq — Parse and deduplicate JSON idea lists from agent output. Built-in most Unix systems.</item>
        <item>sentence-transformers (Python) — Semantic deduplication of idea lists. Install: pip install sentence-transformers</item>
        <item>Miro (SaaS, partial REST API) — Sticky-note creation via API; cluster grouping is manual</item>
        <item>Notion (SaaS, REST API) — Ideal for logging scored idea shortlists</item>
        <item>Linear (SaaS, REST API) — Convert top ideas directly into backlog issues</item>
        <item>Airtable (SaaS, REST API) — Tabular idea scoring with weighted formula columns</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="semantic-dedup-pipeline">
      <p>Semantic dedup pipeline (Python, ~30 lines):</p>
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
from sentence_transformers import SentenceTransformer, util

def semantic_dedup(ideas: list[str], threshold: float = 0.82) -> list[str]:
    model = SentenceTransformer("all-MiniLM-L6-v2")
    embeddings = model.encode(ideas, convert_to_tensor=True)
    keep = []
    dropped = set()
    for i in range(len(ideas)):
        if i in dropped:
            continue
        keep.append(ideas[i])
        for j in range(i + 1, len(ideas)):
            if j not in dropped:
                sim = float(util.cos_sim(embeddings[i], embeddings[j]))
                if sim >= threshold:
                    dropped.add(j)
    return keep
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Always separate the generation prompt from the evaluation prompt — same-call mixing causes premature pruning.</item>
        <item>Inject domain constraints into the generation prompt rather than the evaluation prompt: "ideas must be implementable by a 2-person team" up front produces better raw lists than filtering later.</item>
        <item>Run a Reverse Brainstorm variant on the same problem as a sanity check — if the negatives are hard to reverse into positives, the problem framing may be wrong.</item>
        <item>Store raw idea lists (pre-dedup, pre-score) in a scratch doc for future re-use; today's rejected idea may be valuable in a different context.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>"Brainwriting simulation" (agent pretends to be 6 different people passing ideas) consistently produces less diverse output than a single well-seeded prompt with persona injection.</item>
        <item>Dot voting by the same agent that generated the ideas is circular — the agent will favor ideas it generated with higher confidence.</item>
        <item>Human checkpoint required before finalizing shortlist: the agent's semantic clustering can silently merge two distinct viable ideas into one cluster, eliminating a viable option.</item>
        <item>Long idea lists (50+) that get passed to a scoring prompt often see the first 10-15 ideas scored more generously due to positional bias.</item>
        <item>Agent-generated idea lists are biased toward patterns already common in training data; genuinely novel ideas require cross-domain prompting or persona injection.</item>
        <item>Brainwriting round-by-round simulation loses the "build on others" benefit because the agent reads its own prior ideas, creating an echo chamber.</item>
        <item>Convergence (clustering, dot voting, scoring) is where agent errors compound — misclassified clusters lead to wrong shortlists.</item>
        <item>Quantity is trivially achieved (100 ideas in seconds) but quality filtering requires human judgment at the evaluation gate.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/prompt-diverge.txt" purpose="Diverge-pass prompt (generation only, no evaluation)"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-reverse.txt" purpose="Reverse Brainstorm prompt with inversion step"/>
      <template path="templates/semantic-dedup.py" purpose="Sentence-transformers semantic deduplication for idea lists"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://dschool.stanford.edu/resources/brainstorm-rules"/>
      <link href="https://www.ideo.com/post/design-thinking-methods"/>
      <link href="https://www.sbert.net"/>
      <ref slug="brainstorming-techniques"/>
      <ref slug="ideation-methods"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
