<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Support SLA — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for solo-SaaS support tiering, business-hours boundary, and canned-reply discipline.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-three-tiers" testable="true">
      <statement>Define EXACTLY three tiers: Community (free), Paid (≥ $19/mo), Enterprise (annual + signed contract). Sub-tiers within Paid (Solo / Pro / Geek) collapse into the Paid SLA — solos cannot operate 5 different SLAs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Help Scout — Solo Support Setup">Operator cognitive load is the bottleneck, not customer-tier granularity. Three tiers cover &gt; 95% of solo SaaS support patterns; more tiers create rule-lookup overhead that erodes reply time.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-business-hours-bound" testable="true">
      <statement>SLA reply times count business-hours only (Mon-Fri, operator timezone, declared start-end). Public SLA page must show timezone and the working window. After-hours = next business day.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo-founder burnout cohort (Justin Jackson, Sarah Hatter ChatTriage essays)">"24h response" interpreted as wall-clock 24h drives weekend work and resentment. Business-hours framing is the only sustainable solo policy and most enterprise customers accept it explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-canned-reply-discipline" testable="true">
      <statement>Operator must use canned-reply skeletons for ≥ 60% of replies. Each canned reply has 3 slots: customer name, ticket reference, specific finding. Custom prose for &lt; 40%.</statement>
      <rationale source="Help Scout / Front cohort data">Canned replies cut median reply time 4-7×. Quality stays equal — customers care about resolution, not bespoke prose. The 60% threshold is the inflection point where operator gains time without sounding robotic.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-escalation-rule" testable="true">
      <statement>Escalate to "drop everything" mode ONLY if: data loss reported, security incident reported, paying customer churned within 7 days, or 3+ users reporting the same break. All other tickets follow tier SLA.</statement>
      <rationale source="Production-incident triage discipline (SRE Book, Beyer et al.)">Without explicit escalation criteria, the loudest customer wins. Concrete triggers force objective triage and protect calendar from squeaky-wheel exploitation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-churn-signal-tag" testable="true">
      <statement>Every reply MUST tag the ticket with a churn-risk signal: GREEN (happy / praise), YELLOW (confusion / friction), RED (frustration / threatens to cancel). Tag drives weekly retention review, NOT the reply itself.</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer success industry standard (Lincoln Murphy, Gainsight)">Solo founders see every ticket in real time but lose the pattern over weeks. The tag is cheap to apply and the pattern (RED clusters) is the leading churn indicator.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Tier defaults">

    <example type="good" title="Default SLA tiers (operator can adjust)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Community (free):    First reply 72h business hours, no weekend.
Paid ($19+/mo):      First reply 24h business hours, priority queue.
Enterprise:          First reply 4h business hours, dedicated channel
                     (Slack or signal), monthly review.

Working hours: Mon-Fri 09:00-17:00 Europe/Lisbon (operator's TZ).
Out-of-hours auto-reply: "Got it. Reply by next business day per
your tier SLA. See SLA: faion.net/sla."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Concrete numbers + visible timezone = trust signal without burnout.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Wall-clock SLA without timezone (r2 violation)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"We reply within 24 hours."

Customer in Tokyo sends ticket at midnight Lisbon.
24h elapses at midnight Lisbon next day. Operator wakes at 7am,
already breached. Reputation damage from a metric the operator
could not physically meet.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Violates r2. Always state timezone AND business-hours window.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
