<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="risk-assessment">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>Structured 5-category risk identification and scoring using probability x impact matrices with one owner, one trigger, and one concrete mitigation per risk.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>risk</tag>
      <tag>risk-register</tag>
      <tag>pre-mortem</tag>
      <tag>due-diligence</tag>
      <tag>startup</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Risk Assessment</title>
    <summary>A structured 5-category (market/product/team/financial/operational) risk identification and scoring process using probability x impact matrices. Each risk gets one owner, one measurable trigger, and a concrete mitigation action (not "monitor + diversify"). Run as a multi-pass agent pipeline: enumerate → red-team pre-mortem → score → human review → convert high-priority risks into SDD tasks.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Entrepreneurs are either blindly optimistic or paralyzed by fear because there is no structured process for identifying and managing business risks. H/M/L scoring is useful only for relative ranking — absolute probabilities are wrong by an order of magnitude. The pre-mortem template is the highest-leverage artifact: a 30-minute exercise surfaces omissions that a solo risk review misses due to optimism bias.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch go/no-go review for a new product, feature, or market entry</item>
        <item>Investor or due-diligence ask requiring a credible risk register plus mitigations</item>
        <item>Quarterly business review where assumptions need re-validation</item>
        <item>After a near-miss incident — formalizing what almost killed the business</item>
        <item>Pivot decision comparing risk profiles of two strategic options</item>
        <item>New regulatory exposure appears on the roadmap (GDPR, AI Act, SOC2, payment rails)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Idea-stage with fewer than 3 customer conversations — risk theater is procrastination</item>
        <item>Tactical sprint planning — use an issue tracker, not a risk register</item>
        <item>One-person side projects with under $1k at stake — overhead exceeds value</item>
        <item>When the team will not assign owners or revisit monthly — a static register is worse than none</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="risk-categories">
      <rule>
        <statement>Enumerate at least 3 risks per category across all 5 categories: market, product, team, financial, operational.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents over-produce market and product risks (well-represented in training data) and under-produce financial, legal, and vendor risks. A minimum quota per category enforces coverage breadth.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="market-risks">
        <list>
          <item>Demand — no one wants it (market too small, poor timing)</item>
          <item>Competition — others win (incumbent copies, well-funded rival)</item>
          <item>Pricing — can't make money (commoditization, price war)</item>
          <item>Trend — market shifts (technology obsolescence)</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="product-risks">
        <list>
          <item>Technical — can't build it (complexity, dependencies)</item>
          <item>Usability — users can't use it (poor UX, learning curve)</item>
          <item>Value — doesn't solve problem (feature gaps, wrong solution)</item>
          <item>Quality — doesn't work well (bugs, performance issues)</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="team-risks">
        <list>
          <item>Skills — lack capabilities (missing expertise)</item>
          <item>Capacity — not enough bandwidth (founder burnout, solo limits)</item>
          <item>Alignment — different goals (co-founder conflict)</item>
          <item>Dependency — key person risk (single point of failure)</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="financial-risks">
        <list>
          <item>Runway — running out of money (cash burn too high)</item>
          <item>Revenue — can't generate income (monetization fails)</item>
          <item>Costs — expenses too high (infrastructure, CAC)</item>
          <item>External — economic downturn (recession, funding winter)</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="operational-risks">
        <list>
          <item>Vendor — dependency fails (API discontinued, pricing change)</item>
          <item>Legal — compliance issues (GDPR, copyright, licensing)</item>
          <item>Security — data breach (hack, data loss)</item>
          <item>Scale — can't handle growth (infrastructure breaks)</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="scoring-and-response">
      <rule>
        <statement>Score each risk as Probability x Impact where H=3, M=2, L=1. Use scores for relative ranking only — not absolute probability. Cap the active risk register at 10 risks; move everything below score 4 to an Accepted archive section.</statement>
        <rationale>H/M/L scoring is useful for forcing triage, not for computing expected loss. Absolute probabilities require FAIR methodology (quantitative). Capping at 10 prevents the register from becoming a comprehensive but unactionable list.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>For each high-priority risk (score 6+), define: one concrete response strategy (Avoid/Mitigate/Transfer/Accept), one specific trigger metric, one named owner, and one measurable action. Reject "monitor + diversify" or "stay agile" as mitigation.</statement>
        <rationale>Generic mitigations are never executed. A trigger metric forces the team to observe a leading indicator; a named owner prevents shared-responsibility diffusion.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="response-strategies">
        <list>
          <item>Avoid — eliminate the risk entirely (high prob, high impact)</item>
          <item>Mitigate — reduce probability or impact (medium risks)</item>
          <item>Transfer — shift to someone else (insurance, contracts)</item>
          <item>Accept — live with it (low risks; move to archive)</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <rule>
        <statement>Review cadence: top 3 risks weekly, full risk register monthly, deep review with external perspective quarterly.</statement>
        <rationale>A 6-month-old risk register reflects a company that no longer exists. Monthly reviews prevent static drift; quarterly outside-view reviews counteract optimism bias that founders apply to their own assessments.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="pre-mortem">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a pre-mortem before every major launch: assume the project failed 12 months from today, write a 500-word post-mortem, then convert each failure mode into a risk row.</statement>
        <rationale>Pre-mortems are the highest-leverage risk identification artifact. They surface omissions that a forward-looking risk review misses because they require assuming failure is already a fact, bypassing optimism bias.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-pipeline">
      <rule>
        <statement>Drive risk assessment as a 4-pass pipeline: (1) researcher agent enumerates candidate risks; (2) red-team agent runs pre-mortem; (3) scorer agent applies prob x impact with citations; (4) human owner reviews and assigns mitigations.</statement>
        <rationale>A single-pass enumeration produces a list anchored on the agent's prior knowledge. A separate red-team agent with a different system prompt (assume failure) surfaces black-swan and tail risks that the enumeration agent's optimism heuristic drops.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never let an agent autonomously execute an "Avoid" decision. Avoid means killing a feature or market — always require a human-in-the-loop gate before executing.</statement>
        <rationale>Avoiding a risk terminates a product direction. An agent making this call autonomously can invalidate weeks of work. The gate must be explicit and logged.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <prompt purpose="enumeration-pass"><![CDATA[You are a risk analyst. Given the product brief in <brief>, enumerate
risks across 5 categories: market, product, team, financial, operational.
For each risk: one-sentence statement, evidence (URL or doc ref),
probability (H/M/L), impact (H/M/L). Output as the Risk Register
markdown table from risk-assessment/README.md. Minimum 3 risks per
category. Cite sources inline.]]></prompt>
      <prompt purpose="pre-mortem-pass"><![CDATA[It is 12 months from today. The launch in <brief> failed. Write a
500-word post-mortem explaining what went wrong. Then convert each
failure mode into a risk row (see Pre-Mortem Template). Be specific:
no "lack of focus" — name the channel, the hire, the assumption.]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Require evidence per row. Reject any risk without a URL, conversation reference, or internal metric.</statement>
        <rationale>Risks without evidence are vibes-based register entries. A URL or document reference forces the agent to ground the risk in observable reality, not inference.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track mitigation cost vs. expected loss. If a mitigation costs more than prob x impact in dollars, accept the risk instead.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams systematically over-spend on low-EV risks (compliance theater) and under-spend on high-EV risks (channel concentration). The cost comparison provides a decision rule.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Diff the risk register across monthly reviews. The delta — new risks, retired risks, score changes — is the actual signal.</statement>
        <rationale>The absolute register is a point-in-time snapshot. The diff reveals whether identified risks are materializing, being mitigated, or being silently ignored.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap at 10 active risks. Anything below score 4 goes to an Accepted archive section, not the live table.</statement>
        <rationale>A register with 30+ items is never reviewed. Focus forces the team to genuinely prioritize.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Owner must be a single named person, not "the team". Each high-priority risk needs one trigger metric per high-priority risk.</statement>
        <rationale>Risks owned by "the team" are unowned. Shared responsibility = no responsibility. A trigger metric makes monitoring automatic, not subjective.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Have someone who is not on the team review the register quarterly. Founders systemically under-rate team and product risks.</statement>
        <rationale>Outside-view reviewer counteracts optimism bias. Internal teams cannot objectively rate their own capabilities or the value of their product.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Tie risks to assumptions. Each risk should reference an explicit assumption from the spec/design — when the assumption is invalidated, the risk changes state automatically.</statement>
        <rationale>Connecting risks to assumptions keeps the register live rather than static. When the assumption is tested and invalidated, the risk row gets a new status without a separate review cycle.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="examples">
      <example type="good" title="SaaS Startup Risk Register">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
| Risk                     | Prob | Impact | Score | Response  |
|--------------------------|------|--------|-------|-----------|
| No product-market fit    | H    | H      | 9     | Mitigate  |
| Key engineer leaves      | M    | H      | 6     | Mitigate  |
| AWS costs spike          | M    | M      | 4     | Accept    |
| Competitor launches      | M    | M      | 4     | Mitigate  |
| GDPR non-compliance      | L    | H      | 3     | Accept    |

Contingency for R1 (No PMF):
- Trigger: fewer than 20 paying customers after 6 months
- Response: pivot to adjacent problem or different segment
- Runway needed: 3 months buffer
- Owner: Founder
        ]]></code>
        <note>Each high-score risk has a concrete trigger metric, not a generic "watch for signals". The trigger is observable, not subjective.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Content Business Risk Register">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
| Risk                        | Prob | Impact | Score | Response |
|-----------------------------|------|--------|-------|----------|
| Platform algorithm change   | H    | H      | 9     | Mitigate |
| Creator burnout             | M    | H      | 6     | Mitigate |
| Payment processor drops us  | L    | H      | 3     | Accept   |
| Piracy/content theft        | M    | L      | 2     | Accept   |

Contingency for R1 (Platform change):
- Trigger: over 30% drop in organic reach over 30 days
- Response: shift budget to email, community, paid ads
- Resources: 3 months content backlog, ad budget reserved
- Owner: Growth Lead
        ]]></code>
        <note>Trigger is a percentage drop with a time window, not "if reach declines". Measurable and monitorable.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Too many risks in the register — 30+ active items.</description>
        <reason>Focus on the top 5-10. Everything below score 4 goes to an Accepted archive; it is still tracked but not in the active review table.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No contingency plans for high-priority risks.</description>
        <reason>Every risk with score 6+ needs a contingency plan with trigger, response, resources, and owner. A risk without a plan is just documentation of a known failure mode.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Optimism bias without outside-view reviewer.</description>
        <reason>Founders rate their own product and team risks too low. An outside reviewer quarterly is the minimum check on this bias.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Probability theater: H/M/L scoring is anchored on gut feel; absolute probabilities are wrong by an order of magnitude.</description>
        <reason>Use it for relative ranking only. Absolute probabilities require FAIR methodology (quantitative loss modeling).</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Black-swan blindness: the framework over-weights known categories (market/product/team/financial/operational). Tail risks (founder health, geopolitics, model regulation) get dropped.</description>
        <reason>Explicitly add a "tail risks" section or use the pre-mortem pass to surface these omissions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Mitigation inflation: every risk gets a generic "monitor + diversify" plan that nobody executes.</description>
        <reason>Require an action verb + owner + measurable trigger. Ban "monitor", "diversify", and "stay agile" as sole mitigations.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Static drift: risk registers age fast — a 6-month-old register reflects a company that no longer exists.</description>
        <reason>Monthly reviews are mandatory. Keep monthly snapshots in git; the delta is the actual signal.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No ROI on mitigation: cost of mitigation rarely tracked vs. expected loss; teams over-spend on low-EV risks (compliance) and under-spend on high-EV ones (concentration in one channel).</description>
        <reason>If a mitigation costs more than prob x impact in dollars, accept the risk instead.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs assign H/M/L confidently with no basis. Ungrounded probability scores inflate register quality perception.</description>
        <reason>Force the agent to cite a source or comparable case for any score. Reject rows where the probability is not grounded in evidence or a base rate.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Category bias: agents over-produce market and product risks and under-produce financial, legal, and vendor risks.</description>
        <reason>Enforce a quota: at least 2 risks per category. Reject submissions missing financial or operational rows.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Recency bias from web search: researcher agents will pull last week's headlines and over-weight them.</description>
        <reason>Cross-check against historical base rates. A single recent event does not change the underlying probability distribution.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Optimism leak from system prompts: if the brief is enthusiastic ("groundbreaking platform"), the agent inherits the tone and scores risks lower.</description>
        <reason>Use a neutral, redacted brief for the risk pass, or flip the agent into adversarial role explicitly.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Mitigation handwaving: agents default to "improve monitoring" / "diversify" / "stay agile" — banned phrases.</description>
        <reason>Require an action verb + owner + measurable trigger. Reject any mitigation that does not name a specific action and a specific person.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Risk register drift on re-runs: re-running the enumeration agent yields a different ID set every time.</description>
        <reason>Use stable hashes (slug of risk statement) instead of sequential IDs, or have the agent diff-merge instead of regenerate, to preserve register continuity across runs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No human checkpoint on "Avoid" decisions. "Avoid" means killing a feature or market.</description>
        <reason>Never let an agent autonomously execute an Avoid response. Hard human-in-the-loop gate required. Log the decision and the reasoning.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Confidentiality leak: risk statements often contain customer names, vendor terms, or unlaunched plans.</description>
        <reason>Run the scrubber agent before any external sharing or before piping into a 3rd-party SaaS.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent can't run the pre-mortem alone. Pre-mortems need divergent perspectives — solo agent runs collapse to one viewpoint.</description>
        <reason>Use 3+ agents with different system prompts (skeptic, customer, competitor) and consolidate. A single-agent pre-mortem produces a list skewed by the single prompt's optimism level.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/riskreg.sh" purpose="Sort risk register by score, lint missing fields and mitigations"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://hbr.org/2007/09/performing-a-project-premortem"/>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/iso-31000-risk-management.html"/>
      <link href="https://csrc.nist.gov/pubs/sp/800/30/r1/final"/>
      <link href="https://www.opengroup.org/forum/security/riskanalysis"/>
      <link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/library"/>
      <link href="https://a16z.com/16-startup-metrics/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
