<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="django-base-model Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Four high-impact base-model antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <antipattern id="fm-1-pk-swap">
      <symptom>Migration drops integer id columns and recreates as UUID. Every ForeignKey on the table breaks. Squashed migrations no longer apply. Backup restore fails.</symptom>
      <root-cause>Developer believed "switching to UUID is just changing the field type". The PK swap requires renaming the column, rewiring every FK in the schema, and rewriting every cached query plan.</root-cause>
      <fix>Reject the PK swap. Apply rule r1-separate-uid: keep integer id as PK; add a separate `uid` UUIDField for external IDs; expose `uid` in API responses; internal joins continue to use id.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-2-missing-partial-unique">
      <symptom>Restoring a soft-deleted row fails with IntegrityError: duplicate key violates unique constraint. The deleted row still occupies the unique index.</symptom>
      <root-cause>Field declared as `email = models.EmailField(unique=True)` on a soft-deletable model. Partial-index requirement was missed in code review.</root-cause>
      <fix>Replace `unique=True` with a `Meta.constraints = [UniqueConstraint(fields=['email'], condition=Q(deleted_at__isnull=True), name='unique_active_email')]`. The validator rule r3-partial-unique-under-soft-delete catches this.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-3-manager-shadowing">
      <symptom>Django admin shows zero deleted users even when querying by deleted_at. loaddata fails to overwrite soft-deleted rows. ORM-level signals fire on hard delete only.</symptom>
      <root-cause>Developer set `objects = SoftDeleteManager()` and removed the default Manager. Tools that expect Model.objects to return ALL rows (admin, loaddata, some migration ops) silently lose access.</root-cause>
      <fix>Preserve both managers: `objects = SoftDeleteManager()` (default — excludes deleted) AND `all_objects = models.Manager()` (every row). Configure admin's `get_queryset` to use all_objects with a "Include deleted" filter.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-4-cascade-soft-delete">
      <symptom>Soft-deleting a Customer hard-deletes their Orders. Compliance review fails: "deleted" customer's order history is gone.</symptom>
      <root-cause>Order.customer = ForeignKey(Customer, on_delete=models.CASCADE). Customer.delete() (soft) triggers QuerySet.delete() on children via cascade — which is the ORM's hard-delete path.</root-cause>
      <fix>Pick on_delete=PROTECT (cannot soft-delete a Customer with active Orders) or SET_NULL (orphan the Order, retain history). The spec's foreign_keys[].on_delete and reason fields force the explicit choice.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
