<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="content-audit-process">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>A structured 6-step process for systematically inventorying and evaluating all content assets, assigning each item an action (Keep/Update/Consolidate/Rewrite/Remove/Review), and producing a prioritized report.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>content-audit</tag>
      <tag>content-strategy</tag>
      <tag>inventory</tag>
      <tag>seo</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Content Audit Process</title>

    <summary>A structured 6-step process for systematically inventorying and evaluating all content assets, assigning each item an action (Keep/Update/Consolidate/Rewrite/Remove/Review), and producing a prioritized report. Triggers a crawler-based or manual inventory, applies multi-criteria scoring, and outputs concrete migration or cleanup recommendations.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without a systematic audit, content decisions are guesswork. The process surfaces stale content before migration, identifies duplicate coverage that dilutes SEO, and generates an evidence-based action list that stakeholders can prioritize. Running it before any redesign or platform migration prevents carrying over problems to the new system.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before a site migration or CMS switch — avoid importing bad content to the new platform.</item>
        <item>When SEO is underperforming and the cause is unclear — old or duplicate content may be to blame.</item>
        <item>When users report finding outdated information — audit scope starts at the affected content type.</item>
        <item>After significant product or pricing changes — detect pages that reference stale information.</item>
        <item>Annually as content governance to prevent slow decay.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>For a single-page or micro-site with fewer than 20 content items — a full audit adds overhead without payoff; a manual review suffices.</item>
        <item>When there is no plan to act on findings — audit data decays quickly; run only when there is owner commitment to execute the action list.</item>
        <item>Mid-sprint as a reactive measure — plan as a dedicated project with tooling and stakeholder buy-in.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="six-step-procedure">
      <p>The audit follows a structured six-step flow: scope, inventory, spreadsheet, evaluation, action assignment, reporting.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Separate inventory (what exists) from evaluation (what to do) — mixing them in one pass produces inconsistent results.</statement>
        <rationale>Inventory is fact-gathering; evaluation is judgment. Separating them ensures facts are complete before judgment is applied, and allows multiple evaluators to be calibrated on the same baseline.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Calibrate quality scoring with two reviewers on a sample of 20 items before the full audit — prevents scoring drift.</statement>
        <rationale>Without calibration, different reviewers apply criteria differently and the audit's scoring becomes subjective noise. A calibration pass on a sample ensures consistency across the full audit.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Anchor "keep" decisions to traffic thresholds and business goals, not opinion: define the threshold before starting the audit.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a threshold, decisions become opinion-based. Example: "keep if 50+ pageviews in past 90 days" is objective; "keep if it seems important" is not.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Assign a single owner to each "update" and "rewrite" action at report time — unassigned items are never done.</statement>
        <rationale>Findings without owners accumulate as spreadsheets without action. Ownership drives execution.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Scoped audit with clear scope">
        <description>Audit scope: help center (all articles tagged "billing" + all articles modified more than 18 months ago). Scope is bounded, measurable, and tied to a business goal (accuracy of billing info). Inventory of 47 articles. Evaluation criteria: accuracy, relevance to current product, word count, last update date. Report recommends: 12 keep, 15 update, 8 consolidate, 12 remove.</description>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Unbounded audit">
        <description>Audit scope: "everything on the website." Produces overwhelming spreadsheet of 1000+ rows. No clear owner. No timeline. Recommendations collect dust.</description>
        <note>Unbounded audits overwhelm and paralyze. Scope is the most important decision.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Running a large audit (1000+ pages) in one pass without chunking.</description>
        <reason>Large audits produce spreadsheets too large for a single agent context window; chunking is required. Also, large audits overwhelm stakeholders; smaller, focused audits per content type are easier to action.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Archive removed content to the trash without staging; broken inbound links surface within days, forcing emergency recovery.</description>
        <reason>Stage removed content to a holding environment first. Broken link patterns surface within 24–48 hours; if they are acceptable, then permanently delete. If not, restore without restoring all 1000 items.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A Claude subagent works well for the evaluation phase: given a batch of URLs with their titles, descriptions, word counts, and analytics metrics, the agent can apply the scoring rubric (accuracy, relevance, quality, SEO, accessibility) and return an action recommendation (keep/update/consolidate/rewrite/remove) with a rationale. Batch size should be capped at 50–100 items per agent call to keep context manageable. The crawl and inventory steps must be done with dedicated tools before the agent is invoked.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Agent context window limits batching: a 1000-page audit must be split into chunks of 50–100 rows with the rubric repeated per chunk.</statement>
        <rationale>Context window limits prevent overwhelm and allow agents to produce high-quality evaluations on smaller, focused sets.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Agents evaluate excerpts, not full pages — the excerpt must include the H1, first 200 words, and any key claims for the score to be meaningful.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents work best with bounded input; a 5000-word article should be abstracted to key claims rather than full text.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Agents do not have access to live analytics — pass pre-exported metrics as structured data in the prompt.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent cannot query GA4 directly; metrics must be pre-exported from your analytics platform and included in the prompt as JSON or CSV.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Quality and accuracy scores are inherently subjective; treat agent output as a first draft, not a final verdict.</statement>
        <rationale>Subjective scoring requires human validation. Agent output is input to human decision-makers, not the decision.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Consolidation recommendations require understanding which pages cover the same topic: agent needs a keyword or topic field to identify duplicates; URL and title alone are insufficient.</statement>
        <rationale>Without topic context, the agent cannot identify which pages are duplicates. Provide a topic or keyword field so the agent can cluster similar content.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Do not ask the agent to both evaluate and rewrite in one call — evaluation quality degrades when generation is mixed in.</statement>
        <rationale>Separate concerns: evaluation is analysis, rewriting is generation. Combining them dilutes both.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Structured evaluation prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a content auditor. For each URL below, evaluate the content against these criteria and return a JSON array.

Criteria (score 1–5):
- accuracy: Is the information current and factually correct based on the excerpt?
- relevance: Does it serve the target audience described?
- quality: Is it well-written, free of jargon, appropriately detailed?
- action: one of keep | update | consolidate | rewrite | remove

Input format: [{ url, title, meta_description, word_count, pageviews_90d, excerpt }]
Output format: [{ url, scores: { accuracy, relevance, quality }, action, rationale }]

Content batch: [JSON]
Target audience: [description]]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>Crawlers, analytics integrations, and content workflow platforms for audit execution.</p>

      <p>CLI tools for crawling and exporting content inventory:</p>
      <list>
        <item><term name="screaming-frog">Crawl site, export URL list with metadata. Desktop app / screamingfrog.co.uk</term></item>
        <item><term name="sitebulb">Crawl + visual audit reports. Desktop app / sitebulb.com</term></item>
        <item><term name="wget --spider">Lightweight recursive link discovery. Built-in on Linux; `wget --spider -r -nd -nv [URL]`</term></item>
        <item><term name="ahrefs-cli">Pull organic traffic data per URL (via API). ahrefs.com/api</term></item>
        <item><term name="ga4-cli">Export GA4 pageview data to CSV. `pip install ga4py` / Google Analytics Data API</term></item>
      </list>

      <p>Services for audit workflow and content management:</p>
      <list>
        <item><term name="Screaming Frog">SaaS/desktop, partial (CSV export). Agent reads export; cannot drive the UI.</term></item>
        <item><term name="ContentKing">SaaS, REST API. Real-time content monitoring; API returns page data.</term></item>
        <item><term name="Ahrefs">SaaS, REST API. Organic traffic, backlinks, top pages per domain.</term></item>
        <item><term name="Google Search Console">SaaS, API. Impressions, clicks, avg position per URL.</term></item>
        <item><term name="GatherContent">SaaS, REST API. Content workflow and migration planning.</term></item>
        <item><term name="Notion / Google Sheets">SaaS. Agent writes audit results to a shared spreadsheet via API.</term></item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Run the crawl at off-peak hours if the site has rate limiting or a CDN with aggressive bot detection.</item>
        <item>Archive removed content to a staging environment before deletion; broken inbound links surface within days.</item>
        <item>Automated crawlers miss gated content, dynamically rendered pages (JS SPAs), PDFs behind login, and content in iframes. Plan manual review for these.</item>
        <item>Analytics data from the past 90 days may not represent seasonal content performance; consider annual patterns.</item>
        <item>Audits surface problems but do not write the content — the remediation work is often underestimated by 3–5x.</item>
        <item>Large audits produce spreadsheets too large for a single agent context window; chunking (50–100 rows per agent call) is required.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/audit-spreadsheet.md" purpose="Column schema for the content inventory spreadsheet"/>
      <template path="templates/audit-report.md" purpose="Executive summary + findings report skeleton"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/content-audits/"/>
      <link href="https://www.contentharmony.com/blog/content-audit-guide/"/>
      <link href="https://developers.google.com/analytics/devguides/reporting/data/v1"/>
      <link href="https://www.contentkingapp.com/support/api/"/>
      <link href="https://gathercontent.com/content-strategy-toolkit"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
