<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solution Assessment — Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of Solution Assessment must enforce.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-four-stage-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run all four assessment types at distinct points: Design (pre-build), Implementation (mid-build), Deployment (go-live), Post-Implementation (30/60/90 days).</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 — Solution Evaluation">A single end-of-project assessment misses fixable implementation errors and lacks a value baseline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-primary-source-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every metric verdict MUST cite at least one evidence URL with retrieved_at timestamp; no verdicts from memory, screenshots, or verbal reports.</statement>
      <rationale source="evidence-based audit practice">Without primary-source citation, agents hallucinate KPI values and humans report the number that supports their preferred conclusion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-sample-size-guard" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every metric row includes sample size; a metric hit on n=12 is statistically inconclusive and may not be called 'Met'.</statement>
      <rationale source="statistical power analysis">Small samples produce variance indistinguishable from noise; underpowered 'success' verdicts waste follow-on investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-triangulation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Triangulate every business-value metric with at least two independent sources (analytics + finance, or analytics + survey).</statement>
      <rationale source="triangulation in mixed-methods research">Single-source verdicts are gameable; two independent sources must agree before a verdict is reliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-deprecated-not-failed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mark requirements as 'Deprecated' (not 'Not Met') when the underlying business need has changed since the requirement was written.</statement>
      <rationale source="requirements lifecycle theory">Forcing Met/Not Met on stale requirements produces misleading reports and penalises delivery teams unfairly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
