<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ADA Title II Compliance 2026 Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules anchoring the ada-title-ii-compliance-2026 methodology, each grounded in a source.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="doj-rule-target-2.1-AA" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conformance target MUST be WCAG 2.1 AA, NOT 2.2; the DOJ April 2024 final rule explicitly references 2.1 AA.</statement>
      <rationale source="28 CFR Part 35 — DOJ Title II rule April 2024">Legal text controls; aiming higher (2.2 AA) is acceptable practice but the audit MUST score against 2.1 AA to evidence Title II conformance.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="population-bucket-deadline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deadline MUST be set by jurisdiction population: April 24, 2026 (&gt;=50,000) OR April 26, 2027 (&lt;50,000). The report MUST state the bucket.</statement>
      <rationale source="DOJ Title II rule">Population-based deadlines are codified; missing the bucket invalidates the report.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="surface-scope-public-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conformance scope MUST cover all public-facing digital services (web, mobile apps, kiosks); internal-only employee systems MUST be excluded from the Title II scope.</statement>
      <rationale source="DOJ Title II rule">Title II scope is public-facing; including internal systems inflates the report unnecessarily, excluding them is a finding gap.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="evidence-not-attestation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conformance MUST be evidenced by a Stage 1-5 accessibility-evaluation audit; a written self-attestation without audit evidence MUST NOT be accepted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Legal precedent: post-rule guidance">Self-attestation has no defensible basis in litigation; audit evidence does.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="third-party-content-included" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Third-party widgets, fonts, embedded videos, and SaaS components hosted on public-facing surfaces MUST be in scope; vendor agreements MUST require WCAG 2.1 AA conformance.</statement>
      <rationale source="DOJ Title II rule + 2025 enforcement letters">DOJ rule does not exempt third-party content; excluding it is the most common compliance gap.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Skip-If preconditions hold, the methodology MUST be skipped and the caller routed to the linked alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="self">Applying this machinery to the wrong workflow burns tokens without producing a usable artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
