<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="RICE for One-Person Cheatsheet Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules reweight RICE for the solo operator and bind the result to a WIP-1 weekly bet inside the Sunday roadmap ritual.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement><strong>Reach</strong> is scored in absolute users or paying customers expected to be affected in the next 30 days, not as a normalised "% of MAU". At solo scale the relevant baselines are tens to a few hundred; using percentages collapses meaningful differences (5 users vs 50 users) into the same Reach=0.1 score.</statement>
      <rationale source="RICE assumes a team's reach baseline; solo builders need adjusted weighting">For a SaaS with 80 active users, "affects 20" is huge and "affects 2" is trivial — both look like 0.x in a percentage scheme. Absolute counts preserve the signal that drives a solo builder's revenue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement><strong>Impact</strong> is forced to a 4-step ladder tied to revenue or retention, not vibes: 3 = item is on the activation or conversion path of a paying segment; 2 = item materially improves retention of existing payers (churn, NPS); 1 = item improves operator efficiency or product polish; 0.25 = nice-to-have, no revenue path. Every Impact score in the backlog must cite the segment or metric that justifies its level.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo builder Impact must be revenue-anchored; vibes inflate everything to 2-3">Without a forced ladder, the operator's own enthusiasm puts every item at Impact 3 and the ranking collapses. The revenue-or-retention anchor is the only thing that survives the solo founder's bias for the next shiny thing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement><strong>Confidence</strong> is collapsed to three discrete levels: H = 1.0 (you have direct evidence — paying users asked for this, or a measured drop-off pinpoints the cause), M = 0.6 (informed inference — analogous case studies, related but indirect evidence), L = 0.3 (guess — no evidence yet). Fractional self-grading ("70% confident") is forbidden; the operator must commit to one of the three.</statement>
      <rationale source="Confidence at solo scale becomes vibes without discrete buckets">"75% confident" is indistinguishable from "70%" and both are usually masked guesses. Three buckets force the operator to either find evidence (move to H) or admit it's a guess (drop to L), which changes the ranking.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement><strong>Effort</strong> is scored in solo dev-days (8 focused hours = 1 day), not dev-weeks, and is multiplied by a context-switch tax of 1.3 if the item requires switching across more than two of: codebase, infra, marketing surface, customer support. The tax converts "looks like 2 days" into "actually 2.6 days" when the work crosses domains the solo operator owns alone.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo builder is the bottleneck; dev-weeks blur the single-person cost">A team can parallelise across roles; a solo operator pays a real context-switch tax that dev-weeks hides. Scoring in days and surfacing the tax keeps the operator from cheerfully under-estimating cross-domain work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement><strong>WIP-1 framing:</strong> at the Sunday roadmap ritual the operator computes RICE = (Reach × Impact × Confidence) / Effort for every backlog item, ranks the list, and commits to the top-1 as the only bet of the week. Items 2-N are visible but not started. If the top-1 is blocked mid-week, the operator picks up item 2 — never both at once. Multi-bet weeks are explicitly forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo builder Sunday roadmap needs WIP-1 framing, not a stack of parallel work">A ranked list without a WIP cap turns into a parallel-work fantasy; the solo operator starts three items and finishes none. WIP-1 converts the same ranking into actual shipping, which is the whole point.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical example">
    <example type="good" title="Sunday ritual for an 80-user solo SaaS">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Backlog after solo-adjusted RICE:

  Item                              Reach Impact Conf  Effort  RICE
  ─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
  Stripe failed-payment recovery     12     3    1.0    2.0d   18.0
  Bulk export of invoices             6     2    1.0    1.0d   12.0
  Marketing-site rewrite             80     1    0.6    5.2d    9.2
                                                (1.3 tax — codebase+marketing)
  New onboarding video                3     2    0.3    1.5d    1.2
  Refactor billing module             8     1    0.6    4.0d    1.2

WIP-1 commitment:
  Week-bet: Stripe failed-payment recovery (RICE 18.0)
  All other items deferred. If Stripe item blocks on a vendor support
  ticket, fall back to Bulk export — not both.

Justifications for audit:
  Reach 12: based on Stripe dashboard, 12 of 80 active users had a failed
   charge in the last 30d.
  Impact 3: payment-recovery is directly on the conversion-of-paying path.
  Confidence 1.0: H — three users emailed about it last week.
  Effort 2.0d: no context tax — single codebase, no marketing change.
]]></code>
      <note>The single weekly bet is now defensible against the operator's own enthusiasm; deferred items remain visible without splitting attention.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
