<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-operations" title="Terraform State Operations">
  <summary>State commands reference, import and moved blocks, force-replace, unlock procedures, and remote state data sources.</summary>

  <section title="Import Blocks (Terraform 1.5+)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use import blocks in .tf files instead of terraform import CLI commands for all new import work; import blocks are reviewable, version-controlled, and run as part of terraform plan.</statement>
      <rationale>CLI import runs immediately with no plan preview. Import blocks show the planned import in terraform plan output, allowing review before apply. They are also idempotent — already-imported resources are ignored.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="hcl"><![CDATA[
import {
  to = aws_vpc.main
  id = "vpc-12345678"
}

import {
  to = aws_subnet.public[0]
  id = "subnet-11111111"
}
]]></code>
    </example>
    <note>After writing import blocks, run: terraform plan -generate-config-out=generated.tf to auto-generate the resource configuration for imported resources.</note>
  </section>

  <section title="Moved Blocks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use moved blocks (Terraform 1.1+) to rename resources or move them to modules without touching the state directly; keep moved blocks in the configuration until all users have applied.</statement>
      <rationale>moved blocks express refactoring declaratively in code. They are visible in plan output, can be reviewed, and avoid the error-prone manual state mv commands.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="hcl"><![CDATA[
moved {
  from = aws_instance.web
  to   = aws_instance.app_server
}

moved {
  from = aws_instance.web
  to   = module.compute.aws_instance.main
}
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="State Commands">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before any manual state operation, backup state with terraform state pull > backup.tfstate; verify the backup; communicate with the team to prevent concurrent modifications.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual state operations are irreversible without a backup. Remote backends have locking but do not protect against logical errors in state commands.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <note>Key state commands: terraform state list (view all resources), terraform state show addr (inspect), terraform state mv src dst (rename), terraform state rm addr (unmanage), terraform state pull/push (download/upload).</note>
    <rule>
      <statement>After any state operation, run terraform plan to verify the state reflects reality with no unexpected changes or diffs.</statement>
      <rationale>State commands can leave gaps between state and actual infrastructure. A clean plan (exit code 0) confirms consistency.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Force-Replace and Unlock">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use terraform apply -replace=resource.name to force replacement of a specific resource; never use terraform taint (deprecated since 0.15.2).</statement>
      <rationale>-replace is explicit, requires an apply confirmation, and shows the replacement in plan output. taint modifies state without a plan preview.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use terraform force-unlock LOCK_ID only after confirming no other apply is running; diagnose the lock cause before unlocking — a crash leaves a stale lock, not an active process.</statement>
      <rationale>Unlocking while an apply is running allows two concurrent applies, which corrupts state. force-unlock is a recovery tool, not a workaround for slow pipelines.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using terraform state push to overwrite remote state without a backup or plan verification.</description>
      <reason>Push overwrites the remote state immediately. If the pushed state is incorrect, there is no automatic rollback — you must recover from versioning.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
