<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-checklist" title="Terraform State Pre-Deployment Checklist">
  <summary>Backend setup, security, import process, migration, disaster recovery, and CI/CD integration checklists.</summary>

  <section title="Backend Setup">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create state infrastructure first (S3 bucket with versioning + KMS, DynamoDB table with prevent_destroy, IAM policy); then configure backend block; then run terraform init -migrate-state if migrating from local.</statement>
      <rationale>Infrastructure must exist before backend initialization. Migration prompt during init copies local state to the remote backend atomically.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate state files by environment (dev/staging/prod) AND by component (networking/compute/database); use the key pattern {env}/{component}/terraform.tfstate.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-state monorepo configurations have large blast radius — one mistake can destroy all production infrastructure. Component separation limits each apply's scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="State Security">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable encryption at rest (SSE-KMS), block all public access, enable access logging, and restrict bucket policy to Terraform CI/CD roles only.</statement>
      <rationale>State files contain passwords and private keys. Encryption protects data at rest; access restrictions limit who can read those secrets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark all sensitive outputs (passwords, connection strings, private keys) with sensitive = true; audit state for accidentally committed plaintext secrets quarterly.</statement>
      <rationale>sensitive = true suppresses output in plan/apply logs. Regular audits catch cases where sensitive data was inadvertently written to state.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Import Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write import blocks and matching resource configuration first; run terraform plan to preview the import; run terraform apply; then run terraform plan again to verify no drift.</statement>
      <rationale>A clean second plan (no changes) confirms the imported resource configuration exactly matches actual cloud state. Any diff indicates missing arguments.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Disaster Recovery">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable versioning on state buckets; set lifecycle policy to expire non-current versions after 90 days; document state file locations for all environments; test recovery quarterly.</statement>
      <rationale>Versioning is the only rollback mechanism for corrupted state. Untested recovery procedures fail under incident pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="CI/CD Integration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use OIDC authentication for CI/CD cloud provider access instead of static IAM access keys; set TF_IN_AUTOMATION=true in pipeline environments; implement plan/apply separation with human review.</statement>
      <rationale>OIDC eliminates long-lived static credentials that can be leaked. TF_IN_AUTOMATION suppresses interactive prompts. Plan/apply separation requires human approval before production changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Storing backend credentials (AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID, AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY) as static CI secrets.</description>
      <reason>Static keys never expire and are frequently leaked in CI logs. OIDC short-lived tokens are scoped to the specific workflow run and expire immediately after.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
