<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="methodologies-detail">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Catalog of 12 enterprise BA frameworks covering governance, communication, elicitation, maintenance, impact analysis, state analysis, and solution evaluation. Includes 50-technique reference.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>babok</tag>
      <tag>frameworks</tag>
      <tag>methodologies</tag>
      <tag>techniques</tag>
      <tag>enterprise</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>BA Methodologies Detail</title>

    <summary>A catalog of 12 enterprise BA frameworks used in BABOK Knowledge Areas 1-6: governance, communication planning, elicitation preparation, requirements maintenance, change impact analysis, current state analysis, future state definition, risk analysis, change strategy planning, requirements architecture, solution options analysis, and solution limitation assessment. Also includes the BABOK 50-technique reference table. Use this as a routing index — classify the user request into one or more of the 12 frameworks, then load content and apply the appropriate template.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Enterprise BA engagements require explicit decision-making processes (governance), communication strategies, structured state analysis, and scored option comparisons. Without a catalog, agents pick the familiar framework (usually requirements modeling from KA-5) and skip governance, communication, and strategy frameworks that have equal importance but lower LLM visibility. The 50-technique table provides a controlled vocabulary for technique selection.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Project kickoff: selecting which of the 12 BA frameworks to run for this initiative.</item>
        <item>Mid-project routing: mapping a stakeholder question to the right BABOK technique before drafting a deliverable.</item>
        <item>Audit or handover: producing a BA artifact inventory showing which frameworks were applied and which are missing.</item>
        <item>Training a new analyst or agent on the catalog of techniques and their fit.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>A single well-scoped deliverable with a known framework — go directly to the dedicated methodology folder.</item>
        <item>Lightweight startup or single-feature work — the 12-framework set assumes enterprise or multi-stakeholder context.</item>
        <item>Pure agile teams with story mapping and backlog grooming — governance, change control, and requirements architecture frameworks often duplicate Scrum ceremonies.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="ba-frameworks">
      <p>Twelve BA frameworks: purpose, four-step process, and template structure for each. Governance through solution limitation assessment.</p>

      <section name="governance-framework">
        <p>1. Governance Framework</p>
        <p>Purpose: establish decision-making processes for requirements. Defines who can approve, who can escalate, and how changes are controlled.</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Define decision rights, change control process, prioritization rules, and approval documentation before any requirements are baselined.</statement>
          <rationale>Without governance, scope changes are approved ad hoc and no one can explain why a requirement was added or removed; audit trails collapse.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <reference path="templates/governance-framework.md">Decision authority matrix and change control process template</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="communication-planning">
        <p>2. Communication Planning</p>
        <p>Purpose: ensure effective communication of BA information to the right audiences in the right format and frequency.</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Identify audience, information need, format, frequency, and channel for each stakeholder group before the project begins. Validate the plan at each phase.</statement>
          <rationale>Without a communication plan, critical information reaches the wrong people at the wrong time; sponsors get developer-level detail and developers get executive summaries.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <reference path="templates/communication-plan.md">Audience matrix and key messages template</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="elicitation-preparation">
        <p>3. Elicitation Preparation</p>
        <p>Purpose: prepare effectively for elicitation activities by defining scope, selecting techniques, and preparing materials before sessions begin.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Define scope — what information is needed, what decisions will be made, what is out of scope.</item>
          <item>Select techniques — match technique to information type and stakeholder preferences.</item>
          <item>Prepare logistics — schedule sessions, book resources, prepare environment.</item>
          <item>Create materials — question guides, visual aids, prototypes or mockups.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="requirements-maintenance">
        <p>4. Requirements Maintenance</p>
        <p>Purpose: keep requirements accurate and useful over the full project lifecycle through version control, attribute management, and periodic quality monitoring.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Version control — baseline management, change history tracking.</item>
          <item>Attribute management — status (draft/approved/implemented), priority, owner, source.</item>
          <item>Quality monitoring — periodic reviews, consistency checks, completeness validation.</item>
          <item>Archival strategy — when to archive, what to retain, access policies.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="change-impact-analysis">
        <p>5. Change Impact Analysis</p>
        <p>Purpose: assess the scope, effort, risk, and stakeholder impact of a proposed requirement change before it is approved or rejected.</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Complete all five impact dimensions — scope, effort, risk, stakeholder impact, and decision support — before recommending accept, reject, or defer.</statement>
          <rationale>Partial impact analysis leads to under-scoped change requests; effort or risk assessments without the other dimensions produce recommendations that surprise the team at implementation time.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <reference path="templates/change-impact.md">Change impact analysis template with scope, effort, risks, recommendation</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="current-state-analysis">
        <p>6. Current State Analysis</p>
        <p>Purpose: understand the existing environment — business context, capabilities, technology landscape, stakeholders, and pain points — before defining the future state.</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Require a context-loading step (document analysis, transcript ingest) before running any current-state framework. An agent cannot produce a valid SWOT for a company it knows nothing about.</statement>
          <rationale>LLMs generate plausible-but-wrong current-state descriptions when no ground truth is provided; hallucinated baselines produce strategies that address problems the organization does not have.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <reference path="templates/current-state.md">Current state assessment: business context, capability assessment, SWOT</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="future-state-definition">
        <p>7. Future State Definition</p>
        <p>Purpose: define the desired future state through vision statement, SMART goals, required capabilities, success metrics, and constraints.</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Every success metric must have a baseline value and a target value. Metrics without baselines cannot prove improvement.</statement>
          <rationale>Agents fabricate plausible industry-standard KPIs when not required to cite sources; require a datasource path for every metric and reject metrics without baselines.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <reference path="templates/future-state.md">Future state vision: goals, capability roadmap, constraints, assumptions</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="risk-analysis">
        <p>8. Risk Analysis</p>
        <p>Purpose: identify and assess risks to the change initiative using probability-impact scoring and define response strategies.</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Attach an evidence column to every risk (incident history, expert judgment, similar project, none). Reject high-impact risks with evidence: none in reviews.</statement>
          <rationale>Probability and impact scores without evidence are guesses; agents consistently assign P/I scores based on plausibility rather than evidence, producing a risk register that looks complete but contains no actionable signal.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <reference path="templates/risk-register.md">Risk register with probability, impact, score, response, owner</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="change-strategy-planning">
        <p>9. Change Strategy Planning</p>
        <p>Purpose: develop the optimal approach for achieving the future state through gap analysis, solution options, transition planning, readiness assessment, and business case.</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Map every identified gap to a named solution option before scoring options. Options not mapped to gaps are feature proposals, not strategy.</statement>
          <rationale>Solution options analysis without explicit gap linkage produces a preference list rather than a strategy; the recommendation becomes subjective rather than traceable to the change rationale.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <reference path="templates/change-strategy.md">Gap analysis, solution options, and transition roadmap template</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="requirements-architecture">
        <p>10. Requirements Architecture</p>
        <p>Purpose: organize requirements into a coherent structure through viewpoints (business/user/technical/operational), decomposition hierarchy, dependency mapping, and completeness check.</p>
        <reference path="templates/requirements-architecture.md">Viewpoints, requirement hierarchy, and dependency table template</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="solution-options-analysis">
        <p>11. Solution Options Analysis</p>
        <p>Purpose: evaluate and recommend the best solution option using weighted criteria scoring across strategic fit, technical feasibility, cost, time to value, and risk.</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Calibrate scoring weights with human stakeholders before the agent applies them. Return recommendation as PENDING_HUMAN_REVIEW until explicit go-ahead is given.</statement>
          <rationale>Agents score every option 3-4 to appear neutral, destroying discriminating power. The 25/20/20/20/15 default weights are illustrative; sponsors must declare their actual weights before the scores are meaningful.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <reference path="templates/solution-options.md">Weighted scoring matrix and recommendation template</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="solution-limitation-assessment">
        <p>12. Solution Limitation Assessment</p>
        <p>Purpose: identify and address current solution limitations through defect identification, root cause analysis, impact assessment, and remediation options evaluation.</p>
        <reference path="templates/solution-limitations.md">Limitation identification, root cause, impact, and remediation template</reference>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="babok-50-techniques">
      <p>BABOK 50 Techniques Reference</p>
      <p>BABOK 50-technique lookup table mapping each technique to its primary use cases across the six knowledge areas.</p>

      <section name="technique-lookup-table">
        <p>Technique Lookup Table</p>
        <rule>
          <statement>Select at most three techniques per request and require a one-sentence justification per technique. Do not apply brainstorming to every input.</statement>
          <rationale>Agents default to brainstorming (technique 5) for every request because it appears early and frequently in training data. Constraining to three techniques with justification forces alignment between the information need and the technique's actual purpose.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>1. Acceptance and Evaluation Criteria — requirements validation, UAT design.</item>
          <item>2. Backlog Management — agile requirements lifecycle.</item>
          <item>3. Balanced Scorecard — strategy analysis, KA-4.</item>
          <item>4. Benchmarking and Market Analysis — current state analysis.</item>
          <item>5. Brainstorming — elicitation, idea generation.</item>
          <item>6. Business Capability Analysis — strategy analysis, KA-4.</item>
          <item>7. Business Cases — change strategy, KA-4.</item>
          <item>8. Business Model Canvas — strategy analysis, KA-4.</item>
          <item>9. Business Rules Analysis — requirements analysis, KA-5.</item>
          <item>10. Collaborative Games — elicitation, KA-2.</item>
          <item>11. Concept Modelling — requirements modeling, KA-5.</item>
          <item>12. Data Dictionary — data requirements, KA-5.</item>
          <item>13. Data Flow Diagrams — process analysis, KA-5.</item>
          <item>14. Data Mining — analysis, KA-5 and KA-6.</item>
          <item>15. Data Modelling — data requirements, KA-5.</item>
          <item>16. Decision Analysis — solution evaluation, KA-6.</item>
          <item>17. Decision Modelling — business rules, KA-5.</item>
          <item>18. Document Analysis — elicitation, KA-2.</item>
          <item>19. Estimation — planning, KA-1.</item>
          <item>20. Financial Analysis — business case, KA-4.</item>
          <item>21. Focus Groups — elicitation, KA-2.</item>
          <item>22. Functional Decomposition — requirements architecture, KA-5.</item>
          <item>23. Glossary — communication, KA-2.</item>
          <item>24. Interface Analysis — requirements analysis, KA-5.</item>
          <item>25. Interviews — elicitation, KA-2.</item>
          <item>26. Item Tracking — requirements management, KA-3.</item>
          <item>27. Lessons Learned — improvement, KA-1 and KA-6.</item>
          <item>28. Metrics and KPIs — performance measurement, KA-6.</item>
          <item>29. Mind Mapping — elicitation and analysis, KA-2 and KA-5.</item>
          <item>30. Non-Functional Requirements Analysis — requirements analysis, KA-5.</item>
          <item>31. Observation — elicitation, KA-2.</item>
          <item>32. Organizational Modelling — current state, KA-4.</item>
          <item>33. Prioritization — requirements management, KA-3.</item>
          <item>34. Process Analysis — current state, KA-4.</item>
          <item>35. Process Modelling — requirements modeling, KA-5.</item>
          <item>36. Prototyping — elicitation and validation, KA-2 and KA-5.</item>
          <item>37. Reviews — verification, KA-5.</item>
          <item>38. Risk Analysis and Management — strategy and evaluation, KA-4 and KA-6.</item>
          <item>39. Roles and Permissions Matrix — requirements analysis, KA-5.</item>
          <item>40. Root Cause Analysis — problem analysis, KA-4.</item>
          <item>41. Scope Modelling — strategy analysis, KA-4.</item>
          <item>42. Sequence Diagrams — requirements modeling, KA-5.</item>
          <item>43. Stakeholder List, Map, or Personas — stakeholder analysis, KA-1.</item>
          <item>44. State Modelling — requirements modeling, KA-5.</item>
          <item>45. Survey or Questionnaire — elicitation, KA-2.</item>
          <item>46. SWOT Analysis — current state, KA-4.</item>
          <item>47. Use Cases and Scenarios — requirements modeling, KA-5.</item>
          <item>48. User Stories — agile requirements, KA-3 and KA-5.</item>
          <item>49. Vendor Assessment — solution evaluation, KA-6.</item>
          <item>50. Workshops — elicitation, KA-2.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/governance-framework.md" purpose="Decision authority matrix and change control process template."/>
      <template path="templates/communication-plan.md" purpose="Audience matrix and key messages template."/>
      <template path="templates/change-impact.md" purpose="Change impact analysis template: scope, effort, risks, recommendation."/>
      <template path="templates/current-state.md" purpose="Current state assessment: business context, capability assessment, SWOT."/>
      <template path="templates/future-state.md" purpose="Future state vision: goals, capability roadmap, constraints, assumptions."/>
      <template path="templates/risk-register.md" purpose="Risk register with probability, impact, score, response, and owner."/>
      <template path="templates/change-strategy.md" purpose="Gap analysis, solution options comparison, and transition roadmap template."/>
      <template path="templates/requirements-architecture.md" purpose="Viewpoints, requirement hierarchy, and dependency table template."/>
      <template path="templates/solution-options.md" purpose="Weighted scoring matrix and recommendation template."/>
      <template path="templates/solution-limitations.md" purpose="Limitation identification, root cause, impact, and remediation template."/>
    </templates>

    <section name="agentic-workflow-patterns">
      <p>Treat the 12 frameworks as a dispatch tree. A planner agent classifies the inbound request into one or more frameworks, then dispatches per-framework subagents where dependencies allow. Always commit the framework classification to a memory file before dispatch — downstream agents read it instead of re-classifying.</p>
      <p>Default sequencing for a greenfield engagement: KA-1 → KA-4 → KA-2 → KA-5 (model) → KA-3 (prioritize and approve) → KA-5 (design) → build → KA-6.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Classify every BA request into one or more frameworks before generating any deliverable. Use the framework classification as shared state that all downstream agents read — never re-classify per task.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping the classification step causes agents to pick the familiar framework (usually requirements modeling) and skip governance, communication, and strategy frameworks that have equal importance but lower LLM visibility.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="known-limitations-and-gotchas">
      <p>BABOK is artifact-heavy. LLMs over-produce structure (10-page docs for a 3-feature MVP). Force scope before generation.</p>
      <p>KA-3 (Lifecycle) requires a system of record (Jira/Linear/ADO). An agent without write access can only emit drafts; traceability matrices stay stale unless wired to the issue tracker.</p>
      <p>KA-4 (Strategy) needs ground truth about current state (org chart, KPIs, capability map). LLMs hallucinate plausible-but-wrong baselines without a document source.</p>
      <p>KA-6 (Solution Evaluation) needs telemetry. No metrics → agent invents metrics. Block this branch unless an analytics datasource is attached.</p>
      <p>LLMs default to KA-5 (modelling) on any input. Fight this — most real failures are KA-1 (no stakeholder map) or KA-3 (no traceability). Make the planner explicitly score all 6 KAs.</p>
      <p>Agents will fabricate "industry standard" KPIs in KA-6. Require a citation or a datasource path for every metric; reject otherwise.</p>
      <p>BABOK terminology collides with agile terminology (e.g. "requirement" vs "story", "stakeholder" vs "persona"). Pin a glossary in the agent's system prompt — drift causes traceability errors when artifacts cross teams.</p>
      <p>Verification (KA-5) is not Validation (KA-5). Two separate tasks. Do not let one prompt produce both — they require different mental modes (quality vs business fit) and a single pass usually does neither well.</p>
      <p>Multi-agent runs across KAs duplicate stakeholder lists. Centralise stakeholder register in one file referenced by all KA agents — never let each agent maintain its own copy.</p>
      <p>KA-3 traceability matrices require stable IDs. If your agent assigns IDs at generation time, they renumber on every run. Use content-hash IDs or pull IDs from the issue tracker before drafting.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Classify before generating. Skipping the framework-routing step makes agents draft requirements specifications when the actual gap is governance planning or communication strategy.</p>
      <p>Persist the classification (e.g. in .aidocs/ba-routing.json) so re-runs converge instead of reclassifying and producing inconsistent guidance across runs.</p>
      <p>For KA-3 (Change Impact Analysis), never let an agent both author and approve a change in the same run — split into author and reviewer agents with different prompts.</p>
      <p>All framework outputs should emit machine-readable artifacts (JSON, BPMN XML, decision tables) alongside the human prose. Prose-only output breaks downstream traceability.</p>
      <p>Use the BABOK competency table (analytical/behavioural/business/communication/interaction) as a tag set for prompt routing — e.g. tasks tagged interaction:facilitation go to the brainstorm skill rather than a solo agent.</p>
      <p>Cap each framework artifact to a hard line budget. KA-1 plan ≤ 200 lines, KA-4 strategy ≤ 300, KA-5 spec ≤ 500 per epic. Without caps LLMs balloon docs.</p>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="knowledge-areas-overview"/>
      <ref slug="knowledge-areas-detail"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
