<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Scope Creep Prevention on Hourly Engagements Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Scope Creep Prevention on Hourly Engagements application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-weekly-budget-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Contract states a weekly budget (e.g., 20 hours/week). When budget exhausted, work pauses until next week OR explicit overage approval.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Without explicit weekly gate, hourly engagement becomes uncapped; gate is the safety valve.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-billable-vs-non-billable-taxonomy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document which activities are billable: heads-down work, meetings, written async. Non-billable: brief 'quick question' Slack, ad-hoc check-ins under 5 min.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Without taxonomy, freelancers either under-bill (resentment) or over-bill (client surprise); explicit list prevents both.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-async-approval-before-work" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any new task &gt;2h estimated requires written confirmation BEFORE work starts. Verbal approval doesn't count.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Verbal asks get re-litigated at invoice; written approval is the legal anchor.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-weekly-summary-with-hours" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>End of each week: send hours-spent summary by task. Surprises minimized when summary is weekly, not monthly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Monthly summaries surprise; weekly creates rhythm + no-surprise norm.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-overage-policy-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If client wants overage, options: (a) bump hourly rate temporarily, (b) defer to next week, (c) hire more freelancers. Choice in client's hands.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Without explicit overage policy, freelancers absorb overage as unbilled work; policy preserves margin.</rationale>
    </rule>

  
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If all Applies-If preconditions hold and no Skip-If disqualifier is present, execute the full procedure from `04-procedure.xml` and commit the artefact described in `02-output-contract.xml`.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's affirmative leaf; pairs the preconditions with the methodology's commit path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Skip-If condition is present (one-shot, &lt;3 instances/year, regulator override, missing owner), do NOT apply this methodology. Route to the sibling/upstream methodology named in `AGENTS.md` Related section.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's skip leaf; prevents over-application of a heavyweight artefact when the loop conditions do not hold.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>