<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="System Status Visibility: Principles and Response Time Rules">
  <summary>Response time thresholds, feedback type selection per duration, loading/success/error state requirements, and state indicator patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Response Time Thresholds">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide visible feedback within 100ms of any user action. For operations taking 1-3s use a spinner. For 3-10s use a progress indicator. For over 10s use a determinate progress bar with percentage and a cancel option.</statement>
      <rationale>NNG research (Miller/Card/Newell) establishes empirical thresholds: under 0.1s feels instantaneous; under 1s users notice the delay but stay engaged; over 10s users lose focus and need continuous feedback to stay. Cancel option over 10s respects user autonomy — they should not be trapped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use skeleton screens instead of spinners when loading content into a known layout. Skeleton screens set accurate spatial expectations and reduce perceived wait time for list and feed content.</statement>
      <rationale>Spinners communicate only "something is loading" without spatial context. Skeleton screens show where content will appear, allowing users to orient themselves during load. They consistently reduce perceived load time in user studies.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Three Required States Per Interactive Element">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every button, form, and link triggering an async operation must implement three states: loading (element disabled + visual indicator), success (confirmation message or visual change), and error (error message with recovery action).</statement>
      <rationale>Missing any one state creates confusion: no loading state causes double-submission; no success state leaves users uncertain the action worked; no error state creates a dead end. All three are required for async operations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Disable the trigger element (button, link) immediately on click during async operations. Re-enable on success or error. Never leave the element active during processing.</statement>
      <rationale>An active button during processing invites repeated clicks. Duplicate form submissions, duplicate payments, and duplicate data creation are direct consequences of missing disabled state. This is also an ARIA requirement (aria-busy).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="State Indicator Patterns">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Inline button state transitions for form submit</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Idle:    [Save]
Loading: [Saving...] (disabled, spinner icon)
Success: [Saved ✓]   (briefly, then returns to [Save])
Error:   error message appears near form with [Retry]
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Document auto-save status (continuous operation)</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Draft"           — unsaved changes exist
"Saving..."       — write in progress
"All changes saved" — current state persisted
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Connection status indicators for real-time features</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Green dot:  Online
Yellow dot: Connecting... (with auto-retry)
Red dot:    Offline — [Retry] [Work Offline]
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Auto-Dismiss Timing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Success toast notifications: auto-dismiss after 3-5 seconds. Error notifications: require manual dismissal — users must read and act on errors; auto-dismiss hides them before they can.</statement>
      <rationale>Success confirmations are informational; missing them is acceptable. Error messages are actionable; auto-dismissing them before the user reads them creates a state where the user does not know what failed or how to fix it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use aria-busy="true" on loading elements. Use aria-live="polite" for non-critical status updates (success toasts). Use aria-live="assertive" only for critical errors requiring immediate attention. Use role="status" for persistent status regions.</statement>
      <rationale>Screen readers do not perceive visual changes to spinners or state transitions. ARIA live regions announce changes to screen reader users. Polite announcements wait for the user to finish their current task; assertive interrupts — use assertive sparingly to avoid disruptive announcements.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
