<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="System Status Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete good patterns for file upload, form submission, and real-time status; antipatterns that cause double-submission and user abandonment.</summary>

  <section title="Good Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>File upload — complete status lifecycle</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Step 1: Click "Upload" → button shows "Uploading..." (disabled)
Step 2: Progress bar appears: "45% — 2.3 MB of 5.1 MB"
Step 3: Speed shown: "1.2 MB/s"
Step 4: Complete → checkmark + "Upload complete" toast
Step 5: Error → "Upload failed: file too large. Maximum is 10 MB." + [Retry]
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Form submission — button state with error recovery</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Click "Submit":
  → button disabled + spinner shown
  → [Success] green banner: "Form submitted successfully"
  → [Error] red banner: "Submission failed. Please check your connection." + [Try Again]
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No loading state: user clicks button, nothing visible happens, user clicks again</description>
      <reason>Without loading state, users cannot tell if their click registered. Repeated clicks cause duplicate form submissions, duplicate API calls, or duplicate payments. The loading state is the signal that the click was received.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Vague status messages: "Please wait...", "Processing...", "Loading..."</description>
      <reason>Duration-free, content-free status messages give users no information to judge whether the wait is acceptable. "Uploading 3 of 5 files" is infinitely more useful than "Processing..."</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Progress bar showing fake/frozen progress (0% → 100% in one jump, or stuck at 99%)</description>
      <reason>Progress bars showing inaccurate progress erode trust more than no progress bar at all. Only use determinate progress bars when the backend provides real progress events. Otherwise use an indeterminate spinner.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Success toast auto-dismissing before user can read it; error toast also auto-dismissing</description>
      <reason>Auto-dismiss on success is acceptable (3-5s is enough). Auto-dismiss on error is never acceptable — users must be able to read the error and act on it. Errors require manual dismissal.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using aria-live="assertive" for routine status updates (e.g., "Changes saved")</description>
      <reason>Assertive live regions interrupt the screen reader immediately, regardless of what the user is doing. Using assertive for non-critical status announcements disrupts users unnecessarily. Reserve assertive for actual errors requiring immediate response.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Measurement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track rage clicks and dead clicks in session recording tools (LogRocket, FullStory) as the primary signal for missing loading states. Duplicate API submissions in server logs are a secondary signal.</statement>
      <rationale>Rage clicks directly indicate user frustration from unresponsive elements. Dead clicks on inactive areas indicate confusion. Both signal missing or invisible feedback states that users are trying to trigger.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
