<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Contractor Audition Rubric Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Contractor Audition Rubric application must enforce. Hard rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-bound-scope" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply Contractor Audition Rubric only to a single instance of the upstream playbook task. Never batch multiple unrelated decisions through one pass.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-conflation pattern — faion-network skill-authoring docs">Batching turns a 1-decision artefact into a debate club. Each instance gets its own record so the rationale is traceable per case.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-typed-input" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every input field has a declared type and a named source (path / URL / artefact id). Free-form prose without a source citation is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-first artefacts — F-066 spec">Untyped inputs let LLMs hallucinate plausible-but-wrong values. Typed + sourced inputs make the output falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The output names a single accountable owner (handle, email, or org role). No `team`, `we`, `us`, or `engineering` as the owner value.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI / single-throat-to-choke — internal PM playbook">Plural ownership = no ownership. Future readers need a named human to chase when the artefact is stale.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-versioned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output carries semver version and `last_reviewed` ISO date. Records older than 90 days without review must be flagged on read.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice — internal audit Q1 2026">Methodology outputs decay; treating them as immutable is a defect. Versioning + review-by-date forces refresh cadence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-input-citations" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The `rationale` field cites at least one input artefact by name; the `inputs_used` list is non-empty unless decision == `no-op`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Hallucination-mitigation — F-066 contract design">Decisions made without a citation chain cannot be audited or reversed safely. Citations bind the output to its evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
