<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agency Cashflow Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `Agency Cashflow Management` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="deposit-floor-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every new engagement MUST require a non-refundable deposit ≥ 30% of contract value before kickoff. Deposit floor below this voids the engagement at sales review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Micro-agency cashflow audit 2024-2026">Deposits below 30% leave the agency funding the engagement; floor is the single most reliable runway protection.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="milestone-payable-on-acceptance" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Milestone invoices MUST issue within 24h of acceptance and carry net-7 terms with named approver per milestone. No bundled-end invoicing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal AR-age analysis">Bundled invoicing balloons AR-age; per-milestone net-7 keeps AR inside the contractor-payable window.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="contractor-payable-window-mapped" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Contractor outflow dates MUST be mapped against expected client inflow dates in the artefact, with a documented bridge action (line of credit, deferred contractor terms, deposit acceleration) when the gap exceeds 30 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps Foundation cashflow patterns">Un-bridged gaps cause emergency credit-card runs; explicit mapping forces the bridge action to be chosen before crisis.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="late-payment-escalation-tiered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Late-payment escalation MUST be a tiered policy (day-1 reminder, day-7 manager call, day-14 work-stop, day-30 collections) with a single named owner per tier. Group handles forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal collections audit">Ad-hoc collections take 60-90 days; tiered escalation lands payment in 14-21 days on average.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="60-day-forecast-rolling" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The artefact MUST contain a rolling 60-day cashflow forecast (weekly granularity) reviewed weekly by the named owner, with variance log per row when actual diverges by &gt; 15%.</statement>
      <rationale source="Agency cashflow postmortem corpus">Forecasts beyond 60 days hallucinate inflows; weekly review with variance-log keeps the forecast honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>