<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Private-Beta / Design-Partner Cohort Recruitment Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Private-Beta / Design-Partner Cohort Recruitment application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="vetted-entry" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every partner is vetted against the criteria list before NDA signature. Members who fail a criterion are declined with a named reason; no 'roster-fillers'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cohort hygiene practice">An unvetted member dilutes signal and inflates cohort cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="signed-expectations" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each partner signs the expectations contract (NDA + cadence + exit ramp). Verbal commitments are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Commitment discipline">Verbal commitments evaporate; signed contracts give the cohort review-time leverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cadence-tracked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cadence attendance is tracked per partner. Two consecutive misses triggers the exit-ramp review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cohort-management literature">Dead-weight partners inflate engagement metrics and crowd out active members.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="value-exchange-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each partner contract names the value the operator delivers (early access, pricing lock, naming credit). Vague 'we'll keep you in the loop' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reciprocity discipline">Without named value exchange the cohort cannot self-renew.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="exit-ramp" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The expectations contract carries an explicit exit ramp: how a partner leaves, what they keep, what they return.</statement>
      <rationale source="Off-boarding hygiene practice">Cohorts without exit ramps accumulate ghost members and leak NDA scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
