<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="requirements-prioritization Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for requirements-prioritization as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Everything is marked Must. No boundaries. Team scope commitment is 150% of capacity.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>No real prioritization occurs; the team commits to 100% scope and blames engineering when the deadline is missed. Enforce the ~60% rule numerically: if Must &gt; 60% of effort budget, reject and re-run with RICE.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Confidence inflation — teams default 100% on everything. No written justification per row.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The Effort divisor stops doing work if Confidence is always high. Without justification, high-confidence scores masquerade as data-driven when they're guesses. Force the choice: 50% (no data), 80% (one data point), 100% (quantified baseline and delta). Make teams write it down.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>HiPPO weighting — highest-paid voice anchors group sessions and reshapes consensus.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The senior person scores 5, others follow. Elicit individually first, compute mean and σ. Reconcile only the high-σ rows. When the SVP walks in and says "that's a 5", the team's individual scores vanish. Use async scoring (Airtable form, Notion DB, CSV upload) to prevent this.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
