<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-tools-and-services" title="CI Tools, Services, and Best Practices">
  <summary>CLI tools, agent-friendly services, limitations, and operational best practices for a production CI pipeline.</summary>

  <section title="CLI Tools">
    <list>
      <item>firecrawl / jina reader: LLM-ready page extraction with JS rendering — primary fallback for SPA pages</item>
      <item>playwright: Custom JS-rendered scrape when API and jina both fail</item>
      <item>rss-parser (npm) / feedparser (py): Newsroom + blog ingestion — use RSS before scraping</item>
      <item>visualping: Diff alerts on rendered pages — cheap raw signal, no synthesis</item>
      <item>phantombuster: LinkedIn hiring/post extraction — use with proxy rotation and respect ToS</item>
      <item>apify actors: Headless scrape for G2, LinkedIn, Product Hunt — pay-per-run</item>
      <item>crunchbase API: Funding/M&amp;A/leadership — ground truth for firmographic data</item>
      <item>ahrefs / semrush API: SEO/SEM moves, top pages, keyword shifts</item>
      <item>g2 Buyer Intent API: Review velocity and intent signals</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Emit one event per delta, never aggregate inside the collector — keeps the audit trail clean and lets the synthesizer see the raw timeline.</statement>
      <rationale>Aggregated events hide the sequence of competitor moves. The synthesizer needs the timeline to detect acceleration patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate "what changed" (Haiku, mechanical) from "so what" (Opus, judgment). Mixing them costs 10x and adds hallucination.</statement>
      <rationale>Opus reasoning on raw HTML diffs is wasteful and noisy. Haiku distills the signal; Opus interprets the pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Subscribe to competitor changelog/RSS first; scraping is the fallback. APIs &gt; RSS &gt; scrape &gt; screenshot diff.</statement>
      <rationale>APIs are reliable and ToS-compliant. Scraping is fragile and legally ambiguous. Use the most reliable source available per competitor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track yourself with the same pipeline to catch what your own marketing site exposes to competitors.</statement>
      <rationale>CI is bidirectional. What you publish about pricing, hiring, and product reveals your strategy to the same tools your competitors use.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Calibrate threat scores against actual lost deals quarterly; recalibrate the prompt if the score does not predict losses.</statement>
      <rationale>An uncalibrated threat score becomes a noise source. Quarterly calibration ties CI to revenue impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM synthesis when the scraped page is paywalled or JS-rendered and returns an empty body.</description>
      <reason>Agents invent competitor features from training data when the source page is empty. Always require source citation per claim; reject unsourced assertions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Daily monitors on pricing pages hidden behind "Contact Sales" generating false silence.</description>
      <reason>These pages never change for anonymous crawlers. Cross-check G2/Capterra and customer reviews instead for pricing signal.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Trusting win-rate improvement claims (e.g., 16% to 45%) from vendor case studies without auditing methodology.</description>
      <reason>Win-rate improvements conflate CI rollout with simultaneous sales enablement and pricing changes. Survivorship bias is severe.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
