<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="requirements-prioritization Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for requirements-prioritization. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document all failure modes and limitations of the chosen method in the prioritization output. Never present a rank without caveats.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A clean-looking score hides the fragility underneath. Making limitations visible forces the human decision-maker to decide if the rank is defensible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Walk the following steps in order; first match wins; document the path and all rejected methods with rationale. Refuse to recommend a method when its prerequisites are missing — return null and request the data. Do not invent missing data.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Method drift mid-run (silently switching RICE to weighted-sum because RICE "felt arbitrary") destroys credibility; locking the method first and scoring after is the only way to prevent gaming.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enforce the 60/20/20 effort budget mechanically: Must ≤60% of capacity; Should ≈20%; Could ≈20%. Reject any run where Must exceeds the budget.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without the budget constraint the labels are meaningless — every stakeholder makes their items Must.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default Confidence to 0.8. Force 1.0 only with a written primary-source link (analytics, prior A/B, customer interview transcript). Calibrate Impact by quartile rank before mapping to the 0.25/0.5/1/2/3 scale.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLM optimism anchors Confidence at 100% and Impact at 1, making the formula degenerate to Reach/Effort and hiding meaningful differences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply Kano only when survey data from ≥30 respondents using functional + dysfunctional question pairs is available. Conference-room Kano without survey data is guessing labels.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Kano categories (Basic, Performance, Delighter, Indifferent, Reverse) change over time — today's Delighter becomes tomorrow's Basic; re-run every 6-12 months.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Floor WSJF Job Size at 1 unit. Calibrate each Cost-of-Delay component (User-Business Value, Time Criticality, Risk Reduction &amp; Opportunity Enablement) with separate evidence; do not let one person score all three components for the same item.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a Job Size floor, tiny items dominate the queue. Correlated CoD components produce a noisier version of RICE rather than a meaningful sequencing tool.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock weights BEFORE scoring items, with stakeholder sign-off. Treat weight changes as a formal change request. Cap at 7 criteria maximum.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without pre-locked weights the method is weight gaming (whoever sets weights wins). Beyond 7 criteria, stakeholders cannot hold the matrix in working memory and weights become arbitrary.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tie every row to a REQ-XXX ID before scoring. Include a status-quo "do nothing" baseline row with effort 0 and current value. Re-run on a trigger (sprint review, quarter end, major new candidate) not on schedule alone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Free-text rows orphan when the rank changes; a status-quo baseline reveals when the entire backlog scores below it — a signal the rank is answering the wrong question.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a sensitivity check: perturb the most leverage-heavy input by ±20% (RICE: Confidence; weighted-sum: top-3 weights; WSJF: Job Size) and mark items whose rank moves more than 5 positions as `low_confidence_rank`.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Items fragile to small input perturbations should not drive large resource commitments without additional data collection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The BA owns three checkpoints between passes: method lock (after pass 1), pre-score data audit (between passes 2 and 3), final memo sign-off (after pass 5).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents making priority calls without human checkpoints produce decisions that lack organizational legitimacy even when the scoring is technically correct.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
