<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-methods" title="Requirements Prioritization — Methods and Selection Decision Tree">
  <summary>Six prioritization methods with mechanics, known failure modes, and a 6-step selection decision tree based on data availability.</summary>

  <section title="Selection Decision Tree">
    <rule>
      <statement>Walk the following steps in order; first match wins; document the path and all rejected methods with rationale. Refuse to recommend a method when its prerequisites are missing — return null and request the data.</statement>
      <rationale>Method drift mid-run (silently switching RICE to weighted-sum because RICE "felt arbitrary") destroys credibility; locking the method first and scoring after is the only way to prevent gaming.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>1. Release-scope (categorical) decision → MoSCoW with 60/20/20 effort budget enforced</item>
      <item>2. SAFe or PI planning context → WSJF (Cost-of-Delay / Job Size, floor Job Size at 1 unit)</item>
      <item>3. Kano survey data available (≥ 30 respondents) → Kano; refuse if no survey data</item>
      <item>4. Reach baseline metric available + item count ≥ 30 → RICE; default Confidence to 0.8</item>
      <item>5. Regulated / audited, explicit criteria weights needed → weighted-sum (cap at 7 criteria, lock weights before scoring)</item>
      <item>6. Item count &lt; 30 or no effort estimates → Value-Effort matrix (quick triage only)</item>
      <item>7. None match → stop; request missing data; do not invent it</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="MoSCoW">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce the 60/20/20 effort budget mechanically: Must ≤ 60% of capacity; Should ≈ 20%; Could ≈ 20%. Reject any run where Must exceeds the budget.</statement>
      <rationale>Without the budget constraint the labels are meaningless — every stakeholder makes their items Must.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating MoSCoW as ordinal ranking within categories.</description>
      <reason>MoSCoW answers "will it ship", not "in what order"; pair with stack rank inside each bucket for sequence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="RICE">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default Confidence to 0.8. Force 1.0 only with a written primary-source link (analytics, prior A/B, customer interview transcript). Calibrate Impact by quartile rank before mapping to the 0.25/0.5/1/2/3 scale.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM optimism anchors Confidence at 100% and Impact at 1, making the formula degenerate to Reach/Effort and hiding meaningful differences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Reach scored as a round number with no source URL.</description>
      <reason>Tag every row with reach_estimated_no_baseline if no source is cited; prevents "10,000 users" invented by optimism.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Kano">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply Kano only when survey data from ≥ 30 respondents using functional + dysfunctional question pairs is available. Conference-room Kano without survey data is guessing labels.</statement>
      <rationale>Kano categories (Basic, Performance, Delighter, Indifferent, Reverse) change over time — today's Delighter becomes tomorrow's Basic; re-run every 6-12 months.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="WSJF">
    <rule>
      <statement>Floor WSJF Job Size at 1 unit. Calibrate each Cost-of-Delay component (User-Business Value, Time Criticality, Risk Reduction &amp; Opportunity Enablement) with separate evidence; do not let one person score all three components for the same item.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a Job Size floor, tiny items dominate the queue. Correlated CoD components produce a noisier version of RICE rather than a meaningful sequencing tool.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Universal Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tie every row to a REQ-XXX ID before scoring. Include a status-quo "do nothing" baseline row with effort 0 and current value. Re-run on a trigger (sprint review, quarter end, major new candidate) not on schedule alone.</statement>
      <rationale>Free-text rows orphan when the rank changes; a status-quo baseline reveals when the entire backlog scores below it — a signal the rank is answering the wrong question.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a sensitivity check: perturb the most leverage-heavy input by ±20% (RICE: Confidence; weighted-sum: top-3 weights; WSJF: Job Size) and mark items whose rank moves more than 5 positions as low_confidence_rank.</statement>
      <rationale>Items fragile to small input perturbations should not drive large resource commitments without additional data collection.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/moscow-template.md">MoSCoW table with 60/20/20 budget enforcement</reference>
  <reference path="templates/rice-template.md">RICE scoring table with data-quality-flag column</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prio_method_and_wsjf.py">Method-picker and WSJF scorer script</reference>
</text>
