<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="activation-framework Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for activation-framework. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define activation as the specific behavior that correlates most strongly with D30+ retention — not as completing onboarding or creating an account.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Internal milestones ("completed setup wizard") are easy to optimize but predict nothing. Retention-correlated behaviors ("shared a doc within 48h", "ran 2 reports within 7d") are the real signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Calculate baseline activation rate and time-to-activation before making any changes; segment by acquisition channel to identify if the problem is channel-specific.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a baseline, you cannot measure improvement. Channel segmentation often reveals that the problem is concentrated in one source (e.g. paid ads have 15% activation vs organic at 45%).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Watch at least 20 session recordings before forming hypotheses; agents cannot replace qualitative pattern recognition from real user behavior.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Funnel data shows where users drop but not why. Session recordings reveal whether the cause is confusion, missing information, performance issues, or unclear next steps.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score every experiment hypothesis on Impact (1-10), Confidence (1-10), and Ease (1-10); prioritize by ICE average; run highest-scoring experiment first.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">ICE forces explicit judgment about ROI before investing engineering effort. Without scoring, teams default to easiest changes (high Ease, low Impact) rather than highest-value work.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
