<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Activation Framework: 7 Steps">
  <summary>Systematic process from defining the activation event through iterative optimization, with funnel mapping example.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define the Activation Event">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define activation as the specific behavior that correlates most strongly with D30+ retention — not as completing onboarding or creating an account.</statement>
      <rationale>Internal milestones ("completed setup wizard") are easy to optimize but predict nothing. Retention-correlated behaviors ("shared a doc within 48h", "ran 2 reports within 7d") are the real signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Activation = "completed 5-step onboarding wizard" — optimizing this can increase completion 40% with zero retention improvement.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Activation = "added 3 contacts within 24h" — users who do this have 3x D30 retention vs those who do not. Validate by comparing retention curves for users who did vs did not perform the event within N days of signup.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Steps 2-4: Measure, Map, Find Drop-offs">
    <rule>
      <statement>Calculate baseline activation rate and time-to-activation before making any changes; segment by acquisition channel to identify if the problem is channel-specific.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a baseline, you cannot measure improvement. Channel segmentation often reveals that the problem is concentrated in one source (e.g. paid ads have 15% activation vs organic at 45%).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Email tool funnel mapping:
  Step 1: Signup           100%
  Step 2: Verify email      70%  (-30% — highest drop)
  Step 3: Connect account   50%  (-20%)
  Step 4: Import contacts   35%  (-15%)
  Step 5: Send first email  25%  (-10%) ← ACTIVATION

Priority order: fix Step 1→2 first (biggest absolute drop).
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Steps 5-7: Reduce Friction, Increase Motivation, Iterate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Watch at least 20 session recordings before forming hypotheses; agents cannot replace qualitative pattern recognition from real user behavior.</statement>
      <rationale>Funnel data shows where users drop but not why. Session recordings reveal whether the cause is confusion, missing information, performance issues, or unclear next steps.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Friction: too many form fields, slow load, required integrations → reduce, pre-fill, defer</item>
      <item>Friction: no guidance after signup → add tooltips, coach marks, sample data</item>
      <item>Motivation: users can activate but do not want to yet → show value earlier, add social proof</item>
      <item>Motivation: wrong user type → segment onboarding by use case</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
