<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-diagnosis" title="Diagnosing Low Activation and Prioritizing Experiments">
  <summary>Symptom-to-cause mapping, ICE scoring for prioritization, and agent-specific gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Diagnosis by Symptom">
    <list>
      <item>Drop at signup step → friction: too many fields, no SSO, password requirements → reduce to email only, add magic link</item>
      <item>Drop at onboarding → complexity: too many steps, no guidance → simplify to 3-5 steps, add templates</item>
      <item>Drop before Aha moment → unclear next step → add tooltips, coach marks, activation checklist</item>
      <item>Drop at core action → UX problems → user test and fix specific friction</item>
      <item>Long time to activate → too many steps → remove non-essential steps, pre-fill defaults</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="ICE Scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score every experiment hypothesis on Impact (1-10), Confidence (1-10), and Ease (1-10); prioritize by ICE average; run highest-scoring experiment first.</statement>
      <rationale>ICE forces explicit judgment about ROI before investing engineering effort. Without scoring, teams default to easiest changes (high Ease, low Impact) rather than highest-value work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/ice.py">Python ICE scorer for ranking activation experiments</reference>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Optimizing for high-completion events rather than retention-correlated behaviors.</description>
    <reason>Agents pick "completed onboarding" as activation because it has 80% completion vs "created a report" at 25%. But only the latter predicts retention. Always force the agent to score activation event candidates against D30 retention lift.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Using "time-to-activation" without a fixed window definition.</description>
    <reason>Leaving the window open inflates activation rate and breaks week-over-week comparisons. Define window explicitly: e.g. "activated within 7 days of signup".</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Attacking the biggest funnel drop-off without confirming it is causal.</description>
    <reason>Funnel drop-offs are correlated with activation failure but not always the direct cause. Confirm with session recordings and user interviews before building the fix.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Reducing signup friction before fixing downstream activation steps.</description>
    <reason>More signups with the same downstream funnel just inflates the top-of-funnel number. Fix activation rate before expanding acquisition.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
