<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Single Interview Fast Loop Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules every one-shot interview must satisfy so the learning compounds instead of evaporating with the moment.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Prep MUST produce a written hypothesis (single sentence, falsifiable) before the interview starts; "I want to learn about onboarding" is not a hypothesis.</statement>
      <rationale>PMs increasingly run one interview at a time without a written anchor and then synthesise into whatever feels memorable. A falsifiable hypothesis converts the interview into a yes/no signal instead of a vibe.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Hypothesis: "Users who churned in their first 7 days did so because
they could not connect their data source within 10 minutes."

Falsifiable: yes — if 3 of 5 churned users we interview report no
data-source friction, the hypothesis is rejected.]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Prep MUST tie the interview to a single decision the interviewer is about to make ("ship feature X or not", "raise price or not"); interviews without a tethered decision are postponed until one exists.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-interview signals are noisy by definition; their value comes from informing one bounded decision, not from accumulating ambient understanding. Tethering the interview to a decision prevents the founder from running interviews as procrastination.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Synthesis MUST be completed within 24 hours of the interview ending; longer delays mean the notes go in the archive without a share-out.</statement>
      <rationale>Memory decay on interview detail is steep — 24h is the empirically observed cliff for accurate verbatim quotes. PMs running one interview at a time need a 24h deadline because there is no batch synth day to fall back on.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The synthesis MUST produce a written artefact with four required slots: hypothesis verdict (supported / rejected / unclear), top 3 verbatim quotes, decision impact (what the interviewer will now do differently), follow-up actions.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a fixed schema, single-interview notes degenerate into stream-of-consciousness and become unsearchable. The four-slot schema keeps the artefact comparable across interviews so 10 single interviews aggregate into a real evidence base.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[# Interview synth — 2026-05-20, Anna K. (churned wk 2)
- Hypothesis (onboarding-friction): SUPPORTED
- Quotes:
  1. "I gave up after 40 minutes of trying to find my API key."
  2. "I thought your docs were for someone who already knew the product."
  3. "I would have paid if the import had just worked."
- Decision impact: ship the import-wizard rework this sprint (was Q3).
- Follow-up: 2 more churned-user interviews this week before locking scope.]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The synthesis artefact MUST be shared with at least one other person (DM, team channel, weekly note) within the 24-hour window; private-only notes do not count as a completed loop.</statement>
      <rationale>A single interview synthesised but never shared has zero compounding value. Share-out forces a second pair of eyes (which catches over-fits) and seeds the org's collective memory so future single interviews can be triangulated.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
