<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="value-stream-management Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for value-stream-management. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define all five Flow Metrics with written definitions pinned in the repository — data source, fields used, entry and exit edges — and require code review on any definition change.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Definition drift across tools (LinearB vs Plandek vs Atlas) causes apparent regressions from definition changes alone. Pinning in code makes changes auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use DORA "elite" thresholds as cohort-relative comparisons, not absolute labels — report where your organization sits relative to its industry peers, not whether it is "elite."</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">DORA thresholds shift over time and vary by industry. Absolute labeling misleads executives into treating industry-relative performance as universally excellent or poor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always report Flow Metrics and DORA together; never present one alone to executives or stakeholders.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">DORA covers Development to Release (DevOps efficiency). Flow covers Customer Request to Release to Customer Outcome (business value delivery). Either alone gives a partial picture that can hide the productivity paradox.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use medians and 85th/95th percentiles, never means, for flow metric reporting; flow distributions are fat-tailed and means systematically understate worst-case customer experience.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A few outlier items with 10x cycle time drive the mean far above the median, making teams appear slower than their typical performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map the value stream end-to-end: customer request → discovery → build → release → operate → customer outcome. Tool boundaries are not stream boundaries.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tool-bounded mapping misses cross-functional wait time (sales hand-off, legal review, onboarding) that frequently constitutes the majority of customer lead time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply Theory of Constraints: identify the one stage contributing the largest share of total lead time and focus the quarter's improvement effort there exclusively.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Improving non-bottleneck stages does not increase system throughput. Multi-tasking improvement efforts dilutes focus without proportional throughput gains.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When reporting AI tooling rollout impact, test lead-time distributions before and after with a statistical test (Mann-Whitney); report association, not causation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI tools often raise developer velocity without reducing customer lead time because the bottleneck moves to adjacent stages (code review, QA, compliance). Claiming causation from observational data is analytically unsound.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints are mandatory at: stream definition, metric definitions, threshold setting, and any action approval.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each checkpoint gates decisions whose errors compound: wrong stream definition produces all downstream metrics in wrong frames.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
