<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-metrics" title="Flow Metrics and DORA Metrics Definitions">
  <summary>Precise definitions for the five Flow Metrics and four DORA metrics, and the rule for pairing them in executive reporting.</summary>

  <section title="Flow Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define all five Flow Metrics with written definitions pinned in the repository — data source, fields used, entry and exit edges — and require code review on any definition change.</statement>
      <rationale>Definition drift across tools (LinearB vs Plandek vs Atlas) causes apparent regressions from definition changes alone. Pinning in code makes changes auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Lead Time: clock-on-wall from customer request accepted to work handed off to customer. Measures end-to-end flow.</item>
      <item>Process Time: time to complete if work were uninterrupted. Measures pure efficiency excluding wait time.</item>
      <item>Cycle Time: time within a specific process stage. Measures stage-level efficiency.</item>
      <item>Percent Complete and Accurate (%C/A): percentage of work items received by the next stage without rework needed. Measures quality at handoff.</item>
      <item>Throughput: items completed per unit time (per week). Measures delivery rate.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="DORA Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Deployment Frequency: how often code deploys to production. Elite: multiple per day.</item>
      <item>Lead Time for Changes: time from commit to production. Elite: under 1 hour.</item>
      <item>Change Failure Rate: percentage of deployments causing a production failure. Elite: under 5%.</item>
      <item>Mean Time to Recovery (MTTR): time to restore service after an incident. Elite: under 1 hour.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use DORA "elite" thresholds as cohort-relative comparisons, not absolute labels — report where your organization sits relative to its industry peers, not whether it is "elite."</statement>
      <rationale>DORA thresholds shift over time and vary by industry. Absolute labeling misleads executives into treating industry-relative performance as universally excellent or poor.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pairing DORA and Flow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always report Flow Metrics and DORA together; never present one alone to executives or stakeholders.</statement>
      <rationale>DORA covers Development to Release (DevOps efficiency). Flow covers Customer Request to Release to Customer Outcome (business value delivery). Either alone gives a partial picture that can hide the productivity paradox.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Reporting DORA elite status while omitting Lead Time trend.</description>
      <reason>A team can achieve DORA elite deployment frequency while customer lead time is stuck flat because the bottleneck has shifted outside the dev process — DORA alone declares victory prematurely.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use medians and 85th/95th percentiles, never means, for flow metric reporting; flow distributions are fat-tailed and means systematically understate worst-case customer experience.</statement>
      <rationale>A few outlier items with 10x cycle time drive the mean far above the median, making teams appear slower than their typical performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/flow-metrics.py">Compute Lead Time, Cycle Time, and Throughput from transitions CSV</reference>
</text>
