<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-vsm-process" title="VSM Mapping Process and Theory of Constraints Application">
  <summary>Steps to map a value stream, identify the primary bottleneck using Theory of Constraints, and detect the AI productivity paradox.</summary>

  <section title="Mapping Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map the value stream end-to-end: customer request → discovery → build → release → operate → customer outcome. Tool boundaries are not stream boundaries.</statement>
      <rationale>Tool-bounded mapping misses cross-functional wait time (sales hand-off, legal review, onboarding) that frequently constitutes the majority of customer lead time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Map current value stream stages with owners, entry and exit criteria, and data sources per stage.</item>
      <item>Step 2: Measure all five flow metrics per stage using existing tool data; identify stages with no data (fix data collection first).</item>
      <item>Step 3: Measure DORA metrics for the DevOps stages within the stream.</item>
      <item>Step 4: Identify primary bottleneck using Theory of Constraints — the stage with the largest share of total lead time AND %C/A below 90% or queue-to-process ratio above 4.</item>
      <item>Step 5: Focus one improvement effort on the primary bottleneck per quarter; do not multi-task improvement initiatives.</item>
      <item>Step 6: Monitor for productivity paradox when AI tooling is rolled out.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Bottleneck Detection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply Theory of Constraints: identify the one stage contributing the largest share of total lead time and focus the quarter's improvement effort there exclusively.</statement>
      <rationale>Improving non-bottleneck stages does not increase system throughput. Multi-tasking improvement efforts dilutes focus without proportional throughput gains.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Proposing multiple "primary bottlenecks" in a VSM analysis.</description>
      <reason>Theory of Constraints requires one primary constraint at a time. Multiple primary bottlenecks signals the analysis has not been committed to a definitive finding.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="AI Productivity Paradox">
    <rule>
      <statement>When reporting AI tooling rollout impact, test lead-time distributions before and after with a statistical test (Mann-Whitney); report association, not causation.</statement>
      <rationale>AI tools often raise developer velocity without reducing customer lead time because the bottleneck moves to adjacent stages (code review, QA, compliance). Claiming causation from observational data is analytically unsound.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Developer velocity increased 40% (commits/day) after Copilot rollout. Customer Lead Time median unchanged at 18 days. Bottleneck detector shows code-review stage grew from 22% to 31% of total lead time — the improvement in coding speed fed a review queue backlog.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using per-user flow metrics for performance management.</description>
      <reason>Flow metrics are system-level measures. Individual attribution is both analytically invalid (team dependencies obscure individual contribution) and an HR liability.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running initial VSM workshop without committing to durable data collection.</description>
      <reason>Fishbone-style workshop insights expire. Converting them to durable metrics requires data-engineering work the methodology underestimates; plan it explicitly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Re-baselining metrics after switching vendors without treating it as a definition change.</description>
      <reason>Vendor computation differences create apparent "regressions" that are purely definitional. Pin computation logic in code, not vendor, and treat vendor switch as a definition change event.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/flow-metrics.py">Compute flow metrics from issue transitions CSV</reference>
</text>
