<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="value-stream-management Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for value-stream-management as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Reporting DORA elite status while omitting Lead Time trend.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A team can achieve DORA elite deployment frequency while customer lead time is stuck flat because the bottleneck has shifted outside the dev process — DORA alone declares victory prematurely.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Proposing multiple "primary bottlenecks" in a VSM analysis.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Theory of Constraints requires one primary constraint at a time. Multiple primary bottlenecks signals the analysis has not been committed to a definitive finding.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Using per-user flow metrics for performance management.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Flow metrics are system-level measures. Individual attribution is both analytically invalid (team dependencies obscure individual contribution) and an HR liability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Running initial VSM workshop without committing to durable data collection.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Fishbone-style workshop insights expire. Converting them to durable metrics requires data-engineering work the methodology underestimates; plan it explicitly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Re-baselining metrics after switching vendors without treating it as a definition change.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Vendor computation differences create apparent "regressions" that are purely definitional. Pin computation logic in code, not vendor, and treat vendor switch as a definition change event.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents inventing VSM stage names or metric definitions not in the provided glossary.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs invent plausible stage names like "Strategic Lead Time" that have no agreed definition. Pin a glossary file and require lookups.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Aggregating flow metrics across heterogeneous teams without segmentation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mixed-team aggregation hides outliers and makes team-specific bottlenecks invisible. Require segmentation by team or product stream.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents auto-actioning a bottleneck finding (re-org, hire, deprioritize) without human approval.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Bottleneck findings are recommendations, not orders. Auto-actioning organizational changes without sponsor sign-off causes harm and destroys trust.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
