<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Interview Methods Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every structured-interview design (competencies, questions, scorecards, debrief) must satisfy before going live with a real candidate.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-competency-cap-4-6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each role family MUST cap competencies at 4-6 with weights that sum to exactly 100%. Scorecards with more than 6 competencies, fewer than 4, or weights that do not sum to 100% are rejected at design review.</statement>
      <rationale source="structured-interview research / Schmidt &amp; Hunter">More than 6 competencies dilute predictive signal because no single interviewer can meaningfully assess each; fewer than 4 collapses the role to one or two traits and over-indexes the bias of the first interviewer.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-observable-verbs-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Behavioral anchors MUST be expressed as observable verbs (e.g., "shipped a migration", "closed a $50k deal", "wrote a runbook"). Trait words ("driven", "strong", "passionate", "rockstar", "self-starter") are banned in anchors and rejected at review.</statement>
      <rationale source="bias-mitigation / structured interviewing literature">Trait words are pure interviewer projection: two interviewers seeing the same candidate disagree systematically on "driven" and agree systematically on "shipped". Observable verbs eliminate the projection axis.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-star-on-behavioral" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every behavioral interview question MUST be answered in STAR (Situation, Task, Action, Result) form; if the candidate gives Situation+Task only, the interviewer MUST probe for Action AND Result before scoring. Scorecards from sessions missing Action+Result are marked unscoreable, not "weak".</statement>
      <rationale source="STAR method / behavioral interviewing canon">Most "weak" scores reflect missing data, not weak candidates: the interviewer never extracted Action and Result. Marking unscoreable instead of weak forces a follow-up probe and protects the candidate from a false negative.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-independent-scoring-before-debrief" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every interviewer MUST submit a written scorecard to a shared store BEFORE the debrief meeting starts. Debriefs that begin before all scorecards are submitted are rejected and rescheduled; verbal-first debriefs are banned.</statement>
      <rationale source="anti-groupthink / hiring committee research">Verbal-first debriefs let the first speaker anchor the room and erase the independent signal. Pre-submitted scorecards preserve dissent and let the committee see which competencies the panel actually disagreed on.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-interview-to-offer-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly audit MUST compute interview-to-offer rate per role family; rates outside the 15-25% band trigger a process review. Above 25% suggests insufficient assessment rigour; below 15% suggests bad sourcing or unrealistic JD.</statement>
      <rationale source="hiring-funnel calibration">The 15-25% band is the empirical sweet spot for structured interviewing programs; drift in either direction signals a specific failure mode the audit can localize (assessment laxity vs. sourcing/JD misalignment) rather than vague "we hire badly".</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies-If preconditions fail OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or to no methodology at all).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application of a methodology produces worse artefacts than no methodology at all because downstream consumers trust the schema and act on bad data. The skip-record makes the non-application traceable so future audits can detect drift.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
