<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process-overview" title="Interview Process Five-Stage Pipeline">
  <summary>End-to-end structured interview pipeline: competency definition, question generation, scorecard, calibration, and debrief synthesis.</summary>

  <section title="Stage 1: Competency definition (opus)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define exactly 4-6 competencies with weights summing to 100%. Each competency must be described in observable verbs ("re-architected payment retry to cut failures"), never traits ("driven", "strong").</statement>
      <rationale>Schmidt and Hunter (1998): structured interviews with observable behavioral anchors are ~2x more predictive than unstructured. More than 6 competencies dilutes the signal; fewer than 4 leaves critical gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 2: Question generation (sonnet)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate 2-3 STAR questions per competency, each in past-tense behavioral framing. Include 2 probing follow-ups per question. Cap at one competency per question — no double-barreled questions.</statement>
      <rationale>Double-barreled questions ("tell me about a time you led a team and resolved conflict") let candidates answer only the easier half, producing incomplete evidence on both competencies.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 3: Scorecard (sonnet)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Behavioral anchors per competency must describe observable outcomes at scores 1, 3, and 5. Never use adjectives for anchors; use specific past-tense action descriptions.</statement>
      <rationale>Without observable anchors, scores reflect similarity to the hiring manager ("5 = reminds me of our best performer") rather than competency evidence, producing homogeneous hires.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 4: Calibration pack (sonnet)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate 3 mock candidate answers (strong/borderline/weak) per question for new interviewer calibration. Use these in the training session, not in real candidate assessment.</statement>
      <rationale>Interviewers who have never calibrated on the same response produce inter-rater agreement (Cohen's kappa) below 0.4 — essentially random scoring that defeats the purpose of structured interviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 5: Debrief synthesis (opus)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run debrief synthesis only after all independent scorecards are submitted. Never before. Surface competencies with score variance &gt;= 2 and evidence vs. impression-only language.</statement>
      <rationale>Debrief synthesis before independent scoring causes anchoring: interviewers adjust their scores toward whoever spoke first, eliminating the value of independent evaluation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Debrief synthesis must not produce a hire/no-hire recommendation. It surfaces data for human decision makers. The hiring decision is always human.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM-produced "hire" recommendations create legal exposure (automated employment decisions under EU AI Act, EEOC) and remove human accountability for the decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/interview-scorecard.md">Competency scorecard with behavioral anchors and hire/no-hire field.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/irr-check.py">Cohen's kappa inter-rater check; gates debrief when kappa &lt; 0.4.</reference>
</text>
