<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-method-catalog" title="Interview Method Catalog">
  <summary>Quick-reference catalog of six interview methods with decision criteria for when to use each.</summary>

  <section title="Structured behavioral interview (STAR)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use for any role where past behavior predicts future performance: managerial, cross-functional, customer-facing. Same questions for every candidate at the same level.</statement>
      <rationale>Inconsistent questions between candidates make comparison impossible and introduce evaluator bias toward candidates whose answers happened to match their prepared questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Technical assessment">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair technical assessment with behavioral for roles at L3+. Time-box at 2-4 hours max. Provide clear evaluation criteria in writing before the candidate begins. Compensate candidate time for take-home assessments &gt;2 hours.</statement>
      <rationale>Uncompensated multi-hour take-homes create selection bias toward candidates who can afford the unpaid time, systematically disadvantaging caregivers and those working multiple jobs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Take-home project: deep evaluation, async, best for senior roles.</item>
      <item>Live coding: real-time problem-solving and thinking-aloud signal.</item>
      <item>Code review: real-world quality judgment, harder to coach.</item>
      <item>System design: senior IC and manager roles.</item>
      <item>Pair programming: collaboration signal, requires calibrated interviewer.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Culture-fit assessment">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use "culture fit" as a scoring dimension without defining it in observable, values-based terms. "Culture fit" as an undefined concept is a documented path to homogeneous, legally vulnerable hires.</statement>
      <rationale>Undefined culture-fit scores correlate with protected-class characteristics (background, communication style, school pedigree) and are the leading cause of disparate impact claims in hiring.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Reference check">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use "Would you rehire them?" as the terminal reference question. Ask about specific behaviors from the candidate's STAR responses when possible, to verify claims.</statement>
      <rationale>"Would you rehire?" forces a binary judgment that correlates more strongly with actual performance than open-ended "what were their strengths?" questions, which produce social desirability bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Hiring committee debrief">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock debrief discussion until all scorecards are submitted. Review high-variance competencies first. Require that every "hire" and "no hire" recommendation cite specific evidence from the interview record.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a process lock, the first speaker anchors the group. High-variance competencies need resolution before consensus, not after — otherwise strong signals get averaged away.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
