<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules-and-gotchas" title="Interview Methods Agent Rules">
  <summary>Competency cap rule, bias/legal review pass, auto-score block, FCRA/GDPR constraints, and calibration drift.</summary>

  <section title="Competency and question constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Hard cap at 4-6 competencies. Run a deduplication pass on generated questions to ensure no question cluster covers the same competency twice from different angles.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs over-produce competencies (8-12 are common outputs) and cluster questions in leadership/communication. Explicit caps and dedup are necessary post-processing steps, not optional.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the question bank per role-level for a minimum of 6 months after calibration. Every change resets the inter-rater baseline, invalidating historical comparison data.</statement>
      <rationale>Per-hiring-manager question variation is the primary cause of "same competency, wildly different hire bar" problems within the same team.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Bias and legal review">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a fresh-context bias review pass on every generated question bank before use. The reviewing agent must not have access to the original generation rationale.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs silently inject protected-class proxies ("willing to relocate with family?", "where are you originally from?"). The reviewing agent needs a clean context to surface these without anchoring to the generator's intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Sending reference-check questions via agent without logging candidate consent in the ATS.</description>
      <reason>FCRA (US), GDPR (EU), and UK GDPR require documented consent before conducting third-party reference checks. Auto-send without consent logging is a compliance violation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Calibration drift monitoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the IRR check (Cohen's kappa) monthly across the same role's scorecards. Flag any interviewer whose kappa vs. peers drops below 0.4 on any competency for calibration.</statement>
      <rationale>Calibration drift is invisible without metrics. An interviewer who scores 5 on communication for every candidate (regardless of evidence) dilutes the panel's signal without being visible to peers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/interview-scorecard.md">Behavioral anchor scorecard per competency.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/irr-check.py">Inter-rater agreement computation with debrief gate at kappa &lt; 0.4.</reference>
</text>
