<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-spatial-rules" title="Spatial UX — Core Rules and Comfort Zones">
  <summary>Rules for placing UI elements in XR space using near/mid/far field zones, world-unit sizing, interaction modality assignment, and ergonomic constraints.</summary>

  <section title="Field Zones">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design the mid field (1-3m) as the default work surface; reserve near field (0-1m) for immediate feedback and far field (3m+) for navigation anchors and environmental context only.</statement>
      <rationale>Mid-field placement provides the best balance of visual clarity, interaction comfort, and spatial immersion across all current XR headsets. Near-field overuse causes vergence-accommodation conflict; far-field overuse degrades text legibility and interaction precision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never place persistent UI above the horizontal plane of the user's eye level — users cannot comfortably look up for extended periods.</statement>
      <rationale>Extended upward gaze (above 25° vertical) causes neck strain within minutes. Content above eye level is appropriate only for transient notifications, not primary work surfaces.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not place interactive elements closer than 0.5m from the user — this is the vergence-accommodation conflict zone where eyes cannot comfortably converge.</statement>
      <rationale>Content placed inside 0.5m forces the eyes to converge at an angle inconsistent with the display's focus distance, causing discomfort and visual fatigue.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Element Sizing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Specify all element dimensions in meters (world units) at the intended placement distance, not pixels — pixel sizing is meaningless in XR.</statement>
      <rationale>A pixel is a display-relative unit with no fixed physical size. XR rendering requires world-space dimensions so elements maintain consistent apparent size as the user moves.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Minimum text size: 0.5° visual angle at placement distance. Minimum interaction target: 1.5° visual angle (approximately 1cm at 1m, scaling linearly with distance).</statement>
      <rationale>Below 0.5° visual angle, text becomes unreadable at normal viewing distances. Below 1.5°, interaction targets require precision that exceeds comfortable hand/gaze pointing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Interaction Modality">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign interaction modality per platform constraints: visionOS primary = gaze + pinch; Quest primary = hand ray or controller; HoloLens = hand gesture + voice.</statement>
      <rationale>Modality mismatch (designing for controller input on a gaze-primary device) produces interaction patterns that feel unnatural and increase error rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Specify spatial audio feedback for all interaction events — spatial audio is a design element, not a developer afterthought.</statement>
      <rationale>In 3D space, audio provides directional confirmation that 2D visual feedback alone cannot. Missing audio design is discovered during development and added inconsistently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Validation Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every spatial layout must be validated by a human designer wearing the target headset before any 3D asset or interaction code is written.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents cannot simulate 3D space, field of view, or head tracking. All spatial specifications are text descriptions that require physical validation — no amount of review on a flat screen substitutes for headset testing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Test every layout both standing and seated — ergonomic comfort zones differ significantly between postures.</statement>
      <rationale>A mid-field panel that works well seated may require uncomfortable neck extension when standing. Posture variation is routinely ignored in XR design reviews conducted at a desk.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="scripts/spatial-comfort.py">Computes minimum element and touch target size at placement distance and visual angle</reference>
</text>
