<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-keyword-strategy" title="Keyword Strategy: Intent, Match Types, Ad Groups, Negatives">
  <summary>Core rules for classifying keywords by search intent, assigning match types, organizing into themed ad groups, and maintaining a shared negative list.</summary>

  <section title="Intent Classification">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every keyword by search intent before assigning a match type.</statement>
      <rationale>Intent determines ad copy, landing page, and bid. Mixing transactional and informational keywords in one ad group produces irrelevant ad copy for one of the two groups, lowering Quality Score and raising CPA.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Intent categories ranked by conversion value: transactional (buy, pricing, trial) &gt; commercial (best, compare, top) &gt; informational (how, what, why) &gt; navigational (brand name, login). Focus budget on transactional and commercial first.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Match Type Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start new campaigns in phrase match; promote to exact match after 30 days of proven CTR and conversions; use broad only with a maintained negative list.</statement>
      <rationale>Phrase match provides reach while filtering obviously irrelevant queries. Exact match for proven keywords ensures budget goes to known-converting queries. Broad without negatives bleeds spend on unrelated searches.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not mix match types for the same keyword theme in the same ad group.</statement>
      <rationale>A phrase and exact version of the same keyword competing in the same ad group splits Quality Score history and creates internal auction competition.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Phrase match for discovery phase, exact for proven performers — kept in separate ad groups or campaigns.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Ad Group: Project Management — Phrase
  "project management software"
  "project management tool"
  "team project management"

Ad Group: Project Management — Exact (after 30 days data)
  [project management software for teams]
  [best project management tool]
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>All keywords set to broad match with no negative list.</description>
      <reason>Broad match triggers on synonyms, related topics, and loosely related queries. Without negatives, budget is consumed by irrelevant clicks before any conversion data accumulates.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Ad Group Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Group keywords into themed ad groups of 10-20 keywords that share a single intent.</statement>
      <rationale>Tight theming ensures every ad in the group is relevant to every keyword. Ad relevance is a Quality Score component; mixed-intent groups depress scores for half the keywords.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Themed grouping — all keywords share the same intent and map to one ad copy and landing page.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Ad Group: Task Management
  "task management software"
  "task tracking tool"
  "task management app"
  [task management for teams]

Ad Group: Project Templates
  "project template software"
  "project planning templates"
  [project management templates free]
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Negative Keywords">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build a shared negative list before launching and review the Search Terms report weekly to add new negatives.</statement>
      <rationale>Negatives are the primary lever for waste reduction. The Search Terms report reveals actual queries triggering your ads; without weekly review, irrelevant spend accumulates unchecked.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Standard negative categories: Unqualified (free, cheap, DIY), Wrong Intent (jobs, careers, salary, tutorial), Wrong Audience (student, beginner, hobbyist), Wrong Product (unrelated categories), Competitors (if not targeting).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Anything that spent more than one target CPA without a conversion must become a negative immediately.</statement>
      <rationale>Spending 1× CPA with zero conversions is statistical evidence that the query is a non-converter for this account. Waiting for more data is expensive.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Score">
    <p>Quality Score is a composite of expected CTR, ad relevance, and landing page experience. Improve it by: using the keyword in ad copy, matching the landing page content to the keyword theme, improving CTR through stronger ad copy, and tightening ad groups to reduce irrelevant impressions.</p>
    <p>Benchmarks: Quality Score below 5 indicates a structural problem (wrong keyword in ad group, mismatched landing page). Score 7+ means the account is healthy for that keyword.</p>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-workflow.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/keyword-plan.md"/>
    <link path="templates/negative-keyword-list.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
