<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-workflow" title="Keyword Workflow: Build and Weekly Harvest">
  <summary>Two operational loops: a one-shot build workflow for new ad groups and a weekly Search Terms harvest loop with agent-specific constraints.</summary>

  <section title="Build Workflow">
    <p>One-shot per ad group. Inputs: seed keywords, landing page URL, competitor list. Steps: expand via Keyword Planner + autocomplete, cluster by intent theme, assign match types (phrase-first), draft negative list. Output: ad group plan ready for upload.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate all agent-generated keywords against Keyword Planner volume before publishing.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs invent keywords that sound plausible ("ai-driven enterprise solution platform") but have zero search volume. Publishing them wastes Quality Score history slots and dilutes ad group relevance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap agent bulk uploads at 50 keyword changes per push; require human approval before larger changes.</statement>
      <rationale>A runaway agent loop can push 5,000 negatives in one session and gut a campaign. Human checkpoints are required before any push that changes more than 50 keywords or negatives.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Weekly Harvest Loop">
    <p>Run weekly. Pull Search Terms report for the last 7-14 days. Classify each query with material spend: KEEP_AS_EXACT (relevant, converting), ADD_NEGATIVE_PHRASE (irrelevant theme), ADD_NEGATIVE_EXACT (specific irrelevant query), NEW_THEME (relevant but no ad group yet). Output as a diff for human review before applying.</p>
    <reference path="templates/harvest-search-terms.py">Google Ads API script to pull Search Terms data for classification</reference>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never auto-apply Search Terms harvest results without human sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale>A single misclassified negative can block an entire keyword theme from serving. The cost of a human review is a fraction of the cost of a week of blocked traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent promotes a query to exact match without checking for duplicates across ad groups.</description>
      <reason>The same keyword exact-matched in two ad groups creates internal competition — both ad groups bid on the same auction, raising your own CPC. Deduplicate account-wide before promoting.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent uses exact-string matching to classify close-variant queries as negatives.</description>
      <reason>Google matches "running shoes" to "shoes for running" by default. String-matching misses close variants and prunes valid queries. Use semantic classification, not substring checks.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Constraints">
    <list>
      <item>Require Keyword Planner volume validation before any new keyword is added.</item>
      <item>Flag INVALID_KEYWORD_TEXT errors on long-tail keywords with punctuation — strip to letters/digits/spaces before submit.</item>
      <item>Match keyword theme to landing page; mismatch is the second-largest Quality Score driver after expected CTR.</item>
      <item>Keep one campaign per language and one per major geo — cross-language keyword pollution is the top cause of low Quality Score.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-keyword-strategy.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/harvest-search-terms.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
