<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Playwright Automation Core Rules" version="2.0.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the playwright-automation methodology. Each pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="role-locator-priority" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Locators MUST follow priority: getByRole &gt; getByLabel &gt; getByText &gt; getByTestId &gt; CSS. CSS locators are allowed only when no semantic role exists, documented inline.</statement>
      <rationale source="Playwright best-practices docs">getByRole uses the accessibility tree — the same API screen readers use. Role-based locators survive class renames and DOM moves; CSS selectors break on the next sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-wait-for-timeout" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>page.waitForTimeout MUST NOT appear in the produced artefact. Use locator auto-wait or expect(locator).toBeVisible({timeout}).</statement>
      <rationale source="Playwright auto-wait docs">Fixed sleeps are flaky — too short on slow machines, too long on fast ones — and mask real timing bugs. Auto-wait adapts to actual readiness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="auth-via-storage-state" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Authentication MUST happen once in a global-setup file and persist to storageState. Tests MUST start with the stored state, never re-login per test.</statement>
      <rationale source="Playwright authentication recipes">Per-test login is the #1 source of suite slowdown and triggers rate-limit lockouts. storageState serialises cookies + localStorage and is reusable across hundreds of headless runs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="trace-on-first-retry" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Playwright config MUST set trace='on-first-retry' and screenshot='only-on-failure'. trace='on' is forbidden in CI.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — CI artefact audit">trace='on' blows CI artefact sizes (5-min run can produce 200MB). 'on-first-retry' captures diagnostics only when tests fail and the runner retries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="strict-mode-narrow-not-broaden" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When getByRole throws 'strict mode violation: multiple elements', the fix MUST be narrowing via { name: 'specific label' } — never broadening the selector.</statement>
      <rationale source="Playwright strict mode docs">Broadening picks an arbitrary element and silently tests the wrong thing. Narrowing keeps the assertion pointed at the intended target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="auth-file-gitignored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>auth.json (storageState output) MUST be in .gitignore and loaded from a secret store at test time.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — secret leak audit">auth.json contains live session tokens; committing it leaks long-lived credentials.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
