<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Testimonial Harvest SOP Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Testimonial Harvest SOP application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-trigger-at-handover" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Harvest MUST trigger at project handover (final deliverable accepted), not at random later dates.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Peak satisfaction sits at acceptance; delays collapse response rate and quote quality.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-three-question-script" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Script MUST use the 3-question form: before-state / outcome / what-changed. Open-ended asks are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">The 3-question script extracts result-specific quotes; open-ended asks yield generic praise.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-written-and-loom" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output MUST be both a written quote AND a Loom video; written-only or video-only is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Written quotes serve landing pages; video serves case studies; both are non-substitutable surfaces.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-outcome-metric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each harvest MUST capture ≥1 outcome metric (number, percentage, or named milestone).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Metric-free quotes do not convert; the metric is the social-proof payload.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-consent-and-rights" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Harvest MUST include explicit publication consent + usage rights scope (web / ads / collateral). Implicit consent is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Reusing testimonials beyond original consent creates legal exposure and breaks customer trust.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
