<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-k-factor-decomposition" title="K-Factor Decomposition and Optimization Priority">
  <summary>K = i * c formula, cycle time as secondary lever, funnel metric definitions, and optimization priority rule (c before i).</summary>

  <section title="K-Factor Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Decompose K into i (avg invites sent per user) and c (invitee conversion rate = signups / invites sent) before deciding where to optimize; optimize c first.</statement>
      <rationale>Improving c lifts every future loop turn because all future invites benefit from higher conversion; improving i only increases volume into the current conversion rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>K = i * c</item>
      <item>i = total invite_sent events / distinct active users in period</item>
      <item>c = invitee_signup events matched to invite tokens / total invite_sent events</item>
      <item>cycle_time = median days between invite_sent and invitee_signup</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Cycle Time Lever">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure cycle time (p50 days from invite_sent to invitee_signup) and treat it as a primary optimization lever alongside i and c.</statement>
      <rationale>K = 0.4 with 3-day cycle time beats K = 0.7 with 60-day cycle time over a quarter in compounding terms.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>reduce cycle time by: one-click mobile signup, pre-filled email, social login for invitees</item>
      <item>track cycle_time weekly; a sudden increase signals friction introduced in a signup change</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Funnel Metrics to Track">
    <list>
      <item>invite_shown: % of active users who see the invite prompt</item>
      <item>invite_sent: % of users who actually send an invite (= share rate)</item>
      <item>invite_clicked: clicks on the invite link by recipients</item>
      <item>invitee_signup: recipients who complete signup</item>
      <item>invitee_active: invitees who reach the activation milestone within D7</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track invitee D30 retention separately from organic D30; if invitee retention is &lt;50% of organic, the loop is poisoning the cohort.</statement>
      <rationale>Incentivized loops attract users who join for the reward, not the product; high K with low invitee retention grows the user count but collapses LTV.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
