<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-optimization-tactics" title="Optimization Tactics by K-Factor Component">
  <summary>Concrete tactics for increasing i (invites sent) and c (invitee conversion), ranked by difficulty and expected impact, with share-moment identification guidance.</summary>

  <section title="Increasing i — Share Moments">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place the share prompt at peak-emotion moments (just completed a milestone, just discovered something great) — not in settings menus.</statement>
      <rationale>Share prompts in settings rely on users seeking them out; achievement-moment prompts capture naturally high intent and produce 3–5x higher share rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>achievement trigger (completed goal, hit milestone) → celebration modal with share button</item>
      <item>discovery trigger (found something valuable) → "share with a friend who'd love this"</item>
      <item>social trigger (want to connect) → "invite teammates to collaborate"</item>
      <item>help trigger (need someone else to use it) → collaborative feature invite</item>
    </list>
    <p>Tactics by difficulty and impact:</p>
    <list>
      <item>achievement triggers — easy / high impact</item>
      <item>multi-channel sharing (email, SMS, copy link) — medium / medium</item>
      <item>viral content (shareable badges, results images) — medium / high</item>
      <item>contact import (bulk invite) — hard / high (privacy constraints; iOS/Android blocked post-2021)</item>
      <item>team features that require collaboration — hard / very high</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Increasing c — Invite Landing Page">
    <rule>
      <statement>Personal invites ("Anna invited you to [Product]") beat brand invites by 20–40% on click and signup; implement with a single DB join on the referral token.</statement>
      <rationale>Named social proof reduces perceived spam risk and creates accountability, increasing click-through before the landing page is even reached.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>personalize invite landing: show inviter name + avatar + their activity context</item>
      <item>add social proof: "join N people using [Product]"</item>
      <item>one-click signup: Google/Apple SSO, pre-filled email from invite token</item>
      <item>show value before signup: preview of what the invitee will access</item>
      <item>mobile-optimize: reduce tap count to ≤3 from invite link to activated account</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Requiring signup to view shared content.</description>
      <reason>Forcing pre-signup registration drops invitee conversion by 40–60%; a preview wall converts better than a hard gate.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Incentive Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reward at value-realization (invitee reaches activation milestone), not at signup, to cut incentive fraud.</statement>
      <rationale>Signup-triggered rewards are easy to game with fake accounts; activation-triggered rewards require genuine engagement that fraud bots cannot mimic at scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>one-time reward: $10 credit after invitee activates</item>
      <item>tiered multi-referral: 1 referral → $10, 5 → $50 + badge, 10 → $100 + premium feature</item>
      <item>two-sided: both inviter and invitee receive reward — higher acceptance rate</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
