<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-fraud-and-monitoring" title="Fraud Detection and Monitoring Cadence">
  <summary>Fraud signals in incentivized loops, quality checks on referred-user retention, and weekly/monthly/quarterly review cadence for viral metrics.</summary>

  <section title="Fraud Detection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Instrument a fraud-checker subagent to review referrer-IP / device-graph anomalies before any reward is issued on a new incentive structure.</statement>
      <rationale>Incentivized loops attract self-referrers and bot signups; raw K looks great while real LTV plummets — "optimizing" without fraud feedback maximizes gameable referrals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>self-referral: inviter and invitee share the same IP, device fingerprint, or email domain</item>
      <item>bot signups: invitee accounts with zero post-signup events within 24h</item>
      <item>reward farming: single user accumulates &gt;10% of all rewards in the period</item>
      <item>velocity anomaly: single referrer sends 10x the median invite rate</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Checks">
    <list>
      <item>invitee D7 retention vs organic D7 retention — flag if invitee is &lt;50% of organic</item>
      <item>invitee LTV vs organic LTV at D90 — if &lt;60%, incentive is attracting wrong users</item>
      <item>invitee-to-inviter conversion: what % of referred users also invite someone? — secondary K</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor K-factor expectations to category benchmarks, not to the README's case study — consumer apps: K=0.1–0.3; B2B SaaS: K=0.05–0.2.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents over-cite Dropbox/Spotify Wrapped as if any product can replicate them; unrealistic K targets lead to dark-pattern share mechanics that backfire.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Review Cadence">
    <list>
      <item>weekly: check K-factor trend, invite funnel drop-offs, top referrers, plan next experiment</item>
      <item>monthly: cohort analysis of signups by source, retention of referred vs organic, fraud check, channel performance</item>
      <item>quarterly: review loop type effectiveness, major product change to improve virality, incentive structure, competitive analysis</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Redesign viral loop mechanics every 12–18 months; users learn the pattern and c decays as familiarity reduces novelty.</statement>
      <rationale>"Personalized invite" wins early then plateaus; design for refresh, not permanence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
