<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Portfolio Strategy (70/20/10) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Portfolio Strategy (70/20/10) plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="default-70-20-10-allocation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Engineering capacity MUST default to 70% H1 / 20% H2 / 10% H3; deviations MUST cite a macro condition (Growth / Stable / Recession) and timeframe.</statement>
      <rationale source="McKinsey — Three Horizons of Growth">Without a default allocation, H1 work consumes 100% of capacity by deadline pressure; the explicit default is the forcing function for innovation budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="every-bet-mapped-to-horizon" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every active bet MUST be tagged H1 / H2 / H3 with the rationale recorded; untagged bets MUST be classified before next sprint kickoff.</statement>
      <rationale source="McKinsey — Three Horizons of Growth">Untagged bets distort allocation reporting; the explicit tag is the input to the allocator script.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="h3-bets-have-kill-criteria" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every H3 bet MUST carry pre-registered kill criteria (signal threshold + observation window); H3 without kill criteria MUST be reclassified or terminated.</statement>
      <rationale source="Eric Ries — The Lean Startup">H3 bets without kill criteria absorb capacity indefinitely; pre-registration is the only structural gate against zombie innovation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="macro-condition-quarterly-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The macro condition (Growth / Stable / Recession) MUST be reviewed quarterly with named indicators (revenue growth %, net cash, market index); intra-quarter changes require named trigger.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — portfolio audit 2025">Implicit macro reads produce panic re-allocations on noise; quarterly review with named indicators is the structural anchor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-reallocation-without-write-down" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reallocating capacity from H3 to H1 MUST come with a written-down decision record (date, indicators, expected duration); silent re-allocation MUST be rejected at retro.</statement>
      <rationale source="Annie Duke — Thinking in Bets">Silent re-allocations turn into permanent allocation drift; the decision record is the only durable counter.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
