<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="portfolio-strategy Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for portfolio-strategy. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Classify H1 only if an item serves an existing paying segment, ships within 12 months, and operates in a known market. Default to H3 with confidence &lt;= 0.4 if revenue_evidence is empty.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs over-classify items as H2/H3 because descriptions sound novel. The revenue-evidence requirement anchors classification in commercial reality rather than novelty of language.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track allocation by engineering cost (loaded dollars or person-weeks), not by ticket count. A 1-line H1 fix and a 3-engineer-month H3 spike both count as "1 ticket" — that destroys the allocation math.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ticket-count allocation produces portfolios that look balanced but are heavily skewed in actual resource spend. Cost tracking is the only way to measure the real split.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-classify quarterly, not annually. SaaS bets graduate or die fast; an H3 from Q1 is often H2 by Q3 or already cancelled.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Annual classification locks in outdated horizons. A quarterly cadence catches graduation events (H3 → H2 after design-partner validation) and zombie prevention (H3 that never graduated but still consumes budget).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-commit a kill threshold for every H3 bet at funding time (e.g. "kill if no design partner by month 4"). Without it, H3 zombies eat next year's H2 budget.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">H3 bets without kill criteria persist indefinitely because there is no natural endpoint. The kill threshold provides a forcing function that removes zombies without political overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run two passes: (1) sonnet-class analysis agent classifies each backlog item H1/H2/H3 and emits an allocation table; (2) opus-class strategy agent compares actual vs target given macro condition and proposes re-allocations. Both produce structured JSON for audit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixing classification and strategy in one pass loses the audit trail. When a classification decision is wrong, a two-pass approach makes it visible and correctable before it affects the strategy output.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
