<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-horizons" title="Three Horizons Portfolio Model">
  <summary>The 70/20/10 Three Horizons model with macro-condition adjustments, classification rubric, limitations, and the engineering-cost tracking requirement.</summary>

  <section title="Horizon Definitions">
    <p>H1 (Core, 70%): incremental improvements to existing products, 0-12 months, known market, low risk. Metrics: revenue, retention, efficiency. H2 (Adjacent, 20%): extensions to new markets or segments, 12-24 months, partial validation, medium risk. Metrics: market validation, early revenue. H3 (Transformational, 10%): new business models or technologies, 24-36 months, option value, high risk. Metrics: learning velocity, option value.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Classification Rubric">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify H1 only if an item serves an existing paying segment, ships within 12 months, and operates in a known market. Default to H3 with confidence &lt;= 0.4 if revenue_evidence is empty.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs over-classify items as H2/H3 because descriptions sound novel. The revenue-evidence requirement anchors classification in commercial reality rather than novelty of language.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Track allocation by engineering cost (loaded dollars or person-weeks), not by ticket count. A 1-line H1 fix and a 3-engineer-month H3 spike both count as "1 ticket" — that destroys the allocation math.</statement>
      <rationale>Ticket-count allocation produces portfolios that look balanced but are heavily skewed in actual resource spend. Cost tracking is the only way to measure the real split.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Re-classify quarterly, not annually. SaaS bets graduate or die fast; an H3 from Q1 is often H2 by Q3 or already cancelled.</statement>
      <rationale>Annual classification locks in outdated horizons. A quarterly cadence catches graduation events (H3 → H2 after design-partner validation) and zombie prevention (H3 that never graduated but still consumes budget).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Macro-Condition Adjustments">
    <p>Growth economy: 60/25/15 (more bets). Stable economy: 70/20/10 (standard). Recession: 80/15/5 (protect core). Write the macro condition into the OKR doc. When the condition changes, the ratio change is automatic and uncontroversial.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-commit a kill threshold for every H3 bet at funding time (e.g. "kill if no design partner by month 4"). Without it, H3 zombies eat next year's H2 budget.</statement>
      <rationale>H3 bets without kill criteria persist indefinitely because there is no natural endpoint. The kill threshold provides a forcing function that removes zombies without political overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Horizon labels becoming political: every team lobbies to be H3 for more freedom and fewer KPIs.</description>
      <reason>Use the classification rubric with a neutral arbiter (portfolio-classifier agent) and require revenue_evidence for any H1 label. When classification is evidence-based, lobbying loses its lever.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>H3 budget starved first when H1 slips: teams then claim they "do innovation" while the budget shows zero.</description>
      <reason>Lock H3 budget at the start of the quarter before sprint planning. Once H1 work claims all capacity, H3 is invisible in retrospect. Pre-commitment is the protection.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating 70/20/10 as empirically optimal rather than a starting heuristic.</description>
      <reason>The numbers originated as a Google PR artifact from 2005. Treat them as a reasonable starting point, calibrate to your market and stage, and document why you deviated if you do.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/portfolio-allocate.sh">Compute current vs target horizon allocation from a CSV backlog</reference>
</text>
