<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="portfolio-strategy Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for portfolio-strategy as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Horizon labels becoming political: every team lobbies to be H3 for more freedom and fewer KPIs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use the classification rubric with a neutral arbiter (portfolio-classifier agent) and require revenue_evidence for any H1 label. When classification is evidence-based, lobbying loses its lever.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>H3 budget starved first when H1 slips: teams then claim they "do innovation" while the budget shows zero.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Lock H3 budget at the start of the quarter before sprint planning. Once H1 work claims all capacity, H3 is invisible in retrospect. Pre-commitment is the protection.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating 70/20/10 as empirically optimal rather than a starting heuristic.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The numbers originated as a Google PR artifact from 2005. Treat them as a reasonable starting point, calibrate to your market and stage, and document why you deviated if you do.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Three Horizons assumes time-sequenced horizons (H3 becomes H2 becomes H1). Many SaaS bets never graduate; they die or stay niche.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pure time framing misleads. Instruct the agent that horizons are about risk + evidence today, not a fixed escalator.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-portfolio dependencies (shared platform, shared auth, shared data pipeline) are invisible in horizon math.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Surface cross-portfolio dependencies in a separate matrix; allocation math alone hides them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Classifier over-tagging items as H2/H3 because the prose description sounds novel.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force requirement: revenue_evidence field must be present and non-empty for H1 classification. Default all items without evidence to H3 with low confidence. Novelty of language is not a classification criterion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent computing allocation percentages from ticket counts instead of engineering cost.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Validate the input schema before classifying. If eng_cost_usd or person_weeks is missing, refuse to compute allocation percentages and return an error prompting for the field.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Macro condition buried in a long prompt and silently dropped by the rebalancer.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pass macro condition as a structured field in a dedicated XML element, not as a sentence in prose. The model must output the condition it used in the JSON response for auditability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Rebalancer hallucinating new initiatives to fill H3 budget ("suggest H3 bets").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Constrain the rebalancer to picking from the existing list. If new H3 bets are needed, run a separate brainstorm cycle and feed the survivors back in as classified items.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent making the rebalance decision unsupervised when drift exceeds 3pp.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The allocation decision is a CPO call, not an agent call. Automate drift detection and alerting; escalate to a human when any horizon drifts beyond the threshold. Never let the agent commit a rebalance to production.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
