<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cross-Channel CPA Rollup Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that turn cross-channel attribution from a vendor-supplied fiction into a defensible internal rollup.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-single-attribution-model" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The rollup MUST use ONE documented attribution model — default: last non-direct click within a 30-day click window + a separate view-through column with a 1-day post-impression window. Each channel's self-reported conversion count is recorded for reference but does NOT enter the rollup CPA. The attribution policy is committed and dated.</statement>
      <rationale source="Adopting one model is the only way to compare channels; cf. Forrester attribution research">Vendor-reported CPA sums to &gt; total conversions because every platform claims credit. A single internal model — even imperfect — produces a comparison that adds up.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-gross-spend" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Channel cost MUST be reported as gross spend: ad platform billing + agency/management fees + creative production amortization + any platform-specific premium. Net-of-rebate spend is reported as a separate column. CPA is computed with gross.</statement>
      <rationale source="Marketing-finance reconciliation practice">Agency-fee-less CPA reports a number the business does not actually pay. Using gross makes the CPA reflect real economics; net is a vanity input for negotiation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-dedup-id" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conversions MUST be deduplicated by a unifying customer ID (email hash, user ID, anonymized identifier). A conversion counts once across all channels. If the user clicked Meta then Google then converted, the rollup attributes per model — not once per channel.</statement>
      <rationale source="Identity-resolution practice in adtech (LiveRamp, server-side stitching)">Without deduplication, the rollup over-counts conversions and under-estimates CPA. Identity stitching closes the loop.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-organic-baseline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Organic + referral + direct traffic MUST be reported on the rollup as separate rows with their own cost basis (typically zero or the cost of the SEO/content investment amortized). Paid CPA is reported against the incremental conversions over the organic baseline, not against gross conversions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Incrementality testing research (Meta lift studies, geo-experiments)">Paid channels frequently claim conversions that would have happened organically. Reporting the organic baseline forces honest incrementality conversations.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-cohort-lens" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Beyond single-touch CPA, the rollup MUST include a 90-day cohort retention column per channel: of the customers acquired in week N, how many were still active at day 30/60/90. A channel with low CPA and low retention is over-credited; one with higher CPA and high retention may be under-credited.</statement>
      <rationale source="LTV/CAC framework; cf. David Skok, SaaS metrics">CPA in isolation rewards channels that source low-quality users. The cohort lens surfaces the difference and informs budget allocation correctly.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Rollup row using all rules">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Week: 2026-W20
Channel: Meta paid
Gross spend: $4,800 (incl. $600 agency fee)
Attributed conversions (last non-direct, 30d): 32
Self-reported conversions: 51 (recorded, not used)
CPA: $150 ($4,800 / 32)
View-through count (1d): 18 (caveat: lift untested)
Day-30 cohort retention: 71% (vs Google 83%, organic 84%)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Single model, gross spend, dedup, view-through separated, cohort lens included.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Per-channel claim aggregated">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Meta reports: 51 conversions, $4.8k spend, CPA $94
Google reports: 42 conversions, $3.2k spend, CPA $76
Combined CPA: $86  (51+42=93 conversions, $8k spend)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Total conversions claimed (93) exceeds actual (likely 50-60 unique). CPA is fictional. Violates r1, r3.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
