<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="CPA Rollup Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six failure modes that make the rollup mislead budget allocation. Each has a detector and a repair.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="high">
      <description>Double-counting — conversion attributed to multiple channels because dedup ID is missing or unstable.</description>
      <detector>Sum of attributed_conversions across channels &gt; actual unique conversions in CRM</detector>
      <repair>Audit identity-resolution: ensure customer ID is stable across sessions, hashed consistently, and present on every touchpoint. Re-run rollup.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="high">
      <description>Agency fees and creative production costs excluded — CPA looks artificially low.</description>
      <detector>gross_spend equals ad-platform billing only AND agency invoice exists for same period</detector>
      <repair>Add fees to gross_spend per r2. Re-evaluate channel viability — some channels flip from "winning" to "losing" once fees are included.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="high">
      <description>View-through count added to attributed conversions to "make Meta CPA look better."</description>
      <detector>attributed_conversions per channel exceeds what the attribution model alone would produce AND view_through column is empty</detector>
      <repair>Separate view-through into its own column. Report CPA with click-only attribution. If view-through is critical to the business, fund an incrementality test to quantify it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="high">
      <description>Branded-search paid cannibalizes organic — Google paid CPA looks great but conversions would have happened on organic.</description>
      <detector>Branded keywords drive &gt;= 30% of Google paid conversions AND incremental_over_organic for those keywords is near zero</detector>
      <repair>Carve branded vs non-branded into separate rows. Apply incrementality lens. Consider pausing branded paid (geo-test if uncertain).</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Cohort retention column not populated — channel allocation rewards low-quality acquisition.</description>
      <detector>cohort_d30 column blank across &gt; 3 channels for cohorts older than 30 days</detector>
      <repair>Wire the cohort retention computation. If CRM doesn't track activity, define minimum viable signal (login, action, purchase). Cohort lens is what catches mercenary channels.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Attribution policy quietly changed mid-quarter ("last click within 7 days" became "linear across 30 days") — historical comparison invalid.</description>
      <detector>attribution-policy.md modified more than once per quarter AND historical rollup not re-run with new model</detector>
      <repair>Treat attribution changes like an experiment: version the model, re-run the last 90 days under both, document the delta, brief the team. Don't change silently.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>Channel-vendor dashboards may include narrative ("Meta lifted incremental conversions by 30%") that is not evidence. The rollup uses raw spend/conversion data, not vendor narratives.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>Weekly review by growth lead + finance partner. The rollup is the artifact; the conversation is the gate. Budget shifts &gt; 20% across channels require two-week confirmation before commitment.</p>
  </section>
</text>
