<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-board-setup" title="GitLab Board Types, Scoped Labels, and WIP Limits">
  <summary>Rules for configuring GitLab Issue Boards with scoped labels and WIP limits for state-machine semantics.</summary>

  <section title="Board Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use project-level boards for single-repo workflows; use group-level boards for cross-project visibility in multi-team programs.</statement>
      <rationale>Group boards aggregate issues across subgroups but inherit labels inconsistently — agents moving issues across groups can lose label context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Board list types available: Label (workflow stages), Assignee (workload view), Milestone (release planning), Iteration (sprint board). Multiple boards per project requires GitLab Premium.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoped Label Scheme">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use "::" syntax for all workflow, priority, and type labels to enforce mutual exclusivity — an issue can hold only one label per scope prefix.</statement>
      <rationale>Without scoped labels, an issue can carry both "workflow::backlog" and "workflow::in-progress" simultaneously, corrupting board state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[labels:
  workflow:
    - "workflow::backlog"
    - "workflow::ready"
    - "workflow::in-progress"
    - "workflow::review"
    - "workflow::testing"
    - "workflow::done"
  priority:
    - "priority::critical"
    - "priority::high"
    - "priority::medium"
    - "priority::low"
  type:
    - "type::feature"
    - "type::bug"
    - "type::tech-debt"
    - "type::docs"]]></code>
      <note>Scoped labels are mutually exclusive within their prefix. An issue transitions by swapping the label (e.g., workflow::backlog replaced by workflow::in-progress).</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep total label count under 25 per project; archive or rename rather than accumulate.</statement>
      <rationale>Label sprawl makes triage harder and slows label picker rendering in the UI.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Board Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set WIP limits at the team's measured throughput, not aspirational capacity; tighten if cycle-time degrades.</statement>
      <rationale>WIP limits backed by observed data are defensible; aspirational limits get ignored under pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[board_configuration:
  name: "Development Board"
  lists:
    - type: label
      label: "workflow::backlog"
      position: 0
    - type: label
      label: "workflow::ready"
      position: 1
      limit: 10
    - type: label
      label: "workflow::in-progress"
      position: 2
      limit: 5
    - type: label
      label: "workflow::review"
      position: 3
      limit: 3
    - type: label
      label: "workflow::testing"
      position: 4
    - type: closed
      position: 5
  filters:
    milestone: "v1.0"
    labels: ["type::feature"]]]></code>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Issue and MR templates must be version-controlled in ".gitlab/" and reviewed via MR like code, not edited through the UI.</statement>
      <rationale>UI-only edits produce unreviewed changes to team process with no audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Iterations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use GitLab Iteration cadences with automatic creation for sprints; do not create iterations manually one by one.</statement>
      <rationale>Cadence automation ensures consistent sprint length and reduces admin overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[iteration_cadence:
  title: "Development Sprints"
  start_date: "2024-01-01"
  duration: 2  # weeks
  upcoming: 4
  automatic: true]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-automation.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/scoped-labels.py"/>
    <link path="scripts/seed_labels.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
