<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gitlab-boards Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gitlab-boards. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use project-level boards for single-repo workflows; use group-level boards for cross-project visibility in multi-team programs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Group boards aggregate issues across subgroups but inherit labels inconsistently — agents moving issues across groups can lose label context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use "::" syntax for all workflow, priority, and type labels to enforce mutual exclusivity — an issue can hold only one label per scope prefix.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without scoped labels, an issue can carry both "workflow::backlog" and "workflow::in-progress" simultaneously, corrupting board state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep total label count under 25 per project; archive or rename rather than accumulate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Label sprawl makes triage harder and slows label picker rendering in the UI.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set WIP limits at the team's measured throughput, not aspirational capacity; tighten if cycle-time degrades.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">WIP limits backed by observed data are defensible; aspirational limits get ignored under pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Issue and MR templates must be version-controlled in ".gitlab/" and reviewed via MR like code, not edited through the UI.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">UI-only edits produce unreviewed changes to team process with no audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use GitLab Iteration cadences with automatic creation for sprints; do not create iterations manually one by one.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cadence automation ensures consistent sprint length and reduces admin overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Auto-transition issues via the REST API labels endpoint from CI jobs, not via quick-action syntax in description bodies created by PUT requests.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Quick actions parse on POST (create/comment) but NOT on PUT (description edit) — explicit label API calls are reliable in all contexts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Wire "Closes #N" into MR description as a CI lint rule; do not rely on humans to add it manually.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Auto-close on merge requires the exact phrase in the MR description. Human compliance without enforcement is near zero on busy teams.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use push options to set MR labels at branch creation time via "-o merge_request.label" instead of manually labeling post-creation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents and developers creating branches this way produce consistent label state without UI interaction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Subscribe webhooks at the project scope for narrow targeting; subscribe at system scope only when you need all projects and can filter on payload.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Broad system webhooks deliver high volume; agents listening must filter carefully or process irrelevant events at cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rotate webhook secret tokens carefully — breaking the signature check breaks all listening agents simultaneously without obvious error.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">GitLab webhook signature validation is token-based and does not provide a rotation grace period.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Triage Service Desk issues with labels only after content enrichment; never auto-close Service Desk issues without human review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Service Desk emails carry sparse fields and potentially sensitive attachments. Auto-close can permanently dismiss customer requests without resolution confirmation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply human-in-the-loop checkpoints for: board structure changes, label-scheme changes, auto-close rules, and group-level moves.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These operations affect all team members simultaneously and are difficult to reverse cleanly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
