<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-automation" title="GitLab CI Automation and API Integration">
  <summary>Rules for automating issue transitions via GitLab CI and REST API, including quick-action behavior and webhook routing.</summary>

  <section title="CI-Driven Issue Transitions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Auto-transition issues via the REST API labels endpoint from CI jobs, not via quick-action syntax in description bodies created by PUT requests.</statement>
      <rationale>Quick actions parse on POST (create/comment) but NOT on PUT (description edit) — explicit label API calls are reliable in all contexts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[# .gitlab-ci.yml
update_issue_on_mr:
  stage: notify
  script:
    - |
      curl --request PUT \
        --header "PRIVATE-TOKEN: $GITLAB_TOKEN" \
        --data "labels=workflow::review" \
        "$CI_API_V4_URL/projects/$CI_PROJECT_ID/issues/$ISSUE_ID"
  rules:
    - if: $CI_MERGE_REQUEST_IID
      when: always]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Putting quick-action strings like "/label ~workflow::review" in a PUT request body to update issue description.</description>
      <reason>Quick actions only parse on initial POST creation or comment creation. PUTs to description do not re-trigger quick-action parsing, so the label is silently ignored.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Merge Request Auto-Close">
    <rule>
      <statement>Wire "Closes #N" into MR description as a CI lint rule; do not rely on humans to add it manually.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-close on merge requires the exact phrase in the MR description. Human compliance without enforcement is near zero on busy teams.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use push options to set MR labels at branch creation time via "-o merge_request.label" instead of manually labeling post-creation.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents and developers creating branches this way produce consistent label state without UI interaction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[git push -o merge_request.create \
  -o merge_request.label="workflow::review" \
  -o merge_request.assign="@reviewer" \
  origin feature/my-branch]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Webhook Routing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Subscribe webhooks at the project scope for narrow targeting; subscribe at system scope only when you need all projects and can filter on payload.</statement>
      <rationale>Broad system webhooks deliver high volume; agents listening must filter carefully or process irrelevant events at cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Rotate webhook secret tokens carefully — breaking the signature check breaks all listening agents simultaneously without obvious error.</statement>
      <rationale>GitLab webhook signature validation is token-based and does not provide a rotation grace period.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Service Desk">
    <rule>
      <statement>Triage Service Desk issues with labels only after content enrichment; never auto-close Service Desk issues without human review.</statement>
      <rationale>Service Desk emails carry sparse fields and potentially sensitive attachments. Auto-close can permanently dismiss customer requests without resolution confirmation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[service_desk:
  enabled: true
  auto_labels:
    - "source::service-desk"
    - "workflow::triage"]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-board-setup.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-agent-usage.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
