<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Quarterly Retainer Review Script Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="850" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every quarterly retainer review must enforce to convert review-time into renewal-time.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-45-minute-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The call is 45 minutes. Hard stop. Segments: data 10 min, outcomes 15 min, blockers 10 min, renewal 10 min. If you run past, you've lost the renewal momentum.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gainsight QBR data, 2024">Gainsight 2024 customer-success data: QBRs over 60 minutes correlate with lower renewal rates (-12 pp) because they drift into advocacy/complaint mode. 45 min forces preparation density and signals respect for client time.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-named-decision-exit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The call ends with one of four explicit decisions named aloud by the client: (1) continue same terms, (2) scale up scope, (3) scope down, (4) terminate. "Let me think about it" is not a decision — push for at least a date by which they will name one.</statement>
      <rationale source="Chris Voss, Never Split the Difference (2016), ch. 7 - 'no' as decision">Open-ended endings produce churn invisible until the renewal date passes. Forcing a named decision (or a named date) makes the next step actionable. The four-option frame anchors the conversation away from binary "yes/no" stress.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-data-over-narrative" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The first 10 min is data-only: hours used / hours bought, SLA % met, scope items shipped vs. agreed. No interpretation, no spin. Numbers visible on screen the whole time.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kahneman, Thinking Fast and Slow - anchoring effect">Numbers shown first anchor the client's reference frame in objective territory. Narrative-first reviews let the client anchor on emotion (last bad week) instead of quarter trend. Data must precede story.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-scope-delta-written" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the decision is "scale up" or "scope down", the exact scope delta is written into the decision-record JSON live during the call. Hours, deliverable types, SLA target. Verbal-only changes don't bind.</statement>
      <rationale source="Statement-of-work / change-order discipline; Mike Monteiro, Design Is a Job (2012), ch. 5">Verbal scope changes are the #1 source of next-quarter conflict in service businesses. Writing them live makes both parties read them; client confirmation in real time is the contract amendment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-24h-follow-up" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A 1-page email follow-up arrives within 24h of the call: decision, scope delta, next-quarter dates, action items per side. If you can't send it in 24h, your call was too long.</statement>
      <rationale source="HubSpot sales follow-up data, 2024">HubSpot 2024 data: client-signed contract amendments arrive 3x faster when follow-up is sent within 24h vs. 48h+. Cognitive recall decays past 24h; the email is the binding artifact.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Decision-record after a 45-min QBR">
      <code lang="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "client": "Acme Inc.",
  "quarter": "Q2-2026",
  "decision": "scale_up",
  "scope_delta": {
    "hours_bought_per_month_from": 40,
    "hours_bought_per_month_to": 60,
    "new_deliverables": ["weekly content audit", "monthly SEO report"],
    "sla_target_response_hours": 4
  },
  "effective_date": "2026-07-01",
  "next_review_date": "2026-10-15",
  "client_decision_maker": "M. Chen (CMO)",
  "agency_lead": "yourname",
  "follow_up_email_sent_at": "2026-04-16T18:00:00Z"
}
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2 (named decision), r4 (scope delta written), r5 (follow-up timestamp captured).</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Open-ended exit">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Client at minute 47: "We're really happy with the work. Let me sync with finance and get back to you."
Agency lead: "Sure, no problem!"

Problem: violates r2 (no named decision, no date). 6 weeks later
client renews at original scope minus $1k/month "due to budget constraints."
Repair: at minute 42 — "Totally. To plan capacity my side, can we put a date
on the finance sync? Even a Slack reply by Friday works."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 + r2 violation pattern that turns a renewal into a discount conversation later.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
