<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-quarterly-estimates" title="Quarterly Estimated Tax Payments">
  <summary>Who must pay quarterly estimates, when they are due, and how to compute them using the safe-harbor rule to eliminate underpayment penalties.</summary>

  <section title="Who Must Pay">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pay quarterly estimated taxes if you expect to owe $1,000 or more in federal income tax for the year. Most profitable solopreneurs meet this threshold by Q1 of their first profitable year.</statement>
      <rationale>The IRS assesses the underpayment penalty quarterly, not annually. Missing a payment and trying to compensate at year-end still incurs penalties for the missed quarters.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Due Dates">
    <p>US federal quarterly deadlines: Q1 (Jan–Mar) due April 15; Q2 (Apr–May) due June 15; Q3 (Jun–Aug) due September 15; Q4 (Sep–Dec) due January 15 of the following year. Note: April 15 covers both Q1 estimate and the prior-year tax return filing.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set calendar reminders 2 weeks before each quarterly due date. A missed due date incurs a penalty at the federal short-term interest rate, assessed daily, for that specific quarter's payment shortfall.</statement>
      <rationale>The penalty compounds for the duration of underpayment. A Q1 missed payment accrues a penalty for the full nine months until April 15 of the following year.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Safe-Harbor Calculation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the safe-harbor rule to eliminate underpayment risk: pay 100% of prior-year tax liability in equal quarterly installments (110% if prior-year AGI exceeded $150,000). This eliminates the underpayment penalty regardless of actual current-year income.</statement>
      <rationale>Variable-income businesses cannot reliably project current-year profit mid-year. The safe-harbor method decouples quarterly payments from unpredictable income, eliminating penalty risk at the cost of potentially overpaying — refunded at filing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When AGI exceeded $150,000 in the prior year, use the 110% safe-harbor threshold, not 100%. Agents miss this nuance consistently and produce underpayment plans that still accrue penalties for high earners.</statement>
      <rationale>The IRS 110% rule for high earners (Pub 505) is a discrete threshold, not a gradual scale. Missing it results in a penalty for the full year.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/safe-harbor.py">Quarterly federal estimate calculator: computes both safe-harbor and current-year amounts, outputs the higher</reference>
    <p>Simple approach: set aside 25–30% of every payout into a dedicated tax savings sub-account. Transfer to estimated payments each quarter. This is the operationally simplest approach for early-stage irregular income.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Setup Checklist">
    <p>One-time setup: form business entity, open business bank account, create a separate tax savings account, set up bookkeeping system (QuickBooks, Wave, or Xero), set quarterly calendar reminders.</p>
    <p>Ongoing monthly: record all income, categorize expenses, keep receipts, calculate monthly profit, transfer 25–30% to tax savings.</p>
  </section>
</text>
