<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-records-and-penalties" title="Record Keeping, Penalties, and Audit Preparedness">
  <summary>Required record retention periods, penalty types and avoidance strategies, and audit red flags to eliminate from the start.</summary>

  <section title="Record Retention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep tax returns permanently. Keep receipts, bank statements, invoices, mileage logs, and asset depreciation records for 7 years. Use digital formats with two-location backup.</statement>
      <rationale>The IRS has 3 years to audit a return in normal circumstances, 6 years if income is understated by 25%+, and indefinitely for fraud. 7-year retention covers the 6-year window with a safety margin.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Folder structure: taxes/YEAR/receipts/, invoices/, bank-statements/, quarterly-estimates/, tax-return.pdf; taxes/permanent/entity-formation/, major-contracts/.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Reconcile books monthly, not annually. Year-end reconciliation is where deductions get lost. Convert receipts to PDF with a corresponding row in an expenses CSV or accounting file at capture time.</statement>
      <rationale>Memory-based reconciliation after 11 months misses deductions, produces misclassified expenses, and creates audit risk from inconsistent categorization patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Penalties">
    <p>Penalty types: Underpayment (owing $1K+ at filing — variable rate compounding daily, avoided by safe-harbor), Late filing (5%/month up to 25% — avoided by filing or extending on time), Late payment (0.5%/month on unpaid tax — avoided by paying estimated taxes), Accuracy (20% of underpayment — avoided by documentation and CPA review).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the extension form (Form 4868) if you cannot file by April 15. Extensions extend the filing deadline to October 15 but do NOT extend the payment deadline — any taxes owed are still due April 15.</statement>
      <rationale>A common mistake: filing an extension and believing no payment is due. The late-payment penalty (0.5%/month) begins immediately after April 15 regardless of extension status.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Audit Red Flags">
    <p>Red flags to avoid from day one: claiming 100% home office deduction (claim actual use percentage only), large round-number deductions (use exact amounts from receipts), cash-heavy business without receipts, Schedule C losses for multiple consecutive years without documentation of profit motive, 100% business-use vehicle claim.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep personal and business finances completely separate from the first day: dedicated business checking account and business credit card. Commingled finances is the single largest audit risk for sole proprietors.</statement>
      <rationale>Commingled accounts make it impossible to distinguish personal from business expenses without reconstruction. Auditors treat commingled accounts as evidence of inadequate books, which shifts the burden of proof to the taxpayer.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
