<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ops-tax-compliance Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ops-tax-compliance as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs cite tax rules from prior years as current-year law.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always require the agent to cite an IRS publication number and revision date. Standard deduction, mileage rate, HSA/401(k) limits change annually. Verify against IRS.gov before acting.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents produce confident-sounding state nexus conclusions for jurisdictions the business has never operated in.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>State nexus rules vary on dozens of dimensions (economic nexus thresholds, affiliate nexus, click-through nexus). Agents flatten this to single-rule reasoning. Require a CPA for any new-state nexus determination.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent pastes full tax IDs, SSNs, EINs, or bank account numbers into prompts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Any data in the prompt can appear in logs, context summaries, or API response metadata. Use a scrubber pipeline before any LLM call involving financial records.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent drafts a response to an IRS notice without mandatory CPA sign-off.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>IRS-facing communications trigger formal processes. An incorrect response can waive defenses or create new liability. Agents should only prepare a facts-and-timeline summary for the human and CPA to review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
