<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-year-end-and-state" title="Year-End Planning, State Compliance, and AI-Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>December action checklist to minimize tax liability, state nexus and sales tax considerations, and LLM limitations for tax work.</summary>

  <section title="Year-End Planning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reassess S-Corp election each December once SE-eligible income exceeds approximately $80–100K. The election can save $5–15K in self-employment tax annually at that income level.</statement>
      <rationale>SE tax is 15.3% on net self-employment income. An S-Corp allows splitting income into salary (SE-taxable) and distributions (not SE-taxable), reducing the SE-taxable portion. The savings compound annually.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>December year-end checklist: review annual profit and calculate current tax liability, max out retirement contributions (Solo 401(k) or SEP-IRA reduce taxable income dollar-for-dollar), purchase qualified equipment under Section 179 (deduct full cost in current year), pay outstanding business expenses to accelerate deductions, consider deferring income to January if expecting a lower-income year next year, calculate Q4 estimate due January 15.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="State Tax Compliance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Determine nexus in each state where you have customers, employees, or business activity before exceeding sales thresholds. Selling SaaS into CA/NY/WA above $100K in revenue or 200 transactions in 12 months typically creates nexus and tax registration obligation.</statement>
      <rationale>States have aggressive nexus enforcement and can assess back taxes plus penalties and interest retroactively. Early registration costs a few hours; retroactive compliance costs a lawyer and months of reconciliation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Multi-state checklist: determine nexus in each state, register for state taxes where required, set up state quarterly estimates, track sales by state for reporting, file state returns separately from federal.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>For SaaS businesses, check whether marketplace facilitator status applies before registering for direct sales tax collection. If you sell through a platform that collects and remits on your behalf, direct registration may be unnecessary.</statement>
      <rationale>Marketplace facilitator treatment eliminates the compliance burden for sales made through covered platforms. Registering unnecessarily creates ongoing filing obligations without benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLMs cite tax rules from prior years as current-year law.</description>
      <reason>Always require the agent to cite an IRS publication number and revision date. Standard deduction, mileage rate, HSA/401(k) limits change annually. Verify against IRS.gov before acting.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents produce confident-sounding state nexus conclusions for jurisdictions the business has never operated in.</description>
      <reason>State nexus rules vary on dozens of dimensions (economic nexus thresholds, affiliate nexus, click-through nexus). Agents flatten this to single-rule reasoning. Require a CPA for any new-state nexus determination.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent pastes full tax IDs, SSNs, EINs, or bank account numbers into prompts.</description>
      <reason>Any data in the prompt can appear in logs, context summaries, or API response metadata. Use a scrubber pipeline before any LLM call involving financial records.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent drafts a response to an IRS notice without mandatory CPA sign-off.</description>
      <reason>IRS-facing communications trigger formal processes. An incorrect response can waive defenses or create new liability. Agents should only prepare a facts-and-timeline summary for the human and CPA to review.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
