<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-pdca-cycle" title="PDCA-Reflexion Cycle for SDD">
  <summary>The four phases of the Reflexion learning loop mapped to SDD task execution.</summary>

  <section title="Phase Mapping">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every SDD task execution must follow Plan → Do → Check → Act. Skipping any phase degrades the learning signal.</statement>
      <rationale>Reflexion only improves agent quality when all four phases complete. Skipping Check means no reflection is generated; skipping Act means no memory is updated.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Plan Phase">
      <rule>
        <statement>Load session.md (if continuing), keyword-filter patterns.md for relevant patterns, keyword-filter mistakes.md for domain warnings. Summarize in 5 bullets before proceeding.</statement>
        <rationale>Loading the entire patterns.md and mistakes.md burns 5-15k tokens of context budget. Keyword filtering to 3-5 relevant entries is both faster and more precise.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section title="Do Phase">
      <rule>
        <statement>Execute the task with loaded patterns applied. Deviate from patterns only with a documented reason. Track which patterns are used.</statement>
        <rationale>Pattern tracking enables usage-count updates in the Act phase, which in turn updates confidence scores.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section title="Check Phase">
      <rule>
        <statement>Evaluate output against each acceptance criterion using external signals (test results, linter, type checker). Report each AC as PASS or FAIL with evidence. Do not self-report PASS without external signal.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs in self-evaluation exhibit systematic optimism — they report AC as PASS when they would fail against an independent test suite. External tests must be the authoritative signal.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section title="Act Phase">
      <rule>
        <statement>After any PASS: extract a PAT-NNN entry for patterns.md if a novel successful approach was used. After any FAIL: append a MIS-NNN entry to mistakes.md. Update session.md.</statement>
        <rationale>Reflections written immediately after task completion are accurate. Reflections written at session end produce generic patterns ("write tests first") without project-specific context.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="SDD Quality Gate Integration">
    <list>
      <item>L1 (Spec review): load domain patterns before analysis</item>
      <item>L2 (Design review): load architecture patterns</item>
      <item>L4 (Pre-code): load coding patterns and mistakes for the task domain</item>
      <item>L5 (Post-code): run external tests, generate verbal reflection</item>
      <item>L6 (Complete): update memory files, close or update session.md</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Retry Limit">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set a maximum of 3 Reflexion retry attempts per task. After 3 cycles, escalate to human review.</statement>
      <rationale>Reflexion improves on first and second retry but has diminishing returns. A third failure with updated reflections indicates a gap that verbal reinforcement cannot fix alone.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
