<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-memory-architecture" title="Reflexion Memory Architecture">
  <summary>Structure and update rules for the four memory files in .aidocs/memory/.</summary>

  <section title="Memory Files">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain exactly four memory files in `.aidocs/memory/`: patterns.md, mistakes.md, decisions.md, session.md. Keep them in the same repository as the code they govern.</statement>
      <rationale>Memory files in a different repo from the code produce context drift — patterns reference files and patterns that no longer exist in the agent's working tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="patterns.md">
    <rule>
      <statement>A PAT-NNN entry must include: domain, context (when it applies), problem it solves, solution (actionable steps or code), confidence score, usage count, and source task ID.</statement>
      <rationale>Patterns without context cannot be retrieved accurately. Patterns without confidence scores cannot be prioritized by the agent during Plan phase loading.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Write patterns in "When X, do Y" format, not as descriptions of what worked. "When migrating tables with >100k rows, batch the update" not "batching worked well".</statement>
      <rationale>Prescriptive patterns are directly actionable. Descriptive patterns require the agent to re-derive the action, introducing drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="session.md">
    <rule>
      <statement>Clear session.md at the start of each new project. Session context from a previous project causes the agent to apply irrelevant patterns and miss-attribute mistakes.</statement>
      <rationale>Session.md is project-scoped. Multi-agent pipelines sharing session.md across projects produce write conflicts and corrupted context.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Memory Maintenance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Archive patterns with confidence below 0.3 or unused for 90+ days into patterns-archive.md. Do not delete — archived patterns may be relevant again if the domain returns.</statement>
      <rationale>Stale patterns loaded in context introduce noise. High-scoring but untouched patterns may have been invalidated by framework upgrades or architectural changes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Loading the full patterns.md without keyword filtering before a task.</description>
      <reason>A mature project's patterns.md can reach 15-20k tokens. Full loads exceed the practical context budget before the task description is even added.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
