<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Productized Service Launch Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules including a `skip-this-methodology` rule. Each pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Productized Service Launch artefact carries a single named owner (person, not &apos;team&apos; / &apos;we&apos;). Anonymous artefacts rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBOK 7 Tailoring + RACI practice">RACI: anonymous artefacts accumulate edits-by-anyone; rollback authority becomes unclear.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-anchor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every non-trivial field in the Productized Service Launch output is anchored to a verbatim citation (URL / ticket id / transcript id / metric snapshot). No anchor → field rejected as fabrication.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice (Anthropic + OpenAI tool-use guides 2025)">LLMs cheerfully invent plausible values without inputs; verbatim anchoring makes the artefact falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="versioned-template" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Productized Service Launch template is versioned (semver). Each filled instance records the template_version it used so downstream consumers can re-parse legacy artefacts.</statement>
      <rationale source="Schema-evolution practice (Avro / Protobuf)">Templates without version pinning become a one-way ratchet; old instances become unreadable when the template drifts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="human-checkpoint" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No binding action (commit / send / charge / ramp / freeze) is taken on a Productized Service Launch output until a named human reviewer (not the producing agent) signs off.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO 27001 A.6 segregation-of-duties">Self-approval defeats the audit trail; agent + reviewer is a two-key system on irreversible actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="review-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Productized Service Launch instance carries a last_touched ISO timestamp; instances with no touch in N cycles auto-archive instead of silently rotting.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene (Etsy ops handbook 2014)">Un-owned, un-touched artefacts metastasize and the operator stops trusting the whole library.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip when: no approved design spec OR outbound list &lt; 30 prospects OR beta cohort &lt; 3. Methodology overhead does not pay back outside its preconditions.</statement>
      <rationale source="scope-guard practice">Scope guard: applying a methodology outside its preconditions produces noise without signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
