<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Chunking Code AST — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules: dispatch by language, AST primary path, dedup overlapping chunks, log on fallback, version on strategy change.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-language-dispatch" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CodeChunker MUST dispatch on language: Python goes through `ast.parse` + node walk; JS/TS goes through tree-sitter (regex only as last-resort fallback); other languages go to the generic line splitter.</statement>
      <rationale source="LangChain / LlamaIndex code-splitter design">A single regex path on a multi-language corpus mis-splits decorators, generics, and arrow functions. Language dispatch is the only path that scales.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-ast-primary-python" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Python files MUST be chunked via `ast.parse` walking FunctionDef, AsyncFunctionDef, ClassDef. Each chunk MUST carry name, type, docstring, start_line, end_line.</statement>
      <rationale source="Python ast docs + code-search retrieval benchmarks">Decorators, type annotations, and nested definitions are handled correctly only by the AST path. Regex splitters lose nested-class boundaries.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-dedup-overlapping" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When the AST walk emits both a class chunk and its method chunks, the emitted list MUST be deduplicated by (name, start_line) before indexing, OR the class-level chunk MUST be excluded.</statement>
      <rationale source="Vector-store nearest-neighbour skew analysis">Overlapping chunks inflate the index and skew k-NN scores toward classes with many methods. Dedup keeps ranking stable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-fallback-warning" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any fallback from AST/tree-sitter to the generic line splitter MUST log a structured warning with file, language, reason so the caller can flag the file for re-ingest after the parse issue is fixed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion-network ingestion incident log">Silent fallback ships chunks without name/type/docstring, breaking name-based retrieval. The warning is the only handle the caller has.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-version-on-strategy-change" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Changing the chunking strategy (e.g. AST then tree-sitter, or different dedup policy) MUST bump strategy_version and write to a versioned collection name. Mixed-strategy indices MUST NOT exist.</statement>
      <rationale source="Re-index incident analysis">Mixing strategies under one collection name causes hits from old chunks to surface alongside new ones, with incompatible metadata.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
