<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="active-listening">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>communicator</domain>
    <summary>RASA (Receive, Appreciate, Summarize, Ask) listening practice that ensures the speaker feels understood; reaches Level 5 empathic listening.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>active-listening</tag>
      <tag>rasa</tag>
      <tag>empathy</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>communication</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="mom-test"/>
      <ref slug="stakeholder-communication"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Active Listening</title>

    <summary>A structured listening practice (RASA: Receive, Appreciate, Summarize, Ask) that ensures the speaker feels understood before the listener responds. Combines paraphrasing, mirroring, open questions, and empathic reflection to reach Level 5 empathic listening — understanding both content and emotion.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>People who don't feel heard withhold information, resist decisions, and disengage. Active listening is the single highest-leverage technique for requirements gathering and conflict de-escalation: it costs nothing and directly reduces the "missing information" failure mode. Research shows 80% of communication problems trace to listening failures, not speaking failures.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Requirements gathering sessions with stakeholders or clients</item>
        <item>1-on-1 meetings where trust or engagement is at risk</item>
        <item>Customer discovery interviews (especially with skeptical interviewees)</item>
        <item>Conflict situations where one party feels misunderstood</item>
        <item>Performance discussions or coaching conversations</item>
        <item>Generating interview scripts that follow RASA: open questions, paraphrase prompts, silence cues</item>
        <item>Coaching prep: producing reflective-listening response starters keyed to a specific emotional context</item>
        <item>Transcript post-processing: identifying where the interviewer talked too much (&gt;20% of words) or used closed questions</item>
        <item>Requirements gathering support: converting a stakeholder conversation into structured observations using RASA labels</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Real-time agent conversations — agents cannot perform empathic listening live; they can scaffold it but not execute it</item>
        <item>High-stakes interpersonal conflicts — a script-driven approach risks feeling mechanical and backfiring</item>
        <item>Situations where a direct answer is needed and the other party is not emotionally engaged</item>
        <item>Asynchronous text threads where silence and pace cues are absent</item>
        <item>Replacing empathic presence: the Level 5 "empathic listening" in the framework requires reading emotional state from tone and body language, which text-based agents cannot do from transcripts alone</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="rasa-framework">
      <p>The RASA model (Receive, Appreciate, Summarize, Ask), the five empathic listening levels, and the reflective listening formula for communicating both content and emotional understanding.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Work through all four RASA steps in every substantive conversation: Receive (full attention), Appreciate (acknowledgment), Summarize (reflect back), Ask (open follow-up).</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping Summarize is the most common failure — without paraphrasing, the speaker cannot confirm their message was understood and will either repeat or withhold detail.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Requirements session with a skeptical stakeholder.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
R: No phone, eye contact, note-taking only.
A: "I see", nods, "Go on..."
S: "So if I understand you, the current process takes 4 hours
    because the data export step is manual — is that right?"
A: "Can you walk me through what happens after the export?"
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="open-vs-closed-questions">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use What, How, and Tell-me-about openers instead of Is, Do, or Did — closed questions produce yes/no answers that close down exploration.</statement>
        <rationale>Open questions give the speaker control of the answer scope, which surfaces information the interviewer did not know to ask about.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Is the system slow?"
"Do you like the design?"
"Did that cause a problem?"
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"How does the system perform under load?"
"What do you think about the design?"
"How did that affect your team?"
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="empathic-listening-levels">
      <rule>
        <statement>Target Level 5 (Empathic) in high-stakes conversations: understand both the content of what is said and the emotional state of the speaker.</statement>
        <rationale>Levels 1-4 process words; Level 5 processes meaning and feeling. Decision-makers and clients operating under stress communicate 40-60% of their actual concern through emotional register, not explicit words.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Level 1 — Ignoring: not listening at all</item>
        <item>Level 2 — Pretending: "uh-huh" with no engagement</item>
        <item>Level 3 — Selective: hearing only parts while forming a reply</item>
        <item>Level 4 — Attentive: focusing on words, taking notes</item>
        <item>Level 5 — Empathic: understanding feeling AND content</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="reflective-listening-formula">
      <rule>
        <statement>Reflect both content and feeling using the formula: "It sounds like you're [FEELING] because [CONTENT]."</statement>
        <rationale>Naming the feeling signals that you are operating at Level 5; the speaker either confirms (and feels understood) or corrects (providing higher-quality signal).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"It sounds like you're frustrated because the deadline keeps moving."
"It seems like you're excited about this new approach."
"I hear that you're concerned about the budget implications."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="mirroring-technique">
      <rule>
        <statement>Mirror by repeating the last 1-3 words of the speaker's sentence as a question — do not add interpretation.</statement>
        <rationale>Mirroring is the lowest-friction technique that produces the highest elaboration rate. It signals attention without leading the speaker toward a particular answer.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Speaker: "We're really struggling with the deployment process."
You: "The deployment process?"
Speaker: [elaborates with root cause and context]
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="silence-technique">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pause 3-5 seconds after the speaker finishes before responding — do not fill silence immediately.</statement>
        <rationale>People add the most important information after the first pause. Immediate response signals that you were waiting to speak, not listening.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="paraphrasing">
      <rule>
        <statement>Paraphrase at least once per conversation using: "If I understand correctly, you mean..."</statement>
        <rationale>Paraphrasing forces the listener to synthesize rather than just hear, and gives the speaker an explicit correction opportunity before assumptions harden.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="barriers-and-fixes">
      <rule>
        <statement>Identify and neutralize the five common barriers before entering a high-stakes listening situation.</statement>
        <rationale>Each barrier converts a potential Level 5 interaction into Level 3 or lower, degrading information quality and trust.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Planning response — fix: commit to understanding before forming any reply</item>
        <item>Judging — fix: suspend judgment until the speaker has fully finished</item>
        <item>Interrupting — fix: wait 2 seconds after they stop before speaking</item>
        <item>Advising prematurely — fix: ask "Do you want advice or just to vent?" before offering solutions</item>
        <item>Distractions — fix: remove phone, close laptop before the conversation begins</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-workflow-patterns">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use agents for pre-conversation scaffolding and post-conversation analysis, not live listening execution.</statement>
        <rationale>Active listening is fundamentally reactive to real-time emotional signals. Agents can generate question scripts and annotate transcripts, but cannot adapt in real time to tone or body language.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Two-pass agent workflow for a requirements session.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Pass 1 (before): Generate RASA-structured question flow for the session goal.
  - Output: Receive-phase opener, Appreciate phrases, Summarize starters, 5 open Ask questions.
  - Constraint: no yes/no questions, no "Is..." or "Do you..." openers.

Pass 2 (after): Annotate transcript with RASA labels.
  - Flag: closed questions used by interviewer
  - Flag: interviewer word-share > 20% in any 3-turn window
  - Flag: Summarize step skipped
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <p>A subagent receives a conversation goal (e.g., "requirements gathering session with a skeptical stakeholder") and outputs: (1) a RASA-structured question flow, (2) 5-10 paraphrase/reflection starters tuned to expected emotional register, (3) a closed-to-open question conversion for any pre-existing question list. After the human conducts the conversation, the agent receives the transcript and annotates it: each turn labeled by RASA step, word-count ratio check, and barrier identification.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents: General Claude Sonnet call — question generation and transcript annotation; sufficient for RASA tagging. faion (communicator domain) — for cross-methodology context (mom-test, stakeholder-communication).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <prompt purpose="rasa-question-flow"><![CDATA[
Generate a RASA-structured question flow for: <CONVERSATION_GOAL>.
Interviewee profile: <ROLE/CONTEXT>.
Output format:
- Receive: [opening, set attention]
- Appreciate: [acknowledgment phrases]
- Summarize: [paraphrase starters]
- Ask: [5 open follow-up questions]
No yes/no questions. No "Is..." or "Do you..." openers.
      ]]></prompt>
      <prompt purpose="transcript-annotation"><![CDATA[
Annotate this conversation transcript.
For each interviewer turn: label as R/A/S/A (RASA), note if it's a closed question,
note if the interviewer speaks more than the interviewee in any 3-turn window.
Transcript: <TRANSCRIPT>
      ]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools and services that support transcript-based active listening workflows.</p>
      <list>
        <item>whisper (OpenAI) — Transcribe recorded conversations for post-analysis. Install: pip install openai-whisper</item>
        <item>pyannote.audio — Speaker diarization to separate interviewer vs. interviewee turns. Install: pip install pyannote.audio</item>
        <item>nltk — Word count and sentence type (interrogative) detection on transcripts. Install: pip install nltk</item>
        <item>Otter.ai (SaaS, REST API) — Speaker-labeled transcripts; agent can parse speaker turn ratios</item>
        <item>Dovetail (SaaS, partial REST API) — Tag transcript highlights with RASA labels</item>
        <item>Loom (SaaS, no API for transcript) — Video recording; use third-party transcription then agent analysis</item>
        <item>Fireflies.ai (SaaS, REST API) — Auto-transcription + meeting search; good for post-session analysis</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Build the question script before the conversation, but mark questions as "adaptable" — the script is a scaffold, not a reading list.</item>
        <item>For requirements gathering, use Mirroring (repeat last 1-3 words as a question) as a low-effort, high-yield technique; it is the easiest for a human to apply naturally without a script.</item>
        <item>Run the "closed-to-open" conversion on any existing requirement spec questions before a stakeholder session — most specs contain implicit yes/no questions.</item>
        <item>After the conversation, use the transcript annotation pass to identify which RASA steps were skipped (usually Summarize); feed that gap back into coaching notes.</item>
        <item>The "ask for advice or just vent?" technique from the Barriers section prevents misaligned responses; make it a default opener in sensitive conversations.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Agents generating "open" questions often produce questions that start with "What" or "How" but are still leading ("What problems did you have with X?" implies X caused problems). Check for embedded assumptions.</item>
        <item>Transcript word-count analysis does not account for sentence density — a human may say 20 words but pack in 3x the information of an agent's 60-word turn.</item>
        <item>Empathic reflection statements generated without knowing the interviewee's emotional context can land as condescending or inaccurate ("It sounds like you're frustrated..." when they were calm).</item>
        <item>Human checkpoint required: before acting on a synthesized requirements list derived from a transcript, a human must validate that the RASA annotations match the actual intent of the conversation.</item>
        <item>Silence (the 3-5 second pause) is the most effective active listening tool and the one completely absent from agent-driven text exchanges; compensate with explicit "Is there anything you'd like to add?" prompts.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Generating empathic reflection statements without knowing the interviewee's emotional context.</description>
      <reason>Statements like "It sounds like you're frustrated..." land as condescending or inaccurate when the person was calm. Reflection statements must respond to observed signals, not be pre-generated.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Using "What" or "How" openers for questions that still embed assumptions.</description>
      <reason>"What problems did you have with X?" assumes X caused problems. Check every open question for embedded assumptions before the session.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <section name="word-ratio-checker">
      <p>Word-ratio checker (measures whether interviewer dominated):</p>
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
def speaker_ratio(transcript: list[dict]) -> dict[str, float]:
    """
    transcript: list of {"speaker": "A"|"B", "text": "..."}
    Returns word share per speaker as float 0-1.
    """
    from collections import defaultdict
    counts: dict[str, int] = defaultdict(int)
    for turn in transcript:
        counts[turn["speaker"]] += len(turn["text"].split())
    total = sum(counts.values()) or 1
    return {k: round(v / total, 3) for k, v in counts.items()}

# Usage: if ratio["INTERVIEWER"] > 0.20 → flag as dominated
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/prompt-rasa-question-flow.txt" purpose="Prompt to generate a RASA-structured interview script for a given goal"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-transcript-annotation.txt" purpose="Prompt to annotate a transcript with RASA labels and quality flags"/>
      <template path="templates/speaker-ratio.py" purpose="Python snippet to measure interviewer word-share from a transcript"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.ccl.org/articles/leading-effectively-articles/coaching-others-use-active-listening-skills/"/>
      <link href="https://www.mindtools.com/CommSkll/ActiveListening.htm"/>
      <link href="https://fireflies.ai/api"/>
      <ref slug="mom-test"/>
      <ref slug="stakeholder-communication"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
