<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="minimum-product-frameworks">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>A selection matrix for choosing one of nine "minimum product" frameworks — MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC — before the first spec.md is written.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>minimum-product</tag>
      <tag>framework-selection</tag>
      <tag>product-strategy</tag>
      <tag>mvp</tag>
      <tag>market-strategy</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Minimum Product Frameworks</title>
    <summary>A selection matrix for choosing one of nine "minimum product" frameworks — MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC — before the first spec.md is written. The matrix maps market condition (blue/red ocean), buyer type (B2B/consumer), differentiator, and technical uncertainty to the right framework. Each choice must be versioned in a framework-choice.md with two explicit exit criteria before scoping begins.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>"Just build an MVP" is the wrong default in crowded markets where users already have "good enough" alternatives. In red oceans, MVP can be strategically suicidal: users will not switch without a lovable, marketable, or technically superior alternative. The matrix forces a defensible framework choice based on market evidence, not reflex.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>New product or major module — before the first spec.md exists.</item>
        <item>Team is reflexively saying "let's ship an MVP" without checking market density, buyer type, or differentiator.</item>
        <item>Pivot moment: current build is failing on retention or conversion — re-pick the framework before re-scoping.</item>
        <item>Multiple stakeholders disagree on what "minimum" means — use the matrix as a forcing function.</item>
        <item>Pre-investment or pre-board memo: justify the chosen framework against blue/red ocean and ICP positioning.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Methodology already chosen and validated — go straight to that framework's scoping doc; do not re-litigate.</item>
        <item>Pure feature work inside a shipped product — use release-planning, feature-prioritization-rice, or MoSCoW instead.</item>
        <item>Hard-deadline regulated launches where scope is dictated by compliance, not strategy.</item>
        <item>Tiny fix-it-fast tasks (&lt;1 sprint) — framework choice overhead exceeds value.</item>
        <item>Internal tools with one stakeholder — pick MFP and move on.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="the-nine-frameworks">
      <list>
        <item>MVP (Minimum Viable Product): test core assumptions in a new market with an unvalidated idea.</item>
        <item>MLP (Minimum Lovable Product): create emotional connection in a crowded market requiring differentiation.</item>
        <item>MMP (Minimum Marketable Product): generate revenue in B2B or enterprise sales contexts where a sellable surface is required.</item>
        <item>MAC (Minimum Awesome Component): differentiate via one killer feature where feature-based differentiation is the strategic bet.</item>
        <item>RAT (Riskiest Assumption Test): validate the biggest risk in a high-uncertainty project before any full build.</item>
        <item>MDP (Minimum Delightful Product): exceed expectations in a premium positioning context where delight is the brand promise.</item>
        <item>MVA (Minimum Valuable Product): deliver measurable business value in enterprise or ROI-focused contexts.</item>
        <item>MFP (Minimum Functional Product): prove technical feasibility first in complex technology or infrastructure projects.</item>
        <item>SLC (Simple, Lovable, Complete): balance simplicity and polish in consumer apps where all three attributes are simultaneously required.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="decision-matrix">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply the decision matrix: blue ocean unvalidated → MVP or RAT; red ocean many competitors → MLP or MAC; enterprise B2B → MMP or MVA; consumer emotion-driven → MLP or MDP; technical uncertainty → MFP then expand.</statement>
        <rationale>The default "MVP" is correct only in genuinely uncontested markets. In red oceans, users already have "good enough" alternatives — an MVP that is merely functional gives them no reason to switch.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every framework choice must include two explicit exit criteria — one quantitative (metric + threshold + measurement window) and one disqualifying kill criterion — before scoping begins. Without exit criteria the framework is decorative.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams pick "MLP" because it sounds nicer than "MVP" without changing scope. The exit criteria are the only mechanism that enforces the actual definition of "done enough to advance."</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pick exactly one framework per scope cycle. "MVP+MLP hybrid" is a hedge that produces neither validation rigor nor delight investment. Force the choice, then re-pick on the next pivot.</statement>
        <rationale>Hybrid choices distribute effort across two conflicting optimization targets — speed-of-learning (MVP) and quality-of-experience (MLP) — and optimize for neither.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="crowded-market-insight">
      <rule>
        <statement>When 3+ "good enough" competitors exist, the default framework flips to MLP or SLC. In crowded markets, "viable" is table stakes — users will not switch for a product that merely works.</statement>
        <rationale>Users in crowded markets bear switching costs (data migration, habit change, team retraining). They will absorb those costs only for a product that is clearly better on an emotional or economic dimension, not merely functional.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Reflexively choosing MVP without checking competitor density, buyer type, or differentiator.</description>
        <reason>"Just build an MVP" is a 2010s default that does not generalize to 2026 categories where AI-assisted competitors can clone functional surfaces in weeks. Framework choice must be grounded in market evidence.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="three-pass-selection-workflow">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pass 1 — Research: a market-researcher agent gathers competitor count, ICP, buyer type, switching cost, and risk profile into market-context.yml before the selection agent runs. Refuse to run the matrix if market-context.yml is missing or buyer is "unknown."</statement>
        <rationale>Agents lacking market context will default to MVP (training bias from 2010s startup canon). Requiring a completed market-context.yml as a pre-condition forces evidence-first selection.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pass 2 — Selection: a PM agent applies the decision matrix to market-context.yml, scores all nine frameworks, and emits framework-choice.md with the chosen framework, the rejected ones, and two exit criteria. Score every framework before naming the winner.</statement>
        <rationale>Scoring rejected frameworks forces honest disagreement rationale and prevents post-hoc justification of a predetermined choice.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pass 3 — Hand-off: the chosen framework's downstream methodology agent (mvp-scoping, mlp-planning, etc.) consumes framework-choice.md as its input contract. Abort and request re-pick if the choice file is older than 14 days or refers to a different framework.</statement>
        <rationale>Stale choice files decouple framework and scope; a sprint that starts with an outdated framework choice ships the wrong minimum product.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="re-pick-on-pivots">
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-run the matrix on every pivot — failed validation, missed activation target, or strategy shift. Append the new decision as a dated section in framework-choice.md; never rewrite history.</statement>
        <rationale>The pivot history is the most useful single input to next year's selection heuristics. Rewriting history destroys institutional memory about what conditions trigger which framework failures.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>MFP is a stepping stone, not a destination. Pre-commit the trigger that ends MFP (e.g., "first internal demo passes", "API latency &lt; 100ms at 1k RPS") before MFP work starts.</statement>
        <rationale>Without an explicit graduation trigger, teams stay in MFP indefinitely because "technical feasibility" is never fully resolved — there is always one more edge case.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Acronym soup as theatre: teams pick "MLP" because it sounds nicer than "MVP" without changing scope or adding exit criteria.</description>
        <reason>The framework name is irrelevant without a written exit criterion per framework. The choice is decorative unless it changes what gets built and when you stop.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Single-axis market read: using only blue/red ocean without considering buyer (B2B/consumer), distribution (PLG/sales-led), or regulatory load.</description>
        <reason>The nine-framework table under-specifies; in practice buyer type and distribution model often dominate the framework choice more than competitive density alone.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No transition rule: README says "MFP then expand" but doesn't define what triggers the transition (metric? time? validation event?).</description>
        <reason>Agents will sit in MFP forever without an explicit graduation trigger and acceptance criteria.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>MAC ambiguity: "Minimum Awesome Component" overlaps heavily with MLP and SLC; in red oceans a MAC often is the lovable hook, double-counting the same scope.</description>
        <reason>The methodology doesn't fully disambiguate MAC from MLP; agents may conflate them without additional context about the category.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>MVA vs MMP overlap: Both target enterprise/ROI; the methodology doesn't disambiguate.</description>
        <reason>In practice, MMP = sellable, MVA = measurable business value — agents conflate them without clear distinction.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No cost dimension: all nine frameworks treated as equally expensive in the decision matrix.</description>
        <reason>MLP and MDP cost 2-4x MVP for the polish budget; recommending MLP without surfacing the cost delta produces naive choices that surprise engineering in sprint planning.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Framework lock-in: Once "MLP" is in the deck, switching to RAT after a failed validation is socially expensive.</description>
        <reason>Methodology offers no de-escalation path. Re-picks should be reframed as learning, not failure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Survivorship-bias source: "MVP is suicide in 2026" is a strong claim drawn from crowded-SaaS storytelling; doesn't generalise to vertical SaaS, B2B niches, or dev-tools where MVPs still win.</description>
        <reason>The framework is weighted toward horizontal SaaS assumptions; vertical and deep-tech contexts may validate differently.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Treat the matrix as a routing decision, not a build instruction. Drive it with a 3-pass subagent flow: (1) a research agent gathers market-condition evidence (competitor count, alternatives, ICP, buyer, switching cost) — emits a structured market-context.yml; (2) a PM agent applies the decision matrix to that file and emits a framework-choice.md with the chosen framework, the rejected ones, and the exit criterion; (3) the chosen framework's downstream methodology agent (e.g. mvp-scoping, mlp-planning) consumes that file as its input contract. Re-pick on every pivot (failed validation, missed activation target). The choice file is versioned in .aidocs/product_docs/framework-choice.md — diffing it across pivots is the audit trail.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>faion-product-manager: orchestrator. Reads the matrix, calls research agent, emits the choice file.</item>
        <item>faion-market-researcher-agent: produces market-context inputs: competitor density, ICP, buyer type, switching cost. Required before the matrix can be applied.</item>
        <item>faion-research-agent modes validate, personas, pains: confirms the chosen framework's assumption (e.g. "users will pay for lovable" or "buyer cares about ROI").</item>
        <item>mvp-scoping / mlp-planning / sibling methodology agents: downstream consumers of the choice; one fires depending on the matrix output.</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent: converts the chosen framework's scope into a spec.md → design.md → tasks chain.</item>
        <item>brainstorm skill: diverge/converge when the matrix is genuinely tied between two frameworks (e.g. MLP vs MDP); avoids single-LLM lock-in.</item>
        <item>framework-pivot-detector agent (worth creating): re-runs the matrix when an activation/retention/win-rate metric crosses a threshold; emits a "re-pick recommended" alert with rationale.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <p>Framework selection pass:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a product manager applying the 9 minimum product frameworks
matrix. Inputs: <market-context.yml> and <icp.yml>.

For each of MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC:
- score 0-3 on fit with market_condition + buyer + differentiator
- list the single strongest reason for and against
Pick the top-1 with a 1-sentence rationale and write 2 explicit
exit criteria (metric + threshold). Output framework-choice.md.
Refuse to pick if any of: market_condition is missing, buyer is
"unknown", or two frameworks tie above score 2 — return
"need-discovery" and list the gap.]]></code>
      <p>Framework re-pick (post-pivot):</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a PM auditor. Inputs: framework-choice.md (current),
last-30-days metrics snapshot, post-mortem of the failed validation.

Decide: stay (state why), pivot to <framework> (state why and what
changes), or escalate (matrix can't decide — name the missing data).
No prose unless one of the three. Append decision to
framework-choice.md as a new dated section; never rewrite history.]]></code>
      <p>Framework hand-off to scoping:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are <chosen-framework>-scoping agent (e.g. mlp-planning).
Input: framework-choice.md. Constraint: do not re-litigate the
choice. Produce: scope.md with in/out lists, the one assumption
this framework is built to test, the kill-criterion. If the input
file is older than 14 days or refers to a different framework,
abort and request a re-pick.]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>gh CLI: PR-review the framework-choice.md so PM + founder co-sign. https://cli.github.com</item>
        <item>claude (Anthropic CLI): Run the 3-pass selection flow headlessly via cron / makefile target. https://docs.anthropic.com</item>
        <item>dbt / metabase: Encode framework exit criteria as SQL models so "did we hit MVP exit?" is auditable. https://docs.getdbt.com</item>
        <item>growthbook / statsig: Encode the RAT (riskiest assumption test) as a feature flag + experiment with a stop condition. https://docs.growthbook.io</item>
        <item>posthog (HogQL): Pull activation / retention / NPS for MLP and MDP exit-criterion verification. https://posthog.com/docs</item>
        <item>typeform / tally API: Cheap qualitative validation for MLP "lovable" claim before any code. https://www.typeform.com/developers</item>
        <item>productboard API: If used, sync the chosen framework + exit criteria to roadmap items. https://developer.productboard.com</item>
        <item>linear / jira API: Tag every initiative with the framework label; agents use it to filter. https://developers.linear.app</item>
        <item>notion API: Versioned framework-choice doc with comment-thread history. https://developers.notion.com</item>
        <item>pmf-survey (Sean Ellis) tooling: "How would you feel if you couldn't use this product?" — exit-criterion proxy for MVP→MLP transition. https://pmfsurvey.com</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <list>
        <item>Productboard (SaaS, API yes): Tag features by framework; agents filter MVP-vs-MLP scope.</item>
        <item>Aha! (SaaS, API yes): Roadmap layer; encode framework as a custom field.</item>
        <item>Linear / Jira (SaaS, API yes): Initiative-level framework tag; sprint planning respects it.</item>
        <item>Notion / Confluence (SaaS, API yes): framework-choice.md lives here when not in repo.</item>
        <item>Mixpanel / Amplitude / PostHog (SaaS / OSS, API yes): Exit-criterion measurement; agents pull cohorts for re-pick decisions.</item>
        <item>Hotjar / FullStory / LogRocket (SaaS, API limited): Qualitative signal for MLP/MDP "lovable / delightful" claims.</item>
        <item>Sprig / Survicate / Maze (SaaS, API yes): In-product surveys; cheap MLP validation without code changes.</item>
        <item>LaunchDarkly / GrowthBook / Statsig (SaaS / OSS, API yes): Encode RAT as a flag with a stop rule; agents control rollout.</item>
        <item>Userpilot / Appcues / Pendo (SaaS, API yes): MDP onboarding polish layer without engineering churn.</item>
        <item>ProductPlan (SaaS, API yes): Roadmap visualisation per framework type.</item>
        <item>Gainsight (SaaS, API yes): MMP / MVA buyers — track ROI-style adoption metrics.</item>
        <item>Reforge / Lenny's library (content, n/a): Framework selection essays; LLM context for prompt grounding.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pair every framework choice with two exit criteria — one quantitative (metric + threshold) and one disqualifying (kill-criterion). Without exit criteria the framework is theatre.</item>
        <item>Version the choice file in git, not Notion. framework-choice.md belongs next to the spec; pivots show as commits.</item>
        <item>Default to MVP only when market is genuinely uncontested. If 3+ "good enough" competitors exist, the default flips to MLP or SLC; "we'll iterate to lovable later" rarely happens.</item>
        <item>Pick exactly one framework per scope cycle. "MVP+MLP hybrid" is a hedge; force a single choice and let the next cycle re-pick.</item>
        <item>MFP is a stepping stone, not a destination. Pre-commit to the trigger (e.g. "first internal demo passes") that ends MFP and enters MVP/MLP.</item>
        <item>MMP / MVA need a sales letter before code. Write the buyer's purchase-justification memo first; if it doesn't read as compelling, the framework is wrong.</item>
        <item>Run a "framework retro" 30 days post-launch. Did the chosen framework's exit criteria fire? Was the rejected alternative actually better in hindsight? Feed back into selection heuristics.</item>
        <item>Keep MAC use rare. A killer feature without a product is a demo, not a business; require explicit founder sign-off before picking MAC.</item>
        <item>Score every framework, not just the winner. Forces honest disagreement rationale; hides nothing in the prompt log.</item>
        <item>In red oceans, lead with the differentiator type, not the framework. "Lovable, marketable, or delightful" is the real choice; MLP/MMP/MDP are wrappers.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Acronym hallucination: LLMs invent extra frameworks (MUP, MEP, MWP) under prompt pressure.</description>
        <reason>Constrain to the exact 9-row enum; reject any output naming a framework outside the list.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Default-to-MVP drift: Any LLM trained on 2010s startup canon will pick MVP unless explicitly told to consider crowded-market evidence.</description>
        <reason>Force the agent to print the matrix score per framework before naming the winner.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Crowded-market over-claim: Without competitor evidence, agents will declare every market "crowded" to justify MLP.</description>
        <reason>Require competitor_count + named competitors in market-context.yml; refuse to pick if missing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Exit-criterion vagueness: Agents emit "good user feedback" or "high adoption" as exit criteria.</description>
        <reason>Validate that each criterion has a metric, a threshold, and a measurement window.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Framework-then-justify failure: Agent picks first, rationalises second.</description>
        <reason>Mitigate by structured output: scores per framework BEFORE the chosen one, in a JSON schema the prompt enforces.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Confounding with mvp-scoping methodology: Agent jumps straight into in/out scope before picking the framework.</description>
        <reason>Pipeline must enforce: choice file exists → only then scoping methodology runs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Pivot inertia: Agent re-confirms the original framework even when metrics scream pivot.</description>
        <reason>Force a structured "stay vs pivot" decision with rejection-reason for the rejected option.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No human checkpoint on enterprise commitments: MMP/MVA implies sales contracts and SLAs — agents must not autonomously promote to these without a founder/PM sign-off step.</description>
        <reason>Add a human gate before MMP/MVA selection goes live.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hand-off contract drift: Downstream methodology agents read the choice file; if framework changes mid-cycle without re-running the downstream agent, scope and framework drift apart.</description>
        <reason>CI: hash the choice file in the spec front-matter; mismatch fails the build.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>2026-claim staleness: README says "in 2026 MVP is suicide in crowded markets" — agents will quote this verbatim in pitches.</description>
        <reason>Phrase it as a heuristic, not a law, to avoid over-confident decks.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="pick-framework-script">
      <p>The README ships only the matrix table. The missing artefact is a machine-readable framework-choice file the downstream agents can consume. The pick-framework.sh script is intentionally rule-based (not LLM) so the choice is auditable; the LLM agent fills the exit-criteria stubs and reviews the rationale.</p>
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[#!/usr/bin/env bash
# pick-framework.sh — apply the 9-framework matrix to a market-context file.
# Inputs: .aidocs/product_docs/market-context.yml
# Output: .aidocs/product_docs/framework-choice.md (versioned via git)
set -euo pipefail
ctx=".aidocs/product_docs/market-context.yml"
out=".aidocs/product_docs/framework-choice.md"
[ -f "$ctx" ] || { echo "missing $ctx — run market-researcher agent first" >&2; exit 2; }
mkdir -p "$(dirname "$out")"
python3 - "$ctx" "$out" <<'PY'
import sys, yaml, datetime
ctx = yaml.safe_load(open(sys.argv[1])); out = sys.argv[2]
m = ctx.get("market_condition", "").lower(); b = ctx.get("buyer", "").lower()
diff = ctx.get("differentiator", "").lower(); tech = ctx.get("tech_uncertainty", False)
rules = [
    (lambda: tech, "MFP", "Technical feasibility unknown — prove infra first."),
    (lambda: "enterprise" in b or "b2b" in b, "MMP", "Enterprise buyer needs sellable surface."),
    (lambda: "crowded" in m or "red ocean" in m, "MLP", "Crowded market — emotional differentiation required."),
    (lambda: "premium" in diff or "luxury" in diff, "MDP", "Premium positioning needs delight."),
    (lambda: "high uncertainty" in ctx.get("risk_profile", "").lower(), "RAT", "Validate riskiest assumption before scope."),
    (lambda: "consumer" in b and "simple" in diff, "SLC", "Consumer + simplicity — Simple/Lovable/Complete."),
    (lambda: True, "MVP", "Default: blue ocean, low cost, fast learning."),
]
chosen, why = next((f, w) for cond, f, w in rules if cond())
with open(out, "w") as f:
    f.write(f"# Framework choice — {datetime.date.today().isoformat()}\n\n")
    f.write(f"**Chosen:** {chosen}\n\n**Rationale:** {why}\n\n")
    f.write("## Inputs\n```yaml\n" + yaml.safe_dump(ctx) + "```\n\n")
    f.write("## Exit criteria\n- TODO: define metric + threshold\n- TODO: define kill-criterion\n")
    f.write("\n## History\n- " + datetime.date.today().isoformat() + f": initial pick = {chosen}\n")
print(out, chosen)
PY
git add "$out"]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="hand-off-contracts">
      <p>Framework choice ↔ downstream. Artifacts, owners, readers, formats, and cadence:</p>
      <list>
        <item>market-context.yml: owned by market-researcher agent, read by PM agent, YAML in .aidocs/product_docs/, per scope cycle.</item>
        <item>framework-choice.md: owned by PM agent, read by mvp-scoping / mlp-planning / RAT agents, markdown dated history, per scope cycle, append-only.</item>
        <item>Exit-criteria block (inside choice file): owned by PM, read by analytics agent, YAML inside markdown, reviewed weekly.</item>
        <item>Re-pick decision: owned by framework-pivot-detector, read by PM and founder, new section in choice file, triggered by metric breach.</item>
        <item>Framework retro: owned by PM, read by team, .aidocs/product_docs/retros/&lt;date&gt;.md, 30 days post-launch.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/framework-choice.md" purpose="Versioned choice document skeleton: chosen framework, rationale, exit criteria, history section."/>
      <template path="templates/pick-framework.sh" purpose="Bash + Python: rule-based first-pass framework selection from market-context.yml; emits choice file for LLM review."/>
    </templates>
    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/pick-framework.sh" purpose="Applies decision rules to market-context.yml; writes framework-choice.md; commits it to git."/>
    </scripts>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com"/>
      <link href="https://www.syncdev.com/minimum-viable-product/"/>
      <link href="https://blog.crisp.se/2016/01/25/henrikkniberg/making-sense-of-mvp"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
