<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026 Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For product teams in 2026, default to Figma (design/collaboration/handoff) + Firefly Services API (asset generation) as a combined stack.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The two platforms are complementary, not mutually exclusive. Figma REST API offers the richer agent-automation surface. Firefly provides commercial-safe image generation. Using both eliminates the need to choose.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Revisit the platform decision every 6 months — tie the review to Figma Config and Adobe MAX annual conferences.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Both platforms ship major AI feature changes at their annual conferences. Any comparison older than 6 months may reference retired or renamed features. Quarterly refresh keeps the decision current.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document the toolchain decision in the project's AGENTS.md so agents operating on the project know which APIs to target.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents cannot discover which platform a team uses from code alone. An explicit entry in AGENTS.md prevents agents from targeting the wrong API (Figma vs. Adobe) when automating design tasks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agents produce the toolchain analysis; humans make the final platform decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tool selection involves expertise, team culture, and migration cost that cannot be fully captured in a scoring rubric. Agent output is a structured input to the decision, not the decision itself.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide team size, subscription tier, and task list as explicit inputs — agents cannot discover these from code.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents cannot access Figma billing or Adobe license information. Without explicit inputs, the agent will hallucinate or guess plan capabilities incorrectly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
