<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-comparison" title="Figma vs Adobe 2026 Platform Comparison">
  <summary>Market position, 2026 strategy focus, and decision rules for platform selection.</summary>

  <section title="Market Position">
    <list>
      <item>Figma — core strength: collaboration and UI; AI focus: workflow automation; target: product teams; pricing: per-seat; integration: API-first</item>
      <item>Adobe CC — core strength: visual creation and enterprise; AI focus: content generation (Firefly); target: creative professionals; pricing: Creative Cloud bundle; integration: suite-integrated</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="2026 Strategy Focus">
    <list>
      <item>Figma: end-to-end product development platform, AI-driven design and prototyping, developer handoff optimization, design system management</item>
      <item>Adobe: content creation powerhouse, Firefly across all CC apps, enterprise licensing, multimedia production</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Decision Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>For product teams in 2026, default to Figma (design/collaboration/handoff) + Firefly Services API (asset generation) as a combined stack.</statement>
      <rationale>The two platforms are complementary, not mutually exclusive. Figma REST API offers the richer agent-automation surface. Firefly provides commercial-safe image generation. Using both eliminates the need to choose.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Revisit the platform decision every 6 months — tie the review to Figma Config and Adobe MAX annual conferences.</statement>
      <rationale>Both platforms ship major AI feature changes at their annual conferences. Any comparison older than 6 months may reference retired or renamed features. Quarterly refresh keeps the decision current.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Document the toolchain decision in the project's AGENTS.md so agents operating on the project know which APIs to target.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents cannot discover which platform a team uses from code alone. An explicit entry in AGENTS.md prevents agents from targeting the wrong API (Figma vs. Adobe) when automating design tasks.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying a product-team comparison to a creative agency workflow.</description>
      <reason>"Best tool" conclusions do not transfer across team types. A product team prioritizes collaboration and dev handoff; a creative agency prioritizes asset creation and multimedia output. Use team-type-specific weights.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Including pricing data from training data in a recommendation.</description>
      <reason>Pricing structures change. Always fetch current pricing from official sources before including it in a recommendation — per-seat vs. bundle calculations depend on team size and current plan tiers.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
