<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026 Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026 as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Applying a product-team comparison to a creative agency workflow.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"Best tool" conclusions do not transfer across team types. A product team prioritizes collaboration and dev handoff; a creative agency prioritizes asset creation and multimedia output. Use team-type-specific weights.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Including pricing data from training data in a recommendation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pricing structures change. Always fetch current pricing from official sources before including it in a recommendation — per-seat vs. bundle calculations depend on team size and current plan tiers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Referencing AI feature names rather than capabilities in automation scripts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Both platforms have changed their AI feature names multiple times since 2024. Prompt patterns should reference capabilities (e.g., "text-to-vector generation") not product names (e.g., "Firefly Draw") that may be renamed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Assuming Adobe Creative Cloud API is headless for automation pipelines.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Adobe CC automation via UXP requires a human session inside a CC app. Purely headless pipelines must use Firefly Services (enterprise only). Standard CC plans have no headless automation surface.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
