<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-architecture" title="fail2ban Architecture">
  <summary>fail2ban components on Ubuntu 24.04: jails combine filter + log source + thresholds + action; nftables backend bans IPs; systemd journal is the log source for services logging to journald.</summary>

  <section title="Component Pipeline">
    <p>Log files or systemd journal → fail2ban-server → filters match patterns → jails count matches → actions ban/unban via nftables.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use backend=systemd for services that log to journald (sshd on Ubuntu 24.04). Use backend=auto for services with explicit log files (nginx). Never set logpath when using backend=systemd — it is silently ignored.</statement>
      <rationale>The systemd backend reads the journal directly; there is no log file path. Including logpath with backend=systemd triggers a warning and may prevent the jail from starting correctly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Configuration Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never edit jail.conf or fail2ban.conf. Create all customizations in jail.local (global defaults) and jail.d/*.conf (per-jail drop-ins). These survive package upgrades.</statement>
      <rationale>jail.conf is overwritten on package upgrade. jail.local and jail.d/ files are preserved. This mirrors the sshd_config.d/ pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>/etc/fail2ban/jail.local — global defaults (bantime, findtime, maxretry, ignoreip, backend, banaction)</item>
      <item>/etc/fail2ban/jail.d/*.conf — per-jail drop-ins</item>
      <item>/etc/fail2ban/filter.d/*.conf — filter regex patterns</item>
      <item>/etc/fail2ban/action.d/*.conf — ban/unban actions</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="nftables Backend">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set banaction=nftables and banaction_allports=nftables[type=allports] in [DEFAULT]. Ubuntu 24.04 uses nftables as the default firewall backend; mixing iptables and nftables rules causes conflicts.</statement>
      <rationale>fail2ban defaults to iptables on older systems. Ubuntu 24.04 uses nftables via UFW. Setting the nftables banaction explicitly ensures fail2ban's bans integrate correctly with the existing ruleset.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Key CLI Commands">
    <list>
      <item>sudo fail2ban-client status — show all jails and summary</item>
      <item>sudo fail2ban-client status sshd — detailed jail status with banned IPs</item>
      <item>sudo fail2ban-client set sshd unbanip 1.2.3.4 — unban a specific IP</item>
      <item>sudo fail2ban-client reload — reload config without clearing ban state (use instead of restart)</item>
      <item>sudo fail2ban-regex /var/log/nginx/access.log /etc/fail2ban/filter.d/nginx-botsearch.conf — test filter</item>
      <item>sudo nft list ruleset | grep -A5 "f2b" — inspect active nftables ban rules</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use fail2ban-client reload (not restart) after config changes. reload preserves existing ban state; restart clears all bans.</statement>
      <rationale>Restarting fail2ban unbans all currently banned IPs, giving active attackers an immediate window to reconnect.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
