<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-jail-configs" title="Jail Configurations">
  <summary>Standard jail configurations for SSH, nginx, and recidive ban escalation — with recommended thresholds and the ignoreip whitelist required before enabling any jail.</summary>

  <section title="ignoreip Whitelist">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always whitelist localhost, Docker networks (172.16.0.0/12, 10.0.0.0/8), your static IP, VPN subnet, and all Cloudflare IP ranges BEFORE enabling any jail. A misconfigured whitelist bans you immediately on first nginx scan.</statement>
      <rationale>fail2ban bans based on log patterns without geographic awareness. Your own monitoring tools, Docker containers, and Cloudflare proxy IPs all generate traffic that matches scanner patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/jail.local">Global jail.local with ignoreip and nftables backend</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="SSH Jail">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure SSH jail with maxretry=3, findtime=600, bantime=3600. Use filter=sshd[mode=aggressive] to catch invalid user attempts in addition to failed passwords.</statement>
      <rationale>3 failures in 10 minutes is aggressive enough to block brute-force (which tries hundreds per minute) while allowing legitimate multi-key authentication failures without permanent lockout.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/jail-sshd.conf">SSH jail drop-in config</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="nginx Jails">
    <list>
      <item>nginx-http-auth — catches 401 errors from nginx basic auth (error.log)</item>
      <item>nginx-botsearch — catches 404 probes for vulnerability paths (access.log), maxretry=10</item>
      <item>nginx-limit-req — catches nginx rate limit violations (error.log)</item>
      <item>nginx-bad-request — catches malformed HTTP requests, 400 responses (access.log)</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/jail-nginx.conf">nginx jails drop-in config</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Recidive Jail (Ban Escalation)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure the recidive jail: if an IP is banned 3 times in 24 hours, ban it for 1 week on ALL ports using banaction=nftables[type=allports]. recidive requires /var/log/fail2ban.log to exist — logtarget must not be set to journal-only.</statement>
      <rationale>Short bans (1h) do not deter persistent scanners. Recidive escalates to a week-long all-ports block for IPs that return after being banned, effectively removing persistent attackers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/jail-recidive.conf">Recidive jail drop-in config</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Ban Time Escalation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable bantime.increment=true in [DEFAULT] with bantime.factor=2 and bantime.maxtime=604800 to automatically double ban time for repeat offenders within the same jail, up to 1 week maximum.</statement>
      <rationale>Linear ban times do not deter automated scanners. Exponential escalation per IP makes repeated attempts progressively more costly without manual intervention.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
