<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-custom-filters" title="Custom Filters and Cloudflare">
  <summary>Writing custom failregex patterns for application-specific log formats, testing filters with fail2ban-regex, and fixing the Cloudflare real-IP problem where proxy IPs are banned instead of actual attackers.</summary>

  <section title="Custom Filter Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place custom filters in /etc/fail2ban/filter.d/&lt;name&gt;.conf with a [Definition] section containing failregex patterns. Use &lt;HOST&gt; as the placeholder for the IP address. Test every filter with fail2ban-regex before enabling the jail.</statement>
      <rationale>An unmatched filter silently produces zero bans — there is no error. fail2ban-regex validates the pattern against real logs before deployment, showing match count and sample matched lines.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="ini"><![CDATA[
# /etc/fail2ban/filter.d/webapp-auth.conf
[Definition]
failregex = ^<HOST> -.*"POST /api/auth/login.*" 401
            ^<HOST> -.*"POST /api/auth/token.*" 401
ignoreregex = ^<HOST> -.*"GET /api/auth/refresh.*" 401
]]></code>
      <note>datepattern may need to be set if the log format uses non-standard timestamp formatting.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Testing Filters">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run fail2ban-regex against the actual log file before enabling any jail. Check that the match count is non-zero and that the IP capture group works (shows actual IPs, not empty). A zero exit code does not mean matches were found — check stdout.</statement>
      <rationale>fail2ban-regex returns exit 0 even if no matches are found. Agents and operators must read the match count line explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
sudo fail2ban-regex /var/log/nginx/access.log /etc/fail2ban/filter.d/webapp-auth.conf
# Check output for:
# Failregex: N total  (must be > 0)
# Sample matched: 185.x.x.x -... "POST /api/auth/login..." 401
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Cloudflare Real-IP Problem">
    <rule>
      <statement>When nginx is behind Cloudflare, configure nginx real_ip module with Cloudflare's IP ranges and real_ip_header CF-Connecting-IP so nginx logs the actual client IP. Without this, fail2ban bans Cloudflare proxy IPs, blocking all traffic through that proxy.</statement>
      <rationale>Cloudflare forwards traffic from a small set of well-known IP ranges. If nginx logs the Cloudflare proxy IP instead of the real client IP, fail2ban will ban Cloudflare itself, disrupting all CDN-proxied traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="nginx"><![CDATA[
# /etc/nginx/nginx.conf — http block
set_real_ip_from 103.21.244.0/22;
set_real_ip_from 103.22.200.0/22;
set_real_ip_from 103.31.4.0/22;
# ... add all current Cloudflare ranges from https://www.cloudflare.com/ips-v4
real_ip_header CF-Connecting-IP;
]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hardcoding Cloudflare IP ranges in nginx or fail2ban ignoreip. Cloudflare's IP ranges change over time.</description>
      <reason>Fetch the live list with: curl https://www.cloudflare.com/ips-v4. Stale hardcoded ranges miss new Cloudflare IPs and create silent gaps.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
