<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="E-commerce Checkout BA Pack Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules with rationale + source for ecommerce-checkout-ba-pack. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="flow-states-enumerated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pack MUST enumerate all 12 checkout states: cart, address, shipping, summary, payment-init, 3DS / SCA, payment-confirmed, order-created, receipt-sent, error, retry, abandon-recovery; missing states are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="PCI DSS + PSD2 SCA flow">PCI DSS + PSD2 SCA flow — applies to E-commerce Checkout BA Pack.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="edge-case-catalogue" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pack MUST contain at least 25 edge cases: declined card, 3DS challenge fail, partial stock, address-validation fail, currency mismatch, tax exempt, discount stack collisions, etc. Each carries trigger + expected handling.</statement>
      <rationale source="E-commerce checkout failure research">E-commerce checkout failure research — applies to E-commerce Checkout BA Pack.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="nfr-thresholds" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>NFR table MUST pin: time-to-interactive &lt; 3s, payment authorisation &lt; 5s P95, error-rate &lt; 0.5% P50, abandonment &lt; industry median; each backed by an observable metric.</statement>
      <rationale source="Web vitals + payment-provider SLAs">Web vitals + payment-provider SLAs — applies to E-commerce Checkout BA Pack.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="regulatory-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pack MUST include regulatory checklist: PSD2 SCA, GDPR consent, PCI DSS scope, OSS/IOSS (EU), local-tax-id capture if B2B, age-verification if regulated goods.</statement>
      <rationale source="PSD2 + GDPR + PCI DSS">PSD2 + GDPR + PCI DSS — applies to E-commerce Checkout BA Pack.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="psp-integration-spec" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For each payment provider, pack pins: API version, webhook contract, retry policy, idempotency key strategy, refund flow, dispute flow.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stripe / Adyen / Mollie API references">Stripe / Adyen / Mollie API references — applies to E-commerce Checkout BA Pack.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="a11y-min-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Checkout MUST meet WCAG 2.2 AA: keyboard nav, ARIA labels, contrast ratios, error-recovery hints, no time-limited steps without warning.</statement>
      <rationale source="WCAG 2.2 AA">WCAG 2.2 AA — applies to E-commerce Checkout BA Pack.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="test-data-set" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pack ships test-data set for every PSP: success card, declined card, 3DS-required card, refundable scenario, dispute scenario.</statement>
      <rationale source="PSP sandbox documentation">PSP sandbox documentation — applies to E-commerce Checkout BA Pack.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the engagement is not e-commerce or has no checkout flow, return `skipped`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to E-commerce Checkout BA Pack.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
