<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="strategy-analysis-current-state Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for strategy-analysis-current-state. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Current-state assessment MUST cover all six areas: business processes, organization structure, technology landscape, people and skills, data and information, and external factors. Skipping any one area MUST be documented as a known gap with an owner and a resolution plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Skipping any one area is the most reliable failure mode of strategy analysis; the omitted area typically surfaces in the gap analysis as an unplanned dependency that delays delivery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A stakeholder coverage matrix MUST be produced before current-state sign-off. Rows are the six areas; columns are stakeholder roles; each cell records "interviewed: yes/no" and an evidence link. Empty rows block sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without the matrix, the BA cannot demonstrate that the current state is representative rather than the view of the loudest voices in the room.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every PESTLE cell MUST cite a primary source (regulator publication, industry report, the org's own telemetry, financial filings) stamped retrieved_at. Cells citing secondary synthesis or agent-generated prose without a primary source MUST be flagged for re-elicitation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tech-landscape and PESTLE evidence go stale fast; vendor websites can plant favorable framing. Primary sources with dates allow the BA to defend the evidence under audit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
