<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="immersive-design-principles">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>Framework for XR/AR/VR/MR design covering immersion-level selection, motion-comfort mitigations, accessibility coverage per WAI XAUR, spatial layout rules, and performance floors.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>xr-design</tag>
      <tag>vr</tag>
      <tag>ar</tag>
      <tag>immersive</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Immersive Design Principles</title>
    <summary>A framework for XR/AR/VR/MR experience design covering immersion-level selection (passthrough, blended, fully immersive, portal), motion-comfort mitigations (vignette, snap turn, teleport, grounding), comfort settings completeness, spatial layout rules, and WAI XAUR accessibility coverage. Default every new experience to highest-comfort settings; let users opt into lower comfort.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Poor immersive design causes motion sickness, disorientation, fatigue, and safety issues that drive users to abandon a session and not return. Visual-vestibular mismatch is the primary failure mode — it is caused by smooth locomotion without a stable reference frame, frame rates below 90 FPS, or latency above 20 ms. Accessibility omissions (no seated mode, no captions, no voice commands) exclude large user populations and violate WAI XAUR.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing or auditing VR/AR/MR/passthrough experiences across Meta Quest, Apple Vision Pro, PSVR2, PICO, HoloLens.</item>
        <item>Choosing the right immersion level for a use case.</item>
        <item>Reviewing comfort settings, locomotion, grounding, and motion-sickness mitigations before user testing.</item>
        <item>Making spatial UIs accessible across vision, hearing, mobility, and cognitive needs.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure 2D web/mobile work — use `wcag-22-compliance` and `a11y-basics` instead.</item>
        <item>Hardware/optics tuning (IPD, lens distortion) — those live in the engine/SDK layer.</item>
        <item>Game-feel tuning where intentional motion sickness is a deliberate design choice.</item>
        <item>Conversion-rate optimization for XR storefronts — adjacent topic, not this skill.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="immersion-level-taxonomy">
      <p>Four levels, each with distinct design constraints: Passthrough (real world plus overlays; AR navigation, information overlay); Blended (mixed real and virtual; MR workspace with virtual monitors, productivity, collaboration); Fully Immersive (complete virtual environment; VR game, training simulation); Portal (windows into virtual space; VR meeting room view with easy exit).</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Name the immersion level explicitly before designing any spatial experience. Never conflate passthrough and fully immersive — their comfort, interaction, and accessibility constraints are different.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents conflate VR (occluded) and AR (passthrough); design decisions for one cause harm when applied to the other.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="spatial-depth-zones">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Place UI elements and interactive controls in the near zone (0.5-2 m), main content and interactive objects in the mid zone (2-10 m), and scenery in the far zone (10 m and beyond).</statement>
        <rationale>Objects placed outside their appropriate depth zone cause eye strain (too near) or interaction failure (too far); depth zones match natural human vergence and accommodation ranges in XR.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Never head-lock UI elements. Use world-locked or body-locked panels at 1.5-3 m, eye level.</statement>
        <rationale>Head-locked UI follows every head movement and causes immediate nausea; world-locked UI stays stable as the user looks around.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="motion-and-transitions">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Implement realistic motion physics: gravity, momentum, inertia, collision feedback, and synchronized haptics. Couple every visual transition with an audio and haptic cue.</statement>
        <rationale>Visual transitions without audio or haptic cues cause vestibular surprise — the brain expects multimodal confirmation of environment changes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Prefer user-initiated transitions over automatic ones; use gradual fade in/out (not instant) with audio cues and visual mode indicators.</statement>
        <rationale>Sudden mode changes without user agency are a primary source of disorientation and loss of presence.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Respond to physical space: adjust content to room size, warn about obstacles, reposition UI for comfort, and adapt to lighting conditions when in passthrough or blended modes.</statement>
        <rationale>Ignoring physical context in blended and passthrough modes creates collision risk and UI overlap with physical objects.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="motion-sickness-mitigations">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Default every new XR experience to the highest-comfort settings; let users opt into lower comfort, never the opposite.</statement>
        <rationale>A 5-10% nausea-prone subgroup will fail experiences that test fine on the rest; conservative defaults protect the most sensitive users without restricting others.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always offer at least two locomotion methods (teleport plus smooth, or teleport plus seated). Pin teleport-as-default; smooth is opt-in with vignette on.</statement>
        <rationale>Smooth locomotion without teleport excludes motion-sensitive users and wheelchair users; agents recommend smooth as the "modern" default and must be explicitly corrected.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Motion sickness: fixed reference points (cockpit, dashboard, ground plane), vignetting during movement, teleportation instead of smooth movement.</item>
        <item>Disorientation: consistent horizon, north indicator, stable floor and ground plane always visible.</item>
        <item>Eye strain: proper convergence distance, focal point guidance, correct depth of field.</item>
        <item>Arm fatigue: supported positions, alternative inputs, rest prompts at intervals.</item>
        <item>Simulator sickness: maintain 90+ FPS and under 20 ms latency; reduce scene complexity before dropping frame rate.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="performance-floors">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Minimum 90 FPS per eye for VR; 60 FPS minimum for AR. Maximum 20 ms head-tracking latency and 50 ms controller latency. Drop visual fidelity before dropping below the FPS floor.</statement>
        <rationale>Dropping below the performance floor causes simulator sickness regardless of all other design decisions; frame rate is non-negotiable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="scale-and-grounding">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use human-scale for familiar objects (doors 2 m, tables 70-75 cm, chairs 45 cm). When scaling differently, make it obvious with a size reference (human for scale) and gradual transition.</statement>
        <rationale>Unexpected scale breaks depth perception and comfortable interaction; scale ambiguity is disorienting.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep the floor/ground plane visible at all times with consistent appearance; maintain a stable horizon. These are the two primary grounding cues that reduce nausea.</statement>
        <rationale>Loss of ground plane causes floating feeling and disorientation; an unstable horizon is the single fastest driver of vestibular mismatch.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="guardian-and-play-space">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Implement a guardian/chaperone system: visual boundary when approaching walls, haptic warning, audio alert option, pause on boundary crossing, easy re-centering.</statement>
        <rationale>Physical collisions with real-world objects are a safety hazard; guardian systems are the standard mitigation across all major XR platforms.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="vision-accessibility">
      <list>
        <item>High contrast mode with toggle.</item>
        <item>Large text options; minimum readable size is larger in XR than on screen — test at the actual viewing distance.</item>
        <item>Audio descriptions for all informative visual elements.</item>
        <item>Haptic feedback as alternative to visual-only signals.</item>
        <item>Voice navigation for all interactions.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="hearing-accessibility">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Add visual captions in 3D space for all audio-cued events; captions must be size- and position-adjustable.</statement>
        <rationale>Spatial-audio captions are commonly omitted; require a captions story for every voiced or audio-cued event in design review.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Haptic feedback synchronized with sound events.</item>
        <item>Visual indicators (directional flash) for audio alerts from off-screen sources.</item>
        <item>Per-source volume controls.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="mobility-accessibility">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Seated mode must be fully functional: every interaction reachable while seated, all content viewable without standing or walking. Wheelchair-user parity is a hard requirement, not an afterthought.</statement>
        <rationale>Seated mode is the most commonly omitted accessibility feature in room-scale VR design; agents skip it unless explicitly checked.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Teleportation for all movement (not just as comfort option).</item>
        <item>Voice commands for all actions.</item>
        <item>Controller-free options where platform supports hand tracking.</item>
        <item>Adjustable height settings to accommodate different physical heights and seated postures.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cognitive-accessibility">
      <list>
        <item>Simplified UI mode with reduced information density.</item>
        <item>Clear, step-by-step instructions; no assumed prior XR experience.</item>
        <item>Pauseable experiences with no time pressure during paused state.</item>
        <item>Difficulty adjustment where applicable.</item>
        <item>Memory aids: hints, reminders, progress indicators.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="wai-xaur-compliance">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Treat WAI XAUR (W3C XR Accessibility User Requirements) as the requirements floor, not a nice-to-have. It covers disability cases that vendor design guidelines miss.</statement>
        <rationale>Platform-vendor guidelines (Meta, Apple, Valve) are consensus documents that lag novel interaction patterns; XAUR is the authoritative accessibility requirements source for XR.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Default every new XR experience to the highest-comfort settings; let users opt into lower comfort, never the other way.</item>
        <item>Always offer at least two locomotion methods (teleport + smooth, or teleport + seated).</item>
        <item>Never head-lock UI; world-locked or body-locked panels at 1.5–3 m, eye-level.</item>
        <item>Run a 30-minute extended-session test before shipping — short demos hide fatigue and drift.</item>
        <item>Couple every visual transition with audio + haptic cue to reduce vestibular surprise.</item>
        <item>Treat WAI XAUR as the requirements floor, not a nice-to-have — it covers cases vendor docs miss.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-platforms">
      <p>Agents should be familiar with these tools for XR design and implementation:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Unity XR Interaction Toolkit — Built-in locomotion, comfort vignette, snap turn.</item>
        <item>Unreal OpenXR + VR Template — Unreal equivalent, includes teleport + comfort.</item>
        <item>WebXR Device API + three.js — Browser XR experiences.</item>
        <item>OVRMetricsTool — Quest perf overlay (FPS, latency, GPU/CPU).</item>
        <item>Apple Reality Composer Pro — Vision Pro spatial layout previewing.</item>
        <item>W3C XAUR Checklist — Reference accessibility requirements.</item>
        <item>Meta Horizon Developer Hub — Quest perf + crash data.</item>
        <item>Apple App Store Connect — visionOS reviews, crash reports.</item>
        <item>Unity Cloud / DeepLink — XR analytics + remote config for comfort defaults.</item>
        <item>Fmod / Wwise — Spatial audio integration; agent can author event banks.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow-and-limitations">
      <p>Use the methodology as a checklist for design review and a generator for comfort/accessibility settings menus. Agents drive the structured passes (immersion-level fit, locomotion options matrix, grounding/horizon presence, comfort settings completeness) and emit a punch list. Human XR designers and at least one motion-sensitive tester gate any approval. Code-level checks (FPS budget, latency, controller mapping) belong to engine-specific subagents (Unity, Unreal, WebXR), not this one.</p>
      <p>Guidelines are platform-vendor consensus; novel XR form factors (smart glasses, AR contact lenses, neural inputs) outpace them. Frame-rate / latency floors (90 FPS, &lt;20ms motion-to-photon) are device-class assumptions — mobile AR has different floors. "Comfort" is heavily individual: a 5% nausea-prone subgroup will fail experiences that test fine on the rest. Accessibility recs here overlap `vr-design-patterns`, `ar-design-patterns`, `spatial-accessibility` — agents must avoid duplicate work. Most heuristics are not testable from code alone — require headset + human or in-headset analytics.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Agents conflate VR (occluded) and AR (passthrough) — force the agent to name the immersion level explicitly before designing.</item>
        <item>LLMs propose smooth locomotion as the "modern" default and forget teleport — pin teleport-as-default in the prompt.</item>
        <item>Comfort claims like "reduces nausea by 30%" are unsupported; require citation or remove.</item>
        <item>Agents skip seated-mode coverage for room-scale designs — explicit "wheelchair user reaches all controls seated" check.</item>
        <item>Spatial-audio captions are commonly omitted; require a captions story for every voiced/audio-cued event.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoints: motion-sensitive tester pass, accessibility partner review, perf-budget sign-off (90 FPS Quest 3, 90 FPS Vision Pro, 60 FPS for AR phone).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/comfort-settings.json" purpose="Default comfort-settings schema for XR experiences (locomotion, visual, audio, interaction)."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.oculus.com/resources/bp-overview/"/>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/designing-for-visionos"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xaur/"/>
      <link href="https://docs.unity3d.com/Packages/com.unity.xr.interaction.toolkit@latest"/>
      <link href="https://dev.epicgames.com/documentation/en-us/unreal-engine/vr-template-in-unreal-engine"/>
      <link href="https://immersiveweb.dev"/>
      <ref slug="vr-design-patterns"/>
      <ref slug="ar-design-patterns"/>
      <ref slug="spatial-accessibility"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
