<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="05-examples" title="Traceability Tooling Comparison (Jira / ADO / Polarion) Worked Example" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>One end-to-end worked example for Traceability Tooling Comparison (Jira / ADO / Polarion). Shows the artefact filled against a realistic input set.</summary>

  <section title="Scenario">
    <p>
      A pro-tier operator is running the recurring activity tied to Traceability Tooling Comparison (Jira / ADO / Polarion). The named consumer is the engagement
      owner; inputs are pinned to the operator's source-of-truth (engagement file, ticket tracker, decision log).
      The operator applies the procedure and produces a versioned artefact.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Inputs">
    <list>
      <item>Triggering activity: recent instance within the last 30 days, recorded in the engagement file.</item>
      <item>Named consumer: engagement owner (handle + email).</item>
      <item>Source-of-truth: <code>engagements/&lt;client-slug&gt;/2026-05-23.md</code>.</item>
      <item>Prior cycle's artefact (if any) for trend comparison.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Walk-through">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — preconditions check passes; Applies-If satisfied, no Skip-If triggers.</item>
      <item>Step 2 — three inputs gathered and pinned with stable paths.</item>
      <item>Step 3 — every rule from 01-core-rules walked; conformance recorded; one rule initially fails (defensive rationale) and is repaired by adding an input citation.</item>
      <item>Step 4 — template under <code>templates/</code> filled; output validates against the JSON Schema from 02-output-contract.</item>
      <item>Step 5 — validator exits 0; artefact handed to the named consumer with a "ready for owner review" flag.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Result">
    <p>
      The named consumer signs off in &lt; 1 review cycle because the artefact is owner-named, input-cited, and
      schema-valid. The artefact is versioned 1.0.0 with <code>last_reviewed = 2026-05-23</code>; the next refresh
      will bump version per the change-class rule.
    </p>
  </section>
</text>
