<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="mobile-ux-basics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Mobile-first design methodology covering touch target sizing, thumb-zone placement, navigation patterns, form optimization, performance budgets, and platform conventions (iOS vs Android).</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>mobile-ux</tag>
      <tag>mobile-first</tag>
      <tag>touch-design</tag>
      <tag>responsive-design</tag>
      <tag>performance</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>mobile</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Mobile UX Basics: Touch Design, Navigation, and Performance</title>

    <summary>A mobile-first design methodology covering touch target sizing, thumb-zone placement, navigation patterns, form optimization, performance budgets, and platform conventions (iOS vs Android). Start with the smallest screen, expose only essential features, then enhance for larger viewports. Touch targets must be at least 44x44pt (iOS) or 48x48dp (Android) with 8px spacing between them. Lock the codebook before coding begins; adding themes mid-study invalidates cross-participant comparison.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Desktop designs scaled down fail on mobile: touch targets are too small, primary actions fall outside the thumb zone, and 53% of users abandon pages that load in over 3 seconds. Mobile context (partial attention, short sessions, variable network) demands a distinct design approach, not a responsive rescaling of a desktop layout.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Auditing an existing mobile experience for thumb-zone, touch-target, performance, and platform-convention compliance.</item>
        <item>Pre-launch checklist enforcement before each mobile release: Lighthouse mobile score, accessibility, touch-target sizes.</item>
        <item>Code review for mobile-affecting PRs: flagging small touch targets, hidden navigation, blocking JS, missing input types.</item>
        <item>Cross-platform parity reviews: same flow on iOS vs Android — list of platform-convention divergences.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Greenfield strategic mobile design — start with research (interviews, diary studies) before applying basics; this knowledge is downstream.</item>
        <item>Native-only platform-specific work where Apple HIG / Material 3 are the primary reference — load those directly.</item>
        <item>Single-component visual polish — that is UI/visual design feedback, not mobile-UX methodology.</item>
        <item>No mobile users in the product's audience — effort is wasted on unused contexts.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="mobile-first-approach">
      <rule>
        <statement>Design for the smallest screen first, identify core content and features, then add enhancements for larger screens.</statement>
        <rationale>Designing for mobile first forces focus on essential content. Scaling down a desktop design produces a cramped, unusable result because mobile has fundamentally different input, attention, and network constraints.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="mobile-context-factors">
      <p>Mobile context is fundamentally different from desktop:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Attention: partial attention, frequent interruptions — never rely on sustained focus.</item>
        <item>Time: short sessions, quick tasks — design for task completion in under 60 seconds for core flows.</item>
        <item>Location: variable environments (sun glare, one-handed use, movement).</item>
        <item>Connection: slow or unreliable network — 53% of users abandon if load exceeds 3 seconds.</item>
        <item>Input: touch, sometimes voice — no hover, no right-click, no precision pointer.</item>
        <item>Screen: small and varying sizes with high pixel density.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="five-key-principles">
      <rule>
        <statement>Provide exactly one primary action per screen.</statement>
        <rationale>Multiple competing actions force users to make decisions under the cognitive constraints of mobile context (partial attention, glare, movement). One primary action removes this decision.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Place primary actions in the thumb zone (lower third of screen).</statement>
        <rationale>Reachability for one-handed use is physical. Primary actions placed in the hard-to-reach upper zone increase task abandonment on phones held in the dominant hand.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Focus: one primary action per screen.</item>
        <item>Simplify: reduce choices and steps.</item>
        <item>Speed: fast loading, instant feedback.</item>
        <item>Reachability: important actions in the thumb zone (lower third).</item>
        <item>Context: leverage device capabilities (GPS, camera, biometrics).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="platform-differences">
      <rule>
        <statement>Follow platform conventions for navigation, modals, and primary actions — do not port iOS patterns to Android or vice versa.</statement>
        <rationale>Users have strong mental models from their platform. Cross-platform pattern violations produce "feels wrong" friction that is impossible to attribute in usability tests but measurable in task success rates.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Navigation: iOS uses bottom tab + back gesture; Android uses bottom nav + system back button.</item>
        <item>Touch targets: iOS minimum 44x44pt; Android minimum 48x48dp; spacing 8px between targets.</item>
        <item>Modals: iOS uses bottom sheets; Android uses full-screen overlays or dialogs.</item>
        <item>Primary actions: iOS right side of screen; Android floating action button.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="touch-targets">
      <rule>
        <statement>Minimum touch target: 44x44pt (iOS) or 48x48dp (Android). Minimum spacing between targets: 8px. Apply to all interactive elements including links, icons, and checkboxes.</statement>
        <rationale>Human finger pad is 40-60px wide. Targets smaller than 44pt produce 30-50% higher error rates on touch input. Insufficient spacing causes adjacent-target mis-taps even when individual targets meet the minimum size.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/touch-target-audit.js">Playwright script detecting touch targets below threshold at iPhone 13 viewport.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="navigation-patterns">
      <rule>
        <statement>Choose navigation pattern based on section count: bottom tab bar for 3-5 main sections; hamburger menu only for many infrequently-accessed sections.</statement>
        <rationale>Bottom tab bar is the highest-discoverability mobile navigation pattern. Hamburger menus hide navigation and increase task completion time by 2-3 steps for any navigation action.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Bottom tab bar: 3-5 main sections with roughly equal usage frequency.</item>
        <item>Hamburger menu: many sections where most are rarely accessed.</item>
        <item>Tab bar: 2-5 content types within one section.</item>
        <item>Gesture navigation: supplement to visible controls, never the sole means of navigation.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="forms">
      <rule>
        <statement>Set the correct HTML input type for every form field. Use inputmode and autocomplete attributes to trigger the right keyboard and enable autofill.</statement>
        <rationale>Wrong keyboard type (e.g., alphabetic for phone number) is the highest-leverage 5-minute mobile fix. Users must dismiss and reopen keyboards when the wrong type appears, which inflates form abandonment by 10-20%.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Minimize required fields to the absolute minimum for the task.</item>
        <item>Show progress for multi-step forms.</item>
        <item>Enable autofill via correct autocomplete attributes.</item>
        <item>Show/hide password toggle on password fields.</item>
        <item>Clear, inline error messages immediately after invalid input.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="gestures">
      <rule>
        <statement>Always provide a visible alternative for every gesture. Never rely on a gesture as the sole way to trigger an action.</statement>
        <rationale>Gestures are invisible affordances. Users who do not discover them fall back to alternative paths or abandon the task. Discoverability requires a visible control paired with an optional gesture shortcut.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Tap: select or activate — always the primary interaction.</item>
        <item>Swipe horizontal: navigate or reveal actions — pair with visible navigation controls.</item>
        <item>Pull down: refresh — pair with a visible refresh button.</item>
        <item>Pinch: zoom — provide visible zoom controls for accessibility.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="accessibility">
      <rule>
        <statement>Respect prefers-reduced-motion media query on all animations. Flag components missing this handling in code review.</statement>
        <rationale>Vestibular disorders affect 35% of adults over 40. Animations that ignore reduced-motion preferences cause dizziness and nausea, making the product unusable for a significant subset of mobile users.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Touch targets: 44x44pt minimum (doubles as accessibility requirement).</item>
        <item>Screen reader: VoiceOver (iOS) and TalkBack (Android) support required.</item>
        <item>Text size: respect system font-size settings; do not force fixed sizes.</item>
        <item>Color contrast: WCAG AA minimum (4.5:1 for normal text, 3:1 for large).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="core-web-vitals">
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat Core Web Vitals as PR-blocking budgets: LCP below 2.5s, INP below 200ms, CLS below 0.1. Test on a Slow-3G throttle profile — the median real-world mobile connection is closer to Slow-3G than fast-4G.</statement>
        <rationale>53% of mobile users abandon pages taking more than 3 seconds to load. LCP is the primary user-perceived load metric. INP (Interaction to Next Paint) replaced FID in 2024 as the responsiveness standard. CLS measures layout stability — high CLS causes accidental taps on wrong elements.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>LCP (Largest Contentful Paint): below 2.5s — largest visible content rendered.</item>
        <item>INP (Interaction to Next Paint): below 200ms — responsiveness to user input.</item>
        <item>CLS (Cumulative Layout Shift): below 0.1 — layout stability during load.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="optimization-techniques">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run audits at three viewports minimum: 360x640 (small Android), 390x844 (iPhone), 768x1024 (tablet). Single-viewport audits miss responsive breakpoint bugs.</statement>
        <rationale>Responsive sites have breakpoint-specific behavior. A touch-target that passes at iPhone size may fall below threshold at the 360px Android viewport where content reflows differently.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Images: WebP format, responsive srcset, lazy loading, explicit width and height to prevent CLS.</item>
        <item>JavaScript: code splitting, defer non-critical, minimize bundle size.</item>
        <item>Network: service worker caching, CDN, Brotli compression.</item>
        <item>Loading states: skeleton screens instead of blank content areas during fetch.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ci-integration">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use the median of 3 Lighthouse runs before failing a PR. Lighthouse scoring is non-deterministic on variable networks; a single run produces false failures.</statement>
        <rationale>Lighthouse variance is 5-15 points on performance score depending on CPU load and network simulation. A median-of-3 approach reduces false failures from CI infrastructure variability.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Report both field data (CrUX, RUM) and lab data (Lighthouse) in performance reports. Lab-only reports create false confidence when real-user conditions differ from the test environment.</statement>
        <rationale>Lab tests use consistent throttling profiles. Real users have diverse device capabilities and network conditions. A 90th-percentile CrUX LCP of 4s on a page with a 2.2s Lighthouse LCP means your lab is not representative of your actual user population.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="testing-matrix">
      <rule>
        <statement>Test on at minimum: one recent iPhone, one recent Android flagship, one budget Android (Moto G or equivalent). Budget Android is the highest-leverage device for catching performance regressions.</statement>
        <rationale>Budget Android devices have CPU speed 5-10x slower than flagship devices. Performance issues that are invisible on a Pixel 7 become critical failures on a Moto G. If your product has users in emerging markets, budget Android IS your median device.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>iPhone (recent model + one generation old): iOS platform behavior.</item>
        <item>Android flagship (Pixel or Samsung): Android platform behavior.</item>
        <item>Budget Android (Moto G or similar): performance on constrained hardware.</item>
        <item>Tablet (iPad, Android tablet): layout at larger mobile viewport.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Run as a CI-integrated audit: a static-analysis agent parses HTML/Flutter/React Native/SwiftUI source for touch-target sizes, input types, navigation patterns, and gesture handlers; a dynamic-analysis agent runs Lighthouse + Playwright at multiple mobile viewports producing perf + accessibility reports; a synthesis agent reconciles findings into a prioritized issue list keyed to the mobile-UX checklist. Human reviewers triage P1 issues; agents auto-file P2/P3 as tickets.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>`faion-ux-researcher-agent` — owns the checklist, performs heuristic-style review.</item>
        <item>`faion-frontend-developer` (from `solo/dev/frontend-developer`) — translates UX findings into specific code changes (CSS, component props, breakpoints).</item>
        <item>`faion-accessibility-specialist` (from `pro/ux/accessibility-specialist`) — runs WCAG + mobile-AT-specific checks (VoiceOver, TalkBack rotor).</item>
        <item>`faion-cicd-engineer` — wires Lighthouse + axe + Playwright budgets into PR gates.</item>
        <item>`faion-conversion-optimizer` — analyzes mobile funnel drop-off vs UX issues.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="source-review-prompt-pattern">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Component source: {tsx_or_swift_or_kotlin}
Viewport context: 360x640 mobile.
Check: touch targets ≥44x44pt, input types appropriate to data type, no hover-only affordances, primary actions in thumb zone (lower 1/3), no horizontal overflow.
Output JSON list of {issue, severity, line, fix_hint}.]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="funnel-and-ux-correlation-pattern">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[GA4 funnel by device: {funnel_json}
UX audit findings: {audit_json}
Map drop-off steps to UX findings. Output: step, drop_rate, candidate UX cause, evidence_link.]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>Tools and services for mobile UX audit:</p>
      <list>
        <item>`lighthouse` / `lhci`: Mobile perf + a11y + best-practices scoring. Install: `npm i -g @lhci/cli lighthouse`.</item>
        <item>`axe-core` (`@axe-core/cli`): A11y violation detection at multiple viewports. Install: `npm i -g @axe-core/cli`.</item>
        <item>Playwright: Multi-viewport, multi-device emulation. Install: `npm i -D @playwright/test`.</item>
        <item>`webhint`: Best-practice scanner (pwa, perf, a11y). Install: `npm i -g hint`.</item>
        <item>Chrome DevTools Protocol (CDP): Custom audits (touch-target measurement, thumb-zone heatmap). Ref: https://chromedevtools.github.io/devtools-protocol/</item>
        <item>`react-native-debugger` / `flipper`: Native-app inspection. Ref: https://github.com/jondot/awesome-react-native#debugging</item>
        <item>Xcode `xcrun simctl`: iOS simulator automation. Bundled with Xcode.</item>
        <item>`adb`: Android device automation. Android SDK platform tools.</item>
        <item>`pa11y-ci`: Accessibility CI gate. Install: `npm i -g pa11y-ci`.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="saas-services">
      <p>Services and apps for mobile testing and monitoring:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Lighthouse CI Server (OSS): Self-hosted perf budgets per branch.</item>
        <item>BrowserStack / Sauce Labs (SaaS): Real-device cloud testing via APIs.</item>
        <item>Firebase Test Lab (SaaS): Android device farm; pricing-friendly gcloud CLI integration.</item>
        <item>WebPageTest (SaaS + OSS): Real-network mobile testing (3G Slow, Edge) via REST API.</item>
        <item>CrUX (Chrome UX Report) (SaaS): Field metrics from real users via BigQuery + REST.</item>
        <item>SpeedCurve (SaaS): Continuous mobile perf monitoring with API.</item>
        <item>Maze + Lookback (SaaS): Mobile usability sessions on real devices.</item>
        <item>App Store Connect / Play Console (SaaS): Crash + ANR data correlated with UX via APIs.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Run audits at three viewports minimum: 360x640 (small Android), 390x844 (iPhone), 768x1024 (tablet). Single-viewport audits miss responsive breakpoint bugs.</item>
        <item>Treat Core Web Vitals targets (LCP &lt;2.5s, INP &lt;200ms, CLS &lt;0.1) as PR-blocking budgets, not aspirations.</item>
        <item>Test on a Slow-3G throttle profile in Lighthouse; the median real-world mobile connection is closer to slow-3G than to fast-4G.</item>
        <item>Verify `inputmode` and `autocomplete` attributes on form fields — these are the highest-leverage 5-minute mobile fixes available.</item>
        <item>Check thumb-zone reachability dynamically: primary CTA position relative to viewport bottom matters more than absolute pixel coordinates.</item>
        <item>Reduced-motion respect: agents should grep for `prefers-reduced-motion` queries and flag missing handling on animation-heavy components.</item>
        <item>Always cross-reference Apple HIG and Material 3 specs directly when platform conventions are at stake — README is generic.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Headless browsers don't render `:hover`, `:active`, or `prefers-color-scheme: dark` realistically. Run audits with explicit emulation flags, not defaults.</item>
        <item>Lighthouse scoring is non-deterministic on flaky networks; use median-of-3 runs in CI before failing a PR.</item>
        <item>Touch-target measurement misses elements with hit-area expanded via `::before` pseudo-elements or padding tricks. Pair geometric measurement with manual spot-check.</item>
        <item>Native (iOS/Android/RN/Flutter) source analysis requires platform-specific subagents; a generic web-trained agent will misread `Pressable` props or `UIButton` configuration.</item>
        <item>LLM-generated mobile recommendations frequently cite outdated patterns (e.g., "use a hamburger menu") that current research shows underperform. Cross-check against NNg's recent mobile-nav research.</item>
        <item>Performance and UX findings get conflated in reports; keep them in separate sections — fixes have different owners (frontend vs platform vs design).</item>
        <item>Field data (CrUX, RUM) and lab data (Lighthouse) should both appear in reports; agents that only ship lab numbers create false confidence.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/touch-target-audit.js" purpose="Playwright script that flags tap targets smaller than 44x44 at iPhone 13 viewport."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/"/>
      <link href="https://m3.material.io/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/mobile-ux/"/>
      <link href="https://web.dev/vitals/"/>
      <link href="https://web.dev/articles/inp"/>
      <ref slug="responsive-design"/>
      <ref slug="accessibility-basics"/>
      <ref slug="web-performance"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
