<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Growth SEO Fundamentals Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Growth SEO Fundamentals application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-technical-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Fix Technical SEO blockers (crawlability, indexability, Core Web Vitals, HTTPS, canonicals) BEFORE investing in On-Page or Off-Page work. The pillar order is Technical → On-Page → Off-Page; reversing it spends content + link budget on a site that cannot rank.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source 2026-05-20">A single critical Technical issue (robots.txt blocking, no sitemap, broken canonicals) creates a ranking ceiling no amount of content or backlinks can break.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-match-search-intent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Classify the target query's intent (Informational / Commercial / Transactional / Navigational) BEFORE writing the page; produce the content format that matches the intent. A how-to guide ranking for a comparison query under-performs regardless of keyword density.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source 2026-05-20">Google ranks for user satisfaction, not keyword matching. Format mismatch causes high bounce, which signals low quality and demotes the page.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-on-page-baseline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every indexable page MUST satisfy the on-page baseline: title ≤60 chars with primary keyword, meta description 120-160 chars, single H1 containing the keyword, URL slug short + hyphenated, ≥1 descriptive internal link, ≥1 authoritative external citation, schema markup appropriate to the page type.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source 2026-05-20">These elements collectively signal what the page is about and demonstrate authority + relevance; missing any one of them removes a ranking signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-link-quality-over-quantity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Acquire links by quality, not volume: one editorial link from a DR ≥60 relevant site outweighs 50 directory / forum links. Refuse purchased links, link farms, and excessive reciprocal-linking schemes; they trigger algorithmic + manual penalties.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source 2026-05-20">Google's link evaluator considers authority, relevance, anchor naturalness, and placement; low-quality patterns risk Penguin-style demotion or manual action.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-monthly-baseline-metrics" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track these five metrics monthly: organic traffic month-over-month, keywords ranking in top 10, domain authority on a 6-12-month trend, Core Web Vitals (all green in CrUX), organic CTR (≥3%). Stagnation in any one signals a pillar-level bottleneck to investigate before adding work.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source 2026-05-20">These five metrics span all three pillars; reporting on one in isolation hides which pillar is failing and routes effort to the wrong fix.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-28 chunk-02 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
