<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-three-pillars" title="SEO Three Pillars">
  <summary>The three interdependent SEO pillars — Technical, On-Page, Off-Page — and their audit checklists.</summary>

  <section title="Pillar 1: Technical SEO">
    <rule>
      <statement>Fix technical SEO blockers before investing in content or link building — a site that cannot be crawled and indexed ranks for nothing regardless of content quality.</statement>
      <rationale>Technical issues (blocked robots.txt, noindex tags, crawl errors) create a ceiling that content and backlinks cannot overcome. The order of operations matters: Technical first, On-Page second, Off-Page third.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Crawlability: robots.txt allows important pages (test in Search Console)</item>
      <item>Indexability: key pages appear in site:domain.com search</item>
      <item>Performance: Core Web Vitals pass (LCP, INP, CLS)</item>
      <item>Mobile: passes Google Mobile-Friendly Test</item>
      <item>HTTPS: SSL certificate installed, no mixed content</item>
      <item>Structure: XML sitemap exists and submitted to Search Console</item>
      <item>Canonicalization: no duplicate content, correct canonical tags</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>robots.txt with "Disallow: /" blocking all crawling</description>
      <reason>This is the single most common technical SEO disaster — frequently introduced during development and left deployed. Results in zero indexed pages. Always verify robots.txt before and after any site launch.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Pillar 2: On-Page SEO">
    <rule>
      <statement>Match search intent before optimizing for keywords — content that mismatches what the searcher wants will not rank regardless of keyword density.</statement>
      <rationale>Google's ranking objective is user satisfaction, not keyword matching. Informational intent queries need guides/explainers; commercial intent needs comparisons/reviews; transactional intent needs product pages. Intent mismatch causes high bounce rates that signal low quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Title tag: primary keyword + benefit, under 60 characters</item>
      <item>Meta description: compelling summary, 120-160 characters</item>
      <item>URL: short, keyword-rich, hyphen-separated</item>
      <item>H1: single H1 containing primary keyword</item>
      <item>Content: covers topic completely, beats competitors in depth</item>
      <item>Internal links: link to related pages with descriptive anchor text</item>
      <item>External links: cite authoritative sources (signals trustworthiness)</item>
      <item>Schema markup: Article, Organization, FAQ as appropriate</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Pillar 3: Off-Page SEO">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize link quality over quantity: one link from a DR 60 relevant site outweighs 50 links from DR 20 irrelevant directories.</statement>
      <rationale>Google's link quality assessment considers domain authority, relevance, anchor text naturalness, and link placement. High-volume low-quality link building can trigger algorithmic or manual penalties.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Guest posting on relevant, high-authority publications</item>
      <item>Resource link building: resource pages in your niche</item>
      <item>HARO / journalist queries: inbound high-authority links</item>
      <item>Digital PR and original research: links from media coverage</item>
      <item>Avoid: buying links, link farms, excessive reciprocal linking</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Organic traffic: growing month-over-month</item>
      <item>Keywords in top 10: increasing count</item>
      <item>Domain authority: growing over 6-12 month horizon</item>
      <item>Core Web Vitals: all green in Search Console</item>
      <item>Click-through rate: above 3% for organic listings</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
