<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-content-optimization" title="Content Optimization">
  <summary>Search intent classification, content depth requirements, keyword optimization, and freshness rules for on-page SEO.</summary>

  <section title="Search Intent Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify search intent before writing content — create the format that matches what the searcher expects to find.</statement>
      <rationale>A page targeting "best project management tools" that is structured as a how-to guide (not a comparison) will rank poorly even with perfect keyword optimization, because the format mismatches the informational + commercial intent behind the query.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Informational: how-to guides, explainers, definitions ("what is RAG")</item>
      <item>Commercial investigation: comparisons, reviews, "best X" lists</item>
      <item>Transactional: product pages, pricing pages, sign-up flows</item>
      <item>Navigational: brand-specific searches — optimize for brand terms</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Depth">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cover the topic completely — include all subtopics and related questions that top-ranking competitors cover, plus at least one angle they do not.</statement>
      <rationale>Google's ranking assesses comprehensiveness relative to competing pages. A page missing sections that all competitors include will be ranked lower as less authoritative on the topic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Analyze top 3 SERP results: word count, sections covered, questions answered</item>
      <item>Extract "People Also Ask" questions and answer them in the article</item>
      <item>Cover edge cases and advanced scenarios that thin content ignores</item>
      <item>Add unique value: original research, first-hand experience, contrarian angle</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Freshness">
    <rule>
      <statement>Update outdated content with new information and change the "last updated" date — do not publish duplicate new articles when a refresh would serve the same purpose.</statement>
      <rationale>Google rewards freshness for queries where recency matters. A refreshed authoritative article with existing backlinks outperforms a new article with no backlinks targeting the same keyword.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Keyword stuffing — repeating the target keyword unnaturally throughout the content</description>
      <reason>Google penalizes keyword stuffing as a spam signal. Semantic search understands topical relevance without keyword repetition; natural language performs better.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Targeting high-volume keywords without assessing difficulty</description>
      <reason>New or low-authority sites cannot rank for competitive head terms. Starting with long-tail keywords (lower volume, lower difficulty) builds authority that eventually enables ranking for head terms.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Expecting SEO results within weeks</description>
      <reason>New content takes 3-6 months to rank; authority building takes 12+ months. Abandoning SEO due to no visible results at 30 days is the most common reason SEO investments fail.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
