<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Affinity Diagramming Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Affinity Diagramming application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="silent-first-pass" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>First clustering pass MUST be silent — no naming, no discussion. Groups emerge only after every card is placed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Affinity-diagramming literature">Pre-naming biases placement; silent sort produces honest groups.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="label-after-cluster" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cluster labels are written AFTER the silent pass. Pre-existing labels are erased and re-derived from cards.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cluster-naming discipline">Pre-existing labels recruit cards that don't belong, distorting the cluster shape.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="orphan-bucket" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cards that don't fit any cluster go to a labelled 'orphan' bucket — never forced into the nearest cluster. Orphans ≥5% of total trigger re-clustering.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mis-clustering avoidance">Forced placement hides outlier signals; orphan rate is a quality metric.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="size-confidence-per-cluster" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each cluster carries size (card count) and confidence (distinct sources × recency). Single-source clusters are tagged 'anecdotal'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Confidence-calibration practice">Stakeholders default to high-confidence reading without explicit confidence bands.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="segment-tag-preserved" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each cluster carries the segment distribution of its cards. Cross-segment clusters are flagged and reviewed for split.</statement>
      <rationale source="Segment-awareness discipline">Cross-segment clusters merge incompatible jobs and dilute the theme.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
