<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Container Image Digest Pinning Policy Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>≥5 testable rules grounding the image-digest-pinning-policy methodology, each paired with rationale and source reference.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="prod-manifests-by-digest" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production Kubernetes manifests and Helm values MUST pin container images by sha256 digest, never by floating tag.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Floating tags allow upstream re-tag to inject new code into running clusters; digests are immutable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="registry-allow-list" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin only images from the org-approved registry allow-list; mirror upstream images into a controlled registry before pinning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Pinning to an unmirror'ed external registry creates a single-vendor uptime dependency for the cluster.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rotation-cadence-documented" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each image class has a documented maximum-age (e.g. 30 days for base, 7 days for CI runners) and a rotation owner.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Pinning without rotation is the documented foot-gun — old digests stop receiving CVE fixes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="exception-register" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any unpinned tag in production lives in an exception register with an owner, expiry date and remediation plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Exceptions exist; an undocumented exception is indistinguishable from a violation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="admission-gate-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cluster admission (Kyverno / OPA / built-in policy) rejects pods whose images are not digest-pinned in the relevant namespaces.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Policy-as-code is the only durable enforcement; reviewer discipline alone has measurable slippage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, do NOT run this methodology — return early with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree's negative branch must terminate cleanly without partial output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold AND scope is explicit, run the methodology end-to-end and produce the canonical artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree positive-branch terminus; aliases the apply-end-to-end verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
