<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Trade-off Decision Methods Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the trade-off-decision-methods methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale; the final rule is the skip-this-methodology gate referenced by the decision tree.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-matrix-is-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Weighted decision matrix MUST be the default method. Other methods MUST be chosen only when matrix limitations are documented (multi-attribute conflicts, deep uncertainty, time-driven payoff, strategic positioning).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal method-selection audits.">Matrix is the cheapest defensible method; defaulting elsewhere produces ceremony without payoff.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-atam-for-multi-attribute" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ATAM MUST be selected when the decision involves &gt; 2 quality attributes with documented conflict (perf vs sec vs cost), or when stakeholder breadth is cross-org and audit-defensibility matters.</statement>
      <rationale source="SEI ATAM publications.">ATAM produces utility trees + scenarios + tradeoffs that a flat matrix cannot capture.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-cost-of-delay-for-time-driven" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cost of Delay MUST be applied when payoff is time-sensitive (market window, regulatory deadline, dependency chain). The decision MUST quantify $/week of delay.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reinertsen — Principles of Product Development Flow.">Time-driven decisions are systematically deprioritised when only weighted matrix is used; CoD surfaces hidden cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-wardley-for-strategic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Wardley Mapping MUST be applied when the decision spans strategic positioning, build-vs-buy of evolving capabilities, or commodity-vs-custom routing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Simon Wardley — Wardley Mapping.">Wardley maps reveal evolution-stage mismatches that matrix scoring misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-real-options-for-uncertainty" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Real Options framing MUST be applied when uncertainty is high, the decision is reversible-with-cost, and waiting carries documented value (information arrival). Decision MUST quantify the option value vs commit-now value.</statement>
      <rationale source="Real Options literature; Black-Scholes-inspired strategy.">High-uncertainty decisions optimised by weighted matrix often commit prematurely; Real Options models the value of waiting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When prerequisites hold (question, options, uncertainty, breadth), apply r1 → r5 and emit the ADR.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology design — gate rule.">Order encodes default → exception escalation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do NOT use when (a) single option, (b) routine reversible choice, (c) hard mandate. Exit with note.</statement>
      <rationale source="Preconditions — skip gate.">Method-routing ceremony for trivial decisions wastes review.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
