<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-ceremony-rules" title="Agile Ceremony Rules and Time-Boxes">
  <summary>Mandatory constraints for all five Scrum events: time-boxes by sprint length, single sprint goal, Definition of Ready/Done, and action-item closure threshold.</summary>

  <section title="Time-Box Reference">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never run a ceremony past its time-box; end on time even if the agenda is incomplete — incomplete items become backlog.</statement>
      <rationale>Ceremonies that overrun erode trust in the process; the team learns that the schedule is fictional and stops preparing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Time-boxes by sprint length: Planning: 2h/4h/8h for 1wk/2wk/4wk. Daily: 15min always. Review: 1h/2h/4h. Retro: 45min/90min/3h. Refinement: 1-2h/2-4h/4-8h.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Sprint Goal">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write one sprint goal per sprint, before selecting backlog items. Reject a goal that does not answer "what changes for users?"</statement>
      <rationale>Without a sprint goal, the daily standup becomes a status report and the team has no shared criterion for success. LLM-generated goals tend to be vacuous ("complete sprint backlog") — reject them by the same test.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Definition of Ready and Done">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply Definition of Ready at refinement (acceptance criteria, dependencies, estimate, fits in sprint, testable). Apply Definition of Done at planning. Both must be agreed before the first sprint begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Without DoR, sprint scope is undecided at planning start. Without DoD, done means different things to developer, tester, and stakeholder.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Retro Action-Item Closure">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Track retro actions as backlog items tagged with their originating sprint. If closure rate falls below 70% over three consecutive sprints, declare the retro format broken and change it.</statement>
      <rationale>Retros where actions are never implemented produce cynicism faster than no retro at all. The 70% threshold is a measurable signal that the format is working.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Ceremony Overhead Ceiling">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Total ceremony time per person must not exceed 10% of sprint capacity. Audit the calendar every quarter; kill any recurring meeting where more than 20% of attendees would not voluntarily opt in.</statement>
      <rationale>Beyond 10%, the team trades delivery time for coordination overhead without proportional benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
