<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-event-setup" title="Per-Event Setup and Tool Configuration">
  <summary>Agendas and PM tool config for Sprint Planning, Daily Standup, Sprint Review, Retrospective, and Backlog Refinement.</summary>

  <section title="Sprint Planning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Split planning into two parts: Part 1 (what) — review goal, top items, acceptance criteria. Part 2 (how) — break stories into tasks, estimate, identify dependencies, commit. Each part gets equal time.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing what and how in a single session causes scope confusion; the team commits before understanding the work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Jira setup: backlog view + sprint-planning mode, filter "status = Ready AND sprint IS EMPTY", show story points + AC + priority. Linear setup: new cycle with dates, backlog filter "state:backlog", priority sort.</p>
    <reference path="templates/sprint-planning.md">Sprint planning artifact template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Daily Standup">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer walk-the-board format over three-questions format: start from the rightmost column, discuss each in-flight item, identify blocks. Focus on flow, not individuals.</statement>
      <rationale>Walk-the-board surfaces WIP age and blocking dependencies visually; the classic three-questions format produces individual status reports the team reads serially.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Update the board in real time during standup; never let a standup pass without moving cards. The tool is the record of the event.</statement>
      <rationale>A standup that doesn't touch the board is theater; the board and the conversation must stay synchronized.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Sprint Review">
    <rule>
      <statement>Sprint Review must include real users or external stakeholders, not only the dev team. An internal-only review is waste.</statement>
      <rationale>The purpose of the review is stakeholder feedback that adjusts the backlog; internal audiences cannot provide it. Stakeholder participation is mandatory per Scrum Guide 2020.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Agenda: welcome 5min, sprint goal recap 5min, demos 45min, feedback 15min, backlog discussion 15min, next preview 5min. Metrics to display: sprint goal met, story points completed, velocity trend.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Retrospective">
    <rule>
      <statement>Rotate retro format every 4-6 sprints (Start-Stop-Continue, 4Ls, Sailboat, Mad-Sad-Glad). Rotate the facilitator each sprint.</statement>
      <rationale>Fixed format produces diminishing returns; rotation keeps the exercise fresh and distributes facilitation skill across the team.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/retrospective.md">Retrospective artifact template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Backlog Refinement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Planning Poker for estimation: everyone votes secretly, reveal simultaneously, discuss only the outliers, re-vote if needed. Consensus must be recorded in the tool before the session ends.</statement>
      <rationale>Simultaneous reveal prevents anchoring on a first estimate; discussing outliers surfaces missing context without silencing quieter team members.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>T-shirt sizing map: XS=1pt, S=2-3pt, M=5pt, L=8pt, XL=13+ (must be split before committing). Any item over L at refinement is rejected from the next sprint until split.</p>
  </section>
</text>
