<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-remote-async" title="Remote and Async Ceremony Patterns">
  <summary>Timezone-aware ceremony design: async standup constraints, distributed team rules, ceremony health measurement.</summary>

  <section title="Async Standup Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Async standup prompts must focus on goal-progress and blockers, not "what did you do yesterday". Reject prompts that produce individual status reports.</statement>
      <rationale>Status questions produce status answers; goal-progress questions keep the team aligned on the sprint goal rather than individual task lists.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use tz-aware scheduling for async standups; recalculate after daylight-saving transitions. Naive UTC offsets break twice a year.</statement>
      <rationale>A standup that works in March may exclude APAC or Eastern Europe after the DST shift. Encode acceptable hours per participant in the bot config.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/standup-bot.yaml">Geekbot-compatible async standup configuration</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Distributed Team Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maximum one sync ceremony per day for distributed teams; Sprint Planning and Retrospective may share a day, but no more than two sync events back-to-back.</statement>
      <rationale>Zoom fatigue compounds across sessions; more than one long sync per day collapses participation quality by the second event.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Any global recurring meeting must either rotate its time across quarters or run two sessions. Document the rotation schedule in the team calendar.</statement>
      <rationale>A fixed "Tue 10:00 UTC" permanently excludes APAC time zones from meaningful participation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Ceremony Health Measurement">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Run a ceremony health survey (1-5 scale) every quarter. Track: time-box compliance, sprint-goal-met rate, retro action closure rate, velocity stability. Trigger a retro on ceremonies if any metric scores below 3.</statement>
      <rationale>Without measurement, ceremony decay is invisible until the team openly refuses to attend. Quantified health scores make the problem surfaceable before that point.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ceremony rituals re-imported when a team has moved to flow-based delivery.</description>
      <reason>Sprint cadence imposed on a Kanban team adds overhead without benefit; the team "does Scrum ceremonies for Kanban" and cargo-cults both methods badly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
