<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="cloudflare-domain-dns">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>server-craft</domain>
    <summary>Buy a domain on Cloudflare Registrar and configure DNS (A/AAAA + CNAMEs) to point to your own server with proxy on, Full(Strict) SSL, and verified propagation.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>cloudflare</tag>
      <tag>dns</tag>
      <tag>registrar</tag>
      <tag>domain</tag>
      <tag>nameservers</tag>
      <tag>ssl</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>dns</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-05-02</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="ssl-tls-management"/>
      <ref slug="nginx-reverse-proxy"/>
      <ref slug="fail2ban-setup"/>
    </related>
    <applies-to>both</applies-to>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Cloudflare Domain Purchase and DNS Configuration</title>
    <summary>End-to-end procedure to buy a domain on Cloudflare Registrar, point it at your own server with A/AAAA records for apex+www, optional subdomain CNAMEs, decide proxy on/off per record, and lock SSL to Full(Strict). Includes propagation checks and optional API automation.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Cloudflare Registrar sells domains at wholesale registry cost (no markup, no upsell), and routing DNS through Cloudflare gives free DDoS protection, edge caching, analytics, and a 15-year origin certificate that eliminates the 90-day Let's Encrypt renewal cycle. Configuring it correctly the first time avoids two classic outages: (1) Flexible-SSL redirect loops and (2) AAAA records left dangling on dual-stack origins.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Buying a brand-new domain and pointing it at your VPS or dedicated server</item>
        <item>Migrating an existing domain to Cloudflare Registrar after the 60-day ICANN transfer lock has expired</item>
        <item>Replacing the registrar's nameservers with Cloudflare's authoritative NS for an existing domain</item>
        <item>Adding a new server (apex + www + a few subdomains) behind Cloudflare proxy</item>
        <item>Centralizing DNS for multiple sites under one Cloudflare account for unified WAF and analytics</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Domain is locked at the current registrar (transfer lock, recent registration &lt;60 days, or registry-lock service) — wait or unlock first</item>
        <item>TLD is not supported by Cloudflare Registrar (e.g. .ua, .io specialty extensions, ccTLDs requiring local presence) — keep current registrar, only delegate NS</item>
        <item>Domain uses DNSSEC at the parent and you cannot coordinate a DS-record swap without downtime — schedule a maintenance window or disable DNSSEC first</item>
        <item>You need DNS features Cloudflare does not support (e.g. DNAME chains, NAPTR for SIP, dynamic record TTL below 60s on free plan)</item>
        <item>Origin server has no public IPv4 and no IPv6 — DNS records would be unreachable</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <how-to>
      <step>Search availability on Cloudflare dashboard → Domain Registration → Register Domains. Enter the desired SLD; Cloudflare displays the wholesale price for every TLD it supports. If unavailable, use `whois example.com` from the CLI to confirm registration status before deciding.</step>
      <step>Purchase the domain. Provide WHOIS contact info (Cloudflare enables WHOIS privacy by default for supported TLDs), enable auto-renew, set the billing email to a monitored address, and enable 2FA on the Cloudflare account before clicking buy. Payment method is charged at the registry rate; no markup.</step>
      <step>Choose DNS mode. Default for Cloudflare-registered domains is full Cloudflare DNS (zone hosted on Cloudflare authoritative nameservers, e.g. `NAME.ns.cloudflare.com` where NAME is a per-zone label). For domains transferred in but managed externally, you may instead point Cloudflare's secondary DNS or run "DNS only" — for new purchases keep the default full-Cloudflare mode.</step>
      <step>Add A/AAAA records for apex and www. In the DNS tab → Records → Add record. Apex (`@`): type A, content = server IPv4 (e.g. `46.225.58.119`), proxy = ON (orange cloud), TTL = Auto. Repeat as type AAAA with the server's IPv6 if the origin is dual-stack. Add `www` as another A/AAAA pair OR a CNAME pointing to the apex — pick one shape and stick with it.</step>
      <step>Decide proxy on/off per record. Orange cloud (proxied) hides the origin IP, applies WAF/DDoS/cache, and requires a valid origin cert for Full(Strict). Gray cloud (DNS only) exposes the origin IP and is required for raw TCP/UDP services (SSH, SMTP, custom ports), wildcard SSL via Let's Encrypt DNS-01 on non-HTTP ports, and any service Cloudflare's HTTP/2 reverse proxy cannot speak.</step>
      <step>Add subdomain CNAMEs as needed. Example: `api` → CNAME `@` proxied; `mail` → A record gray-cloud (proxy off, mail must hit origin directly); `cdn` → CNAME to a static-host endpoint, proxied. Keep TTL on Auto for proxied records — Cloudflare ignores TTL when proxied.</step>
      <step>Set SSL/TLS mode to Full (Strict). SSL/TLS tab → Overview → encryption mode = Full (Strict). Then SSL/TLS → Edge Certificates → enable Always Use HTTPS, enable Automatic HTTPS Rewrites, set Minimum TLS Version to 1.2, enable TLS 1.3. Issue a Cloudflare Origin Certificate (15-year, RSA 2048 or ECC P-256) and install it on your origin nginx — see `ssl-tls-management` methodology.</step>
      <step>Configure apex/www redirect with a Bulk Redirect or Page Rule. Decide canonical: either `www → apex` (modern, shorter) or `apex → www` (cookieless apex). Rules → Redirect Rules → "Forwarding URL" → 301, preserve path and query string. Set HSTS only after both sides serve HTTPS cleanly.</step>
      <step>Verify propagation. Wait 1–5 minutes (Cloudflare DNS is near-instant once NS delegation is correct). Run `dig example.com +short`, `dig AAAA example.com +short`, `dig www.example.com +short`, then `curl -I https://example.com`. Confirm `server: cloudflare` header (proxied) or your origin's server header (DNS only). Check SSL Labs for grade A or higher.</step>
      <step>Enable optional automation. Generate an API token (My Profile → API Tokens → Create Token → Zone:Read + DNS:Edit, scoped to one zone). Store in 1Password. Use `flarectl` or `cf-terraforming` to manage records as code; commit the Terraform state outside the repo or in encrypted form.</step>
    </how-to>

    <warning>
      <p>Never set Cloudflare SSL mode to Flexible when the origin nginx redirects HTTP→HTTPS. Flexible terminates TLS at Cloudflare and re-issues plain HTTP to the origin; nginx then 301s back to HTTPS, Cloudflare re-proxies, and the browser hits ERR_TOO_MANY_REDIRECTS within ~10 hops. The fix is always Full (Strict) plus a real origin certificate.</p>
    </warning>

    <rule>
      <statement>Always pair an A record with a matching AAAA record when the origin is dual-stack, OR explicitly disable IPv6 on the origin if you only want to publish A.</statement>
      <rationale>Browsers and resolvers prefer IPv6 (Happy Eyeballs). A stale or missing AAAA leads to intermittent connection failures from IPv6 clients while IPv4 users see no problem — the hardest class of "works for me" bug to diagnose.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Enable WHOIS privacy, registrar lock, account 2FA, and auto-renew before publishing the domain anywhere.</statement>
      <rationale>Domain hijacking and accidental expiry are catastrophic and silent. Cloudflare enables most of these by default but auto-renew defaults can drift if billing fails — verify each one explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <commands>
      <command name="whois">whois example.com | head -30</command>
      <command name="dig-a">dig example.com +short</command>
      <command name="dig-aaaa">dig AAAA example.com +short</command>
      <command name="dig-www">dig www.example.com +short</command>
      <command name="dig-ns">dig NS example.com +short</command>
      <command name="dig-trace">dig +trace example.com</command>
      <command name="curl-https">curl -I https://example.com</command>
      <command name="curl-www">curl -I https://www.example.com</command>
      <command name="curl-redirect">curl -ILk http://example.com</command>
      <command name="ssl-labs">echo "https://www.ssllabs.com/ssltest/analyze.html?d=example.com&amp;hideResults=on"</command>
      <command name="flarectl-list">flarectl dns list --zone example.com</command>
      <command name="flarectl-create-a">flarectl dns create --zone example.com --name '@' --type A --content 46.225.58.119 --proxy</command>
      <command name="flarectl-create-aaaa">flarectl dns create --zone example.com --name '@' --type AAAA --content 2a01:4f8::1 --proxy</command>
      <command name="flarectl-create-www-cname">flarectl dns create --zone example.com --name www --type CNAME --content example.com --proxy</command>
      <command name="cf-api-list-zones">curl -s -H "Authorization: Bearer $CF_TOKEN" https://api.cloudflare.com/client/v4/zones | jq '.result[] | {name, id, status}'</command>
      <command name="cf-api-list-records">curl -s -H "Authorization: Bearer $CF_TOKEN" "https://api.cloudflare.com/client/v4/zones/$ZONE_ID/dns_records" | jq '.result[] | {type, name, content, proxied}'</command>
      <command name="cf-terraforming">cf-terraforming generate --resource-type cloudflare_record --zone $ZONE_ID &gt; records.tf</command>
    </commands>

    <prompt purpose="generate-dns-plan"><![CDATA[
You are a DNS architect. Produce a structured DNS plan for Cloudflare.

INPUT (provided by caller):
- domain: <apex domain, e.g. example.com>
- origin_ipv4: <single IPv4 address, e.g. 46.225.58.119>
- origin_ipv6: <single IPv6 address or "none">
- subdomains: list of {name, kind} where kind ∈ {http, mail, raw-tcp, static-cdn}
- canonical: "apex" or "www"
- email_provider: "self-hosted" | "google" | "fastmail" | "none"

OUTPUT (JSON only, no prose):
{
  "zone": "<domain>",
  "ssl_mode": "full_strict",
  "records": [
    {
      "type": "A" | "AAAA" | "CNAME" | "MX" | "TXT",
      "name": "@" | "www" | "<sub>",
      "content": "<value>",
      "proxied": true | false,
      "ttl": 1,
      "comment": "<why this record>"
    }
  ],
  "redirects": [
    { "from": "<src>", "to": "<dst>", "status": 301 }
  ],
  "notes": [
    "<warning or constraint>"
  ]
}

RULES:
1. Apex A and AAAA: proxied=true unless kind requires raw TCP.
2. www: CNAME to apex, proxied=true (mirror canonical decision in redirects).
3. mail.* (kind=mail): A record, proxied=false (Cloudflare proxy is HTTP only).
4. raw-tcp subdomains: proxied=false.
5. static-cdn: CNAME, proxied=true.
6. If email_provider = google: add MX records 1/5/5/10/10 for ASPMX.L.GOOGLE.COM family + TXT SPF "v=spf1 include:_spf.google.com ~all".
7. If origin_ipv6 = "none": omit AAAA records, add note "origin is IPv4 only".
8. Always include TXT _dmarc with policy=none initially.
9. Always include redirect from non-canonical to canonical with 301.
10. ttl=1 means "Auto" in Cloudflare API.

Validate: every proxied=true record must have a content addressable over HTTP/HTTPS on the origin. Output JSON only.
]]></prompt>

    <checklist>
      <check>Cloudflare account has 2FA enabled (TOTP or WebAuthn) before purchase</check>
      <check>Billing email is a monitored mailbox; not a single human's personal address</check>
      <check>Registrar lock is ON for the new zone (Cloudflare default — verify in dashboard)</check>
      <check>WHOIS privacy is enabled (Cloudflare default for supported TLDs — verify)</check>
      <check>Auto-renew is enabled and a valid payment method is attached with no nearing-expiry card</check>
      <check>Nameservers at the registry match Cloudflare's assigned NS pair (run `dig NS example.com +short` against an external resolver)</check>
      <check>A record present for apex with correct origin IPv4; AAAA present iff origin is dual-stack</check>
      <check>www record present (A or CNAME, consistent with canonical decision)</check>
      <check>Proxy state (orange/gray cloud) chosen deliberately per record — documented inline in record comments</check>
      <check>SSL/TLS mode set to Full (Strict) — never Flexible, never Off, never plain Full</check>
      <check>Origin certificate (15-year Cloudflare origin cert) installed on nginx and verified with `openssl s_client`</check>
      <check>Always Use HTTPS enabled; Minimum TLS Version = 1.2; TLS 1.3 enabled</check>
      <check>HSTS enabled only after all subdomains serve HTTPS cleanly; preload only after at least 6 months of stable HSTS</check>
      <check>Redirect rule from non-canonical host to canonical (301), path and query preserved</check>
      <check>API token created with least-privilege scope (Zone:Read + DNS:Edit, single zone) and stored in 1Password</check>
      <check>Propagation verified externally (`dig @1.1.1.1`, `dig @8.8.8.8`, `curl -I https://example.com` from a different network)</check>
    </checklist>

    <verify>
      <step>Run `dig NS example.com +short @1.1.1.1` and confirm the two Cloudflare nameservers match what the dashboard assigned.</step>
      <step>Run `dig example.com +short @1.1.1.1` and `dig AAAA example.com +short @1.1.1.1`. Verify proxied records resolve to a Cloudflare anycast IP (104.x or 172.67.x for IPv4; 2606:4700:: for IPv6), NOT your origin IP — that means proxy is active.</step>
      <step>Run `curl -I https://example.com` and check `server: cloudflare` header plus a 200 (or expected redirect chain). Run `curl -ILk http://example.com` and confirm a single 301→HTTPS, no loop.</step>
      <step>Run `dig +trace example.com @1.1.1.1` from a clean resolver and confirm the chain: root → TLD → Cloudflare NS → final A. No SERVFAIL, no NXDOMAIN.</step>
      <step>Visit `https://www.ssllabs.com/ssltest/analyze.html?d=example.com&amp;hideResults=on` and require grade A or A+. If A-, fix HSTS or cipher suite at the origin.</step>
      <step>Hit the Cloudflare API: `curl -s -H "Authorization: Bearer $CF_TOKEN" https://api.cloudflare.com/client/v4/zones?name=example.com | jq '.result[0].status'` — must return `"active"`. Then `GET /zones/$ID/dns_records` and confirm record set matches the plan.</step>
      <step>From a second network (mobile hotspot, VPN exit in another region), repeat `curl -I https://example.com` to confirm propagation is global, not cached locally.</step>
    </verify>

    <example type="good" title="apex + www both proxied, Full(Strict)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
DNS records for example.com (zone on Cloudflare):

Type   Name   Content                Proxy   TTL    Comment
A      @      46.225.58.119          ON      Auto   IPv4 origin
AAAA   @      2a01:4f8:c012:abcd::1  ON      Auto   IPv6 origin (dual-stack)
CNAME  www    example.com            ON      Auto   www mirrors apex
A      mail   46.225.58.119          OFF     Auto   SMTP must hit origin
MX     @      mail.example.com (10)  -       Auto   inbound mail
TXT    @      "v=spf1 mx -all"       -       Auto   SPF
TXT    _dmarc "v=DMARC1;p=none"      -       Auto   DMARC monitoring

SSL/TLS:
  mode = Full (Strict)
  minimum TLS = 1.2
  Always Use HTTPS = ON
  Origin certificate (15y) installed on nginx

Redirect rule:
  www.example.com/* → https://example.com/$1   (301)

Verification:
  $ dig example.com +short
  104.21.45.67
  172.67.123.89
  $ curl -I https://example.com
  HTTP/2 200
  server: cloudflare
]]></code>
      <note>Origin IP is hidden (resolver returns Cloudflare anycast IPs). Mail subdomain stays gray-cloud so SMTP works. Mixed-protocol clients (IPv6 mobile) get AAAA and connect cleanly.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Flexible SSL with origin HTTPS redirect — infinite loop">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Cloudflare config (broken):
  SSL/TLS mode = Flexible

Origin nginx (also broken in combination):
  server {
    listen 80;
    return 301 https://$host$request_uri;
  }
  server {
    listen 443 ssl;
    ...
  }

Result for browser hitting https://example.com:
  1. Browser → Cloudflare (HTTPS terminated at edge)
  2. Cloudflare → origin port 80 (Flexible mode = HTTP)
  3. nginx 301 → https://example.com
  4. Browser → Cloudflare → origin port 80 → 301 → ...
  ERR_TOO_MANY_REDIRECTS after ~10-20 hops.

Fix: switch SSL to Full (Strict), install origin cert, never Flexible.
]]></code>
      <note>Symptom is identical regardless of which page you load — every URL loops. Diagnose with `curl -ILk http://example.com` and count the 301 chain.</note>
    </example>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Adding only an A record on a dual-stack origin and forgetting AAAA. The server has working IPv6 (Hetzner, OVH, DigitalOcean default), but the Cloudflare zone publishes IPv4 only.</description>
      <reason>Cloudflare's edge will still proxy over IPv6 to the origin if AAAA is published; if it is not published, IPv6 clients still reach Cloudflare (anycast covers v6) but you lose the option to publish IPv6-only services and you create asymmetry between A and AAAA reverse-DNS expectations. Worse, if you later disable proxy (gray cloud) for a record without adding AAAA, IPv6 clients stop resolving entirely while IPv4 users see no issue — diagnosis takes hours.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Pointing the apex A record at Cloudflare while leaving an old A record in another DNS provider's zone (split horizon caused by stale registrar NS).</description>
      <reason>Until the registry NS swap propagates, half the world resolves via the old provider (stale IP) and half via Cloudflare (correct IP). Users see intermittent failures for up to 48h. Always verify `dig NS example.com +short` from multiple resolvers before declaring migration done.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="ssl-tls-management"/>
      <ref slug="nginx-reverse-proxy"/>
      <ref slug="fail2ban-setup"/>
      <link href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/registrar/"/>
      <link href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/dns/"/>
      <link href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/ssl/origin-configuration/ssl-modes/full-strict/"/>
      <link href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/api/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
