<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="mlp-planning">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Four-layer audit (Functional → Reliable → Usable → Delightful) to upgrade MVP to Minimum Lovable Product. MLP = MVP + targeted delight in high-frequency flows.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>mlp</tag>
      <tag>retention</tag>
      <tag>product-polish</tag>
      <tag>ux</tag>
      <tag>user-delight</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
    <applies-to>both</applies-to>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>MLP Planning</title>
    <summary>Plan the upgrade from a validated MVP to a Minimum Lovable Product: a four-layer audit (Functional → Reliable → Usable → Delightful) that identifies the specific gap between "it works" and "I love it". MLP = MVP + targeted delight in high-frequency, high-visibility interactions. The process ends with explicit completion criteria tied to retention and NPS targets, not feature counts.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>MVPs validate ideas but fail to retain users. Competing products in crowded markets are already "good enough", so users try an MVP and leave for better UX. Retention requires emotional connection, and the four-layer model gives a concrete, auditable path to it: delight cannot be bolted on randomly — it must be layered on top of solid function, reliability, and usability.</p>
      <p>2025/2026 consumer SaaS benchmarks: median Day-7 retention ≈ 25%, Day-30 retention ≈ 8%, NPS ≈ 31. Top-quartile products clear Day-30 retention 18%+ and NPS 50+. The gap between median and top-quartile is almost entirely experience quality, not feature count, which is exactly what the MLP audit measures and closes.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>MVP is live, core hypothesis validated, but Day-7/30 retention is weak.</item>
        <item>Users complete the core flow but don't return or recommend.</item>
        <item>You're preparing a second-wave release specifically targeting retention.</item>
        <item>NPS is below 30 and you need a structured diagnosis.</item>
        <item>Activation rate is acceptable but week-over-week churn is rising.</item>
        <item>App store / review reception is "useful but not loved" — 3-4 stars with comments about polish, not function.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Problem hypothesis is still unvalidated — validate with MVP first.</item>
        <item>No usage data yet; MLP audit requires actual interaction patterns to rate layers.</item>
        <item>B2B/enterprise deal where retention is driven by contract, not experience.</item>
        <item>Prioritising more features over polishing existing ones is a strategic choice — revisit after feature bets resolve.</item>
        <item>Core funnel is broken (activation under 20%) — fix Layer 1 functionally before rating Layers 2–4.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="four-layer-model">
      <p>The four-layer model that defines the path from a functional MVP to a Minimum Lovable Product, with a rating scale and MLP threshold rule.</p>
      <p>Minimum Lovable Product is the smallest version that delivers core value, creates emotional connection, and gives users a reason to stay and recommend. MLP = MVP + delight. Not more features — better experience.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every layer must be solid before adding the next. Delight built on unreliable foundations is wasted.</statement>
        <rationale>Users notice inconsistency before they notice charm. A delightful animation on a crashy flow increases frustration, not affection.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Layer 1 — Functional: core job completes, no blocking bugs, acceptable performance (TTFB &lt; 800ms, primary action &lt; 2s on median device).</statement>
        <rationale>MVP baseline. Without this, nothing else matters. Use real-user metrics from analytics, not synthetic benchmarks.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Layer 2 — Reliable: consistent experience, error handling, edge cases covered, works as expected every time. Crash-free sessions ≥ 99.5%, error-rate ≤ 0.5%, no silent failures.</statement>
        <rationale>Reliability is the prerequisite for trust. Users forgive a rough UI; they do not forgive data loss or silent failures.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Layer 3 — Usable: easy to learn, efficient to use, minimal friction, good defaults. Time-to-first-value &lt; 90s; core action ≤ 3 clicks; SUS score ≥ 68.</statement>
        <rationale>Usability reduces the cognitive tax per session. High friction kills retention even when the product works perfectly.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Layer 4 — Delightful: emotional satisfaction, surprising moments, premium feel, shareable moments. At least one "wow" moment within first session; one micro-celebration per success state.</statement>
        <rationale>Delight creates word-of-mouth and emotional attachment that purely functional products cannot generate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Rate each core feature 1–5 on each layer. MLP threshold: all features at 4+ on all four layers.</statement>
        <rationale>The threshold is not perfection (5) but sufficiency (4). Rating below 4 on any layer signals a gap that blocks MLP readiness.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Polish priority = user pain (1–5) × frequency (sessions/week) × visibility (% of users who hit the flow). Focus on high-frequency, high-visibility interactions first.</statement>
        <rationale>Delight in rarely-seen flows is invisible. The same effort on the core daily action multiplies impact across all sessions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>MVP goal is to validate; MLP goal is to retain. MVP focus is functionality; MLP focus is experience. MVP emotion is "it works"; MLP emotion is "I love it". Word-of-mouth is unlikely from MVP users and likely from MLP users.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="mlp-planning-process">
      <p>Five-step process for planning the gap between a validated MVP and a Minimum Lovable Product.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 1: Audit Your MVP. For each core feature, rate 1–5 on all four layers using session recordings, error logs, and a 6–10 user interview round. Any feature below 4 on any layer is a gap that must be closed before declaring MLP.</statement>
        <rationale>The audit makes the gap visible and concrete, replacing "the UX needs work" with specific layer deficits per feature.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 2: Identify Delight Opportunities. Scan four moments for delight: first impression (onboarding), core action (the main thing users do), success moments (when they win), and recovery moments (when things go wrong).</statement>
        <rationale>Delight in error states is disproportionately memorable — it converts frustration into loyalty. Most products ignore this.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Speed delight: faster than expected (instant search results, optimistic UI updates)</item>
        <item>Simplicity delight: easier than expected (one-click checkout, magic-link auth)</item>
        <item>Personality delight: unexpected charm (clever copywriting, on-brand empty states)</item>
        <item>Anticipation delight: knows what they need (smart defaults, recently-used pinning)</item>
        <item>Celebration delight: acknowledges success (confetti, streak badges, weekly summaries)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 3: Prioritize Polish. Apply the formula: polish priority = user pain × frequency × visibility. Only invest in high-frequency, high-visibility interactions in the first MLP wave.</statement>
        <rationale>Polish on a rarely-seen screen is invisible to most users. The same effort on the daily core action compounds across every session.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 4: Define MLP Criteria. Write explicit MLP criteria for your target user segment covering all four layers with measurable outcomes. Template: "For [user segment] MLP means: [functional criteria], [reliable criteria], [usable criteria], [delightful criteria]. Measured by: [verification method]."</statement>
        <rationale>Without explicit criteria, MLP becomes subjective and the team will never agree it has been reached.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 5: Plan the Gap. For each feature, document: current state, MLP target, what is missing, and effort. This becomes the MLP backlog, ordered by polish priority score.</statement>
        <rationale>The gap analysis converts the audit rating into actionable tasks with known scope.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <how-to>
      <p>Concrete sequence an autonomous agent can execute end-to-end, producing the MLP plan deliverable in `mlp-plan.md` from raw product data.</p>
      <step>Collect inputs: 30 days of analytics export (DAU, Day-7/30 retention, funnel completion), error/crash log summary, 6–10 user-interview transcripts, and the live core-features list. Save to `inputs/`.</step>
      <step>Run the four-layer audit per feature. For each core feature, score Layer 1–4 on the 1–5 rubric using the data — never guess. Record evidence (metric or quote) in a column next to each score.</step>
      <step>List all sub-4 cells from the audit. Each is a gap. Tag each gap with its layer and the metric/quote that revealed it.</step>
      <step>Map the four delight moments (onboarding, core action, success, recovery) for the dominant user journey. For each moment, write current experience and one specific delight intervention.</step>
      <step>Compute polish priority score = pain × frequency × visibility for every gap and delight opportunity. Sort descending.</step>
      <step>Write explicit MLP completion criteria for each layer, every criterion with a measurable outcome and verification method.</step>
      <step>Build the MLP backlog as a table (task, layer, effort, impact, priority) using the top 60–80% of the prioritized list. Drop the long tail.</step>
      <step>Render the deliverable from the template. Open `templates/mlp-plan.md`, fill every placeholder, save to `.product/mlp-plan.md`. Add a measurement plan with baseline-to-target metrics.</step>
      <step>Schedule reviews: a polish demo every 2 weeks; remeasure retention/NPS every 4 weeks; ship MLP only when verification (below) passes.</step>
    </how-to>
    <commands>
      <command name="export-analytics">curl -s "$ANALYTICS_API/retention?range=30d" -H "Authorization: Bearer $TOKEN" -o inputs/retention-30d.json</command>
      <command name="run-nps-survey">npx delighted-nps send --segment active-d7 --sample 200</command>
      <command name="session-recording-export">posthog export --type recording --filter "is_first_session=true" --limit 25 -o inputs/recordings/</command>
      <command name="audit-scaffold">cp templates/mlp-plan.md .product/mlp-plan.md &amp;&amp; $EDITOR .product/mlp-plan.md</command>
      <command name="validate-this-methodology">python3 scripts/validate-methodology-xml.py skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/mlp-planning/methodology.xml</command>
    </commands>
    <prompt purpose="LLM-assisted four-layer audit of one feature given session data and user quotes"><![CDATA[
You are a product UX auditor. Score the feature below on the four MLP layers
(Functional, Reliable, Usable, Delightful) using a 1–5 rubric.

INPUTS:
- Feature name: <feature>
- Last 30d analytics: <json blob with completion rate, error rate, p95 latency, DAU>
- Crash/error log digest: <text>
- 5 verbatim user quotes about the feature: <list>

OUTPUT (JSON only):
{
  "feature": "<name>",
  "scores": {
    "functional": {"score": 1-5, "evidence": "<metric or quote>"},
    "reliable":   {"score": 1-5, "evidence": "<metric or quote>"},
    "usable":     {"score": 1-5, "evidence": "<metric or quote>"},
    "delightful": {"score": 1-5, "evidence": "<metric or quote>"}
  },
  "gaps":         ["<one line per layer scoring < 4>"],
  "top_polish":   "<single highest-leverage polish action>",
  "delight_idea": "<one concrete delight intervention tied to a moment>"
}

Rules:
- Never invent data; if evidence is absent for a layer, output score=null and evidence="insufficient data".
- A single broken edge case caps Reliable at 3.
- A delight idea must name a specific moment (onboarding, core action, success, recovery).
]]></prompt>
    <prompt purpose="MLP completion-criteria writer — fills Step 4 deliverable"><![CDATA[
Given the audit JSON for ALL core features and the product's target user segment,
produce explicit MLP completion criteria.

For each layer (Functional, Reliable, Usable, Delightful) write 1–3 criteria.
Every criterion MUST be:
- measurable (metric + threshold), e.g. "crash-free sessions ≥ 99.5%"
- verifiable (state the data source: analytics, NPS survey, session replay, etc.)
- segment-specific (mention the user segment from the prompt)

Output Markdown matching the "MLP Completion Criteria" section of templates/mlp-plan.md.
Add a final Measurement Plan table with columns: Metric | MVP Baseline | MLP Target | Source.
]]></prompt>
    <checklist>
      <check>30-day analytics export, error/crash log digest, and 6–10 user interview transcripts are saved under `inputs/`.</check>
      <check>Every core feature has four scores (Functional/Reliable/Usable/Delightful) with cited evidence — no blank cells.</check>
      <check>All sub-4 scores are listed in a Gap Register with the failing metric or quote.</check>
      <check>Four delight moments (onboarding, core action, success, recovery) each have a current-state line and a target intervention.</check>
      <check>Polish priority = pain × frequency × visibility computed for every backlog candidate; backlog sorted by score.</check>
      <check>MLP completion criteria are explicit per layer, measurable, and tied to a verification method.</check>
      <check>Measurement plan lists Day-7, Day-30 retention, NPS, and core-action completion with MVP baseline and MLP target.</check>
      <check>Backlog drops the long tail; only items in the top 60–80% of the prioritized list are scheduled for MLP wave 1.</check>
      <check>No "more features" line items unless they are the only fix for a Layer 1 gap.</check>
      <check>Polish demo cadence (every 2 weeks) and remeasure cadence (every 4 weeks) are calendared.</check>
    </checklist>
    <verify>
      <step>Run `python3 scripts/validate-methodology-xml.py skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-planning/mlp-planning/methodology.xml` and confirm it prints `PASS`.</step>
      <step>Confirm `.product/mlp-plan.md` exists and contains: feature audit table, delight opportunities, polish backlog, MLP completion criteria, and measurement plan — no unreplaced `[placeholder]` tokens.</step>
      <step>Verify each completion criterion has a metric, threshold, and named data source. Reject any criterion stated only in adjectives ("fast", "smooth").</step>
      <step>Re-score all features after MLP wave ships; confirm every layer is ≥ 4. Any cell still &lt; 4 blocks the MLP claim.</step>
      <step>Sample retention 4 weeks after ship: Day-30 retention must improve ≥ 30% relative to baseline AND NPS must improve ≥ 15 absolute points to ratify "MLP achieved".</step>
      <step>Run a 5-user think-aloud session on the polished core action; ≥ 4 of 5 must complete unaided in &lt; 90s and report a positive emotional reaction unprompted.</step>
    </verify>
    <section name="mlp-planning-examples">
      <p>Worked examples of MVP-to-MLP upgrade paths with layer-by-layer improvements and measured outcomes.</p>
      <example type="good" title="Note-Taking App">
        <note>MVP: create, edit, delete notes, basic formatting — functional but bland. NPS 30, Day-30 retention weak.</note>
        <note>MLP additions by layer — Reliable: auto-save with visual confirmation. Usable: keyboard shortcuts, quick capture. Delight: smooth animations, satisfying micro-sounds, Zen mode for focused writing, clever empty states.</note>
        <note>Result: retention increased 40%, NPS rose from 30 to 55.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Invoicing Tool">
        <note>MVP: create invoices, send to clients — functional but clunky.</note>
        <note>MLP additions by layer — Reliable: payment confirmation notifications. Usable: templates from past invoices, client auto-fill. Delight: celebration on payment received, "You've earned $X this month" dashboard.</note>
        <note>Result: users create 2x more invoices, NPS 60.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Adding more features instead of polishing existing ones when retention is low.</description>
        <reason>More features increase scope without addressing the quality gap. Users who left due to rough UX won't return for more features with the same rough UX.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping MVP validation and going straight to MLP polish.</description>
        <reason>Polish on an unvalidated core value is expensive waste. Validate the job-to-be-done first, then polish the delivery.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Surface-level polish (color changes, fonts) without addressing interaction quality.</description>
        <reason>Cosmetic polish without fixing interaction friction does not move retention or NPS.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Generic delight not tailored to the specific audience.</description>
        <reason>Confetti on task completion delights consumer app users; it annoys enterprise finance users in the same moment. Delight must match emotional context.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Adding Layer 4 delight without completing Layers 1–3.</description>
        <reason>Delight on top of unreliable or unusable flows increases frustration. Users notice the inconsistency more than the charm.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Declaring MLP using vibes instead of remeasured retention and NPS.</description>
        <reason>Without before/after metrics the team will declare MLP based on internal demos, then be surprised when retention is unchanged.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/mlp-plan.md" purpose="Full MLP planning document: feature audit table, delight opportunities, polish backlog, completion criteria, measurement plan."/>
      <template path="templates/delight-sprint.md" purpose="Focused sprint template for adding delight to one workflow area."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="micro-mvps"/>
      <ref slug="minimum-product-frameworks"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
