<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="plg-optimization-tactics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>conversion-optimizer</domain>
    <summary>ICE-scored tactics for activation, free-tier-to-paid, and expansion in PLG products. Upgrade prompts at 80% of limit, one per session, zero in first session.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>plg</tag>
      <tag>activation</tag>
      <tag>conversion</tag>
      <tag>upgrade-prompts</tag>
      <tag>ice-scoring</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>PLG Optimization Tactics</title>

    <summary>A tactics catalog for improving activation, free-tier-to-paid, and expansion conversion in an existing PLG product. Core rules: pair every tactic with the metric it moves and a current baseline; show upgrade prompts at 80% of limit (not 100%); cap prompts to one per session and zero during the first session; name a comparable customer and quantify value in all upgrade copy; reject "Upgrade Now" and "Premium Plan" as CTA text.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Post-PMF PLG products plateau because teams lack a structured tactic backlog tied to measurable funnel steps. This methodology provides an ICE-scored tactic index covering activation friction reduction, free-tier balance, self-serve checkout design, and expansion signal detection. ICE scoring ensures the backlog is ordered by impact x confidence x ease rather than team preference.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Running an existing PLG product where activation, free-tier-to-paid, or expansion conversion has plateaued and you need a backlog of tested tactics rather than a strategy rewrite.</item>
        <item>Designing a free tier or self-serve checkout from scratch and want a pre-curated list of friction points to instrument before launch.</item>
        <item>Generating in-product upgrade copy, feature-gate messaging, and pricing-page variants that follow the methodology good vs bad patterns.</item>
        <item>Producing a quarterly A/B test backlog scored against the included onboarding/upgrade/pricing test idea bank.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF teams without measurable activation data — generic tactics distract from PMF discovery.</item>
        <item>Pure sales-led ACVs above ~$50K where self-serve patterns do not survive procurement; route to sales-led playbooks instead.</item>
        <item>Single-event transactions (one-shot ecommerce, ticketing) where there is no expansion or seat-growth surface to optimize.</item>
        <item>Hard-regulated products (healthcare, banking) where "instant access, no approval" recommendations conflict with compliance.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="activation-friction-reduction">
      <rule>
        <statement>Reduce signup to 3 fields maximum (name, email, password) with instant access. Move any additional qualification fields to a post-activation profile step.</statement>
        <rationale>Each additional field reduces signup completion by 5-10%. 10-field forms fail ~70% of users before they experience any value.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never show a blank canvas on first login. Pre-seed with sample data, templates, or a pre-filled demo object. The target "empty state time" before the user sees populated content is under 2 minutes.</statement>
        <rationale>Empty states force users to think before they have context. Pre-seeded content reduces time-to-value and increases Day-0 activation rate by 20-40%.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="progressive-onboarding">
      <rule>
        <statement>Reveal features contextually as users take actions rather than teaching everything upfront. Gate each next capability on completing the previous one.</statement>
        <rationale>Showing all features at once overwhelms users and dilutes focus on the core activation path. Progressive reveal increases feature adoption depth without increasing early drop-off.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Project management tool: 4-step progressive reveal tied to user actions.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1. Login → Create first task (core value demonstrated)
2. Add 3 tasks → Show task organization options
3. Organize tasks → Show collaboration features
4. Invite teammate → Show advanced reporting/analytics
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="free-tier-balance">
      <rule>
        <statement>Design the free tier to give enough value to reach the Aha moment with clear natural upgrade triggers (usage limits, feature gates, user limits) — not so generous that there is no incentive to upgrade, not so restrictive that the user cannot experience value.</statement>
        <rationale>Too-generous free tiers produce low conversion (users never hit limits). Too-restrictive tiers produce high abandonment (users cannot see value before hitting a wall).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Feature gates: basic vs premium features — upgrade trigger is needing advanced functionality.</item>
        <item>Usage limits: 5 projects, 100MB storage — upgrade trigger is hitting capacity at meaningful usage.</item>
        <item>User limits: 1-2 users free vs unlimited team — upgrade trigger is team growth.</item>
        <item>Time limits: 14-day trial of premium features — upgrade trigger is trial expiration with demonstrated value.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="upgrade-prompt-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Show upgrade prompts at 80% of limit consumption, never at 100%. Cap upgrade prompts to one per session and zero during the first session. Never show during a critical workflow or immediately after a recent dismissal.</statement>
        <rationale>Prompts at 100% arrive too late — the user has already hit a wall and is frustrated. First-session prompts break trust before value is demonstrated. Over-prompting trains users to dismiss all prompts.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>All upgrade copy must: name a comparable customer, quantify the value (hours saved, projects unlocked), name the specific plan, and include two CTAs (primary: upgrade, secondary: see example or learn more). Reject "Get More Features", "Upgrade Now", and "Premium Plan" as CTA text.</statement>
        <rationale>Generic upgrade copy does not connect the user's current need to the plan's value. Named customer + quantified benefit copies convert at 2-3x generic CTA text in A/B tests.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Feature gate message: team exceeds 3-member free limit.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Teams like Acme Corp save 10 hours/week with unlimited member access.
 Your team is ready for [Product] Team plan."
 [Upgrade to Team] [See what's included]
]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Generic upgrade prompt — no customer, no value quantification.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"This feature is for Pro users only."
[Upgrade]
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="self-serve-checkout">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pricing pages must have: 2-4 tiers maximum, a feature comparison table, an annual discount (15-20%), and no "Contact Sales" button for basic or pro tiers. Instant access on upgrade — no approval wait.</statement>
        <rationale>More than 4 tiers introduces choice paralysis. Hiding annual discount reduces LTV. "Contact Sales" on standard tiers is a conversion cliff that routes self-serve users into a sales process they did not want.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="expansion-signals">
      <rule>
        <statement>Monitor team-growth signals (multiple users from same domain, @mentions, external sharing), power-user signals (daily active usage, API usage, integration connections), and upsell-readiness signals (feature gate hits 3+ times, pricing page visits). Route PQL-qualified users to targeted upgrade prompts; do not show expansion prompts to users who have not hit these signals.</statement>
        <rationale>PQL-based prompts sent at behavioral readiness convert at 3-5x prompts sent on time-based schedules alone.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ab-test-idea-bank">
      <p>Onboarding tests: number of signup fields (2 vs 3 vs 5); social login vs email-only; interactive walkthrough vs tutorial video; empty state vs pre-filled templates; progress checklist vs progress bar.</p>
      <p>Upgrade prompt tests: prompt timing at 70% vs 80% vs 90% of limit; prompt format (banner vs modal vs sidebar); CTA copy ("Upgrade" vs "Unlock" vs "Get unlimited"); price anchoring (monthly vs annual shown first).</p>
      <p>Pricing page tests: 2 vs 3 vs 4 tiers; annual discount amount (15% vs 20% vs 25%); feature comparison layout (table vs cards); CTA position (top vs bottom vs both); FAQ placement.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <list>
        <item>Lift bands ("+10-25%") are aggregate; agents must not promise them as forecasts. Always reframe as hypotheses with ICE scoring.</item>
        <item>Free-tier limit choices are the single highest-leverage decision but the methodology gives only directional guidance; this requires human judgment + cohort data, not LLM inference.</item>
        <item>Expansion playbooks assume team/seat surface; usage-based products need a different signal model (consumption curves, not invitee count).</item>
        <item>Tactics list is timeless; pricing-page best practices change yearly — verify against current Stripe/ProfitWell/Reforge posts before shipping copy.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Treat this methodology as a tactics catalog that a Claude subagent indexes and queries. The orchestrator first pulls current funnel metrics from the analytics tool, the subagent then maps each weak step to candidate tactics from this catalog, scores them with ICE, and emits a ranked test backlog plus draft copy variants. A human PMM reviews free-tier-limit and pricing-page changes before they ship; copy variants and A/B test specs can ship via approval-gated PRs.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-growth-agent — primary owner; wraps this catalog and emits structured tactic recommendations. plg-tactic-mapper spawned subagent — input: drop-off step + segment, output: 3-5 tactics with rationale and ICE skeleton. copy-variant-writer subagent — turns a single feature gate or upgrade prompt into 5 variants following the bad/good rules in this methodology.</p>

      <prompt purpose="PLG tactic mapper for funnel drop-off"><![CDATA[
You are plg-tactic-mapper. Read the PLG optimization tactics methodology.
Input: { stage: "activation|free-to-paid|expansion", weak_step: "<event>", current_rate: 0.XX, segment: "<seg>" }.
Output JSON: [{ tactic, source_section, hypothesis, ice: {impact, confidence, ease}, instrumentation }].
No prose outside the JSON array.
]]></prompt>

      <prompt purpose="Copy variant writer for upgrade prompts"><![CDATA[
You are copy-variant-writer. Given { feature_gate, current_copy, plan_target }, produce 5 variants
that follow the methodology "Good Examples" rules: name a similar customer, quantify the value, name
the plan, and end with a two-button CTA. Reject any variant matching the listed "Bad Examples".
]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <list>
        <item>posthog CLI / API — Pull funnel + activation cohorts; trigger feature flags for A/B tests (pip install posthog; https://posthog.com/docs/api)</item>
        <item>mixpanel Query API — JQL/Insights for activation funnel and free-to-paid cohorts (https://developer.mixpanel.com/reference/query-api)</item>
        <item>amplitude REST API — Cohort + funnel pulls, behavioral cohorts for PQL (https://www.docs.developers.amplitude.com/analytics/apis/)</item>
        <item>stripe CLI — Inspect checkout sessions, pricing tiers, proration logic</item>
        <item>appcues API — Programmatically deploy onboarding checklists / progressive flows (https://developer.appcues.com/)</item>
        <item>growthbook / flagsmith — OSS feature-flag + A/B test infra (https://docs.growthbook.io/)</item>
      </list>
      <list>
        <item>PostHog: OSS + SaaS, Yes — full REST + flag API — Best end-to-end for autonomous agents</item>
        <item>Amplitude: SaaS, Partial — read APIs solid, write requires SDK</item>
        <item>Mixpanel: SaaS, Yes — JQL flexible; good for ad-hoc tactic-impact queries</item>
        <item>Stripe Billing: SaaS, Yes — Drive plan changes, proration tests via Pricing Tables API</item>
        <item>Appcues / Pendo / Userflow: SaaS, Partial — Use for progressive onboarding tactics</item>
        <item>Chameleon: SaaS, Partial — Good for upgrade-prompt placement experiments</item>
        <item>Reforge / OpenView reports: Source, Read-only — Benchmark anchoring; agent should cite, not invent benchmarks</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ice-scoring-template">
      <example type="good" title="ice_score.py — score tactic backlog">
        <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# ice_score.py — score tactic backlog from this methodology
from dataclasses import dataclass

@dataclass
class Tactic:
    name: str
    impact: int      # 1-10 expected lift on the target metric
    confidence: int  # 1-10 evidence strength (own data > industry > guess)
    ease: int        # 1-10 inverse cost (eng + design weeks)

    @property
    def ice(self) -> int:
        return self.impact + self.confidence + self.ease

    def bucket(self) -> str:
        if self.ice >= 24: return "test_now"
        if self.ice >= 18: return "this_quarter"
        if self.ice >= 12: return "if_capacity"
        return "backlog"

def rank(tactics: list[Tactic]) -> list[Tactic]:
    return sorted(tactics, key=lambda t: t.ice, reverse=True)

# Agents emit Tactic(...) instances per methodology section, then call rank().
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Always pair a tactic with the activation/expansion metric it moves and a current baseline; tactics without baselines are theatre.</item>
        <item>Run the "TOO GENEROUS / TOO RESTRICTIVE / BALANCED" free-tier sketch as an explicit subagent step before recommending any limit change.</item>
        <item>For upgrade prompts, enforce the rules: name a comparable customer, quantify saved time/value, name the plan; reject "Upgrade Now" and "Premium Plan" copy.</item>
        <item>Trigger PQL-based prompts at 80% of limit, never 100% — agent should hard-code this as a guardrail in generated configs.</item>
        <item>Cap upgrade prompts to one per session and zero during the first session; bake this into any auto-generated Appcues/Pendo flow.</item>
        <item>Keep 4 or fewer pricing tiers and require an annual-discount field in any pricing-page draft; reject layouts that hide it.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs recommend "remove all limits" or "give 30-day trial" — this conflicts with the balanced-tier guidance.</description>
        <reason>Pin the system prompt to the specific limit-type matrix in this methodology.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-generated upgrade copy drifts to generic SaaS language ("powerful features", "enterprise-grade").</description>
        <reason>Add a post-filter that scans for these tokens and rewrites them using named customers and quantified value.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents writing directly to a paid Stripe price object or live Appcues flow.</description>
        <reason>Gate every mutation behind a human-approved PR or ticket.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Free-tier limit changes shipped autonomously by agent with high ICE score.</description>
        <reason>Free-tier limit changes must be reviewed with finance + retention data — never let an agent ship a limit change autonomously.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>PQL scoring weights reused from last quarter's coefficients without re-fitting.</description>
        <reason>Require the agent to re-fit weights against converted cohorts every quarter.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Empty State Time under 2 minutes" target used without server-side data seeding step in the onboarding flow spec.</description>
        <reason>Agents producing onboarding flows must explicitly include the seed step or the metric is unreachable.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ice-scorer.py" purpose="Dataclass for ICE-scoring tactic backlog; bucket() returns test_now / this_quarter / if_capacity / backlog"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.profitwell.com/recur/all/freemium-pricing-strategy"/>
      <link href="https://stripe.com/guides/saas-checkout-optimization"/>
      <link href="https://chartmogul.com/blog/expansion-revenue/"/>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog/feature-gating-strategies"/>
      <link href="https://openviewpartners.com/product-led-growth/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
