<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-hacker-news-launch">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>Launch a technical product on Hacker News with Show HN: build account reputation first, write descriptive non-hypey titles, post 8–10 AM ET weekdays, stay engaged 24–48 hours.</summary>
    <category>growth</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>hacker-news</tag>
      <tag>product-launch</tag>
      <tag>community-marketing</tag>
      <tag>developer-audience</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <applies-to>both</applies-to>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Hacker News Launch Strategy</title>

    <summary>A launch strategy for Hacker News (Show HN) focused on substance over marketing: build account reputation through genuine participation first, write descriptive non-hypey titles, post at 8–10 AM ET on weekdays, and stay engaged with all feedback for 24–48 hours. HN rewards technical depth and authenticity; it penalizes marketing language and friction.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>HN can drive tens of thousands of visitors in a single day — developers, founders, and investors who are unusually high-intent for technical products. But the community actively flags promotional content. The mechanism: HN's ranking algorithm amplifies early velocity, so a post that earns 10 upvotes in the first hour reaches the front page; staying engaged extends the session and earns more upvotes organically.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Launching a developer tool, open-source project, or technical product.</item>
        <item>Publishing a deep technical blog post or research finding.</item>
        <item>Product has a public demo that requires no signup to experience.</item>
        <item>Account has existing karma from genuine participation (2+ weeks).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Consumer apps, lifestyle products, or anything non-technical — wrong audience entirely.</item>
        <item>Marketing-speak product or landing page — HN will flag it before you can fix it.</item>
        <item>No time to stay engaged for a full day post-launch — momentum requires real-time responses.</item>
        <item>New account with no comment history — first post looks like spam and gets flagged.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="hn-culture-values-audience">
      <p>Hacker News readers are: software engineers and engineering managers (60%+), startup founders with technical backgrounds, investors affiliated with YC ecosystem, students and researchers. They are skeptical of hype, reward intellectual honesty, and test claims immediately. A broken demo or incorrect technical claim will be surfaced in comments within 15 minutes.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Write titles that describe what the product does technically, not what it achieves for the user. Avoid superlatives, buzzwords, and marketing adjectives entirely.</statement>
        <rationale>HN's community actively downvotes and flags marketing language. The algorithm treats flag velocity as a quality signal. A flagged post disappears from the front page within minutes.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Post types on HN:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Show HN: [Product] — [Description] — for products with a public demo. No signup required to see value.</item>
        <item>Launch HN: [Company] ([URL]) — for YC companies at batch launch. YC affiliation adds credibility automatically.</item>
        <item>Technical blog post — link to a deep technical article. Title is the article headline, no "Show HN" prefix.</item>
        <item>Open source project — Show HN with GitHub link. OSS projects get strong organic upvotes from the developer community.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="title-formula">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Format: "Show HN: [What it does] — [How it's technically interesting or different]". State the fact; do not interpret it as valuable.</statement>
        <rationale>The community decides whether it's valuable. Claiming value in the title reads as marketing and reduces trust.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Descriptive technical titles">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Show HN: A terminal-based Git client written in Rust
Show HN: We built a search engine for research papers
Show HN: Open source alternative to Airtable
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Marketing-language titles to avoid">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Show HN: The best way to manage your tasks  (marketing claim)
Show HN: Check out our startup!  (vague, self-promotional)
Show HN: Revolutionary AI-powered productivity app  (hyperbolic)
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="pre-launch-account-building">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Before posting any product, build an account history of 2–4 weeks: comment thoughtfully on technical topics, share interesting links that are not your own, answer questions in your domain. Achieve 50+ karma points minimum.</statement>
        <rationale>New accounts with no history get flagged as spam within minutes regardless of content quality. HN's anti-spam heuristics specifically target zero-history accounts posting product links.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Polish the landing page: fast load (no heavy animations), clear explanation, demo visible without signup, pricing transparent.</item>
        <item>Write the first comment in advance: technical backstory, problem context, what feedback you want, honest known limitations.</item>
        <item>Clear your calendar for the launch day — engagement must be continuous for 24–48 hours.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="launch-day-strategy">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Post at 8–10 AM Eastern Time on Tuesday, Wednesday, or Thursday. Post the first comment immediately after submitting (within 60 seconds).</statement>
        <rationale>US morning maximizes initial upvote velocity from the largest HN user base. The first comment establishes context before anyone else comments — it frames the entire discussion.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Monitor comments continuously. Respond within 15 minutes to every substantive comment.</item>
        <item>Fix any bugs or broken links mentioned in real-time and post an update reply.</item>
        <item>Thank critics who point out legitimate issues — publicly acknowledging criticism earns respect.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="engagement-by-feedback-type">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Never get defensive, ask for upvotes, or ignore legitimate technical criticism. Doing any of these produces a pile-on that buries the post.</statement>
        <rationale>HN users interpret defensiveness as admission that criticism was valid. Asking for upvotes is explicitly against HN guidelines and gets the post killed. Ignoring technical criticism signals the product is not production-ready.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Technical critique: thank, explain your reasoning, acknowledge trade-offs honestly.</item>
        <item>Bug report: acknowledge immediately, fix if possible, update the comment thread.</item>
        <item>Feature request: note interest, share whether it's on the roadmap or why it isn't.</item>
        <item>Trolls: no response, or a single brief factual correction.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Engaged makers are rewarded by the algorithm. Posts with high-activity comment threads stay on the front page longer and accumulate more upvotes. An active maker response pattern is a strong positive signal.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="examples">
      <example type="good" title="Successful HN Launch: Developer Tool">
        <description>A terminal file manager written in Rust with all success factors present.</description>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Success factors:
  - Descriptive, non-hypey title (Rust = technically credible)
  - Open source with GitHub link (community can inspect and contribute)
  - Fast, polished demo without signup
  - Author responded to every comment within minutes
  - Honestly acknowledged what the tool doesn't do
  - Fixed two bugs reported in comments within the day

Results:
  Points: 500+
  Time on front page: 12 hours
  GitHub stars gained: 2,000
  Contributors who joined: 50
  Traffic: ~80,000 visits in 48 hours
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Failed HN Launch: Marketing Language">
        <description>A post with all failure patterns: marketing language, vague description, signup friction, defensive tone.</description>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Failure factors:
  - Marketing language in title ("revolutionary")
  - Vague description (what does it actually do?)
  - Required signup before seeing any functionality
  - Defensive replies to critical comments
  - No technical details shared

Results:
  Points: 3
  Flagged as self-promotion within 20 minutes
  Negative comment thread remained as search result
  Post disappeared from /newest within 1 hour
]]></code>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Asking friends to upvote, posting in Slack communities simultaneously, or using other vote-manipulation tactics.</description>
        <reason>HN's spam detection flags coordinated upvoting. These tactics are explicitly prohibited by HN guidelines and easily detected. An agent must not attempt to automate any of these.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration-and-limitations">
      <p>Agents add value in two phases for HN launches: (1) pre-launch content preparation — given the product's technical stack, problem statement, and key design decisions, draft the Show HN title, first comment, and a supporting technical blog post following HN's preferred structure (problem → approaches considered → what was built → deep-dive → results → learnings); (2) post-launch comment response drafting — given incoming HN comments, draft factual, non-defensive responses that acknowledge critique and provide technical depth.</p>

      <p>Human must post all responses and should do a final tone review before any public comment.</p>

      <p>HN traffic is typically a one-day spike; it does not convert to sustained organic search traffic the way a strong SEO article does. Post ranking is a black box; timing, initial upvote velocity, and community mood all interact in ways agents cannot predict or simulate. Agents cannot build HN karma or post history for you — participation must be done by a real person over weeks. The HN audience is vocal about product flaws; an agent-drafted first comment cannot anticipate every technical critique in real-time. HN's spam detection flags posts from new accounts, posts with identical IPs across multiple submissions, and coordinated upvoting — agents must not attempt to automate any of these.</p>

      <p>Agents default to polished, enthusiastic copy — HN commenters immediately recognize and downvote "marketing voice"; instruct agent to write in builder voice (plain, honest, technical). Show HN title character limits: HN does not enforce a strict limit but titles over 80 characters get truncated in feeds — validate length after generation. Agents may suggest "guerrilla" tactics (asking friends to upvote, posting in Slack communities simultaneously) that HN flags as vote manipulation — explicitly prohibit these in the system prompt. First comment drafts by agents often lack real technical depth because agents summarize rather than explain; provide the agent with actual architecture details, code snippets, or benchmark data to include. Human-in-loop checkpoint: post the Show HN submission and first comment manually — never automate submission; HN's systems detect automated submissions. Response drafts for hostile comments need human review before posting — a factually correct but poorly toned response can escalate a thread and damage the post's reception.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/show-hn-first-comment.txt" purpose="First comment template: backstory, technical approach, status, feedback asks, known limitations."/>
      <template path="templates/technical-blog-post.txt" purpose="Blog-post-as-launch structure: problem, approaches, what we built, deep-dive, results."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/newsguidelines.html"/>
      <link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/newsfaq.html"/>
      <link href="https://hn.algolia.com/api"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/HackerNews/API"/>
      <link href="https://builtbywords.substack.com/p/how-to-launch-on-hacker-news"/>
      <link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/library/6g-how-to-launch-again-and-again"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
