<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-key-themes" title="2026 Exam Key Themes: Sustainability, AI, Governance, Value Delivery">
  <summary>What each new Business Environment theme requires in coverage and common agent/content errors for each.</summary>

  <section title="Sustainability">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat sustainability as a first-class theme covering environmental, social, and economic dimensions. Reference a specific standard (GPM P5 v2.0, ISO 14001, or ISO 21502 sustainability clause) — do not leave it as an abstract goal.</statement>
      <rationale>The exam expects candidates to cite frameworks, not principles. "Be environmentally aware" is not an exam-ready answer; "apply GPM P5 Standard" is.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents citing "PMI Sustainability Standard" as a single document.</description>
      <reason>No such single document exists. The correct references are GPM P5 v2.0, ISO 14001, ISO 21502 sustainability provisions, and UN SDGs. Clarify which standard applies to the context.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="AI in Project Management">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin the AI-in-PM topic list per ECO version; do not let the agent re-derive it from training data. AI-in-PM surface area is unstable — freeze a topic list per ECO version.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM training data on AI-in-PM is ahead of the ECO content; agents generate plausible but unverified topics that do not map to exam questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Governance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Distinguish governance (oversight frameworks, decision rights, accountability) from PMO operations and from SOX-style financial controls — the exam tests each separately. Do not conflate them in curriculum content.</statement>
      <rationale>Governance theme overlaps PMO operations and PfMP/PgMP scope and financial controls; agents and curricula routinely conflate them, producing content that prepares for none of them well.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Value Delivery">
    <rule>
      <statement>Frame value delivery in terms of outcomes (benefits realised by stakeholders) not outputs (deliverables produced). Exam questions test whether candidates orient around business value, not deliverable completion.</statement>
      <rationale>PMBOK 7 explicitly shifted from output-orientation (knowledge areas, deliverables) to outcome-orientation (performance domains, value). Curricula that still frame success as "on time, on budget, on scope" are misaligned.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
