<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Data Analysis Framework">
  <summary>Data analysis components, five-step process, three modeling levels, and entity-relationship notation.</summary>

  <section title="Five-Step Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — Identify data needs: for each user role and system function, ask what information is displayed, captured, calculated, stored, and shared.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping need identification produces a data model that stores what developers guess rather than what the business requires.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Define data elements: document each attribute with name, business definition, type, format, valid values, source, and owner.</statement>
      <rationale>Without business definitions, developers implement technical interpretations that conflict across systems and reports.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Create data model at three levels: conceptual (high-level entities and relationships for business stakeholders), logical (detailed attributes and rules for BA and developers), physical (tables, columns, indexes for database developers).</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing levels produces models that are too abstract for developers or too technical for business review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Analyze data quality across six dimensions: accuracy, completeness, consistency, timeliness, validity, uniqueness. Measure each with a quantitative metric before defining improvement targets.</statement>
      <rationale>Unmeasured data quality produces subjective "bad data" complaints with no baseline to track improvement against.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5 — Define data rules: document validation rules, derivation formulas, default values, constraints, and uniqueness requirements as testable statements.</statement>
      <rationale>Business rules embedded in code without documentation become invisible and are lost when developers change; they must live in the data dictionary.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Data Quality Dimensions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure accuracy as error rate (% of records with incorrect values vs. authoritative source), completeness as missing value %, consistency as conflict count across systems, timeliness as average data age, validity as % of records violating business rules, uniqueness as duplicate rate.</statement>
      <rationale>Each dimension requires a distinct metric; a single "data quality score" hides which dimension is failing and which remediation to apply.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Modeling Levels">
    <p>Conceptual: entities and relationships only, no attributes. Audience: business stakeholders. Purpose: confirm scope.</p>
    <p>Logical: entities with all attributes, data types, relationships with cardinality, business rules. Audience: BA, developers. Purpose: design contract.</p>
    <p>Physical: tables, columns, indexes, foreign keys, partitioning. Audience: database developers. Purpose: implementation spec.</p>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/data-dictionary.md">Per-entity data dictionary template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/data-requirements.md">Project-level data requirements document</reference>
</text>
