<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-quality-rules" title="Data Quality Rules and Business Rules">
  <summary>Six quality dimensions with measurable metrics and data business rule types with examples.</summary>

  <section title="Quality Dimension Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign each data quality dimension a numeric score (1-5), a traffic-light status (Green/Yellow/Red), and a remediation priority (H/M/L) in the assessment report.</statement>
      <rationale>Qualitative assessments ("data is inconsistent") produce no remediation priority; numeric scores enable comparison across dimensions and tracking over time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never declare a dimension "Green" without a measured sample from production data of at least 100 records or 10% of total volume, whichever is larger.</statement>
      <rationale>Small samples miss systemic issues; a 1% error rate on 10,000 records represents 100 corrupted records that will affect operations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Data Rule Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document every business rule as one of: Validation (field-level constraint), Derivation (formula), Default (initial value), Constraint (cross-field or cross-entity), or Uniqueness (key definition).</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing rule types in a single list makes it impossible to generate validators, ETL transformations, and database constraints from the same document.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Validation: Email must contain @ and a domain with at least one dot</item>
      <item>Derivation: OrderTotal = sum(LineItem.Quantity * LineItem.Price) + ShippingCost - DiscountAmount</item>
      <item>Default: CustomerStatus defaults to "Prospect" on record creation</item>
      <item>Constraint: ShipDate must be on or after OrderDate</item>
      <item>Uniqueness: CustomerID is system-generated and immutable; Email is unique across all active customers</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No data dictionary — every developer defines data elements independently.</description>
      <reason>Without shared definitions, integration and reporting produce conflicting numbers that erode trust in all data.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping data quality assessment — assuming existing data is correct before migration.</description>
      <reason>Data quality issues discovered during migration cause project delays; assessing early allows remediation to run in parallel with development.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No data ownership defined — no one accountable for data accuracy or access.</description>
      <reason>Unowned data degrades over time; ownership assigns the accountability needed to maintain quality rules.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring historical data — modeling current state without considering how data changes over time.</description>
      <reason>Temporal requirements (audit trails, soft deletes, effective-date ranges) discovered after the physical model is built require schema rework.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/data-quality-assessment.md">Quality assessment report with per-dimension scoring</reference>
</text>
