<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-structure-and-patterns" title="File Structure, File Change Table, and Usage Rules">
  <summary>File structure table and file change table from the authentication example, plus rules for injecting examples as few-shot context and gotchas for agents using examples.</summary>

  <section title="File Change Table">
    <p>Every design.md must include a file change table with Action (CREATE/MODIFY/DELETE), File, Description, FR, and AD columns. Missing test files is the most common omission.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Auth feature file change table — observe that test files are explicit entries</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Action | File                              | Description                  | FR     | AD    |
|--------|-----------------------------------|------------------------------|--------|-------|
| CREATE | src/auth/handlers/register.ts    | User registration endpoint   | FR-001 | AD-001, AD-002 |
| CREATE | src/auth/handlers/login.ts       | User login endpoint          | FR-004 | AD-002, AD-004 |
| CREATE | src/auth/handlers/logout.ts      | User logout endpoint         | FR-005 | AD-004 |
| CREATE | src/auth/services/password.ts    | Password hashing/verification| FR-003 | AD-002 |
| CREATE | src/auth/services/jwt.ts         | JWT generation/verification  | FR-004 | AD-003, AD-004 |
| CREATE | src/auth/services/email.ts       | Email validation             | FR-002 | AD-001 |
| CREATE | src/auth/middleware/protect.ts   | JWT auth middleware          | FR-006 | AD-004 |
| CREATE | src/auth/types.ts                | TypeScript interfaces        | FR-001 | -     |
| CREATE | src/auth/index.ts                | Router configuration         | FR-001 | -     |
| CREATE | database/migrations/001_users.sql| User table schema            | FR-001 | -     |
| CREATE | tests/auth/register.test.ts      | Registration tests           | FR-001 | -     |
| CREATE | tests/auth/login.test.ts         | Login tests                  | FR-004 | -     |
| CREATE | tests/auth/middleware.test.ts    | Middleware tests              | FR-006 | -     |
]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>File change table without test file entries.</description>
      <reason>Agents stop after source files and treat tests as optional. Tests must be explicit CREATE entries or they will not be implemented.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Using Examples as Few-Shot Context">
    <rule>
      <statement>Inject the relevant example domain (auth for user-identity features, payment for transactional features) as a structural reference in the design-generation prompt. Never mix domains.</statement>
      <rationale>TypeScript interface examples cause agents to generate TypeScript even in Python projects if example is injected without domain filtering.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Annotate example ADs with why each alternative was rejected, not just what was rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>The rejection reason is where agents learn decision-making. An alternatives table without rejection reasons produces agents that list straw-man options.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Review the generated design against the FR coverage table — every FR-X from spec must appear in at least one AD and one file entry.</statement>
      <rationale>The coverage table is the reconciliation step that catches FRs that slipped through the AD drafting pass.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent copies bcrypt cost 12 or JWT 7-day expiry from example into every project.</description>
      <reason>Examples encode defaults, not decisions. Always filter example technology choices through the project constitution.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Alternatives Considered table always has exactly 2-3 rows because example has 2-3 rows.</description>
      <reason>The example count is illustrative. Complex decisions may need 4+ alternatives. Prompt explicitly to consider all real options.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent reproduces directory tree diagrams as ASCII art from file structure examples.</description>
      <reason>Project rules prohibit ASCII art. Use directory tree format (allowed) or a file change table only.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/fr-coverage-check.py">Verifies every FR-X from spec appears in design's FR coverage table</reference>
</text>
