<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="design-doc-examples Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for design-doc-examples as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>File change table without test file entries.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents stop after source files and treat tests as optional. Tests must be explicit CREATE entries or they will not be implemented.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent copies bcrypt cost 12 or JWT 7-day expiry from example into every project.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Examples encode defaults, not decisions. Always filter example technology choices through the project constitution.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Alternatives Considered table always has exactly 2-3 rows because example has 2-3 rows.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The example count is illustrative. Complex decisions may need 4+ alternatives. Prompt explicitly to consider all real options.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent reproduces directory tree diagrams as ASCII art from file structure examples.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Project rules prohibit ASCII art. Use directory tree format (allowed) or a file change table only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Component hierarchy examples assume React; agent will confuse these with backend component diagrams.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Examples demonstrate correct structure but cannot show incorrect structure being caught and fixed. Filter examples by technology stack.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Examples are static snapshots; they don't reflect how a real design evolves through review cycles.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Real designs change through feedback. Use examples as calibration points, not final answers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
