<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Freelance Weekly Invoice Cadence Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Freelance Weekly Invoice Cadence methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="invoice-cadence-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Invoice batch runs on a fixed weekday (e.g. Monday 09:00 local) every calendar week the engagement is active; skipping a week silently is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Form-discipline research (Cooper, About Face 2014)">predictability is the whole point — clients reschedule cash around your cadence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="invoice-per-client-row" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every active client produces exactly one invoice row per cycle even if amount is zero; zero-rows MUST carry an explicit reason (paused, refund, free-month) instead of being silently omitted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-omission practice in accounting (FASB ASC 605)">silently empty client rows make 'we forgot' indistinguishable from 'on purpose'.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="reminder-ladder-three-rungs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reminder ladder fires at exactly day +3, +7, +14 past the due date with escalating tone (gentle nudge -&gt; firm follow-up -&gt; pause-engagement notice); ad-hoc reminders outside the ladder are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Collections industry best practice (ACA International)">predictable cadence with three rungs collects most without burning the relationship.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="escalation-needs-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Escalation to pause-engagement requires a single named owner on the operator side AND a single named recipient on the client side; generic mailboxes alone are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene (PMBOK 7 Tailoring)">un-named recipients drop escalations; one human on each side keeps it actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-per-amount" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every non-zero invoice amount MUST cite a verbatim source: timesheet row, scoped deliverable line, or signed retainer clause; fields without anchor are rejected as fabrication.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice for billing automation">LLM-driven invoicing cheerfully invents plausible hours; anchoring keeps it auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="self-approval-forbidden" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Status approved_to_send MUST come from a human reviewer, never the generating agent itself.</statement>
      <rationale source="Self-approval anti-pattern (Faion safety policy)">agent self-approval defeats the human checkpoint and the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
