<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Voice UI Basics Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Voice UI Basics. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-closed-intent-set" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Intent set is closed at ≤20 high-level goals; out-of-set utterances are routed to a fallback intent.</statement>
      <rationale source="Closed-taxonomy principle; VUI platform constraints">Open intent sets explode the disambiguation surface; ≤20 keeps the dialog manager trainable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-prompts-under-15-words" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each prompt is ≤15 words (roughly 5 seconds of speech); longer prompts truncate user attention.</statement>
      <rationale source="Voice-UX literature">Spoken text &gt;15 words exceeds working-memory; users miss the action.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-error-matrix-three-cases" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every flow handles three error cases explicitly: no-input (silence), no-match (utterance does not map to any intent), and fallback (system error). Each has a recovery path.</statement>
      <rationale source="Conversational-design best practice">Silent stranding is the #1 voice UX bug; the matrix forces a recovery path for each case.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-confirmation-on-destructive-intents" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Destructive intents (delete, cancel, purchase) require an explicit yes/no confirmation prompt; one-shot destructive flows are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Safety-discipline convention">Voice misrecognition rates make one-shot destructive flows dangerous; the confirmation absorbs the false positive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-test-with-real-voice" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every flow is tested on the target device with real voice (not text simulator); text-only test passes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Voice-UX testing convention">Real-voice surfaces ASR errors that text simulators hide; without it, flow ships with hidden failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-voice-ui-basics.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
