<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Decision Log Template Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Design Decision Log Template. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-append-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The log is append-only; superseded rows are NEVER edited. A superseding row references the prior row id and the prior row&apos;s status flips to &apos;superseded-by-NNN&apos;.</statement>
      <rationale source="ADR immutability convention">Editing accepted rows destroys the historical record needed to understand the path that produced the current design.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-active-voice-decision" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision text starts with &apos;We will&apos; or &apos;We chose&apos; in active voice; passive phrasing (&apos;it was decided&apos;) is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nygard ADR convention">Active voice forces a clear actor and choice; passive voice hides the decision behind ambiguity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-two-alternatives-min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each row carries at least 2 considered alternatives with a one-line rejection reason; single-option rows are rejected (use a no-decision-yet status instead).</statement>
      <rationale source="ADR-quality audit">Without alternatives the decision is unfalsifiable; the same debate recurs in week 4.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-thread-link-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every row carries the original thread / Figma / standup link so reviewers can audit the original context; prose-only context is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Grounded-decision convention">Untraceable rows become folklore; the link lets future readers reconstruct what was actually said.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-named-owner-and-date" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Owner field is a named handle; row carries last_reviewed date. Stale rows (&gt;180 days unreviewed) surface a warning on read.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI + anti-decay practice">Plural ownership = no ownership; dated review forces refresh cadence on the bank.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-design-decision-log-template.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
