<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Jira Workflow Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Jira Workflow Management methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="one-workflow-per-issue-type" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each issue type (Story / Bug / Task / Epic) MUST have exactly one workflow; per-project workflow forks are forbidden unless an ADR exists.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian docs (workflow schemes)">workflow forks break cross-project reporting and force every dashboard to special-case projects.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="transition-rules-source-of-truth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Transition rules (validators / conditions / post-functions) MUST be defined on the workflow, not in automation rules; mixing both is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian docs">split definitions cause one set of rules to silently override the other; debugging becomes guesswork.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="status-categories-mapped" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every workflow status MUST be mapped to one of Jira's status categories (To Do / In Progress / Done); un-categorised statuses are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian docs (status categories)">without category mapping, boards group statuses incorrectly and cycle-time metrics break.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="automation-namespaced" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Automation rules MUST be namespaced (e.g. project/&lt;scope&gt;/&lt;purpose&gt;) and version-tagged; un-namespaced rules are flagged for cleanup.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Jira automation audits">un-namespaced automation rules accumulate and silently overlap; debugging takes hours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="jql-shared-via-filter" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>JQL queries used by dashboards MUST be stored as shared filters with stable IDs; ad-hoc JQL embedded in dashboards is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian docs (filters)">embedded JQL changes silently when someone edits the dashboard; shared filters preserve audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="permissions-scoped-to-role" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Permission schemes MUST be scoped to roles (Developer / Reviewer / Admin), not individual users.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian security guidance">per-user permissions rot when people change roles and create permission drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
