<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-automation-jql" title="Jira Automation Rules and JQL Queries">
  <summary>Rules for automation rule design, essential JQL query patterns, and integration with CI/CD pipelines.</summary>

  <section title="Automation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Test automation rules in a sandbox project with a copy of production schemes before promoting; tag every automation-created issue with an "automation" label for audit.</statement>
      <rationale>Automation rules that fire in production before testing can transition thousands of issues incorrectly in seconds. Sandbox validation catches logic errors safely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add cycle guards to all automation rules; a rule that triggers rule B that triggers rule A creates infinite loops that burn the monthly automation budget instantly.</statement>
      <rationale>Jira Cloud enforces per-tier monthly automation execution limits. Loops exhaust the budget within minutes, silencing all automations for the rest of the month.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[# Auto-close subtasks when parent done
rule: close_subtasks
trigger: parent_issue_done
condition: all_subtasks_not_closed
action: transition_subtasks_to_done

# Slack notification on blocker
rule: notify_on_blocker
trigger: priority_changed_to_blocker
action: send_slack_message(channel="#dev-alerts")]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Creating automation rules that fire on issue creation without a label filter.</description>
      <reason>Broad creation triggers fire on every issue in the project, including bulk imports, dramatically inflating execution counts and frequently producing incorrect results on migrated issues.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="JQL Query Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate JQL queries with "validateQuery=strict" in the REST API before storing or executing them; never assume a JQL string from an LLM is valid.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs frequently hallucinate Jira field names. The strict validator returns field-level errors that allow targeted correction before silent failures in production.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="sql"><![CDATA[-- My open issues
assignee = currentUser() AND resolution = Unresolved

-- Current sprint backlog
project = PROJ AND sprint in openSprints()

-- Bugs created this week
project = PROJ AND type = Bug AND created >= -7d

-- Blocked items
status = "In Progress" AND flagged = "Impediment"

-- Overdue issues
duedate < now() AND resolution = Unresolved

-- Features without linked stories
issuetype = Feature AND issueFunction not in subtasksOf("issuetype = Story")]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="CI/CD Integration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use "smart commits" to link branches via "PROJ-123" in commit messages; do not rely on humans to manually link PRs to issues after the fact.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual PR-to-issue linking has near-zero compliance on active teams. Smart commits wire the link at source without workflow friction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Convert agent-generated Markdown to ADF (Atlassian Document Format) before writing to Jira description or comment fields; Markdown written directly produces empty or malformed fields.</statement>
      <rationale>Jira's description field accepts HTML/ADF, not Markdown. Agents writing raw Markdown silently produce fields with visible Markdown syntax or empty content.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/workflow-states.yaml">Standard development workflow statuses and transitions with validators</reference>
  <reference path="templates/bulk-transition.py">Bulk JQL-driven issue transition with rate-limit safety</reference>
</text>
