<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="jira-workflow-management Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for jira-workflow-management as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Adding global transitions to "Done" from any state.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Global-to-Done transitions let issues skip QA and review stages, producing false "Done" counts and audit trail gaps.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating automation rules that fire on issue creation without a label filter.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Broad creation triggers fire on every issue in the project, including bulk imports, dramatically inflating execution counts and frequently producing incorrect results on migrated issues.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents writing field names from training knowledge rather than the live Jira field schema.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Jira custom field IDs differ per instance. Cache /rest/api/3/field and provide the schema in the system prompt; reject any output containing field names not in the schema.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Bulk transitions without rate-limit handling on Jira Cloud.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Jira Cloud enforces approximately 50 req/s per site. Unthrottled bulk transitions hit 429s immediately; exponential backoff with Retry-After header is required.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Applying workflows designed for Jira Cloud to a Data Center or Server instance.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cloud and DC/Server have different automation engines, API surfaces, and permission models. Code working on one frequently fails on the other.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
