<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stat-Power Pre-Check Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every Stat-Power Pre-Check application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them. Plus a skip-methodology rule for decision-tree leaves that exit the methodology.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-required-inputs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All five inputs (weekly_visitors, baseline_conversion, target_relative_lift, alpha, power) are typed and present. Missing any = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-first">Verdict math is only as good as the inputs; missing inputs make verdicts folklore.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-no-launch-without-verdict" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No experiment launches without a recorded GO / STRETCH / KILL verdict in the ledger.</statement>
      <rationale source="Pre-flight discipline">Launching without a verdict is how underpowered tests proliferate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-minimum-conversions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Minimum 100 conversions per variant before reading results. Verdicts with smaller minimums are flagged as exploratory.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stat floor">Sub-100 conversions per variant produces noise indistinguishable from signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-sequential-stop-guard" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No sequential / &apos;peeking&apos; stops without a documented sequential-testing method (e.g. SPRT, Bayesian).</statement>
      <rationale source="Multiple-comparisons guard">Naive peeking inflates false-positive rate dramatically.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-lift-as-relative" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Target lift is expressed as a relative percentage (e.g. 10%), never absolute percentage points. Absolute lifts are converted to relative before scoring.</statement>
      <rationale source="Comparability">Relative lift normalises across pages with different baselines.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-window-frozen" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test window is declared up front. Extending without a new verdict invalidates the test.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-window-shopping">Post-hoc window extension manufactures wins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the decision tree resolves to a skip branch — preconditions are not met OR an adjacent methodology fits better.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-tree discipline">Skipping cleanly preserves the integrity of the rubric; misapplied methodologies produce false positives downstream.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
