<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stat Power Pre-Check Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that prevent underpowered CRO experiments from being launched. Each rule is a refusal gate; STRETCH or KILL verdicts are valid outputs, not failures of the methodology.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-required-inputs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before launching ANY CRO experiment, the marketer MUST record five inputs: (a) weekly unique visitors to the test surface, (b) baseline conversion rate over the last 4 weeks, (c) target relative lift expressed as a percentage, (d) significance alpha (default 0.05), (e) desired statistical power (default 0.80). Missing any one input → verdict cannot be issued → experiment cannot launch.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cohen 1988; standard frequentist power analysis">Power analysis is a function of these five inputs. Any one missing makes the verdict guesswork. Forcing the marketer to fill them all converts vague intent ("let's try this") into a calibrated decision, even when the math itself is delegated to a calculator.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-no-launch-without-verdict" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The experiment MUST be tagged with a verdict (GO / STRETCH / KILL) recorded in the experiment ledger before the test goes live. GO = stated lift detectable within the agreed window at stated power. STRETCH = detectable only if window extended OR power lowered to ≥0.70; the extension MUST be approved and logged. KILL = stated lift undetectable in any reasonable window; pivot to a structural change or qualitative method.</statement>
      <rationale source="Experiment-ledger-discipline pattern">Without a recorded verdict, post-hoc rationalisation reigns: any direction of result will be claimed as the intended one. A pre-registered verdict, even informal, anchors the post-test conversation in the original power expectation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-minimum-conversions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each variant MUST be projected to collect at least 200 conversion events over the test window before the experiment is GO. If the projection is below 200/variant the verdict is KILL regardless of what the parametric calculator returns. Use qualitative methods (5-second tests, interviews, session replays) instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practical CRO floors; rule-of-thumb from Evan Miller and CXL Institute">Below ~200 conversions per variant, even theoretically detectable lifts are dominated by week-to-week variance and seasonality. The parametric calculator's confidence is misleading at low counts. The floor is a heuristic guard against false precision.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-no-sequential-peeking" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The test MUST run to the pre-computed sample size before any significance check is performed, OR use an explicit sequential-testing method (Bayesian / mSPRT / always-valid p-values) that controls error under repeated peeking. "Peeking daily and stopping when p &lt; 0.05" is FORBIDDEN and invalidates the verdict.</statement>
      <rationale source="Johari, Pekelis, Walsh 2017 on peeking; Optimizely Stats Engine">Repeated significance checks on fixed-horizon tests inflate the Type-I error far above the nominal alpha. A test designed for alpha=0.05 with daily peeking can have actual false-positive rate of 30%+. The rule is a hard procedural gate, not a preference.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-lift-as-relative" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Target lift MUST be expressed as a RELATIVE percentage on the baseline rate (e.g. "10% lift on a 2% baseline = detect 2.2%"), NOT as absolute percentage points. Calculators that take absolute points MUST receive the correctly converted absolute delta; the AGENTS.md / ledger entry MUST show both.</statement>
      <rationale source="Common power-calculator misuse pattern">Confusing relative percentage with absolute percentage points is the single most common error in CRO power inputs. "10% lift" on a 2% baseline is a 0.2pp delta — about 5x the sample size of a 1pp delta. Forcing both forms in the ledger catches this before launch.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Worked example">

    <example type="good" title="GO verdict — primary landing page, signup flow">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
inputs:
  weekly_visitors: 8000
  baseline_conversion: 3.0%   (4-week mean, stable ±15%)
  target_lift_relative: 15%   (3.0% → 3.45%)
  target_lift_absolute_pp: 0.45pp
  alpha: 0.05
  power: 0.80

calculator: Evan Miller two-proportion
required_sample_per_variant: ~5,400 visitors
projected_conversions_per_variant: ~162 over 1 week, ~648 over 4 weeks

window: 4 weeks
verdict: GO
notes: comfortably above the 200-conversions floor; no peeking; ledger entry created
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1-r5 all satisfied. Both relative and absolute form recorded. Conversions floor cleared at week 2.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="KILL verdict — boutique site, contact-form conversion">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
inputs:
  weekly_visitors: 600
  baseline_conversion: 1.0%
  target_lift_relative: 10%
  target_lift_absolute_pp: 0.10pp
  alpha: 0.05
  power: 0.80

calculator: required_sample_per_variant: ~155,000 visitors
projected_conversions_per_variant: ~6 over 1 week

window: any reasonable window
verdict: KILL
notes: 200-conversions floor unreachable within 6 months; switch to 5-second tests + 5
user interviews on the new headline; revisit with a structural redesign, not an A/B
      ]]></code>
      <note>r3 (conversions floor) hard-fails — the parametric calculator would say "run for 6 months", which is operationally absurd. KILL is the correct verdict.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../../../../pro/marketing/experiment-hypothesis-scoring/"/>
    <link path="../../../../pro/marketing/experiment-ledger-discipline/"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
