<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Decision Log Reconstruction From Git Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Decision Log Reconstruction From Git application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-three-source-triangulation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every reconstructed decision MUST triangulate at least two of: commit message body, PR description, linked ticket. Single-source decisions are flagged 'unconfirmed' and held out of the main log.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Single-source reconstruction yields high false-positive rates (a commit may describe a refactor that happens to coincide with the decision); triangulation is the standard archaeology bias control.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-adr-pattern-match" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The detector MUST emit only decisions that fit the ADR shape: identifiable context + at least one rejected alternative + concrete consequences. Bare 'we did X' commits are skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Including bare changes pollutes the log with code-change records rather than decision records; the receiver cannot tell signal from churn.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-dedupe-by-cluster" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decisions that recur across &gt;=3 commits (e.g. 'use repository pattern') MUST be collapsed into one ADR with a commits list; per-commit duplicates are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Without clustering, the log grows linearly with commit count and becomes unusable; clustering compresses repeat decisions into one entry per topic.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-owner-signoff" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each reconstructed ADR MUST be signed off by a named original-author or current-maintainer. Un-signed ADRs are emitted with status='proposed' and excluded from the published log.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">LLM reconstruction is plausible but often wrong about intent; signoff is the falsifier.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-cross-link-to-commit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every ADR MUST embed the originating commit SHAs and PR numbers. ADRs without back-links are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Without back-links the ADR is hearsay; the SHA is the proof the receiver can re-read in 2 years.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
