<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="azure-devops-boards Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for azure-devops-boards. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Inherited processes only; never customize system fields; pin one process per organization across all projects.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">XML "Hosted XML" process customization is deprecated in ADO cloud. Mixing Agile and Scrum across projects breaks cross-project WIQL queries because work-item type names differ (User Story vs PBI).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tie commits to work items via "AB#1234" in commit message — ADO auto-links the commit, build, and release to the work item without any additional configuration.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AB# linking is the only zero-configuration traceability mechanism in ADO. It creates the commit-to-work-item-to-build-to-release chain that justifies ADO over standalone PM tools.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set up a "definition of ready" board column rule to block User Stories without Acceptance Criteria from entering the sprint; enforce this at the board, not in team norms.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Board-level enforcement is applied universally; team norms are inconsistently applied under sprint pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use iteration path strings exactly as configured — they are case-sensitive and use backslash separators; "Project/Sprint 1" and "Project\Sprint 1" are different paths.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">ADO iteration paths fail silently when the separator or casing is wrong, producing empty assignment results with no error message.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use WIQL for live queries on current sprint and board state; use Analytics OData for any report spanning more than 2 sprints — WIQL is slow and times out on historical trend queries.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">WIQL executes against the live work-item store; it is optimized for current-state lookups. Analytics OData is a pre-aggregated columnar store designed for historical analysis and Power BI integration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write automation rules that set the iteration path on activation only when the field is currently empty; unconditional iteration-set rules override manual assignments.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unconditional iteration assignment on state change silently moves manually-placed items to the current sprint, losing planned placement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always re-fetch a work item after creating it via REST and validate required fields are set — ADO returns 200 OK on partial creation when a custom field value is invalid.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Silent partial creation is ADO's most dangerous API behavior for agents. Re-fetching and validating catches the failure before downstream steps depend on corrupt state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rotate PATs via Azure Key Vault; never embed PAT values in agent system prompts, environment variables in code, or configuration files checked into source control.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">PATs have broad scopes. Embedded PATs are leaked via logs, process lists, and prompt injection. Key Vault provides rotation without code changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints are mandatory at: work-item hierarchy approval before creation, bulk-transition approval, schema changes, and any pipeline configuration change.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These operations affect all team members or the CI/CD pipeline simultaneously and are expensive to reverse.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
