<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process-setup" title="Azure DevOps Boards Process Templates, Hierarchy, and Configuration">
  <summary>Rules for process template selection, work-item hierarchy design, board configuration, and area/iteration path setup.</summary>

  <section title="Process Template Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Inherited processes only; never customize system fields; pin one process per organization across all projects.</statement>
      <rationale>XML "Hosted XML" process customization is deprecated in ADO cloud. Mixing Agile and Scrum across projects breaks cross-project WIQL queries because work-item type names differ (User Story vs PBI).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Basic: Issue, Task — for simple non-engineering projects with minimal hierarchy.</item>
      <item>Agile: Epic, Feature, User Story, Task, Bug — for agile software teams; most agent-friendly due to widespread training data.</item>
      <item>Scrum: Epic, Feature, PBI, Task, Bug, Impediment — for Scrum teams; PBI instead of User Story.</item>
      <item>CMMI: Epic, Feature, Requirement, Task, Bug, Change Request, Review, Risk — for regulated industries requiring full audit trail on every transition.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Work Item Hierarchy">
    <list>
      <item>Epic: large initiative; business value and time criticality fields; maps to OKRs for portfolio reporting.</item>
      <item>Feature: shippable capability within an Epic; must have acceptance criteria and story points.</item>
      <item>User Story (or PBI): unit of user value; Gherkin-format acceptance criteria recommended.</item>
      <item>Task: technical work item with remaining work hours for sprint burndown.</item>
      <item>Bug: defect that can exist at any hierarchy level.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tie commits to work items via "AB#1234" in commit message — ADO auto-links the commit, build, and release to the work item without any additional configuration.</statement>
      <rationale>AB# linking is the only zero-configuration traceability mechanism in ADO. It creates the commit-to-work-item-to-build-to-release chain that justifies ADO over standalone PM tools.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Board Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set up a "definition of ready" board column rule to block User Stories without Acceptance Criteria from entering the sprint; enforce this at the board, not in team norms.</statement>
      <rationale>Board-level enforcement is applied universally; team norms are inconsistently applied under sprint pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[board_settings:
  columns:
    - name: "New"
      state_mapping: ["New"]
    - name: "Active"
      state_mapping: ["Active"]
      wip_limit: 5
      split: true  # Doing/Done split within column
    - name: "Resolved"
      state_mapping: ["Resolved"]
      wip_limit: 3
    - name: "Closed"
      state_mapping: ["Closed"]
  swimlanes:
    - name: "Expedite"
      default: false
    - name: "Default"
      default: true
  card_styles:
    - name: "Blocked"
      condition: "Tags Contains 'Blocked'"
      background_color: "#FF0000"]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Area and Iteration Paths">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use iteration path strings exactly as configured — they are case-sensitive and use backslash separators; "Project/Sprint 1" and "Project\Sprint 1" are different paths.</statement>
      <rationale>ADO iteration paths fail silently when the separator or casing is wrong, producing empty assignment results with no error message.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[iteration_path: "MyProject\\Release 1\\Sprint 1"
area_path: "MyProject\\Backend"]]></code>
      <note>Always escape backslashes in code; use double backslash in strings.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
