<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-queries-automation" title="WIQL Queries, Automation Rules, and Analytics">
  <summary>Rules for WIQL query design, automation rule patterns, pipeline integration, and when to use Analytics OData instead of WIQL.</summary>

  <section title="WIQL Query Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use WIQL for live queries on current sprint and board state; use Analytics OData for any report spanning more than 2 sprints — WIQL is slow and times out on historical trend queries.</statement>
      <rationale>WIQL executes against the live work-item store; it is optimized for current-state lookups. Analytics OData is a pre-aggregated columnar store designed for historical analysis and Power BI integration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="sql"><![CDATA[-- My active items (WIQL)
SELECT [System.Id], [System.Title], [System.State]
FROM WorkItems
WHERE [System.AssignedTo] = @Me
  AND [System.State] IN ('New', 'Active')
ORDER BY [Microsoft.VSTS.Common.Priority]

-- Current sprint burndown (WIQL)
SELECT [System.Id], [System.Title],
       [Microsoft.VSTS.Scheduling.RemainingWork]
FROM WorkItems
WHERE [System.IterationPath] = @CurrentIteration
  AND [System.WorkItemType] IN ('User Story', 'Bug', 'Task')

-- Features without child stories (WIQL)
SELECT [System.Id], [System.Title]
FROM WorkItems
WHERE [System.WorkItemType] = 'Feature'
  AND [System.State] <> 'Closed'
  AND NOT [System.Id] IN (
    SELECT [System.Parent]
    FROM WorkItems
    WHERE [System.WorkItemType] = 'User Story'
  )]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>WIQL WAS queries on large issue sets for historical analysis.</description>
      <reason>WAS queries on transition history time out above approximately 10,000 issues. Use Analytics WorkItemRevisions entity via OData for historical state analysis.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Automation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write automation rules that set the iteration path on activation only when the field is currently empty; unconditional iteration-set rules override manual assignments.</statement>
      <rationale>Unconditional iteration assignment on state change silently moves manually-placed items to the current sprint, losing planned placement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[rules:
  - name: "Auto-close children when parent done"
    trigger: child_state_changed
    conditions:
      - all_children_state: "Closed"
    actions:
      - set_state: "Closed"

  - name: "Set iteration on first activation"
    trigger: state_changed_to_active
    conditions:
      - iteration_is_empty: true
    actions:
      - set_iteration: "@CurrentIteration"]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Pipeline Integration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always re-fetch a work item after creating it via REST and validate required fields are set — ADO returns 200 OK on partial creation when a custom field value is invalid.</statement>
      <rationale>Silent partial creation is ADO's most dangerous API behavior for agents. Re-fetching and validating catches the failure before downstream steps depend on corrupt state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Rotate PATs via Azure Key Vault; never embed PAT values in agent system prompts, environment variables in code, or configuration files checked into source control.</statement>
      <rationale>PATs have broad scopes. Embedded PATs are leaked via logs, process lists, and prompt injection. Key Vault provides rotation without code changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[# azure-pipelines.yml
stages:
  - stage: UpdateWorkItem
    jobs:
      - job: LinkToBoard
        steps:
          - task: UpdateWorkItem@1
            inputs:
              workItemId: $(Build.SourceVersionMessage)
              updateRule: "AddComment"
              comment: "Build $(Build.BuildNumber) completed"]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/create-story.sh">Bash script to create a User Story via ADO REST API</reference>
  <reference path="templates/user-story.md">User Story template with Gherkin acceptance criteria</reference>
</text>
