<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="azure-devops-boards Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for azure-devops-boards as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>WIQL WAS queries on large issue sets for historical analysis.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>WAS queries on transition history time out above approximately 10,000 issues. Use Analytics WorkItemRevisions entity via OData for historical state analysis.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Writing Markdown in ADO description or comment fields from an agent.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>ADO description accepts HTML, not Markdown. Agent-written Markdown displays as literal syntax or empty content. Convert to HTML using pandoc or a sanitizer before writing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Bulk-creating more than 50 work items per batch in parallel.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>ADO throttles bulk creation; unthrottled parallel batches trigger 429s. Chunk in batches of 50 with exponential backoff and check for the Retry-After header.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>WIQL queries with dropped trailing brackets or misquoted field names.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>WIQL is whitespace-sensitive and returns empty results (200 OK, zero items) for malformed queries. Always validate WIQL syntax against a known-good schema before executing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Using display names instead of identity SIDs in @mention comments.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>ADO @mentions require the user identity SID, not the display name. Display names are non-unique and produce invalid mentions. Resolve via the Identities API first.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
