<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-token-architecture" title="Tailwind + Design Token Architecture">
  <summary>How to bridge design tokens to Tailwind via CSS custom properties, separating primitive and semantic layers, enabling runtime theming.</summary>

  <section title="Token Layer Architecture">
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate primitive tokens (raw values: #1A73E8, 16px) from semantic tokens (color.action.primary, spacing.md). Tailwind config exposes only semantic tokens.</statement>
      <rationale>Semantic tokens carry intent — changing "action.primary" updates all primary actions at once. Exposing primitives in Tailwind creates direct hex dependencies that break theming and require global find-replace for any color change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use CSS custom properties as the bridge: Tailwind theme references var(--token-name); the CSS file defines the actual value. Never hardcode hex or pixel values in tailwind.config.js.</statement>
      <rationale>CSS variables as the bridge enables runtime theming (dark mode, multi-brand) without rebuilding Tailwind. The config stays static; only the CSS variable values change per context.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Configuration Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map colors to var(--color-token-name), spacing to var(--spacing-token-name), and typography to separate sub-objects (fontFamily, fontSize, lineHeight) in tailwind.config.js theme block.</statement>
      <rationale>Consistent naming across Figma Variables, CSS custom properties, and Tailwind config eliminates translation errors. One-to-one mapping makes the token → utility class relationship transparent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Tailwind config referencing CSS variables — no hardcoded values</note>
      <code lang="javascript"><![CDATA[
module.exports = {
  theme: {
    colors: {
      primary: {
        default: 'var(--color-primary)',
        hover: 'var(--color-primary-hover)',
      },
      surface: 'var(--color-surface)',
      error: 'var(--color-error)',
    },
    spacing: {
      xs: 'var(--spacing-xs)',
      sm: 'var(--spacing-sm)',
      md: 'var(--spacing-md)',
      lg: 'var(--spacing-lg)',
    },
    fontFamily: {
      sans: 'var(--font-family-sans)',
    },
  },
}
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/tailwind.config.js">Full Tailwind config with all token categories</reference>
    <reference path="templates/tokens.css">Companion CSS file with all custom property declarations</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Dark Mode and Theming">
    <rule>
      <statement>Declare light-mode tokens at :root and dark-mode tokens under [data-theme="dark"] or prefers-color-scheme: dark. Do not mix Tailwind's dark: variant with CSS variable tokens without explicit alpha-channel setup.</statement>
      <rationale>Tailwind's built-in dark: variant applies class-based toggling that may conflict with CSS variable scope. CSS variable overrides per theme selector are simpler and support more than two themes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="JIT Purge and Dynamic Classes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add token-mapped classes assembled dynamically (string concatenation) to Tailwind's safelist to prevent JIT purge from removing them.</statement>
      <rationale>JIT only keeps classes found as complete strings in source files. Dynamic assembly like `bg-${color}-500` produces no matched class in source, so JIT purges the utility. Safelist is the only fix.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Style Dictionary Pipeline">
    <p>For projects with Figma Variables or W3C DTCG token files, use Style Dictionary to transform token JSON to both the CSS custom property file and the Tailwind config token block automatically.</p>
    <reference path="templates/sd.config.js">Style Dictionary build script: W3C token JSON to Tailwind + CSS variables</reference>
  </section>
</text>
