<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="tailwind-design-tokens Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for tailwind-design-tokens as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Hardcoded hex values in tailwind.config.js: colors: { primary: '#1A73E8' }</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hardcoded values require a code rebuild for any color change, cannot be overridden at runtime for theming, and are invisible to CSS variable consumers like Storybook or server-side rendering.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using opacity modifier syntax (bg-primary/50) with CSS variable token values</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tailwind's opacity modifiers require the color value to be in RGB channels format, not a hex string or CSS variable reference. bg-primary/50 silently fails or produces incorrect output when --color-primary is a hex value.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Token naming mismatch between Figma Variables, Style Dictionary output, and Tailwind config</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Three different naming conventions (Figma uses /, Style Dictionary uses -, Tailwind uses .) cause drift that makes automated token pipelines fail and requires manual reconciliation on every design update.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Overwriting the full tailwind.config.js when regenerating tokens from a pipeline</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Full overwrites destroy manual customizations (custom screens, plugins, content paths). Always merge the generated token block into the existing config using Object.assign or spread, never replace.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Dynamic class assembly without safelist: `className={\`bg-\${colorToken}\`}`</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>JIT cannot statically analyze string templates. The class bg-primary assembled at runtime will not exist in the generated CSS because JIT never saw the complete string bg-primary in a source file.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Generating a Tailwind v3 config for a Tailwind v4 project (or vice versa)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tailwind v4 uses a CSS-first configuration approach with @theme directive; there is no tailwind.config.js. Generating v3 config for a v4 project produces a file the framework ignores entirely.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
