<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="negotiation Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for negotiation. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Separate the people from the problem: attack the issue, not the person, and allow the counterparty to maintain dignity throughout.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Attacking the person activates ego defense, which closes down creative solution space. Separating people from problem keeps both parties focused on the shared problem to solve.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Focus on interests, not positions: ask "Why is that important to you?" behind every stated demand to uncover the real need.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Positions are often incompatible; the interests behind them are usually compatible. A "non-negotiable deadline" (position) may mask "I need predictability for downstream planning" (interest) — which can be met with milestone check-ins rather than a fixed date.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Generate multiple options for mutual gain before selecting a solution — brainstorm without commitment, evaluate after.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Separating invention from decision prevents anchoring on the first reasonable option, which is rarely the best option for either party.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use objective criteria (market rates, industry standards, precedent) to evaluate options — never "because I want it".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Objective criteria depersonalize disagreement: neither party is wrong, the criterion is the arbiter. This preserves relationship while enabling firm positions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Determine your BATNA (Best Alternative To a Negotiated Agreement) before every negotiation — this sets your walk-away point and eliminates desperation signals.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Negotiators with no BATNA reveal desperation through concession speed and body language. A known walk-away point makes every offer evaluable against a real alternative.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never reveal a weak BATNA — only disclose your BATNA when it is genuinely strong and will improve your position.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Revealing a weak BATNA destroys leverage and invites the counterparty to push harder, knowing you have no exit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map the Zone of Possible Agreement before negotiating: if your walk-away and the counterparty's walk-away do not overlap, no deal is reachable and alternatives must be generated first.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Entering a negotiation where ZOPA does not exist wastes both parties' time and damages relationship. Identify the overlap — or the absence of one — before the meeting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply at most two Cialdini principles per message — stacking all six reads as a sales script and triggers skepticism.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each principle works because it operates below conscious evaluation. Stacking them makes the pattern obvious, which activates resistance rather than compliance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Anchor first with a specific number, not a range — ranges anchor on the favorable end for the counterparty.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">First numbers set the psychological reference point for the entire negotiation. Ranges like "$80K-$100K" anchor at $80K in the buyer's mind.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After making an offer, stop talking — silence makes the counterparty fill the void, often with a concession.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Discomfort with silence causes most negotiators to soften their position before they need to. Holding silence is leverage that costs nothing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use the nibble (asking for small extras after the main agreement) only after the main agreement is signed, not before.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Pre-agreement nibbles signal that you are still bargaining on the main deal, which reopens closed points. Post-agreement nibbles are small enough that the counterparty's sunk cost prevents reopening.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Respond to "Take it or leave it" by exploring the constraint behind the position, not by accepting or walking out.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">"Take it or leave it" is almost always a posture, not a real constraint. Exploring what created the constraint often surfaces a creative option neither party had considered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Human-in-loop before sending: any agent-drafted offer, counter, or persuasion message must be reviewed by the human before delivery — tone and relationship context cannot be fully captured in a brief.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The agent's BATNA and ZOPA analysis is only as accurate as the inputs; garbage in results in plausible-sounding but wrong brief out.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Simulated counterparties are too rational: real negotiators use emotion, ego, and politics — agent roleplay understates these factors.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Contract language suggestions from the agent are starting points, not final clauses; flag this explicitly in any output that includes contract terms.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The agent cannot measure which Cialdini principle will be effective for a specific individual; A/B testing is required for persuasion copy.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mechanical application of Cialdini tactics in copy can read as manipulative if the underlying offer is weak.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
