<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principled-negotiation" title="Principled Negotiation, BATNA, and ZOPA">
  <summary>Fisher and Ury's four principles of interest-based negotiation, BATNA calculation for walk-away leverage, and ZOPA analysis for determining whether a deal is possible.</summary>

  <section title="Four Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate the people from the problem: attack the issue, not the person, and allow the counterparty to maintain dignity throughout.</statement>
      <rationale>Attacking the person activates ego defense, which closes down creative solution space. Separating people from problem keeps both parties focused on the shared problem to solve.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Focus on interests, not positions: ask "Why is that important to you?" behind every stated demand to uncover the real need.</statement>
      <rationale>Positions are often incompatible; the interests behind them are usually compatible. A "non-negotiable deadline" (position) may mask "I need predictability for downstream planning" (interest) — which can be met with milestone check-ins rather than a fixed date.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Position vs interest analysis.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
POSITION: "I need a 20% raise"
INTEREST: "I need to feel valued and afford my mortgage"
→ Creative options: title change, bonus structure, equity, remote flexibility

POSITION: "Deadline is non-negotiable"
INTEREST: "I need predictability for downstream planning"
→ Creative option: fixed milestone dates with flexible final delivery
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate multiple options for mutual gain before selecting a solution — brainstorm without commitment, evaluate after.</statement>
      <rationale>Separating invention from decision prevents anchoring on the first reasonable option, which is rarely the best option for either party.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use objective criteria (market rates, industry standards, precedent) to evaluate options — never "because I want it".</statement>
      <rationale>Objective criteria depersonalize disagreement: neither party is wrong, the criterion is the arbiter. This preserves relationship while enabling firm positions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="BATNA">
    <rule>
      <statement>Determine your BATNA (Best Alternative To a Negotiated Agreement) before every negotiation — this sets your walk-away point and eliminates desperation signals.</statement>
      <rationale>Negotiators with no BATNA reveal desperation through concession speed and body language. A known walk-away point makes every offer evaluable against a real alternative.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never reveal a weak BATNA — only disclose your BATNA when it is genuinely strong and will improve your position.</statement>
      <rationale>Revealing a weak BATNA destroys leverage and invites the counterparty to push harder, knowing you have no exit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Weak BATNA: "I need this job, I have no other offers"
Strong BATNA: "I have two other offers and can freelance"
→ With a strong BATNA, state it: it shifts the counterparty's ZOPA estimate.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="ZOPA Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map the Zone of Possible Agreement before negotiating: if your walk-away and the counterparty's walk-away do not overlap, no deal is reachable and alternatives must be generated first.</statement>
      <rationale>Entering a negotiation where ZOPA does not exist wastes both parties' time and damages relationship. Identify the overlap — or the absence of one — before the meeting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You:   Walk Away $80K ←→ Target $95K ←→ Aspiration $110K
Them:  Aspiration $75K ←→ Target $90K ←→ Walk Away $105K
ZOPA:  $80K ←→ $105K  (overlap exists — deal is possible)
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/zopa-calculator.py">Python function to compute ZOPA from two walk-away values</reference>
    <reference path="templates/negotiation-prep.txt">Full preparation template covering both sides</reference>
  </section>
</text>
