<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-persuasion-and-tactics" title="Cialdini's Principles, Tactical Moves, and Handling Hard Situations">
  <summary>Cialdini's six principles of persuasion with business applications, five negotiation tactics (anchoring, silence, flinch, bracketing, nibble), and scripts for handling hardball situations.</summary>

  <section title="Cialdini's Six Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply at most two Cialdini principles per message — stacking all six reads as a sales script and triggers skepticism.</statement>
      <rationale>Each principle works because it operates below conscious evaluation. Stacking them makes the pattern obvious, which activates resistance rather than compliance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Reciprocity: give value first — offer a free audit, report, or consultation before asking for anything</item>
      <item>Commitment: get small yes agreements early — "Do you agree quality is important?" → "Does our approach improve quality?" → "Shall we proceed?"</item>
      <item>Social Proof: "Companies like [similar company] saw 40% improvement"</item>
      <item>Authority: cite credentials, data, and research — not just assertions</item>
      <item>Liking: find genuine common ground before disagreeing</item>
      <item>Scarcity: "Only 2 project slots left this quarter" — only use if true</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Tactical Moves">
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor first with a specific number, not a range — ranges anchor on the favorable end for the counterparty.</statement>
      <rationale>First numbers set the psychological reference point for the entire negotiation. Ranges like "$80K-$100K" anchor at $80K in the buyer's mind.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>After making an offer, stop talking — silence makes the counterparty fill the void, often with a concession.</statement>
      <rationale>Discomfort with silence causes most negotiators to soften their position before they need to. Holding silence is leverage that costs nothing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Bracketing to reach a target number.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Target: $90K
Their offer: $80K
Counter: $100K
Expected midpoint: $90K  ← your target
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the nibble (asking for small extras after the main agreement) only after the deal is signed, not before.</statement>
      <rationale>Pre-agreement nibbles signal that you are still bargaining on the main deal, which reopens closed points. Post-agreement nibbles are small enough that the counterparty's sunk cost prevents reopening.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Handling Hard Situations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Respond to "Take it or leave it" by exploring the constraint behind the position, not by accepting or walking out.</statement>
      <rationale>"Take it or leave it" is almost always a posture, not a real constraint. Exploring what created the constraint often surfaces a creative option neither party had considered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"I understand this is your position. Help me understand
the constraints that led to it. Maybe we can find another way
to meet your needs while also addressing mine."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Price objection responses.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Too expensive" → "Compared to what?"
"Over budget"   → "What is your budget?"
"Cheaper elsewhere" → "What else is different?"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Accepting the first offer.</description>
    <reason>First offers are anchors, not final positions. Accepting immediately signals that the offer was too generous, which the counterparty will remember in future negotiations.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Negotiating complex issues over email.</description>
    <reason>Email removes tone and timing signals, which are 60-80% of negotiation information. Use email for documenting agreements, not for reaching them.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
