<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Earned Value Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Earned Value Management. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="baselines-frozen" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>PV (Planned Value) curve and AC (Actual Cost) collection MUST start from frozen scope, schedule, and cost baselines. Estimates-in-flight cannot serve as baseline.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI Practice Standard for EVM (2nd ed.)">EVM math collapses without a stable PV; comparing EV against a moving PV produces nonsense indices.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="ev-from-completion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Earned Value MUST be computed from objective completion criteria (0/50/100 or %-complete rule defined in EVM plan). Subjective 'feels 80%' is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI Practice Standard for EVM">Subjective EV is gameable; objective criteria produce auditable indices.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="indices-thresholds" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CPI and SPI MUST be reported each period with thresholds: ≥0.95 green, 0.85-0.95 amber, &lt;0.85 red. Red triggers corrective-action plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="DoD EVMS Gold Card">Threshold-less reporting hides drift; the rule forces explicit action when indices breach.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="eac-method-cited" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each EAC (Estimate at Completion) value MUST cite its method (BAC/CPI, AC + ETC, optimistic, regression). Mixing methods within one report is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI Practice Standard for EVM">Different EAC methods produce different forecasts; uncited values mislead stakeholders about confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="re-baseline-via-change-control" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-baselining (changing PV mid-project) MUST go through change-control with sponsor approval. Silent re-baselining is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Integrated Change Control">Silent re-baselining hides cost overrun; the rule ties EVM to the change-control audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Earned Value Management fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Earned Value Management outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
