<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="earned-value-management Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for earned-value-management. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use objective % complete only: 0/50/100 rule, milestone-based, or units-completed — never subjective opinion.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Subjective % complete (team says "80% done") corrupts EV and cascades into false SPI/CPI/EAC values. One inflated EV reading misleads stakeholders for the rest of the project.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Color-code: SPI/CPI in [0.95, 1.05] = green; [0.85, 0.95) = yellow; below 0.85 = red.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Consistent thresholds across all reporting periods allow stakeholders to compare status at a glance without reinterpreting scales each time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Flag TCPI greater than 1.10 as likely unrecoverable; escalate to sponsor for re-baseline or scope reduction decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">TCPI greater than 1.10 means the remaining work must be completed 10% more efficiently than the project has averaged — statistically improbable without a structural intervention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track EVM at WBS level 3-4; not at the leaf task level and not at the project summary level only.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Leaf-level tracking generates noise from individual task estimation error. Summary-level tracking hides which work packages are in trouble until the overall CPI collapses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat re-baselining as a P1 event; log it, require CCB approval, never automate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Silent re-baselining is the most common way teams game EVM. A team with CPI 0.70 can re-baseline to show CPI 1.00 overnight. Require an explicit decision record for every re-baseline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enforce single base currency; agents must not silently mix USD/EUR/GBP in AC.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Currency mixing produces nonsense CPI values. Multi-currency programs need FX-hedged EAC with explicit conversion date and rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
