<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-evm-process" title="EVM Process and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Four-step EVM implementation process, common measurement mistakes, and agent-specific pitfalls for automated EVM pipelines.</summary>

  <section title="Four-Step Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Establish Baseline: create a time-phased PV curve (planned spend per period); freeze as BAC with sponsor sign-off</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Measure Progress: per reporting period, collect objective % complete for each WBS element; calculate EV = BAC x %complete; record actual AC</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Calculate Metrics: SV, CV, SPI, CPI, EAC, ETC, VAC, TCPI per WBS element and rolled up to project</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Forecast and Act: trend analysis over 3+ periods; variance analyst flags sustained CPI/SPI below threshold; PM decides corrective action; re-baseline only with CCB approval</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track EVM at WBS level 3-4; not at the leaf task level and not at the project summary level only.</statement>
      <rationale>Leaf-level tracking generates noise from individual task estimation error. Summary-level tracking hides which work packages are in trouble until the overall CPI collapses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat re-baselining as a P1 event; log it, require CCB approval, never automate.</statement>
      <rationale>Silent re-baselining is the most common way teams game EVM. A team with CPI 0.70 can re-baseline to show CPI 1.00 overnight. Require an explicit decision record for every re-baseline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Re-baselining to "fix" red metrics without CCB approval.</description>
      <reason>Hides true variance. A project that has re-baselined three times has three sets of lies as its history. Future forecasts become meaningless.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring early CPI warnings because "it will recover".</description>
      <reason>CPI rarely improves on its own — the "CPI cliff" is empirically documented. A CPI of 0.80 at 20% complete predicts final CPI of 0.70-0.85 in most projects.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Reporting SPI/CPI numbers without a 3-period trend line.</description>
      <reason>A single-period metric value tells you nothing about direction. Stakeholders need trajectory, not a snapshot. Always show last 3 periods together.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce single base currency; agents must not silently mix USD/EUR/GBP in AC.</statement>
      <rationale>Currency mixing produces nonsense CPI values. Multi-currency programs need FX-hedged EAC with explicit conversion date and rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>% complete from PR counts or story point burn is a proxy — calibrate against milestone-based EV gates</item>
      <item>AI tooling cost (token spend) is a real AC component; meter it and include in AC if material</item>
      <item>Effort vs cost confusion: hours × role rate; agents must pull rate-per-role, not a flat blended rate</item>
      <item>LLM narratives mask negative variance with euphemism; require numeric thresholds before any positive wording is permitted in status reports</item>
      <item>EAC = BAC/CPI is pessimistic for early-stage projects; allow EAC = AC + (BAC - EV)/(CPI × SPI) for schedule-sensitive items</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
