<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-product-hunt-launch">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>Four-phase Product Hunt launch: build 500+ email list (4-8 weeks), secure niche hunter (1000+ followers), launch 12:01 AM PT Tue-Thu, reply 1 hour.</summary>
    <category>growth</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>product-hunt</tag>
      <tag>product-launch</tag>
      <tag>community-marketing</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>early-adopters</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <applies-to>both</applies-to>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Product Hunt Launch System</title>

    <summary>Four-phase Product Hunt launch system: build 500+ email list (4-8 weeks), secure niche hunter (1000+ followers), launch 12:01 AM PT Tue-Thu, reply within 1 hour. Never ask for upvotes directly.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Upvote velocity in the first few hours determines the final ranking. Accounts with no pre-built audience or weak listing assets consistently fail because Product Hunt is a social product: early supporters with prior product relationships drive the initial spike that earns Explore placement. The tagline must be under 60 characters and benefit-focused ("Build beautiful landing pages in minutes" not "AI-Powered Landing Page Generator"). A dedicated `/welcome-producthunters` landing page with a custom offer and separate tracking separates PH conversion from organic traffic.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Product is polished and launch-ready; need all listing assets (tagline variants, first comment, gallery descriptions, launch email, social posts).</item>
        <item>Evaluating launch readiness against the 4-week checklist before committing to a date.</item>
        <item>Drafting canned responses for the 5 most likely comment types in advance.</item>
        <item>Post-launch: generating a retrospective for IndieHackers from metrics and comment thread.</item>
        <item>Building a hunter outreach message or waitlist page copy.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Product is not yet functional or has major UX issues — public launch damages credibility permanently.</item>
        <item>Email list under 200 warm contacts — build audience first; launch date can wait.</item>
        <item>Planning to launch on a weekend or during a major tech event — timing is non-negotiable.</item>
        <item>Expecting automated upvoting, fake comments, or inauthentic support coordination.</item>
        <item>Assuming PH traffic alone sustains growth after day 1 — plan post-launch nurture.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="phase-1-prepare">
      <p>Preparation timeline and prerequisites: 4-8 weeks before launch.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Build an email list of 500+ interested users before launch. Without warm contacts, launch support is insufficient for early upvote velocity.</statement>
        <rationale>Upvote velocity in the first hours determines the final ranking. Cold launches with no pre-built audience consistently fail to rank because they have no initial signal.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Secure a hunter with 1,000+ followers in the same niche. Hunter audience overlap with your product category matters more than raw follower count.</statement>
        <rationale>A niche-relevant hunter's followers are more likely to upvote and comment because the product matches their interests. A large generic hunter provides less relevant traffic.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not launch if the product has major UX issues or is not functional. A PH launch surfaces all problems publicly and damages credibility permanently.</statement>
        <rationale>PH comments are indexed and permanent. Negative launch comments about bugs or poor UX will follow the product indefinitely and reduce trust for future prospects.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="phase-2-optimize">
      <p>Optimization phase: 1-2 weeks before launch.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Tagline must be under 60 characters, benefit-focused, and contain no jargon. Validate length programmatically after generation — agents frequently exceed the limit.</statement>
        <rationale>The tagline is the primary hook for PH visitors scanning the feed. Over-limit taglines are truncated. Jargon excludes non-technical visitors who are valid early adopters.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Write the first comment before launch day. Have it ready to paste within 60 seconds of the post going live — early velocity is critical.</statement>
        <rationale>First comments on PH posts receive the most visibility. A prepared maker comment with backstory, differentiators, and a special offer sets the tone for all subsequent engagement.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="tagline-formula">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Tagline formula: [Action verb] [outcome] [for whom] [differentiator]. Under 60 characters. Validate length after generation.</statement>
        <rationale>Action verbs signal what the product does immediately. Outcome communicates value. "For whom" targets the right audience. Under 60 characters prevents truncation in the feed.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Strong tagline with all elements">
        <description>Tagline: "Build beautiful landing pages in minutes" — action verb (Build), outcome (beautiful landing pages), timeframe as differentiator (in minutes). 43 characters.</description>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Weak tagline without user action">
        <description>Tagline: "AI-Powered Landing Page Generator for Modern Businesses" — no action verb for the user, "AI-Powered" is jargon, too long (55 chars but generic). Does not communicate user outcome.</description>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="gallery-structure">
      <p>Product Hunt gallery best practices:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Image 1: Hero shot with tagline overlay</item>
        <item>Images 2-4: Key features with one-sentence explanations</item>
        <item>Image 5: Testimonials or social proof numbers</item>
        <item>Image 6: CTA or pricing summary</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not mention unfinished features in the listing or comments. PH commenters will test everything mentioned; negative comments about missing features compound quickly.</statement>
        <rationale>PH comments are permanent and indexed. Overpromising on launch day creates immediate negative social proof that follows the product indefinitely.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="launch-day-schedule">
      <list>
        <item>12:01 AM PT: Post goes live, first comment posted immediately</item>
        <item>6:00 AM PT: Send launch email to supporter list</item>
        <item>9:00 AM PT: Post on social media channels</item>
        <item>12:00 PM PT: Engage with all comments</item>
        <item>3:00 PM PT: Second social push</item>
        <item>6:00 PM PT: Thank you post, community outreach</item>
        <item>9:00 PM PT: Final engagement push before ranking closes</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Respond to EVERY comment within 1 hour. Never ask for upvotes directly — this is against PH TOS and looks desperate.</statement>
        <rationale>Active maker engagement is a strong positive signal on PH. Accounts with high comment response rates rank better and are perceived as more trustworthy.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="post-launch-leverage">
      <list>
        <item>Within 24 hours: thank supporters, share ranking and stats, collect testimonials from commenters</item>
        <item>Within 1 week: post retrospective on IndieHackers, nurture new email subscribers, follow up with interested users</item>
        <item>Long-term: add "Featured on Product Hunt" badge, include in press kit, use ranking as social proof</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Launching without a pre-built email list or community.</description>
        <reason>Without warm contacts to drive early upvote velocity, the listing never reaches the first page. Building the list before launch is more important than the launch date itself.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Launching on a weekend or during a major tech event.</description>
        <reason>Weekends have fewer active PH users; major events dominate attention. Tuesdays through Thursdays have the highest active user counts and lowest competition.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>First comment drafted as corporate marketing copy.</description>
        <reason>PH community values authenticity. A polished, corporate first comment reduces maker credibility. Write in first-person casual voice and review for authenticity before posting.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Asking for upvotes directly or including "upvote us" or "share with your network" in launch copy.</description>
        <reason>Asking for upvotes directly is a PH TOS violation and, if flagged, can result in removal of the listing. Let the product quality drive upvotes organically.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration-and-limitations">
      <p>An agent is best used in two phases: (1) pre-launch asset generation — given product description, target audience, and key differentiators, produce the tagline, gallery descriptions, first comment, launch email, and social posts; (2) post-launch analysis — given the comment thread export and traffic/signup metrics, produce a retrospective with lessons learned and follow-up actions. On launch day itself, the agent can draft real-time comment responses if given the incoming comment text, but a human must post them. Allow at least 2 hours of human availability on launch day for comment moderation.</p>

      <p>Agents cannot post to Product Hunt or monitor the listing in real-time; human presence is mandatory on launch day. Image and video assets require human design or dedicated design tools — agents can specify requirements but cannot generate compliant visuals. Upvote velocity is a social phenomenon; agent-generated copy improves conversion but cannot guarantee ranking. HN and Reddit cross-posts are separate tactics; PH launch alone does not guarantee sustained traffic after day 1. Product Hunt's algorithm changes; guidance may lag current ranking factors.</p>

      <p>Agents may generate taglines that exceed the 60-character limit; always validate length programmatically after generation. First comment drafts often sound too polished/corporate — instruct agent to write in first-person casual voice and review for authenticity before posting. Agents cannot monitor real-time upvote velocity or detect if the post is being flagged — human must watch the dashboard. Human-in-loop checkpoint: agent drafts responses to comments; human reviews and posts — never allow fully automated comment posting on a public platform. Launch day email timing is critical; agent-generated send schedules should be validated against the subscriber timezone distribution before execution. Agents may include calls to action that violate PH TOS ("upvote us", "share with your network") — explicitly forbid this in the system prompt.</p>

      <p>Best practices: Request the hunt from a hunter with 1,000+ followers in the same niche; hunter audience overlap with your product category matters more than raw follower count. Prepare canned responses for the 5 most likely comment types (how does X work, what's the pricing, is there a free trial, how does it compare to Y, can I use it for Z) — agent can draft these in advance. Do not use launch day to announce unfinished features; HN/PH commenters will test everything mentioned and negative comments compound fast. Add a dedicated landing page URL for PH traffic (e.g., `/welcome-producthunters`) with a custom offer and tracking — measure conversion separately from organic traffic. Post the retrospective on IndieHackers within 48 hours while the launch is fresh — it doubles as marketing and community building.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/first-comment.md" purpose="PH first comment: maker intro, differentiators, special offer, roadmap teaser."/>
      <template path="templates/launch-email.md" purpose="Launch day email to supporters: link, upvote CTA, no-pressure framing."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-asset-generation.txt" purpose="Agent prompt: 5 tagline variants + first comment + launch email."/>
      <template path="templates/check-launch-timing.py" purpose="Validate proposed launch datetime: must be 12:01 AM PT, Tue-Thu."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.producthunt.com/launch"/>
      <link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/library/6f-a-guide-to-product-hunt"/>
      <link href="https://api.producthunt.com/v2/docs"/>
      <link href="https://www.producthunt.com/ship"/>
      <link href="https://makermag.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
