<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Spec Writing Framework">
  <summary>Seven-step process for writing a product specification that separates what from how, includes testable acceptance criteria, and feeds directly into SDD execution.</summary>

  <section title="Core Separation Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>A spec answers WHAT to build and WHY. Design documents answer HOW. Never mix them: requirements describe observable behavior, not implementation choices.</statement>
      <rationale>Specs that include implementation details become obsolete with every architecture decision and force re-review. "The system shall use Postgres" is a design decision; "The system shall return results within 200ms at p95" is a requirement.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="7-Step Writing Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — Answer four context questions before writing: why are we building this, who requested it, what happens if we don't, and how does this fit product strategy?</statement>
      <rationale>Context anchors the spec to a business reason and prevents scope drift during stakeholder review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Write the problem statement: who has it, what specifically it is, how they solve it today, and what the impact is.</statement>
      <rationale>A vague problem statement produces vague requirements. Specificity in the problem propagates to testability in the acceptance criteria.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Write 3–5 goals with measurable current and target values. Write Non-Goals with ≥ 3 explicit exclusions. Non-Goals is mandatory and non-empty.</statement>
      <rationale>Goals without numbers cannot be used to declare success. Non-Goals without items invite scope creep on every review cycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Write user stories in "As a [user], I want to [action], so that [benefit]" format. Include the "so that" — it is the motivation, not optional.</statement>
      <rationale>User stories without "so that" become feature requests with no user context, making prioritization arbitrary.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5 — Assign every functional requirement a unique ID (FR-N) and a M/S/C priority. Every NFR must include a numeric criterion (latency, error rate, uptime).</statement>
      <rationale>FRs without IDs cannot be tracked. NFRs without numbers ("the system shall be fast") are unverifiable and will be interpreted differently by every reader.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 6 — Write Given-When-Then acceptance criteria for every functional requirement. These become test cases — they must be executable, not descriptive.</statement>
      <rationale>The faion-feature-executor skill consumes acceptance criteria as its test specification. Vague criteria ("works correctly") produce vague tests that pass trivially.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 7 — List Open Questions as honest unknowns. Never write "none" unless you have explicitly verified all knowns. Minimum: 1 question or a note "verified all knowns."</statement>
      <rationale>Agents hallucinate answers to unasked questions. Forcing Open Questions to the surface creates a checkpoint for human review before the spec reaches "Approved."</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Length and Versioning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap most specs at 1–3 pages. If longer, split into sub-features. Version the spec: update status field (Draft / Review / Approved / Superseded) on every significant change.</statement>
      <rationale>Specs longer than 3 pages are skimmed, not read. Status versioning ensures stakeholders know which version they reviewed and approved.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/spec-full.md">Full PRD template with all sections</reference>
  <reference path="templates/spec-mini.md">Mini-spec for quick features</reference>
  <reference path="templates/spec-lint.py">Spec linter: validates FR IDs, priorities, AC coverage</reference>
</text>
