<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-antipatterns" title="Spec Writing Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Six spec failures that produce untestable requirements, scope creep, or rework.</summary>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Functional requirements include implementation details ("the system shall use Redis for caching").</description>
    <reason>Implementation details belong in design docs. When the implementation changes, the spec becomes wrong and requires a re-approval cycle that was never needed.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Non-Functional Requirements use qualitative language: "the system shall be fast," "the system shall be secure."</description>
    <reason>Qualitative NFRs cannot be tested. Every engineer interprets "fast" differently. NFRs must include a numeric criterion (e.g., "p95 latency &lt; 200ms", "error rate &lt; 0.1%").</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Non-Goals is empty or missing.</description>
    <reason>An empty Non-Goals invites every stakeholder to add scope in review. Listing what you are NOT building is the fastest way to align a room. Minimum 3 explicit items.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Acceptance criteria use vague language: "the feature works correctly," "the user can complete the flow."</description>
    <reason>Vague criteria pass trivially — any implementation satisfies "works correctly." Each criterion must be a Given-When-Then scenario that a QA engineer can execute without asking a question.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Open Questions section is empty or contains "none."</description>
    <reason>There are always unknowns; "none" means they were not surfaced. Hidden unknowns surface during implementation as blockers. Force a minimum of 1 question or an explicit note confirming all knowns were verified.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Spec exceeds 3 pages for a single feature.</description>
    <reason>Long specs are skimmed, not read. Decision-makers approve without understanding. If a spec is over 3 pages, split into sub-features with separate specs that can be reviewed independently.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
