<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-platform-and-building" title="Platform Selection and Community Building Phases">
  <summary>Platform comparison for 2026, four community-building phases, value delivery cadence, and micro-community engagement advantage.</summary>

  <section title="Platform Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to Discord for real-time community in 2026 (259M MAU, 73% DAU/MAU ratio, AI moderation enabling 10K+ members with 1 mod). Use Slack for B2B/professional contexts where per-seat cost is acceptable. Use self-hosted Discourse for communities where SEO and searchability matter more than real-time engagement.</statement>
      <rationale>Platform choice determines moderation cost, engagement ceiling, and automation surface. Discord's bot ecosystem and free tier fit most 2026 CLG use cases; Slack per-seat cost limits scale for consumer communities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Discord: 259M MAU, 94 min/day avg session, free, AI moderation at scale. Non-gaming has overtaken gaming in growth rate.</item>
      <item>Slack: $12.50/user/month, structured channels, strong B2B fit, Events API enables agent automation.</item>
      <item>Circle.so: owned data, lower platform risk, good for course-creator CLG, weaker real-time engagement.</item>
      <item>Discourse: OSS, self-hosted, fully searchable, best for async technical communities; REST API is agent-friendly.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Community Building Phases">
    <rule>
      <statement>Seed before launch: hand-invite 30+ "founding members" via personal DM with a custom role and welcome thread. Do this manually, not via bot. Open publicly only after seeding produces the first organic peer-help thread.</statement>
      <rationale>Communities launched empty or with automated mass invites fail to reach the critical-mass dynamic where members answer each other's questions. Manual seeding produces the first "product sold to another member" moment that creates CLG ROI.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Phase 1 — Seed (10-50 members): quality over quantity, foster genuine connections, personal invitations only.</item>
      <item>Phase 2 — Build (50-500 members): exclusive content, AMA sessions, peer networking opportunities, member spotlights.</item>
      <item>Phase 3 — Scale (500-2K members): user-generated content channels, challenges, co-creation, active moderation.</item>
      <item>Phase 4 — Cap (2K+): add qualification step or private sub-community for power users (ORBIT Level 3+) to retain engagement premium.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Value Delivery Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deliver one concrete value drop per week — AMA, template release, or behind-the-scenes content. Agents can draft it, but a human ships it. Track whether each drop triggers a peer-help thread within 48 hours as the quality signal.</statement>
      <rationale>Inconsistent value delivery kills community engagement. The weekly cadence trains member expectation and keeps DAU/MAU above 30% even in slow product cycles.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap public community size or add a low-friction application step after ~1K members. The "2.3x higher engagement" micro-community advantage disappears above that threshold.</statement>
      <rationale>Large communities develop audience behavior (lurking, broadcast consumption) rather than peer behavior (helping, sharing). Micro-community premium requires maintaining intimate-enough dynamics.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
