<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-metrics-and-rules" title="Health Metrics, Agent Automation Rules, and Moderation Guardrails">
  <summary>The three core CLG health metrics, agent automation boundaries, moderation rules, and tokenized-rewards caution.</summary>

  <section title="Health Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track these three metrics as the primary CLG health signals: (1) DAU/MAU ratio (target 30%+ for healthy community, 73% for Discord-native communities); (2) peer-help response rate (% of questions answered by a member, not staff, within 24h); (3) member-sourced revenue (deals or upgrades where community interaction preceded the conversion). Member count is a vanity metric.</statement>
      <rationale>The McKinsey value framework anchors CLG ROI on active engagement and revenue attribution, not audience size. A 1K-member community with 40% DAU/MAU generates more acquisition value than a 10K-member community at 5% DAU/MAU.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Automation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>All outbound posts, DMs, and event announcements from agents must go through a human-approval gate before publishing. Only metric reports and internal alert messages may post autonomously.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-posted community content reads as corporate and erodes trust; Discord/Slack ToS treats mass DMs as spam and platform bans cascade across the entire workspace.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For moderation automation: auto-delete only on classifier confidence &gt; 0.95 AND explicit keyword match. For mute/ban: always require human mod approval. Never auto-DM new members at scale.</statement>
      <rationale>Moderation-loop hallucinations — agent flags a member as spam, auto-mutes, member churns — are common and reputation-damaging. False negatives are recoverable; false positives that silence legitimate members are not.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Tokenized Rewards Caution">
    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>Do not implement tokenized rewards without explicit legal review. Treat all token-reward recommendations as opt-in only after sign-off from legal counsel familiar with jurisdiction-specific regulations.</statement>
      <rationale>41% of communities plan token adoption by 2026, but regulatory comfort varies dramatically by jurisdiction. Agents cannot evaluate legal exposure; any automatic recommendation to mint, distribute, or advise on tokens creates liability.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Tracking member count as the primary KPI and growing the community above 2K without an engagement floor.</description>
      <reason>Audience-size growth without engagement depth creates a broadcast community that delivers none of the "24% higher purchase value" CLG benefits.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Moving high-engagement Discord/Slack threads to a searchable forum retroactively instead of at the moment they cross 10 replies.</description>
      <reason>Searchable threads are lost in real-time chat channels; archiving them to Discourse at 10+ replies protects future SEO value and new-member onboarding context.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/clg-health.py">Python function: DAU/WAU/MAU, DAU/MAU ratio, top-10 contributors</reference>
</text>
