<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="IaC Pull-Request Review Checklist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>≥5 testable rules grounding the iac-pr-review-checklist methodology, each paired with rationale and source reference.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="blast-radius-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>PR description names the blast radius (modules + environments affected) and the rollback path before review starts.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Without a named blast radius, the reviewer cannot reason about acceptable change risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="plan-or-diff-attached" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>PR carries the terraform plan / helm diff / kustomize build output as a comment or artefact, dated within the review window.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Reviewing source without plan is reviewing intent without effect — the divergence is where incidents live.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-state-mutation-in-pr" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>PRs that touch state movement (terraform state mv / rm) or destructive replacements MUST flag the mutation in the title and require two approvers.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">State mutations are not retriable; the title-flag is the documented attention-grabbing convention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="secrets-never-in-diff" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The diff MUST not contain plaintext secrets, key material, or cloud account IDs outside the documented allow-list.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Once secrets land in a public PR they are burned even if reverted — never-in-diff is the only safe rule.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="iam-minimum-and-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any IAM change is explicit (no resource = "*"), uses managed policies where possible, and the PR enumerates new permissions in plain language.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">IAM is the recurring breach root cause; explicit + plain-language change forces the reviewer to actually read it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, do NOT run this methodology — return early with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree's negative branch must terminate cleanly without partial output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold AND scope is explicit, run the methodology end-to-end and produce the canonical artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree positive-branch terminus; aliases the apply-end-to-end verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
