<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Resource Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the resource-management methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="cap-effective-capacity-80" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plan to 75-80% effective capacity, never 100% — meetings, interruptions, admin overhead consume at least 20% of nominal hours.</statement>
      <rationale source="DeMarco &amp; Lister Peopleware (slack chapter); Float 70% rule">Plans at 100% utilization collapse on the first sick week or sprint ceremony load.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="bus-factor-min-2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cross-train at least one backup per critical skill; bus factor below 2 is a P1 risk in the risk register.</statement>
      <rationale source="Risk-management practice">Single-person dependency on a critical skill is a project risk comparable to a high-probability technical risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skill-matrix-last-used" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track skills with three levels (learning, proficient, mentor) AND a last-used date.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — skill-matrix decay audits">People grow and skills change; matrices without dates produce mismatched assignments within 6-12 months.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="reconcile-with-schedule-cost" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Resource plan must reconcile with schedule (CPM) and budget (EVM); update all three together when resource changes occur.</statement>
      <rationale source="Integration-management practice">A resource change that does not propagate creates invisible drift — the plan says on-time but the critical path has slipped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="stretch-bench" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep a stretch bench — people with 10-20% slack who can absorb spikes without going over 80% effective capacity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field experience">Without a stretch bench, every unplanned event requires a formal escalation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="calendar-subjects-redacted" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Redact calendar subject lines before any LLM input; keep only duration and recurrence pattern.</statement>
      <rationale source="Privacy practice">Calendar subjects are often sensitive (layoff prep, performance reviews) and may not flow to a model.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Stable single team under 8 people — informal allocation works</item>
      <item>Pure agile teams committed to whole-team ownership — utilization tracking erodes safety</item>
      <item>One-week sprint of throwaway research</item>
      <item>Organisations where utilization % is a performance metric — creates burnout and gaming</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
