<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="resource-management Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for resource-management. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plan to 75-80% effective capacity, never 100% — meetings, interruptions, and administrative overhead consume at least 20% of nominal hours.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Plans at 100% utilization collapse on the first sick week or sprint ceremony load, creating cascading delays. The 20% buffer is not slack — it is the cost of doing knowledge work in a real organisation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cross-train at least one backup per critical skill; bus factor below 2 is a P1 risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A single-person dependency on a critical skill (database, security, deployment) is a project risk comparable to a high-probability technical risk — it should appear in the risk register.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A capacity-planner subagent ingests calendars (PTO, holidays), current Jira/Linear assignments, and skill tags from HR; produces a weekly availability matrix capped at 75% effective capacity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Manual capacity planning is always stale; automated ingestion from authoritative sources (calendar + HR + tracker) produces a plan that updates as reality changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track skills with three levels (learning, proficient, mentor) and a last-used date — skill matrices encoded once go stale fast.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">People grow and their skills change; a matrix without last-used dates produces assignments that mismatch actual capability within 6-12 months of authoring.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Resource plan must reconcile with schedule (CPM) and budget (EVM); update all three together when resource changes occur.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A resource change that does not propagate to schedule and cost creates invisible drift — the plan says on-time but the critical path has already slipped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep a stretch bench — people with 10-20% slack who can absorb spikes without going over 80% effective capacity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a stretch bench, every unplanned event (sick day, unexpected bug, scope addition) requires a formal escalation; a small buffer keeps velocity stable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
