<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Resource Management — Framework and Six-Step Process">
  <summary>Resource categories, the six-step management process, leveling techniques, and effective capacity guidelines.</summary>

  <section title="Resource Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Human: team members, contractors. Key considerations: skills, availability, cost, bus factor.</item>
      <item>Physical: equipment, facilities. Key considerations: location, capacity, scheduling lead time.</item>
      <item>Material: supplies, software licenses. Key considerations: lead time, inventory, renewal cycles.</item>
      <item>Financial: budget, cash flow. Key considerations: timing, approval process, EVM reconciliation.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Human resource planning dominates software and knowledge-work projects. The remaining sections focus on human resources unless otherwise stated.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Six-Step Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Identify requirements — for each work package: what skills, how many people, how long, any special constraints.</item>
      <item>Step 2: Assess availability — current commitments, effective capacity (hours/week at 75-80%), skills and experience, cost rates.</item>
      <item>Step 3: Create resource plan — map resources to activities; produce a resource calendar grid by week and phase.</item>
      <item>Step 4: Level resources — resolve overloads: delay tasks (non-critical), split tasks, add resources, reduce scope, or extend timeline.</item>
      <item>Step 5: Develop the team — training, mentoring, team building, clear expectations, recognition.</item>
      <item>Step 6: Manage the team — track utilization vs. plan weekly; address performance, conflicts, and reassignments.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Effective Capacity Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Plan to 75-80% effective capacity, never 100% — meetings, interruptions, and administrative overhead consume at least 20% of nominal hours.</statement>
      <rationale>Plans at 100% utilization collapse on the first sick week or sprint ceremony load, creating cascading delays. The 20% buffer is not slack — it is the cost of doing knowledge work in a real organisation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Utilization guidelines by zone: under 50% = underutilized; 50-75% = healthy with buffer; 75-85% = optimal for most roles; 85-100% = full capacity, burnout risk rising; above 100% = unsustainable, address immediately.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Leveling Techniques">
    <list>
      <item>Delay tasks: move non-critical-path tasks to later; no scope or cost impact.</item>
      <item>Split tasks: interrupt a task and resume later; useful when work can be paused safely.</item>
      <item>Add resources: requires budget and available skill; ramp-up cost is 2 weeks at 50% productivity for contractors.</item>
      <item>Reduce scope: cut features; requires sponsor approval and change control.</item>
      <item>Extend timeline: delay delivery date; requires sponsor approval and baseline update.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>100% allocation plans that ignore meetings, email, ceremonies, and breaks.</description>
      <reason>These plans always slip on the first sick week or holiday; they create chronic delivery failures that look like execution problems but are actually planning failures.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Skill and Bus Factor">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cross-train at least one backup per critical skill; bus factor below 2 is a P1 risk.</statement>
      <rationale>A single-person dependency on a critical skill (database, security, deployment) is a project risk comparable to a high-probability technical risk — it should appear in the risk register.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/resource-plan.md">Resource plan template with skill matrix and risk section</reference>
    <reference path="templates/capacity.py">Script to compute effective hours per person per week</reference>
  </section>
</text>
