<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="resource-management Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for resource-management as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>100% allocation plans that ignore meetings, email, ceremonies, and breaks.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>These plans always slip on the first sick week or holiday; they create chronic delivery failures that look like execution problems but are actually planning failures.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Calendar API pulls miss informal meetings, pair sessions, and debugging deep dives.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Structured calendar data only captures formally scheduled events; ask the person to confirm their actual available hours before using the raw calendar count for planning.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Allocation agent packs the calendar to 100% if uncapped.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents optimize for filling capacity; hard-cap at 80% effective in the prompt and the output schema to prevent burnout plans.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent auto-rebalances assignments mid-sprint.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mid-sprint reassignments break WIP and disrupt flow. Schedule rebalancing only at sprint boundaries.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents read calendar subjects to assess meeting load.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Calendar subjects are often sensitive (layoff prep, performance review); redact subject lines before any LLM input, keep only duration and recurrence pattern.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
