<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-tools-and-references" title="Resource Management — Tools, Services, and References">
  <summary>CLI tools, SaaS services, best practices, and references for resource planning and capacity management.</summary>

  <section title="CLI Tools">
    <list>
      <item>gcalcli — read Google Calendar events for capacity (https://github.com/insanum/gcalcli)</item>
      <item>khal — CalDAV calendar queries (https://github.com/pimutils/khal)</item>
      <item>jira CLI — pull current assignments + estimates (https://github.com/ankitpokhrel/jira-cli)</item>
      <item>linear-cli — Linear capacity/load by user (npm)</item>
      <item>tempo (Jira plugin API) — worklog + capacity (https://apidocs.tempo.io)</item>
      <item>harvest API — time tracking + capacity (https://help.getharvest.com/api-v2)</item>
      <item>clockify API — free time tracking (https://docs.clockify.me/api)</item>
      <item>bamboohr API — HR data, PTO, headcount (https://documentation.bamboohr.com)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Services">
    <list>
      <item>Float — resource scheduling, REST API; best for agency/consulting contexts (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Resource Guru — bookings + leave, REST API; WFH and holiday aware (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Forecast.it — AI scheduling, GraphQL; integrates with Harvest (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Runn — capacity planning, rich API; supports project + people views (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Microsoft Project for Web — Graph API, Azure AD; enterprise default on Microsoft estate (SaaS).</item>
      <item>OpenProject — self-host, REST API, Gantt + WBS native; for regulated environments (OSS).</item>
      <item>Tempo Planner — Jira-tied, plugin permissioning; useful when already on Jira ecosystem (SaaS).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track skills with three levels (learning, proficient, mentor) and a last-used date — skill matrices encoded once go stale fast.</statement>
      <rationale>People grow and their skills change; a matrix without last-used dates produces assignments that mismatch actual capability within 6-12 months of authoring.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Resource plan must reconcile with schedule (CPM) and budget (EVM); update all three together when resource changes occur.</statement>
      <rationale>A resource change that does not propagate to schedule and cost creates invisible drift — the plan says on-time but the critical path has already slipped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep a stretch bench — people with 10-20% slack who can absorb spikes without going over 80% effective capacity.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a stretch bench, every unplanned event (sick day, unexpected bug, scope addition) requires a formal escalation; a small buffer keeps velocity stable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="References">
    <list>
      <item>PMBoK 7th — Team Performance Domain</item>
      <item>DeMarco &amp; Lister, "Peopleware" — slack chapter on the cost of full utilization</item>
      <item>Allen Ward, "Lean Product and Process Development" — capacity utilization paradox</item>
      <item>Float blog, "The 70% rule for resource planning"</item>
      <item>Sibling methodologies: schedule-development/, cost-estimation/, earned-value-management/, raci-matrix/, procurement-management/</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
