<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Review PR Checklist — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for running design-QA at PR time so design adherence is verified before merge, not discovered post-release.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-ten-item-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every UI-touching PR MUST be checked against all 10 items: (1) Tokens used (no raw values), (2) Components reused (no duplicates of system components), (3) States implemented (per handoff: default / hover / focus / active / disabled / loading / error / empty), (4) Motion compliant (duration / easing from system, prefers-reduced-motion honored), (5) Accessibility intact (focus order, ARIA, contrast), (6) Content rules honored (max-length, truncation, i18n), (7) Breakpoints covered (mobile / tablet / desktop), (8) Image handling (responsive, alt text), (9) Dark-mode parity (if theme is supported), (10) Cross-browser smoke check (Chrome, Safari, Firefox at minimum).</statement>
      <rationale source="Material Design QA Checklist, Polaris adoption metrics">10-item checklist comes from empirical post-release defect analysis. Each item maps to a specific failure mode that ships when not checked. The set is intentionally small enough to fit in a 15-min PR review.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-designer-reviewer-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A named designer or design-engineer MUST be a required PR reviewer for UI-touching PRs. Generic dev peer review does not satisfy design adherence — devs systematically under-detect design drift. Required-reviewer enforcement is via PR-platform rules, not goodwill.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian Design QA practice, Polaris case studies">PRs without designer review show 2-3x higher post-release design-bug rate. Required-reviewer rules are the cheapest enforcement; voluntary "ping me if needed" loops fail because the dev doesn't know what they didn't check.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-evidence-per-item" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each item check MUST include evidence: link to specific lines in the PR diff, screenshot or recording from local-build, or output of a script (e.g., scripts/scan-pr-for-raw-values.py). Pass-without-evidence is forbidden; the reviewer must have actually checked, not skim-approved.</statement>
      <rationale source="Code-review research, Microsoft empirical review studies">Skim-review at PR time produces same defect-find rate as no-review on architectural / design items. Evidence-per-item forces the actual look.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-no-style-cleanup-creep" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The design-QA checklist STAYS in its lane: design-system adherence, accessibility, content rules. It does NOT cover generic code style (formatting, naming), test coverage, business-logic correctness — those belong to peer review and to QA. Mixing scopes both bloats the review and dilutes focus on actual design issues.</statement>
      <rationale source="Code-review effectiveness research, Google Eng Practices">Reviews that try to cover everything cover nothing well. Splitting the review into clear lanes (peer style, architect, design, QA) lets each lane achieve high quality in 10-15 min.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-handoff-deltas-flagged-back" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When the implementation deliberately deviates from the handoff (e.g., dev chose a different component because the specified one had an unforeseen limitation), the design-QA record MUST flag the delta back to the designer. The designer either (a) accepts the delta with rationale (adds to design system as known pattern), or (b) rejects and requests rework. Silent acceptance is forbidden — feedback must return to the design surface.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-system maintenance research, Spotify "design system as a product" practice">Silent deviations decay the design system: variants accumulate in code that the design system doesn't know about. Forcing the feedback loop catches the deviation early — either the system gets a documented new variant or the code gets reverted.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical example">

    <example type="good" title="Design-QA pass with one delta flagged back">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
PR #1421: "Implement subscription comparison page"
Reviewer: jane.s (designer)
Duration: 13 min

1. Tokens used:            PASS  (scripts/scan-pr-for-raw-values.py
                                  clean; manual check confirms)
2. Components reused:      PASS  (uses ds/PricingCard;
                                  no new variants)
3. States implemented:     NEEDS CHANGES — Loading state for
                           "Buy now" button not implemented
                           (handoff specified spinner; ticket #1421
                           commit f3a missing)
4. Motion compliant:       PASS  (200ms ease-out; prefers-reduced-motion
                                  honored — verified in record.mp4)
5. Accessibility intact:   PASS  (axe-core report attached)
6. Content rules honored:  PASS  (longest DE locale tested)
7. Breakpoints covered:    PASS  (320 / 768 / 1280 screenshots in PR)
8. Image handling:         PASS  (img srcset, alt text from spec)
9. Dark mode parity:       PASS  (token-based, automatic)
10. Cross-browser:         PASS  (Chrome 124, Safari 17.4,
                                  Firefox 124 — manual smoke)

Delta flagged back to designer:
  Handoff specified ds/Button-Pricing, but dev used ds/Button-Pricing-XL
  (didn't exist when handoff was written; was added last week).
  Delta acceptable; updating handoff package to reference Button-Pricing-XL.

Decision: changes-needed (item 3 only). Re-review after loading state
fix.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1-r5: full 10-item coverage, evidence per item, designer-as-reviewer, delta flagged back not silently accepted.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Rubber-stamp design review">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
PR #1422: 1,400 lines of UI changes
Reviewer: alex.k (engineer, not designer; assigned because designer "on leave")
Duration: 90 sec
Comment: "lgtm visually"

Post-merge findings 2 weeks later:
- 12 raw #hex values in committed CSS
- 3 duplicated copies of the design-system PricingCard component
  (slight visual differences across them)
- Loading state missing on 4 buttons
- Mobile breakpoint broken
- Dark mode not tested at all

Repair: enforce r1-r3. Designer-as-required-reviewer cannot be
substituted by an engineer "for speed". If designer is genuinely
unavailable, the PR waits OR a design-engineer (cross-trained)
runs the check.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2, r3 violations — substituting designer review with engineer skim creates the exact post-release defects the methodology prevents.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
