<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="design-doc-structure Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for design-doc-structure. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A design document must exist and be approved before the implementation plan is written.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The file change table in design.md is the input to task decomposition in the implementation plan. Without an approved design, the implementation plan has no authoritative file list, and tasks will be created for files that may not be needed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write AD-X entries before filling the file structure table — decisions should drive file layout, not the reverse.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">When the file table is written first, decisions are reverse-engineered from assumed files. Writing ADs first ensures every file in the table exists because of a decision, not because of a pattern the agent knows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every row in the file change table must have both an FR trace and an AD trace; rows with missing traces indicate gold-plating.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">File structure tables include files the agent assumes will be needed from training patterns (index.ts barrel exports, __init__.py files) that are not required by any FR. These produce unnecessary tasks in the implementation plan.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mark security mitigations with the specific threat they address (SQL injection, CSRF, privilege escalation); generic "use HTTPS" entries provide no actionable guidance.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Security sections written as vague checklists are skipped during code review. Specific threat + specific mitigation creates a testable requirement that reviewers can verify in code.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
