<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-checklist" title="Design Document Authoring Checklist">
  <summary>Phase-by-phase checklist for writing a design document from approved spec through quality gate.</summary>

  <section title="Phase 1: Preparation">
    <list>
      <item>Read spec.md completely and extract all FR-X and NFR-X IDs</item>
      <item>Review constitution.md for tech stack and patterns</item>
      <item>Identify reference documents to link (spec, constitution, related designs)</item>
      <item>Confirm spec status is Approved (not Draft)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 2: Architecture Decisions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write AD-X entries before filling the file structure table — decisions should drive file layout, not the reverse.</statement>
      <rationale>When the file table is written first, decisions are reverse-engineered from assumed files. Writing ADs first ensures every file in the table exists because of a decision, not because of a pattern the agent knows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Create at least one AD-X per 2-3 FR-X requirements</item>
      <item>For each AD-X: write Context (why decision is needed)</item>
      <item>For each AD-X: list at least 2 rejected alternatives with concrete rejection reasons</item>
      <item>For each AD-X: state Decision clearly</item>
      <item>For each AD-X: document Consequences (positive and negative)</item>
      <item>Trace each AD to FR-X / NFR-X</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 3: File Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every row in the file change table must have both an FR trace and an AD trace; rows with missing traces indicate gold-plating.</statement>
      <rationale>File structure tables include files the agent assumes will be needed from training patterns (index.ts barrel exports, __init__.py files) that are not required by any FR. These produce unnecessary tasks in the implementation plan.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>List all CREATE files with description, FR trace, AD trace</item>
      <item>List all MODIFY files with scope of change, FR trace, AD trace</item>
      <item>Include test file structure alongside source files</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 4: Data and API">
    <list>
      <item>Define TypeScript interfaces / Pydantic models</item>
      <item>Write SQL DDL separately from TypeScript — they often diverge</item>
      <item>Document all table relationships and indexes</item>
      <item>Document API endpoints with OpenAPI-style request/response JSON</item>
      <item>Define all error response schemas (not just happy path)</item>
      <item>Reference contracts.md for existing API patterns (do not redefine)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 5: Security and Performance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark security mitigations with the specific threat they address (SQL injection, CSRF, privilege escalation); generic "use HTTPS" entries provide no actionable guidance.</statement>
      <rationale>Security sections written as vague checklists are skipped during code review. Specific threat + specific mitigation creates a testable requirement that reviewers can verify in code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Security: auth approach, input validation rules, encryption decisions</item>
      <item>Performance: caching strategy with targets, query optimization, scaling approach</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Gate">
    <list>
      <item>Every FR-X from spec has at least one AD-X in design</item>
      <item>Every NFR-X addressed in security/performance sections</item>
      <item>Every file in file-structure table has FR and AD traces</item>
      <item>All API endpoints have error response schemas</item>
      <item>Data models complete (TypeScript + SQL DDL)</item>
      <item>Dependencies listed with versions</item>
      <item>Spec Coverage matrix 100% complete</item>
      <item>Status: design.md set to Review (human sets to Approved)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
