<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-gotchas" title="Design Document Antipatterns and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Concrete failure modes when writing design documents, with emphasis on AI-agent-specific errors.</summary>

  <section title="Traceability Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>FR-X IDs in spec are non-consecutive (FR-001, FR-003, no FR-002); agent copies them without verifying completeness.</description>
      <reason>Gaps in FR numbering propagate silently into the design traceability matrix. The coverage matrix shows FR-001 and FR-003 covered but misses FR-002 as absent. Run: grep -oP 'FR-\d+' spec.md | sort -u before starting design.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>API contracts in design.md are aspirational and not validated against AC scenarios.</description>
      <reason>An AC that requires a 422 response code may have no corresponding error schema in the design. Contract tests (Dredd) will fail. Cross-reference each AC error scenario against the API contract error responses.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="AD-X Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Alternatives Considered section lists three options that sound reasonable but were never actually evaluated.</description>
      <reason>This is the highest-hallucination-risk section of design.md. Agents produce fluent-sounding alternative evaluations from training data. Only list alternatives that were genuinely considered for this specific project. Prompt: "only list alternatives you can justify with project-specific reasons."</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Consequences section is omitted from AD-X entries.</description>
      <reason>Agents frequently skip Consequences because it requires acknowledging trade-offs. Without it, future agents or developers have no basis for understanding why a different approach wasn't chosen. Enforce via reviewer checklist.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="File Table Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>File structure table includes barrel export files, __init__.py, index.ts stubs not required by any FR.</description>
      <reason>These produce unnecessary tasks in the implementation plan that consume token budget without delivering FR value. Every file in the table must trace to an FR. Files needed only for structural reasons belong in a separate "scaffolding" note.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>File structure table becomes wrong as implementation evolves; design.md is not updated.</description>
      <reason>Agents executing tasks discover additional files needed. If design.md is not updated, it becomes misleading for subsequent tasks. Either update design.md as implementation reveals new files, or freeze it and document deviations in task summaries.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Process Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent marks design.md status as Approved after completing it.</description>
      <reason>Design status change from Review to Approved must be a human action. Agents set Draft → Review; humans set Review → Approved. Never let an agent mark its own design as Approved.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Design phase starts before spec.md is approved.</description>
      <reason>Design decisions are based on shifting requirements. When spec changes after design is started, the FR → AD coverage matrix must be rebuilt from scratch. Gate strictly on spec.md status: Approved before starting design.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
