<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-concepts" title="GitOps Principles, Models, Repository Patterns, and Tool Comparison">
  <summary>Four OpenGitOps principles, push vs pull model trade-offs, repository structure patterns, environment strategy, tool comparison, and progressive delivery mechanics.</summary>

  <section title="Core Principles (OpenGitOps)">
    <list>
      <item>Declarative: infrastructure and applications defined as code in YAML/JSON</item>
      <item>Versioned and immutable: all configuration stored in Git with full history</item>
      <item>Pulled automatically: agents inside clusters pull changes from Git (not pushed by CI)</item>
      <item>Continuously reconciled: automatic drift detection and correction without manual triggers</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Pull vs Push Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer pull-based GitOps for security-focused, multi-cluster, or compliance-driven environments.</statement>
      <rationale>Pull-based (ArgoCD, FluxCD) eliminates cluster credentials from CI pipelines — the agent inside the cluster only needs read access to the Git repo. Push-based requires exposing cluster API credentials to external CI systems, which must be rotated and audited separately.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the hybrid model (CI pushes manifest updates to Git, GitOps agent applies) for most new deployments.</statement>
      <rationale>Hybrid combines push-model velocity for image builds and tag updates with pull-model safety for apply and drift detection. CI never has cluster credentials; the GitOps agent reconciles from Git state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Pull advantages: no external cluster credentials, autonomous drift correction, multi-cluster native, audit trail built-in</item>
      <item>Push advantages: familiar CI/CD patterns, tight sequencing control, simpler initial setup</item>
      <item>Tools (pull): ArgoCD (60% K8s adoption 2025), FluxCD (CNCF graduated), Kargo (multi-env promotion)</item>
      <item>Tools (push): GitHub Actions, GitLab CI, Jenkins</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Repository Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use folder-per-environment, not branch-per-environment, for environment separation.</statement>
      <rationale>Branch-based environments require cross-branch cherry-picks for config changes and make diff visibility hard. Folder-based environments (apps/{app}/overlays/{staging,prod}) keep all environments in one PR diff and enable Kustomize overlays without branching complexity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Monorepo pattern (recommended for organizations with fewer than 50 applications):</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
gitops-repo/
├── apps/
│   └── {app-name}/
│       ├── base/              # kustomization.yaml, deployment.yaml, service.yaml
│       └── overlays/
│           ├── staging/       # kustomization.yaml with staging-specific patches
│           └── production/
├── infrastructure/            # cert-manager, ingress-nginx, external-secrets
├── clusters/
│   ├── staging/
│   └── production/
└── projects/
    └── team-*.yaml           # RBAC and project scoping
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Progressive Delivery">
    <list>
      <item>Canary: gradually shifts traffic percentage (5% → 25% → 50% → 100%) while analyzing Prometheus metrics at each step; auto-rollback on threshold breach</item>
      <item>Blue-Green: runs two identical environments; instant traffic switch after validation; requires 2x resources during deployment window</item>
      <item>Argo Rollouts: native controller for canary and blue-green with metric-driven promotion; integrates with ArgoCD</item>
      <item>Flagger: progressive delivery controller for FluxCD with Istio/NGINX traffic splitting</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Sync Policy Guidelines">
    <list>
      <item>Development: auto-sync enabled, self-heal enabled, prune enabled</item>
      <item>Staging: auto-sync enabled, self-heal enabled, prune enabled</item>
      <item>Production: auto-sync disabled (manual promotion with approval), self-heal enabled, prune disabled or PruneLast</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
