<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Product Analytics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Tracking-plan + funnel/cohort instrumentation discipline (AARRR / North Star) feeding agent-readable BI sources for activation diagnosis, weekly health digests, and experiment readouts.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="tracking-plan-versioned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every product MUST maintain a tracking plan (YAML/JSON) under version control: event_name, properties, owner, status (live/deprecated). Untracked events emitted from code are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Segment / Amplitude tracking-plan governance">Untracked events break trend lines on first deploy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="event-naming-strict" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Event names MUST follow `object_action` (snake_case), past tense. Free-form names produce duplicates that fragment funnels.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mixpanel / Heap naming standards">Naming chaos is the #1 cause of broken funnels in mature instrumentations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="primary-metric-trees" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every product MUST publish a North Star + 2-3 input metrics with explicit causal-link diagrams. Vanity metrics in dashboards without input chain are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sean Ellis / Andrew Chen North Star Metric">Without a metric tree, all metrics look equally important.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="anomaly-rule-set" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The agent-readable health digest MUST cite explicit anomaly rules (e.g., 'any cohort retention WoW change &gt; 3pp', 'funnel step conversion ±10% absolute').</statement>
      <rationale source="GrowthBook anomaly detection patterns">Soft-judgment anomalies vary by run and produce inconsistent alerts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pii-redaction-pre-llm" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Event properties containing PII MUST be redacted before being fed to a remote LLM. Redaction happens at ingest, not at synthesis.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR / CCPA processing constraints">Late redaction creates exposure windows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — pre-MVP without live events; product fully measured by external vendor with no in-app behaviour; compliance lockdown), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
