<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Project Integration Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the project-integration methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="single-source-of-truth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One YAML file (integrated/plan.yaml) in the project repo is the single source of truth; derivatives (slides, PDFs, dashboards) are generated, never hand-edited.</statement>
      <rationale source="Configuration management practice">Manual edits diverge from the source within one week; agents pulling from wrong derivatives produce misleading status reports.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="charter-as-code" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Charter.md lives in the project repo; sponsor approves via PR review with signed commit. Amendments require a new PR, not a stealth edit.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — charter rot postmortems">Git history of charter changes is the audit trail for change authorization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cross-area-impact-memo" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every approved CR requires a cross-area impact memo committed alongside the CR before implementation begins.</statement>
      <rationale source="Change-control practice">Second-order effects (a 2-week delay shifting onto a holiday, breaking a vendor deadline) surface only in cross-area analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="numeric-thresholds-for-status" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Status colour is derived from numeric thresholds, never PM narrative. The threshold table is part of the plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — status-report drift audits">Narrative status is subjective and unreliable; threshold-driven status is deterministic and auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rebaseline-only-on-cr" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-baseline only when scope/budget/contract changes — not when velocity slips. Re-baselining for slip masks chronic delivery problems.</statement>
      <rationale source="EVM practice">Baseline changes are decisions, not corrections; treating slip as a reason to re-baseline hides the root cause and makes EVM meaningless.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="decision-log-adr-per-cr" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One decisions/ directory per project, one ADR-style entry per approved CR with rationale + impact + signature.</statement>
      <rationale source="ADR practice">Decision rationale lost verbally; documented decisions become searchable corporate memory.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Single-team, single-stream work with a stable backlog — Scrum or Kanban already integrates within the team</item>
      <item>Short tactical engagement under 4 weeks with no inter-area trade-offs</item>
      <item>Pure research / discovery phase with no committed scope</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
