<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Project Integration Management — Framework and Activities">
  <summary>The PM-as-integrator model, the six integration activities, charter elements, and integrated change control process.</summary>

  <section title="Integration Role">
    <rule>
      <statement>The PM acts as the cross-area integrator: every decision in one knowledge area must be assessed for impact on all others before approval.</statement>
      <rationale>Silo management optimizes parts and sub-optimizes the whole. A scope CR approved without schedule and cost update creates a multi-week cascade of drift that is invisible until delivery fails.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Integration coordinates: Scope, Schedule, Cost, Quality, Risk, Resources, Communications, Procurement. Each has a subsidiary plan; the integrated plan references all of them from a single YAML source-of-truth.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Six Integration Activities">
    <list>
      <item>Project Charter (Initiation) — authorize project, define high-level scope, bind sponsor commitment. Charter as code: sponsor approves via PR review.</item>
      <item>Project Plan (Planning) — integrate all subsidiary plans into one YAML referencing scope (WBS), schedule, cost, risks, quality, resources, comms, procurement baselines.</item>
      <item>Direct Work (Execution) — lead execution; ensure the plan governs, not informal decisions.</item>
      <item>Monitor and Control (Throughout) — track against integrated baselines; emit GREEN/YELLOW/RED from numeric thresholds, not PM narrative.</item>
      <item>Integrated Change Control (Throughout) — every CR triggers cross-area impact analysis before approval; decisions logged in decisions/ per ADR pattern.</item>
      <item>Close Project (Closure) — formal acceptance, lessons learned, archive, contract closeout. Closure is integration's last mile — do not let the team scatter before it completes.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Charter Elements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every SMART objective in the charter must cite a measurable success criterion; unknowns must be listed as TO_CONFIRM, not omitted.</statement>
      <rationale>Charter generators hallucinate constraints and assumptions to appear thorough. Forcing unknowns to surface as TO_CONFIRM creates a tracked open-question list.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/charter.md">Project charter template with approval block</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Integrated Change Control">
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-baseline only when scope/budget/contract changes — not when velocity slips. Re-baselining for slip masks chronic delivery problems.</statement>
      <rationale>Baseline changes are decisions, not corrections. Treating slip as a reason to re-baseline hides the root cause and makes EVM meaningless.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every approved CR requires a cross-area impact memo committed alongside the CR before implementation begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Second-order effects (a 2-week delay shifting dependencies onto a holiday, breaking a vendor deadline) only surface when impact is computed across all areas — not as a delta on duration alone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Status colour declared GREEN/YELLOW/RED based on PM narrative rather than numeric threshold comparison.</description>
      <reason>Agents over-summarize: declaring "GREEN — on track" without numeric backing is the dominant integration failure. Colour must follow threshold arithmetic.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="templates/integration-status.py">Script: compute status colours from numeric YAML inputs</reference>
    <reference path="templates/status-report.md">Weekly status report template</reference>
  </section>
</text>
