<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-workflow" title="Project Integration Management — Agentic Workflow and Subagents">
  <summary>Integrated-plan-as-code pipeline, subagent roles, change-impact prompt pattern, and AI-specific failure modes in integration contexts.</summary>

  <section title="Integrated Plan as Code">
    <rule>
      <statement>Single source of truth: one YAML file (integrated/plan.yaml) in the project repo; derivatives (slides, PDFs, dashboards) are generated — never hand-edited.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual edits to derivative documents diverge from the source within one week; agents that pull from the wrong derivative produce misleading status reports.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Charter (charter.md) lives in the same repo; sponsor approves via PR merge. A decisions/ directory holds one ADR-style entry per approved CR. This makes the program's decision history searchable.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Recommended Subagents">
    <list>
      <item>charter-author-agent (opus): drafts charter from kickoff inputs, drives sponsor sign-off, captures assumptions and constraints.</item>
      <item>change-impact-agent (sonnet): given a CR, computes impact across all knowledge areas from the integrated plan; emits a markdown impact memo.</item>
      <item>baseline-curator-agent (sonnet): keeps the integrated plan consistent — flags scope without schedule, schedule without cost, risks without owners.</item>
      <item>status-reporter-agent (haiku): renders the status report template from numeric inputs only; colour follows thresholds, never tone.</item>
      <item>closure-agent (sonnet): runs the closure checklist, archives plans, captures lessons learned, generates final acceptance documentation.</item>
      <item>password-scrubber-agent: runs over charter/status/closure docs before distribution; integration artifacts are top leak paths.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Change-Impact Prompt Pattern">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Strict markdown output forces numeric grounding; rejects vague recommendations:</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are the change-impact agent. Inputs:
1. Approved change request (CR-NN.md): scope description, requestor, priority.
2. integrated/plan.yaml: scope (WBS), schedule, cost, risks, quality, resources.
3. Threshold table: GREEN/YELLOW/RED triggers per dimension.

Emit STRICT MARKDOWN:
## Impact Analysis CR-NN
| Area | Current | Proposed | Delta | Status | Notes |
|------|---------|----------|-------|--------|-------|

## Recommendation
- decision: approve | reject | conditional
- conditions: [ ... ]
- new_baseline_required: true|false
- communications: [ stakeholders to notify ]

Rules:
- Numbers come from inputs; never invent.
- Status follows threshold table verbatim.
- Recommend reject if any dimension goes RED without a compensating trade-off.
- Cite at least one risk-register entry if risk delta is non-zero.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent produces cross-area impact analysis that only covers the areas it has API access to.</description>
      <reason>An agent with only Jira access produces schedule-blind reports. Force an input audit: every knowledge area must appear in the impact memo or be explicitly marked "data unavailable".</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Closure declared complete with an empty lessons-learned file.</description>
      <reason>Agents skip lessons learned because there is no code change. Force the closure checklist to fail-close if the lessons file is empty.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Charter sign-off automated by the agent merging its own PR.</description>
      <reason>Charter sign-off is a governance decision requiring sponsor authority; the agent prepares the PR and the sponsor approves the merge.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <list>
      <item>Mandatory human checkpoints: charter approval, baseline changes, CR approval, status colour shifts to RED, closure declaration.</item>
      <item>Decision log entries get duplicated by parallel agents — force a unique-ID generator and advisory lock.</item>
      <item>Integrated plans over 500 lines blow context; page by knowledge area, persist summaries, rehydrate.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
