<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-tools-and-references" title="Project Integration Management — Tools, Services, and References">
  <summary>CLI tools, SaaS platforms, best practices, and references for integrated project management.</summary>

  <section title="CLI Tools">
    <list>
      <item>git + branch protection — charter and integrated plan as code; PR gates sponsor sign-off</item>
      <item>gh / glab — drive change-request issues, link to PRs that update baselines</item>
      <item>yq / jq — read/patch integrated/plan.yaml; aggregate dependencies (apt install yq jq)</item>
      <item>python-docx / python-pptx / pandoc — render charter, status reports, closure docs to org-required formats</item>
      <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc) — render integration diagrams (scope → schedule → cost) and status dashboards</item>
      <item>mpxj — read/write MS Project .mpp schedules from the integrated plan (https://www.mpxj.org)</item>
      <item>pre-commit — block edits to charter.md or baselines without rationale and sponsor reviewer</item>
      <item>make / just — standardize "build status pack" / "render closure" tasks</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Services">
    <list>
      <item>Microsoft Project + Project for the Web — dominant predictive tool; integrates with Teams + Power BI for status.</item>
      <item>Smartsheet — portfolio gantt + dashboards; common integration target (REST API).</item>
      <item>Jira with Plans / Advanced Roadmaps — common host; cross-project dashboards via JQL.</item>
      <item>Azure DevOps — hybrid host: portfolio Plans + team Boards + Pipelines.</item>
      <item>ServiceNow SPM — heavy enterprise PPM with full integration; required where governance is the constraint.</item>
      <item>Confluence / Notion — charter, decisions, status home; pair with the work-graph host.</item>
      <item>DocuSign / Adobe Sign — charter sign-off, formal acceptance (REST API).</item>
      <item>OpenProject / Redmine / Tuleap — self-hosted hosts for regulated/airgapped orgs (REST API).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run an integration check weekly: scope without schedule? schedule without cost? risks without owners? — automate and open issues on failure.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated consistency checks catch silo drift in days rather than months; the weekly cadence is short enough to fix before downstream teams are affected.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep change-control velocity moderate: batch CRs into weekly review — too few hides chaos, too many drowns the integrator.</statement>
      <rationale>Emergency CR streams bypass integrated impact analysis; batching forces discipline while preserving responsiveness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Train sponsors on what they sign — most integration failures are sponsor-driven (silent scope additions).</statement>
      <rationale>If sponsors do not understand the baseline they approved, every informal "can you just add X" becomes an untracked scope change.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="References">
    <list>
      <item>PMI PMBOK 6e — Integration Management Knowledge Area (templates and processes).</item>
      <item>PMI PMBOK 7e — Tailoring + Performance Domains (Planning, Project Work, Delivery, Measurement).</item>
      <item>ISO 21500 / 21502 — international guidance on integration and tailoring.</item>
      <item>Reinertsen "The Principles of Product Development Flow" — queueing theory for integrated cadences.</item>
      <item>Sibling methodologies: change-control/, lessons-learned/, scope-management/, schedule-development/, cost-estimation/, risk-register/, quality-management/, procurement-management/, communications-management/, stakeholder-engagement/</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
