<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Facilitation Anti-Patterns Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six anti-pattern rules every BA workshop facilitator must enforce. Each rule names the failure, gives a detection cue the BA can spot in real time, and prescribes a counter-move that defuses it without humiliating the offender.</summary>
  <section title="The anti-patterns">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sponsor monologue is broken before the five-minute mark. If the sponsor speaks for more than five consecutive minutes inside an elicitation block, the BA interrupts with a written-poll round (sticky notes or chat) addressed to every other participant by name.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stakeholder workshop quality research (sponsor monologue)">When the sponsor holds the floor, every subsequent contribution becomes a reaction to that frame instead of an independent data point — the workshop is now ratifying the sponsor's pre-existing view, not eliciting fresh requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>False consensus is challenged by a forced-dissent round. Before any "are we agreed?" close, the BA explicitly asks "what would have to be true for this to be wrong?" and waits at least 15 seconds of silence before accepting the agreement.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-pattern catalogue for workshops (false consensus)">Heads-nodding is a social-comfort signal, not an alignment signal. Forced dissent surfaces the silent disagreement that otherwise resurfaces as a change request three weeks later.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Anchoring on the first speaker is prevented by silent-first elicitation. For every new question, every participant writes their answer privately for 90 seconds before any verbal sharing; the BA only reveals contributions after collection.</statement>
      <rationale source="Workshop facilitation anti-patterns (first-speaker anchoring)">The first verbal answer becomes the implicit reference point for everyone after. Silent-first collection breaks the anchor and reveals the true distribution of views.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The parking lot has a graveyard clock. Every item moved to the parking lot is tagged with an owner and a "review by" timestamp inside the same session; any item older than two cycles without a decision is auto-escalated to the sponsor with a "kill or schedule" choice — never silently dropped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Parking-lot graveyard anti-pattern">Without an explicit clock, parked items accumulate as dead weight and stakeholders learn that "parking" means "burying". An ownerless, timestampless parking lot destroys trust in the entire elicitation process.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>HiPPO override is logged as a decision, not absorbed as consensus. When the highest-paid person in the room overrides a workshop position, the BA writes the override into the minutes as "decision by authority" with the named decider, the rejected alternatives, and the reason given — never as "the group decided".</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-pattern catalogue (HiPPO / sponsor override)">Laundering an authority decision as group consensus poisons future workshops: dissenters stop contributing because they learn their input is theatre. Naming the override preserves both the decision and the dissent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agenda drift triggers an explicit re-contract, not a quiet continuation. If the conversation drifts off the published agenda for more than ten minutes, the BA stops and asks the room: "do we re-contract to this new topic and drop X, or do we park this and return to X?" — the room must vote before continuing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Workshop drift anti-pattern">Silent drift produces sessions where neither the planned agenda nor the off-topic discussion gets a real decision. Forcing an explicit re-contract preserves the integrity of the deliverable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Counter-moves applied in flight">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Minute 6: sponsor still talking → BA: "Pause — let me capture this on the board so the others can react. Mariia, what would you add or contest from your side?" (r1 broken, named call-out)
Minute 22: "are we agreed?" → BA: "Before we close — what would have to be true for this to be the wrong call?" (15s silence held, r2)
New question on SLA breach handling → 90s silent write before discussion (r3)
"Refund webhook design" parked → tagged owner=Oleh, review_by=next session, escalation date set (r4)
CTO overrides workshop position on event ordering → minutes: "Decision by authority (Andrii, CTO). Alternative considered: idempotent retry queue. Reason: ops cost." (r5)
35 minutes into account-merging debate, agenda item was payment flow → BA: "Re-contract to account-merging and push payment flow to next session, or park this and return now?" (r6)
]]></code>
      <note>Every anti-pattern is caught inside the session and resolved with an explicit, logged action. The artefact (minutes + BPMN draft) survives sponsor pressure and reveals real dissent.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
