<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="risk-register">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Living log of identified threats and opportunities with probability, impact, response strategy, named owner, trigger condition, and status. Reviewed weekly.</summary>
    <category>risk</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>risk-register</tag>
      <tag>pmbok</tag>
      <tag>register</tag>
      <tag>tracking</tag>
      <tag>accountability</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="risk-management"/>
      <ref slug="schedule-development"/>
      <ref slug="cost-estimation"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Risk Register</title>

    <summary>A living log of identified threats and opportunities, each with a probability (1–5), impact (1–5), risk score (P×I), chosen response strategy, named owner, trigger condition, and current status. The register must be reviewed weekly and updated as risks materialize, pass, or merge.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without a documented register, risks have no accountability — every risk becomes a surprise crisis. Stale registers with no owners and "All Accept" strategies provide false comfort. The register forces explicit owner assignment, measurable triggers, and funded contingency, turning reactive fire-fighting into managed uncertainty.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Multi-month delivery requiring a single source of truth for risks across teams</item>
        <item>Audited or regulated programs needing a register with IDs, owners, and decision history</item>
        <item>Programs with quantitative contingency reserves that must be defended to finance</item>
        <item>Cross-vendor or cross-org work where risks span ownership boundaries</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo or hobby projects — a RISKS.md checklist is enough</item>
        <item>Pure-Scrum teams running impediment and retro loops with adequate coverage</item>
        <item>Spike or discovery work where most "risks" are research questions</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="step-1-identify-risks">
      <p>Identify both threats (negative risks) and opportunities (positive risks) across all four categories: Technical, External, Organizational, and Project Management. Identification techniques include team brainstorming, expert interviews, checklist review, historical project analysis, and SWOT analysis.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Identify both threats (negative risks) and opportunities (positive risks) across all four categories: Technical, External, Organizational, and Project Management.</statement>
        <rationale>Registers that capture only threats miss the opportunity to exploit or enhance favorable events. Systematic category coverage prevents blind spots from informal brainstorming.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-2-analyze-probability-and-impact">
      <p>Probability scale (1=Very Low to 5=Very High): VL &lt; 10%, L 10-30%, M 30-50%, H 50-70%, VH &gt; 70%. Impact scale (1=Very Low to 5=Very High): VL &lt; 5% budget/schedule, L 5-10%, M 10-20%, H 20-40%, VH &gt; 40% or project failure.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="step-3-calculate-risk-score">
      <p>Compute Risk Score equals Probability × Impact (1–25); prioritize as High (15–25), Medium (8–14), Low (1–7). Require per-axis rationale for every score to prevent clustering at Medium-Medium. Pair every risk with a measurable trigger condition; without a trigger, the team cannot detect when the risk is activating.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Compute Risk Score = Probability x Impact (1–25); prioritize as High (15–25), Medium (8–14), Low (1–7). Require per-axis rationale for every score to prevent clustering at Medium-Medium.</statement>
        <rationale>Without rationale, analysts default to Medium-Medium, compressing information and hiding true high-priority risks. Per-axis justification forces calibration and distributes scores.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Pair every risk with a measurable trigger condition; without a trigger, the team cannot detect when the risk is activating.</statement>
        <rationale>Trigger-less risks stay academic. A trigger converts risk monitoring from a scheduled exercise to an event-driven alert.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-4-plan-responses">
      <p>For threats: Avoid (eliminate), Transfer (insurance/outsource), Mitigate (reduce P or I), Accept (contingency). For opportunities: Exploit (ensure it occurs), Share (partner), Enhance (increase probability), Accept (take benefit if it occurs).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every risk with score 8 or above must have a named strategy and a specific response action; "Accept" without a contingency is not a valid response for high-score risks.</statement>
        <rationale>The all-accept antipattern gives false comfort. High-score risks without funded contingency will hit the budget as unplanned crisis costs.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-5-assign-owners">
      <rule>
        <statement>Assign exactly one named owner per risk; "the team" is not an owner.</statement>
        <rationale>Shared ownership is no ownership. One owner is accountable for monitoring triggers, executing response if needed, and updating status.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-6-monitor-and-update-weekly">
      <p>Review risks weekly; add new entries, update scores as situation changes, and close risks with explicit outcome (materialized / passed / merged). Never delete a row. Deletion destroys audit history and contingency calculation integrity. Closure with outcome preserves the record for lessons-learned and future project calibration. Weekly review agenda: new risks? scores changed? triggers activated? responses in progress? risks to close? top-5 still accurate?</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Review risks weekly; add new entries, update scores as situation changes, and close risks with explicit outcome (materialized / passed / merged). Never delete a row.</statement>
        <rationale>Deletion destroys audit history and contingency calculation integrity. Closure with outcome preserves the record for lessons-learned and future project calibration.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="examples-threats">
      <example type="good" title="Software project risk register threats">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Software project risk register (5 entries):

R1: Key developer leaves
P=M, I=H, score=12
Strategy: Mitigate
Response: document code + cross-train
Owner: Tech Lead
Trigger: departure notice given

R2: Third-party API deprecated
P=L, I=VH, score=10
Strategy: Accept
Response: build abstraction layer + monitor
Owner: Lead Architect
Trigger: API deprecation announced

R3: Scope creep
P=H, I=M, score=12
Strategy: Avoid
Response: change control process
Owner: PM
Trigger: feature requests + 20%

R4: Performance issues
P=M, I=M, score=9
Strategy: Mitigate
Response: early load testing
Owner: SRE
Trigger: response time > threshold

R5: Budget cut
P=L, I=H, score=8
Strategy: Accept
Response: identify optional features
Owner: PM
Trigger: budget warning from finance]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="examples-opportunities">
      <example type="good" title="Opportunity risks tracked with threats">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Opportunity risks (review at every weekly meeting):

O1: Early delivery possible
P=M, I=H, score=12
Strategy: Enhance
Response: fast-track critical path
Owner: PM
Trigger: tasks completing 20% early

O2: Partnership offer
P=L, I=VH, score=10
Strategy: Exploit
Response: prioritize integration
Owner: Lead Architect
Trigger: partnership confirmed

O3: Positive press coverage
P=M, I=M, score=9
Strategy: Share
Response: prepare press kit
Owner: Marketing
Trigger: press request arrives]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>One-time exercise — risks identified at kickoff, register never updated.</description>
        <reason>Project context evolves weekly; a static register reflects the world as it was, not as it is. Stale scores give false comfort and miss emerging threats entirely.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No owners — risks listed without a named accountable person.</description>
        <reason>Unowned risks are nobody's problem. When they activate, the team scrambles to find who should respond, costing days in crisis mode before a response is even designed.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>All-Accept strategy — every high-score risk marked "Accept" with no contingency funded.</description>
        <reason>Accept without contingency is wishful thinking. High-score risks that materialize hit the project budget as emergency overruns with no pre-approved response plan.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Missing positive risks — register covers only threats.</description>
        <reason>Opportunities that pass unnoticed are value left on the table. A threat-only register uses 50% of the risk management value.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Too vague — "Something might go wrong with the vendor" is not an actionable risk.</description>
        <reason>Vague descriptions prevent probability/impact analysis and make response planning impossible. Every risk needs a specific "what might happen and why" framing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A subagent owns the register's mechanical lifecycle: ingest meeting notes / status reports / change events to surface candidate risks, normalize entries (ID, category, P, I, score, strategy), produce a weekly diff (new / changed / closed / stale), and push updates to the tracker. Humans own probability/impact judgment, response approval, and contingency funding. Recommended subagents: faion-pm-agent owns register, drafts entries, runs weekly diffs. brainstorm (skill) diverge round at kickoff and phase gates to seed the register. faion-business-analyst strong on category coverage (technical/external/organizational/PM). improver reviews closed risks for lessons-learned input.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Risk register curator prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a risk-register curator. Inputs: charter, current register, last
14 days of status reports + meeting notes.
Output JSON with three lists: NEW (proposed entries), CHANGED (id +
field deltas), STALE (id, last_update_date). For every entry include
rationale citing source. Do NOT mutate; emit proposals only.]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Risk scoring prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Score this risk on the 5x5 P/I matrix. Output P, I, score, priority, plus
one-sentence rationale per axis citing project artefacts. If confidence
is low, set needs_review=true and explain.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Stale registers without weekly review cause scores to drift from reality fast. Probability/impact buckets compress information (Medium-Medium swamp). Score = P × I treats risks as independent; correlated risks (vendor delays cluster) are under-weighted. The "All accept" anti-pattern occurs when every row is marked Accept with no contingency funded. Opportunities are systematically under-tracked — registers become threat-only.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>riskman (npm) is a Markdown-driven register with CLI scoring. risk-cli (Python) runs Monte Carlo on EMV inputs. jira-cli syncs risks as Risk issue type with custom fields. gh syncs risks as issues with risk + priority labels. csvkit / dsq query CSV registers. pandoc renders to PDF for steering committee.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <p>Jira RMsis / Risk Management for Jira is SaaS plugin with REST API, first-class risk type, P×I custom fields, register reports. Smartsheet RAID log is SaaS with REST API, strong for PMOs and contractors. Monday.com risk template is SaaS with GraphQL, easy adoption, weak quantitative tooling. ServiceNow GRC is enterprise SaaS with REST API, heavyweight; for regulated programs. Notion risk DB is SaaS with REST API, best for solo / SDD repos; agent fully drives. Active Risk Manager (Sword) is enterprise with SOAP/REST. Resolver is enterprise SaaS with REST API, GRC-heavy organizations.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Pair every risk with a measurable trigger; without a trigger you cannot detect activation. Mandate explicit owner per row — "team" is not an owner. Keep the top-5 risks on every status report; long-tail goes in appendix. Roll EMVs into a single contingency request; finance funds aggregates, not rows. Color-code opportunities and threats; review parity at every weekly meeting. Close risks explicitly with outcome (materialized / passed / merged-into-RX); never delete. For SDD repos: store the register as Markdown + table for diff-friendly history.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>LLMs cluster scores at Medium-Medium; require per-axis rationale to spread distribution. Auto-generated risks are often generic ("vendor delay"); seed with project-specific artifacts (charter, ADRs, vendor SOWs). Agents will assign owners speculatively — leave blank by default and flag for human assignment. Do not allow autonomous closure; closure has audit consequences and impacts contingency calculations. Token budget: send only top-N + changed rows, not the full register, on each turn. Human-in-loop checkpoints: (1) calibration round at kickoff, (2) approval of NEW high-score entries, (3) weekly diff review, (4) any contingency-impacting change.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/risk-register.md" purpose="Full register table: ID, description, category, P, I, score, strategy, response, owner, status"/>
      <template path="templates/risk-card.md" purpose="Individual risk card with assessment, response plan, contingency, trigger, and tracking log"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="templates/risk-audit.py" purpose="Flags stale (>14 days, open), high-priority (score ≥ 15), and no-owner risks from a CSV register"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="risk-management"/>
      <ref slug="schedule-development"/>
      <ref slug="cost-estimation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
