<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="distribution-channel-research">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>5-step framework to identify and prioritize customer acquisition channels: map discovery sources, score channels on fit matrix, model economics, design micro-tests, and build phased mix.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>distribution-channels</tag>
      <tag>customer-acquisition</tag>
      <tag>gtm</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>channel-economics</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Distribution Channel Research</title>

    <summary>A 5-step process for identifying and prioritizing customer acquisition channels: map customer discovery sources, score channels on a weighted fit matrix (audience/cost/time/scale/capability), model economics per channel (LTV:CAC > 3:1 as Phase-2 gate), design micro-tests ($100-500, 4-6 weeks, pre-registered kill criteria), and build a phased channel mix (1 channel first, expand after $10K MRR).</summary>

    <why>
      <p>"If you build it, they will come" is a myth. Entrepreneurs pick channels based on personal preference rather than customer behavior data, or try all channels at once and master none. The fit matrix and economics model force citation of every benchmark number and predefine kill criteria before money is spent — preventing sunk-cost continuation and channel concentration risk.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch GTM planning: product hypothesis exists but no validated path to first 100 users.</item>
        <item>Post-launch when primary channel CAC is climbing and adjacent channels must be researched.</item>
        <item>B2B/B2C pivots where the buyer or buying motion changes (PLG → sales-led or vice versa).</item>
        <item>Solopreneur projects where bandwidth requires mastering 1 channel, not dabbling in 5.</item>
        <item>Periodic audit (every 2 quarters) of the active channel mix against actual customer-source data.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF — channels do not fix a broken product; tests produce misleading CAC.</item>
        <item>Products with strong existing organic pull (60%+ direct traffic) — formal research adds no signal.</item>
        <item>One-off campaigns (event launch, single press hit) where the question is creative, not channel.</item>
        <item>When customer interviews and attribution analytics do not exist and cannot be collected — any output is conjecture.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="organic-channels">
      <title>Organic Channels</title>
      <list>
        <item>SEO: 6-12 month timeline, low cost, sustainable low CAC after maturation</item>
        <item>Content marketing (blog/video/podcast): 3-6 months, low-medium cost</item>
        <item>Social media organic: 3-6 months, low cost, audience-dependent</item>
        <item>Community building (Discord/Slack/forum): 6+ months, low cost, high retention signal</item>
        <item>Word of mouth: ongoing, free — only works after retention is proven</item>
        <item>Product-led growth (in-product virality): timeline varies, low cost</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="paid-channels">
      <title>Paid Channels</title>
      <list>
        <item>Search ads (Google, Bing): immediate results, high cost — best for capturing existing demand</item>
        <item>Social ads (Meta, LinkedIn, TikTok): immediate, medium-high cost — best for creating demand</item>
        <item>Influencer/sponsorships (podcast, newsletter): 1-4 weeks, medium-high cost, hard to attribute</item>
        <item>Affiliate: 1-2 month ramp, variable cost (revenue share only)</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep a "20% experiments" budget non-negotiable even when the primary channel is working — channel concentration risk is the #1 GTM failure mode at $100K+ MRR.</statement>
        <rationale>Channels saturate. Apple ATT, Google cookie deprecation, and algorithm changes have each eliminated primary channels for SaaS companies with no backup. The 20% budget maintains optionality.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="sales-led-channels">
      <title>Sales-Led Channels</title>
      <list>
        <item>Outbound sales (cold email/call): immediate, high cost, best for high-ACV B2B</item>
        <item>Partnerships (co-marketing, integrations): 2-6 month ramp, medium cost</item>
        <item>Conferences/events: 1-3 month conversion cycle, high cost</item>
        <item>Webinars: 1-2 week ramp, low-medium cost</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="viral-and-network-channels">
      <title>Viral and Network Channels</title>
      <list>
        <item>Referral program (incentivized sharing): 1-2 month ramp, variable cost</item>
        <item>App marketplace integrations: 2-4 month build, medium cost</item>
        <item>Embeds (widgets, badges): 1-2 month build, low cost</item>
        <item>User-generated content (templates, showcases): 2-4 months, low cost</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="portfolio-mix-by-stage">
      <title>Portfolio Mix by Stage</title>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Focus on exactly 1 channel from 0 to $10K MRR, expand to 2-3 channels from $10K to $50K MRR, then diversify. 80% effort on 1-2 proven channels, 20% on experiments.</statement>
        <rationale>Trying all channels at once means mastering none. Channel mastery requires iterating 10+ experiments per channel — spreading across 5 channels produces 2 iterations each, which is insufficient for learning the economics.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-1-map-customer-discovery">
      <title>Step 1: Map Customer Discovery</title>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use a free-text "How did you hear about us?" field, not a dropdown — dropdowns force respondents into the wrong bucket and corrupt the discovery map.</statement>
        <rationale>Dropdowns create selection bias toward the channels you already know. Free text surfaces channels you did not consider and catches "dark social" attribution (podcast, friend DM, Slack community).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Customer interviews: "How did you find [competitor]?" and "Where do you usually discover new tools?"</item>
        <item>Analytics: UTM source breakdown, referrer analysis (multi-touch, not last-click)</item>
        <item>Competitor analysis: SimilarWeb traffic mix, Meta Ad Library, LinkedIn Ad Library</item>
        <item>Audience research: SparkToro for "where does this audience hang out?" — sites, podcasts, social handles</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="step-2-channel-fit-matrix">
      <title>Step 2: Channel Fit Matrix</title>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Score each channel on six factors (audience presence 25%, competitors using 15%, cost to test 20%, time to results 15%, scalability 15%, team capability 10%) and require a cited source or interview reference for audience presence and competitors-using scores.</statement>
        <rationale>Uncited scores are preferences disguised as analysis. Forcing citations for the two highest-weight factors prevents agents from recommending SEO by default because training data is saturated with SEO examples.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Viable channels: those scoring above 3.5/5 weighted total AND with LTV:CAC > 3:1 in Phase-2 testing.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="step-3-channel-economics">
      <title>Step 3: Channel Economics</title>
      <list>
        <item>Cost per impression → CTR → CPC → conversion rate → CAC</item>
        <item>LTV:CAC ratio target: > 3:1 for Phase-2 scaling, > 1:1 minimum for Phase-1 micro-tests</item>
        <item>Time to ROI: organic channels typically 6-12 months; paid channels immediate but front-loaded cost</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Treat LTV:CAC > 3:1 as a Phase-2 gate, not a Phase-1 gate — Phase-1 micro-tests are buying signal, not unit economics validation.</statement>
        <rationale>LTV is uncertain for early-stage products. Killing a channel after a $300 test because LTV:CAC is 2:1 is premature — the sample size is too small for economic conclusions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-4-test-framework">
      <title>Step 4: Test Framework</title>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Predefine a kill criterion (e.g., "if CAC > $X after $500 spend, kill") before money is spent — prevents sunk-cost continuation.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-hoc evaluation always finds reasons to continue. A pre-registered kill criterion removes the sunk-cost bias and makes test results actionable regardless of the outcome.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Phase 1 micro-test: $100-500 budget, 1-2 weeks, answer "does this channel generate signal?"</item>
        <item>Phase 2 scale test: $1-5K budget, 1 month, answer "what are the economics?"</item>
        <item>Phase 3 optimize: tune targeting/creative before increasing budget</item>
        <item>Separate "channel" from "creative": 3 distinct creative concepts before killing a channel</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="three-stage-subagent-chain">
      <title>Three-Stage Subagent Chain</title>
      <list>
        <item>Stage 1 — discovery agent: gathers customer attribution (interviews + analytics) + competitor channel evidence; uses faion-research-agent in competitors + personas modes</item>
        <item>Stage 2 — scoring agent: applies channel-fit matrix and economic model; uses growth-marketer + ppc-manager knowledge for CPC/CTR benchmarks</item>
        <item>Stage 3 — test-design agent: produces ranked test plan with budgets, timing milestones, and pre-registered kill criteria; checks with gtm-strategist knowledge for phase gating</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>When the agent has zero customer interviews, flag this explicitly in the output header so the reader knows the input quality — fall back to competitor inference with a clear "UNVERIFIED" label on every inferred channel.</statement>
        <rationale>Channel research output reads plausible but un-actionable when built entirely from competitor inference without customer source data. The quality flag prevents the output from being acted on at the same confidence level as interview-grounded research.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-pattern">
      <title>Prompt Pattern</title>
      <example type="good" title="Channel research prompt with citation and complexity requirements">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Role: distribution-channel research subagent.
Inputs: ICP={...}, product={...}, competitors=[...], current_channels=[...], LTV_estimate=$X.
Tasks:
 1. Map top 5 customer-discovery sources (cite interviews/analytics/competitor evidence; refuse to invent numbers).
 2. Score channels against fit matrix (audience, cost, time, scale, capability). Output table.
 3. Model economics per channel using stated LTV and benchmark CPC ranges (cite source + date).
 4. Recommend Phase-1 test plan: 1 primary + 1 backup, budget $500-2K, milestone-gated stop criteria.
Constraints: no time estimates in days, only complexity (low/med/high). Flag any unverified numbers with [UNVERIFIED].
Return: markdown sections matching channel-report.md.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <title>CLI Tools and Services</title>
      <list>
        <item>SparkToro API: audience hangout discovery (sites, podcasts, social handles) — feeds Step 1</item>
        <item>SimilarWeb API: channel mix per competitor domain (search/social/direct/referral)</item>
        <item>Meta Ad Library (public API): snapshot of active Meta/Instagram ad creatives</item>
        <item>Google Ads Transparency (scrape): Playwright required, no formal API</item>
        <item>ahrefs / semrush API: organic + paid keyword exposure, content gap analysis</item>
        <item>PostHog / Plausible API: self-attribution data export + UTM analysis</item>
        <item>serpapi / serper.dev: programmatic Google search for keyword volume signals</item>
        <item>searxng (self-hosted): NERO runs SearXNG at ~/workspace/tools/searxng for agent loops</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <title>Agent Gotchas</title>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs hallucinating CPC, CPM, and conversion benchmarks without citing source and date.</description>
        <reason>Require the agent to cite source + date for every economic number. Reject answers that fail the citation requirement. CPC/CPM numbers shift 2x+ within 12-24 months.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents over-recommending SEO and content marketing because training data is saturated with those examples.</description>
        <reason>Explicitly prompt for non-obvious channels (integrations, niche marketplaces, communities, podcasts) and require a justification for why standard channels were or were not selected.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Last-click attribution baked into agent reasoning under-crediting dark social, podcast, and community channels.</description>
        <reason>Feed self-reported attribution data alongside analytics. Last-click alone produces wrong recommendations for top-of-funnel channels that have long conversion cycles.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent committing to a Phase 1/Phase 2/Phase 3 calendar with specific dates or week counts.</description>
        <reason>Per workspace rules, no time estimates — phases are gated by milestones (e.g., "after 100 paying customers"), not weeks. Phase gates on outcomes prevent premature scaling.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <title>Best Practices</title>
      <list>
        <item>Anchor every channel claim in either a customer interview (N≥5), an attribution datapoint, or a dated benchmark — reject anonymous "industry says" assertions in agent output.</item>
        <item>Run customer-source surveys with a free-text "How did you hear about us?" field, not a dropdown — dropdowns force respondents into the wrong bucket and corrupt Step 1.</item>
        <item>Treat the LTV:CAC > 3:1 rule as a Phase-2 gate, not a Phase-1 gate; Phase-1 micro-tests are buying signal, not unit economics.</item>
        <item>For each channel test, predefine a kill criterion (e.g. "if CAC > $X after $500 spend, kill") before money is spent — prevents sunk-cost continuation.</item>
        <item>Separate "channel" from "creative": a failed Meta Ads test often means failed creative, not failed channel; rerun with 3 distinct creative concepts before killing.</item>
        <item>Record competitor channel observations with capture date — Meta/TikTok ad libraries are time-windowed and the evidence rots fast.</item>
        <item>For B2B, weight referral and integrations channels higher than the matrix suggests if the product has any network or co-sell surface.</item>
        <item>Keep the "20% experiments" budget non-negotiable even when the primary channel is working; channel concentration risk is the #1 GTM failure mode at $100K+ MRR.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-failure-modes">
      <title>Limitations and Failure Modes</title>
      <list>
        <item>Garbage-in attribution: last-click analytics over-credits paid search and under-credits content/community; the research output inherits that bias unless multi-touch + self-reported attribution are merged.</item>
        <item>Channel saturation drift: CAC numbers from competitor case studies are 12–24 months stale; LinkedIn Ads CPC, Google Ads CPC, and TikTok CPM all moved 2x+ in that window.</item>
        <item>Survivorship bias in "how competitors got users": public case studies skew toward channels that worked; you rarely see the 5 channels they killed.</item>
        <item>LTV uncertainty for early-stage products kills the LTV:CAC math — you cannot threshold a 3:1 ratio when LTV has a 10x confidence interval.</item>
        <item>The 5-step process implies a clean linear flow; in practice steps 2 (channel fit) and 3 (economics) iterate 3–5 times as new data arrives.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/channel-fit-scorer.py" purpose="Scores channels from YAML input against weighted matrix, emits ranked markdown table."/>
      <template path="templates/channels.yaml" purpose="Example input for channel-fit-scorer with three channels pre-scored."/>
      <template path="templates/channel-report.md" purpose="Channel Research Report: discovery insights, evaluation table, economics, competitor analysis, test plan."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="market-research-tam-sam-som"/>
      <ref slug="frameworks"/>
      <link href="https://brianbalfour.com/four-fits-growth-framework">Brian Balfour — Four Fits framework</link>
      <link href="https://a16z.com/the-metrics-that-matter/">a16z — Growth metrics + channel benchmarks</link>
      <link href="https://review.firstround.com/">First Round — How to think about distribution</link>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/">Lenny's Newsletter — Channel benchmarks by stage</link>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/">Reforge — Growth Series channel-economics curriculum</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
