<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stakeholder Engagement (Advanced) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the stakeholder-engagement-advanced methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="classify-from-behaviour-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Classify stakeholder level from behavioural evidence only (attendance, response time, public statements, decisions made). Never classify from assumed intent.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — engagement-classification audits">Polite emails read as Neutral; actual engagement is revealed by action, not tone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="one-level-at-a-time" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Move stakeholders one level at a time. Never plan a jump from Resistant directly to Leading — earn each step with a concrete commitment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Change-management practice">Skipping levels produces shallow engagement that collapses under first pressure; Resistant stakeholders who feel manipulated regress further.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="assessment-matrix-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build the Engagement Assessment Matrix with columns: Stakeholder, Power (H/M/L), Interest (H/M/L), Current Level, Desired Level, Gap (+/-), Next Activity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field experience">The matrix makes engagement gaps visible in one view and drives prioritisation — high power + high gap = highest project risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cadence-driven-engagement" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply contact cadence by quadrant: Manage Closely weekly; Keep Satisfied bi-weekly; Keep Informed weekly broadcast; Monitor monthly summary.</statement>
      <rationale source="Engagement-cadence practice">Over-communicating to low-interest stakeholders trains them to ignore messages.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="drift-flag-on-cadence-breach" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Flag a stakeholder as drifting when last recorded interaction exceeds the cadence threshold for their quadrant with no recorded blocker reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — drift-detection postmortems">Drift is invisible without a system; a stakeholder Supportive 3 months ago may now be Neutral.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>One-off small tasks with no organisational politics</item>
      <item>Adversarial negotiations (procurement, legal disputes) — engagement implies collaboration</item>
      <item>Crisis communications — different discipline, different cadence and tone</item>
      <item>Projects under 4 weeks with a single decision-maker</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
