<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-levels-and-strategies" title="Engagement Levels and Transition Strategies">
  <summary>Five engagement levels with observable indicators and concrete tactics for moving a stakeholder one level at a time.</summary>

  <section title="Engagement Level Definitions">
    <p>Each level is defined by observable behaviour, not assumed attitude.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Unaware — no contact, no information received about the project</item>
      <item>Resistant — actively opposes; blocks decisions, escalates concerns</item>
      <item>Neutral — aware but indifferent; neither helps nor hinders</item>
      <item>Supportive — advocates internally; provides resources or air cover</item>
      <item>Leading — drives adoption; removes barriers on behalf of the project</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify stakeholder level from behavioural evidence only (attendance, response time, public statements, decisions made). Never classify from assumed intent.</statement>
      <rationale>Polite emails read as Neutral by automated tools and optimistic PMs; actual engagement level is revealed by action, not tone.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Transition Strategies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Move stakeholders one level at a time. Never plan a jump from Resistant directly to Leading — earn each step with a concrete commitment.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping levels produces shallow engagement that collapses under the first pressure. Resistant stakeholders who feel manipulated regress further.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Resistant to Neutral — IT Security Director blocking a cloud migration.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Strategy: address concerns directly, involve in requirements definition.
Activities:
  Week 1: 1:1 meeting — listen, do not defend; document their specific concerns.
  Week 2: Security requirements workshop — they co-author the requirements.
  Week 3: Vendor security certification review session.
  Week 4: Joint sign-off on security acceptance criteria.
Evidence of success: written confirmation of participation in Week 4 sign-off.
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Neutral to Supportive — Operations Manager on an efficiency project.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Strategy: demonstrate personal benefit; ask for their input.
Activities:
  - Invite to pilot design session (their domain).
  - Quantify efficiency gains in their team's KPIs, not generic metrics.
  - Ask for their endorsement on the pilot scope document.
Evidence of success: Manager signs pilot scope document or publicly references the benefit.
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Supportive to Leading — Sales Director at product launch.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Strategy: give visible role; share strategic information; public recognition.
Activities:
  - Assign speaking role at launch event.
  - Include in weekly strategy sessions (information access signals trust).
  - Feature in internal success story communication.
Evidence of success: Director proactively recruits other supporters without being asked.
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Warning Signals">
    <list>
      <item>Declining meeting attendance — disengaging; trigger direct outreach within 48 hours</item>
      <item>Sending a delegate — reducing personal priority; understand the cause before escalating</item>
      <item>Negative public comments — active resistance signal; require private conversation, not email</item>
      <item>Going to executives — escalating concern; address the underlying issue immediately</item>
      <item>Silent in meetings — withholding; follow up 1:1 before the next group session</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Treating all stakeholders the same — identical email cadence, identical information level.</description>
    <reason>Stakeholders at different levels and with different power need different content, channel, and frequency. One-size comms accelerates disengagement.</reason>
  </antipattern>
  <antipattern>
    <description>Assuming that support earned once is permanent.</description>
    <reason>Engagement decays under competing priorities, project delays, or broken commitments. Leading stakeholders who feel ignored revert to Neutral within weeks.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
