<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-engagement-plan" title="Engagement Plan and Drift Detection">
  <summary>Assessment matrix structure, cadence rules per power/interest quadrant, and drift detection to prevent silent disengagement.</summary>

  <section title="Assessment Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build the Engagement Assessment Matrix with columns: Stakeholder, Power (H/M/L), Interest (H/M/L), Current Level, Desired Level, Gap (+/-), and Next Activity.</statement>
      <rationale>The matrix makes engagement gaps visible in one view and drives prioritisation — high power + high gap = highest risk to the project.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Sample assessment matrix rows.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Stakeholder    | Power | Interest | Current   | Desired   | Gap | Next Activity         |
|----------------|-------|----------|-----------|-----------|-----|-----------------------|
| CEO            | H     | M        | Neutral   | Supportive | +1  | Demo at Board meeting |
| IT Director    | H     | H        | Resistant | Neutral    | +1  | 1:1 concern session   |
| End Users      | L     | H        | Unaware   | Supportive | +2  | Training webinar      |
| Project Sponsor| H     | H        | Supportive| Leading    | +1  | Strategy co-author    |
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Cadence by Quadrant">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply contact cadence by power/interest quadrant: Manage Closely (H/H) weekly; Keep Satisfied (H/L) bi-weekly; Keep Informed (L/H) weekly broadcast; Monitor (L/L) monthly summary.</statement>
      <rationale>Over-communicating to low-interest stakeholders wastes time and trains them to ignore messages. Under-communicating to high-power stakeholders allows silent resistance to grow.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Drift Detection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag a stakeholder as drifting when the last recorded interaction exceeds the cadence threshold for their quadrant with no recorded blocker reason.</statement>
      <rationale>Drift is invisible without a system. A stakeholder who was Supportive three months ago may now be Neutral — and will be classified as Supportive in the risk register until someone checks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/engagement-drift.py">Python drift detector by quadrant threshold</reference>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Writing an Engagement Plan that is never executed — no rituals, no cadence calendar.</description>
    <reason>A plan without execution triggers decays to a document nobody reads. Rituals (calendar invites, recurring 1:1 agenda items) are the mechanism that makes the plan live.</reason>
  </antipattern>
  <antipattern>
    <description>Letting agents classify stakeholder levels from email tone alone.</description>
    <reason>Polite-tone bias causes systematic over-rating. Require behavioural evidence: attendance, decisions, public statements, response latency.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <reference path="templates/engagement-plan.md">Full engagement plan template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/meeting-prep.md">Single-stakeholder meeting prep brief</reference>
</text>
