<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spec-structure">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd-planning</domain>
    <summary>Full specification structure v2.0 for complex features: problem statement, personas, stories, FR/NFR/AC, out-of-scope, and quality gates for completeness, clarity, consistency, context.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>sdd</tag>
      <tag>specification</tag>
      <tag>structure</tag>
      <tag>quality-gates</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Specification Structure</title>
    <summary>Full spec structure v2.0 for features with 3+ user personas or 8+ functional requirements. The spec answers WHAT and WHY — never HOW. Mandatory sections: Overview, Problem Statement, User Personas, User Stories, Functional Requirements (FR-X with SMART criteria and MoSCoW priority), Non-Functional Requirements, Acceptance Criteria (Given-When-Then), Out of Scope, Assumptions, Dependencies. Typical size: 500–1200 tokens.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Incomplete or ambiguous requirements cause the largest rework in the SDD lifecycle. A structured spec with full FR/AC traceability enables multi-agent executors to verify coverage mechanically (every FR traces to a US, every AC traces to an FR). The two-pass writing process (backbone first, then body) prevents agents from conflating requirements discovery with requirements writing, which produces better-scoped documents.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Features with 3+ user personas or 8+ functional requirements</item>
        <item>Features requiring formal stakeholder sign-off where completeness is auditable</item>
        <item>Complex integrations where NFRs (performance, security, scalability) must be contracted before design begins</item>
        <item>When the spec feeds into a multi-agent executor pipeline and full FR/AC traceability is required</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>MVP features under 5 FRs — use spec-examples-basic condensed format instead</item>
        <item>Internal tooling or developer-only features where user persona sections add no value</item>
        <item>Features on a known pattern (nth CRUD endpoint) where all structural decisions are inherited</item>
        <item>When spec or design doc is still in draft; writing full spec too early wastes tokens when requirements shift</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="document-hierarchy">
      <p>The three planning documents answer different questions and must not be conflated:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Specification: WHAT and WHY — requirements, user stories, acceptance criteria</item>
        <item>Design: HOW — architecture, file structure, API contracts, AD-X decisions</item>
        <item>Implementation Plan: IN WHAT ORDER — tasks, dependencies, token estimates</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Reject any HOW language from a spec document. If an agent inserts architecture choices or file paths into a spec, move them to design.md.</statement>
        <rationale>HOW language in specs conflates requirements with solutions, blocking the design phase's ability to choose between approaches freely.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="required-sections">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>A full spec v2.0 must contain all twelve sections in order: Reference Documents, Overview, Problem Statement, User Personas, User Stories, Functional Requirements, Non-Functional Requirements, Acceptance Criteria, Out of Scope, Assumptions and Constraints, Dependencies, Related Features.</statement>
        <rationale>Partial specs cause design-phase debates about unstated requirements. Every missing section represents a gap that will surface during implementation at higher cost.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every NFR must have a numeric target. "Fast response" is rejected; "&lt; 500ms p95" is accepted. "Secure password storage" is rejected; "bcrypt 12 rounds" is accepted.</statement>
        <rationale>Qualitative NFRs cannot be tested and cannot be cited in design decisions. Numeric targets produce testable quality gates.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Status must be "Approved" before the design phase begins. Agents must not auto-proceed from Draft to Approved — this is a human-in-loop gate.</statement>
        <rationale>Auto-proceeding skips stakeholder alignment. A design built on a Draft spec produces waste if the spec changes during review.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="two-pass-writing-process">
      <p>Pass 1 (discovery): Load constitution.md and any related done/ specs. Generate backbone — Problem Statement, User Personas, User Stories, FR skeleton table with placeholder text. Do not write ACs or NFRs yet.</p>
      <p>Pass 2 (formalization): Fill each FR with SMART requirement text (one unambiguous SHALL statement). Add NFR table with numeric targets. Write AC for each Must-priority FR in Given-When-Then. Complete Out of Scope (at least 3 explicit exclusions). Fill Dependencies section.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run Pass 1 and Pass 2 as separate agent invocations. Do not combine them.</statement>
        <rationale>Combined passes cause agents to conflate requirements discovery with requirements writing, producing FRs that are too specific (implementation details) or too vague (missing validation rules).</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="traceability-requirements">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Traceability must be bidirectional: FR traces to US (forward), AC traces to FR (forward), and AC is validated by FR (back). Orphaned FRs and orphaned ACs are quality gate failures.</statement>
        <rationale>Bidirectional traceability enables mechanical coverage verification: for every Must-priority FR, at least one AC exists and passes, therefore all must-have requirements are satisfied.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="completeness-gate">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>All required sections must be present and non-empty. Problem Statement must have all five fields (Who, Problem, Impact, Solution, Success Metric). FR table must have ID, Requirement, Traces To, and Priority for every row. AC must have Given, When, Then for every scenario.</statement>
        <rationale>Missing sections are not optional — each carries information the design phase requires. An empty "Open Questions" section is worse than no section: it signals the questions were asked but not answered.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Open Questions section left populated (unresolved questions still present) when Status is set to Approved.</description>
        <reason>Unresolved questions are blocker items, not optional notes. They must be resolved before design can begin.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="clarity-gate">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Reject any requirement containing these ambiguous words: good, fast, easy, appropriate, reasonable, support, handle, manage, modern, user-friendly. Replace with measurable criteria.</statement>
        <rationale>Ambiguous requirements produce ambiguous ACs, which produce untestable code. Each ambiguous word is a decision deferred to the developer or agent, who may choose incorrectly.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Each requirement must have exactly one interpretation. If two team members would implement the same FR differently, the FR is too ambiguous and must be rewritten.</statement>
        <rationale>Multiple interpretations mean the spec is not a contract. A spec that is not a contract provides no value over informal discussion.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="consistency-gate">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every FR-ID must be unique within the spec. Every AC must reference a real FR-ID. Every US must have at least one Must-priority FR. MoSCoW priorities must be assigned consistently — not all Must.</statement>
        <rationale>Duplicate IDs and broken references cause executor agents to silently skip or mis-map requirements. All-Must priority is a sign of prioritization debt that will cause scope overrun.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="context-gate">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The spec must reference constitution.md in the Reference Documents table. Related features in done/ must be identified and linked. Out of Scope must have at least 3 explicit exclusions with a timeline (Phase 2, Never, Future).</statement>
        <rationale>Without constitution reference, agents may choose patterns that contradict project standards. Without related feature links, agents may duplicate existing implementations.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="common-quality-failures">
      <antipattern>
        <description>NFRs stated as "The system should be fast and scalable."</description>
        <reason>No numeric target. Untestable. Cannot drive design decisions. Replace with "&lt; 500ms p95" and "10k concurrent users".</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Recommended Skills section left stale from template without being updated after design choices are made.</description>
        <reason>Stale skill references route agents to wrong methodologies. Update after design.md is written.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Related Features table left empty when features/done/ contains clearly related work.</description>
        <reason>Agents will duplicate existing implementations rather than reusing patterns from completed work.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-integration-workflow">
      <p>The spec-structure process runs in two agent passes. Pass 1: load constitution and any related done/ specs, then generate the backbone — Problem Statement, User Personas, User Stories, and a skeleton FR table with placeholder text. Pass 2: fill each FR with SMART detail, write NFRs, write full AC in Given-When-Then, and complete Out of Scope and Dependencies. This separation prevents agents from conflating requirements discovery with requirement writing.</p>
      <p>After both passes, a dedicated review agent checks the quality gate checklist (Completeness, Clarity, Consistency, Context) and returns a structured gap report.</p>
      <section name="recommended-subagents">
        <list>
          <item>General Claude subagent (Opus) — Pass 1 (persona/story/FR discovery from fuzzy brief)</item>
          <item>General Claude subagent (Sonnet) — Pass 2 (SMART FR writing, AC formalization, NFR specification)</item>
          <item>General Claude subagent (Haiku) — quality gate checklist validation (structured output task)</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="prompt-patterns">
        <example type="good" title="Pass 1 — Spec backbone">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Read constitution.md and brief: <brief text>.
Output: Problem Statement, 2-3 User Personas, 3-5 User Stories with MoSCoW priority,
FR skeleton table (ID, Requirement placeholder, Traces To, Priority).
Do not write ACs or NFRs yet.]]></code>
        </example>
        <example type="good" title="Pass 2 — Spec body">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Given this spec backbone, fill:
1. Each FR-X with SMART requirement text (one unambiguous SHALL statement).
2. NFR table: performance (<500ms p95), security (relevant controls), scalability targets.
3. AC for each Must-priority FR in Given/When/Then format.
4. Out of Scope: at least 3 explicit exclusions.
5. Dependencies: internal features + external services.]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section name="cli-tools">
        <list>
          <item>vale — Lint requirement text for ambiguous words ("easy", "fast", "appropriate"). Docs: https://vale.sh</item>
          <item>markdownlint — Enforce section hierarchy and table structure in spec.md. Install: npm i -g markdownlint-cli</item>
          <item>pandoc — Export spec.md to PDF/DOCX for stakeholder sign-off. Install: apt install pandoc</item>
          <item>reqview — Requirements traceability matrix tool; imports markdown FRs. Docs: https://www.reqview.com</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="services-and-apps">
        <list>
          <item>GitHub PR (SaaS, Agent-friendly) — Full spec as PR body; ACs become PR checklist. gh CLI.</item>
          <item>Confluence (SaaS, Partial) — Enterprise stakeholder review; page hierarchy maps to spec sections. REST API.</item>
          <item>Jira (SaaS, Partial) — FR-X → Stories; NFR-X → Constraints; AC → acceptance criteria field. REST API.</item>
          <item>Notion (SaaS, Partial) — Stakeholder visibility; REST API for programmatic creation. Database.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>The spec v2.0 quality gate has four dimensions (Completeness, Clarity, Consistency, Context) — run all four as a structured review, not a quick skim</item>
        <item>Every NFR must have a numeric target ("&lt; 500ms p95", "10k concurrent users") — qualitative NFRs like "fast response" are rejected at quality gate</item>
        <item>"Open Questions" section should gate the spec from Approved status — unresolved questions are blocker items, not optional notes</item>
        <item>Traceability must be bidirectional: FR → US (forward) and US → AC (forward trace) + AC → FR (back trace validation)</item>
        <item>Recommended Skills section should reference the actual faion skill IDs, not generic names</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Agents conflate spec sections with design sections under context pressure — explicit rejection of HOW language in the spec prompt is necessary</item>
        <item>NFR sections generated without numeric targets will cause design-phase debates; enforce numeric targets in the prompt</item>
        <item>The "Related Features" table is often left empty even when feature dependencies exist — always prompt the agent to search done/ specs for related work</item>
        <item>Full spec v2.0 at 800–1200 tokens is safe to include in executor context, but agents may truncate it; provide only the relevant FR and AC sections per task</item>
        <item>Human approval gate (Status: Draft → Approved) must be enforced before design begins; agents that auto-proceed skip stakeholder alignment</item>
        <item>The "Recommended Skills &amp; Methodologies" section at the bottom is frequently stale — agents generate it once and never update it as design choices are made</item>
        <item>"Open Questions" section is a placeholder that teams skip; ambiguities surface later in design and cause rework</item>
        <item>Full spec v2.0 can reach 500–1200 tokens; in context-constrained executor runs, agents may not load the full spec and miss requirements</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/72089.html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scaledagileframework.com/features-and-capabilities/"/>
      <link href="https://cucumber.io/docs/gherkin/reference/"/>
      <link href="https://www.reqview.com/doc/traceability-matrix.html"/>
      <link href="https://vale.sh"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
