<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="terraform-modules-composition Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for terraform-modules-composition. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Flat composition MUST wire module outputs to module inputs explicitly. MUST NOT use data sources to look up resources created by sibling modules in the same root — pass outputs as inputs instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Data source lookups of sibling resources create implicit ordering dependencies that Terraform's dependency graph cannot always resolve, leading to intermittent plan failures on fresh stacks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hierarchical modules MUST expose only the inputs and outputs that callers actually need. Internal wiring between child modules MUST remain private — do not propagate every internal output to the parent interface.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Leaking internal outputs forces callers to understand the implementation. A clean interface lets the stack refactor its internals without breaking callers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use for_each over count when the collection is a named map of objects. MUST NOT use count on module blocks where elements may be inserted or removed from the middle of a list — this causes unnecessary resource destruction and recreation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">With count, removing the second of five items renumbers items 3, 4, 5 to 2, 3, 4. Terraform plans destruction and recreation of three resources. With for_each and a map, only the removed key's resources are destroyed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Common tags (Project, Environment, ManagedBy, Owner, CostCenter) MUST be defined once as a local value and merged into resource tags using merge(). MUST NOT copy the same tags map to every resource block.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A tag key rename requires touching every resource block when tags are duplicated. A single local change propagates everywhere.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
