<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="data-driven-requirements Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for data-driven-requirements. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every requirement must trace back to a business question, then to data sources, then to analysis findings before a requirement statement is written. The sequence is: Business Question → Data Collection → Analysis → Insight → Requirement → Success Metrics.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Requirements written before data analysis capture stakeholder opinion, not evidence. The evidence-based process delays requirement writing until after the analysis phase, flipping the order from traditional waterfall.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define success metrics — with baseline values and measurement methods — before development starts, not after. Lock metric definitions and baseline queries in the requirement document.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Post-implementation metric definition enables Goodhart's Law: when teams define metrics after knowing the result, definitions drift to make the number land.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prioritize requirements using four metric types in combination: usage data (page views, feature adoption) for high-use feature improvements; performance data (error rates, load times) for bottleneck resolution; business metrics (conversion, revenue) for revenue-impacting features; customer feedback (NPS, support tickets) for high-volume pain points.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-metric prioritization is gameable; combining four independent signal types produces a prioritization that is robust to individual metric drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Measure AI/ML feature impact across four areas: operational efficiency (cycle time, throughput, error rate, rework percentage), experience and growth (CSAT/NPS, conversion rate, retention), financial (cost-to-serve, gross margin, working capital), and risk and compliance (policy violations avoided, audit hours saved).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-area measurement (e.g., only efficiency) misses the full value picture; AI features often have their largest impact in a different area than the one that motivated the investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For each metric, define the measurement method, data source, baseline value, and target value before development — never after. Use the same query and the same data source for baseline and post-implementation measurement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Changing data sources or query definitions between baseline and measurement invalidates variance calculations; the numerator and denominator must be comparable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
