<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Data-Driven Requirements Engineering Framework">
  <summary>Evidence-based process from business question to requirement, and BA analytics competencies.</summary>

  <section title="Evidence-Based Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every requirement must trace back to a business question, then to data sources, then to analysis findings before a requirement statement is written. The sequence is: Business Question → Data Collection → Analysis → Insight → Requirement → Success Metrics.</statement>
      <rationale>Requirements written before data analysis capture stakeholder opinion, not evidence. 95% of enterprise AI projects fail without a solid data strategy, and the same pattern applies to feature requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define success metrics — with baseline values and measurement methods — before development starts, not after. Lock metric definitions and baseline queries in the requirement document.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-implementation metric definition enables Goodhart's Law: when teams define metrics after knowing the result, definitions drift to make the number land.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Analytics Competencies for BAs">
    <p>Required competencies: statistical analysis (validate assumptions with data), data visualization (communicate insights), SQL/BI tools (query business data), A/B testing (validate solution options), predictive analytics (forecast feature impact).</p>
    <p>Self-service tools by category: BI dashboards (Tableau, Power BI) for KPI monitoring; SQL interfaces (Mode, Looker) for custom queries; no-code analytics (Dataiku, Alteryx) for automated workflows; NLP query (ThoughtSpot) for natural language exploration.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Analytics-Informed Prioritization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize requirements using four metric types in combination: usage data (page views, feature adoption) for high-use feature improvements; performance data (error rates, load times) for bottleneck resolution; business metrics (conversion, revenue) for revenue-impacting features; customer feedback (NPS, support tickets) for high-volume pain points.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-metric prioritization is gameable; combining four independent signal types produces a prioritization that is robust to individual metric drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/data-driven-req.md">Data-driven requirement template with evidence and success metrics</reference>
</text>
