<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-analytics-prioritization" title="Analytics Prioritization and ROI Measurement">
  <summary>Metric types for data-driven prioritization and the AI/ML ROI measurement framework across four impact areas.</summary>

  <section title="Prioritization Metric Types">
    <list>
      <item>Usage data (page views, feature adoption rate, session depth): prioritize improvements to high-use features; deprioritize features nobody uses even if stakeholders believe they are important</item>
      <item>Performance data (error rates, latency p95, funnel drop-off rates): address bottlenecks that degrade user experience for the largest user segments</item>
      <item>Business metrics (conversion rate, revenue per user, churn rate): focus on features with direct revenue impact measurable within the evaluation window</item>
      <item>Customer feedback (NPS verbatims, support ticket volume by category, user interviews): address the pain points mentioned most frequently across all feedback channels</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="AI/ML ROI Measurement Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure AI/ML feature impact across four areas: operational efficiency (cycle time, throughput, error rate, rework percentage), experience and growth (CSAT/NPS, conversion rate, retention), financial (cost-to-serve, gross margin, working capital), and risk and compliance (policy violations avoided, audit hours saved).</statement>
      <rationale>Single-area measurement (e.g., only efficiency) misses the full value picture; AI features often have their largest impact in a different area than the one that motivated the investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For each metric, define the measurement method, data source, baseline value, and target value before development — never after. Use the same query and the same data source for baseline and post-implementation measurement.</statement>
      <rationale>Changing data sources or query definitions between baseline and measurement invalidates variance calculations; the numerator and denominator must be comparable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Industry Data Points">
    <p>91.9% of organizations report measurable value from data and analytics investments. 65% have adopted or are investigating AI for analytics. Data-driven companies are 23x more likely to acquire customers. 95% of enterprise AI projects fail without a solid data strategy underpinning requirements.</p>
  </section>
</text>
