<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="infra" count="293">
  <methodology slug="action-item-stale-aging" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/action-item-stale-aging">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for action item stale aging that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-year-end-close-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/agency-year-end-close-checklist">
    <summary>Concrete operating checklist covering agency year end close checklist — the small set of items a practitioner runs every cycle so nothing high-leverage gets skipped.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-generated-iac-review-gate" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/server-craft/ai-generated-iac-review-gate">
    <summary>A pre-merge review gate for AI-generated IaC (Dockerfile, Helm, Terraform, GHA) that runs four checks — drift, security, performance, multi-arch — and refuses to land until each clears or is consciously waived.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-terraform-review-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/ai-terraform-review-checklist">
    <summary>Ai Terraform Review Checklist: codified platform / SRE practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/AI-assisted infra review gate (Dockerfile + Helm + Terraform)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-workload-cost-attribution" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/ai-workload-cost-attribution">
    <summary>Ai Workload Cost Attribution: codified platform / SRE practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Weekly cloud cost review' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aiops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/aiops">
    <summary>AIOps applies ML and LLM-powered analysis to IT operations to automate anomaly detection, root cause analysis, and incident remediation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aiops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/aiops">
    <summary># AIOps AI-powered operations for automated incident detection, root cause analysis, and remediation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="alert-deduplication-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/alert-deduplication-playbook">
    <summary>A 6-step playbook for on-call alert dedup — noise audit, fingerprint design, page-vs-ticket routing, suppression windows, paging SLOs, and quarterly review.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="alert-noise-budget" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/alert-noise-budget">
    <summary>Per-service alert noise budget (max pages per shift, max non-actionable alerts per week) with enforcement workflow that retires or tunes any alert that exceeds it.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="argocd-gitops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/argocd-gitops">
    <summary>ArgoCD implements GitOps for Kubernetes: Git is the single source of truth for cluster state, ArgoCD continuously reconciles live state toward the desired Git state.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="argocd-gitops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/argocd-gitops">
    <summary>ArgoCD is a declarative GitOps CD tool for Kubernetes (used in approximately 60% of Kubernetes clusters per CNCF 2025).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-architecture-services" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-architecture-services">
    <summary>Production-ready patterns for AWS service selection, integration, and deployment.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-cfn-terraform-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/aws-cfn-terraform-templates">
    <summary>Production-ready CloudFormation YAML and Terraform HCL templates for common AWS infrastructure patterns: VPC networking, ECS Fargate services, serverless Lambda stacks, RDS PostgreSQL with Secrets Manager, and supporting IAM/S3/ECS configuration JSON.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-cli-compute" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/aws-cli-compute">
    <summary>Reference for AWS CLI commands covering EC2 instance lifecycle, S3 object and bucket management, Lambda function management and invocation, and shared credential configuration patterns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-cli-containers-iac" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/aws-cli-containers-iac">
    <summary>Reference for AWS CLI commands covering RDS and Aurora databases, ECS/EKS/ECR container services, CloudFormation stack management, IAM user/role/policy operations, CloudWatch logs and alarms, and common deployment patterns including blue-green and disaster recovery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-cli-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-cli-setup">
    <summary>Install AWS CLI v2 on Linux, configure named profiles and credential files, and manage authentication via environment variables for multi-account, multi-region workflows.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-cost-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-cost-optimization">
    <summary>AWS cost optimization covers four levers: compute (Reserved Instances, Savings Plans, Spot), storage (S3 tiering, lifecycle policies, EBS cleanup), networking (VPC endpoints, CloudFront, NAT consolidation), and right-sizing (matching instance type to actual utilization).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-ec2-ecs" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-ec2-ecs">
    <summary>AWS compute services: EC2 instances, ECS Fargate, task definitions, and services.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-ec2-provisioning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-ec2-provisioning">
    <summary>Provision EC2 instances with IMDSv2 enforced, encrypted gp3 EBS volumes, and SSM Session Manager (no SSH keys).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-iam-practical-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-iam-practical-patterns">
    <summary>Write least-privilege IAM policies scoped to specific resource ARNs with conditions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-iam-security-foundations" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-iam-security-foundations">
    <summary>AWS security foundations span identity (IAM Identity Center, IRSA, least privilege), encryption (KMS at rest, TLS in transit, Secrets Manager), network controls (security groups, NACLs, PrivateLink, WAF), and detection (GuardDuty, Security Hub, Config).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-infra-llm-prompts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/aws-infra-llm-prompts">
    <summary>Parameterized LLM prompt templates for AWS infrastructure design conversations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-infra-prompt-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-infra-prompt-library">
    <summary>Parameterized prompt templates for generating, auditing, troubleshooting, and documenting AWS infrastructure.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-lambda" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-lambda">
    <summary>Serverless function design, cold start optimization, layer management, and event source configuration for AWS Lambda.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-monitoring-observability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-monitoring-observability">
    <summary>Production AWS observability uses CloudWatch for metrics, logs, and alarms; X-Ray for distributed tracing; an org-level CloudTrail with KMS encryption and log file validation for API auditing; and AWS Config for resource configuration tracking and compliance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-multi-account-landing-zone" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-multi-account-landing-zone">
    <summary>A landing zone is the foundational multi-account AWS environment: an Organizations structure, OU hierarchy, Control Tower (or Landing Zone Accelerator), service control policies, centralized logging, and IAM Identity Center integration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-networking" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-networking">
    <summary>VPC architecture, subnet segmentation, security groups, NACLs, Transit Gateway, and VPC endpoints for AWS.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-s3-storage" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-s3-storage">
    <summary>S3 bucket security, encryption, lifecycle policies, and cross-region replication best practices.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-vpc-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-vpc-design">
    <summary>A production VPC uses a three-tier subnet layout (public/private/database) across a minimum of 3 Availability Zones, per-AZ NAT Gateways for high availability, VPC endpoints for cost-free private AWS service access, and VPC Flow Logs to S3 for security auditing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-vpc-three-tier" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-vpc-three-tier">
    <summary>Build a production three-tier VPC: 9 subnets (3 AZs x public/private/database), per-AZ NAT gateways, free S3 gateway endpoint, interface endpoints for ECR and Secrets Manager, an internet-facing Application Load Balancer with HTTPS, VPC Flow Logs, and Transit Gateway attachment for multi-VPC connectivity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-well-architected-checklists" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/aws-well-architected-checklists">
    <summary>Actionable checklists for all six AWS Well-Architected pillars (Operational Excellence, Security, Reliability, Performance Efficiency, Cost Optimization, Sustainability) plus new-account setup baseline and pre-production readiness gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-well-architected-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/aws-well-architected-framework">
    <summary>The AWS Well-Architected Framework defines 6 pillars (Operational Excellence, Security, Reliability, Performance Efficiency, Cost Optimization, Sustainability) for evaluating production workloads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-app-gateway-waf" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/azure-app-gateway-waf">
    <summary>Application Gateway v2 is a regional Layer 7 load balancer with integrated WAF (Web Application Firewall).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/azure-architecture">
    <summary>Azure enterprise architecture is organized around the Well-Architected Framework (five pillars: Reliability, Security, Cost Optimization, Operational Excellence, Performance Efficiency) and Landing Zones (eight design areas).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-compute" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/azure-compute">
    <summary>Azure compute covers five service tiers — VMs, VMSS (Flexible mode only for new workloads), AKS, Container Apps (serverless, KEDA-based), and App Service.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-front-door" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/azure-front-door">
    <summary>Azure Front Door Premium is a global Layer 7 load balancer, CDN, and WAF service.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-nat-gateway" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/azure-nat-gateway">
    <summary>NAT Gateway provides managed, zone-redundant outbound internet connectivity for private subnets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-nsg-rules" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/azure-nsg-rules">
    <summary>NSGs perform stateful packet inspection using a 5-tuple (source IP, source port, destination IP, destination port, protocol).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-private-link" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/azure-private-link">
    <summary>Private Endpoints inject a NIC with a private IP from your VNet into an Azure PaaS service (Storage, Key Vault, SQL, PostgreSQL, ACR, App Service, etc.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-vnet-hub-spoke" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/azure-vnet-hub-spoke">
    <summary>Foundation of Azure networking: Virtual Network (VNet) provides network isolation with subnets, peering, and delegations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/backup-basics">
    <summary># Backup Basics ## Overview Backup strategies ensure data protection, business continuity, and disaster recovery capabilities.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-cloud-aws" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/backup-cloud-aws">
    <summary>Implement AWS-native backup using AWS Backup service (vaults, plans, cross-region copy rules) for managed resources (RDS, DynamoDB, EBS, EFS), and S3 lifecycle policies for object storage tiering.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-database-mysql-mongo" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/backup-database-mysql-mongo">
    <summary>Implement MySQL/MariaDB backups with mysqldump (logical, portable) and Percona XtraBackup (hot physical, no locking for InnoDB).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-database-postgres" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/backup-database-postgres">
    <summary>Implement PostgreSQL backups using pg_dump for logical snapshots, pg_basebackup for PITR base backups, and pgBackRest for enterprise-grade parallel backup with WAL archiving.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-filesystem-restic" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/backup-filesystem-restic">
    <summary>Implement encrypted, deduplicated filesystem backups using Restic (modern, cloud-native S3/B2/REST backends) or BorgBackup (compression-focused, SSH-based).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-kubernetes-velero" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/backup-kubernetes-velero">
    <summary>Implement Kubernetes cluster backup using Velero with CSI volume snapshots and Kopia as the file system backup (FSB) data mover.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-strategies" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/backup-strategies">
    <summary>Modern backup strategy follows the 3-2-1-1-0 rule: 3 copies, 2 media types, 1 offsite, 1 immutable/air-gapped, 0 verified recovery errors.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-verification-dr" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/backup-verification-dr">
    <summary>Implement automated backup verification (restore-to-temp-target + integrity probe), Prometheus alerting rules for backup age, size anomalies, and duration spikes, and DR runbooks with quarterly full DR drills.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="banking-core-data-residency-rules" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/banking-core-data-residency-rules">
    <summary>Banking Core Data Residency Rules: codified platform / SRE practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/FinTech / HIPAA compliance audit prep (4 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="blameless-retro-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/blameless-retro-template">
    <summary>Human facilitation template for a post-incident blameless retrospective: agenda, time-boxing, language rules, and action-item capture that complements automated postmortem draft generation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="burn-rate-multi-window-alerting" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/burn-rate-multi-window-alerting">
    <summary>Burn Rate Multi Window Alerting: codified platform / SRE practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Design SLOs + error budgets before first deploy' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="canary-gono-go-threshold-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/canary-gono-go-threshold-template">
    <summary>Canary Gono Go Threshold Template: codified platform / SRE practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Canary deploy promote/rollback decision' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="capacity-planning-at-design-time" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/capacity-planning-at-design-time">
    <summary>Capacity Planning at Design Time: codified platform / SRE practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Container vs serverless vs VM decision tree at architecture time' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="capacity-safety-floor-policy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/capacity-safety-floor-policy">
    <summary>Capacity Safety Floor Policy: codified platform / SRE practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Capacity headroom check' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cardinality-and-cost-guardrails" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cardinality-and-cost-guardrails">
    <summary>Cardinality and Cost Guardrails: codified platform / SRE practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Unified observability stack (logs + metrics + traces) in one weekend' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chaos-engineering-practice-for-infra" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/chaos-engineering-practice-for-infra">
    <summary>Infra game-days: Litmus/Chaos Mesh experiment design, steady-state hypothesis, blast-radius containment, learning capture.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cicd-cert-rotation-pipeline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/cicd-cert-rotation-pipeline">
    <summary>Manage certificate rotation through declarative IaC: cert-manager CRDs for Kubernetes, Terraform for cloud-managed certificates (AWS ACM, GCP Certificate Manager), and Docker Compose Traefik for containerised stacks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cicd-mtls-deployment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/cicd-mtls-deployment">
    <summary>Configure mutual TLS for service-to-service authentication: nginx ssl_client_certificate verification, internal CA setup with step-ca or Vault PKI, client certificate issuance and rotation, and mTLS testing via curl.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cicd-tls-renewal-automation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/cicd-tls-renewal-automation">
    <summary>Automate certificate renewal end-to-end: ACME client selection, systemd timer or cron scheduling, post-renew reload hooks, and short-lived cert policy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cicd-tls-validation-gate" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/cicd-tls-validation-gate">
    <summary>Enforce TLS quality as a pipeline gate: run testssl.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-autoscaling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/cloud-run-autoscaling">
    <summary>Cloud Run scales from 0 to 1000+ instances based on concurrent requests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-deployment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/cloud-run-deployment">
    <summary>Cloud Run services accept HTTP requests and scale automatically.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-jobs" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/cloud-run-jobs">
    <summary>Cloud Run Jobs run containers to completion rather than serving HTTP requests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-monitoring" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/cloud-run-monitoring">
    <summary>Cloud Run exports metrics to Cloud Monitoring automatically (request count, latency, instance count, CPU/memory utilization).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-traffic-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/cloud-run-traffic-management">
    <summary>Cloud Run supports revision-based traffic splitting: deploy a new revision without traffic, test it via a tagged URL, then gradually shift traffic using update-traffic commands.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-vpc-access" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/cloud-run-vpc-access">
    <summary>Cloud Run services connect to private VPC resources via Direct VPC egress (preferred) or Serverless VPC Access connectors.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="compute-substrate-decision-tree" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/compute-substrate-decision-tree">
    <summary>Compute Substrate Decision Tree: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Container vs serverless vs VM decision tree at architecture time' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contractor-agreement-template-us-uk-eu" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/contractor-agreement-template-us-uk-eu">
    <summary>Jurisdiction-aware contractor agreement template (US, UK, EU variants) with IP assignment, classification tests, payment terms, and termination — for micro-agencies hiring across the three core markets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-anomaly-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cost-anomaly-runbook">
    <summary>Cost Anomaly Runbook: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Weekly cloud cost review' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-model-spreadsheet-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cost-model-spreadsheet-template">
    <summary>Canonical cloud cost-model spreadsheet template (compute, storage, egress, NAT, observability, backup) with per-cloud variants — replaces re-building the same sheet from scratch for every architecture proposal.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-pr-gate-recipe" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cost-pr-gate-recipe">
    <summary>Cost Pr Gate Recipe: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Cost optimization sweep (4 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cronjob-overrun-monitoring" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cronjob-overrun-monitoring">
    <summary>Cronjob Overrun Monitoring: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Cron / scheduled-job audit (monthly)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cutover-rollback-runbook-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cutover-rollback-runbook-template">
    <summary>Cutover Rollback Runbook Template: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/Legacy-to-modern migration project (~3 months)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cve-exception-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cve-exception-template">
    <summary>Cve Exception Template: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Vulnerability scan + patch (weekly)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="deprecated-api-sweeper-recipe" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/deprecated-api-sweeper-recipe">
    <summary>Deprecated Api Sweeper Recipe delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Kubernetes major-version upgrade (3 weeks)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Detecting deprecated k8s APIs in chart libraries + live clusters is a chore with k</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-aws-monitoring-dr" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-aws-monitoring-dr">
    <summary>Production AWS workloads require CloudWatch dashboards per tier, metric alarms with SNS notifications, X-Ray distributed tracing across Lambda and API Gateway, and a tested DR strategy matched to business RTO/RPO.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-aws-serverless-api" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-aws-serverless-api">
    <summary>The serverless API pattern uses API Gateway HTTP API as the entry point, Lambda on arm64 (Graviton) for compute, DynamoDB (single-table, on-demand) for state, EventBridge for event routing, SQS with DLQ for async buffering, and Step Functions for multi-step orchestration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-aws-service-selection" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-aws-service-selection">
    <summary>Choosing the right AWS service avoids rework.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-aws-terraform-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-aws-terraform-cicd">
    <summary>Terraform projects for AWS follow a per-environment directory layout under infrastructure/environments/.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-aws-three-tier" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-aws-three-tier">
    <summary>The three-tier pattern places the Application Load Balancer in public subnets, application workloads (ECS Fargate or EKS) in private subnets, and Aurora Serverless v2 in isolated database subnets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-elk-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-elk-architecture">
    <summary>The ELK Stack (Elasticsearch, Logstash, Kibana) and its variants (EFK with Fluentd, Elastic Stack with Beats) provide centralized log management, search, and visualization.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-elk-beats-collection" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-elk-beats-collection">
    <summary>Filebeat is a lightweight log shipper deployed as an agent on each host or as a Kubernetes DaemonSet.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-elk-index-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-elk-index-management">
    <summary>Index templates define field mappings and settings for all matching indices before they are created.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-elk-logstash-pipeline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-elk-logstash-pipeline">
    <summary>Logstash processes log streams through input → filter → output pipelines.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-elk-queries-alerting" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-elk-queries-alerting">
    <summary>Kibana Query Language (KQL) enables fast structured filtering in Kibana dashboards.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-algorithms" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-lb-algorithms">
    <summary>Choosing the correct load balancer type and algorithm is the first architectural decision.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-haproxy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-lb-haproxy">
    <summary>HAProxy provides battle-tested L4/L7 load balancing with precise control over timeouts, health checks, ACL routing, and sticky sessions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-health-checks" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-lb-health-checks">
    <summary>Health checks allow the load balancer to remove unhealthy backends from rotation automatically.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-high-availability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-lb-high-availability">
    <summary>A load balancer is itself a single point of failure unless deployed in an HA topology.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-kubernetes" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-lb-kubernetes">
    <summary>Kubernetes provides a layered load balancing model: Service (kube-proxy, L4) distributes traffic across pods; Ingress (Nginx, Traefik, AWS ALB Controller) handles L7 routing, TLS, and host/path rules.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-ssl-tls" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-lb-ssl-tls">
    <summary>The load balancer can terminate TLS (decrypt and forward HTTP to backends), re-encrypt (decrypt and re-encrypt to backends), or pass through (forward encrypted traffic unchanged).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-platform-backstage" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-platform-backstage">
    <summary>Backstage is the CNCF-donated open-source developer portal (originally from Spotify) that combines a service catalog, TechDocs, and a golden path scaffolder (Software Templates) in one plugin-extensible platform.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-platform-crossplane" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-platform-crossplane">
    <summary>Crossplane extends Kubernetes with Composite Resource Definitions (XRDs) so platform teams define infrastructure abstractions (Database, Cache, Network) as custom CRDs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-platform-golden-paths" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-platform-golden-paths">
    <summary>Golden paths are pre-built, opinionated templates for the most common developer tasks (new service, database provisioning, API gateway).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-platform-idp-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-platform-idp-core">
    <summary>An IDP is a self-service layer between developers and infrastructure.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-platform-policy-finops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/devops-platform-policy-finops">
    <summary>Platform governance covers two complementary concerns: policy enforcement (preventing non-compliant workloads from being deployed via OPA/Gatekeeper admission control) and FinOps (providing cost visibility per team/service, pre-deployment cost estimation, and budget controls).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/docker">
    <summary>Docker builds images in layers; each instruction creates a cached layer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/docker">
    <summary>Production-Grade Container Development and Deployment (2025-2026).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-compose" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/devops-engineer/docker-compose">
    <summary>Docker Compose V2 (`docker compose`) declaratively defines multi-container applications in YAML.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-compose" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/infrastructure-engineer/docker-compose">
    <summary>Production-grade Docker Compose patterns for multi-container infrastructure stacks: no version: field, named volumes, custom networks with internal: true for database tiers, health checks on every service with depends_on: condition: service_healthy, resource limits via deploy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-compose" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/cicd-engineer/docker-compose">
    <summary>Docker Compose patterns for CI/CD pipelines: compose.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-image-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/docker-image-optimization">
    <summary>Reduce production Docker image size 70-90% and accelerate CI builds by applying multi-stage builds, strategic layer ordering, cache mounts,.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-language-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/docker-language-templates">
    <summary>Copy-paste Dockerfile and Docker Compose templates for the most common language and framework combinations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-llm-prompts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/docker-llm-prompts">
    <summary>Parameterized LLM prompt templates for the full range of Docker tasks: generating production Dockerfiles, optimizing existing ones, auditing for security, debugging container failures, integrating CI/CD scanning, and designing multi-container architectures.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/docker-optimization">
    <summary># Docker Optimization **Image size reduction, build caching, multi-stage builds, and security hardening** ## Overview Docker image optimization focuses on four key areas: 1.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-security-hardening" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/docker-security-hardening">
    <summary>Apply layered security to Docker containers: run as non-root users, drop Linux capabilities, enforce read-only filesystems, manage secrets via Docker Secrets or Vault, sign images, and scan for vulnerabilities with Trivy or Docker Scout in every CI pipeline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dora-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/dora-metrics">
    <summary>Five DORA metrics measure software delivery performance: Deployment Frequency, Lead Time for Changes, Change Failure Rate, Time to Restore Service (MTTR), and Reliability (SLO compliance).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dora-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/dora-metrics">
    <summary>DORA (DevOps Research and Assessment) metrics are four research-validated KPIs that measure software delivery performance: Deployment Frequency, Lead Time for Changes, Change Failure Rate, and Mean Time to Restore.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dr-drill-scenario-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/dr-drill-scenario-library">
    <summary>Dr Drill Scenario Library delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Disaster-recovery drill + plan refresh (4 weeks)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: A reusable catalogue of DR scenarios (region loss, db corruption, secret-store l</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dr-drill-script-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/dr-drill-script-template">
    <summary>Dr Drill Script Template delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Disaster-recovery plan + live drill' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: backup-verification-dr methodology exists but does not script a full live drill (declaration -</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="drift-classification-taxonomy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/drift-classification-taxonomy">
    <summary>Drift Classification Taxonomy delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Config drift sweep' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Drift detection tools exist; classifying drift into systemic causes (hand-edit, external automation, vendo</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="edge-and-cdn-strategy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/edge-and-cdn-strategy">
    <summary>Edge compute (Cloudflare Workers / Lambda@Edge / Fastly Compute), cache key design, origin shielding, edge auth — the strategy gcp-storage-cdn is missing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="egress-cost-hidden-budget-guide" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/egress-cost-hidden-budget-guide">
    <summary>Egress Cost Hidden Budget Guide delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Capacity + cost-modelling exercise (pre-launch or scale-event)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Egress + NAT + cross-AZ costs are the #1 surprise on cloud b</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="elk-stack-logging" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/elk-stack-logging">
    <summary>The ELK Stack (Elasticsearch, Logstash, Kibana) with Beats is the industry-standard solution for centralized log management, search, and visualization.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-budget-policy-and-freeze-rules" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/error-budget-policy-and-freeze-rules">
    <summary>Error Budget Policy And Freeze Rules delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Design SLOs + error budgets before first deploy' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Once SLOs exist someone has to write the policy that converts burn int</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="eu-sovereign-llm-deployment-bundle" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/eu-sovereign-llm-deployment-bundle">
    <summary>End-to-end bundle for deploying a sovereign EU-hosted LLM stack (Ollama / vLLM, networking, governance, evals) suitable for data-residency-bound customers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="external-secrets-operator-recipe" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/external-secrets-operator-recipe">
    <summary>External Secrets Operator Recipe delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Secrets-management migration: Vault / KMS / SOPS (4 weeks)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: k8s secret injection via external-secrets / CSI is the modern p</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fast-vs-slow-burn-rule" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/fast-vs-slow-burn-rule">
    <summary>Fast Vs Slow Burn Rule delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'SLO error-budget burn review' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Multi-window multi-burn-rate alerting (Google SRE pattern) is referenced nowhere as a stand-alone metho</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fco-commitment-pricing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/fco-commitment-pricing">
    <summary>Commitment-based pricing (Reserved Instances and Savings Plans) delivers 60-75% discounts over on-demand for predictable steady-state workloads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fco-cost-allocation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/fco-cost-allocation">
    <summary>Cost allocation assigns cloud spend to the teams, services, and environments that generate it.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fco-rightsizing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/fco-rightsizing">
    <summary>Rightsizing matches instance sizes to actual workload requirements.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fco-spot-instances" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/fco-spot-instances">
    <summary>Spot instances (AWS), Preemptible VMs (GCP), and Spot VMs (Azure) provide access to unused cloud capacity at 70-90% discounts versus on-demand pricing, subject to 2-minute reclaim notices.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fco-waste-elimination" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/fco-waste-elimination">
    <summary>Cloud waste elimination targets idle and orphaned resources that generate cost with zero value: unattached EBS volumes, orphaned snapshots, stopped instances, unused Elastic IPs, and idle load balancers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-flag-rollout-runbook" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/feature-flag-rollout-runbook">
    <summary>Feature Flag Rollout Runbook delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'RFC → Production: feature delivery (3-6 weeks)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: GitOps progressive delivery exists, but the team-level runbook (who toggles, wh</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/finops">
    <summary>Cloud Financial Operations: the Inform → Optimize → Operate cycle for cloud cost management.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-agentic-workflow" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/finops-agentic-workflow">
    <summary>FinOps with agents is continuous-loop optimization: a daily billing-snapshot agent ingests cost data, a tag-auditor flags untagged resources, an idle-hunter files tickets for waste candidates, and a weekly RI/SP-advisor proposes commitment adjustments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-ai-ml-costs" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/finops-ai-ml-costs">
    <summary>AI/ML workloads present unique FinOps challenges: GPU costs run 5-10x higher than standard compute, token economics are invisible to instance-hour dashboards, and standard rightsizing heuristics (CPU utilization) are misleading for GPU workloads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-cost-visibility" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/finops-cost-visibility">
    <summary>The INFORM phase establishes the visibility foundation for all FinOps work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-devops-cost-alerts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/finops-devops-cost-alerts">
    <summary>Budget alerts at 50/75/90/100% thresholds prevent surprise overspend by notifying teams before the billing period closes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-devops-cost-commitments" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/finops-devops-cost-commitments">
    <summary>Three commitment discount mechanisms cover different workload shapes: Reserved Instances (RI) for stable instance-family workloads (up to 75% savings), Savings Plans for flexible compute baseline (up to 72%), and Spot Instances for fault-tolerant batch/ML (70-90%).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-devops-cost-kubernetes" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/finops-devops-cost-kubernetes">
    <summary>Kubernetes clusters default to uniform over-provisioned node pools with no autoscaling and no workload-aware placement — the result is 25% average CPU and 40% average memory utilization.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-devops-cost-rightsizing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/finops-devops-cost-rightsizing">
    <summary>Rightsizing reduces compute and database instance costs 15-25% by matching resource allocation to actual utilization.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-devops-cost-tagging" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/finops-devops-cost-tagging">
    <summary>Cost allocation accuracy depends entirely on tag compliance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/finops-framework">
    <summary>FinOps is a cultural practice that brings financial accountability to cloud spending through cross-functional collaboration between Engineering, Finance, and Business teams.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-governance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/finops-governance">
    <summary>The OPERATE phase makes cost efficiency self-sustaining through automated policies, budget alerts at multiple thresholds, scheduled dev/test automation, and cost gates embedded in CI/CD pipelines.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gce-autoscaling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gce-autoscaling">
    <summary>The GCE autoscaler adjusts the size of a Managed Instance Group in response to one or more scaling signals: CPU utilization, load balancing capacity, custom Cloud Monitoring metrics, time-based schedules, or ML-based predictive forecasting.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gce-instance-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gce-instance-templates">
    <summary>Instance templates are immutable, reusable VM configurations that define machine type, boot disk image, network settings, service account, labels, and startup/shutdown scripts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gce-managed-instance-groups" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gce-managed-instance-groups">
    <summary>A Managed Instance Group (MIG) maintains a set of identical VMs created from a single instance template, provides autohealing by replacing failed instances, supports rolling updates and canary deployments, and integrates with Google Cloud Load Balancing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gce-spot-vms" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gce-spot-vms">
    <summary>Spot VMs offer up to 91% discount over standard on-demand pricing but can be preempted by GCP with a 30-second warning at any time.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/gcp">
    <summary>GCP production deployments: use Autopilot mode for GKE (pay-per-pod, no node management) unless GPU workloads or privileged containers are required; use Workload Identity Federation to eliminate service account keys for all external workloads (GitHub Actions, GitLab CI, AWS); use Private Service Connect instead of VPC Peering for Google-managed service access.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-arch-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-arch-patterns">
    <summary>Production-ready GCP architectural patterns for GKE clusters, Cloud SQL, Cloud Storage with CDN, microservices on Cloud Run, and data pipelines (Dataflow + BigQuery).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-billing-cost" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-billing-cost">
    <summary>GCP billing is structured around billing accounts linked to projects, with costs attributed via resource labels.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-cloud-run-serverless" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-cloud-run-serverless">
    <summary>Cloud Run and Cloud Functions Gen2 best practices: deploy with a dedicated service account, Secret Manager secrets, VPC connector for private resource access, min-instances for production cold-start elimination, blue-green traffic splitting for safe rollouts, and Binary Authorization for image trust.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-compute-gke" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-compute-gke">
    <summary>Compute Engine and GKE best practices: Shielded VMs with OS Login (no SSH keys), regional managed instance groups with autoscaling and health checks, GKE Autopilot (default) vs hardened Standard clusters with Workload Identity, private endpoints, Dataplane V2 (Cilium), and security hardening checklists.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-gke-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/gcp-gke-architecture">
    <summary>GKE provides two cluster modes (Autopilot and Standard), multiple topology options (zonal/regional/multi-cluster), and several node pool strategies (general, spot, GPU, high-memory).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-iam-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-iam-design">
    <summary>GCP IAM controls who can do what on which resource.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-landing-zone" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/gcp-landing-zone">
    <summary>A GCP landing zone (cloud foundation) is a modular configuration enabling enterprise adoption of Google Cloud.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-llm-prompts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-llm-prompts">
    <summary>Parameterized LLM prompt templates for GCP infrastructure work: generating Terraform HCL for VPC, firewall, service accounts, Cloud Run, and GKE; security audits and IAM policy reviews; connectivity and Cloud Run troubleshooting; cost optimization and committed-use analysis; architecture documentation, runbooks, and compliance checks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-network-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/gcp-network-architecture">
    <summary>GCP networking centers on VPC design (Single, Shared, Hub-and-Spoke), IP address planning for GKE secondary ranges, Private Service Connect for private Google API access, Cloud NAT for egress, and hierarchical firewall policies for org-wide security.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-networking" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-networking">
    <summary>Comprehensive reference for Google Cloud Platform networking: VPC design, subnets, firewall rules, Cloud NAT, load balancing, and security best practices.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-networking-vpc" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-networking-vpc">
    <summary>GCP networking best practices: custom VPC with four subnet tiers (public, private, GKE, database), least-privilege firewall rules with IAP-only SSH, Cloud NAT for private outbound, global HTTPS load balancer with managed SSL, Cloud Armor WAF with OWASP rules and rate limiting, and VPC network checklist.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-org-policies" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-org-policies">
    <summary>Organization policies are mandatory guardrails applied at the org or folder level that override project-level settings.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-overview-cli" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-overview-cli">
    <summary>Google Cloud Platform infrastructure best practices (2025-2026): service catalogue, gcloud CLI setup, authentication, named configurations, CI/CD deployment patterns, disaster recovery, and cost optimization using Recommender and BigQuery billing exports.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-resource-hierarchy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-resource-hierarchy">
    <summary>GCP organizes all resources in a 4-level tree: Organization → Folder → Project → Resource.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-security-iam" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-security-iam">
    <summary>GCP security framework covering IAM least privilege with Workload Identity Federation (no service account keys), VPC Service Controls perimeters for data exfiltration prevention, CMEK encryption, and audit logging.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-storage" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-storage">
    <summary>GCP Cloud Storage is a managed object storage service for storing and accessing data on Google's infrastructure.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-storage-cdn" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/gcp-storage-cdn">
    <summary>Cloud Storage provides four storage classes (STANDARD, NEARLINE, COLDLINE, ARCHIVE) with lifecycle rules to automate class transitions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-terraform-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/gcp-terraform-templates">
    <summary>Production-ready Terraform HCL module set for GCP infrastructure (2025-2026): VPC with four subnet tiers and Cloud NAT, least-privilege firewall rules, per-workload service accounts, Cloud Run v2 service with probes, GKE Autopilot with Workload Identity, Cloud SQL PostgreSQL with private IP and PITR, and a complete example composing all modules.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gdpr-dsar-runbook-product-dev-team" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/gdpr-dsar-runbook-product-dev-team">
    <summary>Gdpr Dsar Runbook Product Dev Team — testable methodology for platform, k8s, networking, cost models. DSAR (Data Subject Access Request) execution is a recurring legal obligation with no concrete runbook in faion: data discovery query patterns, redaction rules, response packaging.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gha-caching-artifacts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gha-caching-artifacts">
    <summary>Cache dependency folders using actions/cache@v4 with lockfile-hash keys and ecosystem-specific restore-keys.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gha-deployment-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gha-deployment-patterns">
    <summary>Structure CD pipelines as staged deploy jobs (staging auto, production manual approval) backed by GitHub Environments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gha-matrix-builds" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gha-matrix-builds">
    <summary>Use GHA matrix strategy to execute jobs across multiple OS and language-version combinations in parallel.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gha-security-hardening" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gha-security-hardening">
    <summary>Pin every action reference to a 40-char SHA, not a tag.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gha-workflow-structure" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gha-workflow-structure">
    <summary>Model every workflow as a DAG of jobs using needs: before writing YAML.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="github-actions-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/github-actions-basics">
    <summary>GitHub Actions is a CI/CD platform integrated directly into GitHub repositories.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="github-actions-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/github-actions-cicd">
    <summary>GitHub Actions automates workflows defined in `.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitlab-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/gitlab-cicd">
    <summary>GitLab CI/CD is an integrated pipeline platform built into GitLab, configured via.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitlab-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gitlab-cicd">
    <summary>GitLab CI/CD is an integrated DevSecOps platform using.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/gitops">
    <summary>GitOps uses a Git repository as the single source of truth for declarative infrastructure and applications.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops-core-principles" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gitops-core-principles">
    <summary>GitOps uses Git repositories as the single source of truth for declarative infrastructure and applications.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops-flux" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gitops-flux">
    <summary>Flux is a lightweight, modular GitOps operator for Kubernetes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops-progressive-delivery" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gitops-progressive-delivery">
    <summary>Progressive delivery extends GitOps with automated canary and blue-green deployments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops-repository-structure" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gitops-repository-structure">
    <summary>The config repository layout is the foundation of a maintainable GitOps setup.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops-secrets-security" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/gitops-secrets-security">
    <summary>Secrets in GitOps require explicit tooling because plaintext secrets in Git are a critical vulnerability.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="grafana-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/grafana-basics">
    <summary>Grafana is an open-source observability platform for visualizing metrics, logs, and traces.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="grafana-dashboards" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/grafana-dashboards">
    <summary>Grafana is the leading open-source observability platform for visualizing metrics, logs, and traces.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="grafana-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/grafana-setup">
    <summary>Grafana setup methodology covering Docker Compose, Kubernetes Helm, and High Availability deployment patterns, with configuration-as-code provisioning for data sources, dashboards, and alerting.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="greenfield-infra-decision-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/greenfield-infra-decision-matrix">
    <summary>Greenfield Infra Decision Matrix — testable methodology for platform, k8s, networking, cost models. DevOps engineers waste days re-deciding self-host vs managed, EKS vs ECS vs Cloud Run, Terraform vs Pulumi. A single decision-matrix methodology with weighting and red-flags would short-circuit this for every new engagement (P4 outsource: pitch faster; P6 p...</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="headroom-cost-model" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/headroom-cost-model">
    <summary>Headroom Cost Model — testable methodology for platform, k8s, networking, cost models. Tradeoff between capacity safety and cost is under-served by current FinOps + scaling content.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="helm-advanced" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/helm-advanced">
    <summary>Advanced Helm techniques for production-grade chart development: library charts for reusable templates, hooks for lifecycle intervention (pre-install, post-upgrade, test), Helm test framework for deployment validation, umbrella charts for multi-service composition, and production patterns (checksum annotations, required values, resource protection).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="helm-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/helm-basics">
    <summary>Helm is the package manager for Kubernetes, enabling templating, versioning, and sharing of Kubernetes manifests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="helm-charts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/helm-charts">
    <summary>Helm is the package manager for Kubernetes (v4+ as of 2026).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="helm-values-diff-reviewer" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/helm-values-diff-reviewer">
    <summary>Helm Values Diff Reviewer — testable methodology for platform, k8s, networking, cost models. Helm bumps frequently break prod due to silent values changes; no methodology covers reading rendered-manifest diffs as a reviewer artifact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/iac-basics">
    <summary>Infrastructure as Code applies software engineering practices to infrastructure management through declarative or imperative code definitions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-patterns-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/iac-patterns-cicd">
    <summary>CI/CD pipeline patterns for Terraform: a six-stage GitHub Actions workflow (fmt/validate/lint/security/plan/apply), OIDC for credential-free cloud authentication, PR plan comments for review, environment-specific apply jobs with approval gates, and scheduled drift detection.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-patterns-composition" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/iac-patterns-composition">
    <summary>Four composition patterns for structuring Terraform across multiple environments and teams: Terramod (environment definitions compose from modules), Landing Zone (self-service pre-configured environment framework), Service Catalog (vetted patterns for complex deployments), and Hub-Spoke (central shared services with isolated workloads).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-patterns-dry" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/iac-patterns-dry">
    <summary>Four DRY techniques for Terraform that eliminate duplication without sacrificing readability: locals for computed/derived values, for_each (not count) for similar resources, dynamic blocks for repeated nested structures, and Terragrunt for eliminating provider/backend boilerplate across environments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-patterns-module-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/iac-patterns-module-design">
    <summary>Five canonical Terraform module patterns (Base, Wrapper, Facade, Factory, Composite) that cover the full design space from single-resource encapsulation to simplified stack facades.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-patterns-testing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/iac-patterns-testing">
    <summary>A four-level testing pyramid for Terraform modules: static analysis catches syntax and policy errors in seconds, native terraform test validates module contracts with plan-only or mock providers, Terratest deploys real resources for integration verification, and OPA/Conftest enforces compliance policies as code.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-pr-review-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/iac-pr-review-checklist">
    <summary>Consolidated reviewer-side checklist for IaC / Helm / GHA pull requests covering blast radius, IAM, state safety, secrets, and rollback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="image-digest-pinning-policy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/image-digest-pinning-policy">
    <summary>Team-level policy for pinning container images by SHA256 digest instead of floating tag, with documented update + rotation discipline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="incident-response-blameless-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/incident-response-blameless-playbook">
    <summary>Severity matrix, IC roles, comms templates, blameless retro structure — the operational practice geek/sdlc-ai/postmortem-auto-draft is missing at pro tier.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jenkins-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/jenkins-basics">
    <summary>Jenkins is an open-source automation server with Groovy-based Declarative (recommended) and Scripted pipeline syntax defined in Jenkinsfiles.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jenkins-pipeline-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/jenkins-pipeline-patterns">
    <summary>Advanced Jenkins pipeline patterns for production-grade declarative pipelines, shared libraries, scripted pipelines, and reusable components throughout organizations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jenkins-pipelines" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/jenkins-pipelines">
    <summary>Declarative Jenkins pipelines for production CI/CD: parallel stages, Kubernetes pod agents, shared libraries, and multi-environment deployment with manual approval gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/k8s-basics">
    <summary>Core kubectl operations, pods, services, namespaces, and fundamental concepts for running containers at scale with reliability and efficiency.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-canary-progressive" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/k8s-canary-progressive">
    <summary>Canary deployment gradually shifts traffic from a stable version to a new version, using metrics analysis to decide whether to promote or rollback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-deployment-workloads" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/k8s-deployment-workloads">
    <summary>Kubernetes orchestrates containerized applications via Deployment (stateless) and StatefulSet (stateful) resources.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-limitrange" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/k8s-limitrange">
    <summary>A LimitRange is a namespace-scoped policy that enforces resource constraints at the individual container or pod level.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-resource-quota" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/k8s-resource-quota">
    <summary>ResourceQuota enforces hard aggregate limits on the total resources a namespace can consume: CPU requests/limits, memory requests/limits, storage, and object counts (pods, services, secrets, configmaps, PersistentVolumeClaims).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-resource-requests-limits" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/k8s-resource-requests-limits">
    <summary>Every container in production MUST declare CPU and memory requests and limits.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-rolling-update" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/k8s-rolling-update">
    <summary>Rolling update is the default and safest Kubernetes deployment strategy for most production workloads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-scaling-availability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/k8s-scaling-availability">
    <summary>HorizontalPodAutoscaler (autoscaling/v2) automatically scales Deployment replicas based on CPU, memory, or custom metrics.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-security-hardening" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/k8s-security-hardening">
    <summary>Kubernetes workload security requires five layers: Pod Security Standards (enforce restricted namespace labels), container securityContext (non-root, read-only root filesystem, drop ALL capabilities), dedicated ServiceAccounts with minimal RBAC, NetworkPolicies enforcing default-deny with explicit allow rules, and secrets never stored in ConfigMaps or environment variables — use secretKeyRef or an external vault.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-version-upgrade-runbook-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/k8s-version-upgrade-runbook-template">
    <summary>K8S Version Upgrade Runbook Template — testable methodology for platform, k8s, networking, cost models. There's k8s-rolling-update + k8s-canary-progressive but no end-to-end upgrade-of-cluster-itself runbook. This is one of the highest-stakes recurring tasks DevOps owns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-vpa-rightsizing-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/k8s-vpa-rightsizing-runbook">
    <summary>Practical recipe for K8s vertical-pod-autoscaler recommend → HPA reconcile → cluster cost reduction, with rollout safety gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kubernetes" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/kubernetes">
    <summary>Kubernetes production readiness requires: always set resource requests AND limits, configure liveness + readiness + startup probes, enforce runAsNonRoot: true + readOnlyRootFilesystem: true + allowPrivilegeEscalation: false + capabilities.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kubernetes-deployment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/kubernetes-deployment">
    <summary>Kubernetes offers two built-in strategies (Recreate and Rolling Update) and three advanced strategies via Argo Rollouts (Blue-Green, Canary, A/B Testing).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-algorithms" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-algorithms">
    <summary>Load balancing algorithms distribute traffic across backend servers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-cloud-terraform" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-cloud-terraform">
    <summary>Terraform modules for AWS ALB (Application Load Balancer) and NLB (Network Load Balancer), and GCP Global HTTP(S) Load Balancer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-haproxy-production" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-haproxy-production">
    <summary>Production HAProxy setup covers: global performance tuning (maxconn, nbthread, cpu-map), TLS 1.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-health-checks" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-health-checks">
    <summary>Health checks are the mechanism by which LBs remove dead backends from rotation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-high-availability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-high-availability">
    <summary>High availability for load-balanced systems requires redundancy at both the load balancer tier and the backend tier, distributed across availability zones or regions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-kubernetes-ingress" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-kubernetes-ingress">
    <summary>Kubernetes Ingress requires: controller deployment with 3+ replicas, PodDisruptionBudget (minAvailable: 2), pod anti-affinity to prevent co-location, topology spread constraints across AZs, explicit resource requests/limits (TLS and regex are CPU-bound), and per-Ingress annotations for TLS redirect, rate limiting, CORS, body size, and timeouts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-layer-selection" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-layer-selection">
    <summary>Choosing between L4 (transport layer) and L7 (application layer) load balancing is the first architectural decision when deploying a load balancer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-monitoring" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-monitoring">
    <summary>LB monitoring requires Prometheus exporters (haproxy-exporter:9101, nginx-exporter:9113), four core alert rules (BackendDown, HighErrorRate &gt;5%, HighLatency p99 &gt;2s, ConnectionPoolExhausted &gt;90%), Grafana dashboards with per-backend breakdown, and centralized log aggregation (ELK/Loki) of LB access logs for audit trail and debugging.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-nginx-production" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-nginx-production">
    <summary>Production Nginx LB: worker_processes auto with worker_rlimit_nofile 65535, upstream zones for shared state, keepalive connections for HTTP/1.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-session-persistence" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-session-persistence">
    <summary>Session persistence ensures requests from the same client always reach the same backend server.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-technology-selection" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/lb-technology-selection">
    <summary>Choose the right load balancer for production using a decision matrix covering HAProxy, Nginx, AWS/GCP/Azure managed LBs, and Kubernetes Ingress controllers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lean-stack-bootstrapper-blueprint" tier="free" path="skills/faion/knowledge/free/infra/lean-stack-bootstrapper-blueprint">
    <summary>Vercel + Supabase + Stripe + Cloudflare lean-stack reference at free tier — the tier-correct alternative to Docker/k8s overkill for indie hackers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="load-balancing-concepts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/load-balancing-concepts">
    <summary>Load balancing distributes network traffic across multiple servers to ensure high availability, reliability, and performance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="manual-override-ledger" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/manual-override-ledger">
    <summary>Manual Override Ledger: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Config drift sweep' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-burn-rate-slo-recipe" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/multi-burn-rate-slo-recipe">
    <summary>Multi Burn Rate Slo Recipe: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Observability stack rollout: logs + metrics + traces + SLOs (8 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-machine-offline-cache" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/multi-machine-offline-cache">
    <summary>Per-machine cache, deterministic offline fallback, license-aware re-activation for the faion CLI on outsource-specialist setups (laptop + workstation + client laptop).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-machine-outsource-dev-env-bootstrap" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/multi-machine-outsource-dev-env-bootstrap">
    <summary>Multi Machine Outsource Dev Env Bootstrap: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/New-project machine setup (laptop + desktop)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-region-active-active-pattern" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/multi-region-active-active-pattern">
    <summary>Traffic policy, data residency, conflict resolution, failover testing — multi-region active-active as a single methodology, not five reference docs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="nginx-configuration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/nginx-configuration">
    <summary>Nginx as high-performance HTTP server, reverse proxy, and load balancer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="nginx-configuration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/nginx-configuration">
    <summary>Nginx is a high-performance HTTP server, reverse proxy, and load balancer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="nomad-async-ops-stack" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/nomad-async-ops-stack">
    <summary>Nomad Async Ops Stack: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Multi-product portfolio rotation: ship N small bets per year' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="observability-stack-decision-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/observability-stack-decision-matrix">
    <summary>Observability Stack Decision Matrix: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Unified observability stack (logs + metrics + traces) in one weekend' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="offline-toolkit-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/offline-toolkit-checklist">
    <summary>Offline Toolkit Checklist: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'p2-indie-hacker/Travel-day low-energy work mode' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="on-call-handoff-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/on-call-handoff-template">
    <summary>On Call Handoff Template: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/On-call handoff' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="on-call-rotation-bootstrap" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/on-call-rotation-bootstrap">
    <summary>A bootstrap kit for designing a humane on-call rotation: shift length, escalation tree, comp-time policy, follow-the-sun handoff, on-call-load metrics, and a dual-track for new joiners.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="on-call-rotation-setup" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/on-call-rotation-setup">
    <summary>On Call Rotation Setup: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'p6-product-dev-team/Cross-role handoff: PM -&gt; Architect -&gt; Dev -&gt; QA -&gt; DevOps in one loop' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="on-call-shift-retro-cadence" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/on-call-shift-retro-cadence">
    <summary>On Call Shift Retro Cadence: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/On-call handoff' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="oncall-handoff-protocol" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/oncall-handoff-protocol">
    <summary>Oncall Handoff Protocol: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'p6-product-dev-team/Cross-role handoff: PM -&gt; Architect -&gt; Dev -&gt; QA -&gt; DevOps in one loop' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="one-person-rollback-runbook" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/one-person-rollback-runbook">
    <summary>One Person Rollback Runbook: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Deploy-day staging-to-prod gate' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="opentelemetry-collector-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/opentelemetry-collector-architecture">
    <summary>Opentelemetry Collector Architecture: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Unified observability stack (logs + metrics + traces) in one weekend' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="opentelemetry-instrumentation-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/opentelemetry-instrumentation-playbook">
    <summary>Opentelemetry Instrumentation Playbook: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Unified observability stack (logs + metrics + traces) in one weekend' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="opentelemetry-rollout-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/opentelemetry-rollout-runbook">
    <summary>Opentelemetry Rollout Runbook: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Observability stack rollout: logs + metrics + traces + SLOs (8 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pci-dss-vendor-evidence-pack" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/pci-dss-vendor-evidence-pack">
    <summary>Pci Dss Vendor Evidence Pack: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/FinTech / HIPAA compliance audit prep (4 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="per-client-credential-isolation-pattern" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/per-client-credential-isolation-pattern">
    <summary>Per Client Credential Isolation Pattern: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/New-project machine setup (laptop + desktop)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="platform-engineering" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/platform-engineering">
    <summary>Internal Developer Platforms (IDP) reduce cognitive load and accelerate delivery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="platform-team-charter-template" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/platform-team-charter-template">
    <summary>Platform Team Charter Template: codified infra practice that turns the recurring 'role-devops-engineer/Greenfield infra bootstrap: k8s + CI/CD + observability + secrets (4 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prometheus-monitoring" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/prometheus-monitoring">
    <summary>Prometheus is the de facto standard for Kubernetes monitoring: pull-based metrics, PromQL queries, Alertmanager routing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prr-checklist-canonical" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/prr-checklist-canonical">
    <summary>PRR Checklist Canonical — pinned checklist for the DevOps engineer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so production-readiness hardening sweep (6 weeks) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="regulated-incident-response-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/regulated-incident-response-protocol">
    <summary>Incident comms under PCI/HIPAA/GDPR breach-notification clocks (72h GDPR, 60d HIPAA) — for outsource specialists in regulated client engagements.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="release-strategy-canary-blue-green-feature-flag" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/release-strategy-canary-blue-green-feature-flag">
    <summary>Picks between blue/green vs canary vs feature-flag vs ring deploys per service shape — the higher-level methodology k8s-canary-progressive misses.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="restore-drill-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/restore-drill-template">
    <summary>Restore Drill Template — pinned template for the DevOps engineer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so backup verification (weekly) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rotation-evidence-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/rotation-evidence-template">
    <summary>Rotation Evidence Template: defines the audit-grade record shape SOC-2 / ISO27001 require for each secret-rotation event so auditors get traceability, not screenshots.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rto-rpo-measurement-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/rto-rpo-measurement-template">
    <summary>RTO/RPO Measurement Template: turns DR drills from theatre into a measurable observation by defining the log format and timestamp checkpoints that produce actual RTO/RPO numbers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rto-rpo-tracking-board" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/rto-rpo-tracking-board">
    <summary>RTO/RPO Tracking Board: defines the standing surface that keeps observed vs. contractual RTO/RPO visible per system across drills and incidents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="runbook-as-code-pattern" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/runbook-as-code-pattern">
    <summary>Runbook as Code Pattern: the pro-tier infra practice of keeping runbooks in the service repo, tested in CI, and deep-linked from alerts — independent of the geek-tier AI-input format.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scheduled-job-decommission-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/scheduled-job-decommission-checklist">
    <summary>Scheduled-Job Decommission Checklist: a structured cron / scheduled-task retirement procedure that prevents orphan-job sprawl found during monthly cron audits.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="secret-consumer-discovery" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/secret-consumer-discovery">
    <summary>Enumerate every consumer of a given secret across repos, services, CI jobs, schedulers, and runtime configs before initiating rotation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="secret-rotation-drill-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/secret-rotation-drill-runbook">
    <summary>Quarterly secret-rotation drill and breakglass runbook producing audit-grade evidence that satisfies SOC2 / ISO 27001 / PCI DSS rotation controls.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="secrets-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/secrets-management">
    <summary>Secrets management in 2025-2026 means eliminating static, long-lived credentials: apps authenticate via cloud identity (IRSA, Workload Identity, OIDC) and receive short-lived dynamic credentials from a secrets backend.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="secrets-rotation-end-to-end" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/secrets-rotation-end-to-end">
    <summary>Rotation lifecycle (cadence, dual-secret window, app-side reload, audit trail) — what secrets-management covers storage of but not rotation of.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-as-code" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/security-as-code">
    <summary>Security as Code embeds protection mechanisms directly into every phase of the software delivery lifecycle.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-container-scanning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/security-container-scanning">
    <summary>87% of production container images contain at least one major vulnerability (2024 Cloud Native Security Report).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-dast" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/security-dast">
    <summary>DAST tests running applications to find vulnerabilities in production-like environments — auth bypass, injection, header misconfigurations — that SAST cannot see.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-policy-as-code" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/security-policy-as-code">
    <summary>Policy as Code codifies compliance and security requirements in version-controlled, testable artifacts enforced by admission controllers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-sast" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/security-sast">
    <summary>SAST analyzes source code before execution to identify vulnerabilities early ("shift-left" security).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-supply-chain" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/cicd-engineer/security-supply-chain">
    <summary>Supply chain attacks target dependencies, build tooling, and secrets in CI rather than the application code itself.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sentry-alert-routing-for-solos" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/devops-engineer/sentry-alert-routing-for-solos">
    <summary>Solo-operator pattern for routing Sentry + Plausible + transactional-email + uptime alerts through filters, digests, and quiet-hours so a single human gets paged only for real, actionable, on-call incidents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sentry-supabase-vercel-wiring" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/sentry-supabase-vercel-wiring">
    <summary>Integration-level wiring for Sentry on the default solo stack (Next.js on Vercel + Supabase): SDK setup, source-map upload, edge-runtime caveats, noise suppression.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="service-ownership-map-template" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/service-ownership-map-template">
    <summary>Service Ownership Map Template — a versioned service→owner artefact that powers triage routing for Sentry / Datadog alerts in product-dev teams.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="shared-infra-capacity-board" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/shared-infra-capacity-board">
    <summary>Shared Infra Capacity Board — a weekly cross-team artefact that surfaces upcoming demand on shared Kafka, Redis, DB, and similar resources before it becomes a fight.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="slo-burn-decision-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/slo-burn-decision-matrix">
    <summary>Decision matrix mapping fast-burn vs slow-burn SLO error-budget patterns to specific operational actions (canary halt, ship freeze, focus shift, accept) so error-budget burn becomes deterministic rather than rhetorical.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="slo-definition-template-per-service-class" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/slo-definition-template-per-service-class">
    <summary>SLI/SLO definition templates keyed by service class (API, async worker, batch, static asset, scheduled job) so SLO authoring stops being dashboard-driven and starts being service-shape-driven, with explicit SLI selection rules and budget calibration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="slo-design-from-user-journeys" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/slo-design-from-user-journeys">
    <summary>SLO Design From User Journeys — how to pick SLIs and SLO targets that anchor on real user journeys (not infra metrics) before the first production deploy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="slo-error-budget-policy-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/slo-error-budget-policy-template">
    <summary>SLO Error Budget Policy Template — a one-page policy artefact mapping error-budget state (healthy / yellow / red / exhausted) to concrete actions (ship / freeze / focus / escalate).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="soc2-control-map-vendor-side" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/soc2-control-map-vendor-side">
    <summary>SOC 2 Control Map (Vendor Side) — a one-page artefact mapping faion's existing SAST/DAST/supply-chain controls onto SOC 2 Trust Services Criteria so audit prep is incremental, not a panic project.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="soc2-control-to-repo-artifact-map" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/infra/soc2-control-to-repo-artifact-map">
    <summary>One-to-many YAML map from each SOC 2 Trust Service Criterion to concrete repo artifacts (file paths, CI jobs, dashboard URLs) so audit evidence pulls in minutes, not weeks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-deploy-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/solo-deploy-checklist">
    <summary>One-page pre/during/post deploy checklist with explicit go/no-go criteria — sized for the solo operator pushing to a single production environment.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-incident-triage-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/solo-incident-triage-checklist">
    <summary>Bedside 4-step triage checklist a solo operator runs in the first 15 minutes of a prod incident — before paging anyone, before diving into logs, before posting to status.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ssl-tls-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/ssl-tls-setup">
    <summary>SSL/TLS (Secure Sockets Layer/Transport Layer Security) provides encryption and authentication for network communications.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="supabase-backup-and-restore-drill" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/supabase-backup-and-restore-drill">
    <summary>Supabase Backup And Restore Drill: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Pre-launch hardening: vibe-coded MVP → safe-to-bill production'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="supabase-rls-audit-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/infra/supabase-rls-audit-checklist">
    <summary>Supabase Rls Audit Checklist: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Pre-launch hardening: vibe-coded MVP → safe-to-bill production'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/terraform">
    <summary>Terraform codifies infrastructure changes in version-controlled HCL, enabling reproducible environments, drift detection, and auditable change history.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/terraform">
    <summary>Production-grade Terraform covers state architecture, module design, workspace strategies, CI/CD integration, security scanning, and compliance governance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/terraform-basics">
    <summary>Core Terraform reference covering HCL syntax, provider configuration, resources, data sources, variables, outputs, locals, and the standard project file layout.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-iac" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/terraform-iac">
    <summary>Terraform manages cloud infrastructure declaratively using HCL, tracking state in a remote backend and applying changes via the plan-apply workflow.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-modules-composition" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/terraform-modules-composition">
    <summary>Module composition is how root modules assemble child modules into a complete infrastructure system.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-modules-prompts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/terraform-modules-prompts">
    <summary>A complete set of prompt templates for AI-assisted Terraform module development.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-modules-security" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/terraform-modules-security">
    <summary>Terraform modules must never embed secrets, must follow IAM and network least-privilege, and must be tested with terraform validate, terraform test (native), and optionally Terratest before release.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-modules-structure" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/terraform-modules-structure">
    <summary>Terraform modules are self-contained packages of Terraform configurations that encapsulate reusable infrastructure components.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-modules-versioning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/terraform-modules-versioning">
    <summary>Published Terraform modules MUST use Semantic Versioning (SemVer) with Git tags, version constraints on every module source reference, and a maintained CHANGELOG.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-state" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/infrastructure-engineer/terraform-state">
    <summary>Remote state configuration, locking, encryption, import, and migration patterns for Terraform.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trace-sampling-tail-vs-head" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/trace-sampling-tail-vs-head">
    <summary>Trace Sampling Tail Vs Head: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-devops-engineer/Unified observability stack (logs + metrics + traces) in one weekend'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="us-uk-eu-compliance-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/devops-engineer/us-uk-eu-compliance-matrix">
    <summary>Side-by-side obligation matrix across US (CCPA/CPRA, state privacy), UK (UK-GDPR, DPA 2018), and EU (GDPR, DSA, AI Act) so a micro-agency founder can check entity registration, data handling, contracts, and tax obligations per market without re-reading three statutes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vdi-vs-byod-decision-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/vdi-vs-byod-decision-matrix">
    <summary>Vdi Vs Byod Decision Matrix: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p4-outsource-specialist/New-project machine setup (laptop + desktop)'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vendor-lock-in-audit-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/infra/vendor-lock-in-audit-checklist">
    <summary>Vendor Lock In Audit Checklist: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-devops-engineer/Container vs serverless vs VM decision tree at architecture time'.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
