<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="infra" count="294" version="3.0" generated="2026-05-25">
  <description>L2 index of methodologies in the infra domain. The retriever reads this after picking infra from L1 domains.xml. Entries list slug + tier + summary; open the leaf meta.json / content/*.xml for full payload.</description>
  <methodology slug="action-item-stale-aging" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/action-item-stale-aging">
    <summary>Produces an aging report on open retro action-items with explicit aging counter and escalation matrix per item.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-year-end-close-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/agency-year-end-close-checklist">
    <summary>Produces a year-end-close artefact recording every checklist item with anchored source-of-truth, status, and aging on open items.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-generated-iac-review-gate" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/ai-generated-iac-review-gate">
    <summary>Review rubric and CI gate for AI-generated infrastructure-as-code: secrets scan, drift check, blast-radius classification, human sign-off thresholds.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-terraform-review-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/ai-terraform-review-checklist">
    <summary>Per-PR checklist that catches the 2026 AI-generated Dockerfile / Helm / Terraform failure patterns (USER 0, latest tag, missing resource limits, broken templating) before they reach production.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-workload-cost-attribution" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/ai-workload-cost-attribution">
    <summary>Per-tenant / per-feature LLM + GPU cost attribution: token-meter ingestion, GPU-second mapping, cost-per-request rollup, monthly invoice-ready report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aiops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aiops">
    <summary>Produces an AIOps platform config (anomaly detection params, RCA pipeline, auto-remediation risk policy with approval matrix) wired through OpenTelemetry.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aiops-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aiops-cicd">
    <summary>Spec for an AIOps program \u2014 anomaly detection signals, promotion rules to incident, trust-tiered automated remediation, and outcome metrics (precision, auto-remediation rate, MTTR).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="alert-deduplication-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/alert-deduplication-playbook">
    <summary>Produces an alert-routing.yaml + audit report that turns a noisy alerting stack into a high-signal page channel under a paging SLO.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="alert-noise-budget" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/alert-noise-budget">
    <summary>Produces a weekly noise-budget report per service and a list of alerts requiring tuning this week (retire / threshold / hysteresis / suppression).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="argocd-gitops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/argocd-gitops">
    <summary>Produces an ArgoCD GitOps config (Application / AppProject / ApplicationSet) with self-heal, sync-waves, and notifications enforcing Git as source of truth.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="argocd-gitops-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/argocd-gitops-cicd">
    <summary>Pull-based GitOps deployment spec with ApplicationSets, sync waves, sync windows, server-side apply, and per-environment self-heal policy \u2014 keeps cluster and Git state convergent.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-architecture-services" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-architecture-services">
    <summary>Production-ready AWS service-selection spec: Lambda vs containers vs hybrid, EventBridge vs Step Functions vs SQS/SNS, Well-Architected six-pillar review with Terraform skeletons and Graviton-first compute defaults.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-cfn-terraform-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-cfn-terraform-templates">
    <summary>Produces production-ready AWS IaC templates (VPC, ECS Fargate, Lambda, RDS) in CloudFormation YAML and Terraform HCL with hardened defaults.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-cli-compute" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-cli-compute">
    <summary>Produces shell scripts using AWS CLI for EC2 / S3 / Lambda lifecycle operations with explicit profile handling and idempotent wait conditions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-cli-containers-iac" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-cli-containers-iac">
    <summary>Produces shell scripts using AWS CLI for ECS / EKS / RDS / CloudFormation / IAM / CloudWatch operations with change-set discipline and rollback paths.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-cli-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-cli-setup">
    <summary>AWS CLI v2 + IAM Identity Center (SSO) baseline config: named profiles, short-lived credentials, MFA enforcement, no long-lived access keys committed to disk in plain text.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-cost-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-cost-optimization">
    <summary>Quarterly FinOps report: Cost Explorer drill-down by tag + Savings Plan coverage + Graviton coverage + Spot adoption + Instance Scheduler + rightsizing recommendations, signed by a named owner against pinned thresholds.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-ec2-ecs" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-ec2-ecs">
    <summary>EC2 + ECS Fargate production spec: task definitions, service auto-scaling, capacity providers, IAM task roles, network mode, observability hookups, and rollout discipline (blue/green via CodeDeploy).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-ec2-provisioning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-ec2-provisioning">
    <summary>EC2 provisioning spec: latest AL2023 + Graviton AMI, IMDSv2-only, SSM-managed (no SSH keys), userdata via cloud-init, hardened security groups, Nitro Enclaves where attestation matters.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-iam-practical-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-iam-practical-patterns">
    <summary>Practical IAM patterns: SSO permission sets, Permissions Boundaries on developer roles, SCPs at org level, IAM Access Analyzer review, conditional policies (MFA, source IP, tag) with worked examples per pattern.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-iam-security-foundations" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-iam-security-foundations">
    <summary>Baseline IAM hygiene: root account hardened, CloudTrail org-wide multi-region, GuardDuty + Security Hub enabled, password policy + MFA + access-key rotation policy, AWS Config rules pinned to CIS baseline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-infra-llm-prompts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-infra-llm-prompts">
    <summary>Produces parameterized LLM prompt templates for AWS architecture design conversations with structured context, constraints, and required output format.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-infra-prompt-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-infra-prompt-library">
    <summary>Curated, versioned, owner-signed prompt library for AI-assisted AWS IaC work (Terraform, Cloud Run, ECS, IAM) with required guardrails (no-secret-leak, source-of-truth pinning, idempotence checks) per prompt class.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-lambda" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-lambda">
    <summary>Lambda production spec: function design (size, memory, layers), cold-start mitigation (SnapStart, provisioned concurrency), event source mapping (SQS, Kinesis, DynamoDB Streams), idempotency, observability (X-Ray, structured logs), and IAM scope.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-monitoring-observability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-monitoring-observability">
    <summary>Production observability spec: CloudWatch metrics + logs + alarms + Container Insights + X-Ray tracing + OpenTelemetry collector, with SLO-derived alarms (burn-rate multi-window), structured logs, and dashboards per service.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-multi-account-landing-zone" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-multi-account-landing-zone">
    <summary>AWS landing zone spec: OU hierarchy (Security, Workloads, Sandbox, Suspended), Control Tower or homegrown baseline, SCP guardrails, baseline IAM Identity Center permission sets, log + audit accounts, cross-account network hub.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-networking" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-networking">
    <summary>VPC + subnet + route + security-group + Transit Gateway spec: tiered subnets (public / private / data), VPC endpoints for AWS services, TGW hub-spoke, security groups by role (no 0.0.0.0/0), VPC Flow Logs on.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-s3-storage" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-s3-storage">
    <summary>S3 production spec: block public access default-on, SSE-KMS encryption, versioning + MFA-delete on critical buckets, lifecycle policies (IA / Glacier), bucket policies with explicit deny, Object Lock for immutability, replication for DR.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-vpc-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-vpc-design">
    <summary>VPC design spec: CIDR plan via IPAM, \u2265 2 AZ subnets, tiered (public / private / data), VPC endpoints, Flow Logs, route table discipline, IPv6 dual-stack where new, named-owner per VPC.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-vpc-three-tier" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-vpc-three-tier">
    <summary>Three-tier VPC reference architecture spec: public subnet (ALB + NAT) \u2192 private subnet (app workloads) \u2192 data subnet (RDS + ElastiCache), security groups by role, Multi-AZ, no cross-tier inbound shortcuts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-well-architected-checklists" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-well-architected-checklists">
    <summary>Produces a binary pass/fail Well-Architected checklist across the 6 pillars (OpEx, Security, Reliability, Performance, Cost, Sustainability), used as a pre-launch gate or quarterly review.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aws-well-architected-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/aws-well-architected-framework">
    <summary>Quarterly Well-Architected review report: six pillars (Op Excellence, Security, Reliability, Performance, Cost, Sustainability) with finding-per-question, named owner per finding, remediation plan with due date.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-app-gateway-waf" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/azure-app-gateway-waf">
    <summary>Regional L7 LB + WAF spec for Azure: dedicated delegated subnet, Detection \u2192 Prevention WAF rollout, Key Vault-managed TLS, OWASP 3.2 baseline, bot protection on internet-facing GW.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/azure-architecture">
    <summary>Produces an Azure architecture spec: 5-pillar WA evaluation + 8 Landing Zone design areas, with AVM+Bicep IaC and Zero-Trust identity model (ESLZ Terraform deprecated Aug 2026).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-compute" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/azure-compute">
    <summary>ADR that pins per-workload Azure compute tier (VM / VMSS / AKS / Container Apps / App Service) with managed identity, workload identity, Spot mix, reserved instance, and cost-optimisation choices.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-front-door" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/azure-front-door">
    <summary>Global L7 LB + CDN + WAF spec: Private Link origins for production, Front-Door-only NSG on App Gateway, propagation-aware deploy pipeline, WAF tuning + bot protection.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-nat-gateway" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/azure-nat-gateway">
    <summary>Spec for managed zone-redundant outbound: IP count sized to concurrent connections, idle-timeout tuned to app shape, SNAT-port monitoring + alerting, predictable static egress IPs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-nsg-rules" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/azure-nsg-rules">
    <summary>Deny-by-default NSG policy: explicit DenyAll at priority 4096, exact-CIDR allow rules, flow logs v2 to Storage + Log Analytics, 30-day retention floor.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-private-link" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/azure-private-link">
    <summary>Private Link spec: per-service Private DNS zones linked to consumer VNets, public access disabled on target resource, registration-disabled VNet links, approved Private Endpoint connections.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="azure-vnet-hub-spoke" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/azure-vnet-hub-spoke">
    <summary>Hub-spoke topology spec: /16 per VNet, /24 per subnet, no CIDR overlap, bidirectional peering, mandatory subnet delegations, Terraform-only changes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/backup-basics">
    <summary>Versioned backup strategy spec: 3-2-1-1-0 floor, RPO/RTO targets per service tier, immutable + air-gapped copy, restore-test cadence, named DR owner.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-cloud-aws" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/backup-cloud-aws">
    <summary>AWS-native backup: S3 hardened (versioning + block-public-access + KMS + lifecycle), AWS Backup vaults + plans + cross-region copies, S3 Object Lock for ransomware-proof immutability.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-database-mysql-mongo" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/backup-database-mysql-mongo">
    <summary>Database backup spec: mysqldump + XtraBackup for MySQL with binlogs, mongodump + replica-set oplog for Mongo, restore-drill cadence, named DBA owner.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-database-postgres" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/backup-database-postgres">
    <summary>Generates a production PostgreSQL backup pipeline (pg_dump / pg_basebackup / pgBackRest + WAL archiving) with integrity verification, S3 offsite copy, and PITR-ready WAL monitoring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-filesystem-restic" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/backup-filesystem-restic">
    <summary>Generates an encrypted filesystem backup pipeline using Restic (or BorgBackup) with S3/B2 backend, retention policy, weekly repo check, and systemd timer wiring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-kubernetes-velero" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/backup-kubernetes-velero">
    <summary>Generates a Velero installation + Schedule CRDs + CSI snapshot wiring + Kopia data mover config for full + namespace-scoped cluster backups with pre/post hooks for stateful apps.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-strategies" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/backup-strategies">
    <summary>Produces a backup spec applying the 3-2-1-1-0 rule (3 copies, 2 media, 1 offsite, 1 immutable, 0 verified errors) with automated restore verification and RPO/RTO targets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="backup-verification-dr" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/backup-verification-dr">
    <summary>Produces an automated backup verification report (restore-drill cron + Prometheus alerting on age/size anomalies + DR runbook) that proves the RPO/RTO target before an incident.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="banking-core-data-residency-rules" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/banking-core-data-residency-rules">
    <summary>Per-jurisdiction data residency spec for core banking workloads: PII residence, processor residence, cross-border transfer locks, supervisory-authority notification triggers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="blameless-retro-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/blameless-retro-template">
    <summary>Produces a blameless retro record: 4-block agenda (timeline → contributing factors → generative discussion → action items + meta), language-rule enforcement, owner+date per action item, published within 48h.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="burn-rate-multi-window-alerting" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/burn-rate-multi-window-alerting">
    <summary>Canonical Google-SRE 1h/6h/24h burn-rate alert recipe (page + ticket levels) wired to a published SLO and reviewed quarterly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="canary-gono-go-threshold-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/canary-gono-go-threshold-template">
    <summary>Per-service published thresholds (latency, error-rate, business KPI) that automate canary promote / rollback decisions without runtime debate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="capacity-planning-at-design-time" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/capacity-planning-at-design-time">
    <summary>Forces RPS forecast, headroom floor, autoscaling ceiling, regional reservation choices to be written into the architecture spec before first deploy, not patched in production.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="capacity-safety-floor-policy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/capacity-safety-floor-policy">
    <summary>Published policy file (YAML) that pins per-service safety-floor headroom thresholds, audit cadence, breach response, and the named owner \u2014 replaces tribal-knowledge thresholds.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cardinality-and-cost-guardrails" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cardinality-and-cost-guardrails">
    <summary>Published guardrail config (label allow-list, drop rules, log-volume budget, recording-rules) that caps the dominant 2026 observability-cost driver: cardinality explosion.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chaos-engineering-practice-for-infra" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/chaos-engineering-practice-for-infra">
    <summary>Production-safe chaos engineering programme: hypothesis-driven experiments, blast-radius gating, GameDay cadence, learning capture, regression test conversion.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cicd-cert-rotation-pipeline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cicd-cert-rotation-pipeline">
    <summary>Generates an IaC-driven certificate rotation pipeline using cert-manager Certificate CRDs, Terraform ACM/GCP, or Docker Compose + Traefik — author → render → scan → apply, with no private keys in Git.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cicd-mtls-deployment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cicd-mtls-deployment">
    <summary>Generates an mTLS deployment recipe (step-ca / Vault PKI as internal CA + nginx client-cert verification + short-lived per-pod certs) replacing shared long-lived client certs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cicd-tls-renewal-automation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cicd-tls-renewal-automation">
    <summary>Generates an automated ACME renewal pipeline (certbot / acme.sh / lego under systemd timer + renewal hooks) that eliminates manual rotation outages for public-facing TLS.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cicd-tls-validation-gate" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cicd-tls-validation-gate">
    <summary>Adds a CI gate that runs testssl.sh + sslyze + (optional) SSL Labs against staging and blocks promotion to production unless A+ grade, cipher policy, and certificate chain validity all pass.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="claude-code-hooks" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/claude-code-hooks">
    <summary>Claude Code hook configuration: PreToolUse, PostToolUse, UserPromptSubmit, SubagentStop, Notification — wired to project pre-commit, secrets blocking, telemetry routing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-autoscaling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cloud-run-autoscaling">
    <summary>Cloud Run autoscaling spec: concurrency tuning (per-instance), min-instances for warm pool, max-instances cap, CPU-always-allocated vs request-based, scaling targets + worked formulas.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-deployment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cloud-run-deployment">
    <summary>Cloud Run deployment spec: revision tagging, traffic split (canary / blue-green), service account least-privilege, secret access via Secret Manager, container image hardening, ingress controls, observability hooks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-jobs" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cloud-run-jobs">
    <summary>Cloud Run Jobs for batch processing: parallel task execution, CLOUD_RUN_TASK_INDEX work distribution, idempotency, checkpointing, Cloud Scheduler integration, and Terraform configuration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-monitoring" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cloud-run-monitoring">
    <summary>Cloud Run observability: structured JSON logging, Cloud Monitoring dashboards, SLO alerting, Cloud Trace propagation, gcloud log queries for services and jobs, and cost optimization monitoring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-traffic-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cloud-run-traffic-management">
    <summary>Cloud Run traffic management: blue-green deployments, canary rollouts, gradual traffic shifting, rollback procedures, revision tagging, and Cloud Build CI/CD integration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-run-vpc-access" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cloud-run-vpc-access">
    <summary>Cloud Run networking: Direct VPC egress vs Serverless VPC connectors, ingress controls, multi-container sidecars (Cloud SQL proxy, OpenTelemetry), Private Service Connect, and firewall configuration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="compute-substrate-decision-tree" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/compute-substrate-decision-tree">
    <summary>Produces a decision record selecting VM vs container vs serverless for a Greenfield component with explicit trade-offs and named owner.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contractor-agreement-template-us-uk-eu" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/contractor-agreement-template-us-uk-eu">
    <summary>Produces a baseline contractor agreement (US 1099, UK IR35-aware, EU with DE/FR/PT/ES addenda) ready for attorney review before first signature.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-anomaly-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cost-anomaly-runbook">
    <summary>Produces a per-anomaly investigation artefact (input data, root-cause hypotheses, owner, action) for one cloud cost spike per pass.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-model-spreadsheet-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cost-model-spreadsheet-template">
    <summary>Produces a defensible multi-cloud cost-model spreadsheet covering compute / storage / network / operations / buffer with sourced unit rates and 0.5x/1x/2x scenarios.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-pr-gate-recipe" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cost-pr-gate-recipe">
    <summary>Produces a CI gate config that blocks merge when an IaC PR exceeds the team's monthly cost-delta budget.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cronjob-overrun-monitoring" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cronjob-overrun-monitoring">
    <summary>Produces a monitoring config (Prometheus rules + metadata) that alerts on cron overlap, skip, and duration creep across the scheduler.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cutover-rollback-runbook-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cutover-rollback-runbook-template">
    <summary>Produces a multi-wave migration cutover runbook with go/no-go gates, comms tree, and proven rollback for each wave.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cve-exception-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/cve-exception-template">
    <summary>Produces a time-bounded CVE exception decision record with compensating controls, expiry, and named owner.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="deprecated-api-sweeper-recipe" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/deprecated-api-sweeper-recipe">
    <summary>Produces a sweep report listing deprecated k8s APIs found in chart libraries + live clusters with cited tool + replacement API per finding.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-aws-monitoring-dr" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-aws-monitoring-dr">
    <summary>Produces a monitoring + DR spec: CloudWatch dashboards per tier, tiered alarms (page/business-hours/digest), X-Ray tracing, and a tested DR strategy (backup/pilot-light/warm-standby/active-active) matched to RTO/RPO.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-aws-serverless-api" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-aws-serverless-api">
    <summary>Produces a Terraform config for a serverless API: API Gateway HTTP API + Lambda arm64 + X-Ray Active + DynamoDB single-table + EventBridge + SQS DLQ + Step Functions, with throttling + custom domain.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-aws-service-selection" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-aws-service-selection">
    <summary>Produces a decision-record for AWS compute + database service selection mapped against the 6 Well-Architected pillars, with rationale per pillar and Graviton-default for compute.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-aws-terraform-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-aws-terraform-cicd">
    <summary>Produces a Terraform project layout (per-env dirs + shared modules + S3+DDB backend) + GitHub Actions OIDC CI/CD (plan on PR, sequential apply per env with prod approval).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-aws-three-tier" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-aws-three-tier">
    <summary>Produces Terraform for a three-tier VPC: public ALB, private app tier (Fargate/EKS), isolated DB subnets with Aurora Serverless v2 + SG-by-reference + multi-AZ.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-elk-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-elk-architecture">
    <summary>Produces an ELK / EFK cluster architecture spec: node roles (master / data-hot / data-warm / coordinating), hot-warm-cold tier sizing, deployment model (ECK / Docker Compose), capacity plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-elk-beats-collection" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-elk-beats-collection">
    <summary>Produces a Filebeat config (DaemonSet on K8s, or per-host) with autodiscover, multiline + JSON parsing, fields_under_root=true, and shipping to Elasticsearch / Logstash.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-elk-index-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-elk-index-management">
    <summary>Produces ES index management config: index templates (mappings + settings) + ILM policy (hot→warm→cold→delete via rollover) + write alias for time-series logs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-elk-logstash-pipeline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-elk-logstash-pipeline">
    <summary>Produces a Logstash pipeline (input → filter → output) with grok / JSON parsing, PII masking, multi-pipeline isolation, dead-letter queue, and tuned worker / batch settings.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-elk-queries-alerting" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-elk-queries-alerting">
    <summary>Generates an ELK ops baseline (KQL query bank, Elasticsearch DSL aggregations, Watcher/Kibana alerting rules, dashboard inventory, kibana.yml hardening) for log-driven observability.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-algorithms" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-lb-algorithms">
    <summary>Generates a load-balancer architecture decision record: chosen LB layer (L4/L7/DNS/Global), algorithm (round-robin / least-conn / weighted / IP-hash / consistent-hash), and session-affinity strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-haproxy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-lb-haproxy">
    <summary>Generates a production-ready HAProxy (or Nginx) load-balancer config — frontend/backend separation, ACL path routing, sticky cookies, stick-table rate-limiting, L4 DB mode, SSL termination, and Docker Compose bundle.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-health-checks" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-lb-health-checks">
    <summary>Generates an LB health-check spec: liveness vs readiness endpoints, dependency checks, tuned interval/fall/rise parameters, language-specific implementation skeletons (Go / FastAPI / Node).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-high-availability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-lb-high-availability">
    <summary>Generates an LB high-availability design: HA topology (active-passive / active-active / anycast / DNS failover), cloud LB choice (ALB / NLB / GLB), and infra-as-code skeleton.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-kubernetes" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-lb-kubernetes">
    <summary>Generates a Kubernetes load-balancing spec: Service type per workload, Ingress controller choice (Nginx/Traefik/AWS ALB Controller), readiness+liveness probes, and rolling-update guards.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-lb-ssl-tls" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-lb-ssl-tls">
    <summary>Generates an LB TLS spec: termination strategy (termination / re-encryption / passthrough), TLS 1.3 cipher list, HSTS policy, OCSP stapling, and cert lifecycle plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-platform-backstage" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-platform-backstage">
    <summary>Generates a Backstage rollout plan: catalog model (entities + relations), TechDocs source layout, Software Templates (golden paths), plugin allowlist, and SRE ownership model.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-platform-crossplane" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-platform-crossplane">
    <summary>Generates a Crossplane composition spec: XRD shape, claim contract, security defaults, blast-radius caps, and a published self-service Database/Cache/Network abstraction.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-platform-golden-paths" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-platform-golden-paths">
    <summary>Generates a golden-path catalogue: template inventory (new service / database / API), required guardrails (CI, observability, security scans), opt-out policy, and adoption metric.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-platform-idp-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-platform-idp-core">
    <summary>Generates an IDP charter: platform mission, target personas, capability inventory (provisioning / observability / cost / security), success metrics, and product-team ownership model.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="devops-platform-policy-finops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/devops-platform-policy-finops">
    <summary>Generates a platform governance bundle: OPA/Gatekeeper admission policies, per-team cost visibility, pre-deployment cost estimation, and embedded policy gates in golden paths.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/docker">
    <summary>Generates a Docker baseline config: multi-stage Dockerfile skeleton, layer order for cache, non-root user, HEALTHCHECK, exec-form CMD, .dockerignore, and Compose service spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-compose" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/docker-compose">
    <summary>Generates a Docker Compose V2 stack — healthchecks on every depends_on target, named volumes, 127.0.0.1 port bindings to bypass UFW, no legacy version: field.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-compose-cicd" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/docker-compose-cicd">
    <summary>Generates a CI-only Docker Compose override — no port bindings, health-check waits, teardown discipline — so integration test stacks run reliably under CI runners.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-compose-infra" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/docker-compose-infra">
    <summary>Generates a production-grade Compose stack — internal networks for DB tier, deploy.resources caps, restart unless-stopped, modern compose.yaml filename, named volumes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-image-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/docker-image-optimization">
    <summary>Generates a Docker image optimization plan: target size, base-image choice, multi-stage layering, cache mounts, .dockerignore, and per-language minification recipes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-infra" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/docker-infra">
    <summary>Production-grade Docker containerization: image building, optimization, networking, storage, security hardening, and deployment best practices for 2025-2026.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-language-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/docker-language-templates">
    <summary>Generates a curated Dockerfile + Compose template per language (Python, Node, Go, Rust, Java, static) — multi-stage, non-root, health-checked, with optimization defaults applied.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-llm-prompts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/docker-llm-prompts">
    <summary>Generates a Docker LLM prompt library: parameterized prompts for Dockerfile generation, optimization audit, security review, troubleshooting, CI integration, and architecture review.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-optimization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/docker-optimization">
    <summary>Generates an optimized Dockerfile (multi-stage + BuildKit cache mounts + distroless/Wolfi base + pinned digest + non-root) targeting &lt;200MB images and zero-CVE base.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="docker-security-hardening" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/docker-security-hardening">
    <summary>Generates a Docker security hardening spec: non-root user, capability drops, read-only filesystem, secrets policy, image signing, and CI vulnerability scan gate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dora-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/dora-metrics">
    <summary>Generates a DORA metrics dashboard spec: data sources, four core metrics + reliability, target band, collection cadence, and feedback loop into team rituals.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dora-metrics-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/dora-metrics-cicd">
    <summary>Generates a DORA metrics report (Deployment Frequency, Lead Time for Changes, Change Failure Rate, MTTR + Reliability) with deploy-event ingestion, Prometheus rules, schema, and Grafana wiring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dr-drill-scenario-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/dr-drill-scenario-library">
    <summary>Reusable catalogue of disaster-recovery scenarios (region loss, db corruption, secret-store loss, identity provider outage, vendor breach) with declaration, run, restore, and post-mortem steps.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="dr-drill-script-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/dr-drill-script-template">
    <summary>Per-drill script template covering declaration → runbook execution → restore validation → success criteria check → post-mortem within 7 days, scored against RTO/RPO targets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="drift-classification-taxonomy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/drift-classification-taxonomy">
    <summary>Closed taxonomy for infrastructure drift causes (hand-edit, external automation, vendor change, legitimate-emergency, unknown) so terraform plan diffs route to the right fix path instead of being silently re-applied.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="edge-and-cdn-strategy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/edge-and-cdn-strategy">
    <summary>Edge compute + CDN strategy spec: pick Cloudflare Workers / Lambda@Edge / Fastly Compute, cache-key design, origin shielding, edge auth, fallback path, cost ceiling per request.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="egress-cost-hidden-budget-guide" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/egress-cost-hidden-budget-guide">
    <summary>Pre-launch + scale-event capacity exercise focused on the hidden cost trio: egress to internet, cross-AZ data, NAT-gateway processing, with per-feature attribution and per-region cap.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="elk-stack-logging" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/elk-stack-logging">
    <summary>Generates an ELK (or OpenSearch) deployment recipe (Elasticsearch + Logstash/Vector + Kibana + Filebeat/Vector agents) with ILM, security, and dashboards for production observability.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-budget-policy-and-freeze-rules" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/error-budget-policy-and-freeze-rules">
    <summary>Error-budget policy that converts SLO burn into deterministic actions (canary halt, ship freeze, focus shift, accept) with named owner, revert criteria, and stakeholder comms.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="eu-sovereign-llm-deployment-bundle" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/eu-sovereign-llm-deployment-bundle">
    <summary>Production deployment spec for EU-sovereign LLM stack: in-EU inference, EU-Act compliance hooks, in-EU vector store + observability, no-egress data plane.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="external-secrets-operator-recipe" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/external-secrets-operator-recipe">
    <summary>Production-ready ESO setup recipe: ClusterSecretStore configuration per backend, ExternalSecret manifests, refresh interval calibration, RBAC, secret-store identity, alerts on sync failure.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fast-vs-slow-burn-rule" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/fast-vs-slow-burn-rule">
    <summary>Multi-window multi-burn-rate alerting rule: configure 4 windows (1h fast, 6h sustained, 3d slow, 30d trend) with calibrated burn-rate thresholds so SLO violations alert at the right cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fco-commitment-pricing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/fco-commitment-pricing">
    <summary>Generates a commitment-pricing plan (RIs / Savings Plans / 1-3yr commitments) for steady-state workloads delivering 60-75% discount, with utilization monitoring and unused-commitment alarm.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fco-cost-allocation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/fco-cost-allocation">
    <summary>Generates a tagging policy + enforcement (SCP/Org Policy) + chargeback report wiring so every cloud resource carries accurate metadata for cost attribution to team, service, environment.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fco-rightsizing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/fco-rightsizing">
    <summary>Generates a rightsizing decision-record (CPU/Memory percentile baseline → recommended size + Graviton migration) targeting 20-40% compute spend reduction with no SLO impact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fco-spot-instances" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/fco-spot-instances">
    <summary>Generates a spot / preemptible instance plan (with checkpointing + interruption handler + instance diversification) delivering 70-90% cost reduction on fault-tolerant workloads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fco-waste-elimination" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/fco-waste-elimination">
    <summary>Generates a waste-elimination plan (idle resources audit list + non-prod scheduling config + cleanup automation policy) that targets 25%+ waste reduction and 70% non-prod compute savings.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-flag-rollout-runbook" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/feature-flag-rollout-runbook">
    <summary>Staged feature-flag rollout runbook: 1/10/50/100% cohorts, kill switch, SLO-tied auto-rollback, flag-cleanup TODO, post-rollout audit.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops">
    <summary>Generates a FinOps cycle spec for the Inform → Optimize → Operate phases: tagging coverage, anomaly detection, rightsizing cadence, and commitment strategy with per-team accountability.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-agentic-workflow" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops-agentic-workflow">
    <summary>Generates a continuous-loop agentic FinOps config (billing-snapshot, tag-auditor, idle-hunter, RI/SP-advisor agents) with human-in-the-loop approval gates and safe-automation gotchas.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-ai-ml-costs" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops-ai-ml-costs">
    <summary>Generates an AI/ML cost-control config (GPU spot strategy with checkpointing + inference caching + quantization + batch policy + per-run/per-request attribution) for training and inference.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-cost-visibility" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops-cost-visibility">
    <summary>Generates an INFORM-phase config (tag taxonomy + cost allocation rules + dashboard sources + KPI baselines) establishing the visibility foundation before any optimization work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-devops-cost-alerts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops-devops-cost-alerts">
    <summary>Generates a cost-alert + anomaly investigation spec: threshold alerts (50/75/90/100% of budget), anomaly detector, LLM-assisted investigation prompts, and executive report template.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-devops-cost-commitments" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops-devops-cost-commitments">
    <summary>Decision record for cloud commitment portfolio (Reserved Instances, Savings Plans, Spot) sized to workload shape after rightsizing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-devops-cost-kubernetes" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops-devops-cost-kubernetes">
    <summary>Cost-optimisation report for Kubernetes clusters: pool topology, autoscaling targets, Spot allocation and resource-request right-sizing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-devops-cost-rightsizing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops-devops-cost-rightsizing">
    <summary>Rightsizing report matching compute and database allocations to observed P95 utilisation, with downsize and family-change recommendations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-devops-cost-tagging" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops-devops-cost-tagging">
    <summary>Mandatory cost-tagging policy: required keys, normalisation rules, untagged-resource quarantine and chargeback-ready exports.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops-framework">
    <summary>Generates the program-level FinOps config (phase assessment + team structure + RACI + cadence + phase-specific checklists) that scaffolds the cultural practice end-to-end.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finops-governance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/finops-governance">
    <summary>Generates an OPERATE-phase config (automated policies + tiered budget alerts + dev/test auto-stop + CI/CD cost gates via Infracost) that sustains optimization without manual policing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gce-autoscaling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gce-autoscaling">
    <summary>Configure GCE autoscalers for MIGs using CPU, load-balancing, custom Cloud Monitoring metrics, schedule-based, and predictive signals with scale-in controls to prevent flapping.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gce-instance-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gce-instance-templates">
    <summary>Design, version, and manage GCE instance templates as the single source of truth for VM configuration in Managed Instance Groups and standalone deployments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gce-managed-instance-groups" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gce-managed-instance-groups">
    <summary>Deploy and operate GCE Managed Instance Groups (MIGs) for production: regional vs zonal placement, health checks, autohealing, rolling updates, and canary deployments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gce-spot-vms" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gce-spot-vms">
    <summary>Use GCE Spot VMs (up to 91% discount) for fault-tolerant batch and burst workloads: instance templates, shutdown scripts, MIG autohealing, GKE spot node pools, and cost-optimization patterns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp">
    <summary>Decision record selecting GKE Autopilot vs Standard, Cloud Run sizing, Workload Identity Federation and Private Service Connect for production GCP workloads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-arch-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-arch-patterns">
    <summary>Production-ready GCP patterns: regional GKE, Cloud SQL HA, Cloud Run with VPC egress, Pub/Sub DLQ, Dataflow+BigQuery. Concrete commands and verifications.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-billing-cost" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-billing-cost">
    <summary>Configure GCP billing accounts, budget alerts at multiple thresholds, BigQuery billing exports, and cost allocation labels for per-team chargeback and spend optimization.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-cloud-run-serverless" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-cloud-run-serverless">
    <summary>GCP Cloud Run and Cloud Functions Gen2 best practices: secure service deployment, VPC connector, blue-green traffic splitting, Secret Manager integration, and Cloud Run security/setup checklists.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-compute-gke" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-compute-gke">
    <summary>GCP Compute Engine and GKE: Shielded VMs, OS Login, regional MIG autoscaling, GKE Autopilot vs Standard hardened clusters, Workload Identity, Dataplane V2, and compute/GKE security checklists.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-gke-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-gke-architecture">
    <summary>Architecture spec for GKE: cluster mode (Autopilot/Standard), regional vs zonal topology, node-pool taxonomy and Workload Identity wiring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-iam-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-iam-design">
    <summary>Design GCP IAM strategy: least privilege, predefined roles, service account setup, Workload Identity Federation for GKE, and auditing overly permissive bindings.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-landing-zone" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-landing-zone">
    <summary>Landing-zone spec for new GCP organisations: folder hierarchy, baseline org policies, Workload Identity Federation, centralised logging and billing-export wiring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-llm-prompts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-llm-prompts">
    <summary>Parameterized LLM prompts for GCP: Terraform generation (VPC, Cloud Run, GKE), security audits, IAM review, connectivity troubleshooting, cost optimization, migration, compliance, and runbooks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-network-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-network-architecture">
    <summary>Network spec for GCP: Shared VPC topology, CIDR allocation for GKE secondary ranges, Private Service Connect, Cloud NAT and hierarchical firewall policy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-networking" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-networking">
    <summary>Comprehensive GCP networking reference: VPC design, subnets, firewall rules, Cloud NAT, load balancing, and security best practices for production workloads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-networking-vpc" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-networking-vpc">
    <summary>GCP networking: custom VPC with three-tier subnets, firewall rules (least privilege), Cloud NAT, global HTTPS load balancer, Cloud Armor WAF, VPC Service Controls perimeter, and networking checklists.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-org-policies" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-org-policies">
    <summary>Implement GCP organization policies to enforce security constraints: restrict resource locations, disable SA key creation, enforce OS Login, require labels, and set up Security Command Center.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-overview-cli" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-overview-cli">
    <summary>GCP service overview, gcloud CLI setup, authentication, configuration management, CI/CD deployment patterns, disaster recovery, and cost optimization commands.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-resource-hierarchy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-resource-hierarchy">
    <summary>Design and configure GCP resource hierarchy (org/folders/projects), naming conventions, required labels, and project setup to enforce governance at scale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-security-iam" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-security-iam">
    <summary>GCP IAM least-privilege config: Workload Identity Federation, VPC Service Controls, CMEK rotation, audit-log routing produced as Terraform-friendly JSON policy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-storage" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-storage">
    <summary>Cloud Storage bucket spec (config artefact): storage class, lifecycle rules, CMEK, IAM bindings, retention, Cloud CDN attach — produced as Terraform-ready JSON.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-storage-cdn" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-storage-cdn">
    <summary>Configuration for Cloud Storage classes, lifecycle policies, versioning and Cloud CDN cache rules sized to access pattern and retention policy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gcp-terraform-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gcp-terraform-templates">
    <summary>Production Terraform module set spec for GCP (VPC, firewall, SA, Cloud Run v2, GKE Autopilot, Cloud SQL, WIF) — produced as a module-manifest config plus root composition.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gdpr-dsar-runbook-product-dev-team" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gdpr-dsar-runbook-product-dev-team">
    <summary>Engineer-friendly Data-Subject-Access-Request runbook: intake, identity verify, system-by-system extraction, redaction, packaging, 30-day SLA delivery + audit.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gha-caching-artifacts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gha-caching-artifacts">
    <summary>Generates a GHA cache + artifact config (ecosystem-specific cache keys + retention policy + Docker layer cache via Buildx + cache-vs-artifact decision per job).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gha-deployment-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gha-deployment-patterns">
    <summary>Generates a CD config (staged deploys with environment protection + reusable workflows + composite actions + canary/blue-green choice + release automation with changelog).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gha-matrix-builds" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gha-matrix-builds">
    <summary>Generates a matrix-strategy config (axes + include/exclude + fail-fast policy + per-combination artifacts + concurrency) for parallel multi-OS / multi-version testing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gha-security-hardening" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gha-security-hardening">
    <summary>Generates a security-hardened workflow config (SHA-pinned actions + OIDC for cloud auth + per-job token permissions + pull_request_target audit + actionlint gate).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gha-workflow-structure" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gha-workflow-structure">
    <summary>Generates a workflow-structure config (trigger types + concurrency groups + jobs-as-DAG via needs + environment protection + scheduled jobs + manual escape hatch).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="github-actions-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/github-actions-basics">
    <summary>Generates an entry-level GHA config (single repo workflow with trigger + permissions + a canonical 2-job pipeline + cache + artifact) that pre-installs the discipline of the later methodologies.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="github-actions-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/github-actions-cicd">
    <summary>Hardened GitHub Actions workflow config: SHA-pinned third-party actions, minimal permissions, OIDC to cloud, fork-safe pull_request_target gating.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitlab-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gitlab-cicd">
    <summary>GitLab CI configuration: staged pipelines, child pipelines for monorepos, OIDC auth to cloud, protected variables and required Merge-Request approvals.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitlab-cicd-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gitlab-cicd-cicd">
    <summary>Generates a GitLab pipeline config (stages + jobs DAG via needs + rules + protected/masked variables + sast/secret scanning + cache/artifact split) for DevSecOps pipelines.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gitops">
    <summary>GitOps spec for declarative delivery: repo layout (apps + envs), reconciler choice (Argo CD vs Flux), drift policy and progressive rollout gating.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops-core-principles" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gitops-core-principles">
    <summary>Generates a GitOps-adoption config (declarative-state baseline + Git-as-source-of-truth policy + tool choice ArgoCD vs Flux + push-vs-pull model + phased rollout) per the OpenGitOps four principles.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops-flux" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gitops-flux">
    <summary>Generates a Flux config (GitRepository + Kustomization + HelmRelease + ImagePolicy CRDs + multi-source reconciliation + notification controller) for Kubernetes GitOps without a UI.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops-progressive-delivery" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gitops-progressive-delivery">
    <summary>Generates a progressive-delivery config (canary or blue-green via Flagger or Argo Rollouts + automated metric-based rollback + traffic shifting via service mesh or ingress).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops-repository-structure" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gitops-repository-structure">
    <summary>Generates a GitOps config-repo layout config (monorepo with base + overlays per env + Kustomize/Helm patterns + multi-team tenant structure + promotion via PRs).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gitops-secrets-security" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/gitops-secrets-security">
    <summary>Generates a GitOps secrets-and-security config (SOPS with age/KMS or Sealed Secrets or External Secrets + RBAC least-privilege + AI-agent gotchas + secret rotation cadence).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="grafana-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/grafana-basics">
    <summary>Generates a Grafana baseline config (datasource registry + dashboards-as-code via JSON / Grafonnet + alerting rules + folder structure + RBAC) covering metrics + logs + traces.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="grafana-dashboards" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/grafana-dashboards">
    <summary>Dashboard spec: RED/USE structure, variable parameterisation, alert-linked panels and version-controlled JSON dashboards with provisioning manifests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="grafana-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/grafana-setup">
    <summary>Generates a Grafana deployment config (Docker / Kubernetes / HA topology + database backend + provisioning configuration + Alloy agent migration + RBAC + backup) for production-grade setup.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="greenfield-infra-decision-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/greenfield-infra-decision-matrix">
    <summary>Pre-build decision matrix for greenfield infra: self-host vs managed, EKS vs ECS vs Cloud Run, Terraform vs Pulumi, single-region vs multi-region, with weighting + red-flags + go/no-go criteria.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="headroom-cost-model" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/headroom-cost-model">
    <summary>Headroom + cost model that captures capacity safety margin per resource, per-resource cost, peak-traffic projection, and triggers a re-evaluation when actual usage crosses 70% of provisioned capacity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="helm-advanced" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/helm-advanced">
    <summary>Production Helm chart spec (config): library charts, hooks, tests, umbrella composition, checksum annotations, required-values guards, resource-policy keep.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="helm-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/helm-basics">
    <summary>Helm chart bootstrap spec (config): Chart.yaml + values.yaml + templates/ + Chart.lock with environment-specific values files and release-lifecycle conventions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="helm-charts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/helm-charts">
    <summary>Helm chart scaffold: Chart.yaml v2 with kubeVersion, values.schema.json, pinned dependencies, lint-clean templates and test hooks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="helm-values-diff-reviewer" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/helm-values-diff-reviewer">
    <summary>Renders the values delta for a Helm bump as a reviewable artefact: rendered-manifest diff + risk classification per change + named approver per risk tier, so silent values changes cannot ship to prod.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/iac-basics">
    <summary>IaC adoption decision-record (config): tool choice (Terraform vs Pulumi vs CDK), state backend, secret strategy, CI pattern, baseline module catalogue.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-patterns-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/iac-patterns-cicd">
    <summary>Pipeline spec (config) for Terraform/Pulumi CI: plan-on-PR + apply-on-merge gates, WIF auth, drift detection, atlantis/spacelift mode, environment promotion.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-patterns-composition" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/iac-patterns-composition">
    <summary>Module composition rubric (config): root vs leaf modules, dependency graph rules, output contracts, inter-module data passing without circular refs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-patterns-dry" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/iac-patterns-dry">
    <summary>DRY rubric (config) for IaC repos: when to factor (rule of three), for_each over copy-paste, locals + module inputs, env-overlay via tfvars/Pulumi stack config.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-patterns-module-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/iac-patterns-module-design">
    <summary>Module shape spec (config): minimal-surface inputs, typed outputs, README + examples, versioning rules, deprecation policy, validation block discipline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-patterns-testing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/iac-patterns-testing">
    <summary>Test-pyramid spec (config) for IaC modules: validate/fmt/lint (unit), plan-diff (component), terratest/integration (real cloud), policy-as-code (OPA/Sentinel) gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="iac-pr-review-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/iac-pr-review-checklist">
    <summary>Reviewer checklist for IaC / Helm / GitHub-Actions pull requests covering blast radius, IAM, state safety, secrets and rollback procedure.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="image-digest-pinning-policy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/image-digest-pinning-policy">
    <summary>Policy config pinning container images by SHA256 digest in production manifests with documented rotation cadence and exception register.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="incident-response-blameless-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/incident-response-blameless-playbook">
    <summary>Severity matrix + IC RACI + comms templates + blameless retro structure as one versioned artefact, with named owners per role and a published cadence \u2014 the operational scaffold pro-tier teams need.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jenkins-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/jenkins-basics">
    <summary>Generates a Declarative Jenkinsfile + JCasC YAML with K8s/Docker agents, zero-executor controller, pinned plugins, withCredentials secrets, and post cleanup.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jenkins-pipeline-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/jenkins-pipeline-patterns">
    <summary>Generates production-grade Declarative Jenkinsfiles + version-pinned Shared Libraries + isolated parallel stages + K8s pod templates for brownfield orgs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jenkins-pipelines" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/jenkins-pipelines">
    <summary>Declarative Jenkinsfile scaffold: typed parameters, parallel stages, Kubernetes pod agents, shared-library pinning and post-build cleanup.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-basics">
    <summary>Workload baseline spec (config): Deployment + Service + ConfigMap + Secret + RBAC ServiceAccount; namespace, labels, probes, container security context defaults.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-canary-progressive" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-canary-progressive">
    <summary>Progressive-delivery spec (config): Argo Rollouts / Flagger strategy, weight steps, analysis templates with SLO queries, auto-promote / auto-rollback thresholds.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-deployment-workloads" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-deployment-workloads">
    <summary>Workload-kind decision-record (config): Deployment vs StatefulSet vs DaemonSet vs Job vs CronJob - pick rule + manifest skeleton with required fields per kind.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-limitrange" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-limitrange">
    <summary>Per-namespace LimitRange config: container defaults, min/max bounds, ratio constraints - produced as a namespaced YAML applied before workloads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-resource-quota" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-resource-quota">
    <summary>Namespace ResourceQuota config: aggregate CPU/memory/storage caps, object-count caps, pod-priority scopes - produced as YAML enforced cluster-wide.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-resource-requests-limits" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-resource-requests-limits">
    <summary>Per-container request/limit config: CPU + memory pair design, QoS class targeting, headroom ratio, observability hooks - produced as patch spec for Deployment containers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-rolling-update" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-rolling-update">
    <summary>Rolling-update strategy config: maxUnavailable / maxSurge tuning, PodDisruptionBudget pair, minReadySeconds, progressDeadlineSeconds - produced as a Deployment patch.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-scaling-availability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-scaling-availability">
    <summary>Scaling + availability spec (config): HorizontalPodAutoscaler v2, topology-spread, anti-affinity, PDB, multi-AZ node-pool target - produced as deployment-extension manifest.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-security-hardening" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-security-hardening">
    <summary>Pod-and-namespace hardening config: PodSecurity Admission (Restricted), NetworkPolicy default-deny, NoNewPrivileges, dropped capabilities, readOnlyRootFS, image-policy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-version-upgrade-runbook-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-version-upgrade-runbook-template">
    <summary>End-to-end runbook spec for major-version K8s upgrade: API deprecation audit, addon compat, etcd backup, control-plane upgrade, node-pool rolling refresh, validation, rollback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="k8s-vpa-rightsizing-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/k8s-vpa-rightsizing-runbook">
    <summary>Runs the VPA recommend → soak → HPA-reconcile → canary → full-rollout → recompute cycle and produces a per-cluster cost-reduction report with audit trail.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kubernetes" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/kubernetes">
    <summary>Production-readiness checklist for Kubernetes workloads: resource requests + limits, three probes, hardened security context, PDB, image pinning and HPA wiring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kubernetes-deployment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/kubernetes-deployment">
    <summary>Decision record selecting Rolling Update, Blue-Green or Canary deployment strategy with rollback wiring and progressive-delivery gating.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-algorithms" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-algorithms">
    <summary>Generates a load-balancing algorithm choice (round-robin, weighted RR, least-conn, weighted LC, least-response-time) + LB config snippet driven by traffic profile.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-cloud-terraform" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-cloud-terraform">
    <summary>Generates Terraform HCL for AWS ALB/NLB or GCP Global HTTP(S) LB with TLS-1.2+ listener, S3/CS access logs, deletion protection, target groups, and WAF wiring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-haproxy-production" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-haproxy-production">
    <summary>Generates a production HAProxy config with TLS-1.2+/1.3, stick-table rate-limiting, path-based ACL routing, keepalived VIP HA, and tuned maxconn/nbthread.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-health-checks" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-health-checks">
    <summary>Generates /health + /health/live + /health/ready endpoints (Python/Node/Go) with bounded dependency probes + LB probe config (intervals + thresholds).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-high-availability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-high-availability">
    <summary>Generates an HA LB topology decision-record (active-pass/active-act, multi-AZ, anycast vs DNS GSLB, drain wiring) with explicit failure-domain analysis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-kubernetes-ingress" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-kubernetes-ingress">
    <summary>Generates a Kubernetes Ingress / Gateway API config with ≥3-replica controller + PDB + anti-affinity + topology-spread + TLS via cert-manager + per-route annotations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-layer-selection" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-layer-selection">
    <summary>Generates a layered LB topology decision (L4 vs L7 vs hybrid L4-front-of-L7) consistent with traffic profile, content routing, and TLS strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-monitoring" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-monitoring">
    <summary>Generates a Prometheus scrape + 4-alert rule set + Grafana dashboard + log shipping config for HAProxy / Nginx LBs with per-backend dimensions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-nginx-production" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-nginx-production">
    <summary>Generates a production Nginx LB config with worker tuning, upstream zone, keepalive, TLS 1.2+, security headers, rate-limit zones, and proxy_next_upstream retry.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-session-persistence" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-session-persistence">
    <summary>Generates a session-persistence decision (externalize → cookie-sticky → IP-hash) + LB config snippet picking the right method for the client + scaling constraints.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lb-technology-selection" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lb-technology-selection">
    <summary>Generates a decision-record naming the LB technology (HAProxy / Nginx / cloud-managed / K8s ingress) based on layer, environment, scale, and ops capacity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lean-stack-bootstrapper-blueprint" tier="free" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/lean-stack-bootstrapper-blueprint">
    <summary>Produces a free-tier reference architecture spec: Vercel + Supabase + Stripe + Cloudflare + one observability vendor, with cost ceiling, upgrade triggers, and vendor-lock acceptance note.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="load-balancing-concepts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/load-balancing-concepts">
    <summary>Picks LB layer (L4/L7), algorithm, health-check + session-persistence policy, and HA topology for a given service.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="manual-override-ledger" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/manual-override-ledger">
    <summary>Decision-record ledger for every config drift override: who, what, why, time-to-revert, link to upstream PR. Turns ad-hoc out-of-band changes into auditable records.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-burn-rate-slo-recipe" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/multi-burn-rate-slo-recipe">
    <summary>Multi-window multi-burn-rate SLO alert configuration: short+long windows for fast/slow burn detection, alert routing, false-positive tuning, runbook hooks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-machine-offline-cache" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/multi-machine-offline-cache">
    <summary>Spec for faion CLI per-machine cache, deterministic offline fallback, license-aware re-activation across laptop + workstation + client-issued device.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-machine-outsource-dev-env-bootstrap" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/multi-machine-outsource-dev-env-bootstrap">
    <summary>Spec for bootstrapping a senior outsource specialist's multi-machine dev env (laptop + desktop + VDI) per engagement, with isolation per client.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-region-active-active-pattern" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/multi-region-active-active-pattern">
    <summary>Active-active multi-region architecture spec: write conflict policy, eventual-consistency budget, partition-tolerance plan, regional failover drill cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="nginx-configuration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/nginx-configuration">
    <summary>Nginx server configuration: TLS profile, upstream health checks, rate-limit zones, security headers and proxy-cache sizing for production workloads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="nginx-configuration-cicd" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/nginx-configuration-cicd">
    <summary>Produces an nginx config (server block + snippets) for reverse-proxy + TLS 1.2/1.3 + security headers + caching, with rate-limit zones and explicit upstream definition.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="nomad-async-ops-stack" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/nomad-async-ops-stack">
    <summary>Generates a nomad-ops spec — offline-tolerant editor stack, timezone-aware payment ops schedule, async customer-support SLA — so a digital-nomad solo founder operates from flaky wifi without dropped balls.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="observability-stack-decision-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/observability-stack-decision-matrix">
    <summary>Decision-record matrix for choosing observability stack (Prometheus+Loki+Tempo vs Datadog vs New Relic vs Grafana Cloud) based on team size, budget, compliance, vendor-lock tolerance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="offline-toolkit-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/offline-toolkit-checklist">
    <summary>Offline-ready laptop checklist for indie hackers on travel days: pre-synced Notion, repo clones, env vars, Stripe CSV exports, and a deterministic restore drill before flight.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="on-call-handoff-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/on-call-handoff-template">
    <summary>Per-shift on-call handoff report template: open incidents, watch-list alerts, paged-but-resolved log, planned maintenance, hand-over notes per service.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="on-call-rotation-bootstrap" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/on-call-rotation-bootstrap">
    <summary>Bootstrap kit for designing a humane on-call rotation: shift length, escalation tree, comp-time policy, follow-the-sun handoff, on-call-load metrics, and a dual-track for new joiners.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="on-call-rotation-setup" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/on-call-rotation-setup">
    <summary>On-call rotation configuration: shift length, schedule generator, primary/secondary tiers, paging policies, compensation, fairness audit cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="on-call-shift-retro-cadence" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/on-call-shift-retro-cadence">
    <summary>Per-shift retrospective cadence + report: what paged, what was noise, what should auto-remediate, what alerts to delete. Feeds back into runbook + alert tuning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="oncall-handoff-protocol" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/oncall-handoff-protocol">
    <summary>Structured on-call handoff: open incidents, pending follow-ups, known-quiet-period plans, paged-but-not-resolved items, escalation contacts, fatigue note.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="one-person-rollback-runbook" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/one-person-rollback-runbook">
    <summary>Verified rollback runbook for solo SaaS: code revert, database migration down, feature-flag flip, smoke checks, and a single dry-run pass before the staging-to-prod gate opens.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="opentelemetry-collector-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/opentelemetry-collector-architecture">
    <summary>Architecture spec for OTel Collector deployment: agent vs gateway tier, receivers/processors/exporters pipeline, batching + retry, mTLS, capacity sizing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="opentelemetry-instrumentation-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/opentelemetry-instrumentation-playbook">
    <summary>Step-by-step instrumentation playbook: auto-instrumentation vs manual, semantic-convention tags, trace context propagation, sampling, baggage, PII scrubbing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="opentelemetry-rollout-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/opentelemetry-rollout-runbook">
    <summary>Step-by-step rollout runbook for OTel: pilot service, sampling baseline, collector capacity, vendor cutover, decommission of legacy agents, KPI dashboards.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pci-dss-vendor-evidence-pack" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/pci-dss-vendor-evidence-pack">
    <summary>Audit-ready evidence pack template for PCI-DSS vendor assessments: scope statement, SAQ type, AoC, network diagrams, key-management proof, quarterly ASV scan, pen-test summary.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="per-client-credential-isolation-pattern" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/per-client-credential-isolation-pattern">
    <summary>Per-client credential isolation pattern: pinned config artefact that separates SSH/GPG/cloud credentials per client engagement so a leak in one engagement cannot cascade to others.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="platform-engineering" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/platform-engineering">
    <summary>Produces an Internal Developer Platform (IDP) spec: golden paths, service catalogue choice, DORA + platform metrics, RBAC + AI-agent citizenship model.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="platform-team-charter-template" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/platform-team-charter-template">
    <summary>Platform team charter: mission, customers, scope/non-scope, paved-road services, SLAs, support model, success metrics, anti-charter (what we do NOT do).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prometheus-monitoring" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/prometheus-monitoring">
    <summary>Prometheus monitoring spec: metric naming + label cardinality limits + recording rules + alert hygiene + scrape-interval discipline for Kubernetes workloads.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prr-checklist-canonical" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/prr-checklist-canonical">
    <summary>PRR (production-readiness review) checklist: fixed-shape, owner-signed, evidence-anchored, quarterly-reviewed gate run before any new service goes to production.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="regulated-incident-response-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/regulated-incident-response-protocol">
    <summary>Regulated incident response protocol: clock-aware playbook that orders isolation, compliance-officer first-call, pre-approved comm templates, and counsel-reviewed postmortem under PCI/HIPAA/GDPR clocks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="release-strategy-canary-blue-green-feature-flag" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/release-strategy-canary-blue-green-feature-flag">
    <summary>Release strategy decision record: picks between canary, blue-green, feature-flag, or ring deploy per service shape with observation window, rollback trigger, and cleanup policy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="restore-drill-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/restore-drill-template">
    <summary>Restore drill template: fixed-shape weekly backup-verification artefact with RTO targets per data class, evidence anchors, and named owner for outcome review.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rotation-evidence-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/rotation-evidence-template">
    <summary>Rotation evidence template: audit-grade record shape (who/what/when/old-fingerprint/new-fingerprint/consumers-notified) SOC2/ISO27001/PCI auditors accept in lieu of screenshots.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rto-rpo-measurement-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/rto-rpo-measurement-template">
    <summary>RTO/RPO measurement template: log-format + timestamp-checkpoint schema that turns DR drills from theatre into recorded recovery-time / recovery-point numbers comparable across drills.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rto-rpo-tracking-board" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/rto-rpo-tracking-board">
    <summary>RTO/RPO tracking board: standing surface that pairs contractual RTO/RPO targets with observed values per system across drills and real incidents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="runbook-as-code-pattern" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/runbook-as-code-pattern">
    <summary>Runbook-as-code pattern: keep runbooks in the service repo, version them, test them in CI, and deep-link from alerts so stale or wrong steps fail loudly before an incident.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scheduled-job-decommission-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/scheduled-job-decommission-checklist">
    <summary>Scheduled-job decommission checklist: structured cron / scheduled-task retirement procedure with consumer-impact survey, parallel-run window, and evidence of clean stop.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="secret-consumer-discovery" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/secret-consumer-discovery">
    <summary>Secret consumer discovery: enumerates every consumer (repo, service, CI job, scheduler, runtime config) of a given secret before rotation so no callsite is missed and no rollback is improvised.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="secret-rotation-drill-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/secret-rotation-drill-runbook">
    <summary>Secret rotation drill runbook: quarterly rotation + breakglass exercise that produces audit-grade evidence satisfying SOC2 / ISO27001 / PCI rotation controls without scrambling on the day.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="secrets-management" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/secrets-management">
    <summary>Secrets management spec: eliminate static credentials, use cloud identity (IRSA / Workload Identity / OIDC), short-lived dynamic credentials, 30-day rotation, ESO for Kubernetes injection.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="secrets-rotation-end-to-end" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/secrets-rotation-end-to-end">
    <summary>Secrets rotation end-to-end: full lifecycle (cadence, dual-secret window, app-side reload, audit trail) that secrets-management storage docs assume but never spell out.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-as-code" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/security-as-code">
    <summary>Embed security gates as code in every SDLC phase: OPA / Kyverno policies, SAST / SCA / DAST scans wired into CI, signed artifacts, runtime admission control with audit trail.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-container-scanning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/security-container-scanning">
    <summary>Produces a CI config (workflow YAML + trivy.yaml + .trivyignore + cosign signing job) that scans every image build, generates an SBOM, and signs the image with Sigstore keyless OIDC.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-dast" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/security-dast">
    <summary>Produces a DAST CI config (ZAP or Nuclei) that scans STAGING only, with explicit scope file, scheduled cadence, and SARIF upload — never targets production.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-policy-as-code" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/security-policy-as-code">
    <summary>Produces a Kyverno ClusterPolicy bundle (or OPA/Gatekeeper Rego pack) deployed via GitOps in audit-first mode, with kyverno test / conftest verify unit tests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-sast" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/security-sast">
    <summary>Produces a SAST CI config (Semgrep / CodeQL / etc.) with PR-gate on CRITICAL+HIGH only, MEDIUM+LOW informational, baseline for legacy code, and pinned scanner version.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-supply-chain" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/security-supply-chain">
    <summary>Produces a supply-chain config bundle (pre-commit + CI hooks, SBOM gen, license policy) plus a fix-PR workflow for known-vulnerable dependencies.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sentry-alert-routing-for-solos" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/sentry-alert-routing-for-solos">
    <summary>Generates a solo-alerting.yaml config — Sentry + Plausible + email-bounce + uptime → filter → digest → quiet-hours → single channel — so one human is paged only for actionable incidents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sentry-supabase-vercel-wiring" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/sentry-supabase-vercel-wiring">
    <summary>Concrete integration recipe wiring Sentry into a Next.js-on-Vercel + Supabase solo stack: source-map upload via bundler plugin, edge-runtime sampling cap, Supabase auth-payload scrubbing, RLS error classification.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="service-ownership-map-template" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/service-ownership-map-template">
    <summary>Service ownership map: per-service owning team, on-call contact, SLO link, runbook link, dependencies, current health badge — kept in version control.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="shared-infra-capacity-board" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/shared-infra-capacity-board">
    <summary>Shared infra capacity board: weekly cross-team surface that pairs upcoming demand on shared Kafka/Redis/DB with current headroom so capacity fights are scheduled, not surprised.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="slo-burn-decision-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/slo-burn-decision-matrix">
    <summary>Decision matrix mapping fast-burn vs slow-burn SLO error-budget patterns to specific operational actions (canary halt, ship freeze, focus shift, accept) so error-budget burn becomes deterministic.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="slo-definition-template-per-service-class" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/slo-definition-template-per-service-class">
    <summary>SLI/SLO definition templates keyed by service class (API, async worker, batch, static asset, scheduled job) with explicit SLI selection rules and error-budget calibration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="slo-design-from-user-journeys" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/slo-design-from-user-journeys">
    <summary>SLO design from user journeys: anchors SLIs and SLO targets on observable user journeys (not infra metrics) before the first production deploy so error budget tracks real harm.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="slo-error-budget-policy-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/slo-error-budget-policy-template">
    <summary>SLO error budget policy: one-page artefact mapping budget state (healthy / yellow / red / exhausted) to concrete actions (ship / freeze / focus / escalate) with a named owner.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="soc2-control-map-vendor-side" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/soc2-control-map-vendor-side">
    <summary>SOC 2 control map (vendor side): one-page artefact mapping existing SAST/DAST/supply-chain controls onto SOC 2 Trust Services Criteria so audit prep is incremental, not a panic project.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="soc2-control-to-repo-artifact-map" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/soc2-control-to-repo-artifact-map">
    <summary>Per-SOC2-control mapping to live repo artifacts (CI config, runbook, IaC file, audit log path) — so auditors and engineers reference the same evidence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-deploy-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/solo-deploy-checklist">
    <summary>Generates a one-page pre/during/post deploy checklist for a solo operator — explicit go/no-go criteria per line — gated by a documented rollback path.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-incident-triage-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/solo-incident-triage-checklist">
    <summary>Generates a one-page incident-triage checklist for a solo operator — assess, contain, communicate, fix, learn — gated by a named on-call owner.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ssl-tls-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/ssl-tls-setup">
    <summary>SSL/TLS setup spec: TLS 1.3 default, modern cipher suite, automated cert renewal (cert-manager / Let's Encrypt), HSTS preload, OCSP stapling, mTLS for service-to-service where applicable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="supabase-backup-and-restore-drill" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/supabase-backup-and-restore-drill">
    <summary>Generates a quarterly Supabase backup-and-restore drill plan + verified-restore evidence — provider snapshot + pg_dump + restore-to-clone — gated by an actual successful restore.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="supabase-rls-audit-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/supabase-rls-audit-checklist">
    <summary>Generates a per-table Supabase RLS audit — enable flag, SELECT/INSERT/UPDATE/DELETE policy presence, anon/auth role coverage — gated by row-level test fixtures.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/terraform">
    <summary>Terraform spec: HCL modules, remote state (S3 + DynamoDB or Terraform Cloud), explicit provider version pinning, plan-review-apply gate, drift detection, secret-free state hygiene.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/terraform-basics">
    <summary>Core Terraform spec: HCL 8-block structure, providers with version pins + default tags, meta-arguments (for_each vs count), lifecycle, remote state with locking, standard file layout.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-iac" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/terraform-iac">
    <summary>Terraform IaC architecture spec: module composition pattern, state-isolation per environment, monorepo vs polyrepo decision, blast-radius limits per workspace, refactor playbook for legacy resources.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-infra" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/terraform-infra">
    <summary>Production-grade Terraform project spec: directory layout, state architecture, CI/CD plan-then-apply gates, tfsec/checkov scanning, OIDC auth, Atlantis flow, drift detection.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-modules-composition" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/terraform-modules-composition">
    <summary>Module composition spec: how root modules wire children, pass outputs as inputs, handle for_each over module instances, avoid deep nesting and circular dependencies.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-modules-prompts" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/terraform-modules-prompts">
    <summary>Prompts spec for AI agents authoring or refactoring Terraform modules: required context (state shape, provider versions, naming convention), output shape, gating questions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-modules-security" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/terraform-modules-security">
    <summary>Per-module security checklist: sensitive var marking, no hardcoded secrets, encryption-by-default, least-privilege IAM, tfsec/checkov in module CI.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-modules-structure" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/terraform-modules-structure">
    <summary>Per-module file structure spec: main.tf, variables.tf with validation, outputs.tf, versions.tf, README.md, examples/. Defines single-responsibility boundary.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-modules-versioning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/terraform-modules-versioning">
    <summary>Semantic versioning spec for Terraform modules: when to bump major/minor/patch, registry publishing flow, version pinning rules in consumers, deprecation policy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="terraform-state" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/terraform-state">
    <summary>Remote state architecture spec: backend choice (S3+DynamoDB, GCS, Terraform Cloud), locking, encryption, import/mv/rm operations, moved blocks, state file recovery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trace-sampling-tail-vs-head" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/trace-sampling-tail-vs-head">
    <summary>Trace sampling decision record: picks between head-based and tail-based sampling per service shape with retention budget, error-bias rule, and replay path for hot-debugging.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="us-uk-eu-compliance-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/us-uk-eu-compliance-matrix">
    <summary>Side-by-side obligation matrix across US (CCPA/CPRA, state privacy), UK (UK-GDPR, DPA 2018), EU (GDPR, DSA, AI Act) covering entity registration, data handling, contracts, tax, so micro-agencies check obligations per market without re-reading three statutes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vdi-vs-byod-decision-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/vdi-vs-byod-decision-matrix">
    <summary>VDI vs BYOD decision matrix: scored decision record picking between virtual desktop infrastructure and bring-your-own-device per client engagement using data-class, residency, audit, and cost axes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vendor-lock-in-audit-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/infra/vendor-lock-in-audit-checklist">
    <summary>Vendor lock-in audit checklist: scored review of platform-specific surface (managed services, proprietary APIs, egress costs, data-format) producing an exit-cost estimate per dependency.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
