<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="product-lifecycle Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for product-lifecycle. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require at least 6 quarters of data before making a stage assessment. One-quarter dip does not equal Decline.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Short data windows produce false stage calls. A temporary dip from seasonality or a one-off event looks identical to structural decline with fewer than 6 data points.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use category-specific baselines for growth thresholds, not the classic defaults (20%=growth, 10%=maturity). Consumer apps: 100%+; B2B vertical SaaS: 30%; mature enterprise: 10%.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs anchor on framework defaults. Injecting category baselines prevents misclassifying a healthy 15%-growth B2B product as "Maturity" when its peers grow at 12%.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sunset is a feature, not a failure: provide a clear migration path and grace period. Plan customer communications before announcing.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Silent EOL destroys trust and forces customers to scramble. Proactive migration support preserves the relationship and reputation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Strategy must match stage. Growth tactics on a declining product and efficiency focus on an early-stage product both waste resources.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mismatched strategy is the core failure lifecycle management solves. Growth spend on decline accelerates burn; efficiency focus on Introduction starves learning loops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every stage assessment must include an alt hypothesis: "what would I expect if this assessment is wrong?"</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-hypothesis stage calls are overconfident. An alt hypothesis makes the assessment falsifiable and triggers re-evaluation when signals diverge.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start transition planning one quarter before the expected stage change. Capability gaps (team mix, infra, KPIs) take a quarter to fill.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stage transitions that catch teams unprepared result in wrong-stage activity continuing for months past the transition point, wasting resources.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stage transition decisions (kill, sunset, double-down) are leadership decisions. Agent output is decision-support only; it never auto-publishes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stage transition triggers resource reallocation, team changes, and customer communications. These have organizational authority requirements agents do not satisfy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
