<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-lifecycle-stages" title="Product Lifecycle Stage Definitions">
  <summary>Four lifecycle stages with characteristics, focus areas, key metrics, and stage-assessment indicators.</summary>

  <section title="Stage Overview">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require at least 6 quarters of data before making a stage assessment. One-quarter dip does not equal Decline.</statement>
      <rationale>Short data windows produce false stage calls. A temporary dip from seasonality or a one-off event looks identical to structural decline with fewer than 6 data points.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use category-specific baselines for growth thresholds, not the classic defaults (20%=growth, 10%=maturity). Consumer apps: 100%+; B2B vertical SaaS: 30%; mature enterprise: 10%.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs anchor on framework defaults. Injecting category baselines prevents misclassifying a healthy 15%-growth B2B product as "Maturity" when its peers grow at 12%.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Introduction Stage">
    <list>
      <item>Revenue: low or negative</item>
      <item>Growth: high uncertainty, frequent pivots</item>
      <item>Profitability: negative</item>
      <item>Competition: low</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <item>Focus: product-market fit, learning, core feature refinement, user feedback</item>
      <item>Key metrics: activation rate, early retention (D7), NPS from early users</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Growth Stage">
    <list>
      <item>Revenue: rapidly increasing</item>
      <item>Growth: 20%+ YoY (category-adjusted)</item>
      <item>Profitability: improving, often breakeven</item>
      <item>Competition: increasing</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <item>Focus: customer acquisition, feature expansion, team growth, infrastructure scaling</item>
      <item>Key metrics: growth rate, CAC, LTV, market share, MRR</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Maturity Stage">
    <list>
      <item>Revenue: stable or slowly growing</item>
      <item>Growth: below 10% YoY (category-adjusted)</item>
      <item>Profitability: peak margins</item>
      <item>Competition: intense</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <item>Focus: efficiency, retention, incremental improvements, cost optimization</item>
      <item>Key metrics: profitability, churn, NPS, efficiency ratios</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Decline Stage">
    <list>
      <item>Revenue: decreasing YoY</item>
      <item>Growth: negative</item>
      <item>Competition: shifting to newer technology</item>
      <item>Customers: actively migrating away</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <item>Focus: cash harvesting, managed decline, migration support, sunset planning</item>
      <item>Key metrics: cash flow, migration rate, support cost, timeline to sunset</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Sunset is a feature, not a failure: provide a clear migration path and grace period. Plan customer communications before announcing.</statement>
      <rationale>Silent EOL destroys trust and forces customers to scramble. Proactive migration support preserves the relationship and reputation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
