<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-lifecycle-strategy" title="Stage-Appropriate Strategy, Assessment Process, and Agent Workflow">
  <summary>Strategy table per stage, assessment process, transition planning, agent pipeline, and critical gotchas for lifecycle classification.</summary>

  <section title="Stage-Appropriate Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Strategy must match stage. Growth tactics on a declining product and efficiency focus on an early-stage product both waste resources.</statement>
      <rationale>Mismatched strategy is the core failure lifecycle management solves. Growth spend on decline accelerates burn; efficiency focus on Introduction starves learning loops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Introduction: MVP, iteration | awareness marketing | lean operations</item>
      <item>Growth: features + scale | acquisition marketing | build team and infra</item>
      <item>Maturity: optimize + extend | retention marketing | efficiency focus</item>
      <item>Decline: maintenance only | migration support | wind down costs</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Assessment Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Pull 8 quarters of: revenue, growth rate YoY, gross margin, net revenue retention, new logos, churn</item>
      <item>Step 2: Compare against category baselines (not framework defaults)</item>
      <item>Step 3: Assess stage with confidence band (High/Medium/Low) and alt hypothesis</item>
      <item>Step 4: Apply stage-appropriate strategy; identify misaligned current activities</item>
      <item>Step 5: Plan transition — what signals next stage, what capabilities are needed</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every stage assessment must include an alt hypothesis: "what would I expect if this assessment is wrong?"</statement>
      <rationale>Single-hypothesis stage calls are overconfident. An alt hypothesis makes the assessment falsifiable and triggers re-evaluation when signals diverge.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/lifecycle-assessment.md">Metrics table, stage indicator matrix, assessed stage with confidence, actions to start/stop, transition planning.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/stage-strategy-guide.md">Per-stage focus areas, KPI targets, investment priorities, risks, transition triggers.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Transition Planning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start transition planning one quarter before the expected stage change. Capability gaps (team mix, infra, KPIs) take a quarter to fill.</statement>
      <rationale>Stage transitions that catch teams unprepared result in wrong-stage activity continuing for months past the transition point, wasting resources.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent softening "Decline" to "plateau", "transition", or "consolidation".</description>
      <reason>Decline is emotionally loaded and agents soften it. Force the literal stage label in the prompt schema and validate the output field against an allowlist.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Declaring "back to Growth" from one quarter of re-acceleration after a PLG or AI feature drop.</description>
      <reason>Single-quarter re-acceleration could be a blip. Require 2+ sustained quarters before upgrading a stage assessment.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Conflating company stage with product stage in a multi-product company.</description>
      <reason>Individual products within a growing company can be in Decline. Specify product scope explicitly in every assessment prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-Loop Checkpoints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage transition decisions (kill, sunset, double-down) are leadership decisions. Agent output is decision-support only; it never auto-publishes.</statement>
      <rationale>Stage transition triggers resource reallocation, team changes, and customer communications. These have organizational authority requirements agents do not satisfy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
