<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-benefits-framework" title="Benefits Realization Framework">
  <summary>Six-step process for identifying, quantifying, assigning, planning, tracking, and reporting project benefits from initiation through post-delivery measurement.</summary>

  <section title="Output vs Outcome vs Benefit">
    <list>
      <item>Output — what the project delivers (a new CRM system)</item>
      <item>Outcome — behavioral change that the output enables (sales team uses the CRM daily)</item>
      <item>Benefit — measurable value from the outcome (20% more deals closed per quarter)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every benefit must have a quantified target and a named owner before project approval.</statement>
      <rationale>"Soft benefits" without a metric cannot be tracked or disputed. Requiring quantification at approval time forces honest benefit claims and creates accountability before work begins.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Six-Step Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Identify: answer "why are we doing this?" and "how will success be measured?" for each stakeholder group</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Quantify: for each benefit, define metric, baseline value (pre-project), target value, and expected realization date</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Assign Owner: benefit owner is a business stakeholder, NOT the project manager; PM hands off at go-live</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Plan: document prerequisites, enablers (training, process changes, adoption activities), measurement method, and data source</item>
      <item>Step 5 — Track: pull actual values from source systems post-launch; compare to target; compute % realized</item>
      <item>Step 6 — Report: executive-ready status with trend, barriers, recommendations; escalate at-risk benefits to sponsor</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Freeze baseline values in writing with date and source query before launch — agents can re-pull but not redefine.</statement>
      <rationale>A baseline that can be redefined post-hoc makes the benefit un-measurable. Lock the T-0 values in the register; subsequent measurements are compared against them.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Attribution">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-register a control cohort or comparator before launch for any benefit where attribution is contested.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc attribution ("revenue grew, but was it the project or seasonality?") is unresolvable without a pre-planned counterfactual. Difference-in-differences requires a control group defined before intervention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Lead indicators: adoption rate, NPS — track monthly; early signal of benefit trajectory</item>
      <item>Lag indicators: revenue, cost reduction — track quarterly; realize 6-18 months post-launch</item>
      <item>Cap claimable benefits at portfolio level to prevent double-counting across projects</item>
      <item>Sunset the benefits register at 24 months unless extended — long tails distort portfolio metrics</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/benefits-register.md">Benefits register table with all required fields</reference>
    <reference path="templates/benefits-report.md">Post-launch benefits status report template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/business-case-benefits.md">Business case benefits section with ROI/NPV calculation</reference>
  </section>
</text>
