<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-benefits-antipatterns" title="Benefits Realization Antipatterns and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Common failure modes in benefits realization and specific pitfalls when agents participate in benefit cataloging, measurement, and attribution.</summary>

  <section title="Structural Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>PM owns benefits after go-live instead of business stakeholder.</description>
      <reason>PMs move to the next project. Benefits that outlast the PM's tenure need a business owner who is accountable for adoption and process change — the two primary enablers of realization.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Benefits register ignored after project closes ("fire and forget").</description>
      <reason>Most benefits realize 6-18 months post-launch. A register reviewed only at go-live misses the window where corrective action (change management, re-training) can still save the benefit.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Benefits overstated in the business case to secure project approval.</description>
      <reason>Inflated benefits create a credibility trap: if realized benefits are 40% of promised, the next project from the same team faces funding skepticism regardless of merit.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Double-counting the same revenue lift across two projects in the same portfolio.</description>
      <reason>Each claimed benefit inflates the portfolio ROI. Cap total claimable benefit at portfolio level and require attribution sign-off from the CFO or PMO for any benefit over a materiality threshold.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require the agent to fail closed when baseline data is missing — never allow "industry average" substitution.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents fabricate baselines from benchmarks when the actual pre-launch value is absent. A fabricated baseline makes the benefit permanently unmeasurable; better to block the benefit claim and demand the real data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Counterfactual analysis: require pre-registered DiD/synthetic control plan; do not let the agent pick a model post-hoc (p-hacking)</item>
      <item>Adoption metrics from telemetry can be inflated by bots; segment human vs automated traffic before computing realization %</item>
      <item>ROI calculations: agents ignore time-value-of-money; require NPV, not raw nominal sum</item>
      <item>Benefit ownership decays silently when owners leave; build a cron check that the owner's email still resolves to an active employee</item>
      <item>Currency and inflation: agents must use the same deflator for baseline and actual measurements</item>
      <item>"AI productivity gain" is the most over-claimed benefit category; require independent validation and a documented measurement method</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="scripts/benefits-track.py">Pull current metric values vs target, emit JSON status and % realized</reference>
    <reference path="scripts/diff-in-diff.py">Difference-in-differences attribution estimation</reference>
  </section>
</text>
