<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="benefits-realization Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for benefits-realization as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>PM owns benefits after go-live instead of business stakeholder.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PMs move to the next project. Benefits that outlast the PM's tenure need a business owner who is accountable for adoption and process change — the two primary enablers of realization.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Benefits register ignored after project closes ("fire and forget").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Most benefits realize 6-18 months post-launch. A register reviewed only at go-live misses the window where corrective action (change management, re-training) can still save the benefit.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Benefits overstated in the business case to secure project approval.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Inflated benefits create a credibility trap: if realized benefits are 40% of promised, the next project from the same team faces funding skepticism regardless of merit.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Double-counting the same revenue lift across two projects in the same portfolio.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each claimed benefit inflates the portfolio ROI. Cap total claimable benefit at portfolio level and require attribution sign-off from the CFO or PMO for any benefit over a materiality threshold.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
