<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="pm-certification-changes-2026 Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for pm-certification-changes-2026 as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>The README is a single-page summary; it omits the actual ECO (Examination Content Outline) tasks/enablers per domain. Agents that quote percentages without ECO tasks produce shallow study plans.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Anchor to PMI Standard for Earned Value (2024), PMBOK 7e, Agile Practice Guide, and the published 2026 ECO PDF.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>"Sustainability" and "Tailoring" are PMI buzzwords; LLMs hallucinate plausible-sounding but non-PMI definitions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Anchor content to authoritative PMI sources: PMBOK 7e, Agile Practice Guide, Process Groups Practice Guide.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Domain weights are not exam question counts; PMI uses scaled scoring per domain. Agents that promise "you must get 26% of Business Environment correct" are wrong.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PMI scaled scoring is not public. Use weights to allocate study effort, not to predict raw question distributions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Exam item bank evolves continuously after July 2026; static content goes stale within months of release.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Plan for ongoing revision. Treat curriculum as a living document, not a one-time PDF.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Regional language exams (UA, RU, ES, ZH) lag English by 1–3 quarters; weights are the same but examples differ.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Translate examples with PMI vocabulary, not literal translation. Maintain language parity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Generating PMP mock questions with LLMs without human PMP-holder review before delivery.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs invent plausible PMI vocabulary that does not appear in the ECO or source texts. Auto-generated PMP items distributed to candidates without review damage exam credibility and candidate preparation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating domain weights as direct question-count percentages.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PMI uses scaled scoring per domain; "26% Business Environment" does not mean 26% of raw questions map to that domain directly. Agents that promise specific question counts mislead candidates.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Applying the 2026 ECO to candidates sitting before July 1, 2026.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-cutover candidates are tested on the 2021 outline; using the new weights for them introduces wrong material and creates confusion about what to prioritize.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs invent PMI vocabulary that "sounds right" (e.g., "Strategic Tailoring Index").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a glossary check against PMBOK 7e index before accepting any term.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Domain weight drift: agents fed old outlines (42/50/8) will silently regress.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin the 33/41/26 weights in the system prompt, not a retrieval doc that can be evicted.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>"Business Environment" is the largest growth area and most under-represented in legacy material — quotas alone do not fix shallow content; require new examples per enabler, not paraphrases.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Invest in original content creation, not repackaging.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Distractor design is hard for LLMs — they often produce options that are obviously wrong or two-correct.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run a self-critique pass on every generated question.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Region/language: same weights, different idioms. Translation agents that copy English idioms into UA/PT lose realism.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Employ bilingual PMI-certified reviewers for regional variants.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Citation hallucination: LLMs love fake page numbers. Validate citations by retrieving the cited PDF page text and checking for keyword overlap before publishing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Build a validation hook into the publishing pipeline.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Never let an agent decide if a candidate is "ready"; emit readiness signals (sub-domain confidence, mock score trend) and let a human instructor make the call.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Preserve human judgment on certification decisions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>PDU/CCRS reporting: do not auto-submit PDUs on a candidate's behalf — PMI compliance issue; agents only draft.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Maintain audit trail and compliance responsibility with human instructors.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
