<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-strategy-and-research" title="Content Strategy, Pillars, and Keyword Research">
  <summary>Defining content pillars mapped to ICP pain points, keyword intent classification, and topic prioritization.</summary>

  <section title="Content Pillars">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define 3-5 content pillars before any keyword research or content creation; each pillar must map to a specific ICP pain point.</statement>
      <rationale>Random content production confuses topical authority signals; pillars enable the algorithm to classify the site as an authority on specific topics, not a generalist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Email marketing tool content pillars</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1. Email marketing tactics (core product alignment)
2. Newsletter growth (adjacent pain point)
3. Email copywriting (skill needed by ICP)
Content mix: 60% SEO-focused, 30% thought leadership, 10% product updates
Publishing cadence: 2 posts/week
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Types by Funnel Stage">
    <list>
      <item>Awareness: blog posts, social content, podcasts — attract via informational keywords</item>
      <item>Consideration: guides, comparisons, webinars — educate on alternatives</item>
      <item>Decision: case studies, demos, free trials — remove objections</item>
      <item>Retention: tutorials, product updates, community — keep customers activated</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Keyword Intent Classification">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every keyword by intent before assigning a content type; wrong content type for the intent reduces conversion even with good rankings.</statement>
      <rationale>A transactional keyword ("notion pricing") requires a product page, not a blog post. Mismatched intent wastes creation effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Informational ("how to manage remote teams"): blog post or guide</item>
      <item>Commercial ("best project management tools"): comparison or listicle</item>
      <item>Transactional ("notion pricing"): product page or pricing page</item>
      <item>Navigational ("slack login"): homepage, do not target with content</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Prioritization Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize high-volume + low-difficulty keywords first; skip low-volume + high-difficulty combinations entirely.</statement>
      <rationale>High-difficulty keywords require domain authority that takes 12-18 months to build; starting with low-difficulty wins generates traffic and builds authority in parallel.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>High volume + low difficulty: quick wins — do first</item>
      <item>High volume + high difficulty: long-term plays — plan for months 6-12</item>
      <item>Low volume + low difficulty: easy wins — fill gaps</item>
      <item>Low volume + high difficulty: skip entirely</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Brief Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every piece of content requires a brief with: primary keyword, search intent, target audience, unique angle, and 2 competitor URLs to beat.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent output quality is directly proportional to brief specificity; vague briefs produce commodity content. Competitor URLs improve output quality significantly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/content-brief.txt">Full content brief template with all required fields</reference>
  </section>
</text>
