<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-creation-and-distribution" title="Content Creation, Distribution, and Measurement">
  <summary>Blog post structure, quality rules, distribution checklist, content ROI formula, and common failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Blog Post Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure every blog post as: keyword-rich headline → hook → definition → why it matters → step-by-step → examples → mistakes → tools → conclusion + CTA.</statement>
      <rationale>This structure matches the top-ranked content pattern for informational queries across most niches; deviating requires a clear differentiation reason.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every published post must be better than the top 3 results and contain at least one piece of original insight, data, or example not present in competitors.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic aggregation content does not rank or convert. E-E-A-T (experience, expertise, authoritativeness, trustworthiness) requires original contribution.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Distribution Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Spend 50% of total content production time on distribution; publishing without distribution is the primary reason content marketing fails to produce traffic.</statement>
      <rationale>The "if you build it they will come" assumption fails in competitive niches. Every piece needs at least 5-7 distribution touchpoints in the first week.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/distribution-checklist.txt">Day-1/Week-1/ongoing distribution steps per published piece</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Distribution Channels">
    <list>
      <item>Owned: email newsletter (day 1), blog, social profiles</item>
      <item>Earned: guest posts, podcast appearances, PR mentions, community shares</item>
      <item>Paid amplification: promoted posts, content discovery (Outbrain/Taboola), retargeting</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Content ROI Formula">
    <p>Content ROI = (Revenue from Content - Content Cost) / Content Cost x 100%</p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Concrete ROI calculation example</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Blog drives 1,000 visits/month
2% convert to trial, 10% trial-to-paid conversion
20 customers x $50/month = $1,000 MRR
Content cost: $500/month (writer + tools)
ROI = ($1,000 - $500) / $500 = 100%
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Traffic: Google Analytics (reach)</item>
      <item>Time on page + scroll depth: engagement quality</item>
      <item>Keyword rankings: Google Search Console</item>
      <item>Backlinks: Ahrefs or Moz (domain authority signal)</item>
      <item>Conversions: GA + product analytics (actual business impact)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Publishing without a distribution plan — "if you build it they will come" approach.</description>
      <reason>Content discovery does not happen organically in competitive niches; active distribution is required for the first 12 months.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Giving up before 12 months of consistent publishing.</description>
      <reason>SEO compounds over 6-12 months; early months produce minimal traffic regardless of content quality. Quitting before compounding begins wastes all prior investment.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Quantity over quality — publishing 5+ thin posts per week.</description>
      <reason>Low-quality content hurts domain authority and brand credibility; fewer better posts outperform in rankings and conversion.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring internal linking between related posts.</description>
      <reason>Internal links distribute page authority and signal topical clusters to search engines; absence reduces ranking potential of all posts.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
