<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="technical-debt-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>A six-step framework for making technical debt visible, quantified, and systematically paid down covering debt registration, impact scoring, capacity allocation, and prevention policies.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>technical-debt</tag>
      <tag>product-management</tag>
      <tag>engineering</tag>
      <tag>prioritization</tag>
      <tag>roadmap</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Technical Debt Management</title>
    <summary>A six-step framework for making technical debt visible, quantified, and systematically paid down — covering debt registration, impact scoring (interest × contagion / effort), capacity allocation, and prevention policies. Debt is classified into six types (deliberate, accidental, bit-rot, design, documentation, test) and prioritized against product work using the same backlog cadence.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Technical debt is invisible to non-technical stakeholders and never competes fairly against features. Without a register and a scoring formula, teams default to ignoring debt until a crisis forces a disruptive rewrite. Anchoring "interest" to measurable slowdown (PR cycle time, MTTR, test flakiness) makes debt economically comparable to feature investment.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Roadmap velocity visibly declining despite stable headcount — need a quantified debt register to defend capacity allocation.</item>
        <item>Quarterly planning where 15-20% of capacity is reserved for paydown and engineering needs a prioritized list.</item>
        <item>Post-P0 outage or regression cluster where the post-mortem identifies debt as root cause.</item>
        <item>Before a major architectural change (auth rewrite, billing migration) — surface debt on the change surface so it is eliminated, not carried forward.</item>
        <item>Multi-repo solopreneur portfolio where debt silently compounds in lower-traffic repos.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF prototypes where the entire codebase is deliberate prudent debt by design — track only debt that blocks the next validation experiment.</item>
        <item>Single-file scripts and one-shot data migrations — registration cost exceeds rewrite cost.</item>
        <item>When engineering has lost trust in PM prioritization — repair trust first via engineer-driven sprints, then introduce the scoring matrix.</item>
        <item>Bit-rot dependency upgrades that are fully automatable (Renovate / Dependabot) — automate, do not bureaucratize.</item>
        <item>Crisis quarters (runway &lt; 6 months, regulator deadline) — freeze the register, ship survival features, resume after.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="when-to-use-agentic">
      <p>A PM is forced to defend roadmap velocity to the business (CEO / board / customer success) when shipping is visibly slowing despite the same headcount, and needs a quantified, item-by-item debt register instead of "engineering says it's slow".</p>
      <p>Quarterly planning where 15-20% of capacity is reserved for paydown; the PM must hand engineering a *prioritized* list (interest × contagion / effort) so reservation does not become a free-for-all.</p>
      <p>Right after a P0 outage, a noisy regression cluster, or a failed launch — when the post-mortem reveals debt as the root cause and the org is briefly willing to fund repayment.</p>
      <p>Before a major architectural change (auth rewrite, billing migration, multi-tenant cutover) — surface debt that touches the change surface so the rewrite eliminates it instead of carrying it forward.</p>
      <p>When acquiring a codebase / vendor / open-source fork: produce a baseline debt register before signing off on integration.</p>
      <p>For solopreneur / faion-net-style portfolios (nero, neromedia, pashtelka, etc.): a single PM-engineer needs a shared register across 5+ small repos so debt does not silently compound in the lower-traffic ones.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="debt-types">
      <p>Technical debt is the implied cost of additional rework caused by choosing easy solutions now instead of better approaches that take longer — borrowing against future productivity.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Deliberate: conscious shortcut, e.g. "ship now, refactor later."</item>
        <item>Accidental: discovered a better pattern after the fact.</item>
        <item>Bit rot: environment changed around stable code — outdated dependencies.</item>
        <item>Design debt: architecture that cannot scale to the next requirement.</item>
        <item>Documentation debt: missing docs mean only one person can maintain the system.</item>
        <item>Test debt: missing tests prevent safe changes to production code.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Deliberate prudent debt is acceptable; deliberate reckless debt is not. Inadvertent debt must be discovered and registered as soon as identified.</statement>
        <rationale>Reckless debt accumulates compounding interest; prudent debt is a conscious trade-off with a planned repayment date.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="six-step-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 1 — Make debt visible: tag every known item in the issue tracker with a tech-debt label; capture what, why, time tax, and fix cost per item.</statement>
        <rationale>Invisible debt cannot be prioritized; registration is the prerequisite for all downstream steps.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 2 — Quantify impact: measure interest as (development slowdown × frequency) + risk cost. Require at least one evidence source (build-time graph, incident post-mortem, PR cycle time delta).</statement>
        <rationale>Without instrumented data the interest score is political; evidence anchors the number to reality.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 3 — Prioritize: score each item on interest rate (40%), contagion (20%), effort to fix (20%), alignment with planned work (20%). Priority = Impact × Alignment / Effort.</statement>
        <rationale>Alignment-weighted scoring ensures the lowest marginal cost paydown happens during adjacent feature work.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 4 — Allocate capacity: reserve 15-20% of every sprint continuously plus one focused quarterly debt sprint. Maintain a separate, visible budget line — never let it merge with the feature backlog.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a hard, visible budget line the allocation evaporates under feature pressure every sprint.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 5 — Pay down strategically: fix during related features (lowest marginal cost), fix highest-interest first, fix blocking debt, batch related items for efficiency.</statement>
        <rationale>Batching related debt reduces context switching cost; fixing during related work amortizes setup overhead.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 6 — Prevent new debt: Definition of Done must include "no new unregistered debt"; code review catches it; architectural decisions are documented.</statement>
        <rationale>Prevention cost is always lower than remediation cost; gate at the point of creation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="anti-patterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Tracking debt item count instead of interest reduction — closing 20 cheap items while leaving the one item that causes 40% of PR delay.</description>
        <reason>Item count is a vanity metric; the business impact is in interest rate reduction (build time, MTTR, PR cycle time).</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>A 6-month-old register with 30-50% stale entries — items fixed silently, descriptions outdated, owners departed.</description>
        <reason>Stale registers destroy credibility; teams stop trusting and stop maintaining them. Re-baseline quarterly.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Registering automatable bit-rot (dependency upgrades, formatter violations) as debt items.</description>
        <reason>Machine-fixable items waste PM prioritization bandwidth; automate via Renovate/Dependabot and remove from the register.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Debt items deferred 4+ quarters with no decision — zombie entries that destroy register credibility.</description>
        <reason>Every zombie must become either "done next quarter" or "accepted debt" — a positive, explicit choice.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ignoring debt entirely — no register, no allocation, no visibility.</description>
        <reason>Without registration, debt is invisible to stakeholders and can never be prioritized against features.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>All-or-nothing approach: waiting for a "debt sprint" that never gets scheduled because features always win.</description>
        <reason>Continuous small allocation (15-20% per sprint) is more durable than periodic large allocations that are always displaced by roadmap pressure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No business case for debt items — technical language only, no $ or hours quantification.</description>
        <reason>Non-technical stakeholders cannot prioritize an item described only in technical terms. Every item needs a business-impact statement (hours/sprint lost, incidents caused, features blocked).</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="worked-examples">
      <section name="example-legacy-api-dual-maintenance">
        <p>Old API v1 still maintained alongside v2 with 20 remaining users. Interest: 3 hours/sprint maintaining both + risk of v1 bugs affecting v2 users + cannot deprecate without a migration plan. Interest rate: High (ongoing time tax). Effort: Medium (migration path for 20 users). Alignment: High (API work planned next quarter). Decision: Score = High × High / Medium = prioritize in Q2 alongside planned API improvements. Lowest marginal cost because the team is already context-loaded on the API surface.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="example-missing-test-coverage-on-billing">
        <p>Billing module has 10% test coverage. Impact: 2 hours extra manual testing per release, fear of changing billing code, a previous billing bug cost $5K. Interest: Medium-High. Effort: High (complex business logic requires deep domain understanding). Alignment: Medium (billing feature planned but not next sprint). Decision: Add tests as part of billing feature work — Boy Scout approach. Not standalone because alignment is medium; standalone effort is high without feature context.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="common-mistakes">
        <antipattern>
          <description>Ignoring debt entirely — no register, no allocation, no visibility.</description>
          <reason>Without registration, debt is invisible to stakeholders and can never be prioritized against features.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>All-or-nothing approach: waiting for a "debt sprint" that never gets scheduled because features always win.</description>
          <reason>Continuous small allocation (15-20% per sprint) is more durable than periodic large allocations that are always displaced by roadmap pressure.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>No business case for debt items — technical language only, no $ or hours quantification.</description>
          <reason>Non-technical stakeholders cannot prioritize an item described only in technical terms. Every item needs a business-impact statement (hours/sprint lost, incidents caused, features blocked).</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations-and-gotchas">
      <p>The "interest" metric (slowdown × frequency) is rarely measured — teams guess and the score becomes politics. Without instrumented build-time / PR-cycle-time / incident-frequency data, the matrix is theatre.</p>
      <p>Registers rot fast: items get fixed silently, descriptions go stale, owners leave. A 6-month-old register typically has 30-50% incorrect entries.</p>
      <p>"20% of every sprint" almost always degrades to 0% under feature pressure. Without a hard, visible budget line (separate JIRA epic, separate burn-down) the allocation evaporates.</p>
      <p>Boy-Scout-rule paydown is invisible to the register and the matrix — debt gets fixed but the metrics still say it's there. Counts of *closed* debt items mislead.</p>
      <p>Cross-cutting debt (e.g., "global auth context", "no event schema") cannot be scoped as one ticket. The matrix wants atomic items; reality has graphs. Debt items either explode into 40 tickets or get one ticket that never closes.</p>
      <p>Debt that lives in a *vendored or external* dependency (NPM, PyPI, third-party SaaS) often cannot be paid down at all — only worked around. Registers that don't separate "ours" from "theirs" misallocate effort.</p>
      <p>LLMs are trained on tutorial code. They will flag legitimate idiomatic patterns as "debt" (e.g., service objects, factories, dependency injection in Python) and miss structural debt (missing abstractions, wrong module boundaries) because it has no local syntactic signal.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive paydown as a three-pass loop. Pass 1 (sonnet-class, cheap, batched): a code-scanner agent walks the repo, parses TODO/FIXME/XXX, lints (`ruff`, `eslint`, `vulture`, `deadcode`), checks dependency freshness (`npm outdated`, `pip-audit`, `cargo outdate`), test coverage deltas, and emits a candidate JSON debt list — one item per finding with a `confidence` score. Pass 2 (opus-class, fewer items): a triage agent merges candidates into the human-curated register, attaches `interest`, `contagion`, `effort`, `alignment` from a rubric, and flags items needing human input (root-cause unclear, owner missing, business impact ambiguous). Pass 3 (sonnet-class): a planner agent reads next-quarter's roadmap and re-scores `alignment` per item ("is this debt on the surface area we will touch?"), then produces a paydown plan: which items get fixed during feature work (lowest marginal cost), which get a dedicated ticket, which stay deferred with a revisit date. Always emit structured JSON; never trust prose. Use `brainstorm` only when the team disagrees on what *counts* as debt.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>`faion-sdd-executor-agent` — once the paydown plan is approved, drive each debt-paydown ticket as a normal SDD task with constitution / spec / test-plan; debt fixes that skip SDD reintroduce debt.</item>
        <item>`improver` — quarterly review loop: read last quarter's register, compare planned vs. actual paydown, log the gap as a *meta-debt* item ("we said 20%, shipped 6%"), feed forward.</item>
        <item>`feature-executor` — when a feature ticket is tagged "touches debt area X", auto-include the debt fix in the same task plan (Boy Scout, but explicit).</item>
        <item>A custom `debt-scanner` subagent (worth creating): input = repo path + last register; output = `{candidate_items[], confidence, evidence_paths[], suggested_type}`. Stateless, run on every PR or nightly.</item>
        <item>A custom `debt-triage` subagent: input = candidate list + register + roadmap; output = scored register + paydown plan JSON. Cheap to re-run weekly.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="scanner-prompt-pattern">
      <prompt purpose="technical-debt-scanner">
        <![CDATA[You are a technical-debt scanner. Walk the repo at <path>. Emit JSON only:
[{id, type: deliberate|accidental|bit_rot|design|docs|test,
  location: "file:line", description, evidence: ["lint_rule", "TODO_text", ...],
  confidence: 0-1, suggested_type, related_files: [...]}]
Rules:
  - Do not flag idiomatic framework patterns (service objects, DI, factories).
  - Require ≥2 evidence types for confidence > 0.6.
  - Skip vendored / generated / .venv / node_modules paths.
  - Group findings by module; one item per logical defect, not per line.]]>
      </prompt>
    </section>
    <section name="triage-prompt-pattern">
      <prompt purpose="technical-debt-triage">
        <![CDATA[You are a debt triage PM. Given <register.json>, <new_candidates.json>,
<roadmap.json>, output JSON: updated register with interest (0-5), contagion (0-5),
effort (0-5), alignment (0-5), priority_score = (interest + contagion) * alignment / max(effort, 1).
Mark items needing human review (no business impact stated, owner unknown,
description ambiguous). Do not invent items. Do not auto-close existing items —
flag them as "fixed?" instead and require a human confirmation.]]>
      </prompt>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>code-climate CLI / Codacy CLI — Static debt scoring (cyclomatic, duplication, churn-vs-complexity hotspots) — https://codeclimate.com/quality</p>
      <p>sonar-scanner (SonarQube / SonarCloud) — Industry-default debt rating (A-E) + remediation-time estimates per file — https://docs.sonarsource.com</p>
      <p>cloc + tokei — Quantify per-module size; pair with churn for a hotspot map — `apt install cloc; cargo install tokei`</p>
      <p>git log --pretty=format:"%h %s" --shortstat + git-of-theseus — Code-age + churn analysis; debt clusters live where churn is high but tests are absent — `pip install git-of-theseus`</p>
      <p>vulture (Python) / ts-unused-exports / knip (JS-TS) — Dead-code detection; dead code is debt with negative interest — `pip install vulture`; `npm i -g knip`</p>
      <p>pip-audit, npm audit, cargo audit, osv-scanner — Bit-rot debt: insecure / outdated deps — https://github.com/pypa/pip-audit</p>
      <p>Renovate / Dependabot CLI configs — Continuous, automated bit-rot paydown — https://docs.renovatebot.com</p>
      <p>lizard — Cyclomatic complexity per function across 20+ languages — `pip install lizard`</p>
      <p>radon — Python-specific maintainability index, halstead metrics — `pip install radon`</p>
      <p>git hotspots (custom one-liner, see Templates) — Fastest free signal of where debt actually hurts — n/a</p>
      <p>gh / glab / jira-cli — Bulk-tag issues with `tech-debt`, query `is:open label:tech-debt` for the register — https://cli.github.com</p>
      <p>claude CLI (Claude Code) — Drive scanner / triage / planner subagents on the register and emit JSON — https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/claude-code</p>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <p>SonarQube / SonarCloud (OSS + SaaS) — "Technical debt ratio" + "remediation effort" per file; PM-readable; expensive at scale</p>
      <p>Code Climate Quality (SaaS) — Maintainability grade per file; good PR-bot; weak on architectural debt</p>
      <p>Codacy (SaaS) — Multi-language, OSS-friendly free tier, GitHub-native</p>
      <p>Snyk Code (SaaS) — Combines security debt + bit-rot debt; agent-driven auto-PRs</p>
      <p>Stepsize (acquired by GitClear) (SaaS) — Built specifically for debt registers tied to JIRA/Linear; PM-oriented</p>
      <p>GitClear (SaaS) — Diff-quality + churn-based debt analytics for PMs</p>
      <p>Cortex / OpsLevel / Backstage (SaaS / OSS) — Service catalogs with "scorecards" — good place to track org-wide debt KPIs</p>
      <p>Linear / Jira / GitHub Projects (SaaS) — Where the register actually lives; pair with API for bulk updates</p>
      <p>Productboard / Aha! (SaaS) — Surface a debt "lane" alongside features so it competes for capacity in the same UI</p>
      <p>Grafana + Prometheus + custom exporters (OSS) — DIY dashboard: build-time, PR-cycle-time, flaky-test rate, MTTR — the *consequences* of debt</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Anchor every register item to evidence. Required fields: `interest_evidence` (URL to a slow-build chart, an incident post-mortem, a PR-review-time graph) and `business_evidence` (cost in $ or hours, named affected feature). Items without both default to `priority = 0` and never get scheduled.</p>
      <p>Track paydown by interest reduction, not item count. Closing 20 cheap items can be theatre; closing the one item that drops PR cycle time 40% is the win. Pair the register with build-time / cycle-time / MTTR dashboards and report deltas.</p>
      <p>Couple debt budget to roadmap budget in the same UI. If the register lives in a separate tool, debt loses every prioritization fight. Same backlog, same scoring, same review cadence.</p>
      <p>Auto-bit-rot. Anything machine-fixable (deps, formatters, unused-imports) should be a Renovate / Dependabot / pre-commit hook, not a register entry. Register only debt that requires judgment.</p>
      <p>Boy-Scout-rule with a ledger. When a feature ticket touches a debt area, the engineer must close the related register item *or* explicitly defer with a reason. Without the ledger, Boy Scout work is invisible to PM.</p>
      <p>Re-baseline quarterly. Delete items where the original author left and no one can describe the impact. Stale items are noise; noise kills the register.</p>
      <p>Pre-commit a kill rule. Any debt item that has been deferred 4+ quarters either gets done next quarter or gets *closed as accepted debt* — a positive choice not to fix it. Zombie items destroy register credibility.</p>
      <p>Separate "ours" from "theirs". Track vendored / SaaS / external-dep debt in a different list with different remediation strategies (workaround, fork, replace, accept).</p>
      <p>Tie the 20% allocation to the engineering manager's quarterly review, not just the PM's. If only the PM owns the budget, engineering will trade it away every sprint.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Scanner agents over-flag idiomatic patterns (DI, factories, service classes, async generators, match-case). Counter with a per-language allow-list of patterns and a `≥2 evidence types` rule before raising confidence above 0.6.</p>
      <p>LLMs are blind to *missing* abstractions. They cannot detect "this should have been a state machine" or "this module should not exist". Hotspot + churn analysis must come from deterministic tooling, not the LLM.</p>
      <p>Triage agents will silently re-rank items each run because LLM scoring is non-deterministic. Persist the *previous* score in the register and require the agent to justify any score change > 1 point.</p>
      <p>Auto-closing items is the most common destructive failure mode. Force the agent to mark items `fixed?` (with evidence) and require a human or CI signal (test passing, lint clean, dep upgraded) before close.</p>
      <p>Debt registers grow unboundedly when agents run unchecked — every PR adds 5 new items. Cap candidate output (top-N by hotspot score) and require human ack before items enter the canonical register.</p>
      <p>LLMs will hallucinate "estimated remediation time"; prefer T-shirt sizes (S/M/L/XL) over hours. Time estimates from agents have negative information value.</p>
      <p>Cross-cutting debt ("we have no event bus") looks identical to a thousand small items in the scanner output. Run a separate `architecture-review` pass (opus, low frequency) to detect graph-level debt; do not expect the file-level scanner to see it.</p>
      <p>For solopreneur multi-repo setups (faion-net portfolio): run scanners per-repo but maintain *one* cross-repo register, otherwise the same dependency upgrade gets logged 6 times and "fixed" 6 times.</p>
      <p>Never let an agent ship a paydown PR unsupervised on production code. Debt fixes change behaviour silently more often than feature PRs do; require human review and full test suite green.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="references">
      <p>Ward Cunningham, "The WyCash Portfolio Management System" (OOPSLA 1992) — original debt metaphor.</p>
      <p>Martin Fowler, "Technical Debt Quadrant" (2009) — deliberate / inadvertent × prudent / reckless framing used in this methodology's README.</p>
      <p>Philippe Kruchten, Robert Nord, Ipek Ozkaya, "Managing Technical Debt" (Addison-Wesley, 2019) — SEI-derived treatment, the standard reference.</p>
      <p>Adam Tornhill, "Software Design X-Rays" (Pragmatic, 2018) — hotspot analysis (churn × complexity); foundation for the script above.</p>
      <p>McConnell, Steve — "Managing Technical Debt" (Construx whitepaper, 2008) — taxonomy still used by Sonar.</p>
      <p>Carnegie Mellon SEI — "Measuring Technical Debt" research line: https://www.sei.cmu.edu/our-work/projects/display.cfm?customel_datapageid_4050=21339</p>
      <p>Stripe — "The Developer Coefficient" (2018) — quantified business cost of debt; PM-friendly numbers.</p>
      <p>SonarSource SQALE method documentation: https://docs.sonarsource.com/sonarqube/latest/user-guide/metric-definitions/</p>
      <p>Stepsize / GitClear blog archives (2020-2024) — practical PM-engineering debt operating models.</p>
      <p>Renovate docs: https://docs.renovatebot.com — automated bit-rot paydown blueprint.</p>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/debt-register.md" purpose="Debt register skeleton with per-item fields (type, impact, effort, priority)."/>
      <template path="templates/debt-prioritization-matrix.md" purpose="Quarterly scoring table and sprint debt budget template."/>
      <template path="templates/debt-hotspots.sh" purpose="Bash script: churn × complexity hotspot analysis feeding a scanner subagent."/>
    </templates>
    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/debt-hotspots.sh" purpose="Finds high-churn + high-complexity files; emits JSONL for triage agent."/>
    </scripts>
  </content>
</methodology>
