<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-pipeline-structure" title="Jenkins Pipeline Structure">
  <summary>Declarative pipeline syntax with essential options, parallel stages, when conditions, and post-build actions.</summary>

  <section title="Declarative vs Scripted">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to declarative syntax. Use scripted (node block) only when you need dynamic logic such as detecting changed services at runtime.</statement>
      <rationale>Declarative is readable, maintainable, and supports all built-in features. Scripted requires Groovy expertise and is harder to review.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Essential Options">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every pipeline must include: timeout, timestamps, buildDiscarder, and disableConcurrentBuilds in the options block.</statement>
      <rationale>timeout prevents hung builds consuming agents; buildDiscarder prevents disk exhaustion; disableConcurrentBuilds prevents race conditions on shared environments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="groovy"><![CDATA[
options {
    timeout(time: 30, unit: 'MINUTES')
    timestamps()
    buildDiscarder(logRotator(numToKeepStr: '10'))
    disableConcurrentBuilds()
    ansiColor('xterm')
}
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Parallel Stages">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use parallel blocks for independent tasks (unit tests, integration tests, security scans) to reduce total build time.</statement>
      <rationale>Sequential execution of independent tasks wastes time. Parallel execution of three 5-minute stages takes 5 minutes, not 15.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="groovy"><![CDATA[
stage('Test') {
    parallel {
        stage('Unit Tests') {
            steps { container('node') { sh 'npm run test:unit -- --coverage' } }
            post { always { junit 'junit.xml' } }
        }
        stage('Integration Tests') {
            steps { container('node') { sh 'npm run test:integration' } }
        }
        stage('Security Scan') {
            steps { container('node') { sh 'npm audit --audit-level=high' } }
        }
    }
}
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="When Conditions and Approval Gates">
    <rule>
      <statement>Gate production deployments with an input block requiring named approvers. Use when { branch 'main' } to prevent feature branches from deploying.</statement>
      <rationale>Unnamed approvals allow anyone to click through. Named submitter restriction enforces change control without external tooling.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="groovy"><![CDATA[
stage('Deploy to Production') {
    when { branch 'main' }
    input {
        message "Deploy to production?"
        ok "Deploy"
        submitter "admin,deployers"
    }
    steps { /* kubectl apply */ }
}
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Post Actions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always clean the workspace in post { always { cleanWs() } }. Send failure notifications in post { failure { ... } }.</statement>
      <rationale>Stale workspace files cause intermittent failures in subsequent builds. Post-failure notifications alert the team without requiring manual monitoring.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hardcoding secrets directly in the pipeline environment block.</description>
      <reason>Secrets in Jenkinsfiles are committed to version control and visible in build logs. Use withCredentials() or the credentials() binding instead.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
