<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="elicitation-techniques">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-core</domain>
    <summary>Deterministic selector for 10 BABOK v3 elicitation techniques. Always pick 1-3 with triangulation: interview + observation, survey + focus group, or document + interview.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>elicitation</tag>
      <tag>babok</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>techniques</tag>
      <tag>stakeholder-engagement</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Elicitation Techniques</title>

    <summary>A deterministic technique-selector for the 10 BABOK v3 elicitation techniques (interview, workshop, focus group, observation, survey, document analysis, prototyping, brainstorming, interface analysis, collaborative game). Select a ranked mix of 1-3 techniques based on concrete situation inputs — never a single technique in isolation. Always triangulate: pair at least two techniques where the second challenges the first.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Stakeholders cannot reliably articulate what they need; the BA must draw it out using the right combination of techniques. The wrong technique wastes sessions or misses whole classes of requirements (e.g., interface analysis is systematically skipped by teams using only the 8-item shortlist). A scored selector with explicit data prerequisites forces transparency about what the team actually knows.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Early-discovery phase: choosing a technique mix from BABOK's 10 and justifying each pick</item>
        <item>Training or onboarding a junior BA or LLM agent needing a deterministic decision tree</item>
        <item>Mixed-method project where triangulation (interview + observation + document analysis) is needed on the same workflow</item>
        <item>Mid-project scope renegotiation: re-elicit only the changed area with the cheapest adequate technique</item>
        <item>Budget/time pressure: structured selector beats ad-hoc choice when sessions must be minimized</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>The technique is already locked by org policy (e.g., regulated industry mandates signed workshops)</item>
        <item>Continuous-discovery shop on a stable product (Teresa Torres cadence) — that is its own pattern</item>
        <item>One-stakeholder, one-sitting situation — just run the interview; selector adds overhead</item>
        <item>Pure UX research with users (not stakeholders) — use ux-researcher/ techniques instead</item>
        <item>Hackathon or spike — prototype and time-box; no BABOK ceremony needed</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="the-10-babok-v3-techniques">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use the full 10-item BABOK v3 list: interview, workshop, focus group, observation, survey, document analysis, prototyping, brainstorming, interface analysis, collaborative game. Never limit to 8 — interface analysis and collaborative games are systematically missed and produce integration-requirement gaps.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams using only the common 8 miss interface requirements (system boundary integrations) and creative convergence options.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Interview — deep individual understanding; best for sensitive topics or unique knowledge holders; cap at 60 min</item>
        <item>Workshop — group consensus on complex topics; use when multiple perspectives are required; cap at 90 min; require ≥40% hands-on time</item>
        <item>Focus Group — similar-user perspectives; produces hypotheses, not requirements (group-think risk); need ≥6 participants</item>
        <item>Observation — passive/active/participant; best for discovering current-state reality vs stated process; cap 2 h/session</item>
        <item>Survey/Questionnaire — broad quantitative input; require N-target + confidence interval + pre-registered analysis plan</item>
        <item>Document Analysis — extract requirements from existing artifacts; record doc_version + retrieval_date; validate with stakeholders</item>
        <item>Prototyping — paper/wireframe/mockup/working; validates design understanding; BABOK also counts in Requirements Analysis</item>
        <item>Brainstorming — idea generation; always pair with a structured convergence step (6-3-5, Round-Robin) — vanilla brainstorming produces volume, not quality</item>
        <item>Interface Analysis — list all inbound/outbound system interfaces; derive integration requirements; commonly skipped</item>
        <item>Collaborative Game — creative elicitation (Product Box, Speed Boat, 20/20 Vision); structured divergence, not a meeting type</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="selection-decision-tree">
      <rule>
        <statement>Walk the decision tree in order; first match wins; cap the output at 3 techniques; document rejected techniques with rationale.</statement>
        <rationale>More than 3 picks means the situation is under-specified — push back to stakeholder-analysis and ba-planning first.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>1. release-scope decision → interview first (sensitivity=high adds weight)</item>
        <item>2. goal=discover_current_state → observation THEN interview (not OR)</item>
        <item>3. goal=build_consensus + group ≥ 4 → workshop</item>
        <item>4. stakeholder_count ≥ 30 + locales &gt; 1 → survey</item>
        <item>5. goal=validate_design + prior_artifacts ≥ 1 → prototyping</item>
        <item>6. goal=generate_ideas → brainstorming + collaborative game (both; brainstorm diverges, game converges)</item>
        <item>7. goal=derive_integrations → interface analysis</item>
        <item>8. prior_artifacts ≥ 3 or regulated=true → document analysis first</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Sequence cheap-then-expensive: document analysis → observation → interview → workshop → prototyping. Stop when confidence target is met.</statement>
        <rationale>The cheapest techniques surface context that makes subsequent expensive sessions more efficient.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="triangulation-rule">
      <rule>
        <statement>Never select a single technique. The second technique must challenge the first: interview claim → observation reality; survey trend → focus-group nuance; document-stated process → observation of actual practice.</statement>
        <rationale>Single-technique elicitation systematically misses the gap between stated and actual behavior, the most common source of late requirement changes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag each elicited statement as stated, observed, or inferred. Treat observed as gold, stated as silver, inferred as bronze; downstream prioritization must respect the tier.</statement>
        <rationale>Blending tiers without tagging causes the same weight to be applied to a vendor assumption and a direct user observation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Leading questions in interview guides ("isn't it true that X?", "don't you find Y difficult?").</description>
        <reason>Leading questions produce confirmation bias; lint guides for "don't you", "wouldn't", "isn't it true" before sending to a stakeholder.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Workshop agenda filled with talk slots; fewer than 40% hands-on activities.</description>
        <reason>Agents skew to presentation slots; the loudest voice dominates and real requirements stay tacit.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Document analysis citing a regulation version that has since been superseded.</description>
        <reason>Outdated regulatory requirements invalidate downstream artifacts silently; record doc_version + retrieval_date on every source.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="two-step-agent-pattern">
      <rule>
        <statement>Drive elicitation as a two-step decision: (1) classify the situation with concrete inputs, (2) select a ranked technique mix with rationale. Never combine steps — a single agent that both classifies and generates guide templates conflates selection bias with execution.</statement>
        <rationale>Separating selection from execution allows the selection output to be reviewed and approved by a human BA before scheduling sessions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Technique-selector prompt — strict JSON output, all inputs required">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are technique-selector-agent. Inputs (all required):
  stakeholder_count, locales, time_budget_days,
  sensitivity in {low,med,high},
  prior_artifacts[],
  regulated in {true,false},
  goal in {discover_current_state, build_consensus, validate_design,
            generate_ideas, quantify_demand, derive_integrations}

Choose 1-3 techniques from BABOK v3 full list:
[interview, workshop, focus_group, observation, survey, document_analysis,
 prototyping, brainstorming, interface_analysis, collaborative_game]

Rank by expected info-yield-per-hour for THIS situation. Output:
{
  picks: [{technique, rationale_cites_inputs[], est_sessions, prerequisite}],
  rejected: [{technique, why_not}],
  triangulation_pair_recommended: boolean
}
Refuse to output if stakeholder_count or goal is null.
]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Interview-guide agent prompt — max 6 questions, no leading phrasing">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are interview-guide-agent.
Inputs: {topic, interviewee_role, objectives[], prior_artifacts[]}
Constraints:
  6 main questions max
  >=2 open + >=2 probing + 1 closing
  No leading phrasing (ban: "don't you", "wouldn't", "isn't it true")
  Each question must reference an objective by index
Output: strict JSON matching the interview-guide template sections.
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>technique-selector-agent (sonnet) — pure selector; reads stakeholder-analysis output; emits ranked technique mix</item>
        <item>interview-guide-agent (haiku) — fills interview-guide template from topic + role + prior artifacts</item>
        <item>workshop-agenda-agent (sonnet) — drafts agenda, enforces ≥40% hands-on time, picks collaborative-game variants by goal</item>
        <item>interface-analysis-agent (sonnet) — lists inbound/outbound system interfaces; derives integration requirements</item>
        <item>brainstorm — use as the converge step after BABOK brainstorming elicitation</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Single-row table fixation: agent reads the selection table and returns one technique, never a mix.</description>
        <reason>Force the prompt to return a mix with an explicit triangulation pair; reject any output with only one technique.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Default-to-interview bias when inputs are sparse.</description>
        <reason>Require explicit stakeholder_count and goal fields; return an error if either is null rather than defaulting to interview.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent proposes "ask the user how they do X" instead of "watch the user do X" when goal is discover_current_state.</description>
        <reason>When goal == discover_current_state, force at least one observation slot in the output.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Brainstorming convergence skipped — agent returns 30 ideas without ranking.</description>
        <reason>Mandate a converge prompt (brainstorm review pass) before the brainstorming output is accepted.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Survey question type imbalance — agent over-uses Likert scale.</description>
        <reason>Mix multiple-choice + ranking + 1 open question per section; validate against a known-good template.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="human-in-the-loop-checkpoints">
      <list>
        <item>Technique selection signed off by a human BA before scheduling any sessions</item>
        <item>Interviews and workshops run by humans — agents prepare, do not converse with stakeholders</item>
        <item>Synthesis pass into requirement stubs reviewed by humans before feeding requirements-lifecycle</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/interview-guide.md" purpose="Interview guide: objectives, background, main, and closing question sections"/>
      <template path="templates/workshop-agenda.md" purpose="Workshop agenda with time blocks, activity types, materials, and expected outputs"/>
    </templates>

    <section name="when-technique-selection-fails">
      <antipattern>
        <description>The README lists only 8 techniques when BABOK v3 names 10 elicitation techniques.</description>
        <reason>Teams using only the common 8 miss interface analysis and collaborative games. These techniques address system boundaries and creative convergence — skipping them produces integration-requirement gaps.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>The selection table appears one-to-one; real situations need a combination.</description>
        <reason>Real situations require paired techniques where the second challenges the first. Agents tend to pick a single row and stop, missing triangulation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Selector returns a default (interview) regardless of context when inputs are sparse.</description>
        <reason>Selection rule depends on hidden variables: stakeholder count, geographic distribution, sensitivity, pre-existing artifacts, time budget, regulatory regime. Without those inputs the selector fails.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Focus groups treated as a neutral technique when they have statistical biases.</description>
        <reason>Focus-group consensus is biased toward extroverts and toward agreeing with the facilitator. Treat output as hypotheses, not requirements.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Brainstorming alone produces volume, not quality.</description>
        <reason>Always pair with a convergence step (brainstorm does this; vanilla brainstorming does not).</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Document analysis on regulations/standards loses validity fast.</description>
        <reason>The regulation version cited may be superseded. Selector must record doc_version and retrieval_date.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Prototyping treated inconsistently across BABOK sections.</description>
        <reason>BABOK counts prototyping in both elicitation and requirements-analysis-and-design. Without a clear scope flag agents double-count it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="subagent-workflow">
      <p>Drive ba-core elicitation as a two-step decision: (1) classify the situation with concrete inputs, (2) select techniques with rationale per pick. Inputs are stakeholder count, locale spread, time budget, sensitivity, evidence already on hand, regulatory regime. Output is a ranked technique mix with a justification that cites the input variables. Execution is delegated to downstream workflows (artifacts, transcripts, redaction). Keep this focused on fundamentals and selection logic.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-custom-agents">
      <list>
        <item>technique-selector-agent (model: sonnet) — pure selector, no execution. Inputs: situation JSON. Output: ranked techniques + rationale + estimated session count.</item>
        <item>interview-guide-agent (model: haiku) — fills the interview-guide template from topic + role + 3 prior artifacts; cheap because the template is fixed.</item>
        <item>workshop-agenda-agent (model: sonnet) — drafts the workshop-agenda template, balances divergent vs. convergent slots, picks collaborative-game variants (Product Box, Speed Boat) when goal is creative.</item>
        <item>interface-analysis-agent (model: sonnet) — handles the missing technique: list inbound/outbound interfaces of the system under study, derive integration requirements.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="integration-with-sdd">
      <p>Use faion-sdd-executor-agent to wrap each elicitation session as an SDD task with a checklist tied to the technique chosen (interview-prep, workshop-agenda, observation-protocol, etc.). Use brainstorm as the converge step after BABOK "brainstorming" elicitation; raw ideation is one prompt, ranked-merge is another, review pass kills duplicates.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="training-and-onboarding">
      <rule>
        <statement>When training or onboarding a junior BA or LLM agent, use this methodology as the deterministic decision tree. Provide concrete situation inputs: stakeholder count, geographic distribution, time budget, sensitivity level, pre-existing artifacts, and regulatory regime.</statement>
        <rationale>Without structured inputs the selector defaults to interview regardless of context. The decision tree works only when situation variables are concrete.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="scope-renegotiation-workflow">
      <rule>
        <statement>When renegotiating scope mid-project, re-elicit only the changed area with the cheapest adequate technique.</statement>
        <rationale>Full re-elicitation of a stable area wastes sessions. Targeted re-elicitation with the cheapest technique (document analysis or observation before interview) reaches acceptable confidence faster.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="continuous-discovery-vs-per-project-selection">
      <rule>
        <statement>This methodology is for per-project elicitation planning, not for continuous-discovery cadences on stable products.</statement>
        <rationale>Continuous-discovery shops (Teresa Torres style, weekly customer-interview cadence) follow a different pattern where technique choice is fixed and the variation is in stakeholder cohort rotation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ux-research-vs-stakeholder-elicitation">
      <rule>
        <statement>This methodology applies to stakeholder elicitation (business stakeholders, domain experts, process owners). For pure UX research with end users, use ux-researcher/ techniques instead (usability tests, diary studies, eye-tracking).</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholder elicitation and UX research have different artifacts, sample sizes, and success criteria. Confusing them produces requirements that are internally consistent but misaligned with user experience.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-pattern-technique-selector">
      <p>Two short prompts drive the workflow: classify situation, then select. Both return strict JSON so a wrapper can validate and route. Technique-selector-agent inputs are: stakeholder_count, locales, time_budget_days, sensitivity (low/med/high), prior_artifacts[], regulated (true/false), and goal (discover_current_state, build_consensus, validate_design, generate_ideas, quantify_demand, or derive_integrations). Output is ranked techniques with rationale citing inputs, estimated session count, and prerequisite conditions. Refuse to output if stakeholder_count or goal is null.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="quality-gates">
      <rule>
        <statement>Require explicit cost-to-accuracy trade-offs per technique. For each technique, document: estimated time investment, confidence gain, required prerequisites, known statistical biases, and failure modes.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents and junior BAs skip the trade-off analysis and pick a single technique, missing the triangulation principle.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Use the BABOK v3 full list of 10 techniques. Add interface analysis and collaborative games to any shorter list — agents that only see 8 systematically miss integration requirements and creative-elicitation options.</item>
        <item>Never pick a single technique. Triangulate at least 2; the second technique is chosen to challenge the first (interview claim → observation reality, survey trend → focus-group nuance).</item>
        <item>Sequence cheap-then-expensive: document analysis → observation → interview → workshop → prototyping. Stop as soon as confidence target is met.</item>
        <item>Tag each elicited statement as stated, observed, or inferred. Treat observed as gold, stated as silver, inferred as bronze; downstream prioritization should respect the tier.</item>
        <item>Cap the technique-selector output at 3 picks per situation. More than 3 means the situation is under-specified — push back to stakeholder-analysis and ba-planning.</item>
        <item>Pre-read every interview/workshop with a 1-pager: objectives, prior artifacts, glossary. Skipping the pre-read is the most common quality leak.</item>
        <item>Distinguish brainstorming the technique from brainstorming the meeting type. The technique demands a structured divergence rule (6-3-5, Crazy Eights, Round-Robin).</item>
        <item>For surveys, design with N-target + confidence interval + pre-registered analysis plan. Otherwise the response is anecdote with statistics applied.</item>
        <item>Time-box: interview ≤60 min, workshop ≤90 min, observation ≤2 h per session. Past those bounds notes degrade and recall drops.</item>
        <item>Keep an "open questions" log per session. The next session's first job is to close items from the log; close-rate is a meaningful BA quality metric.</item>
        <item>Document the rejected techniques and why. Reviewers and auditors check the negative space; an "interview-only" plan with no rationale is a smell.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="additional-ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Leading questions in guides: "don't you", "wouldn't", "isn't it true".</description>
        <reason>Prep agents bias toward confirmation. Lint guides before sending to a stakeholder.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Document-analysis hallucination: agents cite "the spec says X" without a path and line range.</description>
        <reason>Require `path:line-line` citation; reject claims without it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Observation translated to interview: agents propose "ask the user" instead of "watch the user".</description>
        <reason>When goal == discover_current_state, force at least one observation slot.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Collaborative-game selection: agents pick the most-mentioned game (Product Box) regardless of fit.</description>
        <reason>Provide a small lookup {goal: [games]} and constrain selection.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Scope creep into business-analyst variant: agents invent PII pipelines and consent forms.</description>
        <reason>Keep ba-core narrow — selection plus fundamentals — and route execution-heavy concerns to the sibling business-analyst skill.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="mandatory-human-in-the-loop-checkpoints">
      <list>
        <item>Technique selection itself is signed off by a human BA before scheduling any sessions.</item>
        <item>Interview/workshop is run by humans (agents prepare, do not converse with stakeholders).</item>
        <item>Synthesis pass into requirements stubs is reviewed by humans before the stubs feed requirements-lifecycle/.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="references">
      <list>
        <item>IIBA BABOK Guide v3, ch. 4 "Elicitation and Collaboration" + Part 10 technique catalog</item>
        <item>ISO/IEC/IEEE 29148:2018 §6.4 Elicitation</item>
        <item>Steve Portigal, "Interviewing Users" 2nd ed. (Rosenfeld, 2023)</item>
        <item>Erika Hall, "Just Enough Research" 2nd ed. (Rosenfeld, 2019)</item>
        <item>Hohmann, "Innovation Games" (Addison-Wesley, 2006) — Product Box, Speed Boat, 20/20 Vision</item>
        <item>Gause &amp; Weinberg, "Exploring Requirements: Quality Before Design"</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <reference path="templates/interview-guide.md">Interview guide template with objective-linked question sections</reference>
    <reference path="templates/workshop-agenda.md">Workshop agenda template with time blocks and deliverables</reference>
  </content>
</methodology>
