<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Audience Driven Pivot Decision Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Audience Driven Pivot Decision application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="audience-asset-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Operator MUST own a verifiable audience asset (list / community / customer base) ≥500. Pivot without an audience is repivot; route to that methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audience-as-moat research">Audience-as-moat research — anchors Audience Driven Pivot Decision rule `audience-asset-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-of-unsolved-jobs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pivot MUST cite ≥3 distinct unsolved jobs surfaced in customer interviews within the last 90 days. No interviews = no pivot.</statement>
      <rationale source="Continuous discovery">Continuous discovery — anchors Audience Driven Pivot Decision rule `evidence-of-unsolved-jobs`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="explicit-kill-criterion-old-product" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The old product&apos;s kill criterion MUST be written + dated. The pivot does not start until the old product hits the kill condition or the operator commits to dual-running with a sunset date.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-record discipline">Decision-record discipline — anchors Audience Driven Pivot Decision rule `explicit-kill-criterion-old-product`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="validation-before-build" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>≥4 weeks of validation (interviews + smoke pages + waitlist conversion) MUST complete before any new product code is written. Build-first pivots fail.</statement>
      <rationale source="MVP validation research">MVP validation research — anchors Audience Driven Pivot Decision rule `validation-before-build`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-surviving-cohort" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The decision-record MUST name the audience cohort that will follow into the new product (size, segment, source). &apos;Existing audience&apos; is too vague.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cohort-segmentation discipline">Cohort-segmentation discipline — anchors Audience Driven Pivot Decision rule `named-surviving-cohort`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
