<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="pain-point-research">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>Systematic methodology for discovering and scoring customer pain points across public sources using a 5-weighted-factor matrix, converting qualitative signal into a comparable priority list.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>research</tag>
      <tag>pain-points</tag>
      <tag>customer-research</tag>
      <tag>problem-validation</tag>
      <tag>scoring-framework</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Pain Point Research</title>

    <summary>A systematic methodology for discovering and scoring customer pain points across public sources (Reddit, G2, App Store, Quora, Upwork). The rule: define audience + context first, mine at least 3 source tiers, capture verbatim quotes with URLs, score each pain on 5 weighted factors (Frequency 30%, Severity 25%, Reach 20%, Spend 15%, Alternatives 10%), then extract root causes via 5-Whys for the top findings.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Founders who skip structured pain-point research either miss the real problem or build for the wrong audience. Surface-level scanning of a single source produces survivorship bias and outrage artifacts. The scoring matrix converts subjective gut-feel into a comparable priority list, and 5-Whys prevents building for first-order symptoms instead of root causes.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-MVP: target audience defined but no validated problem yet.</item>
        <item>Choosing between 3-5 candidate ideas — score the underlying pains to break ties.</item>
        <item>Exploring an unfamiliar niche where domain intuition is weak.</item>
        <item>Repurposing existing research (G2 reviews, Reddit threads) into a structured opportunity backlog.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>You already have paying users — switch to user interviews and cancellation post-mortems; stranger pain points add noise.</item>
        <item>Highly regulated domains (healthcare, finance) where complaints are NDA'd and public signal is misleading.</item>
        <item>B2B enterprise where buyers don't post complaints publicly — use expert calls and analyst reports instead.</item>
        <item>Quantitative effect sizes are required — this methodology yields qualitative signal only.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="scope-definition">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define audience, context, and domain before searching; never begin mining without a written scope statement.</statement>
        <rationale>Vague scope produces unactionable findings. "Founders" is too broad; "solo founders, US, post-launch B2B SaaS, under $10k MRR" produces searchable, comparable pain points.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Proper scope definition">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Audience: Freelance web developers
Context: Client project management
Domain: Remote services
Goal: Find 20 pain points in 4 hours
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="source-tiers">
      <p>Tier 1 (highest signal): direct complaints — Reddit sorted by top/controversial, Twitter/X rants, Product Hunt negative reviews, G2/Capterra 1-3 star reviews, App Store 1-2 star reviews.</p>
      <p>Tier 2 (problem indicators): questions — Quora "how to" queries, Stack Overflow duplicates, subreddit FAQ sections, Google "People Also Ask" results.</p>
      <p>Tier 3 (communities): Slack groups, Discord servers, Facebook groups, Indie Hackers discussions.</p>
      <p>Tier 4 (jobs and gigs): Upwork job posts, Fiverr popular gigs, LinkedIn job listings for "looking for someone to...".</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Mine at least 3 source tiers per research session; never rely on a single source type.</statement>
        <rationale>Reddit alone is biased toward complainers. Mixing Tier 1 complaints with Tier 2 questions and Tier 4 gigs triangulates the real pain landscape.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Capture the verbatim quote and URL for every pain point; never substitute an agent's paraphrase.</statement>
        <rationale>Paraphrases lose signal and cannot be re-validated. Every quote must link to an actual URL or it is worthless for downstream validation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="pain-categories">
      <p>Classify each pain point into one of eight categories:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Time Waste — takes too long to do X (example: "spend 2 hours updating reports").</item>
        <item>Money Loss — costs more than it should (example: "paying $200/mo for features I don't use").</item>
        <item>Complexity — too hard to understand or configure.</item>
        <item>Integration — tools don't work together; copy-paste between apps.</item>
        <item>Reliability — doesn't work consistently; crashes regularly.</item>
        <item>Support — can't get help; no response from support.</item>
        <item>Process — workflow is broken; too many approvals for simple changes.</item>
        <item>Learning — hard to get started; long setup time.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="scoring-matrix">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Score every pain point using: Score = (Frequency × 0.30) + (Severity × 0.25) + (Reach × 0.20) + (Spend × 0.15) + (Alternatives × 0.10). Scale each factor 1-5.</statement>
        <rationale>The weighted formula prevents single-factor inflation. Frequency dominates because a pain that affects users daily is a stronger product anchor than a catastrophic but rare pain.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Frequency (30%): 1 = rarely, 3 = weekly, 5 = daily.</item>
        <item>Severity (25%): 1 = annoying, 3 = painful, 5 = blocking.</item>
        <item>Reach (20%): 1 = few people, 3 = many, 5 = everyone in defined audience.</item>
        <item>Spend (15%): 1 = $0 spent solving it, 3 = some spend, 5 = significant spend.</item>
        <item>Alternatives (10%): 1 = many alternatives exist, 3 = few, 5 = none.</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Priority thresholds: score above 4 = critical (high priority), 3-4 = significant (worth solving), 2-3 = moderate (could be a feature), below 2 = minor (deprioritize).</statement>
        <rationale>Clear numeric thresholds prevent subjective override of the scoring. A score of 3.8 is not "basically a 4"; it is significant but not critical.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="root-cause-analysis">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run 5-Whys analysis for the top 3 scored pain points; the first-order pain is rarely the right thing to build.</statement>
        <rationale>Building for first-order symptoms produces features, not products. Root causes reveal structural opportunities that competitors also miss.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="5-Whys analysis">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Pain: "I spend 3 hours/week on expense reports"
Why 1: Reports are manual
Why 2: System does not auto-import receipts
Why 3: No OCR integration
Why 4: IT will not approve new tools
Why 5: Tool approval process takes 6 months
Root cause: Organizational friction in tool adoption
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="scoring-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Inflating Reach to 5 ("everyone has this") without three distinct sources mentioning it.</description>
        <reason>Complaints are loud and unrepresentative. Cap Reach at 4 unless multiple independent sources confirm broad prevalence.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Splitting scoring across multiple agent calls, each with a fresh context window.</description>
        <reason>The scoring rubric drifts between calls; item 40 gets a different standard than item 1. Score the full batch in one agent call with the rubric in the system prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Mining only one source type (e.g., only Reddit) and treating results as representative.</description>
        <reason>Reddit skews toward complainers and outliers. The "fine but mediocre" majority — where most opportunity lives — doesn't post there.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <how-to>
      <step>Write a scope statement: audience, context, domain, and research goal (e.g., "find 20 pain points in 4 hours").</step>
      <step>Identify 3-4 sources per tier: Tier 1 (Reddit, G2, App Store), Tier 2 (Quora, Stack Overflow), Tier 3 (Discord, Slack), Tier 4 (Upwork, Fiverr).</step>
      <step>For each source, search using keywords related to the audience and context; save at least 20 raw results (posts, reviews, comments).</step>
      <step>Extract pain points as verbatim quotes with URLs. Each quote must link to an actual source (no paraphrases).</step>
      <step>Categorize each quote into one of the 8 pain categories.</step>
      <step>Score each pain point using the 5-factor matrix (Frequency, Severity, Reach, Spend, Alternatives), 1-5 each, in a single batch.</step>
      <step>Sort by final score (descending) and identify the top 10 pain points.</step>
      <step>Run 5-Whys analysis for the top 3, drilling from first-order pain to root cause.</step>
      <step>Extract 2-3 business angles from each root cause (e.g., direct solution, integration play, process reform).</step>
      <step>Pair with problem-validation interviews to test the top pain points with real users.</step>
    </how-to>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Run as a 3-stage pipeline. Stage 1 (haiku): mine sources in parallel — one agent per Tier source (Reddit, G2, App Store, Quora, Upwork). Each returns a JSON list of {quote, url, source, raw_category_guess}. Stage 2 (sonnet): a single dedupe + categorize agent merges, removes near-duplicates, assigns one of the 8 categories, and applies the scoring rubric. Stage 3 (opus): an opportunity-extraction agent reads the top-N scored points, runs 5-Whys, and proposes business angles. Human reviews stage-2 categories and stage-3 angles before any further work.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Define audience + context BEFORE searching. "Founders" is too broad; "Solo founders, US, post-launch B2B SaaS, &lt;$10k MRR" is searchable.</item>
        <item>Capture the verbatim quote and URL — never the agent's paraphrase. Paraphrases lose signal and can't be re-validated.</item>
        <item>Use ≥3 source tiers. Reddit alone is biased toward complainers; mix with Quora questions and Upwork gigs to triangulate.</item>
        <item>Score in a single sitting with a single agent — splitting scoring across calls drifts on the rubric.</item>
        <item>Re-run quarterly for the same audience; pain-point landscape shifts (LLMs killed many "I spent 2 hours on X" complaints in 2024).</item>
        <item>Always extract root cause via 5-Whys for the top 3. The first-order pain is rarely the right thing to build.</item>
        <item>Pair with problem-validation and jobs-to-be-done — a high-score pain that fails JTBD-fit is a feature, not a product.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs invent plausible Reddit quotes when given a topic without raw text input. Always pass scraped text into context, not just a topic; require URLs.</item>
        <item>Categorization drifts mid-batch (the model "decides" Time-Waste means something different by item 40). Use one explicit category list in every system prompt.</item>
        <item>Models inflate Reach scores ("everyone has this") because complaints are loud. Cap Reach at 4 unless ≥3 distinct sources mention it.</item>
        <item>Cross-language pain points: a UA-language Reddit thread is invisible to most agents. Use a translator agent in stage 1 explicitly.</item>
        <item>Human checkpoint: opportunities from stage 3 should be reviewed before any go-to-market work — opus output is plausible but unvalidated; treat as hypotheses.</item>
        <item>Don't let the agent "summarize" — keep raw quotes in the log. Summaries lose the verbatim signal needed for downstream JTBD interviews.</item>
        <item>Never let the same agent both score AND extract opportunities; opportunity-pull biases scoring.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <list>
        <item>Survivorship and outrage bias: 1-star reviews skew loud edge cases, missing the "fine but mediocre" majority where most opportunity lives.</item>
        <item>Score weights (Frequency 30% / Severity 25% / Reach 20% / Spend 15% / Alternatives 10%) are heuristic; agents quote them as if they were calibrated, which they aren't.</item>
        <item>Reddit/Twitter scraping is increasingly rate-limited and ToS-restricted; agent pipelines that hit the API directly break or violate terms.</item>
        <item>Without demographic context, "Reach 5 = everyone" inflates score for niche pain. Always anchor reach in the defined audience scope, not the internet.</item>
        <item>LLMs hallucinate plausible-sounding quotes — every quote in the log MUST link back to an actual URL or it's worthless for follow-up validation.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/pain-point-log.md" purpose="Research log template: scope, PP-NNN entries with scores, summary by category, top-5 list."/>
      <template path="templates/reddit-mining.md" purpose="Reddit-specific extraction template with posts analyzed, pain points found, notable quotes."/>
      <template path="templates/batch-scorer.py" purpose="Python script: reads JSON list of pain points, computes weighted score, outputs CSV."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.cbinsights.com/research/startup-failure-reasons-top/"/>
      <link href="https://www.indiehackers.com/post/how-to-find-startup-ideas-by-mining-pain-points"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/how-to-find-the-right-customer-problem"/>
      <ref slug="jobs-to-be-done"/>
      <ref slug="problem-validation"/>
      <ref slug="niche-evaluation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
