<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Compliance Matrix — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules governing matrix construction, freshness, and the legal-review boundary.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-seven-row-coverage" testable="true">
      <statement>The matrix has EXACTLY 7 rows in fixed order: (1) ENTITY-REGISTRATION, (2) DATA-PROCESSING-BASIS, (3) DPA / PROCESSOR-TERMS, (4) COOKIE / CONSENT, (5) MARKETING-EMAIL, (6) AI-ACT / AUTOMATED-DECISIONS, (7) SALES-TAX / VAT. Skipping a row leaves the founder blind to a real obligation.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 5/6/13/30 + CCPA 1798.100 + EU AI Act 2024 + IRS / HMRC tax rules">These 7 rows cover ~90% of routine micro-agency obligations across the three jurisdictions. Reducing to fewer rows leaves common gaps (cookie banner, AI act); adding more rows pushes into specialist sector regs.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-not-legal-advice" testable="true">
      <statement>EVERY row of EVERY emitted matrix MUST be marked `requires_legal_review: true` and prefixed with the disclaimer "NOT LEGAL ADVICE — this is a structured starting point for counsel review". Outputs MUST NOT be presented as the final compliance position.</statement>
      <rationale source="ABA Model Rule 5.5 / SRA Code of Conduct / EU lawyer regulations">An LLM emitting compliance positions without disclaimer creates legal-exposure for the operator AND potentially for the methodology distributor. The disclaimer is a hard requirement, not optional copy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-threshold-check" testable="true">
      <statement>Per row, the matrix MUST evaluate threshold applicability with current numeric thresholds: CCPA — annual gross revenue &gt; $25M OR 100k+ consumers OR 50%+ revenue from selling PII; UK-GDPR — any processing of UK residents' data; EU GDPR — any processing of EU residents' data; EU AI Act — high-risk system OR GPAI provider classification.</statement>
      <rationale source="CCPA §1798.140 / GDPR Art. 3 / EU AI Act Art. 6 + 51">Generic "you might need this" reduces signal; threshold-conditional output tells the founder WHICH rows actually bind them today.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-statute-freshness" testable="true">
      <statement>Source data (statute references, thresholds, fees) MUST cite an effective date no older than 18 months. Statutes change (CPRA 2023, EU AI Act 2024, US state privacy expansions). Stale data → wrong recommendations.</statement>
      <rationale source="Empirical regulatory-change cadence 2020-2026">US state privacy laws shipped 13+ statutes between 2020-2026 (CA, VA, CO, CT, UT, OR, TX, MT, IA, IN, TN, FL, DE). 18-month staleness window catches the major shifts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-first-action-anchor" testable="true">
      <statement>Every binding row (where threshold check passes) MUST emit a SPECIFIC first action with an owner role and an artifact, not generic "consult counsel". Examples: "Update DPA template with EU Standard Contractual Clauses 2021/914 (owner: legal/ops; artifact: DPA-v3.docx)".</statement>
      <rationale source="GTD / OKR action-orientation practice">Compliance gets shelved when actions are abstract. Concrete first-action moves the matrix from "good chart" to "executed change".</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="The 7-row layout">

    <example type="good" title="Row-3 (DPA / processor terms) example">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Row: DPA / processor terms

| Jurisdiction | Obligation                                | Threshold     |
|--------------|-------------------------------------------|---------------|
| US           | None federally; CCPA §1798.140 if "service provider" | CCPA-bound only |
| UK           | UK-GDPR Art. 28 — written contract        | Any UK data   |
| EU           | GDPR Art. 28 — written DPA + SCCs for transfers | Any EU data   |

First action (if bound):
  Update DPA template:
    - Art. 28(3) processor obligations clauses
    - EU SCCs 2021/914 modules 2 (controller→processor)
      and 4 (processor→subprocessor) as applicable
    - UK IDTA / Addendum for UK transfers
  Owner: legal/ops
  Artifact: DPA-v3.docx
  requires_legal_review: true
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1-r5 all visible: row coverage, threshold-tested, concrete first action, legal-review flag.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Generic "you might need a DPA" (r5 violation)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Row: DPA terms

"You should consider whether you need a Data Processing Agreement
with your vendors. Consult legal counsel."

(No threshold check, no specific action, no artifact, no jurisdiction
breakdown.)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Useless. Generic compliance text doesn't get acted on; the matrix shelf-rots.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
