<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="cohort-implementation Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for cohort-implementation. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always use COUNT(DISTINCT user_id), never COUNT(*) in cohort queries.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Duplicate events from retry logic, client-side buffering, or ETL replays inflate retention percentages. COUNT(DISTINCT) is the only safe aggregate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store cohort tables in long-format (cohort, day_offset, retention_pct) and pivot only in BI tools.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Wide-pivot in SQL is inflexible — adding a new day_offset value requires a schema change. BI tools pivot interactively. Long-format also enables dbt tests on the retention_pct column.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Materialize cohort_size as a column on every output row.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Downstream tools should never recompute cohort_size via subquery. Recomputing is fragile to filter changes and expensive at scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin the retention metric definition in the model description; a silent change from login to core_action invalidates all historical comparisons.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cohort comparisons are only valid when the retention metric is identical across cohorts. Metric drift is invisible until someone notices a suspicious trend jump.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use LEFT JOIN events ON user_id, not INNER JOIN, to preserve cohort_size denominator.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">INNER JOIN silently drops users with no activity in the join window, making cohort_size appear smaller than actual and inflating retention percentages.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
