<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Docker Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules for the docker methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale + concrete remediation hook.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="multi-stage-build" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production Dockerfiles for compiled languages MUST use multi-stage builds and copy only the final binary/artefacts into a distroless or minimal base.</statement>
      <rationale source="Docker multi-stage docs">Single-stage images include build toolchains, source, and dev dependencies that bloat the image and widen the attack surface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="non-root-user-and-healthcheck" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production images MUST set a non-root `USER` and include a `HEALTHCHECK` instruction.</statement>
      <rationale source="OCI / Docker security docs">Running as root inside a container amplifies escape risk; missing healthchecks blind orchestrators to crash-loops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="minimal-base-and-pinned-tags" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Base images MUST be pinned to an immutable digest (`@sha256:...`); floating tags like `:latest` are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Supply-chain security best practice">Floating tags break reproducibility and let upstream image swaps inject untracked changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="dockerignore-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Dockerfile MUST be accompanied by a `.dockerignore` covering `.git`, secrets, build artefacts, and node_modules / venv equivalents.</statement>
      <rationale source="Docker build context docs">Without `.dockerignore` secrets and large directories leak into the build context, balloon image size, and risk credential exfiltration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="buildkit-cache-mounts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CI builds for dependency-heavy stacks (pip, npm, apt) MUST use BuildKit cache mounts (`--mount=type=cache`).</statement>
      <rationale source="BuildKit docs">Without cache mounts, every CI build re-downloads dependencies, multiplying build minutes and bandwidth cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="vuln-scan-before-push" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Images MUST be scanned by Artifact Analysis (or Trivy/Grype) before push to production registries; CRITICAL CVEs MUST block the push.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — supply-chain policy">Pushing unscanned images bypasses the only automated gate that catches known-vulnerable base images.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the input fails ALL "Applies If" preconditions or matches ANY "Skip If" disqualifier, do not apply this methodology — route the task to the adjacent sibling instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Even flat checklists need an explicit skip leaf in the decision tree; this rule is the universal terminal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
