<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Grafana Dashboard Design Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>≥5 testable rules grounding the grafana-dashboards methodology, each paired with rationale and source reference.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="red-or-use-structure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every service dashboard MUST follow RED (Rate / Errors / Duration) for request-driven services or USE (Utilisation / Saturation / Errors) for resources.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">RED/USE are the literature-validated minimum panels; freeform panels miss the symptoms on-call needs first.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="dashboard-as-code" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store dashboard JSON in Git, generate via grafonnet / jsonnet where multiple dashboards share variables, and deploy via Grafana provisioning manifests.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Hand-edited dashboards drift between environments; provisioning + JSON in Git keeps them reproducible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="variable-parameterisation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Parameterise dashboards on service / namespace / region variables and forbid hard-coded label values inside panel queries.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Hard-coded labels create N copies of the same dashboard; variable parameterisation collapses them to one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="alert-linked-panel" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Link every alert to the dashboard panel that triggered it and embed the alert query in that panel.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Without an alert→panel link, on-call wastes minutes finding the visualisation that explains the page.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="retention-aware-queries" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Match panel queries to the retention of the data source — do not query 30-day rollup for a real-time panel or 1-min raw for a quarterly view.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Mismatched query range blows out backend query cost or returns no data — both kill dashboard trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, do NOT run this methodology — return early with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree's negative branch must terminate cleanly without partial output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold AND scope is explicit, run the methodology end-to-end and produce the canonical artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree positive-branch terminus; aliases the apply-end-to-end verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
