<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-design-principles" title="Grafana Dashboard Design Principles">
  <summary>RED/USE/Four Golden Signals frameworks, variable types, and visualization selection guide.</summary>

  <section title="Observability Frameworks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use RED (Rate, Errors, Duration) for service dashboards and USE (Utilization, Saturation, Errors) for infrastructure/hardware dashboards. Do not mix them in the same row.</statement>
      <rationale>RED answers "is the service healthy from the user's perspective?" USE answers "is the infrastructure saturating?" Mixing them creates cognitive overhead for on-call engineers who need fast answers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>RED Rate: requests per second — sum(rate(http_requests_total[5m]))</item>
      <item>RED Errors: failed request percentage — rate of 5xx / total rate</item>
      <item>RED Duration: request latency P50/P90/P99 via histogram_quantile</item>
      <item>USE Utilization: resource busy percentage (CPU, memory, disk)</item>
      <item>USE Saturation: queue/wait length (load average, memory pressure)</item>
      <item>USE Errors: hardware or driver error events</item>
    </list>
    <p>Four Golden Signals (Google SRE) = Latency + Traffic + Errors + Saturation. Equivalent to RED + Saturation from USE. Prefer RED/USE for clarity of purpose.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Dashboard Structure Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure dashboards hierarchically: summary row at top (stat panels), detail rows below (time series). Use Grafana 12 Tabs to segment cluster/namespace/pod views without splitting into separate dashboards.</statement>
      <rationale>On-call engineers need the summary answer in under 5 seconds. Separate dashboards require navigation time; tabs keep context while segregating detail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every dashboard must have at minimum three variables: datasource (type: datasource), namespace (type: query), and interval (type: interval with auto).</statement>
      <rationale>Datasource variable enables multi-cluster reuse. Namespace variable enables team-specific scoping. Interval variable prevents fixed time windows from producing misleading rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Variable Types">
    <list>
      <item>Query: dynamic values from data source (e.g., label_values for namespace, pod). Use refresh=1 (on dashboard load) for slow-changing values.</item>
      <item>Interval: time aggregation (1m, 5m, 15m, 1h). Set auto_min to avoid over-querying at short time ranges.</item>
      <item>Datasource: allows switching Prometheus instances; enables multi-cluster dashboard reuse.</item>
      <item>Custom: predefined static list. Use for environment selector (prod/staging) when values are known.</item>
      <item>Constant: hidden configuration value (e.g., SLO threshold). Avoids hardcoding in every panel expression.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Visualization Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Stat panels for current values needing instant color-coded status. Use Time series for trends. Use Gauge for percentage values with min/max bounds (SLO compliance, error budget). Use Table for multi-dimensional comparisons.</statement>
      <rationale>Choosing the wrong panel type forces users to mentally transform data. A Stat panel for a time-based trend loses context; a Time series for a single current value adds unnecessary visual noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Time series metrics: Time series panel with smooth line interpolation</item>
      <item>Current single value with thresholds: Stat panel with colorMode=value</item>
      <item>Percentage with min/max: Gauge panel</item>
      <item>Ranked comparison: Bar gauge or Table</item>
      <item>Distribution over time: Heatmap (ideal for latency histograms)</item>
      <item>Log streams: Logs panel (Loki datasource)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
