<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-provisioning" title="Grafana Dashboard Provisioning">
  <summary>Dashboard-as-code via ConfigMap, GitOps pattern, and the dashboard maturity model.</summary>

  <section title="Provisioning via ConfigMap">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provision all production dashboards as Kubernetes ConfigMaps with the grafana_dashboard=1 label. Never rely on UI-created dashboards in production.</statement>
      <rationale>UI dashboards are lost on pod restart or cluster recreation. ConfigMap-provisioned dashboards are version-controlled, reviewed in PRs, and survive infra events. The label triggers automatic discovery by Grafana's sidecar.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: v1
kind: ConfigMap
metadata:
  name: my-service-dashboard
  namespace: monitoring
  labels:
    grafana_dashboard: "1"
data:
  my-service.json: |
    {
      "title": "My Service",
      "uid": "my-service-v1",
      "schemaVersion": 38,
      "version": 1,
      "panels": []
    }
]]></code>
      <note>Set a stable uid in the dashboard JSON. UIDs are used in links between dashboards and must not change after initial provisioning.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Grafana Provisioning Config">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure Grafana to load dashboards from a folder mounted via the sidecar. Set allowUiUpdates: false in production to prevent UI drift from the Git-managed source.</statement>
      <rationale>allowUiUpdates: true allows operators to save UI changes that are then lost on the next pod restart (they are not written back to the ConfigMap). Disabling it enforces the GitOps workflow.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# grafana-provisioning/dashboards/default.yaml
apiVersion: 1
providers:
  - name: default
    orgId: 1
    type: file
    disableDeletion: false
    allowUiUpdates: false
    options:
      path: /var/lib/grafana/dashboards
      foldersFromFilesStructure: true
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Dashboard Maturity Model">
    <p>Move teams from Low to High maturity deliberately — do not attempt to jump directly to High without foundations in place.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Low: ad-hoc creation in UI, no variables, hard-coded data source names, no version control. Dashboard sprawl; nobody knows which dashboard is authoritative.</item>
      <item>Medium: variables for namespace/pod, consistent naming conventions, dashboards organized by service/team, basic GitOps (manual export to Git). Reliable for known services.</item>
      <item>High: all dashboards provisioned via GitOps, shared template dashboards for new services, usage tracking to retire stale dashboards, automated dashboard generation from service metadata. Dashboards survive cluster rebuilds.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Annotations for Context">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add deployment and alert annotations to all service dashboards. Annotations correlate metric changes with the events that caused them.</statement>
      <rationale>Without deployment markers, engineers spend minutes correlating a latency spike to the release that caused it. Annotations make the correlation instant and reduce MTTR.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "name": "Deployments",
  "datasource": {"type": "prometheus", "uid": "${DS_PROMETHEUS}"},
  "enable": true,
  "expr": "changes(kube_deployment_status_observed_generation{namespace=\"$namespace\"}[5m]) > 0",
  "titleFormat": "Deploy: {{ deployment }}",
  "iconColor": "blue"
}
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
