<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-phases" title="30-60-90 Day Plan: Phase Definitions and Success Criteria">
  <summary>Three-phase ramp framework (Learn/Contribute/Execute) with milestone types, success criteria per phase, and check-in cadence.</summary>

  <section title="Core Principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every milestone in a 30-60-90 plan must be anchored to a concrete, observable artifact; never use the verbs "understand", "be familiar with", or "learn about" as milestone criteria.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague verbs cannot be verified at the day-30 review; the manager and hire will disagree on whether the milestone is complete. Observable artifacts (PR merged, doc written, customer call completed, deal proposed) have a clear binary: done or not done.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Co-author the plan with the hiring manager and the new hire on Day 1; plans written by HR alone become checkboxes nobody reads after week 2.</statement>
      <rationale>Ownership of the plan predicts adherence. When the new hire participates in setting the milestones, they internalize them as personal commitments rather than corporate requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 1: Days 1-30 (Learn)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Days 1-30 are a learning phase; do not assign project ownership or execution pressure in the first 30 days unless the role explicitly requires immediate delivery (e.g., revenue-critical backfill).</statement>
      <rationale>Pushing delivery into the learn phase causes early burnout, poor-quality output, and missed context that creates technical or relationship debt. The day-30 review is the correct gate for confirming readiness to contribute.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Day-30 Success Criteria">
      <list>
        <item>Can describe the team's current quarter goals and how this role contributes to them.</item>
        <item>Has met all key stakeholders within and adjacent to the team.</item>
        <item>Has read and can locate all critical documentation for the role.</item>
        <item>Has identified one area of friction, risk, or opportunity (written 1-pager observation).</item>
        <item>Has documented goals for days 31-60 in a shared artifact with the manager.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 2: Days 31-60 (Contribute)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Phase 2 ends with ownership of at least one completed project, however small; a completed project is a stronger signal than partial progress on a large one.</statement>
      <rationale>Completing a scoped project demonstrates the full delivery cycle (planning, execution, communication, handoff) at whatever scale is appropriate. A partial large project reveals nothing about completion behavior.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Day-60 Success Criteria">
      <list>
        <item>Has owned and completed at least one project end-to-end (scope appropriate to role and level).</item>
        <item>Has received and acted on feedback from at least two sources (manager and peer or stakeholder).</item>
        <item>Works with minimal supervision on familiar tasks.</item>
        <item>Has proposed at least one improvement to a team process, tool, or practice.</item>
        <item>Has documented goals for days 61-90 in a shared artifact.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 3: Days 61-90 (Execute)">
    <rule>
      <statement>By day 90, the hire must work independently on 80%+ of their responsibilities; anything below this threshold triggers a formal performance conversation, not an extension of the onboarding period.</statement>
      <rationale>Extending the onboarding frame past 90 days without a performance conversation obscures underperformance and delays the manager's decision. The 90-day review is the formal transition from onboarding to standard performance management.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Day-90 Success Criteria">
      <list>
        <item>Meets or exceeds performance expectations on primary job responsibilities.</item>
        <item>Works autonomously on 80%+ of tasks without requiring guidance.</item>
        <item>Has contributed to team goals in a measurable, visible way.</item>
        <item>Has a documented development plan for the next quarter.</item>
        <item>Is integrated into team culture (included in social and professional rituals).</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Check-In Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the day-30 review at day 25 to leave 5 days of correction opportunity before the formal milestone; never use the review as the first signal of problems.</statement>
      <rationale>If issues surface first at the day-30 review, the correction window is zero. Running at day 25 gives 5 days to course-correct before the formal gate, converting the review from a verdict into a coaching tool.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Check-in schedule: day 7 (early pulse, informal), day 25-30 (30-day review), day 45 (skip-level: hire meets manager's manager, removes reporting-chain blind spot), day 60 (60-day review), day 90 (formal performance review).</p>
  </section>
</text>
