<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="shell-productivity">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>server-craft</domain>
    <summary>Modern CLI toolkit replacing traditional Unix utilities: bat, eza, fd, ripgrep, delta, starship, zoxide, fzf, btop, duf, dust. Covers Ubuntu naming conflicts, installation, fzf/bat/fd cross-wiring.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>shell</tag>
      <tag>cli-tools</tag>
      <tag>productivity</tag>
      <tag>ubuntu</tag>
      <tag>fzf</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Shell Productivity</title>
    <summary>Modern CLI toolkit for Ubuntu/Debian servers replacing traditional Unix utilities with faster, more informative alternatives: bat (cat), eza (ls), fd (find), ripgrep (grep), delta (git diff), starship (prompt), zoxide (cd), fzf (fuzzy finder), btop (top), duf (df), dust (du). Covers installation from apt and GitHub releases, Ubuntu naming conflicts (batcat/fdfind), shell integration, and fzf/bat/fd cross-wiring.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Traditional Unix tools work but lack color coding, git integration, and smart defaults. For a solo developer managing multiple projects via SSH, tools like fzf (Ctrl+R history search), zoxide (frecency-based cd), and delta (side-by-side diff) save significant time daily. The modern stack is an investment that compounds with every session.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Setting up a new Ubuntu VPS where default shell tools slow down daily admin</item>
        <item>Server rebuild: restoring the developer's modern tool stack alongside dotfiles</item>
        <item>Improving agent-generated shell pipelines with tools that have better output formats</item>
        <item>Auditing which tools are installed before writing scripts that depend on them</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Minimal containers or CI environments where image size matters (stick to POSIX tools)</item>
        <item>Scripts that must run on arbitrary servers without knowing what tools are installed</item>
        <item>Environments with strict package policy (air-gapped, compliance-hardened)</item>
        <item>Scripts checked into shared repos where others may not have the same tools</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="modern-cli-tools">
      <section name="tool-reference">
        <list>
          <item>bat — replaces cat: syntax highlighting, git change markers, line numbers, automatic paging</item>
          <item>eza — replaces ls: color-coded permissions, git status column, icons, tree view</item>
          <item>fd — replaces find: faster, respects .gitignore, simpler syntax, Unicode-aware</item>
          <item>ripgrep (rg) — replaces grep: multi-threaded, respects .gitignore, better output formatting</item>
          <item>delta — replaces git diff output: side-by-side view, syntax highlighting, line numbers</item>
          <item>starship — replaces PS1 prompt: cross-shell, git-aware, language version display, fast</item>
          <item>zoxide — replaces cd: frecency-based jump, interactive mode with fzf</item>
          <item>fzf — fuzzy finder: Ctrl+R history, Ctrl+T file picker, Alt+C directory jump</item>
          <item>btop — replaces top/htop: full UI with process tree, network, disk, beautiful layout</item>
          <item>duf — replaces df: color-coded table, filters, human-readable by default</item>
          <item>dust — replaces du: visual tree sorted by size, respects .gitignore</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="ubuntu-naming-conflicts">
        <rule>
          <statement>On Ubuntu/Debian, bat is installed as batcat and fd is installed as fdfind; create /usr/local/bin symlinks to avoid breaking scripts and fzf integrations.</statement>
          <rationale>The name conflicts exist because bat conflicts with the Ubuntu bat (Bytes Around Text) command and fd conflicts with an older package. Without symlinks, all scripts expecting bat/fd by name fail silently.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <example type="good">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Install from apt (Ubuntu 24.04)
sudo apt install -y bat fd-find fzf ripgrep btop duf

# Fix Ubuntu naming conflicts
sudo ln -sf /usr/bin/batcat /usr/local/bin/bat
sudo ln -sf /usr/bin/fdfind /usr/local/bin/fd

# Verify
bat --version
fd --version
          ]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section name="github-release-installs">
        <note>Tools not in Ubuntu 24.04 apt repos or where the apt version is too old: eza, delta, starship, zoxide, dust.</note>

        <example type="good">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# eza (latest via PPA)
sudo mkdir -p /etc/apt/keyrings
wget -qO- https://raw.githubusercontent.com/eza-community/eza/main/deb.asc \
    | sudo gpg --dearmor -o /etc/apt/keyrings/gierens.gpg
echo "deb [signed-by=/etc/apt/keyrings/gierens.gpg] http://deb.gierens.de stable main" \
    | sudo tee /etc/apt/sources.list.d/gierens.list
sudo apt update && sudo apt install -y eza

# delta (git diff)
DELTA_VER="0.18.2"
wget -q "https://github.com/dandavison/delta/releases/download/${DELTA_VER}/git-delta_${DELTA_VER}_amd64.deb" -O /tmp/delta.deb
sudo dpkg -i /tmp/delta.deb && rm /tmp/delta.deb

# starship (prompt)
curl -sS https://starship.rs/install.sh | sh -s -- -y

# zoxide (smart cd)
curl -sSfL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/ajeetdsouza/zoxide/main/install.sh | sh
          ]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>

      <reference path="templates/install-cli-tools.sh">Idempotent install script for all tools on Ubuntu 24.04 with existence checks</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="tool-integration">
      <rule>
        <statement>Wire all three: fzf uses fd as its file source and bat for previews; this creates a compound tool where Ctrl+T shows file previews with syntax highlighting.</statement>
        <rationale>fzf's default file source (find) is slow and noisy. fd is 5-10x faster and respects .gitignore. bat previews eliminate the need to open files just to check their content while browsing.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="fzf-wiring">
        <example type="good">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# ~/.bashrc — fzf integration block (after fzf installation)
eval "$(fzf --bash)"

# Use fd as the default file source (faster, respects .gitignore)
export FZF_DEFAULT_COMMAND='fd --type f --hidden --follow \
    --exclude .git --exclude node_modules --exclude .venv --exclude __pycache__'

export FZF_CTRL_T_COMMAND="$FZF_DEFAULT_COMMAND"
export FZF_CTRL_T_OPTS="--preview 'bat --color=always --style=numbers --line-range=:300 {}'"

# Alt+C: directory jump with eza preview
export FZF_ALT_C_COMMAND='fd --type d --hidden --follow --exclude .git'
export FZF_ALT_C_OPTS="--preview 'eza --tree --level=2 --color=always {}'"
          ]]></code>
        </example>

        <reference path="templates/fzf-config.sh">fzf shell integration block with bat preview, fd file source, and helper functions</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="delta-integration">
        <example type="good">
          <code lang="ini"><![CDATA[
# ~/.gitconfig — delta as git pager
[core]
    pager = delta

[interactive]
    diffFilter = delta --color-only

[delta]
    navigate = true
    side-by-side = true
    line-numbers = true
    syntax-theme = TwoDark
          ]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section name="starship-zoxide">
        <example type="good">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# ~/.bashrc — add at the end (after other exports)
# starship: replaces PS1 prompt
eval "$(starship init bash)"

# zoxide: frecency-based cd replacement
eval "$(zoxide init bash)"
# Usage: z foo     -> cd to most visited directory matching 'foo'
#        zi foo    -> interactive pick with fzf
          ]]></code>
        </example>

        <reference path="templates/starship.toml">Minimal server-optimized starship config: hostname on SSH, git status, fast scan timeout</reference>
      </section>

      <section name="agent-gotchas">
        <rule>
          <statement>In agent-generated scripts that run in CI or headless environments, never use aliases or modern tools without checking for their existence first.</statement>
          <rationale>Agents writing scripts often assume the developer environment. Scripts that call bat, eza, or fd without existence checks fail on minimal containers, CI runners, or servers where only apt defaults are installed.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Adding eval $(starship init bash) to a non-interactive shell init file like /etc/environment or a service ExecStartPre.</description>
          <reason>starship requires an interactive TTY. Running it in non-interactive contexts (systemd services, cron jobs) either fails silently or adds unusable ANSI escape codes to the environment.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Overriding cat with bat globally in scripts that parse command output.</description>
          <reason>bat adds ANSI color codes and paging that break programmatic parsing. Gate the alias with command -v and use \cat or command cat in scripts to bypass it.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/install-cli-tools.sh" purpose="Idempotent install script for all tools on Ubuntu 24.04"/>
      <template path="templates/starship.toml" purpose="Minimal server-optimized starship prompt config"/>
      <template path="templates/fzf-config.sh" purpose="fzf shell integration block with bat preview and fd file source"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
