<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Tax Compliance and Filing Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `ops-tax-compliance` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-quarterly-dates-locked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock IRS quarterly due dates (April 15, June 15, September 15, January 15) in the operator's calendar at year-start. Missing a date for any reason triggers a late-payment penalty even with safe-harbor compliance.</statement>
      <rationale source="IRS estimated-tax rules (IRC § 6654; Pub 505)">The penalty for late payment accrues regardless of whether the safe-harbor amount is correct. Calendar locks remove the dominant failure mode (forgetting).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-record-keeping-system" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain a structured record-keeping system (accounting software or ledger spreadsheet) with monthly close. Shoebox-of-receipts or 'I'll sort it at year-end' approaches are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="IRS substantiation rules (IRC § 6001)">Year-end sorting under deadline produces both lost deductions and inaccurate filings. Monthly close keeps records audit-ready throughout the year.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-year-end-deduction-sweep" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a structured year-end deduction sweep in November-December: retirement contributions, Section 179 equipment, expense acceleration, charitable contributions. Skipping the sweep two years in a row is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tax-planning practice (AICPA Personal Financial Planning)">Year-end sweep captures deductions that disappear at year-end (Section 179 placed-in-service date; SEP-IRA deadline). Skipping it permanently loses the deduction window.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-file-on-time-or-extend" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>File the annual return on time, OR file an extension AND pay the estimated balance by April 15. Extension without payment is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="IRS extension rules (Form 4868 instructions)">Extension extends the time to file, NOT the time to pay. Filing extension without payment accrues late-payment penalty + interest from April 15.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-non-us-localisation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For non-US operators, replace the IRS-specific items with the local equivalent (HMRC / Finanças / DPS) and update due-dates and safe-harbor logic. Applying IRS rules to non-US operators is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="International tax practice">Tax compliance is jurisdiction-specific. Copy-pasting IRS rules into a non-US workflow misses local deadlines and rules entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
