<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="User Interviews Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding User Interviews. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-question-then-decision" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every research project starts from a question and the decision that question will inform; questions without decisions are skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Erika Hall — Just Enough Research">Research without a decision producer drifts into theatre.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-semi-structured" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interview guides are semi-structured — fixed topic blocks, open follow-up — and capped at 45 to 60 minutes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Pure structured kills depth; pure unstructured loses comparability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-quotes-not-paraphrase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Synthesis quotes participants verbatim with timestamps; paraphrase only with a clear marker.</statement>
      <rationale source="UX-research practice">Paraphrased quotes lose signal and inherit researcher bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-saturation-tracked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sample size is justified by saturation, not a fixed number; stop only when two consecutive interviews add no new themes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Glaser and Strauss — grounded theory">Fixed sample sizes either over- or under-sample reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-consent-and-pii" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Consent forms cover recording, sharing, and retention; PII is removed from transcripts before sharing beyond the research team.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR and research-ethics practice">Sharing raw PII breaches ethics and may breach law.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-user-interviews.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
