<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="plausible-analytics Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for plausible-analytics. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deploy the Nginx proxy before launch on any site targeting a technical audience. Without it, 20-40% of users running adblockers are invisible.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Plausible's default script URL (plausible.io) is blocked by most adblockers. A proxied script via the site's own domain bypasses these blocks, restoring data accuracy for privacy-conscious technical users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>In Next.js and Gatsby, guard plausible() calls with typeof window !== 'undefined' to prevent SSR errors.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Plausible's JavaScript function runs in the browser only. SSR environments do not have a window object. Calling plausible() during server-side rendering throws a ReferenceError.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exclude own visits during development by setting localStorage.setItem('plausible_ignore', 'true') in the browser console.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Development visits that appear in analytics data distort traffic numbers. The localStorage flag is persistent across sessions and survives page reloads.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define goals in the Plausible dashboard before firing events from code — events that do not match a defined goal are silently ignored.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Plausible requires goals to be pre-registered in the dashboard settings. Firing events without corresponding goal definitions produces no data in the dashboard.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use CSS class tagged events for CTA click tracking when possible — no JavaScript code changes needed when adding new buttons.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tagged events reduce deployment friction: a designer can add a tracking class in HTML without touching JavaScript. This is also more resilient to JS bundle changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Verify the Plausible plan supports revenue tracking before implementing — this feature is only available in the hosted Business plan, not in Community Edition (CE).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Revenue tracking silently fails on plans that do not support it. Verifying the plan before implementation avoids lost revenue data without error messages.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use exact period parameter values: day, 7d, 30d, month, 6mo, 12mo, or YYYY-MM-DD,YYYY-MM-DD. Non-standard formats return errors.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents frequently use incorrect period formats (e.g., "last_30_days", "30_days", "1m") that are not valid for the Plausible API and produce 400 errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use exact property values in breakdown queries. Valid examples: event:page, visit:source, visit:device, visit:country.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents hallucinate property names based on what "seems right" (e.g., "page:url", "traffic:source"). Only properties in the official API documentation work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Stats API is fully headless and agent-compatible — no browser interaction required. Use it from server-side scripts and agent pipelines directly.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unlike most analytics tools, Plausible's Stats API does not require OAuth or browser sessions. A simple Bearer token is sufficient for all read operations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
