<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SoW Traced-Assumptions Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that make every SoW clause defendable against post-signature scope disputes.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1" testable="true">
      <statement>Every in-scope deliverable line in the SoW body MUST carry an inline assumption ID in the format `[A-NN]` (e.g., `[A-07]`), placed at the end of the clause. A deliverable line without an ID is a draft, not a SoW item.</statement>
      <rationale>Without per-line IDs, a dispute cannot be argued at the clause level — only at the whole-SoW level, which is what kills margin. ID-per-clause forces the BA to map each commitment to its trace before sign-off.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2" testable="true">
      <statement>The SoW MUST ship with an `assumptions.md` appendix where each `[A-NN]` maps to: (a) a concrete artefact path or URL, (b) the artefact section/timestamp, (c) one-line restatement of the assumption, (d) the named stakeholder who confirmed it. Any `[A-NN]` referenced in the body but missing from the appendix blocks sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale>The trace IS the defence. A bare assumption number with no source is the same as no source; the appendix is the artefact the BA shows when a client says "we never agreed to that".</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3" testable="true">
      <statement>Every exclusion clause ("the following is OUT of scope: ...") MUST also carry an `[A-NN]` ID. Exclusions are commitments in reverse and disputed just as often as inclusions.</statement>
      <rationale>Outsource shops over-document inclusions and under-document exclusions; the costly disputes are usually "but we thought X was included" — i.e., a missing exclusion trace. IDs on exclusions force symmetric rigour.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4" testable="true">
      <statement>Every pricing-model assumption (volumes, peak load, third-party SLAs, integration counts) MUST be a separate `[A-NN]` line in the appendix, even when it does not appear in the SoW body. The fixed price is conditioned on these assumptions; a breach is a change-request trigger.</statement>
      <rationale>Pricing assumptions are where fixed-price engagements bleed. Tying the price to enumerated IDs lets the BA invoke the change-request protocol the moment one is violated, instead of arguing intent.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5" testable="true">
      <statement>The SoW MUST include a "Change Request Protocol" clause that explicitly requires any future scope change to cite the affected `[A-NN]` ID(s) and the artefact line that supersedes them. A change request without an ID citation is rejected by the protocol.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a citation rule, the trace is decorative. Tying the change protocol to assumption IDs makes the traceability operational rather than archival.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies-If preconditions fail OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or to no methodology at all).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application of a methodology produces worse artefacts than no methodology at all because downstream consumers trust the schema and act on bad data. The skip-record makes the non-application traceable so future audits can detect drift.</rationale>
    </rule>


  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## In-scope deliverables

- Build customer onboarding flow with email + phone verification, up to 3 form steps. [A-04]
- Integrate single payment provider (Stripe) using the Payment Intents API. [A-07]

## Out of scope

- Multi-currency support; system is single-currency (EUR) for v1. [A-12]

## Appendix: assumptions.md

| ID | Source artefact | Section / timestamp | Statement | Confirmed by |
|----|-----------------|---------------------|-----------|--------------|
| A-04 | interviews/2026-04-15-vp-ops.md | 00:12:30 transcript | Onboarding will not exceed 3 form steps for v1 | Maria Lopes (VP Ops) |
| A-07 | decisions/payments-provider-2026-04-22.md | "Decision" paragraph | Stripe only for v1; Adyen deferred | Tomás Silva (CFO) |
| A-12 | reqs/non-functional.md | line 47 | v1 supports EUR only | Maria Lopes (VP Ops) |
      ]]></code>
      <note>Each clause is defendable. A dispute on "we expected multi-currency" lands on A-12 with a named source, not on a verbal argument.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## In-scope deliverables

- Build a customer onboarding flow.
- Integrate payments.

## Assumptions

- Standard scope assumptions apply.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Unbounded inclusions, no IDs, no appendix entries. Every clause is a future dispute waiting to happen — the SoW protects nothing.</note>
    </example>

  </section>
</text>
