<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cloud Run Traffic Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for the cloud-run-traffic-management methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale + concrete remediation hook.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="canary-traffic-split" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Canary rollouts MUST start at ≤5% traffic to the new revision and increase only after smoke tests + monitoring pass.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Run rollout docs">Lower initial split caps blast radius from a bad revision while still producing real production telemetry.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="tagged-revision-promote" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each new revision MUST be deployed with `--no-traffic --tag &lt;name&gt;` first, smoke-tested via the tagged URL, then promoted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Run revisions docs">Tagged URL allows production-equivalent smoke testing without exposing real users to the unreleased revision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="split-by-revision" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A/B experiments MUST pin two stable revisions and split traffic by percentage — never split between an active deploy and a tag.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — release engineering review">Splitting against an actively-changing target produces non-stationary experiments and noisy results.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rollback-with-revision-pin" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rollback MUST be performed by promoting a known-good revision to 100% traffic, not by redeploying a previous container image.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Run rollback docs">Revision-pin rollback is atomic and instant; image-redeploy rollback can introduce regressions in unchanged config.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="traffic-tag-cleanup" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stale revision tags MUST be cleaned up after promotion; expired tags pollute the Cloud Console and confuse on-call.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — service-hygiene audit">Long-lived tags accumulate and obscure the active rollout state during incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the input fails ALL "Applies If" preconditions or matches ANY "Skip If" disqualifier, do not apply this methodology — route the task to the adjacent sibling instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Even flat checklists need an explicit skip leaf in the decision tree; this rule is the universal terminal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
