<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="zero-click-search-adaptation Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for zero-click-search-adaptation. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shift the primary goal from driving traffic to becoming the source AI answers cite — being cited in AI Overviews is more valuable than being a skipped organic link.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">In a world where 83% of AI Overview searches end without clicks, measuring success purely by sessions misses the actual value delivered. Brand awareness, citation authority, and downstream branded search growth are the real outcomes that convert.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Implement Article and FAQ schema markup — studies show +28% AI citation rate for pages with proper structured data.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI crawlers parse structured data to understand content purpose and authority signals. Structured data reduces ambiguity in content interpretation, making the page a more reliable citation candidate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prioritize content formats that AI systems use as citation sources: original research with current statistics, expert analysis with unique opinions, and comprehensive guides with structured data.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI systems cite sources that are authoritative, specific, and current. Generic content that aggregates existing information is replaced by the AI Overview itself; original data and analysis provides the source the AI needs to cite.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stop tracking only sessions; add search impressions, branded query growth, AI citation rate, and on-SERP actions to the success scorecard.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Session-only measurement in a zero-click environment produces false negative signals — a page generating thousands of SERP impressions with low CTR (because the AI Overview answered the query) is delivering value not captured in session data.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
