<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Review Facilitation — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for running the 60-minute weekly design review so it produces decisions, not vibes. Each rule has a known violation pattern.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-60-min-hard-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The review MUST end within 60 minutes (hard cap). Agenda allocation: 5 min intake recap, 35-40 min structured critique (time-boxed per artifact based on stage — early-explore: 5 min, refined-comp: 10 min, pre-handoff: 15 min), 10 min decisions, 5-10 min action capture. Overflow goes to next week's review, NOT extended time.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cal Newport deep-work research, Jake Knapp Sprint methodology">Hour-plus reviews show steeply declining attention quality. Hard cap forces ruthless prioritization at intake. Overflow protocol prevents the cap from being an aspiration — the review actually ends.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-structured-feedback-protocol" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every piece of feedback MUST be tagged as one of: CLARIFYING ("what does this state represent?"), SUGGESTING ("what if you tried X?"), BLOCKING ("this violates ADR-007 / cannot ship as-is because Y"). Forbidden: "looks great" / "I don't love it" / "feels off" — vague feedback is rejected by the facilitator with a prompt to retag.</statement>
      <rationale source="Adam Connor — Discussing Design, Discussing Design book research">Vague feedback wastes time and doesn't change designs. Tagged feedback creates predictable interactions: clarifying = info; suggesting = optional consideration; blocking = must address. Designers respond differently to each, and review proceeds faster.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-decision-or-explicit-defer" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every artifact discussed MUST end with one of: DECISION (specific path forward, owner, date), DEFER (named follow-up: who decides, by when, with what new input), or KILL (explicit no-go with reason). Forbidden: "let's think about it" / "let's iterate" without owner + date.</statement>
      <rationale source="GTD action capture, design-ops process research">"Let's iterate" produces zero accountability. Explicit decision / defer / kill creates a record that the artifact has been HANDLED. Without it, the same artifact comes back next week with the same questions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-scribe-during-not-after" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A named scribe captures decisions + actions IN THE MEETING, in real time, in a shared doc visible to attendees. The scribe reads back captures at end of each artifact for confirmation. Forbidden: facilitator-writes-notes-from-memory-after-meeting.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meeting effectiveness research, post-meeting memory studies">Post-meeting notes from memory lose 40-60% of decisions and most action-owner assignments. In-meeting capture with live readback catches misinterpretations while everyone is still present.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-24h-recap-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A recap email / message MUST go out within 24 hours of the meeting with: decisions list (per artifact), action items (with owner + date), defer list (with follow-up trigger), and link to the meeting record. Recipients: all attendees + any cross-functional stakeholders affected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Knowledge-management research, change-management literature">Decisions decay without artifact. 24h recap creates the durable record that downstream teams reference. Missing the 24h window correlates with attendees disputing the decisions next week, defeating the meeting's purpose.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical example">

    <example type="good" title="Tagged feedback + clean decision">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Artifact: "Onboarding screen v3"
Stage: refined-comp (10-min time-box)
Designer: jane.s

Facilitator opens: "Goals: confirm primary CTA copy + decide on
  field-order. Anything else is suggesting, not blocking."

Feedback round (round-robin, tagged):
  alex.k:    CLARIFYING — "is the secondary action a button or link?"
             jane.s answers: it's a link, not a button.
  mark.p:    SUGGESTING — "what if 'Continue' were 'Start free trial'?"
             jane.s: noted; will A/B in a future test.
  pat.r:     BLOCKING — "the 'Email' field is below 'Workspace name',
             but workspace creation requires email auth — order is wrong."
             jane.s: agreed, will swap.
  liam.h:    SUGGESTING — "could the illustration be smaller?"
             jane.s: noted; will park unless it impacts heat-map data.

Decision (captured by scribe, read back at end):
  - Decision: swap field order so Email comes first.
    Owner: jane.s. Date: 2026-05-22 (before handoff).
  - Defer: copy A/B for primary CTA. Owner: mark.p. Trigger:
    when onboarding-conversion baseline is stable post-launch.

Time used: 9.5 min (within 10-min box).
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2, r3, r4: tagged feedback, clean decision/defer split, scribe captured with readback.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="LGTM cascade + no decisions">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Artifact: "Onboarding screen v3"
Time: 25 min (over allocated 10 min)

Feedback:
  alex.k: "looks great"
  mark.p: "I like it, maybe the button could be different?"
  pat.r:  "feels off but I can't put my finger on it"
  liam.h: "love the illustration"

End of artifact discussion: "let's iterate." No owner, no date,
no scribe notes.

Two weeks later: same artifact in review, same vague feedback,
same lack of decision. Designer frustrated; team time wasted.

Repair: enforce r1-r4. Vague feedback gets retagged on the spot;
"let's iterate" gets converted to "decision: jane.s revises X by Y".
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1-r4 violations — the standard zombie-review pattern.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
