<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Process Mining Tool Shortlist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules with rationale + source for process-mining-tool-shortlist. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="weighted-criteria" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shortlist MUST score each tool against weighted criteria (ingestion fit, query language, visualisation, conformance check, conformance check, total cost of ownership, vendor lock-in); weights agreed with sponsor before scoring.</statement>
      <rationale source="MCDM (multi-criteria decision-making) practice">MCDM (multi-criteria decision-making) practice — applies to Process Mining Tool Shortlist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-anchor-per-score" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each tool score MUST cite evidence: vendor demo recording, sample event log result, G2 reference call, hands-on POC; un-anchored scores forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Vendor-evaluation research">Vendor-evaluation research — applies to Process Mining Tool Shortlist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="at-least-three-tools" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shortlist MUST contain at least 3 tools (commercial + open-source); single-tool shortlists are not shortlists.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-quality practice">Decision-quality practice — applies to Process Mining Tool Shortlist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ownership-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each shortlist row MUST have a single named owner who ran the evaluation; consensus authorship is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-owner accountability">Single-owner accountability — applies to Process Mining Tool Shortlist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="review-by-date" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shortlist carries a review-by date (default 6 months); past that, vendor landscape may have shifted enough to invalidate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene">Operational hygiene — applies to Process Mining Tool Shortlist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="decision-record-attached" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Final pick is recorded as an ADR (architecture decision record) attached to the shortlist; tool-pick without ADR is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-record practice">Decision-record practice — applies to Process Mining Tool Shortlist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rejected-options-documented" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rejected tools MUST list rejection reason; silent omission is forbidden because the next engagement re-derives the rejection.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-quality research">Decision-quality research — applies to Process Mining Tool Shortlist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If tool choice is already mandated or the scope is below the methodology break-even, return `skipped`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to Process Mining Tool Shortlist.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
