<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="spatial-design-tools Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for spatial-design-tools. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stage 1 (Concept): Use 2D wireframes in Figma with explicit spatial annotations — depth layers, scale references relative to human height, reach zones. Do not attempt to design spatial interactions in 2D beyond basic flow.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">2D tools cannot represent depth, scale, or arm reach; spatial annotations communicate intent to developers without requiring 3D tooling at concept stage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stage 2 (Low-fi Prototype): Build a rough spatial prototype in ShapesXR or equivalent and test it in the target headset with representative users before writing any production code.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Key spatial UX problems — arm fatigue, uncomfortable viewing angles, depth misperception, scale errors — are invisible in 2D mockups and only manifest in the headset. Catching them at low-fi stage costs a fraction of fixing them post-development.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stage 3 (High-fi Prototype): Implement in Unity or Unreal with real interactions, performance constraints, and target hardware. Conduct a second round of user testing in the target environment (factory floor, office, home).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Performance constraints (frame rate, rendering budget) affect interaction feel; high-fi prototypes in the development engine expose these issues before production optimization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stage 4 (Production): Include an accessibility review — check gaze+dwell fallback for motor-impaired users, voice command support, comfort for long sessions, and color contrast for passthrough AR overlays.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Spatial accessibility is rarely addressed in production without an explicit review gate; omitting it excludes motor-impaired users and may violate enterprise accessibility requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Move to headset testing at Stage 2 (low-fi), not later. If the team lacks access to the target hardware, use the nearest available headset — any 6DOF device is more informative than any 2D mockup for spatial UX.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Delaying headset testing to high-fi or production is the most common cause of late-stage XR UX failures; the headset test must be part of the design process, not a QA activity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Claude as a "spatial pipeline librarian" — it picks the right tool per stage (concept → low-fi → high-fi → production), generates scaffolding (Unity C# MonoBehaviours, USDA scene files, glTF transforms), and writes the headset test plan. The headset-bound creative work (hand-sketching in ShapesXR, sculpting in Gravity Sketch) stays human; the agent prepares import scripts, file conventions, and review checklists around it. Always pair agent output with a human in-headset validation pass — pixel-perfect 2D ≠ comfortable 3D.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agentic workflow separates deterministic scaffolding from creative and embodied design work, allowing agents to accelerate the pipeline without replacing human spatial intuition.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
