<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-tools-and-workflow" title="Spatial Design Tools — Tool Landscape and Workflow">
  <summary>Tool selection guide and four-stage design-to-development workflow for spatial XR design, from 2D wireframes through low-fi headset prototyping to high-fidelity production.</summary>

  <section title="Tool Landscape">
    <list>
      <item>Figma with 3D plugins: 2D wireframes with spatial annotations; suitable for concept and specification only</item>
      <item>ShapesXR: VR-native low-fidelity prototyping directly in a headset; primary tool for early spatial UX validation</item>
      <item>Gravity Sketch: VR-native 3D design and sketching; suitable for 3D form design and organic spatial layouts</item>
      <item>Unity: industry-standard XR development platform; used for high-fidelity interactive prototypes and production</item>
      <item>Unreal Engine: high-fidelity rendering for XR; suited to visualization-heavy enterprise applications</item>
      <item>Reality Composer Pro: Apple's tool for visionOS spatial content; required for Vision Pro production</item>
      <item>Spark AR: Meta AR effects and passthrough content; consumer-focused AR</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Four-Stage Design-to-Development Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 1 (Concept): Use 2D wireframes in Figma with explicit spatial annotations — depth layers, scale references relative to human height, reach zones. Do not attempt to design spatial interactions in 2D beyond basic flow.</statement>
      <rationale>2D tools cannot represent depth, scale, or arm reach; spatial annotations communicate intent to developers without requiring 3D tooling at concept stage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 2 (Low-fi Prototype): Build a rough spatial prototype in ShapesXR or equivalent and test it in the target headset with representative users before writing any production code.</statement>
      <rationale>Key spatial UX problems — arm fatigue, uncomfortable viewing angles, depth misperception, scale errors — are invisible in 2D mockups and only manifest in the headset. Catching them at low-fi stage costs a fraction of fixing them post-development.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 3 (High-fi Prototype): Implement in Unity or Unreal with real interactions, performance constraints, and target hardware. Conduct a second round of user testing in the target environment (factory floor, office, home).</statement>
      <rationale>Performance constraints (frame rate, rendering budget) affect interaction feel; high-fi prototypes in the development engine expose these issues before production optimization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 4 (Production): Include an accessibility review — check gaze+dwell fallback for motor-impaired users, voice command support, comfort for long sessions, and color contrast for passthrough AR overlays.</statement>
      <rationale>Spatial accessibility is rarely addressed in production without an explicit review gate; omitting it excludes motor-impaired users and may violate enterprise accessibility requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="When to Enter the Headset">
    <rule>
      <statement>Move to headset testing at Stage 2 (low-fi), not later. If the team lacks access to the target hardware, use the nearest available headset — any 6DOF device is more informative than any 2D mockup for spatial UX.</statement>
      <rationale>Delaying headset testing to high-fi or production is the most common cause of late-stage XR UX failures; the headset test must be part of the design process, not a QA activity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
