<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="cicd-mtls-deployment Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for cicd-mtls-deployment as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using long-lived shared client certs (validity 1 year+) for service-to-service mTLS across multiple microservices.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Wildcard certs or shared service certs spread across teams. A single key compromise requires mass rotation with no revocation guarantee (OCSP/CRL is unreliable at scale). Use per-service short-lived certs from an internal CA instead.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Disabling HSTS preload without verifying every subdomain is reachable via HTTPS first.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>HSTS preload with the wrong domain creates a permanently unreachable subdomain for any user whose browser has cached the HSTS policy. Only add preload after auditing every subdomain in the HSTS scope.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Pasting private keys into chat sessions or CI/CD environment variable values as plain text for debugging mTLS issues.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Private keys in chat history, CI/CD logs, or environment variable exports are permanently compromised. Use Vault dynamic secrets or CI/CD secret stores (GitHub Secrets, GCP Secret Manager) to inject private material at runtime without exposing it in logs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Configuring mTLS with ssl_verify_client on nginx but not validating $ssl_client_verify in the backend application.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>nginx may be bypassed by internal routing, misconfigured load balancers, or direct-to-backend traffic in Kubernetes. The backend MUST verify the ssl_client_verify header value equals SUCCESS before trusting any client identity headers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
