<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="help-documentation">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>Contextual, task-focused help in a layered hierarchy: inline hints, tooltips, FAQs, and guides. Reduce support costs and adoption friction.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>help-systems</tag>
      <tag>documentation</tag>
      <tag>ux</tag>
      <tag>support</tag>
      <tag>content</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Help and Documentation</title>

    <summary>Users who cannot find answers give up, generating support costs and reducing adoption. Help content reduces friction only when it is discoverable at the moment of confusion, written in user language (not product-team language), and maintained in sync with the actual UI.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Users who cannot find answers give up, generating support costs and reducing adoption. Help content reduces friction only when it is discoverable at the moment of confusion, written in user language (not product-team language), and maintained in sync with the actual UI.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Writing or auditing in-app help content: tooltips, empty states, onboarding tours, inline hints</item>
        <item>Generating knowledge base articles or how-to guides from product specs or changelogs</item>
        <item>Auditing existing documentation for staleness, gaps, or coverage against support ticket patterns</item>
        <item>Building a help search index from existing markdown/docs content</item>
        <item>Creating contextual help copy for complex forms, settings pages, or error states</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Replacing interface design improvements — if the UI requires a tooltip to be understood, the UI is broken first</item>
        <item>Producing final user-facing copy without human editorial review (accuracy and tone)</item>
        <item>Generating API reference documentation without code-level context (hallucination risk on technical details)</item>
        <item>Substituting for user research on what users actually struggle with — support ticket analysis must precede content strategy</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="agent-integration-workflow">
      <p>An agent ingests support ticket clusters (or user interview themes) and maps each to a help content type (tooltip, FAQ, how-to, onboarding step). It then generates draft content for each gap using the Help Content Template. A second agent runs a help audit pass against the existing docs index, producing a gap/staleness report. Output is a prioritized content backlog with draft content ready for human editorial review before publishing.</p>

      <note>Recommended subagents: faion-sdd-executor-agent (runs structured help content generation tasks from an implementation-plan task file); General Claude subagent (opus) (analyzes support tickets and maps to help content gaps; handles nuanced user confusion patterns).</note>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Help content must be generated only after support ticket analysis or user research identifies specific user confusion patterns. Agent-drafted content requires human editorial review before publishing.</statement>
        <rationale>Generated documentation without ground-truth user research produces plausible-sounding but incorrect instructions. Step-by-step guides hallucinate features that do not exist or miss edge cases visible only in real support tickets.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Inline hints must be ≤15 words, tooltips ≤40 words, how-to articles must include a Result section describing what success looks like.</statement>
        <rationale>Length constraints force clarity; tooltips longer than 40 words are rarely read. Result sections prevent user confusion about whether the task completed successfully.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Help Content Generation Prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are a technical writer creating contextual help for [product feature].
Given this feature description: [description]
Generate help content for three levels:
1. Inline hint (≤15 words) shown below the input field
2. Tooltip (≤40 words) shown on ? icon hover
3. How-to article (step-by-step, using the Help Content Template structure)
Do not invent behavior not described. Flag any step where you need clarification.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Help Audit Prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Help audit prompt:
Given this list of support tickets grouped by topic: [list]
And this existing help content index: [index]
For each ticket topic:
1. Does existing documentation cover it? (Y/N + link or "missing")
2. Is the content findable via search with natural language queries?
3. Is the content current (no references to deprecated features)?
Output: a gap table with priority (High/Medium/Low) and recommended action.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="where-it-fails">
      <p>Help content created by agents can fail in several critical ways:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents generate plausible but inaccurate step-by-step instructions when they lack ground-truth product screenshots or current UI state</description>
        <reason>Without access to the live product, agents cannot verify that steps match actual UI elements or account for real state transitions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Generated documentation goes stale immediately after product changes — no self-updating mechanism without a pipeline</description>
        <reason>Static documentation quickly diverges from reality; version-pinning screenshots and maintaining a content update schedule are manual processes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Contextual help placement requires UI/UX judgment that agents cannot make from text descriptions alone</description>
        <reason>Agents cannot visualize the layout; human designers must validate that help content appears in the right location without creating visual clutter.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents cannot verify that help content is accessible (screen reader, keyboard navigation) without running automated tools</description>
        <reason>Accessibility must be tested with actual assistive technology; text descriptions alone cannot verify readability or usability for users with disabilities.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Help audit tables generated from requirement lists miss implicit user confusion patterns — support tickets are a better input</description>
        <reason>Real users encounter edge cases and confusing state transitions that requirements documents do not capture.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>The following CLI tools help manage and maintain help content:</p>
      <list>
        <item>mintlify: Docs-as-code platform with search and versioning (npm i -g mintlify / https://mintlify.com/docs)</item>
        <item>docusaurus: Static docs site with full-text search (npx create-docusaurus@latest / https://docusaurus.io)</item>
        <item>vale: Prose linter — enforces plain language, style guide rules (brew install vale / https://vale.sh)</item>
        <item>markdownlint-cli: Validates markdown structure and consistency (npm i -g markdownlint-cli / https://github.com/igorshubovych/markdownlint-cli)</item>
        <item>broken-link-checker: Finds dead links in documentation (npm i -g broken-link-checker / https://github.com/stevenvachon/broken-link-checker)</item>
      </list>

      <p>SaaS and OSS services for help content delivery:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Intercom Articles (SaaS, REST API): Create/update help articles programmatically; search analytics included</item>
        <item>Notion (SaaS, REST API): Draft help content in Notion pages via API; export to publishing pipeline</item>
        <item>Mintlify (SaaS/OSS, CLI + API): Git-based docs with AI search; agents can open PRs for doc updates</item>
        <item>Algolia DocSearch (SaaS, REST API): Power help search with crawled docs; query analytics reveal missing content</item>
        <item>Chameleon / Pendo (SaaS, Partial): In-app guided tours; REST APIs for flow management; no agent-authoring SDK</item>
        <item>ReadMe.com (SaaS, REST API): API docs + guides with version management; supports programmatic content sync</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="help-audit-script">
      <p>Inline script to scan markdown docs for broken internal links and stale screenshots:</p>
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
#!/usr/bin/env bash
# help-audit.sh — check docs dir for broken links and outdated markers
# Usage: bash help-audit.sh docs/
DOCS=${1:-docs}
echo "=== Broken internal links ==="
grep -rEo '\[.*?\]\(([^)]+)\)' "$DOCS" \
  | grep -v 'http' \
  | awk -F'(' '{print $2}' \
  | tr -d ')' \
  | while read -r link; do
      [ ! -f "$DOCS/$link" ] && echo "MISSING: $link"
    done

echo ""
echo "=== Potentially stale content (references to version markers) ==="
grep -rn "TODO\|FIXME\|outdated\|deprecated\|v[0-9]\+\.[0-9]\+" \
  --include="*.md" "$DOCS" \
  | head -40
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Write help content at the moment a feature ships, not retroactively — treat it as a definition of done</item>
        <item>Use support ticket language, not product team language — users search with their words, not yours</item>
        <item>Every how-to article must have a Result section describing what success looks like</item>
        <item>Empty states are help content — design them with action guidance, not just "No items found"</item>
        <item>Version-pin screenshots with the app version they were taken from; stale screenshots erode trust faster than missing ones</item>
        <item>Track zero-results help searches weekly — each is an explicit content gap signal</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <p>When working with agents on help content generation, be aware of these common failure modes:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents cannot verify that generated step-by-step instructions match the actual current UI</description>
        <reason>Always require a human QA pass against the live product before publishing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Generated FAQ answers are often correct in aggregate but wrong in specific edge cases</description>
        <reason>Human review required before publishing; test with actual users if possible.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents producing onboarding tour copy do not know which UI elements exist or their current labels</description>
        <reason>Provide a component inventory as input; require verification against the running product.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Direct publication of agent-generated documentation without editorial review</description>
        <reason>Treat all agent output as first draft requiring editorial review before publishing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents will invent plausible troubleshooting steps that do not correspond to real error states</description>
        <reason>Require a list of actual error codes/states as input to the agent prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/help-content.md" purpose="Step-by-step how-to article structure with overview, steps, result, troubleshooting, and related topics"/>
      <template path="templates/help-audit.md" purpose="Audit table for help availability, common user questions, content quality, gaps, and priorities"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/help-audit.sh" purpose="Bash script to check docs directory for broken internal links and stale content markers"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/help-and-documentation/"/>
      <link href="https://www.writethedocs.org/guide/"/>
      <link href="https://developers.google.com/tech-writing"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/style-guide/welcome/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
