<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Platform Engineering Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1300" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules for the IDP spec. Each rule has empirical roots in Spotify / Humanitec / CNCF platform engineering data.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="backend-first-then-portal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Platform-orchestration logic (provisioning, quotas, RBAC, multi-env mapping) MUST be working before any developer-portal UI is built.</statement>
      <rationale source="Humanitec Platform Engineering State Report 2024">Portal-first creates the illusion of progress while the hard problem — service composition, quota enforcement, identity model — remains unsolved. The portal then leaks orchestration gaps to every user simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="one-golden-path-at-start" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ship exactly ONE golden path in v1. Generalise to multiple paths only after the first one has ≥10 services using it and ≥3 months of feedback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Spotify Backstage adoption case study">Multiple early paths spread the platform team thin; each path gets shallow investment and teams diverge anyway. The rule of three is empirical: deep investment in one path beats shallow investment in five.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="version-templates" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Golden-path templates MUST be semver-versioned (path-v1.2.3). Updates MUST be opt-in via PR; the platform NEVER silently mutates downstream repos.</statement>
      <rationale source="Backstage scaffolder docs">Silent template updates break consumers without warning, eroding trust and causing 'we have to escape the platform' anti-bodies.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="dora-plus-platform-metrics" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The platform team's dashboard MUST display DORA (Deployment Frequency, Lead Time, MTTR, Change Failure Rate) AND platform-specific metrics (self-service adoption rate, TTFD for new devs, ticket trend, NPS).</statement>
      <rationale source="Google DORA report, Humanitec Platform Maturity Model">Without metrics the platform becomes invisible — accountable for nothing. DORA alone misses the platform-specific signal (adoption); platform metrics alone miss the business outcome (delivery velocity).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ai-agents-are-citizens" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>RBAC, quota, audit-log, and identity model MUST treat AI agents as first-class principals (own identity, own scope, own quota) — not as a superuser running on behalf of a human.</statement>
      <rationale source="CNCF AI Agent Identity WG 2026">Conflating agent + human identity makes incidents un-debuggable ('who pushed this?') and creates a privilege-escalation surface where any human's session token is also an AI's token.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="name-the-non-goals" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST contain an `non_goals_year1` block naming what the platform explicitly will NOT do this year.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal platform-team retros across multiple orgs">Without explicit non-goals, every team asks for everything, the platform team over-commits, and confidence collapses when the inevitable cuts happen.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies If preconditions in AGENTS.md do not all hold, OR any Skip If trigger fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and pick a different one — applying the rules here on a mismatched input produces wrong output.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology guard">Methodology selection errors cascade. The cheapest place to abort is before any rule fires.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>