<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="outcome-based-roadmaps">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>Replace feature commitments with metric movements. Each row: problem, outcome metric (baseline→target), 2-3 candidate solutions. Never fewer than 2 solutions; single-solution rows are features.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>roadmap</tag>
      <tag>outcome-orientation</tag>
      <tag>product-strategy</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>solution-flexibility</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Outcome-Based Roadmaps</title>

    <summary>An outcome-based roadmap replaces feature commitments with measurable metric movements — each row states a problem, an outcome ("metric from baseline to target by horizon"), and 2-3 candidate solutions rather than a single committed feature. The rule: never fewer than 2 candidate solutions per outcome; single-solution rows are feature roadmaps in disguise.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Feature roadmaps commit to solutions before validating problems, making pivoting politically difficult even when evidence changes. Outcome roadmaps preserve solution flexibility while maintaining strategic alignment — teams stay committed to the goal, not the implementation path. This enables discovery during execution and eliminates the need to renegotiate the roadmap every time a better solution emerges.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Replacing a feature-list roadmap that has shipped on time but moved no metrics</item>
        <item>Communicating priority to engineers who keep asking "why this feature, not that one"</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF or post-PMF teams where the problem space is clearer than the solution space</item>
        <item>Any team that wants room to discover the right solution without re-renegotiating the roadmap</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Hard-deadline contractual obligations (regulatory, partner integration with launch date) — these need a feature roadmap</item>
        <item>Pure execution phase of a well-validated initiative — outcome framing adds noise; "ship the redesign" is fine</item>
        <item>Teams without metrics infrastructure — you cannot run an outcome roadmap if you cannot measure outcomes</item>
        <item>Cultures that punish missed targets — outcome roadmaps require permission to report negative results</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="structure">
      <p>Defines the required fields for each outcome row and the rule against single-solution commitments.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every outcome row must contain: problem (1 sentence), outcome_metric (the KPI being moved), baseline (current measured value), target (goal value), horizon (this quarter / next quarter), and candidate_solutions (minimum 2, maximum 5). Rows missing any of these fields are invalid and must be flagged or dropped.</statement>
        <rationale>Incomplete rows silently degrade the roadmap into a feature list. A row with a target but no baseline cannot be tracked. A row with a metric but no horizon is not time-bound and therefore not a commitment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Require a minimum of 2 candidate solutions per outcome row. A single-solution row is a feature roadmap in disguise — it has already committed to an implementation rather than preserving solution flexibility.</statement>
        <rationale>The entire point of outcome framing is to keep the solution space open while committing to the goal. One solution = already decided. Two or more solutions = the team has permission to discover what actually moves the metric.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Pair every outcome with a kill criterion: "If [leading indicator] does not move by week 6, drop this outcome." The kill criterion is required at commit time, not at quarter end.</statement>
        <rationale>Kill criteria prevent outcome theatre — spending an entire quarter on an outcome that showed no signal in the first six weeks. Without a kill criterion, teams rationalize continuing indefinitely.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Valid outcome row">
        <note>Problem = "Users contact support for questions answered in the product". Outcome_metric = "support tickets / MAU". Baseline = "0.18". Target = "0.12". Horizon = "Q2 2026". Candidate_solutions = ["in-app contextual help tooltips", "searchable FAQ embedded in product", "proactive onboarding email sequence"].</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Feature roadmap disguised as outcome">
        <note>Outcome row with single solution: "Reduce churn by building a re-engagement email sequence." Sounds outcome-shaped but has already committed to one solution. Add at least one alternative candidate solution.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Feature commitment, not outcome">
        <note>Feature roadmap row: "Build chat feature." Commits to solution before validating the problem. No metric, no baseline, no flexibility to try a different solution.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="process">
      <p>How to convert an existing feature roadmap to outcome rows and generate engineering vs. leadership views from a single source.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>For each row in the existing feature roadmap: (1) state the underlying problem in one sentence; (2) restate as an outcome — "[metric] from [baseline] to [target] by [horizon]"; (3) list 2-3 candidate solutions; (4) flag rows where you cannot identify an outcome — these are pet features or infrastructure items.</statement>
        <rationale>Infrastructure and pet features do not have outcomes because their value is not user-facing. Flag them explicitly so stakeholders understand they are funded on a different basis (technical debt, compliance, founder conviction) rather than on outcome impact.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Sort the translated roadmap by outcome impact, not by feature size or team affinity. Impact = magnitude of metric movement multiplied by strategic importance of that metric.</statement>
        <rationale>Feature roadmaps are often sequenced by development order or team availability. Outcome roadmaps must be sequenced by expected impact, which makes trade-offs explicit.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Generate two views from the same source: (a) Engineering view — each outcome with 2-3 candidate solutions, rough effort per option, current confidence; (b) Leadership view — each outcome with metric, baseline, target, current value, confidence, kill criterion. Both views must trace back to identical source rows via a row ID.</statement>
        <rationale>Traceability ID is essential. When a leadership view shows "churn" and the engineering view shows "re-engagement flow," the connection must be explicit. Views that drift from source produce inconsistent commitments.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>The customer-facing view stays at problem-statement level only. Never expose internal outcome metrics or implementation details to customers — they ask "when does feature X ship?" and the answer is "we are working on [customer problem], here is what we know about our progress."</statement>
        <rationale>Outcome metrics are internal accountability tools. Exposing churn targets or activation rates to customers creates the wrong conversation and anchors customers to implementation commitments rather than problem resolution.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <p>Failure modes that produce fake outcome framing or untrackable commitments, with root causes.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Outcome rewording: translating "Build chat" to "Improve communication outcomes." The words change but no metric, baseline, or target is added. The row is still a feature in disguise.</description>
        <reason>Outcome framing requires a measurable metric movement, not a rephrasing. "Improve communication outcomes" has no baseline and no target, making it untraceable and un-kill-criterion-able.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Single-solution rows: "Reduce churn from 8% to 5% by building a re-engagement email sequence." One solution means the team has already decided the implementation.</description>
        <reason>The value of outcome framing is preserving solution flexibility. A single committed solution collapses outcome framing back into feature roadmap behavior. Require at least 2 candidate solutions to maintain that flexibility.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Unbounded horizons: "Improve retention" with no time target. Teams can claim progress at any point without accountability.</description>
        <reason>An outcome without a horizon is not a commitment. "Improve retention to 40% DAU/MAU" is a vibe until "by end of Q2" is added. All outcome rows require explicit horizon specification.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated baselines: outcome rows that list a baseline number that was never measured, because the metric is not yet instrumented.</description>
        <reason>Invented baselines destroy tracking credibility. If the metric is not instrumented, the row must say "TO BE INSTRUMENTED, owner=X" — never an invented number. Teams cannot improve a metric they cannot measure.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Weekly roadmap rewrites. The agent re-translates the entire roadmap every week, losing the commitment history and making it impossible to track whether outcomes are improving.</description>
        <reason>Outcome roadmaps should be updated at two cadences: (1) weekly metric monitor for progress tracking; (2) quarterly re-decomposition for strategic revision. Rewriting weekly destroys the accountability record.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Stakeholders silently translating outcome rows back to feature commitments. Leadership hears "reduce support tickets by 30%" and immediately asks "which features will you ship to do that?" and anchors on the answer.</description>
        <reason>This is an ongoing communication problem, not a one-time fix. PMs must actively police the framing in every stakeholder interaction, maintaining a "confirmed solutions" list as a strict subset of the roadmap for external timing commitments.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration">
      <p>How autonomous agents integrate outcome-roadmap methodologies into product workflows.</p>

      <p>A translation agent ingests the existing feature roadmap and rewrites every line as "problem + outcome + candidate solutions" — flagging any item that does not have a clear outcome (those are typically infrastructure or pet features). A presenter agent generates two views: the engineering "options + sprint estimates" view and the leadership "outcome metric + confidence" view. A weekly metric-monitor agent reads dashboards and flags drift. Human PM owns the outcome decomposition, the kill criteria, and the conversation with sales.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents: A roadmap-translator agent (Opus) — converts feature lists to outcome statements; high-leverage strategic step. A view-generator agent (Sonnet) — formats one outcome roadmap into engineering vs leadership vs customer views. A metric-monitor agent — pulls leading-indicator data weekly, flags drift &gt; threshold. faion-mlp-impl-planner-agent — once an outcome wins capacity, plans candidate experiments under it.</p>

      <p>Prompt pattern for roadmap translation: "For each row in the current feature roadmap: State the underlying problem (1 sentence). Restate as an outcome: '[metric] from [baseline] to [target] by [horizon]'. List 2-3 candidate solutions (NOT a committed solution). Flag rows where you cannot identify an outcome — these are pet features or infrastructure. Return the rewritten roadmap in markdown, sorted by outcome impact."</p>

      <p>Prompt pattern for view generation: "Given outcome roadmap &lt;roadmap.md&gt;, generate two views: 1. Engineering view: each outcome with 2-3 candidate solutions, rough effort per option, current confidence. 2. Leadership view: each outcome with metric, baseline, target, current value, confidence, kill criterion. Both views must trace back to identical source rows."</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Core principles for running outcome-based roadmaps.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every outcome row has metric + baseline + target + horizon. Drop any row missing those fields.</statement>
        <rationale>Completeness is non-negotiable for tracking and accountability.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Present 2-3 candidate solutions per outcome, never one. Single-solution rows are feature roadmaps in disguise.</statement>
        <rationale>Solution flexibility is the core value proposition.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>The customer-facing view stays at problem-statement level; never expose internal outcome metrics.</statement>
        <rationale>Customer conversations are about problems, not internal metrics or timelines.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Keep outcomes time-bounded (this quarter, next quarter). "Improve retention" with no horizon is a vibe, not a roadmap.</statement>
        <rationale>Bounded horizons enable accountability.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Pair every outcome with a kill criterion: "if leading indicator does not move by week 6, drop this outcome."</statement>
        <rationale>Kill criteria prevent indefinite investment in outcomes showing no signal.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Reserve 20% of capacity for "unscheduled outcomes" — discoveries from the field that did not exist when the quarter started.</statement>
        <rationale>Flexibility for emergent opportunities keeps roadmaps responsive.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Sales objection management: maintain a "confirmed solutions" list that is a strict subset of the roadmap; only those get specific timing externally.</statement>
        <rationale>Prevents customers anchoring on one solution within the candidate set.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Common failure modes when LLMs design or execute outcome roadmaps.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs translate features to outcomes by simply rewording ("Build chat" → "Improve communication outcomes"). That is not an outcome. Force a measurable metric movement per row.</description>
        <reason>Rephrasing is easier than finding metrics. Models lack the domain knowledge to identify outcome-relevant KPIs.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents prefer 1 confident solution per outcome ("the obvious answer"). Force a minimum of 2 candidate solutions to preserve solution discovery.</description>
        <reason>Models optimize for coherent single narratives, not exploring solution space.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Vague outcome verbs (improve, enhance, optimize) creep in. Add a banned-verb instruction or require numeric movement per outcome.</description>
        <reason>Vague language is natural to language models; specificity requires explicit constraint.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>View-generator agents drift between leadership and engineering views — same row says different things. Require traceability ID per row across views.</description>
        <reason>Models optimize for each-view coherence independently, not cross-view consistency.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents hallucinate baselines. If the metric is not instrumented, the row must say "TO BE INSTRUMENTED, owner=X" — never invented numbers.</description>
        <reason>Plausible numbers are easier to generate than admitting measurement gaps.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Human-in-loop checkpoint: outcome decomposition (goal → outcomes) is strategic; humans must own the final tree before any view is generated.</description>
        <reason>Strategic decomposition requires human judgment about impact and importance.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Human-in-loop checkpoint: kill criteria require human sign-off — agents are too quick to delete outcomes the moment metrics wobble.</description>
        <reason>Models over-optimize for "success" signals; kill criteria require human judgment about acceptable risk.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Do not let the agent re-rewrite the roadmap weekly. Cadence: weekly metric monitor, quarterly re-decomposition.</description>
        <reason>Frequent rewrites destroy accountability and commitment history.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Known failure modes and constraints of outcome-based roadmapping.</p>

      <note>"Reduce churn from 8% to 5%" sounds outcome-shaped but is meaningless without leading indicators that move on a quarterly cadence.</note>

      <note>Stakeholders read outcome roadmaps and silently translate them back to features anyway; you have to actively police the framing.</note>

      <note>Sales gets frustrated: prospects ask "when does the chat feature ship?" and outcome framing does not answer that question.</note>

      <note>Engineering gets frustrated when "options, not committed solution" leaves them unable to plan capacity.</note>

      <note>Outcomes without bounds (e.g. "improve activation") become moving targets — must specify "to X by Y date" or it is not an outcome.</note>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/outcome-row.yaml" purpose="Single outcome row schema with all required fields"/>
      <template path="templates/validate-outcomes.py" purpose="Python validator: fails roadmap YAML with missing fields or fewer than 2 candidate solutions"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.prodpad.com/blog/now-next-later-roadmap/"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/the-ultimate-guide-to-product-roadmaps"/>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
