<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-culture-and-formats" title="HN Culture, Audience, and Post Formats">
  <summary>What Hacker News values and penalizes; audience profile; post type selection (Show HN, Launch HN, blog post, OSS); title formula with good and bad examples.</summary>

  <section title="HN Values and Anti-Values">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write titles that describe what the product does technically, not what it achieves for the user. Avoid superlatives, buzzwords, and marketing adjectives entirely.</statement>
      <rationale>HN's community actively downvotes and flags marketing language. The algorithm treats flag velocity as a quality signal. A flagged post disappears from the front page within minutes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Audience Profile">
    <p>HN readers are: software engineers and engineering managers (60%+), startup founders with technical backgrounds, investors affiliated with YC ecosystem, students and researchers. They are skeptical of hype, reward intellectual honesty, and test claims immediately. A broken demo or incorrect technical claim will be surfaced in comments within 15 minutes.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Post Types">
    <list>
      <item>Show HN: [Product] — [Description] — for products with a public demo. No signup required to see value.</item>
      <item>Launch HN: [Company] ([URL]) — for YC companies at batch launch. YC affiliation adds credibility automatically.</item>
      <item>Technical blog post — link to a deep technical article. Title is the article headline, no "Show HN" prefix.</item>
      <item>Open source project — Show HN with GitHub link. OSS projects get strong organic upvotes from the developer community.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Title Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Format: "Show HN: [What it does] — [How it's technically interesting or different]". State the fact; do not interpret it as valuable.</statement>
      <rationale>The community decides whether it's valuable. Claiming value in the title reads as marketing and reduces trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Show HN: A terminal-based Git client written in Rust
Show HN: We built a search engine for research papers
Show HN: Open source alternative to Airtable
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Show HN: The best way to manage your tasks  (marketing claim)
Show HN: Check out our startup!  (vague, self-promotional)
Show HN: Revolutionary AI-powered productivity app  (hyperbolic)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
