<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-hacker-news-launch Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-hacker-news-launch. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write titles that describe what the product does technically, not what it achieves for the user. Avoid superlatives, buzzwords, and marketing adjectives entirely.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">HN's community actively downvotes and flags marketing language. The algorithm treats flag velocity as a quality signal. A flagged post disappears from the front page within minutes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Format: "Show HN: [What it does] — [How it's technically interesting or different]". State the fact; do not interpret it as valuable.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The community decides whether it's valuable. Claiming value in the title reads as marketing and reduces trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before posting any product, build an account history of 2–4 weeks: comment thoughtfully on technical topics, share interesting links that are not your own, answer questions in your domain. Achieve 50+ karma points minimum.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">New accounts with no history get flagged as spam within minutes regardless of content quality. HN's anti-spam heuristics specifically target zero-history accounts posting product links.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post at 8–10 AM Eastern Time on Tuesday, Wednesday, or Thursday. Post the first comment immediately after submitting (within 60 seconds).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">US morning maximizes initial upvote velocity from the largest HN user base. The first comment establishes context before anyone else comments — it frames the entire discussion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never get defensive, ask for upvotes, or ignore legitimate technical criticism. Doing any of these produces a pile-on that buries the post.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">HN users interpret defensiveness as admission that criticism was valid. Asking for upvotes is explicitly against HN guidelines and gets the post killed. Ignoring technical criticism signals the product is not production-ready.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
