<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-launch-checklist" title="Launch Checklist and Engagement Rules">
  <summary>Pre-launch preparation (2–4 weeks), day-before, launch-day, and post-launch steps; engagement rules; response guidelines by feedback type.</summary>

  <section title="Pre-Launch (2–4 Weeks Before)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before posting any product, build an account history of 2–4 weeks: comment thoughtfully on technical topics, share interesting links that are not your own, answer questions in your domain. Achieve 50+ karma points minimum.</statement>
      <rationale>New accounts with no history get flagged as spam within minutes regardless of content quality. HN's anti-spam heuristics specifically target zero-history accounts posting product links.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Polish the landing page: fast load (no heavy animations), clear explanation, demo visible without signup, pricing transparent.</item>
      <item>Write the first comment in advance: technical backstory, problem context, what feedback you want, honest known limitations.</item>
      <item>Clear your calendar for the launch day — engagement must be continuous for 24–48 hours.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Launch Day Steps">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post at 8–10 AM Eastern Time on Tuesday, Wednesday, or Thursday. Post the first comment immediately after submitting (within 60 seconds).</statement>
      <rationale>US morning maximizes initial upvote velocity from the largest HN user base. The first comment establishes context before anyone else comments — it frames the entire discussion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Monitor comments continuously. Respond within 15 minutes to every substantive comment.</item>
      <item>Fix any bugs or broken links mentioned in real-time and post an update reply.</item>
      <item>Thank critics who point out legitimate issues — publicly acknowledging criticism earns respect.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Engagement Rules by Feedback Type">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never get defensive, ask for upvotes, or ignore legitimate technical criticism. Doing any of these produces a pile-on that buries the post.</statement>
      <rationale>HN users interpret defensiveness as admission that criticism was valid. Asking for upvotes is explicitly against HN guidelines and gets the post killed. Ignoring technical criticism signals the product is not production-ready.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Technical critique: thank, explain your reasoning, acknowledge trade-offs honestly.</item>
      <item>Bug report: acknowledge immediately, fix if possible, update the comment thread.</item>
      <item>Feature request: note interest, share whether it's on the roadmap or why it isn't.</item>
      <item>Trolls: no response, or a single brief factual correction.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/show-hn-first-comment.txt">First comment template for Show HN posts.</reference>
</text>
