<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="PMBoK 8 Six Core Principles Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the six-core-principles methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="positive-evidence-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>'Passed: true' requires positive evidence quoting the artefact; absence of failure is not a pass.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — audit-quality audits">LLMs default to all-green outputs because they want to be helpful; forced evidence prevents silent compliance inflation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="fail-blocks-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any principle that fails must block the stage gate; the artefact must be fixed or escalated before review concludes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Governance practice">Audit without a rejection consequence is theatre.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="canonical-six-names" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use exactly the six canonical names when auditing: Adopt Holistic View, Focus on Value, Embed Quality, Lead Accountably, Integrate Sustainability, Build Empowered Teams.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK 8 standard">Renamed principles produce inconsistent diffs across teams.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="sustainability-numeric-proxy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Integrate Sustainability requires a numeric proxy (CO2 estimate, accessibility WCAG level, social-impact scope statement); narrative does not pass.</statement>
      <rationale source="ESG measurement practice">Narrative sustainability is unmeasurable; numeric proxies enable progress tracking.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pin-pmbok-edition" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock the PMBoK edition ('PMBoK 8, six principles') in every system prompt that runs a principle audit; never let the agent infer the edition.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — edition-drift audits">LLMs conflate PMBoK 7 twelve principles with PMBoK 8 six; edition ambiguity produces incorrect audits.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Tactical execution work (sprint planning, ticket triage) — principles too abstract</item>
      <item>Non-PMI environments (PRINCE2, IPMA, SAFe) — vocabulary clashes</item>
      <item>Audit / compliance requiring named standard (ISO 21500, 21502) — principles are guidance</item>
      <item>Technical deep-dives (architecture, security) — principles do not substitute for expertise</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
