<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="PMBoK 8 Six Core Principles">
  <summary>Six principles that anchor every PM decision; each paired with a concrete measurable indicator.</summary>

  <section title="The Six Principles">
    <list>
      <item>Adopt Holistic View — see the project as part of a larger system; consider upstream and downstream effects on organisation and stakeholders. Indicator: context section in charter referencing organisational goals.</item>
      <item>Focus on Value — deliver outcomes and benefits, not just outputs. Indicator: outcomes table mapping each deliverable to a named stakeholder benefit.</item>
      <item>Embed Quality — quality is built into process and definition of done, not inspected in at the end. Indicator: DoD / acceptance criteria present before work starts.</item>
      <item>Lead Accountably — ethical, transparent leadership with clear escalation paths. Indicator: decision log with rationale and RACI with named accountability per deliverable.</item>
      <item>Integrate Sustainability — consider environmental, social, and governance impact throughout. Indicator: at least one measurable sustainability proxy (CO2 estimate, accessibility score, social impact metric).</item>
      <item>Build Empowered Teams — trust, autonomy, psychological safety, and distributed leadership. Indicator: team working agreements exist and team charter was co-created with the team.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="PMBoK 7 to PMBoK 8 Consolidation">
    <p>PMBoK 7 had 12 principles; PMBoK 8 reduces to 6. Key collapses: "Stewardship" + "Leadership" + "Ethics" → Lead Accountably; "Systems Thinking" + "Complexity" → Adopt Holistic View; "Team" + "Leadership" → Build Empowered Teams. The PMBoK 7 "Quality" principle becomes Embed Quality. Sustainability is new and explicit.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Decision Framework">
    <p>Apply at every significant PM decision point. Ask in order:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Does this deliver value? (stakeholder benefit, not just task completion)</item>
      <item>Does this consider the whole system? (upstream/downstream effects)</item>
      <item>Is quality embedded? (DoD, acceptance criteria, not post-hoc testing)</item>
      <item>Am I leading accountably? (transparent rationale, named accountability)</item>
      <item>Is it sustainable? (at least one numeric proxy)</item>
      <item>Does it empower the team? (autonomy, not control; working agreements honoured)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
