<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-audit-rules" title="Principle Audit Rules">
  <summary>Rules for running the six-principle audit as a binary gate, with antipatterns that cause false compliance.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>"Passed: true" requires positive evidence quoting the artefact; absence of failure is not a pass.</statement>
    <rationale>LLMs default to all-green outputs because they want to be helpful. Forced evidence prevents silent compliance inflation.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Any principle that fails must block the stage gate; the artefact must be fixed or escalated before the review concludes.</statement>
    <rationale>Audit without a rejection consequence is theatre; the gate must actually stop work when a principle is violated.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Use exactly the six canonical names when auditing: Adopt Holistic View, Focus on Value, Embed Quality, Lead Accountably, Integrate Sustainability, Build Empowered Teams.</statement>
    <rationale>Renamed principles produce inconsistent diffs and confuse cross-team governance reviews.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Integrate Sustainability requires a numeric proxy (CO2 estimate, accessibility WCAG level, social impact scope statement); a paragraph about sustainability values does not pass.</statement>
    <rationale>Narrative sustainability is unmeasurable; numeric proxies create accountability and enable progress tracking.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Lock the PMBoK edition ("PMBoK 8, six principles") in every system prompt that runs a principle audit; never let the agent infer the edition.</statement>
    <rationale>LLMs conflate PMBoK 7 twelve principles with PMBoK 8 six principles; edition ambiguity produces incorrect audits.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <antipattern>
    <description>All six principles pass without any explicit evidence quotes from the artefact.</description>
    <reason>All-pass outputs without quotes are LLM politeness artefacts; require citations for every passed principle.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Invoking "Build Empowered Teams" to justify removing governance or oversight.</description>
    <reason>Empowerment requires working agreements and decision rights, not absence of process; require an offsetting governance artefact.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Using "Quality" as a standalone domain label (PMBoK 6 vocabulary) inside a PMBoK 8 audit.</description>
    <reason>PMBoK 8 does not have a Quality domain; quality is the Embed Quality principle applied across all domains.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <reference path="templates/principle-audit.md">Six-row audit table template</reference>
</text>
