<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-setup" title="GA4 Setup: Streams, Enhanced Measurement, User Properties">
  <summary>Measurement ID installation, data stream configuration, enhanced measurement events, and user properties.</summary>

  <section title="Data Streams">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create one data stream per platform (web, iOS, Android); use a single GA4 property to unify cross-platform data rather than separate properties per platform.</statement>
      <rationale>Separate properties prevent cross-platform user stitching. A unified property with multiple streams allows unified user_id tracking and cross-platform funnel analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/gtag-snippet.html">GA4 gtag.js installation snippet for web streams</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Enhanced Measurement">
    <p>When enabled, GA4 auto-tracks: page_view, scroll (90% depth), outbound link clicks, site search, video engagement, and file downloads. These require no code but can be selectively disabled.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable BigQuery export from day 1 — it is free for most traffic volumes and bypasses sampling and thresholding that affects the GA4 UI.</statement>
      <rationale>Without BigQuery, agents are limited to sampled, rounded UI data. BigQuery gives raw event-level access, enabling accurate cohort, funnel, and retention queries.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="User Properties">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set user properties (subscription_tier, signup_source) via gtag('set', 'user_properties', {...}) before sending events so that all subsequent events in the session carry the properties.</statement>
      <rationale>User properties must be set before the events they should segment. Setting them after a session starts means those events have null property values in reports.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Event Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Automatic: collected by default — first_visit, session_start, page_view</item>
      <item>Enhanced measurement: scroll, click (outbound), file_download, video_start/complete</item>
      <item>Recommended: Google-defined schemas — login, sign_up, purchase, begin_checkout, add_to_cart</item>
      <item>Custom: product-specific — feature_used, subscription_started, error_occurred</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer recommended event names (login, sign_up, purchase) over custom names when the semantic is identical; Google pre-configures reports and conversion tracking for them.</statement>
      <rationale>Custom event names require manual report configuration. Recommended events flow into built-in reports and conversion funnels automatically.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
