<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-tracking" title="Event Tracking, Custom Dimensions, and Framework Integrations">
  <summary>Recommended event code patterns, custom dimension registration, Data API usage, and React/Django integration.</summary>

  <section title="Key Recommended Events">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="javascript"><![CDATA[
// Sign up
gtag('event', 'sign_up', { method: 'email' });

// Purchase — transaction_id is REQUIRED for deduplication
gtag('event', 'purchase', {
  transaction_id: 'T12345',
  value: 99.99,
  currency: 'USD',
  items: [{ item_id: 'SKU_001', item_name: 'Premium Plan', price: 99.99, quantity: 1 }]
});
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Event Parameters">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep event names under 40 characters and parameter names under 40 characters; values under 100 characters; max 25 parameters per event. Build a validator into the codegen step.</statement>
      <rationale>GA4 silently truncates or drops data that exceeds these limits. There is no error — data just disappears. Agents auto-generating long names from product specs hit this constantly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Register all custom dimensions in GA4 Admin (Admin → Data display → Custom definitions) BEFORE deploying code that sends them; unregistered params are collected but invisible in reports.</statement>
      <rationale>GA4 stores raw event params but only surfaces registered custom dimensions in the UI and Data API. Events sent before registration are not backfilled.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Data API Reporting">
    <reference path="templates/ga4_pull.py">Python Data API helper for daily top-events report</reference>
    <list>
      <item>Common dimensions: date, eventName, pagePath, sessionSource, deviceCategory, country</item>
      <item>Common metrics: eventCount, totalUsers, sessions, averageSessionDuration, bounceRate, conversions</item>
      <item>API quota: 50 concurrent requests, 250k tokens/day per property — a haiku agent in a tight loop can exhaust this</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Server-Side Tracking (Measurement Protocol)">
    <rule>
      <statement>When sending Measurement Protocol events server-side, always pass the client_id from the browser cookie (_ga cookie value); never generate a fresh UUID server-side for existing users.</statement>
      <rationale>A server-side call with a fresh UUID creates a ghost user in GA4 that is counted separately from the real user. This inflates user counts and breaks funnel attribution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/mp_track.py">Measurement Protocol server-side event helper</reference>
  </section>
</text>
