<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-analytics-framework" title="Product Analytics Framework and Implementation">
  <summary>Five-category metric model (AARRR), maturity levels, implementation process from question-first to dashboard rituals, and naming conventions.</summary>

  <section title="Analytics Maturity Levels">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start at Level 2 minimum (user segmentation) before adding instrumentation. Level 1 (page views only) produces no actionable product insights.</statement>
      <rationale>Without user identity, you cannot correlate behavior to outcomes. Retention, activation, and funnel analysis all require persistent user identification.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Level 1 — What happened: page views, signups</item>
      <item>Level 2 — Who did what: user segmentation, events per user</item>
      <item>Level 3 — Why and what if: funnels, cohort retention, A/B experiments</item>
      <item>Level 4 — What will happen: ML models, forecasting</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="AARRR Metric Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Acquisition — visitors, signups, sources, conversion rates, cost per acquisition</item>
      <item>Activation — onboarding completion, time to first key action, activation rate</item>
      <item>Engagement — DAU/WAU/MAU, session frequency, feature usage rates</item>
      <item>Retention — D1/D7/D30 retention, cohort curves, churn rate</item>
      <item>Revenue — MRR, ARPU, LTV, upgrade/downgrade rates, revenue per cohort</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Implementation Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the questions analytics must answer before writing a single tracking call. Maximum 12 events per feature; reject any event without a question it answers.</statement>
      <rationale>Tracking everything produces data lakes nobody queries. 12-event cap forces prioritization. Agents produce 30+ events without this constraint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Object-Action naming convention for events, snake_case for property names. Example: "Account Created", "Feature Used", "Upgrade Started".</statement>
      <rationale>Consistency matters more than cleverness. Inconsistent naming creates duplicate queries and breaks cohort joins across feature boundaries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use server-side instrumentation for revenue, authentication, and upgrade events. Client-side is lossy — 5-15% of conversions leak.</statement>
      <rationale>Client-side events depend on browser execution completing; network errors, ad blockers, and tab closes lose them. Critical business events need server authority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cohort by signup week, not signup date. Never mix monthly and quarterly Reach denominators in the same analysis.</statement>
      <rationale>Date cohorts conflate growth effects with retention; week cohorts isolate them. Mixed denominators inflate some segments 3-4x.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/tracking-plan.md">Tracking plan: user properties, events by stage with triggers and properties.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/dashboard-spec.md">Audience-specific dashboard spec: metrics, charts, segments, refresh cadence.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Review Cadence">
    <list>
      <item>Daily — glance at key metrics for anomalies</item>
      <item>Weekly — review dashboard, note anomalies, document observations</item>
      <item>Monthly — deep dive analysis with findings and recommendations</item>
      <item>Quarterly — goal vs actual comparison and planning</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
