<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-analytics-examples" title="Analytics Examples and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Worked examples of onboarding funnel analysis and feature-retention correlation, plus critical antipatterns and agent-specific failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Worked Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Onboarding funnel analysis revealing a specific drop-off point</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Question: Why is activation low?

Findings (funnel):
  60% start onboarding
  40% complete step 1
  25% complete step 2
  15% complete step 3  ← 62% drop here
  10% fully activate

Root cause: Step 3 = connect data source. Integration takes too long, users give up.

Action: Add "try with sample data" option to skip integration entirely.
Result: Activation rose from 10% to 28% in first cohort after change.
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Feature usage versus 30-day retention — low-usage features drive high retention</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Feature         Usage  30d Retention
Dashboard        90%       45%
Reports          30%       75%
Integrations     20%       80%

Insight: Low-usage features correlate with high retention.
Action: Promote Reports and Integrations in onboarding flow.
Note: correlation only; experiment required to confirm causation.
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM-generated SQL referencing columns that don't exist in the schema.</description>
      <reason>LLMs hallucinate column names that "should" exist. Use sqlglot + schema validation to reject unknown columns before execution.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>DAU definition drift between queries — any-event, core-action, and session-started all produce different numbers.</description>
      <reason>Agents pick whichever definition fits the narrative. Pin one DAU definition in the prompt and add it to the schema as a named metric.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Declaring "Reports drives retention" from N=12 without p-value or sample-size threshold.</description>
      <reason>Agent-generated insights from small samples mirror common SaaS narratives. Force n_users in every output row and wire minimum-sample gates into summarizer prompts.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Sending raw event rows containing email addresses or account IDs to the LLM provider.</description>
      <reason>Raw PII in LLM calls may violate GDPR DPA. Aggregate first or hash identifiers before analysis.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Declaring funnel drop causal without an experiment.</description>
      <reason>Step-3 dropoff is correlation; the fix might help for a different reason. Force "this is correlation; run experiment to confirm" in all insight outputs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-Loop Checkpoints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Any agent-generated dashboard narrative published to leadership must pass human PM review before publication.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent summaries optimize for coherence and miss nuance that a PM catches. Leadership decisions on fabricated insights have real consequences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/query-safe.py">sqlglot validator: blocks LLM SQL with unknown columns before execution against the warehouse.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/analysis-report.md">Structured report template with required limitations section and explicit N-size field.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
