<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-analytics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-analytics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM-generated SQL referencing columns that don't exist in the schema.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs hallucinate column names that "should" exist. Use sqlglot + schema validation to reject unknown columns before execution.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>DAU definition drift between queries — any-event, core-action, and session-started all produce different numbers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents pick whichever definition fits the narrative. Pin one DAU definition in the prompt and add it to the schema as a named metric.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Declaring "Reports drives retention" from N=12 without p-value or sample-size threshold.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent-generated insights from small samples mirror common SaaS narratives. Force n_users in every output row and wire minimum-sample gates into summarizer prompts.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Sending raw event rows containing email addresses or account IDs to the LLM provider.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Raw PII in LLM calls may violate GDPR DPA. Aggregate first or hash identifiers before analysis.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Declaring funnel drop causal without an experiment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Step-3 dropoff is correlation; the fix might help for a different reason. Force "this is correlation; run experiment to confirm" in all insight outputs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
