<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="PMBOK 7 Six Core Principles">
  <summary>The six PMBOK 7 guiding principles with application questions and common violation patterns for each.</summary>

  <section title="Using Principles as Pre-Commitment Heuristics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the six-principle audit before committing to any non-trivial PM decision; auditing after execution recovers nothing.</statement>
      <rationale>Principles function as pre-commitment devices; they catch violations at the cheapest moment (before execution) rather than at the most expensive (after delivery).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="1 — Adopt Holistic View">
    <p>See the project as part of a larger system: organization, portfolio, market, and ecosystem. Decisions that optimize locally often suboptimize the whole.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Application question: "Does this decision consider upstream and downstream effects outside our project boundary?"</item>
      <item>Violation pattern: shipping a feature that solves this project's problem while creating integration debt for three adjacent systems</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="2 — Focus on Value">
    <p>Deliver outcomes (user or business results), not just outputs (artifacts or features). Measure value realization explicitly, not by assumption.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Application question: "Can we measure the value this delivers, and to whom?"</item>
      <item>Violation pattern: 100% delivery rate against scope with 30% outcomes realized — "Focus on Value" is not honored without measurable success criteria</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define at least one project-specific KPI for "value" before starting execution (e.g., NPS+activation, escaped defects, revenue uplift).</statement>
      <rationale>"Focus on Value" without a measurement contract becomes virtue signaling that no one can act on.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="3 — Embed Quality">
    <p>Quality is built in from the start, not tested in at the end. Covers both product quality (defect rate, performance) and process quality (review rigor, observability).</p>
    <list>
      <item>Application question: "Where is quality verified in the workflow — and is it before or after cost is committed?"</item>
      <item>Violation pattern: equating "Embed Quality" with "add tests" while skipping code review, observability, and runbooks</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="4 — Lead Accountably">
    <p>Ethical, transparent leadership with clear decision rights. Accountability requires naming who decides, not just who recommends.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Application question: "Is there a named person accountable for this decision, and do they have the authority to make it?"</item>
      <item>Violation pattern: committee decisions with no single accountable — everyone agrees in the room, no one owns the outcome</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="5 — Integrate Sustainability">
    <p>Consider environmental, social, and economic impact. Requires concrete metrics; "we care about sustainability" without numbers is insufficient.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Application question: "What is the measurable environmental or social impact of this deliverable, and is it acceptable?"</item>
      <item>Violation pattern: skipping the sustainability question entirely in tech projects because it feels irrelevant — cloud carbon, data retention, accessibility all count</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="6 — Build Empowered Teams">
    <p>Trust, autonomy, and collaboration. Empowerment without explicit decision rights is hollow — teams need to know what they can decide without escalation.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Application question: "What decisions can this team make autonomously today, and is that boundary documented?"</item>
      <item>Violation pattern: claiming empowerment while requiring PM sign-off on every PR merge or minor scope decision</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Priority When Principles Conflict">
    <rule>
      <statement>When two principles conflict, weight them by project type — a regulated medical product weights Embed Quality 5/5; an internal hackathon weights Focus on Value 5/5 — and document the weighting in constitution.md.</statement>
      <rationale>The six principles have no built-in priority order; without project-level weighting, the most vocal stakeholder's preferred principle wins by default.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/pmbok7-audit.sh">Emits a six-row PASS/WARN/FAIL markdown audit table for a decision</reference>
</text>
