<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-audit" title="Principle Audit Procedure">
  <summary>PASS/WARN/FAIL audit protocol for the six PMBOK 7 principles, weighting procedure, and agent-specific gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Audit Protocol">
    <rule>
      <statement>Force the audit to identify at least one WARN or FAIL; an all-PASS audit is a signal of bias, not health.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs and humans both mark every principle PASS to be agreeable; a mandatory non-PASS prevents the audit from becoming a rubber stamp.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate the audit step from the decision step; do not let the same agent or person both review and recommend in one turn.</statement>
      <rationale>Combined review-and-recommend produces confirmation bias: the reviewer unconsciously justifies their pre-formed recommendation through the audit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="PASS/WARN/FAIL Definitions">
      <list>
        <item>PASS: principle is fully honored with evidence; no remediation needed</item>
        <item>WARN: principle is partially honored; a specific gap exists with a documented mitigation plan</item>
        <item>FAIL: principle is not honored; no mitigation plan; decision should be reconsidered</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Audit Format">
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Audit this <plan|decision|ADR> against the PMBOK 7 six core principles.
For each principle output: PASS / WARN / FAIL + one-sentence evidence.
End with the single highest-risk principle violation and one concrete mitigation.
Force at least one WARN or FAIL; if all pass, explain why with specific evidence.
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Weighting Procedure">
    <p>Weight principles 1-5 per project type and document in constitution.md. Weighting is not permanent — re-weight at major project milestones.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Regulated medical product: Embed Quality 5, Lead Accountably 5, Holistic View 4</item>
      <item>Internal hackathon: Focus on Value 5, Build Empowered Teams 4, others 2-3</item>
      <item>Sustainability-mandated public project: Integrate Sustainability 5, Lead Accountably 4</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Name one accountable human per principle; principles without owners drift regardless of weighting.</statement>
      <rationale>A highly weighted principle without an owner is still nobody's job; accountability converts weight into action.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Gate Calibration">
    <p>Running the audit on every issue creates noise and reduces compliance. Gate principle audits to decisions that cross significance thresholds:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Scope changes exceeding X% of baseline (set per project in constitution.md)</item>
      <item>Budget changes exceeding Y amount</item>
      <item>Architecture decisions affecting more than one team</item>
      <item>Vendor or tool selections</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent synthesizes the audit and the recommendation in the same prompt turn.</description>
      <reason>Produces confirmation bias; the reviewer unconsciously justifies their pre-formed recommendation through audit language.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent equates "Embed Quality" exclusively with adding tests.</description>
      <reason>Process quality (review rigor, observability, runbooks) is equally within scope; test-only framing misses systemic quality gaps.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent skips "Integrate Sustainability" because it seems irrelevant to tech work.</description>
      <reason>Cloud carbon, data retention periods, and accessibility all count as sustainability dimensions in PMBOK 7; skipping produces an incomplete audit.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/pmbok7-audit.sh">Emits a six-row markdown audit table for a decision</reference>
</text>
