<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Elasticsearch Index Lifecycle Management and Templates Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 rules grounded in Elastic ILM + index-template docs + production incident postmortems.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="index-template-before-data" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An index template (or data-stream template) MUST exist BEFORE the first document is indexed. Default mapping is forbidden in prod.</statement>
      <rationale source="Elastic mapping docs">ES defaults map every string to both `text` and `keyword`, wasting storage + slowing queries. Per-field mappings must be set up-front.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ilm-policy-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every time-series index MUST have an ILM policy attached. Manual deletion / rotation jobs are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Elastic ILM docs">Manual rotation causes accidental data loss or cluster-red. ILM is the only audit-trail-friendly + automatable lifecycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rollover-by-size-or-age" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hot phase MUST rollover by `max_primary_shard_size` (e.g. 50 GB) AND `max_age` (e.g. 7d). Date-stamp daily naming without rollover is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Elastic rollover docs">Daily indices without rollover produce wildly uneven shard sizes (small days waste shards, big days too large). Rollover gives uniform shards.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="write-alias-bound" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ingest target MUST be the write alias (e.g. `logs-write`), not the underlying index. Rollover swaps the alias atomically; ingest agents must never hardcode the physical name.</statement>
      <rationale source="Elastic alias docs">Hardcoded physical index names break on rollover; ingest stops without warning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="shard-count-bounded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Primary shard count per index MUST be 1-3 unless data volume per index &gt; 50 GB. Default 5 shards is forbidden for log workloads.</statement>
      <rationale source="Elastic sharding guide">Oversharding wastes overhead; &gt;20 shards per node per index degrades search. 1-shard default + rollover is the standard for time-series.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies If preconditions in AGENTS.md do not all hold, OR any Skip If trigger fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and pick a different one — applying the rules here on a mismatched input produces wrong output.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology guard">Methodology selection errors cascade. The cheapest place to abort is before any rule fires.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>