<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Pattern Bank Tagging Schema Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Pattern Bank Tagging Schema. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-closed-vocab-surface" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Surface tag is exactly one value from the closed vocabulary (auth | checkout | dashboard | nav | onboarding | settings | profile | search | content | empty-state | error | a11y); custom surfaces are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Closed-taxonomy principle">Open vocabularies erode discipline; closed enums make retrieval deterministic and trainable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-closed-vocab-intent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Intent tag is exactly one value from (educate | persuade | confirm | warn | delight | navigate | input | feedback); free-text intent is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Closed-taxonomy principle">Intent drives many retrieval queries; closed enums prevent overlap and synonym drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-pattern-type-trinary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pattern_type is one of (anti | good | neutral); &apos;good&apos; requires evidence the pattern improved a metric, &apos;anti&apos; requires evidence it harmed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Falsifiability principle">Neutral allows storing patterns whose impact is unknown; the trinary keeps the bank honest about evidence level.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-severity-from-rubric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Severity 0..4 is sourced from the heuristic-eval-severity-rubric; custom severity values are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-source-of-truth convention">Two severity scales in one organisation produce contradictory triage; the rubric is the single source.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-source-link-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every entry carries a source URL or repo path; prose-only source descriptions are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Grounded-decision convention">Untraceable sources turn the bank into folklore; the link lets reviewers re-litigate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-pattern-bank-tagging-schema.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
