<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Structural Design Patterns Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the structural-patterns methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale; the final rule is the skip-this-methodology gate referenced by the decision tree.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-signal-to-pattern" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pattern selection MUST start from a concrete signal: incompatible interfaces → Adapter; class explosion across orthogonal axes → Bridge; tree-of-uniform-leaves → Composite; behaviour stacking on one type → Decorator; broad subsystem entry-point → Facade; access control / lazy load → Proxy; many identical immutable instances → Flyweight.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gang of Four; Refactoring to Patterns (Kerievsky).">Pattern-without-signal produces speculative indirection; signal-first selection matches problem to mechanism.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-cost-bounded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each candidate pattern MUST carry an indirection cost (extra classes / files / runtime hops) and the cost MUST be weighed against documented symptom severity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal pattern-spam audits.">Structural patterns add abstraction; uncosted picks produce towers of indirection that obscure intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-decorator-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decorator stack depth MUST NOT exceed 2 per call site. Cross-cutting stacks (logging + auth + retry + cache + tracing) MUST be composed via middleware pipelines, NOT nested decorators.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal decorator-tower refactor audits.">Deep decorator stacks make stack traces unreadable and resolution of cross-cutting policy impossible; middleware composition is the documented alternative.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-facade-not-godclass" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Facade pattern MUST be applied to a coherent subsystem with a small, stable public surface. A 'Facade' aggregating unrelated domains is a god-class antipattern and MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Refactoring (Fowler).">Facades that grow without scope become god-classes — the very smell they were meant to dissolve.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-flyweight-needs-measurement" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Flyweight MUST be applied only when memory profiling shows the duplicated objects dominate the heap (≥10% of resident set or &gt; 100MB). Speculative Flyweight produces complexity for no gain.</statement>
      <rationale source="Memory profiling case studies.">Flyweight is the most invasive structural pattern; without measured pressure it pays no dividend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When prerequisites hold (signal, catalog, test coverage, impact estimate), apply r1 → r5 and emit the ADR.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology design — gate rule.">Order encodes risk: signal first, cost second, decorator cap third, facade-scope fourth, flyweight evidence fifth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do NOT use when (a) no concrete signal, (b) trivial CRUD, (c) symptom belongs to behavioural / creational family. Exit with note.</statement>
      <rationale source="Preconditions — skip gate.">Wrong-family or signal-less application yields negative-value indirection.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
