<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Mobile UX Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every mobile-ux application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-mobile-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Design for the smallest screen first. Identify core content + a single primary action for mobile; add enhancements for tablet and desktop. Never start from desktop and scale down.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google Web Fundamentals — Mobile-first">Scaling down a desktop design produces tiny targets, broken layouts, and stripped content. Mobile-first forces honest prioritisation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-one-primary-action" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One primary action per screen is a HARD constraint. Two equally weighted CTAs on a mobile screen MUST be split or redesigned to establish clear primary/secondary hierarchy.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — mobile interaction research">Competing actions on small screens cause decision paralysis and lower conversion.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-touch-target" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Minimum touch target: 44x44pt (iOS HIG) / 48x48dp (Material). Minimum spacing between adjacent targets: 8px. Hard minimums — not recommendations.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG; Material Design accessibility guidance">Below minimum produces tap errors and accessibility failures.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-thumb-zone" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Place primary actions in the thumb zone (bottom third of screen). Place destructive or rarely needed actions at the top.</statement>
      <rationale source="Hoober — Mobile Touch Research">75% of mobile interaction is one-handed; bottom-zone placement reduces reach error and fatigue.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-bottom-tab-nav" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use a bottom tab bar (3-5 items) as the primary navigation pattern for mobile apps. Reserve hamburger menus for secondary or overflow navigation only.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — bottom-nav vs hamburger studies">Bottom tabs consistently outperform hamburger menus on discoverability and section awareness.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-input-types" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set correct input type on all form fields (email / tel / number / search). NEVER disable zoom (user-scalable=no).</statement>
      <rationale source="MDN — HTML form input types; WCAG 1.4.4">Correct input types reduce form errors; disabling zoom is an accessibility violation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-core-web-vitals" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hit Core Web Vitals: LCP &lt; 2.5s, FID &lt; 100ms, CLS &lt; 0.1, TTI &lt; 5s. Serve WebP with srcset/sizes; lazy-load below-fold content.</statement>
      <rationale source="web.dev Core Web Vitals">Each 1s delay reduces conversion by ~7%; CLS above 0.1 causes mis-taps when content shifts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r8-platform-gestures" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Respect platform-specific gestures (iOS swipe-from-edge back; Android back gesture). NEVER invent non-standard gestures without a visible affordance + button alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG; Material Design gestures">Trained OS gestures work because users learned them from the OS; custom gestures are undiscoverable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r9-accessibility" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Support VoiceOver / TalkBack. Respect system text-size at 150-200%; never use absolute units that break scaling. Respect prefers-reduced-motion for animations.</statement>
      <rationale source="WCAG 2.2 — Reflow, motion">~15% of users rely on screen readers or system scaling at some point; breaking these excludes them.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
