<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="research" count="87">
  <methodology slug="affinity-diagramming" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/affinity-diagramming">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for affinity diagramming that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-revenue-mix-audit-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/agency-revenue-mix-audit-template">
    <summary>Quarterly research audit that decomposes agency revenue into project / retainer / productized lines with gross margin per line and trend analysis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-valuation-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/agency-valuation-rubric">
    <summary>Numeric scoring rubric for agency valuation rubric that converts qualitative judgment into a comparable 0-100 (or 1-5 weighted) signal usable across cohorts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agent-invocation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/agent-invocation">
    <summary>Reference for invoking faion-researcher agents from orchestrators.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-assisted-persona-building" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/researcher/ai-assisted-persona-building">
    <summary>A three-stage pipeline for building data-driven personas from behavioral analytics data: Haiku ingests and normalizes event exports; Opus identifies cluster boundaries with silhouette validation; Sonnet generates persona narratives, JTBD maps, and pain-point summaries.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-coding-of-qualitative-data-protocol" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/researcher/ai-coding-of-qualitative-data-protocol">
    <summary>Reusable template for ai coding of qualitative data protocol that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-trust-metrics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/market-researcher/ai-feature-trust-metrics">
    <summary>Feature-management method for ai feature trust metrics — what the brief, gate, and rollout artefacts must contain to move a feature from idea to production safely.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-interview-analysis" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/researcher/ai-interview-analysis">
    <summary>A two-stage pipeline for transcribing recorded user interviews and extracting themes, sentiment, and cross-interview patterns at scale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-persona-building" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/researcher/ai-persona-building">
    <summary>Fully automated end-to-end persona generation for large user datasets (1,000+ users): Haiku ingests behavioral event exports via API, Opus validates cluster separability, Sonnet transforms clusters into JSON persona documents consumable by downstream agents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-research-tool-categories" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/researcher/ai-research-tool-categories">
    <summary>A phase-and-budget decision map for selecting research tools across seven categories: exploration, competitor intel, user interviews, survey analysis, sentiment, synthesis, and synthetic research.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-research-tool-categories" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/market-researcher/ai-research-tool-categories">
    <summary>A phase-to-tool classification for AI research pipelines: map each research task to its phase (exploration, competitor intel, interview analysis, survey, sentiment, synthesis, synthetic research), then select the appropriate tool from the approved category map.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-research-tools" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/researcher/ai-research-tools">
    <summary>Stage-to-tool mapping for AI-augmented research pipelines with orchestrator pattern: Haiku for dispatch, Sonnet for synthesis, Opus for validation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-research-tools" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/market-researcher/ai-research-tools">
    <summary>A two-layer agent structure for AI-driven market research pipelines: an orchestrator (Sonnet) selects the right tool for each research stage based on task type and available credentials, then dispatches sub-queries to stage-specific tools.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="asymmetric-churn-power-interview-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/asymmetric-churn-power-interview-protocol">
    <summary>Asymmetric Churn Power Interview Protocol: codified user-research practice that turns the recurring 'p1-solo-saas-builder/Product/Market Fit hunt (post-MVP, pre-traction)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="audience-segmentation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/audience-segmentation">
    <summary>A 5-step methodology for dividing a potential market into distinct, scored groups using 2-3 dimensions drawn from observed data (demographic, behavioral, psychographic, needs-based).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="beta-cohort-recruitment" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/beta-cohort-recruitment">
    <summary>Recruits a private-beta or design-partner cohort with NDA, expectations contract, feedback cadence, and exit ramp — distinct from open user-interview recruiting.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="business-model-planning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/business-model-planning">
    <summary>Business model planning covers four linked frameworks for evaluating whether a niche is worth pursuing and how to monetize it: niche-viability scoring (5-criteria weighted), Blue Ocean / Four Actions (market space creation), Value Proposition Canvas (pain-gain fit), and pricing-model selection.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="business-model-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/business-model-research">
    <summary>Systematic analysis of how a business will create, deliver, and capture value, structured as a Business Model Canvas (9 blocks) plus P10/P50/P90 unit economics (CAC, LTV, LTV:CAC, payback period) and 5 stress tests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="business-model-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/business-model-research">
    <summary>Business model research at the market-researcher level produces a peer-benchmark table — not a single canvas.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="buyer-interview-script-for-freelancers" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/buyer-interview-script-for-freelancers">
    <summary>Mom-Test-style buyer interview script tuned for freelancers selling a service offer — hiring triggers, budget authority, vendor preference, switching pain.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitive-intelligence" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/competitive-intelligence">
    <summary>Point-in-time competitor snapshots go stale within weeks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitive-intelligence" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/competitive-intelligence">
    <summary>Competitive intelligence at the market-researcher level produces three deliverables the general CI loop does not cover: win/loss analysis (coding closed-deal records into structured loss reasons), pricing intelligence (triangulating list price against realized ACV from G2 disclosures and Vendr/Tropic benchmarks), and market-positioning signals (clustering competitor hero copy and buyer language by job-to-be-done).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitive-intelligence-methods" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/competitive-intelligence-methods">
    <summary>A two-sub-methodology bundle — competitor landscape mapping and competitive-intelligence feature analysis — run as a sequential pipeline: landscape first (2x2 positioning + whitespace identification across 15-20 competitors covering all four types), then feature-matrix drill-down (Y/P/N + 0-3 quality score with evidence URL per cell, gap-validation critic with forced skip budget).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitor-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/competitor-analysis">
    <summary>A 5-step framework for systematically studying businesses competing for the same customers: identify (direct / indirect / future), map on a positioning matrix, analyse across 8 dimensions, find gaps, then define differentiation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitor-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/competitor-analysis">
    <summary>Competitor analysis is the systematic study of businesses competing for the same customers, structured as a SWOT-grid + market-share estimation + portfolio scorecard workflow.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitor-tracker-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/competitor-tracker-template">
    <summary>Lightweight monthly competitor-matrix tooling plus a stable weekly scan schema (channels watched, last delta, action queued) so competitor signal does not devolve into noise.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="continuous-discovery" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/continuous-discovery">
    <summary>Teresa Torres' framework for embedding product discovery into the weekly delivery rhythm: daily signal collection (analytics, tickets), weekly customer interviews (2-3), weekly competitor monitoring, weekly assumption testing, bi-weekly OST synthesis, monthly research review.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="continuous-discovery" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/continuous-discovery">
    <summary>Continuous discovery is the practice of running weekly market-scanning and competitor-monitoring loops instead of one-shot research sprints.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="distribution-channel-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/distribution-channel-research">
    <summary>A 5-step process for identifying and prioritizing customer acquisition channels: map customer discovery sources, score channels on a weighted fit matrix (audience/cost/time/scale/capability), model economics per channel (LTV:CAC &gt; 3:1 as Phase-2 gate), design micro-tests ($100-500, 4-6 weeks, pre-registered kill criteria), and build a phased channel mix (1 channel first, expand after $10K MRR).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="distribution-channel-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/distribution-channel-research">
    <summary>Distribution channel research identifies and evaluates the pathways through which customers discover and adopt a product at the market level: traffic-source mix across incumbents, partner/reseller/marketplace landscape, and benchmark channel economics (CPC/CPM/CAC ranges with confidence bands).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-discovery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/feature-discovery">
    <summary>A methodology for identifying, prioritizing, and validating product features before committing engineering effort.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="frameworks" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/frameworks">
    <summary>A toolbox of eight named pre-revenue research frameworks — 7Ps ideation, Paul Graham questions, niche evaluation (50-point matrix), validation criteria, Jobs-to-be-Done, TAM/SAM/SOM, competitive intelligence, and Value Proposition Canvas — treated as a router: the agent picks the smallest subset that answers the current decision, not all eight at once.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="idea-generation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/idea-generation">
    <summary>A methodology for systematically generating viable business ideas using 7 frameworks: Skills Inventory, Pain Point Mining, Job Substitution, Productized Service, Unbundling, Market Stacking, and Your Own Problems.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="idea-generation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/market-researcher/idea-generation">
    <summary>Seven systematic frameworks for discovering solopreneur business ideas: skills inventory, pain-point mining, job substitution, productized service, unbundling, market stacking, and own problems.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="idea-generation-methods" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/market-researcher/idea-generation-methods">
    <summary>A bundle of four complementary pre-validation methods for solopreneur idea discovery: the 7P framework (Pain/Passion/Profession/Process/Platform/People/Product), Paul Graham's four diagnostic questions, systematic pain-point mining (complaint audit + workaround inventory), and a 5-dimension niche scoring matrix.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="insight-evidence-card-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/insight-evidence-card-template">
    <summary>Insight Evidence Card Template — testable methodology for interviews, evidence, synthesis. Synthesis without an evidence-card format yields opinion-shaped insights that stakeholders can dismiss; a card (claim + evidence count + quote + segment) lifts credibility.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="interview-hot-take-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/interview-hot-take-template">
    <summary>Interview Hot Take Template — testable methodology for interviews, evidence, synthesis. 5-bullet capture within 30min preserves the freshness that gets lost by synthesis time. No current methodology forces this discipline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="interview-insight-tagging-schema" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/interview-insight-tagging-schema">
    <summary>Interview Insight Tagging Schema — testable methodology for interviews, evidence, synthesis. Existing user-interviews methodology covers running interviews; there is no shared taxonomy for atomic-insight tagging that feeds an opportunity tree.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="interview-note-synthesis-ai" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/interview-note-synthesis-ai">
    <summary>Clustering insights across 20+ interviews, distinguishing signal from anecdote, producing opportunity-tree-feeding outputs — the synthesis step PMs stop short of.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jobs-to-be-done" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/jobs-to-be-done">
    <summary>Framework that maps customer progress by interviewing recent switchers and tagging Push/Pull/Habit/Fear forces.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jtbd-switch-interview" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/jtbd-switch-interview">
    <summary>Jtbd Switch Interview — testable methodology for interviews, evidence, synthesis. Solo researcher has jobs-to-be-done but not the specific Switch / Forces-of-Progress interview method (push, pull, anxiety, habit). PMs need this to validate AI features specifically because the switch costs are mostly habit/anxiety.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="market-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/market-analysis">
    <summary>Market analysis is the combined methodology for sizing a market (TAM/SAM/SOM), classifying trend timing, mapping the competitive landscape (15-20 named players with URLs), and producing a feature-gap matrix from the top 5 competitors.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="market-research-tam-sam-som" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/market-research-tam-sam-som">
    <summary>Three nested market size calculations (TAM = total addressable, SAM = serviceable available, SOM = realistically obtainable) computed via three independent methods (top-down from reports, bottom-up from customer counts, competitor-based from revenue proxies) and triangulated.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="market-research-tam-sam-som" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/market-research-tam-sam-som">
    <summary>TAM/SAM/SOM sizing quantifies market opportunity through three nested estimates using top-down, bottom-up, and competitor-based methods.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="market-sizing-with-ai" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/researcher/market-sizing-with-ai">
    <summary>AI-assisted TAM/SAM/SOM estimation using top-down and bottom-up triangulation, with explicit assumption documentation and confidence ratings per data point.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="market-sizing-with-ai" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/market-researcher/market-sizing-with-ai">
    <summary>AI-assisted TAM/SAM/SOM estimation via top-down and bottom-up triangulation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="methodologies-detail" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/methodologies-detail">
    <summary>A flat reference page bundling 20 research methodologies as a human-readable cheat sheet and an agent routing index.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="methodologies-index" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/methodologies-index">
    <summary>Routing table mapping 22 research methodology slugs to one of 5 topic files (idea-generation, market-analysis, user-research, business-model-planning, naming-and-domains) and to the corresponding faion-research-agent mode.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mixed-methods-triangulation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/mixed-methods-triangulation">
    <summary>Mixed Methods Triangulation: codified research practice that turns the recurring 'role-ux-ui-designer/AI-assisted research synthesis: interview transcripts → tagged insights → design-backlog' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="naming-and-domains" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/market-researcher/naming-and-domains">
    <summary>Systematic methodology for generating product names and validating domain/handle availability before launch.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="niche-evaluation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/niche-evaluation">
    <summary>After generating ideas, solopreneurs struggle to evaluate which niche is worth pursuing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="niche-evaluation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/market-researcher/niche-evaluation">
    <summary>Six-step framework to assess whether a market segment is viable: define the niche with a one-sentence formula, estimate TAM/SAM/SOM with cited sources, map competitors on a quality-vs-players matrix, score audience accessibility, evaluate monetization potential, and rate personal fit.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="niche-scorecard" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/niche-scorecard">
    <summary>Niche Scorecard: codified research practice that turns the recurring 'p3-technical-freelancer/Specialty niche pivot (8-12 weeks generalist to specialist)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="opportunity-solution-trees" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/opportunity-solution-trees">
    <summary>A visual discovery framework (Teresa Torres) that connects a single business Outcome to Opportunities (customer needs, grounded in evidence), Solutions (3+ per opportunity for compare-and-contrast), and Assumption Tests (one falsifiable experiment per solution).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pain-point-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/pain-point-research">
    <summary>A systematic methodology for discovering and scoring customer pain points across public sources (Reddit, G2, App Store, Quora, Upwork).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="perplexity-ai-research" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/researcher/perplexity-ai-research">
    <summary>A workflow for using Perplexity Pro Search to synthesize cited multi-source research answers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="perplexity-ai-research" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/market-researcher/perplexity-ai-research">
    <summary>Decompose a research question into 3-5 targeted Perplexity sub-queries, dispatch each via the Perplexity REST API with explicit search_recency_filter, collect cited results, de-duplicate sources, and consolidate into a markdown synthesis with a source registry.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="persona-building" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/persona-building">
    <summary>A 5-step process for creating semi-fictional buyer archetypes grounded in real interview data: gather data (minimum 10 interviews), cluster patterns, define 1-3 segments (primary / secondary / negative), build the persona with cited traits, then validate by showing the doc to actual customers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pricing-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/pricing-research">
    <summary>A methodology for determining optimal pricing by combining value-capture math, competitor analysis, Van Westendorp willingness-to-pay research, and tier design.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pricing-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/market-researcher/pricing-research">
    <summary>A six-step pricing framework: quantify value delivered, build a competitor pricing matrix, apply Van Westendorp price sensitivity (4 questions), choose a billing model, design tier structure with feature distribution, and validate via real sales.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="problem-validation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/problem-validation">
    <summary>A methodology for confirming that a problem is real, painful, and worth solving before writing code.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="problem-validation-2026" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/problem-validation-2026">
    <summary>An updated problem validation methodology for 2026 emphasizing continuous evidence-based validation over one-time gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-development-trends" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/product-development-trends">
    <summary>A research lens for current product-development practice trends: AI-augmented ideation, continuous customer feedback loops, rapid-pivot cadence, and cross-functional team structures.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-development-trends" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/product-development-trends">
    <summary>A market-side trend brief that produces TAM/pricing/positioning implications from a scored signal set.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-development-trends-2026" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/product-development-trends-2026">
    <summary>A research lens for the 2026 product-development landscape: four primary trends (AI-augmented ideation, continuous customer feedback, rapid pivots, cross-functional teams) with evidence-collection and signal-scoring methodology.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="product-development-trends-2026" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/product-development-trends-2026">
    <summary>A recurring observability job — not a one-shot research deliverable — that keeps the four product-development trend buckets grounded in dated primary sources.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="research-repo-file-naming-convention" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/research-repo-file-naming-convention">
    <summary>Filename and folder convention for a user-research repository so AI-assisted synthesis (RAG, agent tools, LLM tagging) can locate, group, and cite artefacts deterministically.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="research-repository-ops" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/research-repository-ops">
    <summary>Research Repository OPS — pinned ops for the UX/UI designer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so ai-assisted research synthesis: interview transcripts → tagged insights → design-backlog stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="research-repository-setup" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/research-repository-setup">
    <summary>Research Repository Setup — pinned method for the UX/UI designer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so user research sprint: discovery to recommendations (4 weeks) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="risk-assessment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/risk-assessment">
    <summary>A structured 5-category (market/product/team/financial/operational) risk identification and scoring process using probability x impact matrices.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="risk-assessment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/risk-assessment">
    <summary>Market-risk assessment identifies, scores, and mitigates demand, competition, pricing, trend, and channel risks before committing to a segment or pricing strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="service-blueprint" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/service-blueprint">
    <summary>Service-blueprint methodology extending solo journey-mapping with back-stage operations, support systems, and line-of-visibility for B2B and ops-dependent UX work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="single-interview-fast-loop-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/single-interview-fast-loop-template">
    <summary>Single Interview Fast Loop Template — a 30-minute prep + 24-hour synthesis loop for PMs and founders who run one customer interview at a time, not batched studies.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="success-metrics-definition" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/success-metrics-definition">
    <summary>Teams measure the wrong things or too many things.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="survey-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/survey-design">
    <summary>Survey design is the methodology for creating quantitative research instruments that yield valid, actionable data.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="synthetic-users" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/research/researcher/synthetic-users">
    <summary>AI-generated user profiles that simulate survey and interview responses for directional, pre-validation research.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="thematic-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/thematic-analysis">
    <summary>Thematic Analysis: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-ux-ui-designer/AI-assisted research synthesis: interview transcripts → tagged insights → design-backlog'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trend-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/trend-analysis">
    <summary>A systematic pipeline for identifying and evaluating emerging market trends before acting on them.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trend-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/market-researcher/trend-analysis">
    <summary>Trend analysis at the market-researcher level identifies emerging patterns from industry analyst reports, macroeconomic indicators, regulatory pipelines, and incumbent 10-K filings.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="use-case-mapping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/use-case-mapping">
    <summary>Products get built without clear understanding of how users will actually use them.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-interviews" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/user-interviews">
    <summary>Founders skip user interviews or conduct them poorly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-research-at-scale" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/user-research-at-scale">
    <summary>AI-augmented research operations for N &gt;= 500 sessions/week or &gt;= 50 unmoderated tests, running a 9-stage pipeline: intake → sampling → instrumentation → collection → transcription → coding → synthesis → review → publish.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="validation-paralysis-breaker" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/validation-paralysis-breaker">
    <summary>Validation Paralysis Breaker: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'p2-indie-hacker/Tweet-to-launch sprint: idea to paying user in 3 weeks'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="value-proposition-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/research/researcher/value-proposition-design">
    <summary>Value Proposition Design answers "Why should I choose you over alternatives?" by mapping customer jobs, pains, and gains against your product's pain relievers and gain creators using the Value Proposition Canvas.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="win-loss-interview-program" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/win-loss-interview-program">
    <summary>Sample frame, deal-stage selection, script bias, sales handoff — the specific structure of win/loss interviews user-interviews and problem-validation don't cover.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="workflows" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/workflows">
    <summary>Sequential research state machines for Idea Discovery, Product Research, and Project Naming.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="wtp-survey-questionnaire" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/wtp-survey-questionnaire">
    <summary>Wtp Survey Questionnaire: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-product-manager/Pricing experiment, hypothesis to result'.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
