<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design System Impact Queue Core Rules">
  <summary>The triage discipline that keeps every "this affects the system" note from becoming silent component drift.</summary>
  <section title="Queue contract">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every design or component review ends with an explicit "system impact" check: reviewers either add zero or more entries to the queue, or call "no impact" on the record. The check is part of the review template; reviews that skip it are reopened.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a forced check, the impact gets discussed in the meeting and forgotten in the hallway. Making the check a checkbox on the review template converts ambient awareness into queued work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Each queue entry carries six fields: id, source (link to the review where it was surfaced), description (one sentence), proposed path (promote / fix-local / reject), evidence (screenshots or Figma link), and proposer. Entries missing fields are bounced to the proposer, not silently completed by the triager.</statement>
      <rationale>A queue that gets edited during triage hides the surfacing context — and the same issue gets re-raised next month. Bounce-on-incomplete keeps the surfacing-vs-triage roles separate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The queue is triaged on a fixed weekly cadence (≤30 minutes) by the design-system owner plus one rotating consumer-team representative. Every entry leaves the triage with a decided path; "we'll look at it later" is not a valid outcome.</statement>
      <rationale>"Later" entries accumulate, the queue becomes a graveyard, and the team stops adding new entries. Forcing a decision per entry per week is the only mechanism that keeps the queue trusted as the routing surface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Fix-local entries get a "system note" written into the consumer team's codebase (a comment block or local README section) that says: "Fixed locally because system rejected promotion at QUEUE-NNN; revisit when system adds component X". The note is required at PR-merge time.</statement>
      <rationale>Local fixes without a forward-pointer become invisible drift. The forward-pointer turns the queue into a debt ledger the next reviewer can see.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Queue health is tracked monthly with three metrics: open age (median age of open entries), promotion-rate (% of triaged entries that go to system), and re-raise-rate (% of entries that match a previously-rejected entry). Any metric trending the wrong direction triggers a governance retro.</statement>
      <rationale>Without metrics the queue's failure modes are invisible: stale entries pile up, the system team becomes too permissive or too restrictive, the same idea keeps coming back. Three cheap counters surface each failure mode early.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## QUEUE-2026-05-20-007
- source: design-review/2026-05-20#checkout-flow
- description: Inline error banner uses red-600, system has only red-500/red-700.
- proposed path: promote (new token red-600)
- evidence: figma.com/...frame-12
- proposer: K. Petrenko
- triage 2026-05-22: PROMOTE — RFC-0044 opened, deprecate red-500 alias.
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
slack: "btw the new banner is a slightly different red, fyi @design-team"
]]></code>
      <note>No id, no record, no decision — will be re-raised in the next design review as a new finding.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
