<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Structured Interview Design Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the Structured Interview Design methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale. Hard rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cover 5-7 distinct competencies in the kit; fewer than 5 under-samples role demands, more than 7 dilutes per-round depth.</statement>
      <rationale source="Structured Hiring practice handbook">Empirical hiring data shows correlation peaks around 5-7 competencies; outside this band signal-to-noise drops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every competency maps to exactly one primary round with a named owner; double-coverage creates redundant evidence at the cost of breadth.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — interview audit Q1 2026">Mapping discipline forces explicit choices about what each round measures; redundancy is a sign of unclear scoping, not extra safety.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a dry-run with ≥2 mock candidates before the kit goes live; revise anchors where disagreement exceeds one rubric level.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — interview audit Q1 2026">Live-debugging the kit on real candidates leaks bias into the cohort; dry-run is the cheap stage to fix calibration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Publish the debrief contract alongside the kit (decision rule, dissent recording, deadlock break).</statement>
      <rationale source="Structured Hiring practice handbook">A kit without a debrief contract decays into hallway decisions; explicit contract keeps the process auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit kit annually against hire-success correlation; if correlation &lt;0.4, rewrite anchors and re-calibrate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — interview audit Q1 2026">Kits drift as roles drift; an annual audit catches drift before it propagates into a year of bad hires.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
