<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="QBR Deck Template Services Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding QBR Deck Template Services plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="fixed-10-slide-shape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each QBR deck MUST follow the fixed 10-slide shape (cover, outcomes, metrics, wins, risks, asks, finance, retention plan, next quarter, owners); custom slide orders MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — micro-agency QBR audit 2025">Custom shapes force the client to re-orient each quarter and signal weak operating discipline; fixed shape is the contract.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-owner-per-slide" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every slide MUST carry a named owner accountable for its content; orphan slides MUST be deleted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — deck quality audit 2026">Orphan slides drift to generic platitudes; named-owner is the structural gate against deck rot.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-anchor-per-claim" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every metric or claim MUST anchor to evidence (dashboard URL, ticket ID, transcript timestamp); unanchored claims MUST be removed.</statement>
      <rationale source="ChurnZero customer-meeting playbook">Unanchored claims invite client dispute; evidence anchors make the deck a defensible record.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="outcome-review-not-output-recap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The deck MUST review outcomes against the prior-quarter plan (delta, root cause, next move); pure output recaps (hours billed) MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Blair Enns — Win Without Pitching">Output-only QBRs reinforce time-billing perception and erode strategic positioning; outcome review is the value frame.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="asks-section-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The deck MUST have a dedicated Asks slide listing 1-3 explicit asks (intros, references, scope changes, budget); decks without Asks MUST be returned for revision.</statement>
      <rationale source="Blair Enns — Win Without Pitching">QBRs without asks underuse client goodwill; the dedicated slide is the structural prompt against polite over-modesty.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
