<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="EEAT Signal Pass Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every EEAT Signal Pass Template application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-author-bio-present" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post MUST link to an author bio with credentials and topical expertise. Anonymous or generic 'staff' bylines are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Google E-E-A-T weights authorship signals heavily; anonymous posts under-rank against named-author equivalents.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-last-updated-date" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post MUST display a last-updated date ≤12 months old. Stale or missing dates are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Recency is a ranking factor for evergreen topics; older posts under-perform fresh ones.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-citations-with-links" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post MUST cite ≥3 sources with outbound links. Source-free posts are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Citations signal research depth; AI engines preferentially cite citation-rich content.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-original-quote-or-data" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post MUST contain ≥1 original quote OR original data point. Aggregation-only posts are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Original content is the strongest E-E-A-T signal; aggregation gets demoted.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-schema-markup" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post MUST ship with article schema.org markup including author + datePublished + dateModified. Schema-free posts are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Schema markup unlocks rich results and increases AI-engine extractability.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
