<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-loop-types" title="Five Viral Loop Archetypes">
  <summary>Word of Mouth, Inherent, Incentivized, Content, and Outbreak loops with K ranges, characteristics, and real examples.</summary>

  <section title="Loop Mechanics">
    <p>All viral loops share the same 5-step cycle: user joins → encounters trigger → sends invitation → friend converts → new user repeats the cycle. Loop type determines where the trigger occurs and how strong it is.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Word of Mouth">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use WOM when the product is genuinely exceptional and natural share moments exist at peak satisfaction; do not engineer WOM for mediocre products.</statement>
      <rationale>WOM has low i (not everyone tells friends) but high c (personal recommendation converts strongly). Forcing WOM prompts on a product without real delight backfires — users feel pressured and NPS drops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Typical K: 0.1-0.5</item>
      <item>Examples: Notion (early), Figma (design teams)</item>
      <item>Best for: productivity tools, exceptional consumer products, strong brand</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Inherent Virality">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use inherent virality only when the product functionally requires others to participate; do not force collaboration features onto solo-use products.</statement>
      <rationale>Inherent virality has the highest K ceiling because the invite is required, not optional. Forced inherent virality (fake "invite to see content") gets labeled spam and damages NPS.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Typical K: 0.5-2.0</item>
      <item>Examples: Slack, Zoom, Figma, Google Docs</item>
      <item>Best for: collaboration, team, and multi-player products</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Incentivized (Referral)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use incentivized virality when LTV &gt; 3x CAC and the reward can be sized at 20-50% of CAC without destroying margins; implement double-sided incentives.</statement>
      <rationale>Incentivized virality boosts i but reduces authenticity, lowering c. The net K is viable when the reward economics work. Single-sided referrals feel exploitative and perform 20-30% worse.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Typical K: 0.3-1.0</item>
      <item>Examples: Dropbox (free storage), Uber ($10 credit), PayPal ($10 cash)</item>
      <item>Best for: high-LTV SaaS, fintech, e-commerce with margin room</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Virality">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use content virality when users naturally produce shareable artifacts (scores, results, badges, created content) that embed product branding without feeling like an ad.</statement>
      <rationale>Content virality has variable i (depends on content quality and shareability) and low c (many views, few signups). The share artifact must have novelty and social value — most imitations fail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Typical K: 0.1-0.5 (content platforms can hit 0.8+)</item>
      <item>Examples: TikTok, Wordle (K=1.5+), Spotify Wrapped</item>
      <item>Best for: content creation platforms, social apps, entertainment products</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Outbreak Virality">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not implement outbreak (automated contact import) virality; modern email filters and OS protections block it, and it damages brand reputation.</statement>
      <rationale>Outbreak virality automates invites to full contact lists. It was viable in 1996 (Hotmail email signature). Today it triggers spam filters, breaches CAN-SPAM, and is rejected by app stores.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
