<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-selection" title="Loop Selection, Instrumentation, and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>How to pick the right loop type, instrument share events, and avoid common agent mistakes.</summary>

  <section title="Loop Selection by Product Type">
    <list>
      <item>Collaboration tool → Inherent (primary) + WOM (secondary)</item>
      <item>Consumer app → Content (primary) + WOM (secondary)</item>
      <item>Marketplace → Incentivized (primary)</item>
      <item>Productivity tool → WOM (primary) + Inherent (secondary if team features exist)</item>
      <item>B2B SaaS → WOM (primary) + Incentivized (secondary)</item>
      <item>Gaming → Content (primary) + WOM (secondary)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run at most 2 loops in parallel; instrument them with distinct loop_type property on all invite events so K can be computed per loop separately.</statement>
      <rationale>Attribution between loops is messy without explicit tagging. Running 4 loops at once makes it impossible to know which is contributing and which is wasting engineering effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Share Moments by Loop">
    <list>
      <item>WOM: user achieves their goal; user discovers unexpected value; user solves a major problem</item>
      <item>Inherent: user needs collaboration; user wants to share work; user requires team input</item>
      <item>Incentivized: user completes onboarding; user reaches usage milestone; user is on referral page</item>
      <item>Content: user creates something; user achieves a result; user wants recognition/comparison</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Required Instrumentation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Instrument invite_sent with loop_type, share_channel, and recipient_count properties before launch; without these, K cannot be diagnosed when it drops.</statement>
      <rationale>K drops silently. A redesigned share button can drop i by 40% without any alert. Weekly K split by loop_type and share_channel is the minimum for actionable monitoring.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/viral_sim.py">Python simulator to compare K projections for different loop choices</reference>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Agent recommends "make it inherent" for a non-collaborative product.</description>
    <reason>Forced inherent virality creates fake invite prompts that users reject. It kills NPS without raising K. Inherent virality only works when collaboration is the core value proposition.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Computing K on fewer than 500 invite events and reporting it as meaningful.</description>
    <reason>K is volatile at small samples. Signal:noise ratio is unacceptable below ~500 invites per reporting period. Agent must flag low-power computations explicitly.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Recommending outbreak/spam loops based on outdated case studies.</description>
    <reason>Pre-2005 outbreak mechanics are blocked by modern email filters and mobile OS permissions. Always reject this suggestion regardless of source.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
