<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="viral-loops Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for viral-loops as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent recommends "make it inherent" for a non-collaborative product.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Forced inherent virality creates fake invite prompts that users reject. It kills NPS without raising K. Inherent virality only works when collaboration is the core value proposition.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Computing K on fewer than 500 invite events and reporting it as meaningful.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>K is volatile at small samples. Signal:noise ratio is unacceptable below ~500 invites per reporting period. Agent must flag low-power computations explicitly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Recommending outbreak/spam loops based on outdated case studies.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-2005 outbreak mechanics are blocked by modern email filters and mobile OS permissions. Always reject this suggestion regardless of source.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Models confuse K with conversion rate; force the prompt to specify K = i times c.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>K is the product of average invites per user (i) and invitee conversion rate (c). Conflating K with c leads to wrong optimization decisions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent pushing outbreak (auto-contact-import) loops without explicit human approval.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>TOS and CAN-SPAM landmine. Outbreak mechanics are dead on modern email and mobile platforms.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Weekly K computed on fewer than 500 invites reported as meaningful signal.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>K is noise below ~500 invites per reporting period; agent should flag low-power computations rather than report them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents over-fit on Dropbox/PayPal case studies when recommending a target K.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require it to cite a benchmark range (consumer apps: 0.1-0.3; B2B SaaS: 0.05-0.2) before recommending a target K.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Mobile attribution agents using different client_id across web and app.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Passing different IDs silently breaks K attribution. Use the same client_id consistently across all platforms.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
