<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="stakeholder-engagement">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Systematic identification, classification, and engagement of everyone who affects or is affected by the project using a YAML-based register with mandatory evidence and quadrant-based strategy.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>stakeholders</tag>
      <tag>engagement</tag>
      <tag>power-interest</tag>
      <tag>communication</tag>
      <tag>relationship-management</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Stakeholder Engagement</title>

    <summary>Systematic identification, classification, and engagement of everyone who affects or is affected by the project. The core artifact is a YAML-based stakeholder register (power, interest, attitude with evidence, quadrant, cadence, owner) stored in git so that engagement history is a diff log. Attitude assertions without evidence default to "unknown" — optimistic defaults ("supportive") are a known agent failure mode and a trust risk.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Projects fail when influential stakeholders are missed, misclassified, or over-engaged to the point of fatigue. The Power/Interest grid routes the right level of attention to each quadrant. Static analysis is insufficient — power and interest shift with project phases, org changes, and external events. Without a refresh cadence and a behavioural triangulation step, the register becomes a historical artefact rather than a live management tool.</p>
      <p>The 2x2 Power/Interest grid (Mendelow) flattens multi-dimensional politics; Mitchell-Agle-Wood salience overlay is needed for high-stakes programs. Static analysis goes stale fast — 2 to 6 weeks in dynamic orgs; an unrefreshed register is wrong, not just old. Self-reported attitude is unreliable; people say "supportive" in workshops and undermine in private. Triangulate against behaviour. Hidden stakeholders (works councils, security, procurement, downstream consumers, FinOps, accessibility) are systematically missed without org-chart seeding. LLMs invent plausible-sounding personas; outputs must validate against directory data. Cross-cultural blindness — high-context cultures (JP, KR, parts of EU/MEA) route influence through indirect networks the matrix does not represent. "Manage Closely" is not one strategy — a CFO and a regulator demand opposite tone, cadence, and content; uniform handling fails both. Stakeholder fatigue — well-meant high-touch engagement burns goodwill if asks exceed tolerance.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Project kickoff for any cross-functional initiative with more than 5 named parties.</item>
        <item>Programs with high political risk: M&amp;A, reorgs, regulated rollouts (HIPAA, SOX, GDPR).</item>
        <item>Pre-RFP / vendor selection where the buying committee has hidden influencers (security, procurement, FinOps).</item>
        <item>Multi-stakeholder transformation programs where power and interest shift across phases.</item>
        <item>Pair with communications-management so cadence in the register is reflected in the comms plan.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo founders or teams under 5 stakeholders — direct conversation beats matrix overhead.</item>
        <item>One-off internal hotfixes with no business stakeholder change — RACI is sufficient.</item>
        <item>Crisis/incident response — incident command structure replaces engagement plan during a P0.</item>
        <item>When stakeholder identification is unsolved — run BA stakeholder-analysis first to populate the register.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="register-schema">
      <rule>
        <statement>Store the register in YAML in git (stakeholders/register.yaml), not in a wiki or spreadsheet. Git diffs become the engagement history; CODEOWNERS gates sign-off on attitude changes.</statement>
        <rationale>Wikis erase history; spreadsheets create competing versions. Git-backed YAML makes every change auditable with timestamp and author.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Required fields per stakeholder: id, name, category (Sponsor/User/Customer/Team/Regulator/Supplier/Influencer), power (H/M/L), interest (H/M/L), attitude (+/0/-/unknown), quadrant, evidence list, cadence, channel, owner, last_engaged date.</statement>
        <rationale>Missing fields create ambiguity about who manages the relationship and what the current engagement state is.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="evidence-and-attitude-policy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every attitude assertion must have at least one evidence entry (meeting quote, transcript line, ticket link, survey response). No evidence means attitude defaults to "unknown", not "supportive".</statement>
        <rationale>Agents and humans both have politeness bias — they label stakeholders as "supportive" without behavioural evidence. Unsupported optimistic classification causes under-attention to real resistors.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Triangulate self-reported attitude with at least one behavioural signal: meeting attendance rate, response time to requests, escalation count, survey delta. Single-source attitude is unreliable.</statement>
        <rationale>People say "supportive" in workshops and undermine in private. Cross-referencing behaviour reduces misclassification.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="hidden-stakeholder-review">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a mandatory "hidden stakeholder" review at project kickoff: check legal, infosec, procurement, works council/union, accessibility, downstream consumers, FinOps, and any community/NGO affected parties.</statement>
        <rationale>These categories are systematically missed when the register is seeded from the org chart alone. Each has blocked or derailed projects when discovered late.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never invent stakeholder names or roles; seed from a real org chart export or directory. Any name not in the source list must be flagged "suggested_to_verify" and confirmed by the PM.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents invent plausible-sounding personas when the register is built without a grounding source. Invented stakeholders create phantom engagement and miss real ones.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="privacy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat the stakeholder register as PII under GDPR Art. 9 if attitude fields imply political opinion or health status. Never send the full register to a third-party model without a Data Processing Agreement.</statement>
        <rationale>Attitude, role sensitivity, and relationship context are personal data. GDPR and equivalent regulations require a legal basis for processing and restrict third-party transfer.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="quadrant-engagement-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Default cadence by quadrant: High-High (Manage Closely) → weekly 1:1; High-Low (Keep Satisfied) → biweekly summary; Low-High (Keep Informed) → monthly digest; Low-Low (Monitor) → release notes only. Override only with explicit rationale documented in the register.</statement>
        <rationale>Default cadences are calibrated to stakeholder attention tolerance by quadrant. Ad-hoc cadences without rationale produce either stakeholder fatigue or gaps.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>"Manage Closely" is not one strategy — a CFO and a regulator require different tone, content, and channel even if both are High-High. Document per-stakeholder overrides in the register.</statement>
        <rationale>Uniform high-touch engagement for all Manage Closely stakeholders conflates power with content needs. Regulators require compliance evidence; CFOs require financial narrative.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="refresh-triggers">
      <rule>
        <statement>Refresh the register quarterly at minimum, monthly in volatile contexts (post-merger, leadership change, regulator activity). An unrefreshed register older than 6 weeks is incorrect, not just stale.</statement>
        <rationale>Power and interest change with project phase and org events. A 3-month-old classification of a stakeholder who has since been promoted or reassigned produces misdirected engagement.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap agent edits to 5 stakeholders per run and require human review of the diff before applying. Bulk reclassification erases nuance and creates liability if attitude fields contain sensitive signals.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated bulk updates bypass the validation that human judgment provides on sensitive relationship data.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="calendar-audit">
      <rule>
        <statement>If any stakeholder appears in more than 3 recurring weekly meetings, consolidate or remove one. Stakeholder fatigue erodes goodwill and reduces meeting attendance — the opposite of engagement.</statement>
        <rationale>Well-meant high-touch engagement burns goodwill if asks exceed tolerance. Engagement frequency must be calibrated to the stakeholder's actual capacity to absorb.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-sending communications to executives, regulators, or board members without PM approval.</description>
        <reason>These stakeholders are high-stakes; an error in an automated message to an executive or regulator has disproportionate reputation and legal consequences. Agent drafts; PM or sponsor approves.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Conflating stakeholder (real named person with decision power) with persona (synthesised archetype).</description>
        <reason>Stakeholders require personalised engagement plans; personas are for UX design. Mixing them produces engagement plans that address a fictional composite rather than real decision-makers.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Applying Western-norm engagement defaults to high-context cultures (JP, KR, parts of EU/MEA).</description>
        <reason>Influence routes through indirect networks in high-context cultures; a direct weekly 1:1 invitation to a Japanese executive may be perceived as disrespectful. Add cultural_context field and adjust approach.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Treat the engagement plan as a structured artifact in git: stakeholders/register.yaml (one entry per stakeholder with influence, impact, attitude, quadrant, strategy, cadence, owner, last_engaged, evidence) plus a generated engagement-plan.md. A subagent maintains the register, proposes patches when new evidence arrives (kickoff transcripts, calendar invites, Slack signals, NPS surveys), and emits a weekly engagement digest. The plan never auto-sends to executives — agents draft, humans deliver. Pair with communications-management/plan.yaml so cadence in one is reflected in the other.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-sdd-executor-agent (drives engagement as SDD tasks: TASK_register_baseline, TASK_engagement_plan, TASK_cadence_setup, TASK_quarterly_refresh). Custom register-curator-agent (sonnet) — ingests org chart, kickoff transcripts, RFP, contract; emits patches; never overwrites. Custom attitude-triangulator-agent (sonnet) — cross-references self-reported attitude against meeting attendance, response time, escalation count. Custom engagement-planner-agent (sonnet) — converts register quadrants into Step-5 engagement table (cadence, channel, owner, content) with override rationale required for non-default cadence. Custom salience-scorer-agent (opus) — applies Mitchell-Agle-Wood (power x legitimacy x urgency) on top of the matrix; identifies "definitive" stakeholders requiring daily attention. password-scrubber-agent — runs over engagement docs before commit; the register frequently leaks salaries, candid commentary, customer names.</p>
      <p>Prompt pattern (two-stage discovery → classification → engagement strategy): You are register-curator. Inputs: kickoff transcript, org-chart export, existing register. For each named or implied party, emit STRICT JSON patch: { "action": "add|update", "id": "S-NN", "name": "...", "category": "Sponsor|User|Customer|Team|Regulator|Supplier|Influencer", "power": "H|M|L", "interest": "H|M|L", "attitude": "+|0|-|unknown", "quadrant": "Manage Closely|Keep Satisfied|Keep Informed|Monitor", "evidence": ["quote or org-chart line"], "cadence": "daily|weekly|biweekly|monthly|quarterly|release", "channel": "1:1|email|digest|meeting|portal", "owner": "&lt;role&gt;", "rationale": "&lt;= 2 sentences" }. Rules: never invent people. attitude defaults to "unknown" without evidence.</p>
      <p>Engagement plan prompt: Render Step-5 table from register. Default cadence: HH=Manage Closely (weekly 1:1), HL=Keep Satisfied (biweekly summary), LH=Keep Informed (monthly digest), LL=Monitor (release notes). Override only with explicit rationale.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools: git + git log -- stakeholders/ (native history of relationship changes), yq (read/patch register YAML in pipelines), jq (aggregate JSON exports from CRM/HR systems), graphviz / dot (render influence/impact graph + relationship network), mermaid-cli / mmdc (generate the 2x2 quadrant chart from YAML), pandoc (convert plan to PDF/DOCX for sponsor review), pre-commit (block attitude/quadrant changes without evidence:), gh / glab (mirror engagement actions as issues; CODEOWNERS gates sponsor sign-off), op / 1Password CLI (pull sensitive contact info into the register without committing it).</p>
      <p>Services &amp; apps: Microsoft Graph (Entra ID) (SaaS, REST/Graph, source of truth for internal org chart, reporting lines, group membership; required to seed register without inventing). Workday HCM / Personio / BambooHR (SaaS, REST, authoritative for level, span of control, manager — useful for influence inference). Salesforce (SaaS, REST + Bulk API, authoritative for external customer stakeholders). HubSpot (SaaS, REST, lighter SMB CRM; webhooks drive attitude triggers). Notion / Confluence (SaaS, REST, common register host; weak typing — schema-validate before commit). Jira / Linear (SaaS, REST/GraphQL, stakeholder = issue with custom fields, less ideal but common). Smaply / UXPressia (SaaS, limited API, persona/journey tools; visual artifact only). StakeholderMap.com / Lucidchart / SmartDraw (SaaS, export-only, treat as artifact target, not agent target). Mural / Miro / FigJam (SaaS, REST, workshop canvas for matrix exercises; agents can post sticky notes via API). Slack / MS Teams (SaaS, REST + Events, source for behavioural signal; use with consent). Qualtrics / Typeform / SurveyMonkey (SaaS, REST, periodic stakeholder pulse surveys feeding attitude triangulation).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Store the register in git (YAML), not a wiki — diffs become engagement history; CODEOWNERS gate sponsor sign-off on attitude changes. Require an evidence: field on every attitude assertion (quote, transcript line, ticket link). No evidence → attitude: unknown. Refresh quarterly minimum, monthly for volatile contexts (post-merger, leadership change, regulator activity). Triangulate self-reported attitude with at least one behavioural signal (attendance, sentiment, response time, escalations). Apply the Mitchell-Agle-Wood salience overlay for political risk — flag "definitive" stakeholders for daily attention. Tie cadence to quadrant by default; override only with explicit rationale. One canonical register — if Workday or Salesforce holds source data, mirror nightly; do not maintain two truths. Always run a "hidden stakeholders" review (legal, infosec, procurement, works council/union, accessibility, downstream consumers). Calendar audits prevent burnout — if any stakeholder appears in &gt;3 weekly meetings, consolidate.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Agents invent people; seed with a real org chart export and reject any name not in the source list unless flagged suggested_to_verify. LLMs over-classify everyone as "supportive" by default (politeness bias). Force a 4-way enum (+/0/-/unknown) with unknown default. Stakeholder data is regulated PII (GDPR Art. 9 if attitude implies political opinion or health). Never send the register to a third-party model without DPA. Bulk reclassification is dangerous — cap agent edits to N stakeholders per run (e.g., 5) and require human review on the diff. Stakeholder vs. persona conflation: stakeholder = real named human/role with decision power; persona = synthesized archetype. Separate files. Influence ≠ seniority. A CFO's EA may have more influence on calendar decisions than the CFO; force the agent to consider gatekeepers. Auto-send is forbidden to executives, regulators, customers, and board. Agent drafts; PM or sponsor approves. Sentiment from Slack is lossy and easily misclassified; never act on a single message. Cross-cultural miscoding — agents trained on Western norms misread consensus cultures. Add a cultural_context system prompt for international initiatives. Human-in-the-loop checkpoints (mandatory): adding a stakeholder, changing attitude, escalating to sponsor, dropping a stakeholder from active engagement.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/engagement-due.py" purpose="Lists stakeholders overdue for engagement based on register YAML and cadence."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards/foundational/pmbok"/>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mendelow%27s_matrix"/>
      <link href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/261355131_Toward_a_Theory_of_Stakeholder_Identification_and_Salience_Defining_the_Principle_of_Who_and_What_Really_Counts"/>
      <ref slug="stakeholder-register"/>
      <ref slug="communications-management"/>
      <ref slug="change-control"/>
      <ref slug="requirements-documentation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
