<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-stakeholder-framework" title="Stakeholder Identification, Mapping, and Engagement">
  <summary>Covers the six stakeholder types, Power/Interest grid, four engagement levels, and the 4-step management process with PM-specific columns.</summary>

  <section title="Stakeholder Types">
    <p>Six categories: End Users (customers/employees, need product value); Decision Makers (executives/sponsors, need business outcomes); Influencers (advisors/thought leaders, need credibility and early access); Builders (developers/designers, need clear requirements); Support (customer success/sales, need product knowledge); External (partners/regulators, need compliance and compatibility).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Power/Interest Grid">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map every stakeholder to one of four cells: High Power/High Interest (manage closely), High Power/Low Interest (keep satisfied), Low Power/High Interest (keep informed), Low Power/Low Interest (monitor only).</statement>
      <rationale>The grid converts the implicit political map into a routable communication plan; without it, PMs spend equal time on every stakeholder regardless of impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure power by decisions blocked or unblocked in the last quarter, not by org-chart title.</statement>
      <rationale>A Principal Engineer or Distinguished Architect often has more product veto power than a director; title-based power maps miss these nodes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Engagement Levels">
    <p>Four levels: Partner (active co-creation, regular meetings); Involved (regular input, reviews, feedback sessions); Informed (one-way updates, newsletters, demos); Monitor (minimal contact, periodic check-ins). Assign based on power x interest, not by seniority.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="4-Step Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — Identify: brainstorm using six questions: who uses, pays, approves, builds, supports, and could block this product?</statement>
      <rationale>Silent blockers — those who could block later but are not yet engaged — are the most dangerous category; the six questions force them into view early.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Analyze each stakeholder: what do they want, what do they fear, power level, interest level, and current attitude (supporter/neutral/resistor)?</statement>
      <rationale>Attitude classification determines the engagement tactic; a Resistor with high power needs a 1:1 strategy meeting, not a newsletter.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Plan engagement with explicit cadence, format, content, and named owner for each stakeholder.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague engagement plans ("communicate regularly") decay in one sprint; an explicit cadence ("biweekly 1:1 on Wednesday") survives PM vacation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Execute and adapt: track satisfaction, refresh attitudes monthly for executives (not quarterly), and handle conflicts proactively using the forum appropriate to the power x attitude cell.</statement>
      <rationale>Executive attitudes turn faster than feature-team attitudes; a VP who was Supporter at kickoff can be Neutral by Q2 if metrics dip and no contact was maintained.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="PM-Specific Register Columns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add comms_direction (upward/lateral/downward/external) and decision_rights (Approve/Consult/Inform/None) columns to every stakeholder register.</statement>
      <rationale>Without these columns, every stakeholder appears to have veto power; with them, the PM can confidently say "you are Consult on this, not Approve" — and back it up.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include the management chain (manager, skip-level) as first-class stakeholders.</statement>
      <rationale>PMs who omit skip-levels from the register are blindsided by skip-level reviews; the management chain is not a background stakeholder.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/stakeholder-register.md">Register template with all required columns</reference>
  </section>
</text>
