<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-stakeholder-antipatterns" title="Stakeholder Management Anti-Patterns and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Concrete failure modes PMs face when managing stakeholders, including PM-as-bottleneck, upward-comms inflation, lateral capture, and LLM-specific risks.</summary>

  <section title="Structural Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>PM centralizes all cross-functional communication through themselves (PM as bottleneck).</description>
      <reason>The register should route, not funnel — some engineering-to-sales communication should happen directly with the PM informed, not as a relay. Single-point-of-failure PMs create delays and knowledge silos.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>PM escalates every decision upward, training executives to ignore communications and the team to bypass the PM.</description>
      <reason>Define explicitly what does NOT go upward as deliberately as what does; keep a written "I will decide" column on the decision log.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Lateral capture: a friendly head-of-sales becomes the loudest voice and silently steers the roadmap while appearing as one row among many in the register.</description>
      <reason>Track time spent per stakeholder monthly; if it does not match power x interest, recalibrate. The grid becomes inaccurate when attention diverges from the model.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Same communication format and content sent to all stakeholders regardless of role.</description>
      <reason>Executives need outcomes and risk; engineers need decisions and constraints; customers need benefits and how-to. One message serves none of them well.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Common PM Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring silent stakeholders — not proactively seeking input from those who don't speak up in meetings.</description>
      <reason>Silent stakeholders who were not engaged become the loudest blockers at launch; they had concerns they never voiced because nobody asked.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Only sharing positive updates; hiding challenges until they are crises.</description>
      <reason>Executive trust is built by surfacing bad news early, not by delivering only good news — which trains executives to assume the PM is hiding problems.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No escalation path defined — no explicit process for resolving conflicts within a time limit.</description>
      <reason>Without an escalation path, conflicts fester; an explicit "unresolved in 48h escalates to executive sponsor" creates the pressure needed to resolve things before they block delivery.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent-Specific Gotchas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require the agent to cite a policy document, RACI matrix, or written email when populating decision_rights; lint for unsourced rows.</statement>
      <rationale>Hallucinated decision rights are the most damaging LLM error in stakeholder management — an agent confidently asserting "Head of Legal must approve" when a delegate does causes process delays and legal confusion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Force executive briefs to lead with the worst news in section one, reject drafts that bury risk in section three.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs default to softening bad news for high-power readers; structural rules override sycophancy where stakes are highest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>All escalations must go through humans — never automate an escalation that emails an executive's manager based on sentiment analysis.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-escalation based on inferred executive sentiment is a fireable offense; the consequence is irreversible and the input (tone-scoring) is unreliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/pm-attention-diff.py">Script flagging PM time vs. stakeholder power-x-interest mismatch</reference>
    <reference path="templates/communication-plan.md">Communication matrix and escalation path template</reference>
  </section>
</text>
