<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="stakeholder-management Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for stakeholder-management as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>PM centralizes all cross-functional communication through themselves (PM as bottleneck).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The register should route, not funnel — some engineering-to-sales communication should happen directly with the PM informed, not as a relay. Single-point-of-failure PMs create delays and knowledge silos.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>PM escalates every decision upward, training executives to ignore communications and the team to bypass the PM.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Define explicitly what does NOT go upward as deliberately as what does; keep a written "I will decide" column on the decision log.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Lateral capture: a friendly head-of-sales becomes the loudest voice and silently steers the roadmap while appearing as one row among many in the register.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Track time spent per stakeholder monthly; if it does not match power x interest, recalibrate. The grid becomes inaccurate when attention diverges from the model.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Same communication format and content sent to all stakeholders regardless of role.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Executives need outcomes and risk; engineers need decisions and constraints; customers need benefits and how-to. One message serves none of them well.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring silent stakeholders — not proactively seeking input from those who don't speak up in meetings.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Silent stakeholders who were not engaged become the loudest blockers at launch; they had concerns they never voiced because nobody asked.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Only sharing positive updates; hiding challenges until they are crises.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Executive trust is built by surfacing bad news early, not by delivering only good news — which trains executives to assume the PM is hiding problems.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>No escalation path defined — no explicit process for resolving conflicts within a time limit.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without an escalation path, conflicts fester; an explicit "unresolved in 48h escalates to executive sponsor" creates the pressure needed to resolve things before they block delivery.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Tone-mismatched lateral messages: an LLM-drafted message to sales reads as eng-snobbery; the same draft to eng reads as sales-fluff.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generate per-audience variants from a structured source, never paraphrase a single draft into multiple audiences.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Calendar-scraping privacy: agents mining 1:1 transcripts to update attitude classifications have a high false-positive rate and cross legal lines in some jurisdictions (EU, CA).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Get explicit consent and surface the source quote with every classification change.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Persona-shifting exec proxies: when an exec's chief of staff is the actual decision proxy, an agent that addresses the exec by name in a brief routed through the CoS comes across as oblivious.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Encode the proxy in the register and have the agent address by role, not name.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Multi-agent register drift: if both faion-pm-agent and faion-business-analyst write to the register, conflicting attitude classifications result.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Designate the PM agent as sole writer; BA proposes via a queue file (e.g. .aidocs/product/register-proposals.md) the PM agent reviews.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Long-context token waste: feeding the entire register into every prompt.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Filter by comms_direction or decision_rights for the task at hand. A 200-row register dumped into every brief draft costs more than the briefs save.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Prompt-injection via meeting notes: hostile or careless attendees can paste content into shared notes that the agent ingests.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Treat ingested transcripts as untrusted input; never let the agent take action (send mail, change register) without human confirmation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-team sentiment models are biased: tools that score Slack tone tend to over-flag direct cultures (German, Dutch, Israeli) as "Resistor".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Calibrate or disable; do not let cultural communication style be encoded as attitude.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Promotion-case fabrication: letting an agent draft your promotion narrative directly from the register; LLMs invent decisions you never made.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use the decision log + register to verify, write the narrative yourself.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
