<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-blue-ocean" title="Blue Ocean Four Actions Framework">
  <summary>Four Actions framework for creating uncontested market space, with survivorship-bias warning and example constraints.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Run Four Actions only after a competitor-analysis document exists. Without a baseline of what competitors currently offer, "eliminate" has no meaning.</statement>
    <rationale>Blue Ocean analysis without competitive data produces aspirational fiction. The Strategy Canvas requires actual competitor offerings plotted on the Y-axis before the new curve can be drawn.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Four Actions">
    <list>
      <item>Eliminate: which factors the industry takes for granted should be removed entirely? (typically costly or assumed-required features users rarely value)</item>
      <item>Reduce: which factors should be reduced well below the industry standard? (over-engineered for actual user needs)</item>
      <item>Raise: which factors should be raised above the industry standard? (currently underserved relative to what buyers actually want)</item>
      <item>Create: which factors should be created that the industry has never offered? (generates new demand or new buyer population)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Strategy Canvas">
    <p>Plot the X-axis as key competing factors (price, features, support, onboarding, integrations, etc.) and the Y-axis as level offered (low to high). Plot 3+ real competitors from the competitor-analysis JSON before drawing the new value curve. Require 3 real data points minimum; curves drawn without data are marketing.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Force the Strategy Canvas to plot against at least 3 real competitor data points pulled from competitive-analysis output. LLM-drawn curves default to showing the "winning case" without real competition plotted.</statement>
      <rationale>Survivorship bias: agents produce a strategy canvas that looks like the case study (Cirque, Yellow Tail) without actually plotting competitor offerings. The resulting curve is aspirational, not analytical.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Survivorship Bias Warning">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Citing Cirque du Soleil, Yellow Tail wine, Nintendo Wii, or iTunes as Blue Ocean examples</description>
      <reason>These are the 5-7 textbook cases cited because they succeeded. The failure rate of "create new factor" bets is high and invisible. Require post-2018 examples and reject the canonical textbook cases.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running Blue Ocean analysis on a single niche without a comparison set</description>
      <reason>Blue Ocean is only meaningful when contrasted against a current red ocean; without it you cannot identify what to eliminate or reduce.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/blue-ocean-canvas.md">Blue Ocean Four Actions canvas template</reference>
</text>
