<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-value-proposition" title="Value Proposition Canvas">
  <summary>Customer Profile (jobs/pains/gains) and Value Map (pain relievers/gain creators) with FIT scoring and decay rules.</summary>

  <section title="Customer Profile">
    <list>
      <item>Customer Jobs: functional (tasks to complete), emotional (feelings sought), social (how they want to appear to others)</item>
      <item>Pains: obstacles, frustrations, and risks that block job completion — ranked by intensity</item>
      <item>Gains: desired outcomes and benefits — ranked by relevance (essential, expected, desired, unexpected)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap at most 2 pains above 7/10 per persona. If more than 2 pains exceed 7/10, the agent has inflated the scores.</statement>
      <rationale>Pain inflation makes every problem look existential; it eliminates the prioritization signal that the canvas is supposed to produce.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Bind pains to interview transcript IDs from user-interviews-methods. Uncited pains decay fastest and are the first to be invalidated by market changes.</statement>
      <rationale>VPC pains shift quarterly in early markets; a 6-month-old canvas without transcript anchors is fiction. Citation enables targeted re-validation of specific pain items.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Value Map">
    <list>
      <item>Products and Services: what is offered (feature list, not the benefit)</item>
      <item>Pain Relievers: how each product/service addresses a specific pain — must map 1:1 to pains in the Customer Profile</item>
      <item>Gain Creators: how each product/service enables a specific gain — must map 1:1 to gains in the Customer Profile</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="FIT Assessment">
    <rule>
      <statement>FIT is achieved when Pain Relievers address the top-ranked pains and Gain Creators enable the essential gains. Focus on pains rated 8+ and gains labeled "essential" or "expected" — ignore "nice to have."</statement>
      <rationale>Building against low-intensity pains and desired-but-not-essential gains produces features customers acknowledge but do not pay for.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Canvas Decay Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a valid_until date (90 days from creation) to every VPC. Expire and force regeneration in CI when the date passes.</statement>
      <rationale>VPC pains and gains shift quarterly in early markets. A 6-month-old canvas built on unvalidated assumptions guides product decisions in the wrong direction.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/value-proposition-canvas.md">VPC template with customer profile and value map sections</reference>
</text>
