<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-pricing-models" title="Pricing Model Selection">
  <summary>Six pricing models with selection criteria, Van Westendorp rules, and LLM bias mitigations.</summary>

  <section title="Six Pricing Models">
    <list>
      <item>Freemium: free tier + paid upgrade; best for high-volume, low-marginal-cost products; typical conversion 2-5% system-wide (not "qualified users")</item>
      <item>Subscription: recurring payment for ongoing value; predictable revenue; churn risk requires LTV/CAC above 3:1</item>
      <item>Usage-based: pay for consumption; scales with customer value delivered; revenue unpredictability is the primary risk</item>
      <item>One-time purchase: single payment for perpetual access; simple but no recurring revenue; suits discrete value or impulse buys</item>
      <item>Tiered: different feature levels at different prices; captures more value across segments; requires 3 distinct WTP segments with different jobs-to-be-done to justify</item>
      <item>Per-seat: per-user pricing; clear and predictable; creates resistance to adding users in small teams</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Model Selection Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default-reject "tiered subscription" and force the agent to argue for it. Reject unless 3 distinct WTP segments with different jobs-to-be-done can be named.</statement>
      <rationale>"Tiered subscription" is the default LLM answer for any SaaS regardless of actual economics. Requiring explicit justification defeats this bias and forces evaluation of usage-based and hybrid models that often dominate real economics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For pricing research, never use LLM-simulated willingness-to-pay surveys. Use Van Westendorp with real respondents via a survey tool (Conjointly, Pollfish, Qualtrics).</statement>
      <rationale>LLM-simulated WTP surveys produce regression-to-mean prices ($19/$49/$99) regardless of niche. Synthetic respondents cannot replicate actual buyer psychology or budget constraints.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pricing Research Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: list top 5 competitors' pricing models, tiers, and price ranges (from competitor-analysis output)</item>
      <item>Step 2: calculate value delivered (cost of problem eliminated, time saved in hours per month)</item>
      <item>Step 3: apply Van Westendorp PSM with real respondents — 4 price-sensitivity questions, minimum n=50</item>
      <item>Step 4: test with early users before publishing tiers</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM Bias Mitigations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent recommends "tiered subscription" without naming 3 distinct WTP segments</description>
      <reason>Forces the agent to reason about actual buyer segments and job differences rather than defaulting to the industry template.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>WTP estimates anchored to $19/$49/$99 with no external benchmark</description>
      <reason>Pin to a ProfitWell category report or competitor scrape before letting the agent suggest tiers. Without a benchmark, LLMs regress to round numbers.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/pricing-strategy.md">Pricing strategy document with competitor table and tier definitions</reference>
</text>
