<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Traceability Auto-Maintenance — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that keep the traceability matrix synchronised with the tracker without giving the LLM write authority.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-tracker-source-of-truth" testable="true">
      <statement>The tracker (Jira / Linear / GitHub) is the SOURCE OF TRUTH for ticket existence and titles. The matrix MIRRORS the tracker; never the reverse. If they disagree, the tracker wins and the matrix is reconciled.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO/IEC/IEEE 29148:2018 + Karl Wiegers — Software Requirements">Two competing sources of truth produce two answers. The tracker is where engineers act; the matrix is where the BA reports. Aligning them on tracker-as-source eliminates the drift class.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-weekly-drift-detection" testable="true">
      <statement>Drift detector runs WEEKLY (default Monday 09:00). It compares every matrix link `(req_id → ticket_id)` to current tracker state and classifies into: VALID (ticket exists, title unchanged), RENAMED (exists, title changed), DELETED (ticket gone), MOVED (ticket migrated to new ID).</statement>
      <rationale source="Empirical sprint-cadence research (Atlassian Jira analytics 2023)">Weekly cadence matches sprint rhythm. Daily is noise; monthly accumulates drift past human reconciliation capacity. Monday 09:00 surfaces drift before sprint planning.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-ai-suggester-not-actor" testable="true">
      <statement>LLM proposes REPAIRS as suggestions; it MUST NOT directly write to the matrix. Every repair suggestion lands in a queue + PR awaiting BA approval. Auto-merge is forbidden even for "obvious" repairs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Requirements engineering integrity (INCOSE) / regulated-industry audit trails">Auto-edited requirements artifacts lose audit trail and create compliance exposure (FDA, EASA, SOC-2). BA-in-the-loop is the only legally defensible pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-link-type-discipline" testable="true">
      <statement>Every matrix link MUST declare a `link_type` from a closed list: IMPLEMENTS, VERIFIED-BY, DEPENDS-ON, REFINES, DERIVES-FROM. Repair suggestions preserve the original link_type — LLM may not "fix" by changing the link semantics.</statement>
      <rationale source="ReqIF / IBM DOORS / OSLC RM standards">Untyped links lose the audit story (test coverage vs implementation vs dependency). Repair that changes semantics quietly corrupts compliance reports.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-audit-log" testable="true">
      <statement>Every drift detection AND every repair MUST emit an audit event with: timestamp, matrix path, tracker state hash, repair suggestions, BA approver, approval timestamp. Audit log persists for ≥ 7 years (FDA / EASA standard).</statement>
      <rationale source="21 CFR Part 11 / FDA software validation guidance">Traceability matrices are evidence. Without an audit log of changes, the matrix's value to compliance reviewers collapses. 7 years matches FDA's record-retention rule.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Drift classification examples">

    <example type="good" title="Renamed ticket repair flow">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Matrix row:
  R-042 (Login MFA) → JIRA-2381 ("Implement MFA")
  link_type: IMPLEMENTS

Tracker state (week 14):
  JIRA-2381 → title now "Implement MFA + WebAuthn"

Detector verdict: RENAMED (same ID, title evolved)
Repair suggestion: NONE NEEDED. Log title change in audit.
Note in matrix: "title drift acknowledged 2026-W14".
      ]]></code>
      <note>Renamed is the common, harmless case. Detector logs it; no PR needed.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="good" title="Deleted ticket repair flow">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Matrix row:
  R-067 (Audit export CSV) → JIRA-3104
  link_type: VERIFIED-BY

Tracker state: JIRA-3104 → 404 (deleted by sprint cleanup)

Detector verdict: DELETED
LLM suggestion:
  Search tracker for "audit", "export", "csv" tickets created
  in the last 60 days. Top candidate: JIRA-3210
  ("Compliance report CSV export"), confidence 0.78.

Output: repair-suggestion PR with side-by-side diff.
BA reviews: approves → PR merged → audit event logged.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r3 + r4: LLM suggests, BA approves, link_type unchanged.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Auto-merge repair (r3 violation)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
LLM detects DELETED → finds match with 0.78 confidence → auto-edits
the matrix file. Commits to main without review.

2 sprints later: compliance review. Auditor asks "why does R-067
point to JIRA-3210?". No one knows. Audit log shows no human approval.
Compliance finding raised.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Violates r3. Auto-merge destroys the audit chain.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
