<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="continuous-discovery Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for continuous-discovery. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Allocate 15–20% of team capacity to discovery. Schedule it as recurring calendar blocks; discovery never wins against feature pressure if it is optional.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unscheduled discovery tasks are the first thing dropped under sprint pressure. A fixed calendar slot makes the cost visible and prevents the loop from collapsing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Daily: review the support ticket triage digest and scan analytics for anomalies (&gt;2 sigma from baseline).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Support and analytics are passive behavioral signals that surface pain without requiring user scheduling. Anomaly detection at 2 sigma catches real problems before they accumulate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Weekly: run 1–3 user interviews, synthesize the prior 7 days of feedback into themes against the controlled vocabulary, review competitor changelogs, and draft interview questions for next week.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Weekly interviews compound into 50+ sessions per year — a research corpus no one-time study can match. Weekly competitor review catches market changes before they become strategic surprises.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Biweekly: diff current opportunities against the roadmap, propose adds/removes/re-prioritizations, and have a human decide and record the rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Discovery without a roadmap feedback loop is theater. The biweekly diff is where evidence becomes decisions. Every roadmap change must cite at least one opportunity from the discovery repo.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly: re-baseline the theme vocabulary and audit interview sample for segment bias (who have you not talked to in 90 days?).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Theme vocabulary drift across weeks destroys longitudinal trends. Sample bias audits prevent a discovery process that only hears from engaged power users while passive and at-risk segments go unrepresented.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Schedule daily/weekly tasks via cron, n8n, or a scheduled trigger. Missed weeks erode the loop — automate or it dies.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Human-remembered cadences slip to "when there's time." The discovery loop requires the same infrastructure discipline as any other automated pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain a versioned controlled vocabulary of theme IDs (e.g., T-onboarding-friction). New themes require explicit human approval before being used in synthesis output.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Theme renaming across weeks destroys longitudinal trends. A new theme named "onboarding issues" this week and "activation friction" next week looks like two problems when it is one. Treat vocabulary changes as schema migrations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require evidence_count &gt;= 3 before promoting a signal to a named theme. Themes with fewer than 3 signals are noise, not pattern.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs hallucinate themes from single data points. The minimum evidence threshold prevents one angry user from becoming a roadmap priority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always store verbatim quotes alongside synthesized themes. The summary is a navigation aid; the verbatim is the audit trail.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLM-summarized interviews lose tone, sarcasm, and nuance. When a roadmap decision is challenged, the verbatim — not the summary — is what grounds the argument.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Redact PII before passing interview transcripts or support tickets to any LLM. Use a pre-pass regex or scrubber agent.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Customer names, emails, and identifiers in LLM input create compliance risk and degrade the generalizability of synthesis output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every roadmap change must cite at least one opportunity ID from the discovery repository. Changes without citation are opinion-driven, not evidence-driven.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The citation requirement creates accountability and makes the reasoning auditable when priorities shift in the next cycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Triangulate: use at least two signal types — behavioral (analytics), attitudinal (interviews), and market (competitor monitoring). One source alone misleads.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Analytics shows what users do but not why. Interviews show why but are subject to social desirability bias. Competitor monitoring shows what the market is converging on. None is sufficient alone.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
