<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-cadence" title="Continuous Discovery Cadence">
  <summary>Four-frequency discovery cadence — daily, weekly, biweekly, quarterly — with concrete activities, a capacity allocation rule, and automation requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Capacity Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Allocate 15–20% of team capacity to discovery. Schedule it as recurring calendar blocks; discovery never wins against feature pressure if it is optional.</statement>
      <rationale>Unscheduled discovery tasks are the first thing dropped under sprint pressure. A fixed calendar slot makes the cost visible and prevents the loop from collapsing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Daily Activities">
    <rule>
      <statement>Daily: review the support ticket triage digest and scan analytics for anomalies (&gt;2 sigma from baseline).</statement>
      <rationale>Support and analytics are passive behavioral signals that surface pain without requiring user scheduling. Anomaly detection at 2 sigma catches real problems before they accumulate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Weekly Activities">
    <rule>
      <statement>Weekly: run 1–3 user interviews, synthesize the prior 7 days of feedback into themes against the controlled vocabulary, review competitor changelogs, and draft interview questions for next week.</statement>
      <rationale>Weekly interviews compound into 50+ sessions per year — a research corpus no one-time study can match. Weekly competitor review catches market changes before they become strategic surprises.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Biweekly Activities">
    <rule>
      <statement>Biweekly: diff current opportunities against the roadmap, propose adds/removes/re-prioritizations, and have a human decide and record the rationale.</statement>
      <rationale>Discovery without a roadmap feedback loop is theater. The biweekly diff is where evidence becomes decisions. Every roadmap change must cite at least one opportunity from the discovery repo.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Quarterly Activities">
    <rule>
      <statement>Quarterly: re-baseline the theme vocabulary and audit interview sample for segment bias (who have you not talked to in 90 days?).</statement>
      <rationale>Theme vocabulary drift across weeks destroys longitudinal trends. Sample bias audits prevent a discovery process that only hears from engaged power users while passive and at-risk segments go unrepresented.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Automation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Schedule daily/weekly tasks via cron, n8n, or a scheduled trigger. Missed weeks erode the loop — automate or it dies.</statement>
      <rationale>Human-remembered cadences slip to "when there's time." The discovery loop requires the same infrastructure discipline as any other automated pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/discovery-cadence.py">Script that emits this week's discovery checklist as JSON</reference>
</text>
