<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-synthesis" title="Discovery Synthesis Rules">
  <summary>Rules for clustering feedback into stable opportunity themes, maintaining a controlled vocabulary, storing verbatim evidence, and linking themes to roadmap initiatives.</summary>

  <section title="Controlled Vocabulary">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain a versioned controlled vocabulary of theme IDs (e.g., T-onboarding-friction). New themes require explicit human approval before being used in synthesis output.</statement>
      <rationale>Theme renaming across weeks destroys longitudinal trends. A new theme named "onboarding issues" this week and "activation friction" next week looks like two problems when it is one. Treat vocabulary changes as schema migrations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require evidence_count &gt;= 3 before promoting a signal to a named theme. Themes with fewer than 3 signals are noise, not pattern.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs hallucinate themes from single data points. The minimum evidence threshold prevents one angry user from becoming a roadmap priority.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Verbatim Storage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always store verbatim quotes alongside synthesized themes. The summary is a navigation aid; the verbatim is the audit trail.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM-summarized interviews lose tone, sarcasm, and nuance. When a roadmap decision is challenged, the verbatim — not the summary — is what grounds the argument.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Redact PII before passing interview transcripts or support tickets to any LLM. Use a pre-pass regex or scrubber agent.</statement>
      <rationale>Customer names, emails, and identifiers in LLM input create compliance risk and degrade the generalizability of synthesis output.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Roadmap Linkage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every roadmap change must cite at least one opportunity ID from the discovery repository. Changes without citation are opinion-driven, not evidence-driven.</statement>
      <rationale>The citation requirement creates accountability and makes the reasoning auditable when priorities shift in the next cycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Triangulate: use at least two signal types — behavioral (analytics), attitudinal (interviews), and market (competitor monitoring). One source alone misleads.</statement>
      <rationale>Analytics shows what users do but not why. Interviews show why but are subject to social desirability bias. Competitor monitoring shows what the market is converging on. None is sufficient alone.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/weekly-synthesis.json">JSON schema for weekly synthesis agent output</reference>
</text>
