<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="continuous-discovery Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for continuous-discovery as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Discovery runs every week but roadmap decisions never change in response to findings.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Discovery without a feedback loop into the roadmap is ceremony. If the biweekly diff never produces a proposed change, either the discovery is not surfacing real signals or the roadmap is being protected from evidence.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Weekly interviews recruit only engaged, active users.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Active users are not representative of the full user base. Passive users and at-risk churners have different problems. Run a quarterly sample-bias audit and rotate recruitment criteria to include users with low recent activity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Theme vocabulary grows without governance — new theme names appear each week for the same underlying problem.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Renaming destroys longitudinal analysis. You cannot track whether "activation friction" is improving if it was called "onboarding issues" last month. Lock the vocabulary and require approval for changes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM synthesis is the only artifact — raw transcripts and verbatim quotes are discarded.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Summaries lose tone, nuance, and edge cases. When a decision is challenged, "the LLM said users want X" is not defensible. The verbatim is the source of truth; the summary is a navigation aid.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Discovery cadence is calendar-optional and skips when a sprint is busy.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Discovery always loses to feature pressure if it is optional. Schedule it as non-negotiable recurring blocks and automate the data ingestion steps so the weekly review cannot be skipped without explicit team decision.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
