<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="jenkins-pipeline-patterns Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for jenkins-pipeline-patterns. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pipelines MUST use Declarative syntax as the default structure. Scripted blocks MUST only appear inside script { ... } sections when Declarative cannot express the required logic; such blocks MUST include a code comment explaining why scripted is required. Linters MUST reject pipelines with top-level scripted blocks (outside stage declarations). The declarative when-expression can express most conditional logic: when { branch 'main' }, when { expression { env.BUILD_NUMBER.toInteger() % 2 == 0 } }, when { changeset 'src/**/*.groovy' }.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Declarative enforces team readability and enables pre-merge syntax validation via jenkins-cli declarative-linter. Scripted blocks are opaque to linters, introduce CPS serialization risks, and require agents to test locally before submission. Top-level scripted pipelines hide the entire pipeline structure from governance tooling and Blue Ocean visualization. Declarative when-expressions cover 95% of conditional needs without resorting to scripted blocks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shared libraries MUST be stored in a dedicated Git repository separate from application code. All classes MUST implement java.io.Serializable. Functions MUST be placed in vars/ directory with one verb per function (e.g., buildApp, deployToK8s, notifySlack). The library MUST be version-pinned in @Library annotations (e.g., @Library('platform@v1.4.2') _). Never use floating @main in production pipelines. Library configuration MUST be set in Manage Jenkins &gt; Configure System, with implicit loading disabled (require explicit @Library annotation).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dedicated repos enable independent versioning, testing, and rollback. A library change can be tested in isolation before propagating to all pipelines. Serialization rules prevent opaque NotSerializableException at CPS checkpoints (random failures after hours of build work). Version pinning prevents non-deterministic builds caused by upstream library changes — floating @main picks the latest commit every build, causing subtle behavior changes. Implicit loading disabled ensures visibility: developers see exactly which library version their pipeline uses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shared library directory structure MUST follow: `vars/` (global functions), `src/` (Groovy classes), `resources/` (templates), `test/` (unit tests). Classes in `src/` MUST NOT override built-in Jenkins Pipeline steps. Libraries MUST have a README with usage examples.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Standard structure enables consistent discovery and testing. Overriding built-in steps silently breaks when Jenkins LTS upgrades plugin versions. Testing discipline catches serialization issues early.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Parallel stages MUST be used for cross-platform builds (Linux, Windows, macOS), multi-environment testing (Chrome, Firefox, Safari), and independent tasks (lint, test, scan). Each parallel branch MUST have a clear name. Resource limits MUST be set via agent labels or Kubernetes pod templates to prevent executor starvation. Shared resources (databases, credentials, files) MUST be protected via lock(resource: '...') or dir() to prevent race conditions. Parallel branches MUST NOT share the same workspace by default; use dir(unique_subdir) or ws() to isolate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Parallelism reduces overall pipeline duration significantly (parallel test stages execute wall-clock time faster). Resource limits prevent the common failure where one team's build exhausts all executors and blocks other teams (executor starvation). Explicit naming and locking prevents silent failures from workspace corruption: unit tests writing to target/ and integration tests reading simultaneously cause flaky failures that are hard to reproduce. Jenkins shares workspace by default across parallel branches, requiring explicit isolation via dir(EXECUTOR_NUMBER) or separate ws() blocks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All pipelines MUST declare options { timeout(...) buildDiscarder(...) } to prevent stuck builds and unbounded log retention. Production pipelines MUST have disableConcurrentBuilds() or use lock(resource: 'shared-resource') for pipelines that touch shared state. Timestamps and colored output (ansiColor) MUST be enabled for readability. Stage-level timeouts MAY override global timeout for long-running stages (e.g., integration tests).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A single stuck build can starve the queue for hours, blocking all team members. Unbounded log retention fills disk in weeks and slows Jenkins UI. timeout prevents hung steps (network timeouts, hung processes); buildDiscarder limits history (typically 50 builds, 10 artifacts); disableConcurrentBuilds prevents race conditions on deploy pipelines that modify shared resources. Timestamps enable performance analysis (which stages are slow); colored output makes human log review 10x faster.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Kubernetes agent declarations MUST use the kubernetes {} agent block with an inline pod template. The pod template MUST specify resource requests and limits (CPU, memory). Multiple containers MUST be defined only if parallel tasks use distinct tools (e.g., one Node container, one Docker container). Service accounts MUST be restricted to minimal permissions. Pod templates SHOULD use labels for organization and filtering.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Pod templates enable auto-scaling and per-pipeline resource isolation. Limits prevent memory leaks in one pipeline from crashing the entire cluster. Minimal service accounts follow least-privilege security. Labels enable scheduler affinity rules and cost center tagging.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No credentials MUST be hardcoded in Jenkinsfile or shared libraries. All secrets MUST be stored in Jenkins Credentials store and bound via withCredentials step. Secrets MUST NOT be passed as command-line arguments (use environment variables or stdin, which are masked). Bash set -x MUST be banned inside withCredentials blocks; linters MUST reject this pattern. Log rotation MUST limit history retention to prevent long-term secret exposure via build logs. Credentials binding MUST use usernamePassword, sshUserPrivateKey, or file types (never raw strings).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">withCredentials masks values in logs by doing name-based replacement (PASS variable name becomes ****), but set -x evaluates environment variables before masking happens in output. Jenkins Credentials store uses encrypted storage at rest (using the Jenkins instance key), RBAC for access control, and audit logs for credential reads. Retention limits prevent archived logs from becoming a long-term attack surface. Specific credential types (usernamePassword, sshUserPrivateKey) enable masking of multiple fields and prevent accidental exposure of partial secrets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All pipelines MUST have a post { always { cleanWs() } } block to clean workspace after every build. Production pipelines MUST have post sections for success (deploy notification), failure (alert on-call), and always (metrics). Timeout MUST be set for long-running stages (e.g., integration tests). Flaky operations (e.g., API calls) MUST use retry(3) { ... } for idempotent retries. Post sections support multiple conditions: success (build passed, artifacts published), failure (build failed, alert sent), unstable (tests failed but compiled), aborted (cancelled by user), cleanup (always runs, cleanup operations).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Workspace cleanup prevents disk exhaustion from hundreds of accumulated builds. Post sections ensure stakeholders are informed of outcomes and enable automation (deploy on success, rollback on failure, alert on-call, publish metrics). Retries reduce false failures from transient network issues and external service unavailability. The cleanup step must run regardless of pipeline outcome, preventing zombie workspace processes and disk fragmentation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agents authoring Jenkinsfiles MUST validate syntax using jenkins-cli declarative-linter before submission (piping Jenkinsfile to stdin). Agents MUST NOT run live builds for validation; use jenkinsfile-runner locally if needed. Agents MUST NOT modify plugins.txt or trigger plugin installs on shared controllers. Agents MUST scan generated Jenkinsfiles for hardcoded credentials using a password-scrubber (grep for patterns, check withCredentials wrapping).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Linting catches structural errors before submission. Live build validation burns executor time and pollutes build history with generated builds. Plugin installs are global state mutations that affect all users. Credential scrubbing prevents accidental secret commits.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any Groovy object that holds a reference to a non-serializable type (Pattern, Matcher, JsonSlurperResult, custom objects) MUST be wrapped in a @NonCPS def helper() { ... } method that returns only primitives or lists. Methods without @NonCPS MUST only operate on Serializable types. Closures capturing non-serializable objects MUST be avoided entirely. The @NonCPS wrapper should be idempotent (call it twice, get the same result) because durability restore will not include its state.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">CPS transformation makes durability possible but introduces hidden serialization requirements. Errors only surface at runtime after hours of build work. @NonCPS methods run in-process without CPS wrapping, but restore-after-crash won't include their state — design them to be idempotent helpers that return values, not side-effect containers. Agents authoring shared libraries must be trained to recognize this pattern and apply it immediately when Pattern or custom objects appear.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
