<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Jenkins Pipeline Patterns Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules for production-grade Jenkins pipeline patterns. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="declarative-with-script-escape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pipelines MUST use Declarative syntax at the top level. Scripted blocks are allowed ONLY inside `script { }` sections with a code comment explaining why Declarative cannot express the logic. Top-level scripted pipelines are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Jenkins docs — Pipeline syntax">Declarative enforces team readability and enables pre-merge validation via `declarative-linter`. Scripted blocks are opaque to linters, introduce CPS serialization risks, and hide structure from Blue Ocean.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="shared-lib-dedicated-repo" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shared libraries MUST live in a dedicated Git repository separate from application code. Layout: `vars/` (global functions), `src/` (Groovy classes), `resources/` (templates), `test/` (unit tests). All classes MUST implement `java.io.Serializable`. Vars functions MUST NOT override built-in Pipeline steps.</statement>
      <rationale source="Jenkins Shared Libraries docs">Dedicated repos enable independent versioning, testing, and rollback. Serializable + the standard layout prevents `NotSerializableException` at CPS checkpoints — the single biggest opaque failure mode in long-running Jenkins builds.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="library-version-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every `@Library` reference MUST use a pinned tag (`@Library('platform@v1.4.2') _`). Floating `@main` / `@master` refs are forbidden in production pipelines. Implicit library loading MUST be disabled in `Manage Jenkins → Configure System`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Jenkins Shared Libraries docs">Floating refs pick the latest commit every build, causing non-deterministic builds. A library bug propagates instantly to all 50+ pipelines with no rollback path. Pinning + explicit imports make the dependency graph auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="parallel-workspace-isolation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Parallel branches MUST NOT share the default workspace. Use `dir("branch-${env.STAGE_NAME}")` or distinct `ws()` blocks per branch. Shared resources (DB, credentials, files) MUST be wrapped in `lock(resource: '...')`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Jenkins Pipeline parallel docs">Jenkins shares workspace across parallel branches by default. Concurrent writes to `target/` or `dist/` cause flaky races that only reproduce under load. `lock()` serialises access to shared external state.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="pod-resources-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every `agent { kubernetes { yaml ... } }` container MUST declare both `resources.requests` (CPU + memory) and `resources.limits` (CPU + memory). Privileged containers (docker:dind) MUST be opt-in via explicit `securityContext.privileged: true`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Jenkins Kubernetes plugin docs + K8s scheduling docs">Without requests, the scheduler cannot place pods deterministically. Without limits, a runaway build starves the cluster. Privileged-by-default is a security violation; opt-in keeps the blast radius small.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="options-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every pipeline MUST declare `options { timeout(time: 30, unit: 'MINUTES'); buildDiscarder(logRotator(numToKeepStr: '50', artifactNumToKeepStr: '10')); disableConcurrentBuilds(); timestamps(); ansiColor('xterm') }` (or stricter project values). Deploy pipelines touching shared state MUST also use `lock()`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Jenkins Pipeline best practices">Stuck builds without timeout starve the executor queue for hours. Unbounded log retention fills the controller disk. timestamps + ansiColor cut log review time by ~10x.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
