<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Workflow Spec Phase Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every workflow-spec-phase application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-fr-testable-and-numbered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every functional requirement MUST be numbered FR-N and phrased so that satisfaction is testable from the user's perspective (use SHALL or MUST in the requirement body). Requirements that begin with "The system should be nice" or "It would be great if" are forbidden — they cannot be verified.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO/IEC/IEEE 29148:2018, requirements-engineering research">Testable, numbered requirements are the audit chain that runs from spec to design to task to test. Soft language breaks the chain.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-scope-explicit-out" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The spec MUST include an "Out of Scope" section listing at least 2 things the feature explicitly does NOT do. Scope discipline costs nothing at spec time and saves substantial review time downstream. Empty Out-of-Scope sections are a smell — implicit scope leaks.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD scope-leak research, Wiegers 'Software Requirements'">Out-of-scope statements are the cheapest defense against scope creep. The author who can't name 2 out-of-scope items has not bounded the feature yet.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-success-criteria-measurable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Success Criteria MUST be measurable signals (numbers, percentages, observable outcomes) — not adjectives. "Users find it useful" is forbidden; "≥80% of users complete the refresh flow in &lt;2s" is required.</statement>
      <rationale source="OKR / SMART-goal research, A/B-testing literature">Measurable success criteria let the team decide post-ship whether the feature shipped or merely deployed. Adjective-only criteria produce post-hoc rationalization.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-glossary-for-domain-terms" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the spec uses ≥3 domain-specific terms (e.g., "tenant", "credit", "refresh token", "watershed"), a Glossary section MUST define each term in one sentence. Undefined terms create cross-team interpretation drift.</statement>
      <rationale source="DDD ubiquitous-language research">Shared vocabulary is the first deliverable of any feature spec. Skipping the glossary costs 10x the time at review.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-accepted-gate-by-human" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Promotion of spec.md from `status: Draft` to `status: Accepted` MUST be done by a named human owner — never by the subagent. The subagent MUST emit the spec with `status: Draft` and surface a "ready for owner review" flag.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD human-in-loop research, accountability literature">Auto-Accepted specs decouple commitment from authorship. The human checkpoint is the contract that says "I'll defend this scope in design and execution."</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-00 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
