<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-activation-definition" title="Defining the Activation Event">
  <summary>What activation is, why it matters above other growth levers, and a four-step process to find the correct activation event.</summary>

  <section title="What Activation Is">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define activation as the specific action that most strongly correlates with D30 retention — not setup completion, not first login, not profile creation.</statement>
      <rationale>Setup actions (profile creation, email verification) are necessary but not sufficient for value delivery. The activation event must mark the moment the user experienced the core value proposition. Only retention correlation validates this.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Activation is the moment when a new user first experiences the product's core value — the "Aha moment." Flow: signup → onboarding (setup done) → activation (first real value received) → engagement → conversion.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Why Activation Matters">
    <p>The multiplier effect: with 20% activation rate, 100 sign-ups produce 4 retained D30 users and 1 converted customer (1% signup-to-paid). With 60% activation rate, the same 100 sign-ups produce 18 retained D30 users and 5 converted customers (5% signup-to-paid). Same acquisition cost, 5x revenue. Activation improvement compounds through every downstream funnel stage.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Four-Step Process to Find Activation Event">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a four-step retention correlation process: list candidate actions, measure D30 retention for users who did each action versus those who did not, rank by retention lift, and validate that the top action is achievable in the first session.</statement>
      <rationale>Without empirical correlation testing, teams optimize for the most visible user action rather than the most predictive one. The correlation test eliminates guesswork and frequently reveals surprising results (e.g., "invited team member" predicting retention better than "completed a task").</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Activation Events by Product Type">
    <p>Good vs bad activation definitions by product type: SaaS tool — "completed core workflow" (good) vs "used features" (bad); marketplace — "made first transaction" vs "browsed listings"; social — "connected with a friend" vs "created profile"; e-commerce — "made first purchase" vs "added to cart"; mobile game — "completed level 3" vs "downloaded app".</p>
  </section>
</text>
