<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Activation Optimization Examples">
  <summary>Four real product activation journeys: Slack, Dropbox, Duolingo, Canva — metric, optimization steps, and results.</summary>

  <section title="Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Slack. Activation metric: sent first message in team channel. Optimization journey V1 to V5: V1 35% (basic signup) → V2 45% (team creation prompt) → V3 55% (pre-filled #general channel) → V4 65% (suggested first message) → V5 75% (Slackbot tutorial). Key insight: each 10pp gain came from reducing the friction between account creation and the first social action.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Dropbox. Activation metric: uploaded first file. Key optimizations: desktop app prompt (+20%), showing sync folder after install (+15%), drag-and-drop tutorial (+10%), gamified checklist (+25%). The gamified checklist — install desktop app, upload first file, install mobile, share a folder, invite a friend — produced the largest single activation lift.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Duolingo. Activation metric: completed first lesson. TTV: under 2 minutes. Key insight: first lesson delivered before account creation — signup happened after value was already experienced. Result: 90%+ Day 0 activation rate. Gamification (XP, streak, progress bar) reinforced the value signal immediately.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Canva. Activation metric: created and downloaded first design. Key optimizations: templates first (+40%), social media size presets (+15%), one-click download (+10%), suggested search (+20%). Empty state → template gallery transformation was the single highest-impact change — it eliminated the blank-canvas paralysis that blocked activation.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Pattern Across Examples">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reduce the number of decisions a new user must make before the first value moment; every choice is a potential exit point.</statement>
      <rationale>Each of the four examples above reduced friction by providing a pre-made starting point (suggested message, template, pre-filled channel) rather than asking users to create from scratch. The activation event happened sooner because the path to it was shorter.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/activation-funnel-analysis.md">Activation funnel analysis template for tracking optimization experiments</reference>
</text>
