<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Definition of Done Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Definition of Done Template application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-per-artefact-type" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DoD MUST be defined per artefact type (story, spike, bugfix, refactor, infra change). A single global DoD is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Each artefact type has different ship criteria (a spike is done when the question is answered, not when tests are green); a global DoD over-includes or under-includes for half the work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-binary-gates" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every DoD item MUST be a binary yes/no check with an observable artefact (commit SHA, test run id, doc URL). Subjective items ('code is clean') are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Subjective items collapse to whichever reviewer is in the room; binary + observable items are auditable and consistent.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-named-signoff" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every DoD record MUST carry a named human signoff per gate (tests-by, docs-by, runbook-by, PM-by). 'Team' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Diffused accountability means none; named signoff anchors the DoD to a person who can be asked later.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-telemetry-included" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DoD for any user-facing or business-logic change MUST include 'telemetry added' or an explicit 'no telemetry needed because X' rationale. Skipping the gate is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Without explicit telemetry handling, post-ship blindness compounds; the explicit gate forces a deliberate decision either way.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-records-survive" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every shipped artefact MUST emit a DoD record stored alongside the PR or ticket and findable by SHA. Un-recorded DoD is rejected at the release gate.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Verbal or chat-only DoD is unverifiable in audits and retros; the persistent record is the only artefact that survives memory.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
