<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Micro-Agency P&amp;L Tracker Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five hard rules for a micro-agency P&amp;L tracker that makes the agency's levers visible weekly.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-three-revenue-lines" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Revenue is split into 3 lines: (a) Project (one-shot deliverable), (b) Retainer (recurring monthly fee), (c) Productized (fixed-scope offering with productized pricing). One-off training, workshops, or other &lt; 5% of revenue go into a "Misc" line. Don't lump everything into "client revenue".</statement>
      <rationale source="Profit First (Michalowicz, 2017); BTAR agency financial frameworks">Different revenue lines have different gross margins, cash-flow shapes, and capacity demands. Project work is lumpy + high gross margin but front-loaded effort. Retainer is smooth + lower margin but compounding. Productized is high-margin but requires marketing investment. Mixing them hides which line is dragging the agency down.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-weekly-utilization-snapshot" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Friday compute per-person billable utilization (billable_hours / available_hours). Target ranges: contractors 70-85%, employees 60-75%, founder 30-50% (founder time also goes to sales + ops). Out-of-range triggers conversation, not panic.</statement>
      <rationale source="agency utilization research - Forecast 2024; Karpenko-Saskatoon ratios">Utilization is the leading indicator for revenue: low this week = lower invoices next month. The ranges differ by role: founder at 80% means no time for new business; contractor at 50% means margin loss. Weekly cadence catches drift; monthly is too late.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-retainer-concentration-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No single client &gt; 30% of monthly revenue; top-3 clients &lt; 60%. Crossing either threshold triggers a "concentration risk" alert and a documented mitigation plan: net-new client acquisition, scope-down of dominant client, or productized offering launch.</statement>
      <rationale source="agency benchmark research (HubSpot Agency Report 2024); financial risk concentration heuristics">Above 30% single-client share, that client effectively owns the agency's runway. One bad quarter from them = layoffs. 30/60 is the canonical micro-agency safety threshold. Above 60% top-3, the agency is a high-leverage prop trade rather than a business.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-contractor-margin-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every contractor's role has a target margin: (client_billable - contractor_cost) / client_billable ≥ 35%. Below 35% means agency is a pass-through with overhead. Below 25% means agency is losing money on every hour. Track per-role monthly.</statement>
      <rationale source="agency P&amp;L benchmarks; Profit First markup theory">35% is the agency's overhead + risk premium + profit. Below that the agency isn't earning its existence. Contractors who command client rates close to their own rates should be hired directly or replaced. Margin floor enforcement is the difference between a profitable agency and a glorified staffing firm.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-monthly-close-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>By the 7th of every month, the previous month is "closed": all invoices issued, all expenses categorized, P&amp;L view updated, dashboard refreshed. Past 7th = financial decisions are made on stale data, which is the #1 source of cash-flow surprises.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mike Michalowicz Profit First operational discipline; bookkeeping industry standards">Without a fixed close date, the month slips perpetually and the founder loses real-time signal. The 7th aligns with most accounting software's auto-reconciliation cycle. The monthly close is a habit, not a workflow.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Weekly Friday snapshot">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Week of 2026-05-19 — Snapshot

REVENUE (recognized, not invoiced):
  Project line:    $12,400 (3 active projects)
  Retainer line:   $28,000 (8 retainers @ avg $3,500)
  Productized:     $3,200  (12 audits @ $267)
  Misc:            $0
  Total:           $43,600

UTILIZATION (week):
  You (founder):   42% billable, 35% sales, 23% ops ✓
  Maria (FT dev):  72% billable ✓
  Tom (contractor): 81% billable ✓
  Pat (contractor): 48% billable ⚠ (below floor — book or release)

CONCENTRATION:
  Top-1 (Acme):    24% — below threshold ✓
  Top-3:           54% — below threshold ✓

CONTRACTOR MARGIN (monthly avg):
  Designer role:   42% ✓
  Backend role:    37% ✓
  Mobile role:     28% ⚠ (re-price or substitute)

RUNWAY: 4.3 months at current burn
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1, r2, r3, r4 in one Friday view.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Everything-in-one-line obfuscation">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Client revenue this month: $43,600. We're good."

Hides: 8 retainers + 3 projects + 12 productized are very different exposures.
Hides: 70% of revenue may come from one client.
Hides: Mobile contractor role losing money.
Repair: enforce 3-revenue-line split + concentration alerts.
      ]]></code>
      <note>The "client revenue" single-line view is the canonical opacity pattern.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
