<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="mTLS Service-to-Service Deployment Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the cicd-mtls-deployment methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced by the decision tree.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="internal-ca-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>mTLS MUST use an internal CA (step-ca, Vault PKI, service-mesh issuer) for service identities; public CAs (Let's Encrypt) MUST NOT be used for service-to-service auth.</statement>
      <rationale source="step-ca docs, Vault PKI docs">Public CAs issue identities trusted by the world; internal CAs restrict the trust domain to your services.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="short-lived-certs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per-pod / per-service certs MUST have lifetime ≤ 24h; long-lived client certs (&gt;30 days) are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="SPIFFE/SPIRE design, step-ca docs">Long-lived certs amplify revocation blast radius; short-lived certs auto-expire on compromise.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="no-shared-cert" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each workload identity MUST have its own cert; sharing one client cert across N services is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="SPIFFE Workload Identity spec">Shared certs make impersonation undetectable and rotation impossible without coordinated downtime.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="verify-client-cert-at-edge" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>nginx / envoy MUST be configured with `ssl_verify_client on` (or envoy equivalent) and require a non-empty `$ssl_client_s_dn` to forward requests.</statement>
      <rationale source="nginx ssl_verify_client docs">Without `ssl_verify_client on`, mTLS terminates without enforcement and any client cert is accepted.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="crl-or-ocsp-stapling" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Either CRL distribution point OR OCSP stapling MUST be configured to revoke compromised certs before they expire naturally.</statement>
      <rationale source="RFC 5280, RFC 6066">Without revocation, a stolen private key remains valid until the (short) cert expires; CRL/OCSP shrinks the exposure window.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If application-layer auth (OIDC/JWT-PoP) already provides cryptographic service-to-service auth equivalent to mTLS, this methodology MUST be skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="OAuth2 DPoP RFC">Layering mTLS on top of equivalent app-layer auth duplicates infra without security gain.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
