<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-5stage-cycle" title="5-Stage BPA Cycle Rules">
  <summary>Evidence citation, VA/BN/NVA rubric, future-state diff table, and metrics-source requirements for each BPA stage.</summary>

  <section title="Stage 2: Document Current State">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every row in the Process Steps table must cite a source span (file + line, ticket ID, or transcript timestamp). Rows with no citation are marked "unverified" and blocked from analysis.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs smooth over messy interviews into tidy linear diagrams; workarounds (the actual value) get edited out. Source citations make every step falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Emit a Contradictions section listing any step mentioned differently by two or more sources, verbatim. Do not smooth over contradictions — they are the most valuable signal.</statement>
      <rationale>Contradictions between sources reveal workarounds, tribal knowledge, and undocumented exceptions. Smoothing them produces a map of the ideal process, not the actual one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every step must have an actor column. Steps with a blank actor are rejected by the documentation agent. Single-pool diagrams that lose handoffs between actors are also rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Handoffs between actors are where delays, errors, and miscommunication occur. Losing actor attribution makes the process map unanalyzable for bottleneck detection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run password-scrubber-agent on all raw evidence (SOP docs, Slack exports, ticket histories) before feeding to any other agent. SOPs and tickets routinely contain credentials, customer data, and internal URLs.</statement>
      <rationale>PII and credentials in raw evidence files get embedded in process documentation and spread to wider audiences. Scrubbing at ingestion prevents a class of security incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/process-documentation.md">Current-state doc template with citation column in process steps table.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 3: Analyze">
    <rule>
      <statement>VA/BN/NVA rubric: VA = customer would pay for this step; BN = required by law/policy/system but no customer value; NVA = waiting, rework, transport, duplicate data entry. Pin 3 examples per category in the prompt to prevent drift between runs.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a fixed rubric, VA/BN/NVA labels swing with prompt wording. Two runs on the same step list disagree in 20-30% of rows. Pinned examples anchor classification.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For cycle time and error rate: use only numbers cited in the source documents. If absent, write "Data not available". Never estimate. Never fill table cells with confidence-qualified guesses.</statement>
      <rationale>Hallucinated metrics are worse than missing metrics because they anchor decisions to fabricated baselines. "Data not available" triggers a data-collection action; a guess does not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Rank improvement opportunities by NVA-minutes × frequency (not by NVA-minutes alone). End the analysis with a Top-3 candidates for elimination block ordered by this composite score.</statement>
      <rationale>A 10-minute NVA step that runs 1000 times a day beats a 2-hour NVA step that runs once per quarter. Frequency-weighting changes the prioritization in real workflows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/process-analysis.md">Analysis template with value classification table, pain points, bottlenecks, and improvement opportunities ranked by NVA×frequency.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 4: Design Future State">
    <rule>
      <statement>Express future-state changes as a diff table, not prose: columns are step, current actor, future actor, current system, future system, change type (eliminate/automate/simplify/integrate/parallelize), and risk. Prose descriptions are not actionable and cannot be assigned to an engineer.</statement>
      <rationale>Future-state prose produces "auto-approve orders under $1000" without specifying which system changes or which engineer owns it. The diff table forces specificity on every axis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap improvement proposals at 5, ranked by effort/benefit scores. More than 5 proposals without prioritization is a shopping list, not a recommendation.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs default to "automate" for everything. A 30-improvement list without ranking forces the BA to prioritize what the agent should have prioritized. Eliminate/simplify (cheaper wins) get under-recommended.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 5: Validate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 5 requires human-in-the-loop sign-off from the process owner. The agent prepares a review packet (current-state doc, analysis, future-state diff); a human approves or sends back. Never auto-advance past stage 4 in headless mode.</statement>
      <rationale>Future-state process changes affect real people and systems. Auto-advancing without sign-off produces redesigns that do not account for political, contractual, or operational constraints the agent cannot discover from documents.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
