<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Business Process Analysis Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every business-process-analysis cycle enforces.</summary>
  <section title="The five rules">
    <rule id="r1-source-citation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every documented step cites its source: file path + line / ticket id / transcript timestamp. Steps without source are removed from the model.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK §10.34 Process Modelling">Uncited steps are folklore. Source citation forces evidence over assumption.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-named-lane-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every swimlane labels a NAMED owner (full name + role), not a group ("Ops Team"). Lanes without a named owner block the cycle.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK §10.43 Stakeholder List">Anonymous lanes hide accountability gaps and produce vague requirements downstream.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-value-time-cost-table" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The analysis stage produces a table with columns: step, value-add (Y/N), cycle-time-minutes, cost-usd. Skipping any column fails the stage.</statement>
      <rationale source="Lean / Womack &amp; Jones, Lean Thinking (1996)">Without quantification, redesign decisions reduce to opinion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-future-state-as-diff" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Future state is expressed as a diff table (step, action ∈ {keep, cut, change, add}, expected-delta) — not prose. Each row references the current-state step id.</statement>
      <rationale source="diff-driven specs / Schick, BPMN 2.0 Handbook">Prose future-state hides which current steps survive. A diff is auditable and machine-readable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-stakeholder-signoff" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each lane owner signs off in writing (PR comment, email, Slack ack with timestamp) on both current and future state before report ships.</statement>
      <rationale source="change-management / Kotter, Leading Change (1996)">Unvalidated future-states get rejected at rollout. Written sign-off catches divergence early and protects the BA against scope-creep allegations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Diff row that satisfies r4">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
| step_id | action | expected_delta |
|---------|--------|----------------|
| s-04    | cut    | -120 min cycle, -$18 cost |
| s-05    | change | replace manual entry with n8n webhook; -90 min |
| s-09    | add    | new compliance checkpoint; +5 min, +$0 |
]]></code>
      <note>Each row references current-state step + carries a quantified delta.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Prose future-state that fails r4">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"We will automate the invoice handling and remove manual steps."
]]></code>
      <note>No step ids, no quantified delta, untestable.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
