<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-antipatterns" title="BPA Antipatterns">
  <summary>Agentic and structural failure modes in business process analysis, with concrete mitigations.</summary>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Documenting the ideal process: agent smooths over interview transcripts into a tidy linear diagram. Workarounds disappear.</description>
    <reason>Workarounds are the actual process. They carry the real value and the real waste. Verbatim quotes for any anomaly; the agent is forbidden from paraphrasing them as normal steps.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Hallucinated metrics: cycle-time cells filled with "30 min (estimated)" when no data source is supplied.</description>
    <reason>Estimated metrics anchor decisions to fabricated baselines. Hard-block: "Data not available" if not directly cited in the evidence.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Single-pool bias: LLMs collapse parallel branches into sequential steps and lose multi-actor swimlanes.</description>
    <reason>Handoffs between actors are where bottlenecks occur. Pre-prompt: "Identify all gateways (XOR/OR/AND); never default to a linear flow. Every step must have an actor column."</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Future-state shopping list: agent emits 30 improvements with no prioritization or effort scores.</description>
    <reason>Cap at 5 improvements; require effort/benefit scores ranked by NVA×frequency. A list without ranking forces BA work the agent should have done.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Workaround erasure: "we email Jane because the system is broken" rewritten as "data is transferred to the systems team".</description>
    <reason>The workaround is the finding. Force verbatim quotes for any anomaly. The agent must not paraphrase exceptions into normal-looking steps.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>BPMN output that looks like valid XML but fails Camunda/pm4py validation on import.</description>
    <reason>Always validate BPMN 2.0 XML with pm4py.write_bpmn() or bpmn-validate before archiving. Invalid BPMN cannot be executed, diffed, or imported into downstream tools.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Hallucinated system names: agent invents "ERP" or "CRM" generically when evidence mentions specific systems.</description>
    <reason>Constrain: "Use only system names that appear verbatim in the evidence." Generic names make the process map non-actionable for system-specific redesign.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
