<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Business Storytelling Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding business-storytelling. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="answer-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The artefact MUST lead with the central claim within the first 2 sentences. Burying the answer past sentence 3 is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Barbara Minto — The Pyramid Principle">Executives stop reading the moment their question is answered or visibly delayed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="mece-supports" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Supporting arguments MUST be MECE (Mutually Exclusive, Collectively Exhaustive). Overlapping or non-exhaustive lists are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Barbara Minto — The Pyramid Principle">Overlap signals sloppy thinking; gaps signal missing analysis. Both erode credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="so-what-test" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every fact MUST be paired with its implication. Bare facts ('revenue grew 20%') are forbidden — must add 'which means...'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — exec-review audits">A fact without an implication is incomplete; the audience must infer the point themselves, which is the slow path.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="scqa-or-pixar-for-change" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Change narratives (pivot, layoffs, strategy shift) MUST use SCQA or Pixar — Pyramid alone reads as a directive without context.</statement>
      <rationale source="Dan &amp; Chip Heath — Made to Stick">Without narrative tension, change stories trigger defense; SCQA / Pixar arc earns the buy-in.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="one-frame-per-piece" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An artefact MUST use exactly one framework — Pyramid OR SCQA OR Pixar. Mixing produces incoherent arcs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — copy-edit audits">Mixing frameworks reads as draft scaffolding the author forgot to remove.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
