<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-pyramid-and-scqa" title="Pyramid Principle and SCQA Framework">
  <summary>The Pyramid Principle (lead with answer, support with MECE arguments) and SCQA (Situation-Complication-Question-Answer) for building narrative tension in business communication.</summary>

  <section title="Pyramid Principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lead with the main point (the answer), then provide supporting arguments, then evidence — never build up to a conclusion.</statement>
      <rationale>Busy decision-makers stop reading the moment their question is answered. Bottom-up structure (background → argument → conclusion) forces them to read everything before knowing whether to care. Pyramid Principle means they can stop at the headline if it answers their question.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Project proposal using Pyramid Principle.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
MAIN POINT: "We should migrate to cloud infrastructure"

ARGUMENT 1: Cost reduction
  - Evidence: 40% lower TCO analysis
  - Evidence: Competitor benchmarks

ARGUMENT 2: Scalability
  - Evidence: Current capacity limits
  - Evidence: Projected growth

ARGUMENT 3: Speed
  - Evidence: Deployment time comparison
  - Evidence: Developer survey
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Bottom-up structure that buries the recommendation.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Current infrastructure has high TCO...
capacity is limited...
deployments take 3 hours...
therefore, we should migrate to cloud."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="MECE Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Arguments supporting the main point must be Mutually Exclusive (no overlap) and Collectively Exhaustive (nothing missing).</statement>
      <rationale>Overlapping arguments confuse the audience about whether you have two reasons or one. Missing arguments leave obvious objections unaddressed, which erodes credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="SCQA Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use SCQA when you need to build narrative tension: Situation (shared context), Complication (what changed or threatens), Question (the logical question that arises), Answer (your solution).</statement>
      <rationale>SCQA works because it mirrors how the audience's mind naturally processes a problem. The Complication creates urgency; the Question creates curiosity; the Answer satisfies both. Pure pyramid without SCQA can feel abrupt in presentations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Product pitch using SCQA.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
S: "Our team ships 10 features per quarter"
C: "But 30% have critical bugs in the first week"
Q: "How do we maintain velocity while improving quality?"
A: "Automated testing with 80% coverage gate"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Strategy presentation using SCQA.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
S: "We dominate the SMB market with 60% share"
C: "Enterprise represents 5x larger revenue per customer"
Q: "Should we pursue enterprise, and how?"
A: "Phased approach: mid-market first, then enterprise"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/executive-summary.txt">Executive summary template using Pyramid structure</reference>
  </section>
</text>
