<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-pixar-and-story-elements" title="Pixar Framework, Story Elements, and Data Storytelling">
  <summary>The Pixar causal story structure for change narratives, hooks and concrete language for opening impact, and the before/after/so-what pattern for data storytelling.</summary>

  <section title="Pixar Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the Pixar causal chain for change stories and case studies: each "because of that" link must be a direct consequence of the prior event, not a separate observation.</statement>
      <rationale>The "because of that" connector forces the narrator to establish causality, not just sequence. Without causality, change stories read as coincidences rather than evidence of impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Pixar structure applied to a business automation win.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Once upon a time: our team spent 10 hours/week on manual reporting.
Every day: they copy-pasted data between 5 spreadsheets.
One day: we implemented automated dashboards.
Because of that: reporting time dropped to 1 hour.
Because of that: the team focused on analysis, not data entry.
Until finally: we identified $500K in cost savings.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/case-study.txt">Case study template using Pixar causal structure</reference>
    <reference path="templates/presentation-outline.txt">4-section presentation outline: Hook / Problem / Solution / CTA</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Hooks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Open every presentation or document with a hook in the first 30 seconds: use a surprising statistic, a bold contradiction, or a specific story — not an agenda slide.</statement>
      <rationale>Audiences form engagement decisions in the first 30 seconds. An agenda slide answers a question nobody is asking; a hook creates a question the audience wants answered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Surprising stat: "90% of startups fail. Here's why we won't."</item>
      <item>Question: "What if you could deploy without fear?"</item>
      <item>Bold statement: "Meetings are broken. Let me prove it."</item>
      <item>Story: "Last Tuesday at 2am, our server crashed..."</item>
      <item>Contradiction: "The best code is no code."</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Concrete vs Abstract Language">
    <rule>
      <statement>Replace abstract outcomes with concrete, numbered results. Apply the "so what?" test to every data point: if the implication is not explicit, state it.</statement>
      <rationale>Abstract language ("improved efficiency") is forgettable because it activates no mental image. Concrete numbers anchor understanding and credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Improved efficiency"
"Better customer experience"
"Enhanced security"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Cut processing time from 4 hours to 15 minutes"
"Reduced support tickets by 60%"
"Blocked 10,000 attacks last month"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>The so-what escalation for a reliability metric.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Bad:    "We have 99.9% uptime"
Better: "99.9% uptime means only 8.7 hours of downtime per year"
Best:   "99.9% uptime means your customers never see an error page"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Burying the main recommendation at the end after extensive background.</description>
    <reason>Decision-makers who stop reading mid-document never receive the recommendation. Lead with the answer per Pyramid Principle.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Ending a presentation without a specific call to action.</description>
    <reason>Vague endings produce "let me think about it" deferrals. A clear ask defines what decision is being requested and when.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
