<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="strategy-analysis-gap-analysis Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for strategy-analysis-gap-analysis. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every gap row MUST include a numeric delta (gap_size and gap_unit) derived from the current-state metric and the future-state target. Prose-only gaps MUST be returned for re-elicitation before the gap analysis is signed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Un-measured gaps cannot be prioritized analytically; they become political. Numeric deltas allow weighted scoring in the change strategy evaluation matrix.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Gap priority (H/M/L) MUST be assigned using percentile rank across all gaps, not free H/M/L labeling. Agents MUST be prompted: "Of these N gaps, rank by impact size; assign H to top quartile, M to middle half, L to bottom quartile."</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents cluster around three or around H when given free labeling. Percentile forcing produces a realistic distribution and prevents all gaps from being "high priority."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A gap dependency DAG MUST be produced: each gap row lists which other gaps it blocks. Gaps with zero dependents and low priority are candidates for deferral. The dependency DAG MUST be validated by the BA before the gap analysis is signed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without the dependency DAG, prioritization is popularity-weighted: the most visible gaps surface first regardless of whether they block other gaps. Structural prioritization via DAG is the only way to sequence the change strategy correctly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
