<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Information Architecture Principles">
  <summary>Core IA principles: organization schemes, navigation types, labeling rules, and scalability requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Organization Schemes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Organize content around user tasks and goals, not internal product structure or org chart.</statement>
      <rationale>Internal organization reflects how the team thinks, not how users search. Task-based IA (Shop, Learn, Get Help) maps to user intent; feature-based IA (Products, Platform, Resources) maps to company structure and fails navigation findability tests.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Topic-based: organize by subject matter (most common for content-heavy sites)</item>
      <item>Task-based: organize by what users want to do (best for tool/application navigation)</item>
      <item>Audience-based: organize by user type (use only when audiences have truly distinct needs)</item>
      <item>Chronological: organize by time (logs, news, events)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Navigation Depth and Breadth">
    <rule>
      <statement>Target 4-7 top-level categories; keep navigation to 3 levels maximum depth.</statement>
      <rationale>Below 4 categories feels sparse and forces overloaded categories. Above 7 exceeds comfortable visual scanning range (Miller's Law). Deeper than 3 levels buries content in paths users cannot remember or navigate back from.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Labeling Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write labels in user vocabulary; never use internal codenames, acronyms, or "Misc" / "Other" / "Resources" without specific scope.</statement>
      <rationale>User-language labels require no translation. Internal terminology forces users to learn your vocabulary before they can navigate. "Resources" with no scope defined is the most common navigation label failure — it can contain anything and therefore signals nothing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate labels with 5 users before running a tree test — a wrong label makes tree test data uninterpretable.</statement>
      <rationale>If a label is misunderstood, users take wrong paths not because the structure is bad but because the label failed. Label validation is cheaper than rerunning a full tree test.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scalability">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define rules for where new content types will go before launch; do not add categories reactively when content accumulates.</statement>
      <rationale>Reactive category creation produces inconsistent depth and "miscellaneous" buckets. Pre-defined taxonomy rules keep the IA coherent as content grows.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
