<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-patterns" title="IA Navigation Patterns">
  <summary>Common IA navigation patterns (mega menu, hub-and-spoke, flat structure) with selection criteria and validation workflow.</summary>

  <section title="Mega Menu">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use mega menus for sites with 40+ pages organized into 4+ top-level categories with meaningful subcategories at L2.</statement>
      <rationale>Mega menus expose L2 content without requiring navigation into L1 first, reducing clicks for users who already know their destination category. Overuse on small sites creates visual complexity without benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>E-commerce with Products, Solutions, Resources, Company: each top-level item expands to show 3-6 subcategories in columns, with a featured content block. Users can jump directly to "Enterprise Solutions" without clicking "Solutions" first.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Hub and Spoke">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use hub-and-spoke for task-focused applications where users complete one task per session, then return to a central dashboard.</statement>
      <rationale>Hub-and-spoke minimizes navigation complexity by removing the need for cross-spoke navigation. Users go from hub to task and back — no need to find "related" content or browse.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Flat Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use flat structure (1-2 levels) for small sites with under 20 pages, marketing sites, and portfolio sites.</statement>
      <rationale>Small sites with deep hierarchies bury content unnecessarily. Flat structure keeps all content within 2 clicks of home, reducing navigation overhead for simple content sets.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Validation Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow this mandatory validation sequence: card sort → proposed IA → label validation (5 users) → tree test → refined IA → build.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent-generated or team-designed IA without validation produces navigation that makes sense to the team but fails with real users. Each validation step has a different failure mode; all three are required.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Card sort: discovers how users group content (inputs IA structure)</item>
      <item>Label validation: confirms users interpret category labels as intended (prevents tree test corruption)</item>
      <item>Tree test: confirms users can find specific content in the proposed hierarchy (validates findability)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never treat agent-generated IA as final without tree testing — the most common IA failure mode.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents generate internally consistent structures that may not match user mental models. Tree testing with real users is the only way to validate that users can navigate the structure, not just that the structure is logically coherent.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
