<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="IA Examples and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>E-commerce and SaaS IA examples, common mistakes, and agentic generation workflow with gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="E-commerce IA Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Organization scheme: task-based (Shop, Learn, Get Help). Shop → By Category, By Brand, Sale Items. Learn → Buying Guides, Style Tips, Product Reviews. Get Help → Order Status, Returns, Contact Us. Labels use user verbs, not company nouns. Maximum 2 levels deep.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="SaaS Product IA Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Organization scheme: user journey (Discover, Build, Grow). Discover → Features, Solutions, Pricing. Build → Documentation, API Reference, Tutorials. Grow → Case Studies, Best Practices, Community. L1 names reflect user intent stages, not product feature categories.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Navigation structure mirrors org chart (Marketing, Product, Engineering, Support as L1 categories).</description>
      <reason>Users do not know or care about internal org structure. They navigate by their goals. Org-based IA forces users to guess which department owns the content they need.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Category named "Resources" or "Miscellaneous" without specific scope.</description>
      <reason>"Resources" signals nothing about what it contains. Users cannot predict its contents and skip it in navigation. Everything needs a specific, content-accurate label.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>IA change that affects URL structure shipped without SEO review.</description>
      <reason>URL structure changes break search engine indexing and user-bookmarked links. Any IA change touching URLs requires human sign-off and redirect planning before deploy.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Agent receives product spec or feature list. Produces: (1) proposed category structure at L1 and L2, (2) taxonomy document defining content types and tag groups, (3) sitemap skeleton in markdown, (4) validation plan specifying card sort type and tree test scope. Second agent pass takes card sort results and tree test failure data and produces revised sitemap with changes justified by data.</p>
    <reference path="templates/ia-strategy.md">IA strategy document template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/sitemap.md">Sitemap skeleton template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/taxonomy.md">Taxonomy document template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/sitemap-generator.py">Python script for generating Mermaid diagrams from IA definition</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-ia.txt">LLM prompt for generating IA from a product spec</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent generates IA that mirrors the feature roadmap rather than user goals.</description>
      <reason>Agents producing IA from feature lists default to feature-based categorization. Explicitly instruct: "organize by user goal, not by feature or product area."</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent uses corporate-speak labels (Solutions, Platform, Resources, Ecosystem).</description>
      <reason>These labels are internally meaningful but user-opaque. Require plain-language alternatives in the prompt and validate with 5 users before tree testing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
