<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-antipatterns" title="Interface Analysis Antipatterns">
  <summary>Common failure modes in interface analysis: static drift, volume guessing, async mismatch, auth blindspots, and agentic hallucinations.</summary>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Static spec drift: hand-written Markdown interface specs decay the moment code ships because they are disconnected from the implementation.</description>
    <reason>Generate specs from OpenAPI/AsyncAPI/Protobuf source of truth or sync via oasdiff in CI. Hand-typed specs as primary artifacts guarantee drift within days of the first deploy.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Volume and SLA fields filled with confident estimates pre-launch: "expected: 10,000 requests/day".</description>
    <reason>Pre-launch volume estimates are guesses with order-of-magnitude error. Mark fields "tbd" until load-test data exists. Confident fictions produce wrong capacity planning decisions.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Async event flows (Kafka, webhooks, NATS) documented using the REST interface template.</description>
    <reason>REST templates cannot represent fan-out direction, consumer-side retry semantics, or per-key ordering guarantees. Use AsyncAPI 3.0 for all event-driven interfaces.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Error codes auto-completed with the standard HTTP set even when the API returns only 3 of them.</description>
    <reason>Hallucinated error codes mislead client developers who write error-handling for codes that never fire. Validate against captured traffic; document only codes that the API actually emits.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Auth fields (OAuth scopes, API key header location) generated from the agent's priors without citing the vendor docs.</description>
    <reason>Auth fields are the highest-risk spec fields: wrong scopes produce authorization failures; wrong header names produce 401 errors that look like network issues. Require source-cited auth fields; reject auth rows without evidence URLs.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Payload examples containing placeholder tokens: "field1": "[value]".</description>
    <reason>Tools and agents copy-paste payload examples into tests. Placeholders in examples produce tests that assert against literal "[value]" strings instead of real data. Examples must be literal.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Cross-team interfaces failing at the human boundary: the spec is correct but the other team owns auth rotation and breaks it without notice.</description>
    <reason>Technical specs cannot solve organizational coordination. Pair IF-XXX specs with named contacts and a change-notification protocol. oasdiff in CI catches changes automatically; human contacts catch intentional breaking changes before they deploy.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
