<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="DR Drill Script Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the DR Drill Script Template methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-declaration-step-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Drill MUST start with an explicit declaration step: simulate the trigger condition + confirm the matching scenario id + announce to stakeholders + start the clock.</statement>
      <rationale source="ICS Incident Command pattern">Skipping declaration makes the drill timing invalid; clock-start anchors RTO measurement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-runbook-executed-verbatim" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Runbook steps MUST be executed verbatim by the on-call engineer. Deviations are logged with rationale; ad-hoc fixes are flagged for post-mortem.</statement>
      <rationale source="runbook discipline">Drilling the runbook surfaces gaps in the runbook; ad-hoc fixes mask the gap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-restore-validation-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Drill is NOT green until restore validation passes: data integrity check + smoke test + transaction-replay sample. 'Service responds' alone is not validation.</statement>
      <rationale source="backup-verification-dr">Cosmetic recovery (service up, empty DB) is the most common drill-as-theatre pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-rto-rpo-scored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Drill MUST capture RTO + RPO achieved with timestamps. Failure to hit targets is recorded; the drill is still useful but not 'passed'.</statement>
      <rationale source="DR program metrics">Scoring lets the program track DR maturity over time; un-scored drills are just stories.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-post-mortem-7d" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post-mortem MUST be published within 7 days. Format: timeline + gaps + tickets + sign-off by engineering leader.</statement>
      <rationale source="blameless postmortem culture">Beyond 7 days, memory degrades + tickets don't get filed; the drill becomes lost data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-stakeholder-comms" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Drill announcement MUST go to all stakeholders impacted (security, support, business owners) at start + at restore + at post-mortem publish. Drill comms log captured.</statement>
      <rationale source="communication-incident-response">Silent drills produce real-incident panic in support; comms are part of the drill, not optional.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
