<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-viral-loops">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>growth-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Self-reinforcing cycles where user actions create shareable artifacts. K = i * c (invites/user times conversion). Seven types: inherent, WOM, incentivized, social, collaborative, content, embedded.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>viral</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>k-factor</tag>
      <tag>loops</tag>
      <tag>acquisition</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Viral Loops and Growth Mechanics</title>

    <summary>Viral loops are self-reinforcing growth cycles where a user action creates an artifact that is shared or exposed, motivating new users to join and repeat the action. The K-factor (K = i * c, invites-per-user times conversion rate) quantifies loop strength. Seven loop types exist: inherent, word-of-mouth, incentivized, social, collaborative, content, and embedded. Select one primary loop type matched to your product before engineering, then instrument it and iterate via viral-optimization.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Linear growth (spend money → get users, stop → growth stops) caps the business at acquisition budget. A viral loop with K = 0.3 reduces effective CAC by 30% permanently and compounds over time. Even K well below 1 is valuable; K = 1+ is rare and unstable. Cycle time is as important as K: K = 0.4 with a 3-day cycle outcompounds K = 0.7 with a 60-day cycle over a quarter.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing a growth loop for a new product or vertical (strategic design layer).</item>
        <item>Choosing among loop types: which fits product DNA, ICP, and current PMF stage?</item>
        <item>Planning measurement infrastructure (events, K-funnel, cycle-time tracker) before engineering.</item>
        <item>Companion to viral-optimization (the iterating layer) and ops-churn-prevention (retention side).</item>
        <item>Designing or auditing a growth loop where user output (content, invites, embedded artifacts) creates distribution that brings new users.</item>
        <item>Strategic-level work: matching loop to product type, sizing the realistic K for the category, planning measurement infrastructure.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF: weak product value means weak inviter motivation and the loop fizzles regardless of mechanics. Fix value, then design loops.</item>
        <item>Pure sales-led businesses where unit economics already work — adding viral complexity gives marginal lift.</item>
        <item>Regulated categories (finance, health, gambling) where unsolicited referrals violate FTC/MiFID II/HIPAA or CASL/GDPR compliance rules.</item>
        <item>Products where sharing imposes social cost on the inviter (sensitive niches) — virality is anti-loyalty.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="seven-loop-types">
      <p>Seven viral loop types, their mechanics, canonical examples, and a product-type match guide for selecting the right primary loop.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Inherent: product requires or fails to deliver core value without inviting others (Slack, Zoom). Test: does the product fail to work without the invitee?</item>
        <item>Word of mouth: users talk about the product unprompted (Apple, Notion). Requires a strong product story; cannot be engineered directly.</item>
        <item>Incentivized: explicit rewards for referrals — cash, credits, features (Dropbox +500MB, Uber credits). Measurable, tunable, fraud-prone.</item>
        <item>Social: user output is visible to non-users, creating FOMO (Spotify Wrapped, Wordle). Requires shareable artifacts.</item>
        <item>Collaborative: product improves or requires collaboration, pulling in teammates (Figma, Notion docs). Natural for B2B / team tools.</item>
        <item>Content: users create content that carries branding and CTAs (Canva designs, TikTok). Requires user-generated artifacts with embedded attribution.</item>
        <item>Embedded: product name appears in output ("Made with X", "Sent via X"). Low friction, low K, good for awareness at scale.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="product-type-match">
      <p>Matching loop types to product categories.</p>
      <list>
        <item>B2C social / media: Social + Content loops</item>
        <item>B2B team tools: Collaborative + Inherent loops</item>
        <item>Productivity SaaS: Embedded + Word of mouth loops</item>
        <item>Marketplace: Inherent + Incentivized loops</item>
        <item>Consumer subscription (low viral): Incentivized loop as primary</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pick ONE primary loop type and instrument it completely before designing a second; multi-loop products without a baseline K cannot diagnose regressions.</statement>
        <rationale>Adding a second loop before the first is measured creates attribution confusion — you cannot tell which loop is driving new users or why K changed.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="loop-anatomy">
      <p>Every loop has five structural elements. Define all five before engineering:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Action: what the user does that triggers the loop (completes a task, creates a document, achieves a milestone)</item>
        <item>Artifact: what is created or shared as output (badge, report, invite link, branded content)</item>
        <item>Distribution: how the artifact reaches potential new users (social share, email, in-product, search-indexable)</item>
        <item>Motivation: why a new user would want to join after seeing the artifact (FOMO, utility, social connection)</item>
        <item>Friction: steps to join from artifact exposure (target: one-click signup from invite link)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="k-factor-expectations">
      <p>K-factor category benchmarks to anchor expectations before designing.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Anchor K-factor expectations to category benchmarks before designing — consumer apps: K=0.1–0.3; B2B SaaS: K=0.05–0.2. Designing for K &gt; 0.5 leads to dark-pattern mechanics.</statement>
        <rationale>K &gt; 1 is rare and unstable; most successful products operate at K = 0.1–0.4 and use the viral lift to reduce CAC rather than achieve exponential growth.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cycle-time-lever">
      <p>Cycle time is a primary lever equal in importance to invites-per-user (i) and conversion rate (c).</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Measure cycle time (p50 days from share to invitee activation) and treat it as a lever equal in importance to i and c — halving cycle time roughly squares compounding over a quarter.</statement>
        <rationale>K = 0.4 with 3-day cycle time produces more users in 90 days than K = 0.7 with 60-day cycle time.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Reduce cycle time: one-click signup for invitees, social login, pre-filled email from invite token</item>
        <item>Monitor cycle_time_p50 weekly; sudden increase signals friction introduced by a signup or onboarding change</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="invitee-landing-page-priority">
      <p>The invitee landing page is the highest-priority optimization surface — most loops fail at conversion, not at sharing.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Treat the invitee landing page as the highest-priority optimization surface — most loops fail at conversion, not at sharing.</statement>
        <rationale>Improving the landing page conversion rate multiplies every future loop turn; share-side improvements only increase volume into the current conversion rate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Show inviter name and avatar prominently</item>
        <item>Display value preview before requiring signup</item>
        <item>One-click signup (Google/Apple SSO or email magic link)</item>
        <item>Pre-fill email address from invite token</item>
        <item>Mobile-optimize: target &lt;= 3 taps from invite link to activated account</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="friction-reduction">
      <p>Minimize friction on the invitee side to maximize conversion rate (c in K = i * c).</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Never require signup to view shared content; a preview wall converts better than a hard gate.</statement>
        <rationale>Hard gates drop invitee conversion by 40–60%; previewing the value before requiring signup is the correct pattern for most content and social loops.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="embedded-branding">
      <p>Rules for embedding branding in user-generated output and shared artifacts.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Embed branding in user output only where it adds value to the recipient (source credit, attribution) — not as a tax that degrades the artifact.</statement>
        <rationale>Embedded branding used as a watermark without value to the recipient is perceived as spam; watermarks with source credit (Canva designs, Notion exports) are accepted because they provide context.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Plan to redesign embedded-branding loops every 12–18 months; users learn the pattern and conversion decays as familiarity removes novelty.</statement>
        <rationale>Loops are not permanent — the pattern becomes ambient within 12–18 months and the invitee motivation ("what is this?") disappears.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="case-studies">
      <p>Three canonical viral loop case studies analyzed by loop anatomy and key success factors.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Dropbox: Incentivized Loop">
        <note>Loop anatomy: user needs more storage → refers a friend → friend signs up → both get 500MB → friend needs more storage → loop repeats. Key factors: clear two-sided value exchange, obvious placement, instant reward delivery, shareable link. Result: 60% of signups from referrals, 35% permanent increase in signups. Note: contact-import element of this model is blocked by iOS/Android post-2021.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Spotify Wrapped: Social Loop">
        <note>Loop anatomy: user listens to music all year → Spotify creates personalized annual summary → user shares on social → friends see it and want their own → non-users download Spotify. Key factors: zero effort to create the artifact, designed for social sharing, FOMO for non-users, annual ritual creates predictable spike. Result: millions of social shares, significant December download spike.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Notion Templates: Content Loop">
        <note>Loop anatomy: power user creates a template → shares publicly in Notion gallery or community → others find template via search → need Notion to use it → some become template creators. Key factors: user-generated content, SEO-friendly (indexed by Google), real standalone utility, clear attribution. Loop is SEO-compounding: templates accumulate in search over time.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Use subagents at design time, not at runtime. The flow: agent reads product brief → maps to loop-type taxonomy → drafts loop anatomy (action / artifact / distribution / motivation / friction) → estimates plausible K range from category benchmarks → proposes a measurement plan (events + funnel + cycle-time tracker). A human PM and growth lead approve before engineering. Iteration happens under viral-optimization.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: growth-marketer (opus for strategic design, sonnet for drafts) for loop selection and design; product-strategist (opus) to match loop to product DNA and PMF stage; data-analyst (sonnet) to define K-funnel events and cycle-time measurement; legal-reviewer (opus) to flag CASL / GDPR / FTC issues in incentivized or contact-import loops.</p>
      <prompt purpose="loop-design"><![CDATA[
Input: product brief (what it does, who pays, ICP, current GTM)
Task: 1) recommend ONE primary loop type with a one-paragraph fit argument
      2) draft loop anatomy: action -> artifact -> distribution -> motivation -> friction
      3) estimate realistic K range citing 2 comparable products
      4) list 5 events to instrument before launch
Output: markdown using the README "Loop: <Name>" template
Forbidden: claiming K > 0.5 without a comparable consumer-social precedent
]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>CLI tools and services for viral loop instrumentation and management.</p>
      <list>
        <item>branch.io CLI — Deferred-deeplink attribution for cross-platform invites (https://help.branch.io)</item>
        <item>posthog CLI — Funnel + cohort instrumentation for loop measurement (npm i -g posthog-node)</item>
        <item>growthbook CLI — A/B test loop variants once shipped (npm i -g @growthbook/cli)</item>
        <item>viral-loops API — Templated referral loop scaffolding (https://docs.viral-loops.com)</item>
        <item>dbt-core — Materialize K-factor models in warehouse (pip install dbt-core)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services">
      <p>Agent-friendly SaaS and OSS services for viral loop management and attribution.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Viral Loops (SaaS, Yes REST) — Templated campaigns: waitlist, referral, milestone</item>
        <item>GrowSurf (SaaS, Yes REST) — Lightweight referral / waitlist</item>
        <item>Friendbuy (SaaS, Yes REST) — Two-sided referral, fraud controls</item>
        <item>ReferralCandy (SaaS, Yes REST) — Ecommerce referral, Shopify-native</item>
        <item>Branch (SaaS, Yes REST + SDKs) — Invite link attribution across web + mobile</item>
        <item>AppsFlyer / Adjust (SaaS, Yes REST) — Mobile attribution incl. SKAdNetwork</item>
        <item>Loops.so / Customer.io (SaaS, Yes REST) — Trigger lifecycle messages from loop events</item>
        <item>PostHog (OSS + SaaS, Yes REST + HogQL) — Funnel + retention for loop measurement</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="loop-projection-script">
      <p>Back-of-envelope loop projection (compounding model) to show whether assumed K + cycle yields self-sustaining growth.</p>
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# loop_projection.py — naive compounding model
def project(starting_users, K, cycle_days, days):
    """K = invites_per_user * conversion_rate; per cycle."""
    cycles = days / cycle_days
    if K >= 1:
        # exponential
        return starting_users * (K ** cycles)
    # geometric series sum (decaying contribution)
    total = starting_users * (1 - K ** (cycles + 1)) / (1 - K)
    return total

for K in (0.1, 0.3, 0.5, 0.7, 1.0):
    n = project(1000, K, cycle_days=14, days=180)
    print(f"K={K:.2f}  cycle=14d  180d_users≈{n:,.0f}")
]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pick one primary loop and instrument it deeply before adding a second; multi-loop products without baseline K cannot debug regressions.</item>
        <item>Cycle time is a primary lever — halving cycle time roughly squares the compounded effect over a quarter.</item>
        <item>Embed branding in user output where it adds value to the recipient (link preview, watermark with credit) rather than as a tax.</item>
        <item>Tie inviter rewards to invitee value-realization, not invitee signup, to push fraud below noise.</item>
        <item>Treat the invitee landing page as a top-priority surface — most loops fail at conversion, not at sharing.</item>
        <item>Re-design loops every 12–18 months; users learn the pattern and conversion rate (c) decays.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Known failure modes and measurement limitations for viral loops.</p>
      <list>
        <item>K &gt; 1 is rare and unstable; designing for it leads to dark-pattern shares that backfire.</item>
        <item>Loop math assumes invitees behave like inviters — they often retain worse, especially in incentivized loops.</item>
        <item>"Embedded branding" loops (Made-with-X) decay as the brand becomes ambient; require continuous design refresh.</item>
        <item>Cross-platform attribution (web → mobile, email → app) is broken by ITP, mail-open prefetch, and iOS Mail Privacy Protection — your K may be under-counted by 30–60%.</item>
        <item>Forced sharing (gated content) drives short-term K but kills long-term retention and brand.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs over-cite Dropbox / Spotify Wrapped / Notion as if any product can clone them. Force comparable-precedent matching by stage and category.</item>
        <item>"Inherent" virality is rare — agents will label collaborative-tool features as inherent when they are merely incentivized. Demand the inherent-loop test: "does the product fail to deliver core value without inviting someone?"</item>
        <item>Agents propose mechanics that violate platform TOS (auto-DM friends, contact upload without consent). Filter at template level.</item>
        <item>K-projection math depends on invitee retention; agent models that assume invitee behaves like inviter overstate compounding by 2–5x.</item>
        <item>Generated copy invents social proof ("join 100,000 people") that is factually wrong; numeric claims must be passed in, not produced.</item>
        <item>Cross-platform attribution gaps invalidate K reported by single-tool dashboards — instruct the agent to specify which tool measures which leg.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent recommends auto-DM friends, contact upload without consent, or "share with all contacts" mechanics.</description>
      <reason>These violate platform TOS (LinkedIn, Twitter), CASL, GDPR, and CCPA. Filter at template level — do not let the agent generate these mechanics.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent labels a collaborative-tool invite flow as "inherent virality".</description>
      <reason>Inherent virality has a strict test: does the product fail to deliver core value without the invitee joining? Collaboration invites are typically incentivized or convenience-driven, not inherent.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent invents social proof claims ("join 100,000 people") without input data.</description>
      <reason>LLMs produce plausible-sounding numbers; all numeric claims in invite copy must be passed in as inputs, not generated.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/loop-anatomy.md" purpose="Loop design template: name, type, action/artifact/distribution/motivation/friction, K-factor targets."/>
      <template path="templates/referral-program.md" purpose="Referral program design: value proposition, mechanics, sharing options, tracking, fraud rules."/>
      <template path="templates/loop-projection.py" purpose="Naive compounding model: project user count from K + cycle time over N days."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://andrewchen.com/whats-your-viral-loop"/>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog/growth-loops"/>
      <link href="https://www.forentrepreneurs.com/lessons-learnt-viral-marketing/"/>
      <link href="https://brianbalfour.com"/>
      <ref slug="growth-referral-programs"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
