<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Freelance MSA + SOW Templates Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules define the contractual primitives a P3 freelancer signs every month — split between long-lived MSA and per-engagement SOW, with explicit handling of money, IP, warranty and exit.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The contract package is split into exactly two documents: an MSA that defines everlasting terms (IP regime, confidentiality, indemnity caps, governing law, dispute resolution, payment cycle, termination triggers) and a SOW per engagement that defines deliverables, milestones, price, and acceptance. SOWs may amend the MSA's specifics for one engagement only; they may not silently override IP or indemnity.</statement>
      <rationale source="MSA + SOW pattern needed for monthly contract signing">A single mega-contract per engagement forces re-negotiation of stable terms each time; an MSA-then-SOW split lets the freelancer re-sign in days because only deliverables and price are debated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Payment terms in every SOW must include: (a) an upfront deposit of at least 25% of the SOW value invoiced before work begins, (b) weekly or biweekly progress invoices for T&amp;M work or milestone invoices for fixed-price, (c) net-14 payment terms with a defined late-fee clause (e.g. 1.5%/month or statutory rate, whichever is higher). "Pay on delivery" or "net-60" terms without a corresponding price uplift are explicitly rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Deposit + weekly invoicing — solo cashflow primitive">Solo freelancers cannot finance a buyer's 60-day payment terms; deposits and weekly invoicing keep cashflow positive and reveal payment problems early enough to stop work without taking a fatal loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Intellectual property transfers to the client on full payment of the relevant invoice, not on signature or on delivery. The MSA names the regime as work-for-hire-or-assignment-on-payment with a fallback assignment clause, explicitly carves out: (a) the freelancer's pre-existing IP (libraries, tools, templates) which is licensed back perpetually-royalty-free, (b) general know-how which is not transferred.</statement>
      <rationale source="IP transfer on payment is the freelancer's leverage">Transfer-on-signature gives away the only leverage if the client refuses to pay; transfer-on-payment keeps the work owned by the freelancer until cash clears, which is enforceable in most jurisdictions and is the freelance default for a reason.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Warranty is bounded in two dimensions: scope (delivered code matches the SOW's acceptance criteria; third-party libraries and client-provided systems are excluded) and time (e.g. 30 or 60 days post-acceptance for defect fixes free of charge; beyond that any remediation is a new SOW or T&amp;M). Implied warranties of merchantability, fitness for a particular purpose, and non-infringement are limited to the contract price ceiling.</statement>
      <rationale source="Warranty clause must be bounded — solo freelancer cannot underwrite unbounded liability">An unbounded warranty (e.g. "shall be free of defects for ever") effectively makes the freelancer a perpetual on-call resource for free, which is fatal to a solo practice. Explicit bounds preserve the contract economics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Termination clauses cover three cases: (a) termination for cause (material breach, 14-day cure period), (b) termination for convenience by either party with notice (typically 14 days) and pro-rata payment for work completed up to termination, (c) termination on non-payment after a defined cure period during which the freelancer may suspend work. The MSA explicitly states what survives termination (confidentiality, IP regime for paid work, dispute resolution, accrued payment).</statement>
      <rationale source="Termination is the escape clause that prevents toxic engagements">Without a termination-for-convenience clause the freelancer is trapped in deteriorating engagements; without a non-payment trigger the freelancer must continue working while invoices age. Both clauses are insurance the freelancer routinely needs to invoke.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical example">
    <example type="good" title="MSA + SOW pair for a 10-week engagement">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
MSA (signed once, lives for the relationship):
  §3 Payment cycle: net-14, late fee 1.5%/mo
  §4 IP: assignment on payment; pre-existing IP listed at Annex A is licensed
       back royalty-free; general know-how excluded
  §5 Warranty: 60 days post-acceptance per SOW; liability cap = SOW value;
       no implied merchantability beyond cap
  §6 Termination: for-cause with 14d cure; for-convenience with 14d notice;
       non-payment suspension after 14d past-due
  §7 Confidentiality: 3 years post-termination
  §8 Governing law / venue: agreed (e.g. Portugal / Lisbon arbitration)

SOW-01 (signed per engagement):
  Scope:        described as 4 milestones M1-M4 with acceptance criteria each
  Price:        €36,000 fixed across 4 milestones (€9k each)
  Deposit:      €9,000 (25% = first milestone) invoiced and paid before kickoff
  Cadence:      milestone invoice on each acceptance, net-14
  Out of scope: SSO integration, multi-tenant data partitioning
  Acceptance:   client confirms in writing within 7d of demo or is deemed accepted

Result: SOW is 2 pages, MSA is 8 pages, total signature cycle = 5 business days.
]]></code>
      <note>The MSA does the heavy contractual lifting once. Every subsequent SOW with the same client is a short, fast-to-sign document about deliverables and money.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
