<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Freelance Rate Jump Tactics Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules stage a 30-50% rate jump inside a niche pivot so the new price is defensible from the first proposal.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The new rate is not announced before three credentialing artefacts exist and are publicly visible in the new niche: at least one written case study or detailed teardown of a delivered project, at least one external endorsement (named client testimonial, conference talk, podcast guest spot, or maintained OSS in the niche), and a visibly updated public profile (site, LinkedIn, GitHub) where the niche keyword appears in the first sentence. Operators announcing the new rate without all three roll back on first pushback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Defensibly raise rates 30-50% inside a niche pivot — credentialing must precede pricing">A 30-50% jump without visible credentials is read by buyers as opportunism, not specialty pricing. Public-facing artefacts give the buyer a third-party reason to accept the higher number; without them, the conversation collapses to negotiation by hours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The personal anchor is recalibrated to the new niche's price band before any proposal goes out: the operator collects 5-10 data points (public rate cards, peer surveys, marketplace listings, recent client quotes from peers) for specialists in the same niche and writes down a target band with median and 75th percentile. The new rate is positioned at or just below the 75th percentile for new business, not at the generalist median.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anchor recalibration against the new niche, not the old generalist band">If the operator still benchmarks against generalists they will under-price the niche by definition. Writing down the niche's actual price distribution kills "I'd feel weird charging that much" as a barrier and turns the rate into an empirical position.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Case studies are sequenced in outbound such that the highest-priced case study is introduced first in any new conversation, before the rate is named. Lower-priced or older generalist work is moved to "additional past projects" or removed from the lead-with portfolio. Buyer questions about pricing are answered only after at least one niche case study has been discussed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Case-study sequencing that justifies the jump">Buyers anchor on the first number they see; the first number they see should describe the niche's economics, not the generalist's. Leading with the right case study makes the new rate feel like "more of the same", not "a sudden 50% jump".</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rollout is two-tier: <strong>new leads</strong> see the full new rate from week 1 with no transition discount; <strong>existing clients</strong> receive a written notice with a 60-90 day migration plan that bundles a tangible upgrade (deliverable improvement, faster turnaround, a specialty deliverable the old generalist rate did not include) so the increase is anchored to new value, not raw price. Existing clients who refuse migration are kept on a phase-out schedule, not retained indefinitely at the old rate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Two-tier rollout splits new leads from existing-client migration">Trying to raise rates on existing clients overnight produces churn; trying to keep them all forever at the old rate caps the freelancer's revenue at the generalist ceiling. The two-tier rollout sets the new market price externally while migrating the book on a written schedule.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The operator tracks a single quantitative gate over the first 60 days at the new rate: <em>lead-to-proposal conversion</em> for new niche leads. If the rate is below the niche's market level, conversion stays roughly flat or rises; if it is above, conversion drops materially (e.g. &gt; 40% relative). On a measured drop greater than that threshold across at least 8 qualified leads, the operator does not lower the rate; instead they re-invest in credentialing (r1) or refine the niche statement (r3) and retest in 30 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="The rate-raise needs a quantitative ground truth, not vibes">Without a tracked conversion rate, every "no" feels like proof the rate was too high. The 8-lead floor and the lower the credentialing instead clause prevent the demoralised operator from quietly retreating to the generalist price.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical example">
    <example type="good" title="Generalist Django dev pivoting to fintech compliance">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Weeks 1-6 (credentialing, no price change yet):
  - Ship one detailed teardown post on PCI-DSS-scope-minimisation for a SaaS
  - Speak on a regional fintech meetup (recorded talk → embedded on site)
  - Update site + LinkedIn: "Django + Postgres for regulated fintech (PCI / GDPR)"
  - One pilot for new niche client at near-new rate, written case study

Week 7 (anchor recalibration):
  Collected data points → niche median €110/h, p75 €145/h
  Old generalist rate: €75/h. Target: €135/h (just below niche p75, 80% jump)

Week 8 (new-lead tier active):
  All outbound proposals quote €135/h; case study leads with the fintech work,
  pricing only after the case study is discussed.

Weeks 8-20 (existing-client migration):
  Written notice: "From [date+60d], new rate €120/h for retained clients,
   which now includes a quarterly PCI-scope review previously billed separately."
  3 of 4 clients accept; 1 phased out by week 20.

Week 14 metric check:
  Lead → proposal conversion at new rate: 9 of 14 (64%, was 70% at old rate) →
  within tolerance, do not roll back.
]]></code>
      <note>Every gate was passed before the next move; the rate jump is anchored in artefacts the buyer can see and a metric the operator can track.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
