<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-patterns-and-rules" title="Multimodal Patterns and Dialogue Turn Rules">
  <summary>Core multimodal VUI design patterns and mandatory per-turn structural rules for voice + visual interfaces.</summary>

  <section title="Multimodal Patterns">
    <list>
      <item>Voice-initiated, screen-completed — user speaks a query; screen displays structured results (cards, carousels); voice summarizes aloud.</item>
      <item>Screen-initiated, voice-completed — user taps a form field or list item; voice confirms or elaborates.</item>
      <item>Voice + visual feedback — confirmations and progress states shown on screen while TTS reads them.</item>
      <item>Voice navigation + visual content — user says "next" or "go back" while screen renders the content.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Dialogue Turn Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every dialogue turn must declare four fields: voice_prompt (what the assistant says, max 15 words for smart display), visual_state (component type + content, max 5 items), user_actions (valid voice inputs AND touch actions), and fallback (what happens after 5 seconds of silence).</statement>
      <rationale>Incomplete turns produce states reachable only by voice — users who switch to touch are stranded. The structure enforces completeness at design time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every voice state must have a touch equivalent. If a user cannot complete the task using touch alone, the design is not multimodal — it is voice-only with a broken screen.</statement>
      <rationale>Users switch modalities mid-session constantly: privacy concerns, noisy environment, screen reader mode. Modal lock-in is a usability and accessibility failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit visual card content to 5 items maximum per screen state. For lists longer than 5, paginate and surface navigation affordances for both voice ("say 'next' for more") and touch.</statement>
      <rationale>Smart display screens are small (7-10 inches). Card patterns that work on phones break on small displays. Cognitive overload from dense lists degrades task completion rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Fallback Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define three input tiers: Primary (voice), Secondary (touch/tap), Tertiary (keyboard). No interaction should require voice as the only completion path.</statement>
      <rationale>ASR accuracy varies by accent, noise, and microphone quality. A fallback-free voice-only path fails in the real environments where multimodal devices are deployed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Display streaming visual feedback (waveform animation, typing indicator, partial content) during ASR processing and LLM response generation. Silence of more than 1 second during processing feels broken to users.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM + TTS chain latency is 1-3 seconds. Without visual feedback, users repeat their command or abandon the interaction.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Designing dialogue flows on a phone emulator before testing on target hardware</description>
      <reason>Emulators do not reproduce touch + voice timing, screen size constraints, or microphone quality. Test on actual device hardware before usability testing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Writing voice prompts without defining the persona voice first</description>
      <reason>Tone inconsistency across turns destroys user trust in the product's identity. Define persona before writing a single prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/dialogue-turn-schema.json">JSON schema for a single multimodal dialogue turn</reference>
  <reference path="templates/validate-turns.py">Script to validate a dialogue tree for structural completeness</reference>
</text>
