<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-tools-and-gotchas" title="Tools, Services, Agent Workflow, and Gotchas">
  <summary>CLI tools, platform services, recommended agent workflow, and critical failure modes for multimodal VUI projects.</summary>

  <section title="CLI Tools">
    <list>
      <item>gcloud (Google Cloud SDK) — access Dialogflow CX, Speech-to-Text, Text-to-Speech APIs; cloud.google.com/sdk</item>
      <item>aws CLI — Amazon Alexa Skills Kit, Polly TTS, Transcribe; aws.amazon.com/cli</item>
      <item>az CLI — Azure Cognitive Services (Speech SDK, LUIS); learn.microsoft.com/en-us/cli/azure</item>
      <item>ffmpeg — audio processing and format conversion for TTS output validation; ffmpeg.org</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Services">
    <list>
      <item>Dialogflow CX (Google SaaS) — industry standard for multimodal flows; supports rich responses (cards, chips); REST API agent-friendly</item>
      <item>Amazon Alexa Skills Kit — multimodal templates for Echo Show; APL for visual layer; REST/SDK</item>
      <item>Voiceflow (SaaS) — visual dialogue builder with REST API export; good for rapid prototyping</item>
      <item>ElevenLabs (SaaS) — high-quality TTS; agent can generate voice previews for design review; REST API</item>
      <item>Rasa (OSS) — self-hosted NLU + dialogue management; Python API</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>A Claude subagent can generate a multimodal dialogue script (voice_prompt, visual_state, user_actions, fallback) and validate it programmatically. Visual implementation (actual screen layouts, component assembly) requires human designer review.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents cannot validate touch target sizing, card visual hierarchy, or readability at target screen size without a rendering environment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-design-dialogue.txt">Agent prompt: generate multimodal dialogue script for a task and device</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent-generated dialogue defaults to formal register regardless of persona brief</description>
      <reason>Prompt explicitly for the target persona tone (e.g., "casual, helpful, under 12 words per turn"). Without explicit constraints, LLMs default to formal assistant register.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent assumes instant LLM response with no latency design</description>
      <reason>LLM response latency in a live voice chain is user-visible (1-3s). Agents must design streaming visual feedback for every turn involving an LLM call.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent generates a dialogue tree referencing visual card components without verifying they exist in the design system</description>
      <reason>Always cross-reference generated component types against the actual component library. Non-existent components produce broken screens.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent assumes high ASR accuracy in dialogue design</description>
      <reason>ASR accuracy varies significantly by accent and environment. Designs must include disambiguation turns and robust "I didn't understand" fallbacks for all critical paths.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
