<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="multimodal-vui-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for multimodal-vui-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Designing dialogue flows on a phone emulator before testing on target hardware</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Emulators do not reproduce touch + voice timing, screen size constraints, or microphone quality. Test on actual device hardware before usability testing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Writing voice prompts without defining the persona voice first</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tone inconsistency across turns destroys user trust in the product's identity. Define persona before writing a single prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent-generated dialogue defaults to formal register regardless of persona brief</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Prompt explicitly for the target persona tone (e.g., "casual, helpful, under 12 words per turn"). Without explicit constraints, LLMs default to formal assistant register.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent assumes instant LLM response with no latency design</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLM response latency in a live voice chain is user-visible (1-3s). Agents must design streaming visual feedback for every turn involving an LLM call.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates a dialogue tree referencing visual card components without verifying they exist in the design system</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always cross-reference generated component types against the actual component library. Non-existent components produce broken screens.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent assumes high ASR accuracy in dialogue design</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>ASR accuracy varies significantly by accent and environment. Designs must include disambiguation turns and robust "I didn't understand" fallbacks for all critical paths.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
