<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="seo Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for seo as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Disallowing Googlebot or all AI crawlers in robots.txt by accident (e.g. shipped staging robots to prod)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Site disappears from index within days; recovery requires reindex requests and may take weeks</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Relying on client-side rendering without prerendering for crawl-critical pages</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Some crawlers (notably AI bots and Bingbot) execute JavaScript inconsistently; content may be missed</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Stuffing schema with FAQ/HowTo blocks that do not match visible page content</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Google penalizes mismatched structured data; rich results are revoked and trust score drops</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Multiple H1 tags or missing H1, duplicate titles across paginated archives</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Confuses both classic and AI crawlers about page topic, dilutes ranking signals</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>hreflang pairs that are not bidirectional or omit x-default</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Google ignores the cluster and serves wrong-language pages to international users</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Optimizing only for Google and ignoring AI crawlers (no llms.txt, no entity markup, content gated behind login walls)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Lose the growing share of zero-click and AI-assisted traffic; competitors get cited instead</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
