<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Focus Group Process and Moderation">
  <summary>Session structure, group composition rules, moderation techniques, and recruitment requirements for effective focus groups.</summary>

  <section title="Group Composition Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a minimum of 3 focus groups per user segment before treating findings as stable. Themes from 1–2 groups systematically over-represent the first articulate speaker.</statement>
      <rationale>With 1–2 groups, a single dominant voice can define the "consensus". Three groups provide enough comparison to distinguish genuine themes from dominant-speaker artifacts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Size each group at 6–10 participants: homogeneous enough for comfort and candor, diverse enough for range of opinion. Recruit one extra per group to absorb ~20% no-show rate.</statement>
      <rationale>Below 6 participants, the group lacks sufficient dynamic range. Above 10, time per participant drops below the threshold needed for meaningful contribution and moderation becomes crowd management.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Session Structure">
    <p>Standard 90-minute format (60 minutes for online): welcome and ground rules (5 min), warm-up with an easy question (10 min), three core topics with probe ladders (40–60 min), concept reveal (last 25% — no earlier), wrap-up with final thoughts (5 min).</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Reveal stimulus concepts (mockups, prototypes, copy) in the last 25% of the session only. Concept reveal early in a session biases all subsequent discussion.</statement>
      <rationale>Early concept exposure anchors the group's vocabulary and evaluation frame to the specific concept shown, suppressing the organic attitudes and language the session was designed to uncover.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Use written-first exercises before group discussion for key questions. Have every participant write their response individually before speaking.</statement>
      <rationale>Captures unanchored individual opinions before the first articulate speaker anchors the group. Written-first responses reveal dissent that oral-first discussion suppresses.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Moderation Techniques">
    <section title="Managing Dominant Participants">
      <p>Redirect after first contribution: "Thanks — let's hear from others." Direct questions explicitly to quiet participants by name. Sit adjacent to dominant participants (reduces eye contact as reinforcement). Use round-robin for specific questions to equalize contribution.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Probing Deeper">
      <p>Clarification: "What do you mean by...?" Expansion: "Tell me more about that." Reason: "Why do you feel that way?" Contrast: "How does that compare to...?" Example: "Can you give me an example?" These five probes cover 90% of facilitation needs.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Managing Conflict">
      <p>Acknowledge both views without resolution: "It sounds like there are different experiences here — let's explore both perspectives." Never push for consensus in a focus group — disagreement is data.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Recruitment">
    <rule>
      <statement>Stagger participant arrival 5 minutes before start. Avoid pre-session group bonding that lets a leader emerge before the session begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Pre-session social dynamics can establish a group hierarchy that the moderator then fights for 90 minutes. Staggered arrival prevents "lobby leadership" from transferring into the room.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Compensate all participants equally regardless of contribution. Pay-for-talk incentive structures corrupt data by rewarding quantity over quality.</statement>
      <rationale>Variable compensation creates pressure to speak, producing filler contributions from quiet participants and over-contribution from dominant participants chasing the maximum payout.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
