<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-antipatterns-and-analysis" title="Focus Group Antipatterns and Analysis Framework">
  <summary>Groupthink and dominant-voice antipatterns, cross-group analysis framework, agentic coding schema, and LLM gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>One loud voice asserting a position early, followed by apparent group agreement without independent confirmation.</description>
      <reason>Groupthink: participants anchor on the first articulate opinion and suppress dissent. Written-first exercises and direct probing of quiet participants are the only reliable countermeasures.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating a single group's consensus as representative of the segment.</description>
      <reason>One group's "everyone agreed" is one group's dominant voice. Require at minimum 3 groups and cross-group comparison before any finding enters a decision artifact.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Moderator leading questions: "Don't you think this is confusing?" or "Most people find X helpful — do you agree?"</description>
      <reason>Leading questions suppress genuine reaction and replace it with social compliance. All discussion guide questions must be neutral; run a lint pass on the guide before sessions.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Online focus groups running longer than 60 minutes or with more than 6 participants.</description>
      <reason>Online format loses body language, creates speaking-order awkwardness, and induces fatigue faster than in-person. Shorter sessions with smaller groups preserve data quality.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Analysis Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cross-group comparison is mandatory before reporting. For each theme, record which groups expressed it, strength of consensus, and any between-group divergence.</statement>
      <rationale>A theme present in one group but absent in two others is a segment-specific finding, not a general one. Conflating the two produces misleading recommendations.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <p>Reporting structure per finding: what was heard (summary of discussion), representative quote (verbatim, with participant type), implication (what this means for design or strategy).</p>

    <p>Surprise and contradiction log: document moments where findings contradict research goals or prior data. These are often the most valuable outputs of a focus group.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Drive Claude to scaffold the discussion guide from research objectives, generate screener questions, and draft moderator probe ladders. After sessions, hand transcripts to a thematic-analysis agent that produces cross-group comparison tables and verbatim-quote bundles per theme. A separate "skeptic" agent flags: groupthink moments (anchor speaker + rapid agreement sequence), dominant-voice capture (one speaker contributing more than 30% of utterances), and facilitator-leading (questions containing "isn't it", "don't you think", leading negatives).</p>

    <p>Human-in-loop gate: a human researcher must review themes before they enter any decision artifact. LLMs hallucinate speaker quotes and collapse minority views. Explicitly prompt for "minority views" and "contradictions" — without this, LLM theme synthesis systematically suppresses dissent.</p>

    <p>PII handling: redact names, emails, and health detail before passing transcripts to any model. Recordings often contain consent-scope drift — tag and segment accordingly before analysis.</p>

    <reference path="templates/transcript-themer.py">TF-IDF + k-means theme extraction from transcript JSON with speaker attribution</reference>
  </section>
</text>
