<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="focus-groups Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for focus-groups as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>One loud voice asserting a position early, followed by apparent group agreement without independent confirmation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Groupthink: participants anchor on the first articulate opinion and suppress dissent. Written-first exercises and direct probing of quiet participants are the only reliable countermeasures.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating a single group's consensus as representative of the segment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>One group's "everyone agreed" is one group's dominant voice. Require at minimum 3 groups and cross-group comparison before any finding enters a decision artifact.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Moderator leading questions: "Don't you think this is confusing?" or "Most people find X helpful—do you agree?"</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Leading questions suppress genuine reaction and replace it with social compliance. All discussion guide questions must be neutral; run a lint pass on the guide before sessions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Online focus groups running longer than 60 minutes or with more than 6 participants.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Online format loses body language, creates speaking-order awkwardness, and induces fatigue faster than in-person. Shorter sessions with smaller groups preserve data quality.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
