<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="spatial-interaction-patterns Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the spatial-interaction-patterns methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="primary-plus-fallback-modality" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every critical interaction MUST declare one primary modality AND one fallback modality chosen from {hand-direct, hand-raycast, controller, gaze+dwell, voice, gesture}. Fallback MUST be independent of primary.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple visionOS HIG; Meta Quest Interaction Documentation">Single-modality interactions exclude users with motor differences and break on hardware degradation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="state-machine-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each interaction MUST be modelled as a state machine with at least {idle, hover, active, cancel, error} states. Missing cancel/error states are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — XR usability retros Q1 2026">Missing cancel/error states cause stuck UI when input is lost mid-interaction.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="gesture-vocabulary-closed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Custom gestures MUST be drawn from a closed vocabulary documented in the spec. Adding a novel gesture requires explicit listing + discoverability hint.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG visionOS gestures">Novel undocumented gestures fail learnability tests; users default to platform-standard gestures and get stuck.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="platform-parity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Same interaction MUST work on every declared platform with the modality available on that platform. Spec MUST document per-platform divergence explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — cross-platform XR ports">Hidden per-platform divergence creates surprise bugs and review failures.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="voice-as-equal-modality" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Voice MUST be treated as a first-class modality, not a marketing-only feature. Voice intents MUST appear in the spec with same depth as hand interactions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple visionOS HIG; W3C XAUR">Voice is the most reliable accessibility fallback; demoting it to optional excludes motor-impaired users.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
