<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="django-api Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1400" depth="essential">
  <summary>Eight testable rules for Django REST APIs (DRF or Ninja).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-framework-lock" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick DRF OR Ninja at project bootstrap and lock it. Mixing DRF and Ninja in the same Django app is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="drf + django-ninja docs">URL routing, authentication context, and OpenAPI generation diverge between the two stacks. Mixing them multiplies failure surface and produces inconsistent client SDKs.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-thin-views" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Views contain no business logic. The view: parses request via the input serializer/schema → calls a service function → returns the output serializer/schema. Business logic (DB writes beyond ORM saves, side effects, multi-step transactions) lives in `&lt;app&gt;/services.py`.</statement>
      <rationale source="cosmic-python + django-styleguide">Fat views cannot be unit-tested without an HTTP request and cannot be reused from Celery tasks or management commands. Service layer is the only path to consistent business rules.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-serializer-pair" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each resource has separate Create/Update input serializers and a Detail/List output serializer. Never use one serializer for both directions.</statement>
      <rationale source="drf docs + production audits">A single bidirectional serializer mixes write-only with read-only fields, makes permission-based field gating impossible, and causes refactor cascades when one side needs to change.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-no-all-fields" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>`Meta.fields = "__all__"` is FORBIDDEN on every user-facing serializer or schema. List fields explicitly; mark id/uid/created_at/updated_at as read_only_fields.</statement>
      <rationale source="security audit history">Adding a column to the model silently exposes it through the API. Past leaks include password hashes, JWT secrets, and internal foreign-key IDs. Explicit allowlist is the only safe path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-jwt-config" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>simplejwt configured with access token TTL ≤ 15 minutes, refresh token TTL ≤ 7 days, ROTATE_REFRESH_TOKENS=true, BLACKLIST_AFTER_ROTATION=true. Tokens transmitted via HttpOnly cookies (preferred) or Authorization header.</statement>
      <rationale source="djangorestframework-simplejwt + OWASP cheat-sheet">Short access tokens cap the blast radius of a leaked token; rotation + blacklist prevent refresh-token replay. localStorage is XSS-readable; HttpOnly cookies are not.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-isauthenticated-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DEFAULT_PERMISSION_CLASSES = ['rest_framework.permissions.IsAuthenticated']. AllowAny is forbidden as a default; endpoints that must be public opt in explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale source="drf + breach-history">A locked-down default means a developer who forgets to set permissions cannot accidentally ship a public endpoint. The opposite default has caused multiple public-data-leak incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-object-level-perms" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Resource-ownership checks live in `has_object_permission(request, view, obj)`. `has_permission(request, view)` handles only method + auth gating. Skipping object-level checks is forbidden when the resource is user/org-owned.</statement>
      <rationale source="drf permissions docs">has_permission runs before object fetch (cheap, can't see the object). has_object_permission runs after get_object() and is the only correct place for ownership checks. Putting ownership in has_permission either over-fetches or misses the check entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r8-scoped-throttle-cursor-pagination" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Throttle by scope: at minimum `anon`, `user`, `burst` (for write endpoints), `login` (for auth endpoints). List endpoints use cursor pagination ordered by `(-created_at, -id)` when the dataset can grow unbounded; page-number pagination otherwise.</statement>
      <rationale source="drf throttling + cursor-pagination docs">A single anon/user limit can't distinguish a read flood from a login brute-force. Cursor pagination on an unindexed field causes table scans; the -id tie-breaker ensures stable ordering across same-timestamp rows.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
