<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Azure Architecture (Well-Architected + Landing Zones) Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed in real deployments. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="eslz-terraform-still" severity="high">
      <symptom>Greenfield deployment uses the legacy ESLZ Terraform; first AVM-required feature lands and team faces forced migration.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Microsoft AVM docs">Author copied an old reference architecture from before August 2026.</root-cause>
      <fix>Switch to AVM + Bicep. If Terraform mandate exists, use the AVM Terraform port (community-maintained), not ESLZ.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="network-perimeter-only" severity="high">
      <symptom>Hub-spoke deployed but service-to-service uses connection strings + key vault references; one Key Vault breach exposes everything.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Zero Trust docs">Team treated 'network in private subnet' as the security boundary.</root-cause>
      <fix>Add Managed Identity to every service. Enable PIM for human access. Service-principal secrets banned for new workloads.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="no-pim" severity="high">
      <symptom>Privileged role assignments are permanent; compromise of one admin account = full tenant access.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="PIM docs">PIM rollout deferred 'until later'.</root-cause>
      <fix>Convert all Owner / User-Access-Admin role assignments to PIM-eligible. Activation window 8h; require approval.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="no-policy" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Public IPs created across subscriptions; resources in non-allowed regions; encryption disabled silently.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Azure Policy docs">Policy initiative not assigned at MG level.</root-cause>
      <fix>Assign the baseline initiative at platform MG. Verify daily via Policy Compliance Reports.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>