<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Consistency and Standards Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Consistency and Standards. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-internal-and-external" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit checks both internal consistency (within the product) and external consistency (with platform conventions); ignoring either creates a relearning tax.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen Heuristic #4">Internal-only consistency creates platform-divergent products; external-only creates internally chaotic ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-one-action-one-pattern" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every recurring action (save, delete, share) uses one component, one label, one shortcut across the product.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-system practice">Pattern duplication is the most common heuristic-4 violation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-platform-conventions-honoured" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>iOS and Android conventions are honoured by default; intentional divergence requires a written rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG and Material guidelines">Silent divergence confuses users on their primary platform.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-glossary-enforced" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Approved terminology is enforced by linting; ad-hoc synonyms in microcopy are flagged for review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Content-design practice">Synonym drift makes navigation and search unreliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-component-not-pixel" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit references components in the design system, not pixel-level details; component-grain catches drift earlier.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-system practice">Pixel audits are noisy; component audits catch real divergence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-consistency-standards.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
