<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-types" title="Consistency Types and Hierarchy">
  <summary>Five types of consistency and a priority hierarchy for resolving conflicts between convention levels.</summary>

  <section title="Five Consistency Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply all five consistency types: internal, external, visual, functional, and verbal.</statement>
      <rationale>Each type addresses a different failure mode. A product can be visually consistent but verbally inconsistent (Save vs. Submit vs. Done for the same action), causing user confusion despite uniform appearance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Internal — same behavior and appearance within your product (same button style everywhere)</item>
      <item>External — follows platform and industry conventions (standard icons, expected gestures)</item>
      <item>Visual — colors, typography, spacing are uniform (same primary action color everywhere)</item>
      <item>Functional — same gesture or interaction produces same result in every context</item>
      <item>Verbal — one term per concept across all UI copy and documentation</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Consistency Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>When conventions conflict, follow this priority order: industry conventions, then platform conventions, then product family conventions, then internal application conventions.</statement>
      <rationale>Industry and platform conventions represent learned behavior from millions of users across many products. Violating them forces relearning; following them gives users immediate competency via transfer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>iOS: back button always in top-left, swipe from edge to go back, pull to refresh, tab bar at bottom. These platform conventions must be followed even if an internal convention conflicts.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Canonical Verb Set">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick one canonical verb per UX action and use it everywhere; document the glossary and enforce it in design review.</statement>
      <rationale>Users learn terminology from repetition. Mixed terms for the same action (Create / Add / New / Insert) break that learning and force re-decision at every encounter.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Create → Create (not Add, New, Insert). Delete → Delete (not Remove, Trash, Erase). Edit → Edit (not Modify, Change, Update). Save → Save (not Store, Apply, Confirm).</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Page 1: [Save]. Page 2: [Submit]. Page 3: [Done]. Same action, three labels — user must re-evaluate the button meaning each time.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
