<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-patterns" title="Consistency Implementation Patterns">
  <summary>Implementation patterns for visual, functional, and verbal consistency, including design system requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Visual Consistency Standards">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define a design token system before writing component code; retrofitting tokens into existing code costs 5x more than starting with them.</statement>
      <rationale>Without tokens, every developer hardcodes colors, spacing, and typography values, producing a combinatorial explosion of inconsistencies that no audit can fully correct.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Color tokens: primary-action always #0066CC, destructive always #CC0000, success always #00CC66. Spacing: base 8px, margins are multiples (8, 16, 24, 32).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Functional Consistency Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Establish behavior standards for navigation and interaction that hold across every screen, with no exceptions without documentation.</statement>
      <rationale>One inconsistent screen breaks the learned behavior for the whole product. Users encounter the exception, fail, then begin to distrust every interaction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Logo click: always goes to home. Back button: always goes to previous page. Search: always in top area. Single click: select. Double click: open/edit.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Page 1: [Cancel] [Save]. Page 2: [Save] [Cancel]. Button order reversed — user trained by page 1 will accidentally click Save when trying to Cancel.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Design System Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document every component with: visual examples, usage guidelines, do/don't rules, and accessibility notes — not just appearance specs.</statement>
      <rationale>A component spec that shows only appearance is incomplete. Without usage guidelines, developers apply components in wrong contexts, producing functional inconsistencies despite visual uniformity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Typography: font families, sizes, weights (heading hierarchy and body)</item>
      <item>Colors: full palette with usage rules per semantic role</item>
      <item>Spacing: base unit and grid rules</item>
      <item>Buttons: all variants (primary, secondary, destructive, ghost) and all states</item>
      <item>Form elements: inputs, selects, checkboxes, radio buttons</item>
      <item>Navigation: menus, tabs, breadcrumbs</item>
      <item>Feedback: alerts, toasts, error states</item>
      <item>Icons: consistent icon set with label requirements</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Governance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a consistency audit at the start of each major feature cycle, not at the end; fixing mid-feature is cheaper than post-release.</statement>
      <rationale>Design drift accumulates continuously. Post-release consistency fixes require user communication, staged rollouts, and regression testing. Mid-cycle fixes are local and contained.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
