<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Consistency and Standards Examples">
  <summary>Real-world consistency examples, anti-patterns, and agentic audit workflow for terminology and token enforcement.</summary>

  <section title="Good Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>iOS: back button always in top-left, swipe from edge to go back, pull to refresh, tab bar at bottom. Platform conventions held without exception across every iOS app from Apple.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Google products: consistent Material Design across Search, Gmail, Drive, Docs. Same account menu, same search pattern, shared iconography. Users transfer learned behavior between products at zero learning cost.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Bad Examples">
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Page 1: [Save]. Page 2: [Submit]. Page 3: [Done]. Same action, three different labels. User re-evaluates button meaning at every screen instead of acting automatically.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Page 1: [Cancel] [Save]. Page 2: [Save] [Cancel]. Button order reversed. User trained by page 1 clicks Save when intending Cancel — destructive error caused by inconsistency.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow — Terminology Audit">
    <p>Agent reads all UI copy from i18n files, component templates, or scraped live pages. Groups synonym clusters for each UX concept. Produces terminology audit report with recommended canonical term per concept. Output feeds into design system glossary and component documentation update.</p>
    <reference path="templates/consistency-audit.md">Audit template for visual, functional, terminology, and platform compliance</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-audit.txt">LLM prompt for generating a terminology audit from a list of button labels</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow — Token Enforcement">
    <p>Agent scans codebase for hardcoded CSS color and spacing values that bypass design tokens. Generates migration list with file:line references and recommended token replacements. Can be run in CI via ripgrep or stylelint rules.</p>
    <reference path="templates/audit-colors.sh">Bash script for scanning a codebase for hardcoded hex colors outside design tokens</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent proposes canonical terms without platform HIG validation.</description>
      <reason>LLMs pick the most common term in existing usage, which may be a legacy wrong term. Always validate canonical term selection against Apple HIG, Material Design, or Windows Fluent before adopting.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent treats locale-specific idiomatic differences as inconsistencies (Submit in en-US, Send in en-GB).</description>
      <reason>Scope terminology audits to a single locale first. Cross-locale differences may be intentional and correct.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
