<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>
  <section name="shared-services">
    <summary>Shared vs isolated decision matrix for PostgreSQL and Redis, per-project database setup, and Redis DB number allocation.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>For solo developers running 2-5 projects on one VPS, use a single shared PostgreSQL instance with separate databases per project, and a single Redis with separate DB numbers or key prefixes.</statement>
      <rationale>A solo VPS with 30GB RAM can run one well-tuned PostgreSQL instance versus four independent instances, each consuming 500MB+ for shared_buffers alone. Shared services cost less RAM and have a single backup target. The blast radius of a single shared instance failure is acceptable when one developer can fix it immediately.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section name="decision-matrix">
      <list>
        <item>Shared: lower RAM and disk consumption, single backup, simpler monitoring</item>
        <item>Shared: appropriate for solo dev at 2-5 projects with acceptable isolation</item>
        <item>Isolated: required for compliance, customer data segregation, or team environments</item>
        <item>Isolated: appropriate when one project needs a different PostgreSQL major version</item>
        <item>Isolated: appropriate when a single project justifies dedicated hosting costs</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="postgresql-per-project">
      <rule>
        <statement>Create a separate database and a dedicated database user per project; never share credentials between projects.</statement>
        <rationale>Separate users mean a compromised project cannot query another project's database. Separate databases make per-project backups and restores possible without touching other projects.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="sql"><![CDATA[
-- In shared PostgreSQL (docker exec -it nero-postgres psql -U postgres)

-- Create per-project databases
CREATE DATABASE nero;
CREATE DATABASE meetingtax;
CREATE DATABASE eulaguard;

-- Create per-project users (isolated credentials)
CREATE USER nero_user WITH PASSWORD 'generate-with-openssl';
CREATE USER mtax_user WITH PASSWORD 'generate-with-openssl';
CREATE USER eulag_user WITH PASSWORD 'generate-with-openssl';

-- Grant access — each user can only access its own database
GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON DATABASE nero TO nero_user;
GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON DATABASE meetingtax TO mtax_user;
GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON DATABASE eulaguard TO eulag_user;

-- Set ownership so schema creation works
ALTER DATABASE nero OWNER TO nero_user;
ALTER DATABASE meetingtax OWNER TO mtax_user;
ALTER DATABASE eulaguard OWNER TO eulag_user;
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <reference path="templates/add-database.sh">Script: create PostgreSQL database + user in shared Docker instance with auto-generated password</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="redis-isolation">
      <list>
        <item>DB number allocation: DB 0 = project 1, DB 1 = project 1 Celery, DB 2 = project 2, DB 3 = project 3</item>
        <item>Key prefix alternative: nero:cache:*, nero:sessions:*, mtax:cache:* (all in DB 0)</item>
        <item>DB numbers are simpler to reason about; key prefixes are more flexible but require discipline</item>
        <item>Redis ships with 16 databases (0-15) by default — sufficient for up to 8 projects with 2 DBs each</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="resource-planning">
      <list>
        <item>PostgreSQL shared_buffers: set to 25% of RAM allocated to postgres (e.g., 2GB for an 8GB budget)</item>
        <item>Redis maxmemory: set to prevent Redis from consuming all available RAM on cache growth</item>
        <item>Per-service MemoryMax in systemd units: hard limit that triggers OOM kill before system OOM</item>
        <item>Signal to split to a second server: consistent memory pressure above 85% for 7+ days</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>
</text>
