<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="finops-devops-cost-alerts Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for finops-devops-cost-alerts. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every cloud account, subscription, or project with measurable spend MUST have budget alerts at 50%, 75%, 90%, and 100% of monthly budget. The 50% and 75% alerts notify the team lead. The 90% and 100% alerts escalate to engineering leadership. Alerts MUST be "actual spend" for 50-90% and both "actual" and "forecasted" for 100% (catch overspend before it happens).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Four-threshold alerting gives increasing urgency signal: 50% is informational, 75% is attention, 90% is action required, 100% is escalation. Forecasted alerts at 100% give 5-10 days lead time to intervene before actual overspend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enable native anomaly detection on all cloud accounts: AWS Cost Anomaly Detection, Azure Cost Management alerts, GCP Billing budget alerts with threshold type CURRENT_SPEND. Set anomaly alert threshold to 20% above 7-day moving average for services over $500/month. When an anomaly triggers, investigate within 4 hours using the structured investigation checklist: check CloudTrail/Activity Log for resource changes, review usage metrics for the anomalous service, identify the deployment or configuration event that caused it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">4-hour investigation window limits blast radius: a misconfigured data transfer route or forgotten GPU instance costs $50-500/hour. Acting within 4 hours caps overspend; waiting until end-of-month can mean $10k+ surprises.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Establish the following review cadence: daily anomaly alert review (5 min triage), weekly team cost review (use team cost report prompt + actual CUR/billing data), monthly FinOps team analysis (executive summary prompt), quarterly commitment optimization review (Savings Plan/RI prompt), annually strategy and tooling review. Log each review outcome and action items in a shared FinOps tracker.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Regular cadence prevents FinOps from becoming a reactive firefight. Daily triage catches spikes; weekly reviews catch drift; monthly summaries maintain executive visibility; quarterly reviews optimize commitments before terms renew.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
