<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Backlog Hygiene Cron Checklist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Backlog Hygiene Cron Checklist application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="weekly-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The checklist MUST run weekly. Bi-weekly = drift; monthly = the rot returns in full.</statement>
      <rationale source="Habit-formation research">Habit-formation research — anchors Backlog Hygiene Cron Checklist rule `weekly-cadence`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="stale-sweep-90d" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Items idle &gt;90 days with zero new comment/activity MUST be closed or explicitly snoozed with a revisit date. No silent backlog growth.</statement>
      <rationale source="Backlog-rot research">Backlog-rot research — anchors Backlog Hygiene Cron Checklist rule `stale-sweep-90d`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="dup-merge-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Duplicates MUST be merged (winner inherits comments + votes), not just labeled. Living duplicates poison search.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tracker-hygiene practice">Tracker-hygiene practice — anchors Backlog Hygiene Cron Checklist rule `dup-merge-mandatory`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="top-10-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The top 10 MUST be published in the team&apos;s primary channel each week. Private top-10 = no alignment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stakeholder-visibility research">Stakeholder-visibility research — anchors Backlog Hygiene Cron Checklist rule `top-10-published`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="anti-roadmap-refresh" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Anti-roadmap MUST be re-touched (review expirations, add new declines). Stale anti-roadmap = repeat &apos;what about X&apos; questions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice">Anti-decay practice — anchors Backlog Hygiene Cron Checklist rule `anti-roadmap-refresh`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
