<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="LB Session Persistence Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for session-persistence design. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="externalize-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the application can be modified, session state MUST be externalized to Redis / Memcached / DB before any sticky-session config is added. Sticky sessions are a last resort, not a first choice.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloudflare LB design guide + Cache-aside / session-store patterns">Stickiness pins capacity, complicates scaling, and breaks during deploys. External session storage solves the underlying problem with O(1) lookups and lets the LB stay stateless.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="cookie-over-iphash" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When stickiness is required, cookie-based persistence (LB-inserted or app-managed) MUST be the first choice. IP-hash is allowed ONLY when the fleet is static (no autoscaling) AND clients are NOT behind NAT or VPN.</statement>
      <rationale source="HAProxy + Nginx sticky-session docs">Cookies identify the real user regardless of NAT or scale events. IP-hash collapses thousands of NAT users to one backend and breaks every time the fleet scales.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="no-iphash-asg-nat" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>IP-hash MUST NOT be configured in environments with autoscaling enabled OR with clients behind NAT / VPN.</statement>
      <rationale source="HAProxy + Nginx + ASG docs">Adding/removing backends recomputes the hash and re-routes all sessions; corporate NAT collapses many users to one IP, overloading one backend.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="ssl-session-id-fragile" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>SSL-session-ID-based persistence MAY be considered ONLY when cookies and IP-hash are unsuitable (e.g., pure TCP/TLS, no HTTP). It MUST NOT be the default — TLS 1.3 + session resumption tickets weaken its stickiness.</statement>
      <rationale source="TLS 1.3 RFC 8446 + LB SSL ID references">TLS 1.3 prefers tickets over session IDs; modern clients may rotate IDs per resumption. Cookie persistence is more reliable for HTTP.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="sticky-time-bounded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sticky-cookie / sticky-table entries MUST have a bounded TTL (e.g., 1 h) and MUST be invalidated on backend removal (`cookie SRVID insert indirect nocache` in HAProxy, or `sticky cookie ... expires=1h` in Nginx Plus).</statement>
      <rationale source="HAProxy stick-table docs">Unbounded stickiness pins users to a backend forever — even after rolling deploys remove that backend. TTL + invalidate-on-removal restores predictable distribution.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
