<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="lb-session-persistence Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for lb-session-persistence. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before implementing sticky sessions, evaluate whether session state can be moved to a shared store (Redis, Memcached, database). If the answer is yes, implement the shared store and configure the load balancer with NO persistence. Only implement sticky sessions when shared session storage is not feasible within the current delivery scope.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stateless backends scale horizontally without coordination, survive backend failures transparently, and distribute load evenly. Sticky backends tie session health to instance health, create uneven load when session distributions drift, and complicate autoscaling. The operational complexity cost of sticky sessions exceeds the implementation cost of shared session storage for most applications.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prefer cookie-based persistence (LB-inserted cookie) over source-IP persistence. Cookie-based stickiness survives IP changes (mobile clients switching between Wi-Fi and cellular), NAT/VPN clients (multiple users sharing one IP), and autoscaling events where the targeted backend is replaced — the LB can redirect the cookie to an available backend on failure. Source-IP persistence fails on all three of these common scenarios.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Source-IP persistence maps one IP to one backend. Corporate NAT and mobile carriers collapse thousands of users to a handful of IPs, creating massive load imbalance. Autoscaling events add/remove backends, causing all source-IP-hashed clients to redistribute. Cookies embed the specific backend identity and can be remapped gracefully when the targeted backend is unavailable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>LB-inserted session persistence cookies MUST be configured with: Secure flag (HTTPS only), HttpOnly flag (prevent JavaScript access), and SameSite=Strict or SameSite=Lax (prevent cross-site request forgery via the sticky cookie). Cookie TTL should match the expected session duration — not shorter (causes premature redistribution) and not indefinite (prevents load balancing after session end).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without Secure, the persistence cookie is sent over HTTP and can be intercepted, hijacked, or used to force a client to a specific backend (session fixation via cookie injection). Without HttpOnly, XSS attacks can read the cookie and force targeted backend selection. SameSite prevents CSRF attacks that exploit the stickiness property.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For WebSocket backends, use source-IP or cookie-based persistence at the upgrade request level, and configure tunnel timeouts (HAProxy: timeout tunnel 1h) rather than standard HTTP timeouts. WebSocket connections are long-lived; standard HTTP read/write timeouts (30s-60s) will terminate active WebSocket sessions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">WebSocket connections persist for hours or days. Standard load balancer HTTP timeouts are designed for short-lived request/response cycles. A 30-second server timeout terminates an idle-but-active WebSocket connection, causing client disconnection and reconnection storms.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
