<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-team-cycles" title="Linear Team Configuration and Cycles">
  <summary>Rules for Linear team setup, cycle (sprint) workflow, issue properties, and triage process.</summary>

  <section title="Team Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create one Linear Team per product area (e.g., Backend, Frontend, DevOps). Each team gets a short key prefix (BAK, FRD, OPS) that appears in issue IDs (BAK-123). Use Fibonacci point scale [0, 1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13] for estimates — do not customize to a linear scale.</statement>
      <rationale>Fibonacci scale encodes that estimation uncertainty grows with issue size. Linear scales create false precision for large issues.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure cycle duration to 2 weeks starting on Monday with auto-archive enabled. Create 2 upcoming cycles in advance so sprint planning can pull from the backlog into future cycles without manual cycle creation.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-archive on cycle end moves completed issues out of the active view automatically. Pre-creating upcoming cycles enables planning ahead without blocking the current cycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable Triage with no default assignee. All new issues enter Triage before being moved to the team backlog. Triage is a review gate, not a workflow status.</statement>
      <rationale>Without triage, unscoped issues pollute the backlog and distort cycle planning. The triage step enforces minimum issue quality before any work is committed.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Triage Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the triage decision tree in order: Is it valid? No → Close or mark Duplicate. Is it urgent (P0/P1 bug)? Yes → assign to current cycle with High priority immediately. Is it scoped? No → add "Needs Refinement" label and leave in Triage. Yes → move to Backlog with appropriate labels and estimate.</statement>
      <rationale>A consistent triage decision tree prevents issues from stagnating in Triage or bypassing refinement before entering the backlog.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Issue Properties">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every issue committed to a cycle must have: Status set, Priority set, Estimate (Fibonacci points), Assignee, and at least one acceptance criterion in the description. Issues without estimates in a cycle cause velocity calculations to be meaningless.</statement>
      <rationale>Unestimated cycle issues skew velocity metrics — you cannot calculate planned vs. completed points without estimates on all committed issues.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use sub-issues for issues larger than 8 points. An issue with 13+ points is a project-level item that should be broken down into 2-5 sub-issues of 1-5 points each. Assign the parent issue as the project; sub-issues are the cycle work items.</statement>
      <rationale>Large issues that span multiple cycles create incomplete carry-over. Breaking them down enables partial delivery and more accurate cycle planning.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
