<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-projects-integrations" title="Linear Projects, GitHub Integration, and Views">
  <summary>Rules for Linear project structure, GitHub integration, custom views, and cycle management.</summary>

  <section title="Projects and Roadmap">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Projects for multi-cycle initiatives (e.g., "User Authentication Overhaul"). Projects span cycles and track progress across issues. Cycles provide time-boxing within the initiative. Never use cycles as a substitute for projects — a cycle is a time box, a project is a scope.</statement>
      <rationale>Conflating projects and cycles creates confusion: "Sprint 24" and "OAuth Feature" are different abstractions. Projects group related work by feature; cycles group work by time period.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add milestones within projects for key deliverables. Each milestone has a target date and a list of issues that must be Done before the milestone is met. Milestones appear on the roadmap view.</statement>
      <rationale>Milestones provide stakeholder-visible checkpoints without requiring the entire project to be complete. They enable partial delivery communication.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="GitHub Integration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure branch naming pattern: "{username}/{team-prefix}-{issue_number}-{issue_title_slug}". This enables Linear to automatically link branches to issues without manual linking.</statement>
      <rationale>Automatic branch-to-issue linking is the foundation of the code-task traceability workflow. Manual linking is forgotten by developers under deadline pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable PR status sync: pr_opened → "In Review", pr_merged → "Done". Use "Fixes BAK-123" or "Closes BAK-123" in PR descriptions — not "Relates to". Only "Fixes/Closes/Resolves" trigger automatic transitions; "Relates to" does not.</statement>
      <rationale>The keyword matters: "Relates to BAK-123" creates a link but does not transition the issue. Teams using the wrong keyword lose the auto-close workflow.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Views">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create these standard views: "My Work" (filter: assignee=me, status!=done, group by priority), "Team Board" (filter: team=backend, group by status, show estimates), "Bug Triage" (filter: label=bug, status=triage, sort by created), "Release Scope" (filter: project=vX.Y, status!=canceled, group by status). Each developer should mark "My Work" as their default view.</statement>
      <rationale>The default view determines what a developer sees when they open Linear. "My Work" reduces noise by showing only their assigned items.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cycle Management">
    <rule>
      <statement>Freeze cycle scope after Day 2 of the cycle. Scope additions after Day 2 require removing an existing issue of equal or greater points. Track mid-cycle scope additions in the retrospective.</statement>
      <rationale>Mid-cycle scope additions are the primary cause of cycle incompleteness. A points-in/points-out rule maintains commitments without preventing urgent fixes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>At cycle end, review all incomplete issues before moving them to the next cycle. Incomplete issues that are still valid go to the next cycle. Issues that became invalid or were superseded go back to the Backlog or are canceled. Never auto-move all incomplete issues forward without review.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-forwarding incomplete issues without review creates a cycle-over-cycle backlog of stale work that inflates planned velocity without delivering value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Automatically moving all incomplete issues from Cycle N to Cycle N+1 after cycle close.</description>
      <reason>Stale issues accumulate in active cycles, inflating planned velocity. Review filters out issues that are no longer relevant before committing them to the next cycle.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
