<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Onboarding Program Design Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every repeatable onboarding program must satisfy before standing up across role families.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-named-program-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The onboarding program MUST name a single accountable owner (handle + email) and a named manager-of-record per role family. "HR" or "the team" as owner are rejected; orphan programs decay within one quarter.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI / single-throat-to-choke">Plural ownership means no ownership; named accountability is how the program gets revised when hiring velocity, remote ratio, or eNPS data shifts. Without a named owner the program ages out invisibly.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-preboard-day1-30-60-90" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The program MUST cover all five phases: preboarding, Day 1 orientation, 30-day check, 60-day check, 90-day formal review. Programs missing any phase are rejected as gappy; phases collapsed into one ("we just do 90 days") are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="onboarding research / Bauer's 4 Cs">Each phase covers a different anchor (Compliance, Clarification, Culture, Connection) and a missing phase predictably surfaces as a specific failure mode (Day 1 chaos, 30-day disengagement, 90-day surprise underperformance) months later.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-buddy-pairing-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every new hire MUST be paired with a named buddy (peer, not manager) before Day 1, and the pairing recorded in the HRIS. Unpaired hires are surfaced in the weekly onboarding-health report; "implicit" buddies are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="employee experience research / Buffer + Microsoft onboarding studies">Named buddy pairings raise 90-day retention and shorten time-to-productivity; implicit buddies pair only the socially confident hires and silently disadvantage the rest. Recording the pairing makes the gap visible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-survey-cohort-roll-up" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>30-day, 60-day, and 90-day surveys MUST roll up by cohort (hire month) into the quarterly onboarding-health report. Individual survey responses ship to the named owner; cohort roll-ups ship to leadership. Surveys that do not roll up are rejected as ceremonial.</statement>
      <rationale source="feedback-loop discipline">Per-hire surveys with no roll-up generate sympathy but no system change; cohort roll-ups surface the systemic friction points (equipment, doc gaps, manager pattern) that recur and let the program owner allocate fixes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-remote-parity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For remote or hybrid hires, the program MUST ship asynchronous equivalents of every synchronous Day-1 ritual (welcome lunch → async welcome thread; office tour → recorded walkthrough; ad-hoc desk visits → scheduled buddy calls). Remote hires receiving only the in-office program are rejected at audit.</statement>
      <rationale source="remote-first research / GitLab handbook">Remote hires onboarded through in-office rituals report 2x lower belonging at 90 days; explicit async equivalents are the cheap fix and the audit is how the program owner catches drift back to office-default.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies-If preconditions fail OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or to no methodology at all).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application of a methodology produces worse artefacts than no methodology at all because downstream consumers trust the schema and act on bad data. The skip-record makes the non-application traceable so future audits can detect drift.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
