<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Retainer Reactivation Cadence Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules for the 30/60/90-day post-project reactivation cadence used by solo operators converting one-off projects into retainers.</summary>

  <section title="Cadence rules">

    <rule id="r1-three-touches-max" testable="true">
      <statement>The cadence is exactly three touches: day 30, day 60, day 90 (relative to final delivery acceptance). No fourth touch unless the client replies asking for one. Day-zero send-off does not count as a touch.</statement>
      <rationale>Beyond three timed touches the response rate collapses and the relationship damage from being labelled "the one who chases" exceeds the upside of one more email.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-value-not-pitch" testable="true">
      <statement>Each touch leads with a piece of useful information for the client — a relevant article, a metric they can pull from the shipped work, a question they should be asking — before any mention of follow-on engagement. The retainer offer appears in the LAST paragraph of touch 3 only.</statement>
      <rationale>Cold-reactivation pitches that lead with the ask read as CS chase emails and get archived. Value-first touches re-establish the consulting frame that justified the project rate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-named-trigger" testable="true">
      <statement>Touch 2 (day 60) ties to a named, client-specific trigger — a launch they planned, a quarter-end, a competitor move, a metric checkpoint mentioned in the debrief. Generic "just checking in" subject lines are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Named triggers convert at 3–5x the rate of timeline-only check-ins; the email reads as "I remembered your specific situation" rather than as a CRM ping.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-no-cs-language" testable="true">
      <statement>Forbidden phrases in all three touches: "checking in", "touching base", "circling back", "wanted to make sure", "just to follow up". Replace with a concrete observation or question. A touch containing any forbidden phrase must be rewritten before sending.</statement>
      <rationale>CS-template language signals "automated funnel" to a busy founder; the email is filed without reading. Specific language signals a human peer.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-hard-stop-after-90" testable="true">
      <statement>If touch 3 receives no reply within 14 days, the cadence ends. The contact moves to a quarterly "warm dormant" list (one touch per quarter, value-only, no offer). No additional reactivation attempts inside the 90-day window.</statement>
      <rationale>A hard stop prevents the relationship damage of becoming a perpetual chaser and frees attention for fresh pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <code lang="txt"><![CDATA[
Subject: that Q3 onboarding metric we talked about

Hi Maria — saw that LoopFlow just shipped the activation-email change you
mentioned at our debrief. Pulled the numbers on the cohort you sent over: the
day-1 → day-7 retention bump is ~4pp, well outside noise.

The next obvious lever is the day-8 nudge sequence — that's the kind of thing
I'd usually pair with the activation work as a 2-month follow-on. If that's
on your roadmap for Q4 I have capacity from October 6. Two hours of scoping
this week if you want to compare it to your in-house plan.

— A
]]></code>
    <note>Day-60 touch: named trigger (Q3 onboarding metric), value (cohort number), retainer offer in final paragraph, no CS language.</note>
  </example>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Day 30 email: "Hi Maria, just checking in to see if you need anything else! Happy to help with the next phase whenever you're ready."</description>
    <reason>Violates r2 (no value), r3 (no named trigger), r4 (CS language "checking in"). Reads as automation, gets archived.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
