<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Alert Routing — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that keep one human's attention reliable. If alarm fatigue sets in, the entire system is worse than no alerting.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-source-side-filtering-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Noise reduction happens at the SOURCE (Sentry filter rules, Plausible cooldown, mail-bounce thresholds), not downstream. A rule that lets 100 events through and then filters in the digest layer is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="alerting-pipeline best practice; Google SRE Workbook">Downstream filtering still costs the source's quota, still records in logs, still consumes the operator's brain when scrolling. Source filtering eliminates the noise before it enters the pipeline at all.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-digest-by-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default delivery is hourly digest, not per-event. Only specific high-severity classes (uptime down, payment 5xx burst, security event) bypass digest. New event types start in digest until proven worth waking the operator for.</statement>
      <rationale source="cognitive load research; field experience with solo operators">A solo operator can absorb ~5 interruptions/day before quality drops. Digest collapses 50 events into one readable summary; per-event delivery saturates attention by 10am.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-quiet-hours-hard-cut" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quiet hours (22:00-08:00 operator local time, weekends configurable) HARD-cut all alert delivery except a small allow-list (uptime down ≥10min, error-rate spike ≥100/min, security event). Marketing-soft alerts (Plausible traffic anomaly) NEVER break quiet hours.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stanford sleep research; sustainable-pace agile principle">A woken operator is impaired for the following workday and tends to over-react. The hard cut is the difference between solo operation being sustainable and burning out within 6 months. The allow-list captures only true-business-impact events.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-single-pager-channel" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>There is exactly ONE high-priority channel the operator commits to monitor (a named Telegram chat, a specific email folder, or an SMS number). All high-severity alerts route there. Splitting across channels is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="HCI attention research; field experience">Two channels mean checking both; three means checking none reliably. The single-channel rule forces honest prioritisation: only events worth interrupting that channel pass the gate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-escalation-matrix" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every alert has a defined severity (S1 down, S2 degraded, S3 anomaly, S4 informational) AND a delivery rule per severity. Severity is set at the source; the digest pipeline does not invent severity.</statement>
      <rationale source="standard incident-severity practice; auditability">Without explicit severity, the operator re-evaluates every incoming alert. With severity, the pipeline routes deterministically and the operator's energy goes to response, not triage.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Default severity-to-delivery matrix">
    <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
S1 (production down, payment 5xx burst, security incident, data loss risk):
   immediate page to single channel, breaks quiet hours, retry every 10 min
   until acknowledged.

S2 (degraded perf, error-rate spike on non-critical path, expired cert in 7 days):
   immediate notification during work hours (08:00-22:00), digest only at night.

S3 (Plausible anomaly, new error pattern, mail bounce uptick, slow query):
   hourly digest only. Never wakes the operator.

S4 (info, deploy success, weekly reports):
   daily 09:00 digest.
    ]]></code>
  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Quiet-hours hard cut in action">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
03:14 — Sentry detects 8 errors/min on the export endpoint. Severity tagged S3.
03:14 — Pipeline checks quiet hours: 22:00-08:00 → S3 routed to next 09:00 digest only.
03:14 — Pipeline checks allow-list: S3 not on the list → does not break quiet hours.
03:18 — Uptime monitor reports faion.net down. Severity tagged S1.
03:18 — Pipeline checks allow-list: S1 down on list → pages operator immediately.
Outcome: operator wakes once for the real incident; the export errors are
investigated calmly at 09:30 with coffee.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1-r5 all in play; the operator's sleep is preserved AND the real incident is caught.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="The pager-for-everything anti-pattern">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Sentry: per-event email on every error.
Plausible: per-threshold email on every anomaly.
Uptime: SMS on every flap (5 false alerts/day from flaky network).
Outcome: operator turns off all notifications by month 2; misses the
real Sentry data-loss event at month 3.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1 (no source filtering), r2 (no digest), r3 (no quiet hours), r4 (multi-channel mess), r5 (no severity). The system is worse than no alerting.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
