<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="raci-matrix">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Assign RACI (Responsible, Accountable, Consulted, Informed) roles to tasks. Exactly one Accountable per task; cap Consulted at 3-4 to avoid bottlenecks.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>raci</tag>
      <tag>accountability</tag>
      <tag>role-assignment</tag>
      <tag>stakeholder-management</tag>
      <tag>project-planning</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>RACI Matrix</title>

    <summary>Assign one of four roles — Responsible (does the work), Accountable (single decision owner), Consulted (provides input), Informed (notified after) — to each role for each task or deliverable. The rule: exactly one Accountable per task, no exceptions. Multiple Accountables collapse the escalation path and hide conflicts that only sponsors can resolve.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>"I thought you were handling that" and "who approves this?" are symptoms of undefined accountability. RACI makes implicit role assumptions explicit before work begins, so disputes surface in a kickoff meeting rather than at a missed deadline. The Consulted count is a bottleneck detector: more than 3-4 Consulted per task signals that decisions will be slow.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>New project kickoff with multiple roles (PM, dev lead, QA, DevOps, BA, sponsor) and recurring "who decides?" friction.</item>
        <item>Cross-team features where SDD task ownership is ambiguous (backend + frontend + data + ops).</item>
        <item>Vendor/contractor engagements: clarify what client owns vs what contractor delivers.</item>
        <item>Audit/compliance projects (SOC2, ISO 27001) requiring a named Accountable per control.</item>
        <item>Solopreneur engagements with designer, developer, and VA mix.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>One-person solo task with no external stakeholders — overhead with zero return.</item>
        <item>Pure agile teams with collective code ownership and one PO — RACI flattens to "PO=A, team=R" everywhere; use DACI for decisions instead.</item>
        <item>Highly emergent work where roles shift weekly — matrix decays faster than it is updated.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="role-definitions">
      <p>RACI defines four roles per task. Exactly one role must be Accountable; multiple Responsible is acceptable; Consulted must be capped; Informed should be broad.</p>
      <list>
        <item>R — Responsible: does the work; can be multiple people per task.</item>
        <item>A — Accountable: single final decision maker; escalation endpoint; only ONE per task.</item>
        <item>C — Consulted: provides input before decision; two-way communication; keep to minimum.</item>
        <item>I — Informed: notified after decision; one-way communication; be generous with I.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every task must have exactly one Accountable — no shared A, no A/A splits.</statement>
        <rationale>Two Accountables means neither can make a final decision unilaterally. Teams compromise on "A1/A2", which hides the escalation path and requires a third party to break ties at the worst possible moment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every task must have at least one Responsible.</statement>
        <rationale>A task with only A, C, or I has no one committed to doing the actual work. It will be ignored until the Accountable notices it has not been done.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Cap Consulted at 3-4 per task; more than 4 is a bottleneck signal.</statement>
        <rationale>Each Consulted requires a round-trip communication before work proceeds. Beyond 4, the coordination overhead exceeds the value of the input received.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="construction-steps">
      <p>Build the RACI matrix in five steps, starting with work breakdown and ending with a kickoff walkthrough.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Step 1 — List tasks: use WBS work packages or deliverables as rows.</item>
        <item>Step 2 — List roles: use role titles, not individual names — roles survive personnel changes.</item>
        <item>Step 3 — Assign RACI values: start with A (who owns the outcome?), then R (who does the work?), then C and I.</item>
        <item>Step 4 — Validate: check all four rules; do NOT auto-resolve violations — flag for human.</item>
        <item>Step 5 — Walk in kickoff: review cell-by-cell with all roles present; silent acknowledgement is not consent.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Walk the RACI in the kickoff meeting cell-by-cell with all roles present.</statement>
        <rationale>Paper sign-off on a matrix nobody read produces false consensus. Verbal walkthrough surfaces "I didn't know I was Accountable for that" before work begins, not at the deadline.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="validation-rules">
      <p>After initial assignment, validate the matrix against these four rules. Do not silently auto-correct; flag violations to the Accountable for resolution.</p>
      <list>
        <item>No A: assign an Accountable or escalate to sponsor to pick one.</item>
        <item>Multiple A: force a single choice; surface the conflict to the sponsor if roles dispute ownership.</item>
        <item>No R: assign a Responsible party or remove the task from scope.</item>
        <item>All I in a row: the role is not needed for this task — remove from matrix.</item>
        <item>C count &gt; 4: reduce to essential Consulted only; convert remainder to I.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="examples">
      <example type="good" title="Feature Development Team RACI">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Task                | PM | Product | Engineering | Design | QA
--------------------|----|---------|--------------|---------|----|
Define requirements |  C |    A    |      C       |    C   |  I
Create mockups      |  I |    C    |      I       |    R   |  I
Approve design      |  I |    A    |      C       |    R   |  I
Write code          |  I |    C    |      R       |    I   |  I
Code review         |  I |    I    |      A       |    I   |  I
Write tests         |  I |    I    |      C       |    I   |  R
Deploy to staging   |  C |    I    |      R       |    I   |  C
UAT sign-off        |  I |    A    |      I       |    I   |  R
Production deploy   |  A |    I    |      R       |    I   |  C
]]></code>
        <note>Engineering is A for Code Review (code quality) but R for Write Code — Accountable and Responsible are separated to preserve escalation paths.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Solopreneur with Contractors RACI">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Task        | You  | Designer | Developer | VA
------------|------|----------|-----------|----
Vision      | A/R  |    I     |     I     |  I
UI design   |  A   |    R     |     C     |  I
Development |  A   |    C     |     R     |  I
Testing     |  A   |    I     |     C     |  R
Launch      | A/R  |    I     |     I     |  C
]]></code>
        <note>Even with small teams, RACI prevents "I thought you were handling that" disputes with contractors who have parallel commitments.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>A=R for the senior role on every task.</description>
        <reason>LLMs and inexperienced PMs assign A=R to the project lead because charters say "PM owns delivery". The Accountable should not be doing the work — that conflation breaks the escalation chain.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Assigning C to every named role "to be thorough".</description>
        <reason>Every C requires a feedback round-trip. A matrix with 8 Consulted per task is a meeting schedule, not a responsibility model. Set an explicit cap (3-4 C per task) in the generation prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Storing RACI only in Confluence with no version history.</description>
        <reason>Role changes are invisible without diffs. Keep RACI in source control as CSV; generate Markdown view for Confluence. Agents should output a unified diff when updating, not a full rewrite.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent silently fixes violations by reassigning roles without human review.</description>
        <reason>Every role change has organizational implications. Violations must surface to the human Accountable for resolution — the agent flags but never resolves autonomously.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration-guidelines">
      <p>When using agents to generate or validate RACI matrices, follow these practices to ensure the output aligns with organizational reality.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Force-feed the cap "Consulted ≤ 4 per task" into every agent prompt that generates RACI assignments.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents default to including every stakeholder as Consulted because it seems inclusive. Without explicit constraint, every matrix balloons to 8+ Consulted per task, rendering the matrix unusable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Require agents to output a violation report (using raci-validate.py) before finalizing any matrix.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents miss edge cases like "all-I rows" and "A=R antipatterns" if you do not force a structured validation step. The script surfaces violations; the human decides resolution.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>When updating an existing RACI, output a unified diff (CSV row-by-row) showing what changed, not a full rewrite.</statement>
        <rationale>Full rewrites hide which roles changed, making it hard to discuss impacts. Diffs make role changes explicit and traceable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Recommended agent workflow:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Input: WBS (list of tasks), list of roles, candidate RACI assignments from domain knowledge or user sketch.</item>
        <item>Generation: fill matrix with RACI values, capping C ≤ 4 per task.</item>
        <item>Validation: run raci-validate.py; emit violation report if any rule breaks.</item>
        <item>Review: human Accountables sign off on assignments; agents flag but do not auto-correct.</item>
        <item>Output: CSV with version date; Markdown render for Confluence; diff if updating existing matrix.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Use role titles, not names. "Product Manager", not "Alice Smith" — roles survive people.</item>
        <item>Separate A and R when possible. The Accountable owns the decision; the Responsible executes it. Conflating both breaks escalation.</item>
        <item>Keep the matrix alive. Reassign when roles change; version it in source control. Stale matrices breed confusion.</item>
        <item>Walk in kickoff. Silent acknowledgement of a matrix is not consent. Present cell-by-cell; ask "does this match your understanding?"</item>
        <item>Escalate violations to the sponsor, not to the agent. Multiple A or missing A means organizational ambiguity — humans decide the tie-break.</item>
        <item>Use diffs, not rewrites. When updating, emit what changed so teams can discuss impacts.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/raci-matrix.md" purpose="Blank RACI grid template with role columns and task rows"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/raci-validate.py" purpose="CSV validator checking all four rules with per-violation error output"/>
    </scripts>

  </content>
</methodology>
