<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Social Proof Harvest — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every harvest cycle must enforce. These are HARD rules — eagerness for testimonials cannot override them.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Detect MUST be automated: a saved search, alert, or scraper runs at least daily across every channel where the product gets mentioned organically; manual scrolling does not count as detection.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operations reliability">Solo founders skip manual detection in busy weeks and lose months of signal; automation removes the human discipline cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capture MUST record: source_url, author_handle, author_display_name, verbatim_quote, captured_at, channel; quotes paraphrased by the founder are rejected at capture time.</statement>
      <rationale source="Truth-in-testimonial / FTC endorsement guidelines 16 CFR §255">Paraphrased quotes attributed to a real person create legal exposure and erode trust on inspection; verbatim is the only defensible form.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Consent MUST be explicit and logged: a permission request is sent to the author with the exact quote and the exact publication context; the reply ("yes, you may publish") is stored with timestamp before status flips to `approved`.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 6/7 consent requirements + general personality-rights doctrine">Public visibility on a personal handle is not consent to commercial use; storing the reply is the only defense against a takedown demand.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Publish MUST cite the source: every wall entry links back to the original public mention (tweet URL, post URL, comment URL); broken or deleted source URLs trigger a quarterly "stale-source" review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Credibility / verifiability of social proof">Visitors who can click through and verify trust the quote 4–6x more than uncited blurbs; broken links erode the same trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The quote DB MUST be the single source-of-truth: landing page, sales deck, email signatures, and outbound ALL pull from the same record id; duplicating quotes into multiple stores is prohibited.</statement>
      <rationale source="DRY content management">Diverging copies create stale or conflicting wording and turn one consent record into many ambiguous claims.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Anchored harvest entry">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
quote_id: q_2026_0142
source_url: https://twitter.com/devjane/status/1234567890
author_handle: "@devjane"
author_display_name: "Jane R."
verbatim_quote: "Cut my deploy time from 12 minutes to 90 seconds with @ourproduct."
captured_at: 2026-05-18T09:14:00Z
channel: twitter
consent:
  requested_at: 2026-05-18T10:02:00Z
  granted_at: 2026-05-18T16:41:00Z
  granted_via: dm
status: approved
publish:
  surfaces: [wall, landing-hero-rotation]
]]></code>
      <note>Verbatim, sourced, consented with timestamp, single record drives multiple surfaces.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Un-anchored capture">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Someone on Twitter said our deploys are super fast. Pasted into the landing page.
]]></code>
      <note>No source URL, no author identity, no consent, no record id. Unusable and exposed.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="../growth-customer-testimonials/" />
  </see-also>
</text>
