<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-planning" title="Resource Planning: Roster, Utilisation, Skills, Ramp">
  <summary>Rules for building a YAML roster in git, setting utilisation targets, maintaining the skill matrix, and accounting for ramp time and vacation.</summary>

  <section title="Roster and Allocation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store allocations in git as resources/roster.yaml and resources/allocations.yaml, not in spreadsheets. Git diffs explain why allocations changed; spreadsheets erase history.</statement>
      <rationale>Allocation decisions are context-dependent; understanding why a decision was made requires the diff, not just the current state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Plan to 70% utilisation, not 100%. Reserve 30% per person per week for meetings, unplanned support, learning, and context switching. Flag any allocation exceeding 85% as RED immediately.</statement>
      <rationale>100% allocation means any unplanned event — a sick day, an urgent bug, a stakeholder request — causes a miss. 70% is the empirically sustainable peak for knowledge workers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Rate cards live in 1Password or equivalent secrets store, referenced by ID only in the roster. Never commit monetary rates to the repo.</statement>
      <rationale>Rate cards are commercially sensitive and, in some jurisdictions, legally protected compensation data. Committing them to git creates uncontrolled disclosure risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skill Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Skill matrix entries are dated, self-asserted, and peer-endorsed. Refresh quarterly. Agents must read skills only from the roster YAML — never infer skills from job titles.</statement>
      <rationale>Job titles are unreliable skill proxies. An agent that assumes "Senior Engineer" knows Kubernetes and assigns them a Kubernetes task without checking the roster creates a skill gap that surfaces at the worst time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cross-train pairs for any single point of failure: one person who is the only team member knowing a critical system is a staffing risk. Escalate to the resource manager within one sprint of identifying it.</statement>
      <rationale>SPOF skills create delivery risk that materialises on the one week the critical person is unavailable. Cross-training is the only durable mitigation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Ramp Time and Vacation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Account for ramp time explicitly: a new joiner is 30–50% productive for 4–8 weeks. Under-counting ramp time is a systematic cause of the first milestone slip.</statement>
      <rationale>Ramp time is predictable and consistent across roles, yet it is omitted from resource plans in the majority of projects. Treating a new hire as full capacity from day one is a planning error.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock in PTO and public holidays before committing to milestone dates. Vacation calendars are inputs to the schedule, not afterthoughts.</statement>
      <rationale>Holiday and vacation conflicts discovered after milestone commitments require scope reduction or timeline extension. Discovery before commitment costs a calendar API call.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
