<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-leveling" title="Resource Leveling, Morale Constraints, Contractor Linkage">
  <summary>Techniques for resolving allocation conflicts without causing morale damage, rules for contractor boundary enforcement, and resource management antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Leveling Techniques">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use peak-trough leveling: move non-critical-path tasks into under-utilised weeks before adding resources or extending the timeline. Analyse the critical path first; do not level critical tasks.</statement>
      <rationale>Adding resources to critical tasks has limited ROI (Brook's Law). Non-critical tasks have schedule float that can absorb leveling moves without impacting the delivery date.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap reassignments per person to two per quarter. More frequent reassignments produce context-switching overhead and morale damage that the utilisation math does not capture.</statement>
      <rationale>Resource leveling algorithms optimise utilisation numbers, not morale. A resource who is moved three times in two months is a churn and attrition risk regardless of what the matrix shows.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Contractor Linkage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never allocate a contractor beyond the hours in their signed SOW. Agent must refuse allocation that exceeds the SOW ceiling and flag it to procurement for a change order.</statement>
      <rationale>Over-allocating a contractor without a change order creates an unenforceable claim and a compliance risk if the contractor is classified as a de-facto employee in some jurisdictions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Timezone overlap matters more than raw hours for collaboration-heavy work. Surface timezone_overlap_hours in skill-matching output; minimum 2 hours of business-hour overlap required for daily collaboration.</statement>
      <rationale>A resource in a non-overlapping timezone can provide async output but not synchronous collaboration. Treating them as equivalent to a co-located resource produces daily coordination failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent over-allocates top performers because they have the highest skill scores.</description>
      <reason>Hard-cap any resource at 85% in the allocation engine. Top performers are also the highest attrition risk when consistently overloaded.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Static resource plans not reconciled against actuals for more than two weeks.</description>
      <reason>Allocation plans go stale in 2–4 weeks. An unreconciled plan produces over-confidence in capacity estimates that do not reflect real availability.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skill matching by free-text similarity rather than explicit skill keys from roster.yaml.</description>
      <reason>Embedding-based skill matching from job descriptions produces plausible but unverified matches. Only roster.yaml is authoritative; reject any match not grounded in a roster entry.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Privacy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Skill matrices and performance ratings are PII and commercially sensitive. Require a DPA before sending roster data to a third-party model. Never auto-publish utilisation reports outside the resource management owner.</statement>
      <rationale>In many EU jurisdictions, skill assessments and performance data require explicit legal basis for processing. Uncontrolled publication violates GDPR and damages employee trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
