<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-structure" title="Story Map Structure: Backbone, Walking Skeleton, and Release Slices">
  <summary>Defines the three structural layers of a user story map and the rules that govern each.</summary>

  <section title="Backbone">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use verb phrases for backbone activities; arrange left-to-right in user journey order; limit to 5-10 items.</statement>
      <rationale>Noun-only labels ("Project") lose the action context the team needs. More than 10 activities collapses into a Gantt chart and loses strategic clarity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>E-commerce backbone: Browse Products → View Product → Add to Cart → Checkout → Receive Order</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Backbone labelled "Products, Cart, Payment, Order" — nouns only, no journey verb.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="User Tasks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place user tasks vertically under each backbone activity, ordered top-to-bottom by priority within that column. Every task must be user-observable, not an implementation step.</statement>
      <rationale>Vertical position encodes priority within an activity. "Authenticate user" is an implementation step; "Sign in with email" is user-observable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include at least one error or recovery task per backbone column.</statement>
      <rationale>Happy-path-only maps under-deliver; error flows are discovered after launch rather than before.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Walking Skeleton">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify exactly one task per backbone activity for the walking skeleton. The skeleton must span every column — gaps mean the journey cannot be completed end-to-end.</statement>
      <rationale>A skeleton missing one column produces an MVP that fails at that step. Completeness is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Walking skeleton for e-commerce: See product list | See details | Add item | Enter payment | Get confirmation — one task per activity, all five columns covered.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Walking skeleton silently dropped because "nothing felt minimal" for one activity.</description>
      <reason>Every activity exists because the user must complete it. If no task is minimal there, the activity itself is wrong.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Release Slices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Draw horizontal lines grouping tasks into shippable releases. Each slice must deliver standalone user value — it is not just a list of features.</statement>
      <rationale>A slice that depends on a later slice for value is not a release; it is a phase. Phases are not shippable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit to 3-5 release slices. More than 5 destroys release thinking and turns the map into a roadmap.</statement>
      <rationale>Beyond 5 slices the distinction between releases blurs and planning reverts to feature-list mode.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Release 1 for e-commerce: Filter by category | See images | Update quantity | Enter shipping | Email receipt — one thin horizontal slice per activity, all columns covered.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-process.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/story-map.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
