<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Story Mapping Process: Five Steps">
  <summary>Step-by-step process for building a story map, from framing the journey to slicing releases, with failure modes per step.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Frame the Journey">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before writing any activity, define: who is the user, what is their big goal, and where does the journey start and end. Input persona brief before mapping.</statement>
      <rationale>Without persona context, agents and workshop participants produce generic backbones ("View", "Browse", "Manage") that fit nothing specific.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Build the Backbone">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build the backbone first, collaboratively, with at least one user-voice input (interview notes count). Get backbone approval before generating tasks — backbone errors propagate to every task under them.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping the backbone workshop and jumping to tasks is the number-one failure mode in story mapping.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Backbone drifts toward implementation steps: "Authenticate user", "Query database".</description>
      <reason>Backbone activities must be user-observable life events, not system operations.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Add Tasks">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each activity, write every task the user does there. Arrange vertically by priority. Include at least one error/recovery/abandonment path per column.</statement>
      <rationale>Happy-path-only maps surface incomplete releases; error paths discovered post-launch cost more to fix.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap at 5 tasks per column before requiring justification. More than 5 per column signals the activity is too broad and should be split.</statement>
      <rationale>Uncapped task generation produces 50+ cards; column density above 5 degrades the visual signal the map is meant to provide.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Identify the Walking Skeleton">
    <rule>
      <statement>Draw a line after the single minimum task in each column. Verify the line crosses every column. Name the skeleton explicitly ("walking_skeleton") in any structured data format.</statement>
      <rationale>An unnamed skeleton gets ignored during release planning. Explicit naming forces the team to acknowledge it as the MVP boundary.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Slice Releases">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name each release with a value statement, not a version number. Validate: "Is this shippable to users as-is?" If no, the slice is too thin or incomplete.</statement>
      <rationale>Version numbers carry no product meaning; value statements ("Users can search and buy") communicate scope to all stakeholders.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store the map as structured data (JSON/YAML), not only as a whiteboard image. Agents and humans both need the map queryable.</statement>
      <rationale>Whiteboard images cannot be updated from analytics data or referenced by downstream tools (backlog importers, sprint planners).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Release named "Customers can complete a purchase end-to-end" — value statement. Clear scope for all stakeholders.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Release named "v1.2" — carries no product meaning; team must read the task list to understand scope.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-structure.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/story-map.md"/>
    <link path="templates/validate-story-map.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
