<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-board-setup" title="GitLab Boards — Board Setup and Label Taxonomy">
  <summary>Board types, scoped label taxonomy, configuration rules, WIP limits, and iteration cadence for GitLab Issue Boards.</summary>

  <section title="Board Types">
    <p>GitLab offers project-level boards (single repo) and group-level boards (cross-project visibility, Premium+). Multiple boards per project are available on Premium+.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Sprint Board — filtered to current iteration; tracks committed work in progress.</item>
      <item>Bug Triage Board — filtered to type::bug and open issues; supports daily triage.</item>
      <item>Release Board — filtered to a milestone; tracks release readiness.</item>
      <item>Tech Debt Board — filtered to type::tech-debt; makes invisible debt visible.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use one canonical workflow board per team; additional boards are filtered views, not parallel state machines.</statement>
      <rationale>Parallel state machines create conflicting states — an issue can appear "done" on one board and "in-progress" on another. One board, many views.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoped Label Taxonomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Encode all state machines as scoped labels using the namespace::value syntax; keep active label count at or below 20.</statement>
      <rationale>Scoped labels enforce mutual exclusivity — GitLab allows only one label per namespace per issue, preventing conflicting states (e.g., two workflow:: labels).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/labels.yaml">Full label taxonomy ready to apply via gitlabform</reference>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Minimum viable scoped label set:</note>
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
workflow:
  - workflow::backlog
  - workflow::ready
  - workflow::in-progress
  - workflow::review
  - workflow::done

priority:
  - priority::critical
  - priority::high
  - priority::medium
  - priority::low

type:
  - type::feature
  - type::bug
  - type::tech-debt
  - type::docs
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using flat labels (no :: separator) for workflow states.</description>
      <reason>Flat labels allow multiple conflicting workflow labels simultaneously; the board becomes unreliable as a state representation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="WIP Limits and Iterations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set WIP limits per column (Premium) and enforce them at card entry — block rather than warn.</statement>
      <rationale>WIP limits are the primary mechanism to surface bottlenecks. Warning-only enforcement is ignored under delivery pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure iteration cadence at the group level so all teams share the same sprint boundary.</statement>
      <rationale>Group-level cadence enables cross-team planning in iteration reports; misaligned boundaries make portfolio-level rollups meaningless.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Auto-close via "Closes #N" only on default-branch merges; for feature-branch flows use deploy-job notifications.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-close depends on the default branch target; merges to feature branches will not close issues, leaving board state stale.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Issue Weight Convention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use weight consistently: 0 = unestimated, 1-2 = trivial, 3-5 = standard, 8-13 = large (must break down), above 13 = epic candidate.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing weight semantics (story points vs. hours vs. priority) destroys iteration capacity planning.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
