<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gitlab-boards Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gitlab-boards. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use one canonical workflow board per team; additional boards are filtered views, not parallel state machines.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Parallel state machines create conflicting states — an issue can appear "done" on one board and "in-progress" on another. One board, many views.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Encode all state machines as scoped labels using the namespace::value syntax; keep active label count at or below 20.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Scoped labels enforce mutual exclusivity — GitLab allows only one label per namespace per issue, preventing conflicting states (e.g., two workflow:: labels).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set WIP limits per column (Premium) and enforce them at card entry — block rather than warn.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">WIP limits are the primary mechanism to surface bottlenecks. Warning-only enforcement is ignored under delivery pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Configure iteration cadence at the group level so all teams share the same sprint boundary.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Group-level cadence enables cross-team planning in iteration reports; misaligned boundaries make portfolio-level rollups meaningless.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Auto-close via "Closes #N" only on default-branch merges; for feature-branch flows use deploy-job notifications.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Auto-close depends on the default branch target; merges to feature branches will not close issues, leaving board state stale.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use weight consistently: 0 = unestimated, 1-2 = trivial, 3-5 = standard, 8-13 = large (must break down), above 13 = epic candidate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixing weight semantics (story points vs. hours vs. priority) destroys iteration capacity planning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Encode the workflow as scoped labels in a YAML file (.gitlab/labels.yaml) applied via a CI job — never configure labels manually at scale.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Manual label configuration drifts across projects in a group; idempotent CI application (via gitlabform) keeps all projects consistent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep label count at or below 20 active labels; archive deprecated labels rather than reusing or deleting.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Reusing deprecated labels corrupts history — old issues inherit the new meaning. Archiving preserves the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tie every MR to an issue; every closed issue must reference an MR (except docs-only).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Traceability from requirement to code change is the primary compliance and debugging artifact in regulated environments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Roadmaps + Epics for portfolio (Premium+); keep epics at 3 levels maximum.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Deep nesting (4+ levels) makes roadmap rendering unreadable and cross-team planning impossible without a dedicated tool.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
