<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GitLab Issue Boards Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding GitLab Issue Boards. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="scoped-labels-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Status states MUST be modelled with GitLab scoped labels (`status::`). Free-form labels for status are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitLab Premium docs — Scoped labels">Free-form status labels collide; scoped labels are mutually exclusive within their scope, matching kanban semantics.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="project-scoped-token" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agents MUST authenticate via project-scoped tokens with `api` + `read_repository` minimum. Group or instance tokens forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitLab security docs">Group/instance tokens are over-privileged; project-scoped tokens contain blast radius if leaked.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="milestone-cadence-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Milestones MUST follow a fixed cadence (weekly / biweekly / monthly). Ad-hoc milestone creation forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — GitLab board config audit">Ad-hoc milestones produce inconsistent velocity metrics; fixed cadence makes comparison possible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="board-list-from-scoped-label" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each board list MUST be backed by a single scoped-label value. Free-form lists forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitLab board configuration docs">Free-form lists drift; scoped-label-backed lists stay synchronised with status taxonomy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="iteration-or-milestone-not-both" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each issue MUST be assigned to EITHER an iteration OR a milestone, not both. Dual assignment creates conflicting reports.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitLab iterations docs">Iteration + milestone double-counting inflates velocity and confuses reporting tools.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for GitLab Issue Boards fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying GitLab Issue Boards outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
