<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-workflow" title="GitLab Boards — Agentic Workflow and Automation">
  <summary>How to drive GitLab boards through CI and subagents, including label-curator and triage-router patterns and their failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Agentic Architecture">
    <rule>
      <statement>Encode the workflow as scoped labels in a YAML file (.gitlab/labels.yaml) applied via a CI job — never configure labels manually at scale.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual label configuration drifts across projects in a group; idempotent CI application (via gitlabform) keeps all projects consistent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>CI moves issues across columns on MR events: open → review, merge → closed. Never let agents close issues without an MR or human approval — closure is a decision-authority boundary.</p>
    <reference path="templates/stale-in-progress.py">Audit script for issues idle in workflow::in-progress beyond N days</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Recommended Subagents">
    <list>
      <item>label-curator-agent (haiku): nightly walk over issues; flags issues with multiple workflow:: labels, missing type::, stale workflow::in-progress older than 14 days.</item>
      <item>triage-router-agent (sonnet): incoming issues from Service Desk and external bots — applies type:: + workflow::triage, suggests assignee from CODEOWNERS.</item>
      <item>iteration-planner-agent (sonnet): converts sprint planning template into an actual planning issue with capacity table from team availability.</item>
      <item>mr-board-mover-agent (haiku): runs in CI on MR events; flips workflow::in-progress to workflow::review based on MR state. Idempotent.</item>
      <item>dependency-graph-agent (sonnet): walks /blocks and /relate links, produces Mermaid dependency graph for sprint planning.</item>
      <item>password-scrubber-agent: runs over issue descriptions, comments, and Service Desk emails before any external sharing.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Triage-Router Prompt Pattern">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Two-step: ingest issue → emit structured label assignment:</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are the triage-router agent. Inputs:
1. New issue payload (title, description, attachments).
2. Allowed labels (from .gitlab/labels.yaml).
3. CODEOWNERS map (path → maintainer).

Emit STRICT JSON:
{ "labels": ["type::<...>", "priority::<...>", "workflow::triage"],
  "milestone": <slug or null>,
  "weight": <int 0-13>,
  "assignee_suggestion": "@<username>",
  "rationale": "<= 2 sentences",
  "needs_human_review": true|false }

Rules: never apply more than one label per scoped namespace.
weight=0 means unestimated.
needs_human_review=true if priority::critical, weight>=13, or no clear type.
Quote-pick the rationale from the issue body where possible.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent applies two workflow:: labels; GitLab keeps the last one silently.</description>
      <reason>Scoped-label mutual exclusivity is enforced server-side by keeping the last label applied; the agent believes both stuck. Always verify with a read-after-write API call.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent generates an MR body with "Closes #999" without verifying the issue exists.</description>
      <reason>Auto-close hallucination: the referenced issue may not exist or may be in a different project; validate IDs before committing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent uses REST PUT /issues to trigger Quick Actions like /spend or /assign.</description>
      <reason>Quick Actions only execute when submitted through the notes API or the issue body on creation/update — not via field updates in REST PUT.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Notification spam: bots comment on every state change.</description>
      <reason>Thread updates drown teams; prefer updating the existing thread rather than posting new comments per transition.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <list>
      <item>Mandatory human checkpoints: label taxonomy changes, milestone closure, iteration cadence changes, board deletion, mass relabel, Service Desk priority::critical auto-assignment.</item>
      <item>Service Desk emails are PII; scrub before any external model call.</item>
      <item>Long-context drift: agents reading 1,000 issues at once lose track — page by board column or by label.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
