<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-tools-and-workflow" title="Generative UI Tools and Generation Workflow">
  <summary>Tool landscape, generation loop, quality rules, and human/agent responsibility split for generative UI design.</summary>

  <section title="Tool Landscape">
    <list>
      <item>v0 by Vercel — REST API for component generation; output is React/TSX; agent-callable</item>
      <item>Claude Artifacts — native in-context generation; interactive HTML/React; agent-callable</item>
      <item>Galileo AI — browser-only; no public API; image-based output (not editable component trees)</item>
      <item>Uizard — browser-based; no headless API; image-based output</item>
      <item>Relume — Figma plugin + browser; no API; optimized for marketing/SaaS site structure</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Generation Loop">
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate 3–5 variants per brief, not 1. Single-variant generation anchors the team too early and forecloses design space exploration.</statement>
      <rationale>The purpose of generative UI is to expand the option space cheaply. A single variant is no better than having a designer start from scratch — it still anchors the conversation to one direction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat generated UI as a zero-cost rough draft. Critique aggressively; accept nothing without review.</statement>
      <rationale>Generated output that is accepted without critique carries forward AI defaults (generic aesthetics, missing accessibility, deprecated patterns) into production.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Correct generation loop:</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1. Agent generates 3-5 variants (parallel calls, different style constraints)
2. Human selects variants, marks off-brand elements, flags a11y issues
3. Agent refines selected variant based on critique notes
4. Human runs axe-cli / accessibility audit on refined output
5. Human verifies against brand style guide
6. Approved → isolated branch; marked with AI-generated comment
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run axe-cli or equivalent on all generated HTML before presenting to stakeholders.</statement>
      <rationale>Generated UIs that look accessible routinely have broken focus order, missing live regions, and contrast failures. Automated check is mandatory before any stakeholder presentation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin design tokens explicitly in every generation prompt. Without them, AI defaults to generic Bootstrap-like aesthetics.</statement>
      <rationale>AI generation models have no brand knowledge; explicit token references (color names, type scale, spacing) are the only way to anchor output to the design system.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep generated components isolated from the production codebase until manually reviewed and refactored.</statement>
      <rationale>Generated code frequently uses deprecated APIs, missing responsive breakpoints, and incorrect composition patterns; direct merge without review introduces technical debt.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark all AI-generated components with a comment: "AI-generated — review before production".</statement>
      <rationale>Unmarked AI-generated code becomes invisible in the codebase; marking enables future audits and prevents accidental promotion to production.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using Galileo or Uizard output as Figma-import-ready components.</description>
      <reason>Both produce image-based outputs, not editable component trees; importing into Figma requires manual rebuild from scratch.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using generative UI for design system contributions.</description>
      <reason>Generated components bypass token governance, variant structure, and composition rules; they require significant rework to meet design system standards.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
