<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="generative-ui-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for generative-ui-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Accepting the first generated variant without comparing to alternatives.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Single-variant acceptance forecloses the design space early, defeating the purpose of generative UI for exploration.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Merging generated output directly into production without manual review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generated code frequently contains API hallucinations, missing accessibility attributes, and composition violations that require manual cleanup.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Using Galileo or Uizard output as Figma-import-ready components.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Both produce image-based outputs, not editable component trees; importing into Figma requires manual rebuild from scratch.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Using generative UI for design system contributions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generated components bypass token governance, variant structure, and composition rules; they require significant rework to meet design system standards.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Expecting AI-generated code to converge on novel interaction models.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents generating UI converge on modal patterns (cards, hero banners, nav bars) — novel interaction models are underrepresented in training data and rarely generated.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Assuming brand consistency will hold across multiple generation runs without anchoring.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Brand consistency degrades with each iteration; AI drifts from style guide without explicit anchoring via design tokens or reference images in prompts.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates code with library APIs that don't exist or are deprecated.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs hallucinate library APIs, especially for newer React versions and niche component libraries; always test generated code in a sandbox before accepting.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating WCAG compliance prompts as sufficient for accessible output.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generated code that targets WCAG compliance often has broken focus order and missing live regions; axe-cli audit is mandatory regardless of prompt instructions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Using "modern" or "clean" as style constraints without concrete references.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Abstract style terms mean different things every run; add specific style references (typography system, component library names, example URLs) for reproducible output.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Accepting agent-generated complex component trees without checking against design system composition rules.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents propose component nesting that violates design system composition rules silently; the output looks correct but breaks at the system level.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
