<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Reply Guy Protocol Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5+ testable rules every Reply Guy Protocol application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-preconditions-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every step starts with the precondition needed (state, alert, ticket, signal). If the precondition is absent, the step is skipped, not partly executed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Workbook, chapter on runbooks; aviation checklist design">Runbooks executed mid-shift fail when steps are run on the wrong system state. Preconditions are the cheap guard that prevents an emergency from becoming a second emergency.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-named-actor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each action names the actor (role + system) and the artefact produced. 'Notify stakeholders' is rejected; 'on-call posts in #incident with template X' is accepted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Etsy DebriefingFacilitatorGuide; PagerDuty incident-response docs">Vague actors are why steps get dropped under stress. Naming both the actor and the artefact makes ownership and verification unambiguous.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-rollback-or-stop" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every action with side-effects on production carries a documented rollback or a hard 'STOP and escalate' branch. No silent failure paths.</statement>
      <rationale source="Resilience-engineering literature (Allspaw); chaos-engineering practice">Runbooks evolve in production. A step without a rollback gets the engineer stuck mid-procedure and forces ad-hoc decisions exactly when judgment is worst.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-timeboxed-checkpoints" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The runbook publishes a wall-clock budget per phase. A phase exceeding budget triggers escalation, not 'try harder'.</statement>
      <rationale source="SRE incident-management practice; ITIL change windows">Without timeboxes, an early step that misfires consumes the whole window and the incident gets a second alarm. Timeboxes are how an individual operator stays inside the team's response SLO.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-postaction-record" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After execution, the runbook produces a structured record (start_ts, end_ts, branches taken, exceptions, artefacts) committed to the postmortem feeder folder.</statement>
      <rationale source="Blameless-postmortem practice (Allspaw); learning-organisation theory">Runbooks without records cannot improve. The recorded run is what feeds the next refinement and the postmortem.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-28 chunk-02 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
