<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<domains version="1.0" generated="2026-05-22" canonical="20">
  <description>L1 index of methodology domains. The retriever reads this first, picks 1-3 candidate domains, then reads only those domains' INDEX.xml.</description>
  <domain id="ai-agents" count="101">
    <scope>AI agents and agentic systems - agent architectures, tool use, multi-agent orchestration, memory, planning, evaluation, and production-grade agent patterns.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/ai-agents/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="ai-core" count="82">
    <scope>Core AI / ML foundations - model selection, prompt engineering basics, embeddings, RAG fundamentals, LLM integration patterns, and the underlying primitives that AI-powered features are built from.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/ai-core/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="architecture" count="59">
    <scope>Software architecture - ADRs, API gateway patterns, service boundaries, reversibility tagging, observability design, and other software-architect decisions that shape long-lived systems.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="ba" count="118">
    <scope>Business analysis - requirements elicitation, process modeling, stakeholder management, KPI design, change-request impact analysis, BA core practice and modeling techniques bridging product strategy and delivery.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/ba/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="backend" count="161">
    <scope>Backend engineering - APIs, services, databases, server-side patterns across Python/Node/Java/Rails/PHP/.NET, including auth, caching, queues, background work, contract-first design and enterprise framework patterns.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/backend/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="claude-code" count="9">
    <scope>Claude Code authoring stack - agents, commands, hooks, skills, MCP servers, and project documentation conventions for building reliable agentic tooling on top of Claude.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/claude-code/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="comms" count="26">
    <scope>Communication craft for solopreneurs and small agencies - stakeholder updates, executive demos, contractor and freelancer scripts, negotiation, storytelling, difficult conversations, and customer-facing testimonials.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/comms/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="dev" count="374">
    <scope>Software engineering practice - coding craft, code quality, testing, devtools. The dev bucket covers anything a software developer does day-to-day.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/dev/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="frontend" count="132">
    <scope>Frontend and UI engineering - design systems, component libraries, accessibility, performance, state management, build tooling, and UI/UX implementation patterns for web and spatial interfaces.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="hr" count="15">
    <scope>HR and recruiting practice - full-cycle hiring, structured interview design, STAR method, candidate experience, employer branding, EVP, 30-60-90 onboarding plans, and retention compliance.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/hr/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="infra" count="293">
    <scope>Infrastructure and platform engineering - DevOps, CI/CD pipelines, observability, server craft, cloud, networking, deploy and operate everything that runs the code in production.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/infra/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="marketing" count="276">
    <scope>Marketing practice - content, SEO, growth, PPC, SMM, CRO, GTM. Everything that drives demand and converts it into customers.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/marketing/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="ml-engineering" count="195">
    <scope>Applied ML / AI engineering practice - building, evaluating, deploying, and operating LLM and ML systems: RAG pipelines, agentic patterns, eval-driven development, fine-tuning, prompt engineering, model rollout and MLOps for production AI features.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="pm" count="324">
    <scope>Product + project management - planning, prioritization, stakeholder management, agile/traditional ceremonies, ops, KPIs and roadmap delivery.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/pm/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="product" count="75">
    <scope>Product management discipline - discovery, opportunity sizing, product strategy, launch planning, post-launch review, product operations and account health.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/product/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="research" count="87">
    <scope>Research practice - user research, market research, qualitative coding protocols, AI-assisted persona building, interview analysis and research synthesis.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/research/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="sdd" count="117">
    <scope>Spec-driven development - constitution, roadmap, spec, design, test plan, implementation plan, ADR consequence binding, AI-assisted spec writing, and the full SDD lifecycle from backlog to done.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/sdd/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="sdlc-ai" count="89">
    <scope>Wiring AI agents into the SDLC - lang/lint/test/tracker/kb/task/mr/inc/sec/gov methodologies that connect agents to the development pipeline floor: PR review, kb maintenance, incident triage, governance.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/sdlc-ai/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="security" count="1">
    <scope>Application and supply-chain security - CVE triage, dependency audit cadence, and other repeatable security artefacts for solo and small-team development.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/security/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
  <domain id="ux" count="93">
    <scope>UX design and research practice - UI design, UX research, user research, accessibility specialist work, design ops, usability and conversion design.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/ux/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>
</domains>
