<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<domains version="2.0" generated="2026-05-25" canonical="22" total_methodologies="2614">
  <description>L1 index of methodology domains. The retriever reads this first, picks 1-3 candidate domains via the decision-tree, then reads only those domains' INDEX.xml. The disambiguation block defines hard-edges between near-synonym domains.</description>

  <decision-tree>
                <description>First-match-wins triggers. Phrased from the user's perspective: "user asks about / wants to / is doing X" → route to domain Y.</description>
            
                <step n="1" trigger="building an autonomous agent / ReAct / tool-use / multi-agent / planner-executor">ai-agents</step>
                <step n="2" trigger="prompt engineering, embeddings, RAG basics, LLM fundamentals, model selection">ai-core</step>
                <step n="3" trigger="production LLM serving, RAG pipeline, fine-tuning, MLOps, model rollout, eval harness">ml-engineering</step>
                <step n="4" trigger="wiring an AI agent into PR review / CI / kb maintenance / incident triage / governance pipeline">sdlc-ai</step>
            
                <step n="5" trigger="HTTP API, service contract, server-side framework, DB schema, queue, background job">backend</step>
                <step n="6" trigger="React/Vue/Svelte component, CSS, accessibility, build tooling, state management, design system">frontend</step>
                <step n="7" trigger="general coding craft, testing, code review, refactor, debugging — no specific tier of stack">dev</step>
            
                <step n="8" trigger="ADR, service boundary, system design, capacity planning, technology selection, architecture review">architecture</step>
                <step n="9" trigger="CI/CD, deploy, observability, on-call, Kubernetes, terraform, cloud infra, networking, secrets">infra</step>
                <step n="10" trigger="CVE triage, dependency audit, security-by-design, threat modeling, SOC2/GDPR evidence">security</step>
            
                <step n="11" trigger="requirements elicitation, process model, stakeholder workshop, BPMN, traceability matrix">ba</step>
                <step n="12" trigger="discovery, JTBD, opportunity sizing, product strategy, launch planning, post-launch review">product</step>
                <step n="13" trigger="sprint planning, standup, retro, roadmap, OKR cascade, status report, project ceremonies">pm</step>
            
                <step n="14" trigger="UX research synthesis, usability test, user interview, accessibility audit, journey map, persona">ux</step>
                <step n="15" trigger="market research, competitor scan, survey design, qualitative coding, persona AI-assisted">research</step>
            
                <step n="16" trigger="SEO, content brief, ad copy, growth experiment, funnel, conversion-rate test, launch campaign">marketing</step>
                <step n="17" trigger="status update, demo script, escalation message, contractor brief, difficult conversation">comms</step>
                <step n="18" trigger="hiring loop, structured interview, candidate experience, 30-60-90 plan, offer negotiation">hr</step>
            
                <step n="19" trigger="spec.md / design.md / test-plan.md / implementation-plan.md / SDD ceremony, TASK_NN materialization">sdd</step>
                <step n="20" trigger="Claude Code skill, command, hook, MCP server, plugin authoring, agent file convention">claude-code</step>
              </decision-tree>

  <disambiguation>
                <description>Hard edges between near-synonym domains. "If X belongs to A, never to B" — overrides any decision-tree ambiguity.</description>
            
                <rule pair="dev | backend | frontend">
                  <if>The question is stack-agnostic (refactor, test, code review, debugging discipline)</if>
                  <then>dev</then>
                  <if>The question is about a stack the user touches via HTTP server-side (DB, API, queue, auth)</if>
                  <then>backend</then>
                  <if>The question is about what the end-user sees and interacts with in a browser / native UI</if>
                  <then>frontend</then>
                </rule>
            
                <rule pair="ai-core | ai-agents | ml-engineering | sdlc-ai">
                  <if>"How does this model think / what is a token / which model do I pick" type question</if>
                  <then>ai-core</then>
                  <if>The artefact under design IS an agent (tool-use loop, planner, memory)</if>
                  <then>ai-agents</then>
                  <if>The artefact is production AI infra (serving, batching, eval, RAG pipeline plumbing)</if>
                  <then>ml-engineering</then>
                  <if>The agent is plumbed into the SDLC (PR review bot, kb maintainer, incident triager)</if>
                  <then>sdlc-ai</then>
                </rule>
            
                <rule pair="pm | product | ba">
                  <if>The user produces ceremonies / dashboards / status / sprint artefacts</if>
                  <then>pm</then>
                  <if>The user decides what to build and for whom (discovery, opportunity, JTBD, launch)</if>
                  <then>product</then>
                  <if>The user shapes requirements, models processes, traces requirements across the lifecycle</if>
                  <then>ba</then>
                </rule>
            
                <rule pair="ux | research">
                  <if>Activity produces a design / journey map / accessibility audit / usability test</if>
                  <then>ux</then>
                  <if>Activity produces persona / market understanding / interview analysis without a design output</if>
                  <then>research</then>
                </rule>
            
                <rule pair="architecture | infra">
                  <if>Decision is about long-lived shape (ADR, service boundary, technology choice)</if>
                  <then>architecture</then>
                  <if>Decision is about runtime operation (deploy, observe, scale, recover)</if>
                  <then>infra</then>
                </rule>
            
                <rule pair="sdd | pm">
                  <if>Activity creates a written contract that grounds LLM code generation (spec/design/test-plan)</if>
                  <then>sdd</then>
                  <if>Activity is a project-management ceremony or status-tracking ritual</if>
                  <then>pm</then>
                </rule>
            
                <rule pair="security | infra | architecture">
                  <if>Question is about a specific vulnerability / dependency / CVE / threat model</if>
                  <then>security</then>
                  <if>Question is about who can call what, network ACL, secret rotation cadence</if>
                  <then>infra</then>
                  <if>Question is about whether to centralise/distribute auth, where the trust boundary lives</if>
                  <then>architecture</then>
                </rule>
              </disambiguation>

  <domain id="ai-agents" count="102">
    <scope>AI agents and agentic systems — agent architectures, tool use, multi-agent orchestration, memory, planning, evaluation, production-grade agent patterns.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/ai-agents/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I make my agent stop and ask the human?</ask>
      <ask>How do I evaluate whether my agent's tool calls are correct?</ask>
      <ask>How do I structure a planner-executor split?</ask>
      <ask>How do I protect my agent from prompt injection at the tool boundary?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="ai-core" count="78">
    <scope>Core AI / ML foundations — model selection, prompt engineering basics, embeddings, RAG fundamentals, LLM integration patterns, primitives that AI-powered features are built from.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/ai-core/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>When do I pick Opus vs Sonnet vs Haiku?</ask>
      <ask>How do I structure a prompt that an agent will follow reliably?</ask>
      <ask>What's the cheapest way to add semantic search to my app?</ask>
      <ask>How do I write evals that catch silent regression?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="architecture" count="64">
    <scope>Software architecture — ADRs, API gateway patterns, service boundaries, reversibility tagging, observability design, software-architect decisions that shape long-lived systems.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>Should I split this monolith into services now?</ask>
      <ask>How do I write an ADR a future-me will actually use?</ask>
      <ask>Where does this new responsibility belong in the system?</ask>
      <ask>How do I make my architecture diagram match the running code?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="automation-tooling" count="20">
    <scope>Methodologies in the automation-tooling domain.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>

  <domain id="ba" count="118">
    <scope>Business analysis — requirements elicitation, process modeling, stakeholder management, KPI design, change-request impact analysis, BA core practice + modeling techniques bridging product strategy and delivery.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/ba/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I elicit requirements from a stakeholder who keeps changing their mind?</ask>
      <ask>How do I draw a BPMN that engineers will read?</ask>
      <ask>How do I run a definition-of-ready check on a feature?</ask>
      <ask>How do I trace a regulatory clause to a test case?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="backend" count="147">
    <scope>Backend engineering — APIs, services, databases, server-side patterns across Python/Node/Java/Rails/PHP/.NET, including auth, caching, queues, background work, contract-first design and enterprise framework patterns.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/backend/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I shape an API contract before writing the handler?</ask>
      <ask>How do I rotate secrets without downtime?</ask>
      <ask>How do I model soft-deletes in my Django app?</ask>
      <ask>How do I make my background jobs idempotent?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="claude-code" count="8">
    <scope>Claude Code authoring stack — agents, commands, hooks, skills, MCP servers, project documentation conventions for building reliable agentic tooling on top of Claude.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/claude-code/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I write a Claude Code skill that auto-invokes correctly?</ask>
      <ask>How do I add an MCP server for my custom tool?</ask>
      <ask>How do I structure project AGENTS.md for multi-agent compatibility?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="comms" count="24">
    <scope>Communication craft for solopreneurs and small agencies — stakeholder updates, executive demos, contractor and freelancer scripts, negotiation, storytelling, difficult conversations, customer-facing testimonials.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/comms/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I write a status report stakeholders actually read?</ask>
      <ask>How do I escalate without setting fire to the relationship?</ask>
      <ask>How do I script a difficult conversation with a contractor?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="dev" count="379">
    <scope>Software engineering practice — coding craft, code quality, testing, devtools. The dev bucket covers anything a software developer does day-to-day that's stack-agnostic.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/dev/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I refactor without breaking everything?</ask>
      <ask>How do I write a test that's actually useful?</ask>
      <ask>How do I review a PR without being a jerk?</ask>
      <ask>How do I unflake a slow test suite?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="frontend" count="42">
    <scope>Frontend and UI engineering — design systems, component libraries, accessibility, performance, state management, build tooling, UI/UX implementation patterns for web and spatial interfaces.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/frontend/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I keep my design system honest as components grow?</ask>
      <ask>How do I make a React form that handles validation cleanly?</ask>
      <ask>How do I ship an a11y fix that doesn't regress?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="hr" count="17">
    <scope>HR and recruiting practice — full-cycle hiring, structured interview design, STAR method, candidate experience, employer branding, EVP, 30-60-90 onboarding, retention compliance.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/hr/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I run a structured interview that beats gut feel?</ask>
      <ask>How do I design a 30-60-90 plan a new hire can actually complete?</ask>
      <ask>How do I write a job posting that filters in, not out?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="infra" count="294">
    <scope>Infrastructure and platform engineering — DevOps, CI/CD pipelines, observability, server craft, cloud, networking, deploy and operate everything that runs the code in production.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/infra/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I add tracing without rewriting half the codebase?</ask>
      <ask>How do I deploy with confidence at 6pm Friday? (you don't, but how do you make Monday safer)</ask>
      <ask>How do I structure a runbook the on-call will actually read at 2am?</ask>
      <ask>How do I get my CI from 18 minutes to under 5?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="llm-integration" count="11">
    <scope>Methodologies in the llm-integration domain.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/llm-integration/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
  </domain>

  <domain id="marketing" count="276">
    <scope>Marketing practice — content, SEO, growth, PPC, SMM, CRO, GTM. Everything that drives demand and converts it into customers.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/marketing/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I pick a single distribution channel for my first 100 users?</ask>
      <ask>How do I write a content brief from search intent?</ask>
      <ask>How do I run a CRO experiment that beats noise?</ask>
      <ask>How do I script a launch campaign that doesn't peter out at day three?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="ml-engineering" count="188">
    <scope>Applied ML / AI engineering practice — building, evaluating, deploying, operating LLM and ML systems: RAG pipelines, agentic patterns, eval-driven development, fine-tuning, prompt engineering, model rollout, MLOps for production AI features.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I stand up a RAG pipeline that beats vanilla vector search?</ask>
      <ask>How do I migrate from one LLM provider to another without breaking eval?</ask>
      <ask>How do I run an eval harness in CI?</ask>
      <ask>How do I cut inference cost 40% without quality regression?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="pm" count="284">
    <scope>Product + project management — planning, prioritization, stakeholder management, agile/traditional ceremonies, ops, KPIs, roadmap delivery.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/pm/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I run a 15-minute standup that surfaces blockers, not status?</ask>
      <ask>How do I cascade an OKR from company to team without ritual theatre?</ask>
      <ask>How do I write a weekly status that the CEO actually opens?</ask>
      <ask>How do I refresh my risk register in under an hour?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="product" count="112">
    <scope>Product management discipline — discovery, opportunity sizing, product strategy, launch planning, post-launch review, product operations, account health.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/product/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I decide what to build next when everything looks important?</ask>
      <ask>How do I size an opportunity without making up numbers?</ask>
      <ask>How do I run a kill review on a stalled product line?</ask>
      <ask>How do I plan a launch that doesn't disappoint at week two?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="research" count="82">
    <scope>Research practice — user research, market research, qualitative coding protocols, AI-assisted persona building, interview analysis, research synthesis.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/research/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I code 30 interview transcripts without losing the plot?</ask>
      <ask>How do I size a market without paying for a Gartner report?</ask>
      <ask>How do I build a persona from data, not vibes?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="sdd" count="90">
    <scope>Spec-driven development — constitution, roadmap, spec, design, test plan, implementation plan, ADR consequence binding, AI-assisted spec writing, the full SDD lifecycle from backlog to done.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/sdd/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I write a spec.md an agent can implement without hallucination?</ask>
      <ask>How do I materialise tasks from an implementation-plan?</ask>
      <ask>How do I run an SDD batch through a subagent pool?</ask>
      <ask>How do I know my design.md is ready to leave todo/?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="sdlc-ai" count="91">
    <scope>Wiring AI agents into the SDLC — lang/lint/test/tracker/kb/task/mr/inc/sec/gov methodologies that connect agents to the development pipeline floor: PR review, kb maintenance, incident triage, governance.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/sdlc-ai/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I wire an AI PR reviewer that doesn't drown the team in noise?</ask>
      <ask>How do I let an agent maintain our internal kb without it hallucinating decisions?</ask>
      <ask>How do I make my agent handle an incident triage handoff?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="security" count="1">
    <scope>Application and supply-chain security — CVE triage, dependency audit cadence, threat modeling, repeatable security artefacts for solo and small-team development.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/security/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I triage a CVE in under 30 minutes?</ask>
      <ask>How do I set up dependency-audit cadence that doesn't get ignored?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

  <domain id="ux" count="186">
    <scope>UX design and research practice — UI design, UX research, user research, accessibility specialist work, design ops, usability and conversion design.</scope>
    <l2-index>skills/faion/knowledge/ux/INDEX.xml</l2-index>
    <typical-asks>
      <ask>How do I run a usability test on a prototype in one sitting?</ask>
      <ask>How do I audit a single screen for accessibility?</ask>
      <ask>How do I turn a journey map into a backlog?</ask>
      <ask>How do I write a heuristic eval that a stakeholder can argue with?</ask>
    </typical-asks>
  </domain>

</domains>
