<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Tokens Fundamentals Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Design Tokens Fundamentals. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-three-tiers-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tokens are organised in exactly three tiers: global (raw primitives) → semantic (intent aliases) → component (scoped overrides). Two-tier or four-tier setups are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="W3C DTCG + Style Dictionary docs">Without the hierarchy, semantic tokens hold raw values and component tokens reference semantics directly — both defeat the &apos;update once, apply everywhere&apos; guarantee.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-semantic-references-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Semantic tokens MUST alias a global token via {global.token.path} reference syntax; raw values in the semantic tier are CI-rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="W3C DTCG spec">A semantic token holding a raw hex must be updated in two places when the brand color changes; CI gate is the only reliable enforcement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-intent-not-value-naming" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Semantic tokens are named by intent (color.feedback.error, spacing.md) not by value (color.red, spacing.16); value-based names in the semantic tier are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-system maturity audits">Value-based names ossify; intent-based names survive rebrands and theme changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-single-source-of-truth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Either Figma Variables OR a tokens JSON in the repo — never both as independent sources. The chosen source is named in an ADR.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-source-of-truth convention">Without a single source, Figma and code diverge within weeks; the token-based theming becomes unreliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-major-bump-on-rename" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Breaking token renames bump the major version and ship release notes; additions are minor; value tweaks are patch.</statement>
      <rationale source="SemVer + Style Dictionary changelog convention">Without versioning discipline, downstream packages silently break on rename.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-ci-lint-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CI pipeline runs Style Dictionary build + lint; any semantic token with a raw value fails the build.</statement>
      <rationale source="CI-enforcement principle">Manual review does not scale; automated enforcement is the only reliable governance mechanism.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-design-tokens-fundamentals.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
