<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="tool-migration-process Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for tool-migration-process. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Complete Phase 1 Planning with explicit stakeholder alignment, tool selection or evaluation, scope definition, timeline with 50% buffer over measured dry-run time, and risk assessment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Skipping planning or condensing it into a few days causes scope creep, misaligned expectations, and timeline overruns that compound through subsequent phases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Freeze the field mapping specification at end of Preparation; mid-migration mapping changes silently double scope.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each mapping change requires re-transforming and re-validating already-migrated records.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep the source tool read-only for at least 30 days post-cutover; never delete it during stabilization.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Teams reference historical context from source; premature deletion forces re-migration of data that was intentionally excluded.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Budget 2x the planned stabilization window; it always overruns.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Edge cases and user adaptation issues accumulate in week 3-4 after initial excitement fades.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Design the migration engine as a CLI tool the agent invokes; do not run migrations as inline LLM calls.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Long-running migrations exceed agent token budgets; the CLI pattern keeps the agent as orchestrator with human-reviewable artifacts at each checkpoint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a full dry-run on production data into a sandbox target one week before cutover; measure exact runtime then add 50% buffer.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Rate limits routinely double planned cutover downtime; dry-run measurement is the only reliable source of timing data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Freeze the field mapping specification before the first dry-run; forbid runtime mapping mutations.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each mapping change requires re-transforming already-processed records; LLMs that "fix" mappings on the fly silently corrupt the ID mapping and cause orphaned links.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Force-list the 0.5% of failed records; they are always the most-linked tickets.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A 99.5% success rate looks fine in aggregate but the missing records are disproportionately high-value due to cross-reference density.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Validate three numbers before declaring any wave or cutover successful: issue count, comment count, and attachment count by byte.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Issue count alone misses corrupted comments and missing attachments; the three-number check catches the most common silent data-loss patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cutover on a low-traffic window (Friday afternoon if org tolerates weekend quiet); never mid-week for large migrations.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Weekend windows provide recovery time before full business-hours load resumes; mid-week cutovers interrupt peak productivity with no buffer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-write rollback communications before cutover begins so they can be sent within seconds of a decision to revert.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Rollback decisions under stress are slowed by the need to draft communications; pre-writing removes this bottleneck and enables faster response.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rollback only works if no critical data was created exclusively in the target during cutover; a single shipped feature with target-only context can pin you.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Once teams start creating tickets in the new tool, those records don't exist in the source; rollback would lose that work, making true revert impossible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rate-limit webhook-based notifications to one summary per migration phase; do not send a message per event.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Retry storms in migration engines can trigger hundreds of webhook notifications, spamming channels and causing teams to mute the notifications needed for real alerts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
