<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-phases" title="Migration Phases">
  <summary>Six sequential phases for large-scale PM tool migration, each with defined scope, duration guidance, and exit criteria.</summary>

  <section title="Phase Overview">
    <rule>
      <statement>Execute all six phases in order; skipping Preparation or Pilot is the leading cause of data-loss incidents at cutover.</statement>
      <rationale>Phase 3 (Pilot) surfaces field-mapping failures on a small dataset at low cost; skipping it causes those failures to appear at Phase 4 scale with no rollback window.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Phase 1: Planning (2-4 weeks)">
      <list>
        <item>Stakeholder alignment and sponsorship</item>
        <item>Tool selection or evaluation (see pm-tools-comparison)</item>
        <item>Migration scope definition — in-scope projects, date range, attachments threshold</item>
        <item>Timeline creation with explicit buffer (50% over measured dry-run time)</item>
        <item>Risk assessment: data loss, integration failure, adoption resistance</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 2: Preparation (2-3 weeks)">
      <list>
        <item>Target tool setup and admin configuration</item>
        <item>Field mapping design — document every source field to target field, with fallback for unmapped</item>
        <item>Migration script development (ETL engine — see content/02-etl-engine.xml)</item>
        <item>Test environment creation for dry-run</item>
        <item>Team communication: announce timeline, schedule training</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Freeze the field mapping specification at end of Preparation; mid-migration mapping changes silently double scope.</statement>
        <rationale>Each mapping change requires re-transforming and re-validating already-migrated records.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 3: Pilot Migration (1-2 weeks)">
      <list>
        <item>Select pilot project — representative complexity, NOT the simplest team</item>
        <item>Execute migration with dry-run flag first, then live</item>
        <item>Validate issue count, comment count, attachment byte count</item>
        <item>Sample 50 items by hand before declaring pilot success</item>
        <item>Gather feedback, adjust approach</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Picking the simplest team for the pilot project.</description>
        <reason>Creates false confidence; the simplest team has the fewest edge cases and the most forgiving stakeholders. Failures surface in Phase 4 at scale instead.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 4: Full Migration (1-4 weeks)">
      <list>
        <item>Execute in waves by team or project, not by record type</item>
        <item>Validate each wave (three numbers: issues, comments, attachments-by-byte)</item>
        <item>Address issues between waves; do not accumulate debt</item>
        <item>Monitor rate limits; add 50% buffer to planned wave duration</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 5: Cutover (1 week)">
      <list>
        <item>T-24h: final export from source, backup target, notify all users</item>
        <item>T-4h: set source to read-only, run final migration sync, validate counts</item>
        <item>T-0: enable target for all users, send go-live announcement, support team on standby</item>
        <item>T+1h: verify login success, automations running, address immediate issues</item>
        <item>T+24h: review error logs, collect feedback, document known issues</item>
        <item>T+1w: adoption metrics, complete missing migrations, retrospective, plan source decommission</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep the source tool read-only for at least 30 days post-cutover; never delete it during stabilization.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams reference historical context from source; premature deletion forces re-migration of data that was intentionally excluded.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 6: Stabilization (2-4 weeks)">
      <list>
        <item>Active support channel with named owner</item>
        <item>Fix issues within 24 hours of report</item>
        <item>Run training sessions for high-friction groups</item>
        <item>Document lessons learned; schedule source decommission on a calendar date</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Budget 2x the planned stabilization window; it always overruns.</statement>
        <rationale>Edge cases and user adaptation issues accumulate in week 3-4 after initial excitement fades.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
  </section>
</text>
