<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-etl-engine" title="ETL Migration Engine">
  <summary>Python ETL skeleton for PM tool migration with dry-run flag, per-wave checkpointing, and ID mapping output.</summary>

  <section title="ETL Architecture">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design the migration engine as a CLI tool the agent invokes; do not run migrations as inline LLM calls.</statement>
      <rationale>Long-running migrations exceed agent token budgets; the CLI pattern keeps the agent as orchestrator with human-reviewable artifacts at each checkpoint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a full dry-run on production data into a sandbox target one week before cutover; measure exact runtime then add 50% buffer.</statement>
      <rationale>Rate limits routinely double planned cutover downtime; dry-run measurement is the only reliable source of timing data.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="MigrationConfig Dataclass">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
from dataclasses import dataclass
from typing import Dict

@dataclass
class MigrationConfig:
    source_tool: str
    target_tool: str
    field_mapping: Dict[str, str]   # source_field -> target_field
    status_mapping: Dict[str, str]  # source_status -> target_status
    priority_mapping: Dict[str, str]
    dry_run: bool = True  # always default to dry_run=True
]]></code>
      <note>Always default dry_run to True to prevent accidental live migrations.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Extract-Transform-Load Steps">
    <list>
      <item>Extract: pull all issues from source; log count before processing</item>
      <item>Transform: apply field_mapping, status_mapping, priority_mapping per record; log per-record errors without halting</item>
      <item>Load: create issues in target; record source_id → target_id mapping; checkpoint after each successful write</item>
      <item>Validate: compare three counts (issues, comments, attachments-by-byte) and sample 50 random items by hand</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Freeze the field mapping specification before the first dry-run; forbid runtime mapping mutations.</statement>
      <rationale>Each mapping change requires re-transforming already-processed records; LLMs that "fix" mappings on the fly silently corrupt the ID mapping and cause orphaned links.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Checkpointed Loader">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
#!/usr/bin/env python3
"""Load JSONL of target-shaped issues; resumes from .checkpoint on rerun."""
import json, os, sys, time, requests

CHECKPOINT = ".load_checkpoint"
done = set(open(CHECKPOINT).read().split()) if os.path.exists(CHECKPOINT) else set()
URL = os.environ["TARGET_API_URL"]
TOK = os.environ["TARGET_TOKEN"]

with open(CHECKPOINT, "a") as ck:
    for line in sys.stdin:
        rec = json.loads(line)
        sid = rec["_source_id"]
        if sid in done:
            continue
        for attempt in range(5):
            r = requests.post(URL, json=rec, headers={"Authorization": TOK})
            if r.status_code < 300:
                break
            if r.status_code == 429:
                time.sleep(2 ** attempt)
                continue
            sys.exit(f"FAIL {sid}: {r.status_code} {r.text[:200]}")
        ck.write(sid + "\n")
        ck.flush()
        print(f"OK {sid} -> {r.json()['id']}")
]]></code>
      <note>The checkpoint file enables resume from any point; critical for multi-hour migrations interrupted by rate limits.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Post-Migration Link Fixing">
    <p>Issue links, @mentions in comments, and commit message references all contain source-tool IDs. Fix these in a separate pass after the main migration using the ID mapping JSON.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Force-list the 0.5% of failed records; they are always the most-linked tickets.</statement>
      <rationale>A 99.5% success rate looks fine in aggregate but the missing records are disproportionately high-value due to cross-reference density.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping @mention and user-ID resolution during comment migration.</description>
      <reason>Strips all @mentions silently, breaking notification chains and audit trails for team collaboration history.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/load_resume.py">Checkpointed loader script — resumes from .checkpoint on rerun</reference>
</text>
