<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spatial-ux-fundamentals">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Design principles for 3D/XR interfaces: place UI elements in near (0-1m), mid (1-3m), and far (3m+) field zones; specify element sizes in world units (meters) at placement distance; assign interaction modalities per platform constraints; and validate every layout in a physical headset before development begins.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>xr</tag>
      <tag>spatial-design</tag>
      <tag>ergonomics</tag>
      <tag>3d-ui</tag>
      <tag>vision-pro</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Spatial UX Fundamentals</title>

    <summary>Design principles for 3D/XR interfaces: place UI elements in near (0-1m), mid (1-3m), and far (3m+) field zones; specify element sizes in world units (meters) at placement distance; assign interaction modalities per platform constraints; and validate every layout in a physical headset before development begins.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>2D UI patterns — pixel sizing, flat navigation, pointer interaction — do not transfer to 3D space. Placing content outside comfort zones (above eye level, below 0.5m, in peripheral blind spots) causes neck strain, vergence-accommodation conflict, and motion sickness. Text and touch targets must meet minimum visual angle requirements that vary with placement distance, not screen resolution.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing UI for Apple Vision Pro, Meta Quest, or other XR headsets</item>
        <item>Planning spatial layout of panels, menus, and work surfaces in a 3D environment</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing XR app for ergonomic violations</item>
        <item>Specifying spatial interaction patterns for a development team new to XR</item>
        <item>Creating documentation for a spatial design system (scale, reach zones, field-of-view constraints)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Flat 2D web or mobile interfaces — spatial principles introduce unnecessary complexity</item>
        <item>Early product ideation before target hardware is confirmed — comfort zones vary across headsets</item>
        <item>Accessibility audits without XR-specific assistive technology expertise</item>
        <item>When the development team has no XR SDK experience — specs cannot be implemented without platform capability</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="field-zones">
      <p>XR environments organize content across three spatial zones based on distance and interaction type.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Design the mid field (1-3m) as the default work surface; reserve near field (0-1m) for immediate feedback and far field (3m+) for navigation anchors and environmental context only.</statement>
        <rationale>Mid-field placement provides the best balance of visual clarity, interaction comfort, and spatial immersion across all current XR headsets. Near-field overuse causes vergence-accommodation conflict; far-field overuse degrades text legibility and interaction precision.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Never place persistent UI above the horizontal plane of the user's eye level — users cannot comfortably look up for extended periods.</statement>
        <rationale>Extended upward gaze (above 25° vertical) causes neck strain within minutes. Content above eye level is appropriate only for transient notifications, not primary work surfaces.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Do not place interactive elements closer than 0.5m from the user — this is the vergence-accommodation conflict zone where eyes cannot comfortably converge.</statement>
        <rationale>Content placed inside 0.5m forces the eyes to converge at an angle inconsistent with the display's focus distance, causing discomfort and visual fatigue.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="element-sizing">
      <p>Element size in XR is measured in world units, not pixels. Perceived size depends on distance and visual angle, not screen resolution.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Specify all element dimensions in meters (world units) at the intended placement distance, not pixels — pixel sizing is meaningless in XR.</statement>
        <rationale>A pixel is a display-relative unit with no fixed physical size. XR rendering requires world-space dimensions so elements maintain consistent apparent size as the user moves.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Minimum text size: 0.5° visual angle at placement distance. Minimum interaction target: 1.5° visual angle (approximately 1cm at 1m, scaling linearly with distance).</statement>
        <rationale>Below 0.5° visual angle, text becomes unreadable at normal viewing distances. Below 1.5°, interaction targets require precision that exceeds comfortable hand/gaze pointing.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="interaction-modality">
      <p>Interaction methods vary across XR platforms. Assign modalities based on platform capabilities, not designer preference.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Assign interaction modality per platform constraints: visionOS primary = gaze + pinch; Quest primary = hand ray or controller; HoloLens = hand gesture + voice.</statement>
        <rationale>Modality mismatch (designing for controller input on a gaze-primary device) produces interaction patterns that feel unnatural and increase error rates.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Specify spatial audio feedback for all interaction events — spatial audio is a design element, not a developer afterthought.</statement>
        <rationale>In 3D space, audio provides directional confirmation that 2D visual feedback alone cannot. Missing audio design is discovered during development and added inconsistently.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="validation-requirements">
      <p>All spatial specifications require physical validation in the target device before development.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every spatial layout must be validated by a human designer wearing the target headset before any 3D asset or interaction code is written.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents cannot simulate 3D space, field of view, or head tracking. All spatial specifications are text descriptions that require physical validation — no amount of review on a flat screen substitutes for headset testing.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Test every layout both standing and seated — ergonomic comfort zones differ significantly between postures.</statement>
        <rationale>A mid-field panel that works well seated may require uncomfortable neck extension when standing. Posture variation is routinely ignored in XR design reviews conducted at a desk.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-limitations">
      <p>XR design has inherent constraints that agents cannot overcome without physical testing.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>All spatial specifications produced by agents are hypothetical until validated in a physical headset — treat agent output as a starting brief for human design review, never as implementation-ready specs.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents cannot simulate 3D space, field of view, or head tracking. Comfort zones are text descriptions only.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Comfort zone numbers in agent training data may reflect older guidelines (pre-2024 Apple Vision Pro) — verify against current platform HIG for the specific device.</statement>
        <rationale>XR ergonomic standards are evolving; agent training data may be based on superseded guidelines.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Agents frequently conflate angular size (degrees) with world-space size (meters) — ensure the spec explicitly uses one unit system.</statement>
        <rationale>This confusion creates ambiguous specs that lead to implementation errors.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Latency budgets for comfortable XR interaction (gaze tracking &lt; 20ms, hand tracking &lt; 10ms reprojection) are implementation constraints that must be flagged to the engineering team; agents do not surface them.</statement>
        <rationale>Latency is critical for comfort but invisible in text specifications.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <note>
      Best practices: Design for the mid field (1-3m) as the default work surface — near field is reserved for immediate feedback, far field for navigation only. Specify element dimensions in meters (world units) at the intended placement distance, not pixels. Never place persistent UI above the horizontal plane of the user's eye level. Interaction modality assignment must account for platform constraints: visionOS primary = gaze + pinch; Quest primary = hand ray or controller; HoloLens = hand gesture + voice. Test every layout standing and seated — ergonomic comfort zones differ significantly between postures.
    </note>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/spatial-ux/"/>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/spatial-design"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/xr-ergonomics"/>
      <link href="https://developer.meta.com/horizon/documentation/unity/unity-design/"/>
      <link href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2025/spatial-ux/"/>
    </see-also>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/spatial-comfort.py" purpose="Computes minimum element size and interaction target size at a given placement distance and visual angle"/>
    </scripts>
  </content>
</methodology>
