<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Competitor Analysis Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Competitor Analysis methodology. Every rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale, plus the universal skip-this-methodology gate.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="three-competitor-types" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Identify all three competitor types: direct (5-10), indirect (3-5), future (2-3) with concrete signals.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford, Obviously Awesome (2019)">Direct-only analysis misses substitutes customers actually use and entrants arriving in 18 months.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="positioning-matrix-2x2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plot every competitor on a 2x2 matrix (price vs feature-breadth) before selecting your own positioning.</statement>
      <rationale source="Michael Porter, Competitive Strategy (1980)">Visual mapping surfaces whitespace that a feature list alone obscures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="eight-dimensions-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Analyse each competitor across all 8 dimensions; do not skip dimensions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — pitch-deck reviews">Partial analysis produces a partial gap table; investors probe the dimensions you skipped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="differentiate-on-weakness" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Differentiate on a competitor weakness; scrape 1-star reviews and convert top-3 complaints into your positioning.</statement>
      <rationale source="Dunford, Obviously Awesome">Copying competitors produces table-stakes; complaints-as-headline resonate with dissatisfied users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="source-every-fact-cell" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cite a URL for every factual cell (price, founding year, employee count); reject cells without sources.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Q3 2025 due-diligence rejection">Sourced claims are auditable; unsourced cells are liabilities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="parallel-snapshot-serial-synth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run per-competitor snapshot tasks in parallel; run synthesis serially.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anthropic — orchestrator-workers pattern (2024)">Dumping 10+ competitors into one prompt overflows context and degrades gap analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pin-geography" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin target geography in every prompt; reject competitors whose primary market differs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — multi-region launch audit">Without geo pinning, agents skew toward US companies even for EU/APAC markets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only if all entries in `## Applies If` hold and none of `## Skip If` triggers; otherwise abort and route to the correct methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — decision tree minimum form">A misrouted methodology produces wrong-shape output; the explicit skip rule is the universal default branch from the decision tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
