<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process-steps" title="Cognitive Walkthrough Process Steps">
  <summary>Five-step structured process: prerequisites definition, evaluator assembly, per-step walk, issue documentation, and findings summary.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Prerequisites">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the correct action sequence before any evaluation begins. Mid-walk changes to the sequence invalidate per-step evaluation JSON and make cross-evaluator results incommensurable.</statement>
      <rationale>Action sequence changes mean evaluators evaluated different flows. Per-step issue counts become meaningless because "step 3" refers to different actions across evaluators who used different sequences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/walkthrough-plan.md">Planning template: persona, task, correct action sequence table, interface link, scope.</reference>
    <list>
      <item>Persona: concrete first-time user with specified tech-savviness, prior tools, and product knowledge level.</item>
      <item>Task: a single clear task statement with success criteria.</item>
      <item>Correct action sequence: minimum-clicks happy path, numbered, one action per step.</item>
      <item>Interface: URL or prototype link accessible to all evaluators.</item>
      <item>Scope: explicit list of screens included and excluded.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Assemble Evaluators">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use 2-4 evaluators mixing human and agent roles. Single-evaluator walks miss approximately 40% of issues. Make agent evaluators stateless and independent — do not feed earlier step evaluations into later step prompts.</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple evaluators increase coverage through different perspectives. Agent context window drift (contamination from earlier step findings) inflates false Q2 failures on steps evaluated later in the sequence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>UX designers: bring pattern-library knowledge and interaction design expertise.</item>
      <item>Product managers: bring user-goal and business-context knowledge.</item>
      <item>Developers: bring technical feasibility for fix suggestions.</item>
      <item>Agent evaluator: brings consistent Q1-Q4 application and exhaustive step coverage.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Walk Through Each Step">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture the screen before the action (for Q1-Q3) and after the action (for Q4). Screenshot-only walks without post-action states systematically miss Q4 failures.</statement>
      <rationale>Q4 evaluates the system's response after an action. Evaluating only the pre-action state produces false positives ("progress is shown") when the actual post-action state shows no feedback.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/evaluation-form.md">Per-step evaluation form with Q1-Q4 sections, notes, and issues table.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Document Issues">
    <rule>
      <statement>For every "No" answer: describe the problem, cite the specific UI element, explain why it is an issue for this persona, and provide a concrete fix suggestion. Do not file issues without fixes.</statement>
      <rationale>Issues without fixes stall in triage because the team must first understand the issue before estimating effort. Issues with concrete fixes get resolved in the next sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Summarize Findings">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap the summary report at 3 High-severity issues. Every issue must cite step number, question (Q1-Q4), and a one-line fix. Include at least 3 positive findings — steps that passed — to prevent inadvertent regression.</statement>
      <rationale>Severity inflation (everything rated Medium) makes reports useless for prioritization. Forcing a maximum of 3 High issues requires the reporter agent to differentiate. Positive findings protect successful elements from being "improved" away in redesigns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/cw-findings.md">Walkthrough findings template: executive summary, step issues, priority recommendations, positive findings.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
