<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-reporting" title="Cognitive Walkthrough Reporting">
  <summary>Summary report structure, severity calibration rules, exec-summary constraints, and delta tracking across releases.</summary>

  <section title="Report Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Force the exec summary to 5 bullets or fewer. The reporter agent must operate under a token budget for the executive summary section — unconstrained agents produce 15-20 bullet summaries that stakeholders skip.</statement>
      <rationale>Executive summaries are read; appendices are referenced. The entire value of the walkthrough depends on the exec summary being read. A 5-bullet hard cap forces prioritization and makes the report actually useful.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Executive summary: steps evaluated, issues found, critical issue count, key finding (1 sentence).</item>
      <item>Task overview: persona description, goal, optimal path step count.</item>
      <item>Findings by step: each step with issues, affected question (Q1-Q4), impact, recommendation.</item>
      <item>Issues summary table: step, issue, question, severity (H/M/L), status (open/fixed).</item>
      <item>Priority recommendations: Critical (fix before launch), Important (fix soon), Nice to have.</item>
      <item>Positive findings: at least 3 steps that worked — do not change these in future revisions.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/summary-report.md">Full summary report template with all sections.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Severity Calibration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Constrain severity distribution: at most 20% High, 50% Medium, 30% Low. Agents default to Medium for everything — enforce the distribution via prompt constraint.</statement>
      <rationale>Without distribution constraints, severity ratings are meaningless. An issue list where 90% of items are Medium provides no prioritization signal. The constrained distribution forces the evaluator to differentiate by frequency and task criticality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>High severity: Q2 or Q3 failure on a step required to complete the primary task, or Q4 failure that produces data loss. Medium severity: Q1/Q2/Q3 failures on secondary steps. Low severity: Q4 failures where success is still communicated, or steps on rarely-taken paths.</statement>
      <rationale>Severity must correlate with user impact, not with how interesting the finding is. Tying severity to task criticality and data integrity gives stakeholders a defensible prioritization basis.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Delta Tracking">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track resolved, new, and regressed issues across each re-evaluation run. Report the delta, not just the absolute issue count. The delta is the only metric that proves the walkthrough is paying off.</statement>
      <rationale>A report showing "12 issues found" every sprint provides no value. A report showing "8 resolved, 2 new, 1 regressed" demonstrates that the process is driving improvement and catches regressions before release.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag each finding with the affected screen component name. This enables developers to map issues directly to code without reading the full report.</statement>
      <rationale>Reports that require a developer to read the full narrative before understanding what to change increase triage time and reduce the likelihood that findings are acted on promptly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Multi-Evaluator Reconciliation">
    <rule>
      <statement>When reconciling human and agent evaluators, weight human-only findings 1.5x in tie-breaks. Agent confidence language is uniformly high regardless of certainty — humans express genuine uncertainty.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents produce consistently assertive language even when Q3 evidence is thin. Humans who rate a finding as No but hedge their confidence are expressing genuine uncertainty about edge cases. That hedging is signal, not noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark consensus findings (all evaluators agree) separately from disputed findings (evaluators disagree). Disputed findings require human review before being filed as tickets.</statement>
      <rationale>Disputed findings often reflect ambiguous step definitions or evaluator expertise differences, not genuine Q1-Q4 failures. Auto-filing disputed findings as tickets creates noise that erodes developer trust in the walkthrough process.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
