<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-strategy" title="Attribution Strategy, Configuration, and Incrementality Testing">
  <summary>Choosing a unified source of truth, configuring GA4 and platform attribution settings, and running geo-holdout incrementality tests.</summary>

  <section title="Choosing a Source of Truth">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick one attribution source of truth (usually GA4 data-driven or warehouse on top of GA4 export) and apply it consistently across all budget decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Switching models mid-flight invalidates historical comparisons and causes confusion during budget reviews. A documented, locked model is more valuable than the theoretically best model.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Trust GA4 (data-driven): unified view, misses view-through — best for most teams</item>
      <item>Warehouse-deduped: most accurate, requires ETL pipeline — best for $10k+/month spend</item>
      <item>Trust platform data: detailed but over-counts — use only for within-platform optimization</item>
      <item>Incrementality (geo-holdout): true causal lift — use quarterly to validate model</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="GA4 Attribution Configuration">
    <list>
      <item>Admin → Attribution settings → Reporting attribution model: Data-driven</item>
      <item>Lookback window: 30-90 days (match to sales cycle)</item>
      <item>Acquisition conversion events: configure explicitly</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Incrementality Testing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a geo-holdout incrementality test at least once per quarter when spending $10k+/month to validate the attribution model.</statement>
      <rationale>Data-driven attribution drifts over time and cannot detect true causal lift. A geo-holdout measures actual revenue lift vs. a control region, providing ground truth that no model can replicate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Geo holdout: no ads in test regions, compare conversion lift vs. control</item>
      <item>Conversion lift: platform-native measurement of lift over holdout</item>
      <item>Ghost ads: control group sees placebo ads, not the tested campaign</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run incrementality tests for at least 4 weeks and do not change budgets or targeting during the test period.</statement>
      <rationale>Short tests produce noise, not signal. Budget changes mid-test contaminate the treatment-control comparison and invalidate results.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running an incrementality test for less than 2 weeks or adjusting budgets during the test.</description>
      <reason>Insufficient runtime produces statistically noisy results. Mid-test budget changes alter the treatment condition and make the holdout comparison invalid.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Trusting platform-reported totals for cross-channel budget decisions.</description>
      <reason>Platform totals are over-counted by 20-40% due to cross-channel overlap. Decisions based on them systematically overspend on channels that appear more efficient than they are.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using last-click as the sole attribution model for a multi-touch journey.</description>
      <reason>Last-click assigns zero credit to all upper-funnel touchpoints, leading to systematic under-investment in awareness and consideration channels.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring view-through attribution entirely.</description>
      <reason>Display and video channels drive brand recall that appears as direct traffic. Excluding view-through undervalues awareness spend.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
