<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-ka6-tasks" title="Strategy Analysis — BABOK KA-6 Four Tasks">
  <summary>Four KA-6 tasks with strict input/output contracts, technique selection guidance, and known limitations of purely procedural execution.</summary>

  <section title="Task 1: Analyze Current State">
    <rule>
      <statement>Produce a current-state artifact covering six areas: business processes, organization structure, technology landscape, people and skills, data and information, external factors. Each area row must carry evidence_url and interviewed[] — no area may be populated from assumptions alone.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents that take the README's linear arrow at face value skip the iteration loop; current-state is not a one-sitting output but a validated artifact that may require multiple elicitation rounds.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose techniques explicitly and record the choice: SWOT (engagement cadence tool), PESTLE (macro-environment), capability mapping (what the org can do), value-chain analysis (where value is created), business model canvas (how value is captured). Justify the choice against the question being answered.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents default to SWOT and PESTLE without justification; naming better-fitting techniques (capability mapping, value-chain) produces richer current-state evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Task 2: Define Future State">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every goal in the future state must carry all six fields: metric, baseline, baseline_date, target, target_date, owner. Reject any goal missing a field or where baseline equals target. No "TBD" values — flag and re-elicit.</statement>
      <rationale>Goals with missing baselines cannot generate a gap analysis; goals where baseline equals target are hallucinated progress.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Future state must be signed off by the exec sponsor before risk assessment and strategy work begin.</statement>
      <rationale>Risk assessment and strategy options are meaningless without a locked future state; proceeding without sign-off wastes subsequent work when the target changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Task 3: Assess Risks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Produce two risk registers: risks of making the change AND risks of not making the change. Both are required by BABOK KA-6; an artifact with only one register is incomplete.</statement>
      <rationale>The "do nothing" risk register provides the baseline against which the change strategy is justified; omitting it makes the recommendation unconditional.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Task 4: Define Change Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Present at least three options (build, buy, partner, modify existing, status-quo / do nothing), each with cost-band, time-band, risk-rating, and capability-fit. Never omit the status-quo option — it is the leadership baseline.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents skip the status-quo option because it "feels weak"; without it the recommendation looks unconditional and cannot be challenged fairly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>A change strategy produces a strategy memo, not a plan. A memo has options, a recommendation, and a rationale. Gantt charts and sprint plans are downstream artifacts that belong in implementation-plan.md, not in the strategy.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents confuse strategy with plan; a 30-page implementation roadmap where a 3-page strategy memo was needed delays decisions by burying the recommendation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="KA-6 Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Solution-shaped business need: "we need a CRM" presented as the business need.</description>
      <reason>The framer must reject anything not outcome-shaped; require the stakeholder to state the problem the CRM solves before accepting the request.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Stale current-state artifact used without freshness check.</description>
      <reason>An agent should check last_validated_at and refuse to proceed if the artifact is older than 90 days; stale context produces gap analysis against a changed baseline.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Trace decay: requirements created after KA-6 have no traces_to the originating goal.</description>
      <reason>Pre-commit hook rejects orphan requirements; every requirement must carry a traces_to: GOAL-XX frontmatter entry.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/business-need-statement.md">Business need statement with strategic alignment and measurable success metrics</reference>
  <reference path="templates/gap-analysis.md">Gap analysis table across process, technology, people, and data dimensions</reference>
</text>
