<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="strategy-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for strategy-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Solution-shaped business need: "we need a CRM" presented as the business need.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The framer must reject anything not outcome-shaped; require the stakeholder to state the problem the CRM solves before accepting the request.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Goal hallucination — future-state agent invents measurable-looking goals ("reduce cost 30%") with no source quote.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require source_quote + source_doc per goal; reject any goal without a cited evidence span from an elicitation artifact.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Risk register monoculture — only "change risks" listed, no "do-nothing risks".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Encode both registers as required in the JSON schema; a validator rejects any risk output with only one register.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Vendor-biased options — when the change-strategy-agent has access to vendor docs, options drift toward those vendors.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force brainstorm divergence first; options must include build and status-quo before any vendor option is considered.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale current-state artifact used without freshness check.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>An agent should check last_validated_at and refuse to proceed if the artifact is older than 90 days; stale context produces gap analysis against a changed baseline.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Trace decay: requirements created after KA-6 have no traces_to the originating goal.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-commit hook rejects orphan requirements; every requirement must carry a traces_to: GOAL-XX frontmatter entry.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
