<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="reporting-basics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-agile</domain>
    <summary>Metrics framework, dashboard types, and KPI selection for project visibility across team, management, and executive audiences.</summary>
    <category>reporting</category>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>reporting</tag>
      <tag>dashboards</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>kpi</tag>
      <tag>visibility</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="dora-metrics"/>
      <ref slug="value-stream-management"/>
      <ref slug="predictive-analytics-pm"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Reporting Basics</title>

    <summary>Effective reporting transforms raw project data into actionable insights. This methodology covers metrics framework, dashboard types, and key performance indicators for project visibility.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Projects fail from information asymmetry — teams optimize for the wrong metrics, stakeholders lack visibility into delays until they are irreversible, and decisions are made on stale or incomplete data. Structured reporting with the right KPIs and dashboards for each audience (team, management, executive) closes the gap between execution and oversight.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Setting up new project visibility systems.</item>
        <item>Improving existing reporting capabilities.</item>
        <item>Creating stakeholder-specific dashboards.</item>
        <item>Selecting key metrics and KPIs.</item>
        <item>Replacing ad-hoc status emails with a recurring, audience-tailored dashboard.</item>
        <item>Establishing a metrics framework before introducing OKRs / NorthStar reporting.</item>
        <item>Auditing existing dashboards: which are read, which are stale, which to retire.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>The team has fewer than ~5 issues per week — manual updates are faster than dashboards.</item>
        <item>Highly research / discovery work where outputs are documents not tickets.</item>
        <item>Pre-revenue founder mode: a daily Slack message is cheaper.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="metrics-framework">
      <p>Metrics organize into four categories: delivery, quality, flow, and team. Select 1-2 from each category; over-instrumentation produces noise.</p>

      <section name="delivery-metrics">
        <p>Delivery metrics track output and predictability:</p>

        <list>
          <item>Velocity: Story points completed per sprint.</item>
          <item>Throughput: Issues completed per time period.</item>
          <item>Cycle time: Time from start to completion.</item>
          <item>Lead time: Time from request to delivery.</item>
          <item>Burndown: Work remaining in sprint.</item>
          <item>Burnup: Work completed over time.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="quality-metrics">
        <p>Quality metrics track defect rate and rework:</p>

        <list>
          <item>Escaped defects: Bugs found in production.</item>
          <item>Defect density: Bugs per story point.</item>
          <item>Rework rate: Reopened issues percentage.</item>
          <item>Test coverage: Code coverage percentage.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="flow-metrics">
        <p>Flow metrics expose bottlenecks and process health:</p>

        <list>
          <item>WIP: Work in progress count.</item>
          <item>Flow efficiency: Active time / total time.</item>
          <item>Cumulative flow: Status distribution over time.</item>
          <item>Aging WIP: Time items spend in each state.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="team-metrics">
        <p>Team metrics measure capacity and satisfaction:</p>

        <list>
          <item>Capacity utilization: Actual vs planned hours.</item>
          <item>Focus factor: Productive time ratio.</item>
          <item>Team happiness: Satisfaction score.</item>
          <item>Predictability: Commitment vs delivery.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="dashboard-types">
      <p>Dashboards are audience-specific. Design three: one for the team, one for management, one for executives. Avoid the trap of a single dashboard for all — each audience has different information needs and refresh cadence.</p>

      <section name="team-dashboard">
        <p>Purpose: Daily team visibility. Audience: developers, scrum master. Refresh: real-time.</p>

        <list>
          <item>Sprint burndown: remaining work by day.</item>
          <item>Sprint board: current sprint items (Kanban view).</item>
          <item>Blocker list: filter for blocked/dependencies.</item>
          <item>Team workload: issues per assignee (bar chart).</item>
          <item>Recent activity: last 24h updates (feed).</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="management-dashboard">
        <p>Purpose: Sprint/release status. Audience: product owner, managers. Refresh: hourly.</p>

        <list>
          <item>Sprint progress: percent complete (gauge).</item>
          <item>Velocity trend: last 6 sprints (line chart).</item>
          <item>Release burnup: scope vs completed (chart).</item>
          <item>Risk register: open risks (list).</item>
          <item>Milestone timeline: upcoming milestones (timeline).</item>
          <item>Blockers summary: blocked items count (count widget).</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="executive-dashboard">
        <p>Purpose: Portfolio health. Audience: executives, stakeholders. Refresh: daily.</p>

        <list>
          <item>Portfolio status: all projects health (status grid).</item>
          <item>Delivery confidence: on-track percentage (gauge).</item>
          <item>Resource allocation: team distribution (pie chart).</item>
          <item>Budget vs actual: cost tracking (bar chart).</item>
          <item>Key milestones: next 90 days (timeline).</item>
          <item>Risk heatmap: impact vs probability (matrix).</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="kpi-definitions">
      <p>Key Performance Indicators are the subset of metrics you track actively. Keep 5-7 per audience to prevent metric fatigue.</p>

      <section name="scrum-kpis">
        <p>For Scrum teams:</p>

        <list>
          <item>Velocity: SUM(story_points) WHERE sprint = X AND status = Done. Target: Trending up or stable. Display: line chart of last 10 sprints.</item>
          <item>Sprint commitment: completed_points / committed_points × 100. Target: ≥85%. Display: gauge.</item>
          <item>Sprint goal achieved: Count where sprint_goal = met. Target: 100%. Display: binary indicator.</item>
          <item>Escaped defects: bugs_in_production per sprint. Target: &lt;2. Display: number with trend.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="kanban-kpis">
        <p>For Kanban teams:</p>

        <list>
          <item>Throughput: COUNT(issues) WHERE completed_date in period. Target: Trending up. Display: bar chart (weekly).</item>
          <item>Cycle time: AVG(completed_date - started_date). Target: &lt;5 days. Display: histogram.</item>
          <item>WIP compliance: COUNT(issues in_progress) ≤ WIP_limit. Target: 100%. Display: percentage.</item>
          <item>Flow efficiency: active_time / (active_time + wait_time) × 100. Target: &gt;40%. Display: gauge.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="dashboard-design-principles">
      <p>Design dashboards with information hierarchy and visual consistency:</p>

      <section name="information-hierarchy">
        <list>
          <item>Level 1: Overall Health (traffic light red/yellow/green).</item>
          <item>Level 2: Key Metrics (absolute numbers).</item>
          <item>Level 3: Trend Charts (line/bar graphs).</item>
          <item>Level 4: Detailed Data (scrollable tables with drill-down).</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="color-coding">
        <list>
          <item>Green: On track, no issues.</item>
          <item>Yellow: At risk, needs attention.</item>
          <item>Red: Off track, requires escalation.</item>
          <item>Blue: Information, neutral.</item>
          <item>Gray: Not started, N/A.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="widget-layout">
        <p>Layout follows a three-tier pattern: main metric at top (large), secondary metric at top-right (medium), primary chart spanning the middle (wide), quick-stats row beneath (three small widgets), detailed table at bottom (scrollable).</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Proven patterns for dashboard design and maintenance:</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every widget must answer "which decision does this enable?" Strip widgets without an answer.</statement>
        <rationale>Widgets without a decision driver become status theater — pretty, ignored, never used for decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep top-level dashboards to ≤7 metrics; deeper detail lives one click down.</statement>
        <rationale>More than 7 metrics overload cognitive bandwidth and dilute attention from the critical few.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Tie green/yellow/red thresholds to the team's commitment, not industry averages.</statement>
        <rationale>Generic thresholds produce misleading signals. A threshold is actionable only if the team can influence it.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always show trend arrows next to absolute numbers; absolute alone is meaningless.</statement>
        <rationale>50 open issues is either excellent (trending down from 100) or a disaster (trending up from 25). Context matters.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Mobile-test executive dashboards — they get read in elevators and Ubers.</statement>
        <rationale>Executive dashboards will be viewed on smartphones; an untestable responsive design makes them useless at decision time.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Version dashboard configs in git; treat schema changes like code reviews.</statement>
        <rationale>Without version history, dashboards drift silently from reality. Git history provides the audit trail and rollback path.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Know your audience — tailor detail level and refresh cadence.</statement>
        <rationale>Executives need summary + trend; teams need real-time + blockers. One dashboard for all confuses everyone.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Lead with insights, not data. Dashboard title should be "On Track for Q2 Release" not "Velocity = 42".</statement>
        <rationale>Insights drive decisions; raw data requires interpretation and delays action.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Include recommended actions in dashboard context, not just metrics.</statement>
        <rationale>Red status without a next step frustrates stakeholders. Always pair status with recommended action.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Regular cadence — build trust through consistency. Report at the same time, on the same channel, every period.</statement>
        <rationale>Inconsistent reporting trains stakeholders to ignore it. Consistency builds trust and habit.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Review dashboard effectiveness quarterly: Are they read? Do they drive decisions? Retire stale dashboards.</statement>
        <rationale>Dashboards degrade over time as business questions change. Quarterly audits prevent rot.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Avoid vanity metrics (velocity without context, MTTR without incident count). All metrics must drive a decision.</statement>
        <rationale>Vanity metrics optimize teams for the metric, not the outcome, and destroy the signal-to-noise ratio.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Real-time refresh is rarely needed and quietly burns API quota. Refresh team dashboards hourly, management daily, executive weekly.</statement>
        <rationale>Constant refresh adds no value past a certain cadence and multiplies data-source load.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Use a Claude subagent to assemble the dashboard spec (which widgets, which audiences, which thresholds), then generate the queries / API calls / configuration as code. The agent maintains the spec doc; humans approve threshold changes. Run a weekly "dashboard hygiene" subagent that flags widgets that haven't been opened in N days.</p>

      <section name="recommended-subagents">
        <list>
          <item>faion-pm-agent — drafts dashboard specs per audience and KPI mapping.</item>
          <item>General-purpose Claude subagent — translates spec into Jira JQL, Linear filters, GitHub Projects views.</item>
          <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — stages dashboard config changes through review.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="prompt-patterns">
        <example type="good" title="Dashboard spec generation">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Given audience <executives|managers|team> and goal <X>, propose
5–7 widgets. For each, list: metric formula, data source, refresh
cadence, threshold for green/yellow/red, the decision it enables.
Reject any widget that has no decision attached.]]></code>
        </example>

        <example type="good" title="Dashboard audit">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Audit dashboards under <path>. For each widget output: last-opened
date, decisions made from it in last 90 days, recommendation
(KEEP / FIX / RETIRE) with one-line rationale.]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section name="agent-gotchas">
        <antipattern>
          <description>LLMs love to add charts. Constrain by max-widget count per audience.</description>
          <reason>More widgets = more cognitive load; agents default to comprehensive over focused. Set a hard limit in the prompt.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Agents will fabricate KPI formulas — require explicit data-source field names.</description>
          <reason>LLMs invent plausible-sounding formulas without verifying against actual schema. Always pass the schema as input and validate the output.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Forecasting from velocity needs ≥6 sprints of data; agents will project from 1–2 if not constrained.</description>
          <reason>Insufficient data produces unreliable forecasts. Explicitly require minimum data window in the prompt.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Avoid agents auto-filing Jira/Linear changes from dashboard rules; one bad rule cascades broadly.</description>
          <reason>Programmatic actions from dashboard insights create feedback loops and can cause unintended bulk changes. Always route through human approval.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Ensure the agent labels each metric as leading or lagging; it conflates them silently.</description>
          <reason>Leading (velocity, WIP) vs lagging (escaped defects, rework) metrics serve different purposes. Agents often mix them without distinction, producing misleading dashboards.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools for dashboard automation:</p>

      <list>
        <item>jira-cli — Run JQL, fetch sprint data (brew install ankitpokhrel/jira-cli/jira-cli)</item>
        <item>gh — GitHub Projects fields + issue export (brew install gh)</item>
        <item>glab — GitLab Boards data export (brew install glab)</item>
        <item>linear-cli — Linear cycles, issue exports (https://github.com/evangodon/lr)</item>
        <item>metabase-cli — Programmatic Metabase dashboards (pip install metabase-api)</item>
        <item>grafanactl — Grafana dashboards as code (https://grafana.com/docs/grafana/latest/cli/)</item>
      </list>

      <p>SaaS services with dashboard capability:</p>

      <list>
        <item>Jira Dashboards — SaaS, REST API. Native; gadget vocabulary is dated but functional.</item>
        <item>Linear Insights — SaaS, GraphQL API. Built-in flow metrics, natively understands cycle time.</item>
        <item>Metabase — OSS / SaaS, REST API. Best for SQL-backed dashboards with custom queries.</item>
        <item>Grafana — OSS, REST + JSON API. Strong for time-series + DORA-style metrics.</item>
        <item>Looker Studio — SaaS, API, free. Ties to Sheets/BigQuery; good for cost-conscious teams.</item>
        <item>Hex — SaaS, API. Notebook + dashboard hybrid; strong for exploratory analytics.</item>
        <item>Cumul.io / Plotly — SaaS, API. Embedding into product UI; white-label dashboard capability.</item>
        <item>GitHub Insights — SaaS, GraphQL API. Engineering-flow visibility on top of Projects.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="failure-modes">
      <p>Common pitfalls when implementing reporting systems:</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Reports become "status theater": pretty, ignored, never drive decisions.</description>
        <reason>Dashboards without clear decision points and audience alignment become ornamental. They must answer questions that stakeholders are actually asking.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Vanity metrics (velocity, MTTR-without-context) lead teams to optimize for the metric, not the outcome.</description>
        <reason>When teams are measured on a metric, they optimize for it. Velocity without outcome context incentivizes inflated estimates; MTTR without incident severity incentivizes fast-but-incomplete fixes.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Dashboards drift from reality once their data sources change schema.</description>
        <reason>Schema changes in issue trackers break dashboard queries silently. Version dashboard configs and re-validate after every schema change.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Executive dashboards over-aggregate; root-cause investigation still needs ticket-level access.</description>
        <reason>Aggregation loses signal. An executive dashboard that says "velocity is down" is useless without a path to investigate which issue category or assignee caused the drop.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Real-time refresh is rarely needed and quietly burns API quota.</description>
        <reason>The cost of constant polling is high; the value past a 1-hour cadence is low. Set refresh appropriately and monitor API usage.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="dora-metrics"/>
      <ref slug="value-stream-management"/>
      <ref slug="predictive-analytics-pm"/>
      <link href="https://www.perceptualedge.com/library.php">Information Dashboard Design — Stephen Few</link>
      <link href="https://dora.dev/">DORA metrics</link>
      <link href="https://www.scrum.org/resources/blog/agile-metrics">Scrum Metrics — Scrum.org</link>
      <link href="https://www.kanbanize.com/kanban-resources/kanban-analytics">Kanban Metrics</link>
      <link href="https://kanbanguides.org/">Kanban Guides — Kanban community</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
