<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ba-trends-summary">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-core</domain>
    <summary>Router for six BA trends (2025-2026) with triggers, routing matrix, paste-ready prompts, checklist, commands, and verification gates.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>trends</tag>
      <tag>routing</tag>
      <tag>2025-2026</tag>
      <tag>ba-practice</tag>
      <tag>skill-priorities</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>BA Trends Summary 2025-2026 (Routing Index)</title>

    <summary>Router for six BA trends (AI-enabled decisions, outcome strategy, responsible innovation, resilience, digital trust, sustainability) with concrete triggers, paste-ready prompt, checklist, and verification.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>BA practice is evolving across six identifiable vectors that cut across all traditional knowledge areas. A single index prevents agents from loading every sibling methodology on trend queries and allows rapid routing to the correct downstream methodology for actionable work.</p>
      <p>This file is intentionally a router, not a do-er: it owns triggers, routing rules, and a verify gate. The doing lives in the linked methodologies.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>User or agent message contains: "trend", "trending", "2025", "2026", "what's new in BA", "where should I focus", "skill priorities", "what to learn next".</item>
        <item>Initial orientation to ba-core before any specific methodology is selected.</item>
        <item>Quarterly skill-development planning: pick which 1-2 trends to invest in next.</item>
        <item>Triage: a vague stakeholder request mentions AI / ESG / resilience / privacy and you need to decide which methodology owns it.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Actionable BA work is requested (eliciting requirements, writing user stories, building a stakeholder map) — go directly to the linked methodology.</item>
        <item>You need prompts, checklists, or scripts for a specific technique — those live in the downstream methodologies, not here.</item>
        <item>Detailed framework content (BABOK tasks, BPMN rules, SWOT templates) — load the dedicated methodology instead.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="six-key-trends">
      <list>
        <item>AI-enabled decision making: integrating AI/ML outputs into business decisions and requirements processes. Route to: ai-enabled-business-analysis/.</item>
        <item>Outcome-driven strategy: shifting from feature delivery to measurable business outcomes and OKRs. Route to: strategy-methods/, strategy-analysis/.</item>
        <item>Responsible innovation: ethical frameworks, bias detection, and governance for AI-driven products. Route to: modern-ba-framework/, ba-governance/.</item>
        <item>Operational resilience: continuity planning, failure-mode analysis, and resilience by design. Route to: solution-assessment/, ba-planning/.</item>
        <item>Digital trust: data privacy, security requirements, and stakeholder trust as explicit BA concerns. Route to: ba-governance/, requirements-validation/.</item>
        <item>Sustainability integration: ESG requirements and sustainability metrics as first-class BA artifacts. Route to: strategy-methods/, modern-ba-framework/.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="trigger-to-methodology-map">
      <rule>
        <statement>Match the strongest keyword in the user message against the table; if two trends match, pick the one with the higher routing weight (AI-enabled &gt; digital-trust &gt; outcome-strategy &gt; responsible-innovation &gt; resilience &gt; sustainability).</statement>
        <rationale>Deterministic tie-breaking prevents oscillation between trends and produces reproducible routing across sessions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Keywords "AI", "ML", "copilot", "automation outcome", "model output" → ai-enabled-business-analysis.</item>
        <item>Keywords "OKR", "outcome", "north-star", "value driver", "KPI tree" → strategy-methods, strategy-analysis.</item>
        <item>Keywords "ethics", "bias", "fair", "explainable", "governance board" → modern-ba-framework, ba-governance.</item>
        <item>Keywords "resilience", "continuity", "failure mode", "BCP", "DR", "chaos" → solution-assessment, ba-planning.</item>
        <item>Keywords "privacy", "GDPR", "DPIA", "trust", "consent", "data residency" → ba-governance, requirements-validation.</item>
        <item>Keywords "ESG", "carbon", "sustainability", "scope-3", "green" → strategy-methods, modern-ba-framework.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="critical-success-factors">
      <list>
        <item>Data Quality: ~60% of AI projects fail due to poor data — validate data sources before requirements are written.</item>
        <item>Business Process Clarity: most enterprise AI fails without solid process documentation.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder Alignment: critical for adoption and value realization.</item>
        <item>Continuous Learning: technology evolution requires ongoing upskilling across all six trend areas.</item>
        <item>Ethical Framework: trust and governance are strategic differentiators, not compliance overhead.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="skill-priority-matrix">
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat this matrix as a routing aid only; for actionable skill development, go to the methodology linked under each trend.</statement>
        <rationale>Skill priorities are contextual; the matrix tells you where to start, not what to do.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>AI/ML Literacy — Critical, immediate. Route to: ai-enabled-business-analysis/.</item>
        <item>Data Analytics — High, immediate. Route to: data-driven-requirements/.</item>
        <item>Agile/Enterprise Agile Framework — High, ongoing. Route to: agile-ba-frameworks/.</item>
        <item>Process Mining — Medium, mid-term. Route to: process-mining-automation/.</item>
        <item>Automation Analysis — Medium, mid-term. Route to: process-mining-automation/.</item>
        <item>Strategic Thinking — High, continuous. Route to: strategy-analysis/, strategy-methods/.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <how-to>
      <step>Read the user's request and extract the dominant noun phrase (AI, OKR, ethics, resilience, privacy, ESG, etc.).</step>
      <step>Look up the phrase in the trigger-to-methodology map above; pick the methodology with the higher routing weight if multiple match.</step>
      <step>Stop loading this file. Open the target methodology with Read on `skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/&lt;target&gt;/methodology.xml`.</step>
      <step>If no trend matches, return to ba-core CLAUDE.md and pick by knowledge area instead (planning, elicitation, requirements, strategy, evaluation).</step>
      <step>Confirm the routing by stating: "Routing to &lt;slug&gt; because keyword X matched trend Y." This is the verification gate.</step>
    </how-to>

    <checklist>
      <check>Did the user message contain at least one trigger keyword from the map? If no, do not route via this file — use ba-core CLAUDE.md.</check>
      <check>Did you pick exactly one primary methodology (not a list)? Multi-route only when the user asks for a comparison.</check>
      <check>Did you state the matched keyword and the chosen trend in your response before opening the next file?</check>
      <check>Did you avoid loading any sibling methodology that is not in the routing target?</check>
      <check>Did you skip emitting prompts, templates, or step-by-step technique content from this file? (That work belongs to the downstream methodology.)</check>
    </checklist>

    <commands>
      <command name="open-target">Read skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/&lt;target-slug&gt;/methodology.xml</command>
      <command name="list-siblings">ls skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/</command>
      <command name="validate-this-file">python3 scripts/validate-methodology-xml.py skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/ba-trends-summary/methodology.xml</command>
    </commands>

    <prompt purpose="route-ba-trend-question"><![CDATA[
You are a BA routing agent. Given a user message, output a single JSON object:
{
  "matched_keyword": "<exact phrase from user message>",
  "trend": "ai-enabled | outcome-strategy | responsible-innovation | resilience | digital-trust | sustainability",
  "primary_methodology": "<slug from ba-core>",
  "secondary_methodology": "<slug or null>",
  "confidence": "high | medium | low",
  "reason": "<one sentence>"
}

Rules:
- Use only methodology slugs that exist under skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/.
- If no keyword matches the six trends, set trend=null and primary_methodology=null and ask a clarifying question.
- Tie-break order: ai-enabled > digital-trust > outcome-strategy > responsible-innovation > resilience > sustainability.

User message:
<<<
{{user_message}}
>>>
]]></prompt>

    <template path="inline:trend-routing-decision-record">
      <p>Lightweight decision record the agent appends to its scratchpad after routing:</p>
    </template>
    <example type="good" title="trend-routing-decision-record">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Trend Routing Decision

- Date: 2026-05-01
- User asked: "How do we add explainability to our AI loan-decision flow?"
- Matched keyword: "explainability"
- Trend: responsible-innovation
- Primary methodology: modern-ba-framework
- Secondary methodology: ba-governance
- Confidence: high
- Next action: Read modern-ba-framework/methodology.xml; do not load this file again this session.
]]></code>
    </example>

    <verify>
      <step>Run: `python3 scripts/validate-methodology-xml.py skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/ba-trends-summary/methodology.xml` and confirm exit code 0.</step>
      <step>Confirm the response contains exactly one primary methodology slug, and that slug appears as a sibling directory under ba-core/.</step>
      <step>Confirm no technique-level content (templates, prompts beyond the routing one above, framework rules) was emitted from this file.</step>
      <step>Confirm the matched keyword is quoted verbatim from the user message in the response.</step>
      <step>If the user follow-up requests technique-level work, switch to the downstream methodology and stop quoting this router.</step>
    </verify>

    <warning>Do not use this file as the source of truth for technique content. It is a router. If the agent finds itself drafting requirements, prompts, or frameworks while this file is open, it has already taken a wrong turn — close it and load the routed methodology instead.</warning>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="ai-enabled-business-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="agile-ba-frameworks"/>
      <ref slug="process-mining-automation"/>
      <ref slug="data-driven-requirements"/>
      <ref slug="modern-ba-framework"/>
      <ref slug="ba-strategic-partnership"/>
      <ref slug="ba-governance"/>
      <ref slug="strategy-methods"/>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="solution-assessment"/>
      <ref slug="ba-planning"/>
      <ref slug="requirements-validation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
