<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Spatial Accessibility Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding spatial accessibility audits. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="two-modalities-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every spatial interaction MUST support at least 2 independent input modalities chosen from {gaze+dwell, voice, single-hand, two-hand, controller, switch}. If hand-tracking is primary, the second modality MUST NOT be gaze+dwell alone.</statement>
      <rationale source="W3C XAUR — XR Accessibility User Requirements">Motor limitations, gloves, controllers-only environments, and hand-tracking failures all eliminate single-modality paths. Two independent modalities ensure at least one remains viable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="non-spatial-fallback" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every critical user flow MUST have a non-spatial fallback path: flat-window mode, companion app, or voice-only invocation. Skip-conditions MUST be documented per flow.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG visionOS accessibility">Users unable to tolerate immersion or lacking room-scale space cannot be excluded from core functionality without an alternative path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="seated-mode-parity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every interaction that works in standing mode MUST also work seated. UI MUST reposition to seated eye-height (1.0-1.2 m above ground) when seated mode is active; required upward gaze MUST NOT exceed 20 degrees above horizontal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta VRC.PC.UX — accessibility checks">Enterprise XR, rehabilitation contexts, and users with mobility impairments require seated parity. Sustained upward head tilt causes neck fatigue within minutes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="comfort-options-both" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Locomotion MUST offer BOTH vignette and teleport options; smooth-only locomotion is forbidden. Snap-turn and smooth-turn MUST both be available. Defaults are platform-recommended but user-overridable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta Quest Documentation — comfort best practices">Motion-sickness triggers differ per user; no single solution fixes nausea universally. Configurable options are the only reliable accommodation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="captions-policy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spatial captions MUST default to head-locked subtitles at ~3 m apparent distance. A world-locked option with size + contrast slider MUST be available. Audio descriptions MUST be provided for visually-encoded meaning.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG visionOS accessibility — captions">Head-locked captions are readable during motion; world-locked captions are immersive but unreadable in motion. Defaults favour readability; override favours immersion.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="hardware-tester-mix" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before declaring spatial accessibility compliance, hardware testing MUST include ≥1 low-vision, ≥1 motor-impaired, and ≥1 motion-sensitive tester. Synthetic-only testing is forbidden as compliance evidence.</statement>
      <rationale source="XR Access Initiative — guidance">No automated tool can substitute for real user validation in spatial contexts. Comfort settings that "feel fine" to designers routinely fail real users with vestibular disorders.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
