<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-rules" title="Spatial Accessibility Rules and Input Modality Requirements">
  <summary>Mandatory rules for accessible spatial UI: every interaction needs two input modalities, a non-spatial fallback, and seated-mode parity; comfort and caption requirements are enumerated.</summary>

  <section title="Input Modality Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every spatial interaction must support at least two independent input modalities; one must not be gaze-and-dwell if hand tracking is the primary.</statement>
      <rationale>Motor limitations, gloves, controllers-only environments, and hand-tracking failures all eliminate single-modality paths. Two independent modalities ensure at least one remains viable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a non-spatial fallback (flat-window mode, companion app, or voice-only path) for every critical user flow.</statement>
      <rationale>Users unable to tolerate immersion or lacking the physical space for room-scale interaction cannot be excluded from core functionality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Select object: gaze-and-pinch (primary), voice command "select" (secondary), controller trigger (tertiary). Flat-window fallback for seated users without hand tracking.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Select object: grab gesture only. No alternative; users with motor impairment or low-FOV devices are locked out.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Seated Mode">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every interaction that works standing must also work from a seated position; document any exception with an explicit accommodation alternative.</statement>
      <rationale>Enterprise XR, rehabilitation contexts, and users with mobility impairments require seated-mode parity. "Designed for standing" without a seated path excludes a legally-protected population in regulated industries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Reposition UI to seated eye-height (approximately 1.0-1.2 m above ground) when seated mode is active; do not require the user to look up beyond 20° above horizontal.</statement>
      <rationale>Sustained upward head tilt causes neck fatigue within minutes; ergonomic guidelines for standing-height UI are not appropriate in seated contexts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Comfort and Captions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Offer both vignette and teleport locomotion; never force a single comfort solution — comfort is individually variable.</statement>
      <rationale>Motion sickness triggers differ per user. Smooth locomotion causes nausea in some; snap-turn triggers others. Configurable options are the only reliable accommodation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Default spatial captions to head-locked subtitles at 3 m apparent distance; provide a world-locked option with size and contrast controls.</statement>
      <rationale>Head-locked captions are readable in motion but break immersion. World-locked captions are immersive but unreadable during fast motion. Defaults favour readability; override favours immersion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide audio descriptions for all cinematic and interactive XR moments that convey meaning through visuals alone.</statement>
      <rationale>VoiceOver on visionOS covers only partial screen content; hand-authored audio descriptions remain required for blind users in immersive contexts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/alt-input-matrix.ts">TypeScript auditor: checks each interaction has minimum 2 input modalities</reference>
  </section>
</text>
