<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Spatial Accessibility Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns repeatedly observed in spatial-product audits. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="controller-only-defaults" severity="high">
      <symptom>Interactions assume Quest Touch controllers; hand-tracking-only Vision Pro users cannot complete grab/select; store review rejects submission.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Internal — observed in cross-platform XR ports">Author defaulted to controller-only assumptions without enumerating alternatives; LLMs trained on older XR docs amplify the bias.</root-cause>
      <fix>Run `templates/alt-input-matrix.ts` audit. Every interaction must list ≥2 modalities. Add explicit hand-tracking + voice paths where controllers are primary.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="head-locked-hud" severity="high">
      <symptom>Always-visible HUD locked to head. Vision Pro store review fails ("UI must not be head-locked"); Quest users report nausea.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Apple HIG visionOS — head-locked content forbidden">Author followed legacy XR docs from pre-visionOS era; LLM recommended head-locked from training data.</root-cause>
      <fix>Use head-locked-with-decay or world-locked + recenter affordance. Head-locked allowed only for critical telemetry (battery, safety warnings).</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="synthetic-only-testing" severity="high">
      <symptom>Compliance declared from automated checklists; first real user with vestibular disorder experiences nausea on day-1 demo.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="XR Access Initiative — guidance">Author treated synthetic XR a11y tools as sufficient; comfort thresholds tuned to designer baseline, not user variance.</root-cause>
      <fix>Recruit ≥1 low-vision + 1 motor-impaired + 1 motion-sensitive tester per major release. Block compliance claim until hardware testing log exists.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="head-locked-captions-default-off" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Captions default to world-locked at 5 m; deaf user in moving scene cannot read; complaints filed.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Apple HIG visionOS — captions readability">Author defaulted to "immersive" placement without considering motion legibility.</root-cause>
      <fix>Default captions to head-locked ~3 m. Expose world-locked as an opt-in with size + contrast slider. Audio descriptions mandatory for visually-encoded meaning.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
