<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="spatial-accessibility Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for spatial-accessibility as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs defaulting to controller-only assumptions without enumerating alternatives explicitly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Controllers are unavailable or unusable in many spatial contexts. Force the agent to enumerate all modality alternatives for each interaction rather than assuming a default input path.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent recommending head-locked HUD as a standard pattern from older XR literature.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Apple HIG visionOS forbids head-locked UI; Meta guidelines strongly discourage it for non-telemetry use. Current guidance is the opposite of legacy XR documentation that LLMs were trained on.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Declaring spatial accessibility compliance without hardware testing on real assistive users.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Synthetic XR a11y testing tools are immature. Motion sickness is individually variable and cannot be detected by static analysis. Only real-user hardware testing produces valid compliance evidence.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent recommending head-locked captions universally without considering immersion context.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Caption placement reasoning is poor in current LLMs. Head-locked captions are readable but break immersion; world-locked captions are immersive but unreadable in motion. Heuristics plus human review are required.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
