<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="mobile-ux Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for mobile-ux. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Design for the smallest screen first. Identify the core content and single primary action for mobile. Add enhancements for tablet and desktop. Never start from desktop and scale down.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Scaling down a desktop design produces tiny targets, broken layouts, and stripped-out content. Starting from mobile forces honest prioritization — if something is important enough to show on mobile, it belongs; if not, it is secondary content for larger screens.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One primary action per screen is a hard constraint, not a guideline. Two equally weighted CTAs on a mobile screen must be split into separate screens or redesigned to establish clear primary/secondary hierarchy.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mobile users have partial attention and small screens. Competing actions produce decision paralysis and reduce conversion. The constraint forces product discipline about what matters most at each step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Minimum touch target size: 44x44pt on iOS, 48x48dp on Android. Minimum spacing between adjacent targets: 8px. These are hard minimums, not recommendations.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Touch input is imprecise. Targets below minimum size produce tap errors, frustration, and accessibility failures. Adjacent targets without spacing cause accidental activation of the wrong element.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Place primary actions in the thumb zone — the bottom third of the screen for one-handed use. Place destructive or rarely-needed actions at the top (hard to reach).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Thumb zone models from Steven Hoober's research show 75% of mobile interaction uses one hand. Bottom-zone placement reduces reach error and fatigue for primary actions. Top placement for destructive actions provides natural friction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use bottom tab bar (3-5 items) as the primary navigation pattern for mobile apps. Reserve hamburger menus for secondary or overflow navigation only.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Bottom tab bars consistently outperform hamburger menus on discoverability in usability studies. Hamburgers hide navigation behind a tap, reducing awareness of available sections and increasing navigation errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set correct input type attributes on all form fields: type="email" for email, type="tel" for phone, type="number" for numeric input, type="search" for search. Never disable zoom (user-scalable=no).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Correct input types trigger the right mobile keyboard, reducing form errors significantly. Disabling zoom is an accessibility violation and is blocked by Safari since iOS 10.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Target Core Web Vitals: LCP &lt; 2.5s, FID &lt; 100ms, CLS &lt; 0.1, TTI &lt; 5s. Serve WebP images with srcset/sizes. Lazy-load below-fold content. Never serve retina images to low-bandwidth connections without srcset.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">53% of mobile users abandon pages taking over 3 seconds. Each 1-second delay reduces conversions by ~7%. CLS above 0.1 causes mis-taps when content shifts during load. WebP with srcset reduces image payload by 25-35% vs JPEG without quality loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Design platform-specific interaction patterns where they differ: iOS uses bottom tabs and swipe-from-edge back navigation; Android uses bottom nav bar and back gesture or button. Never assume one platform's gesture behavior on the other.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Users have trained gestures from their OS. Swipe-from-left-edge is iOS back navigation; on Android it may trigger a drawer. Building cross-platform patterns without accounting for these differences causes gesture conflicts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use only standard platform gestures. Always provide a visible alternative (button or link) for every gesture-based action. Never invent non-standard gestures without visible affordances.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Custom gestures are undiscoverable. Users have no way to know they exist without explicit hints. Standard gestures work because users have learned them from the OS; novel gestures require onboarding that most users skip.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build mobile as the baseline with core functionality and touch-optimization. Add tablet enhancements (side panels, more visible content). Add desktop enhancements (full navigation, multi-column, keyboard shortcuts) only after mobile baseline is complete.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Enhancement tiers prevent mobile from being treated as a stripped-down desktop version. The mobile tier is complete and functional on its own; larger screens receive additive enhancements, not different products.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Support VoiceOver (iOS) and TalkBack (Android). Respect system text-size settings — never use absolute units that break at 150-200% text scale. Respect prefers-reduced-motion for animations.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">15% of users rely on screen readers at some point. Large text size settings are common among older users and low-vision users. Breaking text scaling or ignoring reduced-motion preferences excludes significant user populations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
