<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-platform" title="Platform Differences, Gestures, and Progressive Enhancement">
  <summary>iOS vs Android design differences, standard gesture vocabulary, progressive enhancement tiers, and mobile accessibility requirements.</summary>

  <section title="iOS vs Android Differences">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design platform-specific interaction patterns where they differ: iOS uses bottom tabs and swipe-from-edge back navigation; Android uses bottom nav bar and back gesture or button. Never assume one platform's gesture behavior on the other.</statement>
      <rationale>Users have trained gestures from their OS. Swipe-from-left-edge is iOS back navigation; on Android it may trigger a drawer. Building cross-platform patterns without accounting for these differences causes gesture conflicts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>iOS: bottom tab bar, back via left-edge swipe, sheets from bottom, 44pt targets</item>
      <item>Android: bottom navigation, back via gesture or system button, full-screen dialogs, 48dp targets</item>
      <item>iOS: right side for primary actions; Android: Floating Action Button for primary creation action</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Standard Gesture Vocabulary">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use only standard platform gestures. Always provide a visible alternative (button or link) for every gesture-based action. Never invent non-standard gestures without visible affordances.</statement>
      <rationale>Custom gestures are undiscoverable. Users have no way to know they exist without explicit hints. Standard gestures work because users have learned them from the OS; novel gestures require onboarding that most users skip.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Tap: select or activate</item>
      <item>Long press: context menu or selection mode</item>
      <item>Swipe horizontal: navigate between views or reveal row actions</item>
      <item>Swipe vertical: scroll</item>
      <item>Pinch: zoom</item>
      <item>Pull down: refresh (always pair with a visible refresh button)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Progressive Enhancement Tiers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build mobile as the baseline with core functionality and touch-optimization. Add tablet enhancements (side panels, more visible content). Add desktop enhancements (full navigation, multi-column, keyboard shortcuts) only after mobile baseline is complete.</statement>
      <rationale>Enhancement tiers prevent mobile from being treated as a stripped-down desktop version. The mobile tier is complete and functional on its own; larger screens receive additive enhancements, not different products.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Mobile Accessibility">
    <rule>
      <statement>Support VoiceOver (iOS) and TalkBack (Android). Respect system text-size settings — never use absolute units that break at 150-200% text scale. Respect prefers-reduced-motion for animations.</statement>
      <rationale>15% of users rely on screen readers at some point. Large text size settings are common among older users and low-vision users. Breaking text scaling or ignoring reduced-motion preferences excludes significant user populations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Shrinking desktop design to fit mobile viewport instead of redesigning for mobile context</description>
      <reason>Produces tiny touch targets, cramped layouts, and forced-zoom content. Mobile is a different context requiring different information hierarchy, not a smaller copy of the desktop layout.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skeleton screens replaced with generic spinners for content-heavy pages</description>
      <reason>Skeleton screens reduce perceived load time for known-layout content because they set accurate expectations. Generic spinners with unknown duration increase perceived wait times and anxiety.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
