<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Quality Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the quality-management methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="dod-as-code" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock DoD per repo in quality/dod.yaml and version it — agents and CI read the file, not human prose.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — DoD drift audits">Human-prose DoD drifts within weeks; machine-readable file enforced by CI makes 'done' unambiguous and diff-auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="must-vs-should-split" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Separate must items from should items in DoD; only must items block merge — should items open a follow-up issue automatically.</statement>
      <rationale source="Team-velocity field experience">A DoD that blocks every item becomes a bypass incentive under pressure; the split preserves coverage and velocity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="twice-not-duplicated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run quality gates twice: pre-commit (fast — lint, format) and pre-merge (full — tests, coverage, security scan). Do not duplicate slow checks.</statement>
      <rationale source="CI / pre-commit practice">Duplicating slow checks kills developer velocity; checking only late creates surprises. The split is the correct trade-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="escape-rate-leading-indicator" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track defect escape rate (bugs found in production / total bugs) as a leading indicator; apply SPC charting to distinguish signal from noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="Quality-engineering practice (Deming SPC)">A single defect count is a lagging snapshot; escape rate trend exposes whether the quality system is improving or degrading.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="higher-bar-for-agent-code" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For agent-written code, require 90%+ coverage, mutation testing on critical modules, no warning suppressions without explanatory comment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — agent-code quality audits">LLM-generated code requires higher scrutiny; mutation testing reveals tautological tests that pad coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-auto-skip-na" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>N/a tags on DoD items require explicit human approval; the agent cannot auto-skip.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — DoD escape audits">N/a bypass is the most exploited DoD escape hatch.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>One-person prototype before product-market fit — quality gates slow validation</item>
      <item>Spike or research code marked throwaway — formal QC inflates effort 2-3x</item>
      <item>When the team rejects DoD as ceremony — fix the trust issue first</item>
      <item>Aesthetic UX polish — use design review, not quality management process</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
