<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Quality Management — Framework and Three Processes">
  <summary>The Plan-Manage-Control quality triad, quality concepts, metrics taxonomy, and the machine-readable DoD pattern.</summary>

  <section title="Quality Concepts">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build quality in through prevention; do not test it in through detection — prevention costs 10-100x less than production defect resolution.</statement>
      <rationale>Deming's empirical finding from manufacturing: defects found at code review cost a fraction of defects found in production. Every skipped review is a deferred cost with interest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Quality = degree to which requirements are met (not "high quality" — that conflates grade with conformance).</item>
      <item>Grade = category of features (premium vs. basic); low grade is a business decision, not a defect.</item>
      <item>Prevention = building quality in (code review, pair programming, TDD).</item>
      <item>Detection = finding defects after they exist (testing, inspections, UAT) — necessary but more expensive than prevention.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Three Quality Processes">
    <list>
      <item>Plan Quality (before work begins): define standards, metrics, and targets. Lock in quality/dod.yaml per repo.</item>
      <item>Manage Quality (assurance, during work): ensure processes produce quality — code reviews, DoD enforcement, automated testing requirements, retrospectives.</item>
      <item>Control Quality (verification, at completion): verify deliverables meet standards — testing, inspections, defect tracking.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Metrics Taxonomy">
    <list>
      <item>Product metrics: performance, reliability, usability, defect escape rate.</item>
      <item>Process metrics: code coverage %, code review completion rate, DoD compliance %, defect density.</item>
      <item>Perception metrics: customer satisfaction (NPS, CSAT), uptime SLA, response time SLO.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track defect escape rate (bugs found in production / total bugs) as a leading indicator; apply SPC charting to distinguish signal from noise.</statement>
      <rationale>A single defect count is a lagging snapshot; escape rate trend exposes whether the quality system is improving or degrading before customer impact accumulates.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Definition of Done as Code">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock DoD per repo in quality/dod.yaml and version it — agents and CI read the file, not human prose.</statement>
      <rationale>Human-prose DoD drift within weeks of authoring; a machine-readable file enforced by CI makes "done" unambiguous and diff-auditable when the team updates standards.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate must items from should items in DoD; only must items block merge — should items open a follow-up issue automatically.</statement>
      <rationale>A DoD that blocks on every item becomes a bypass incentive under delivery pressure; the must/should split preserves coverage while maintaining merge velocity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/dod.yaml">Machine-readable DoD schema</reference>
    <reference path="templates/dod-validator.py">PR gate script enforcing the DoD</reference>
  </section>
</text>
