<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-tools-and-references" title="Quality Management — Tools, Services, and References">
  <summary>CLI tools, SaaS services, best practices, and references for automated quality management.</summary>

  <section title="CLI Tools">
    <list>
      <item>sonar-scanner — static analysis, code smells, coverage (https://docs.sonarsource.com)</item>
      <item>ruff — Python lint + format; replaces black + flake8 (pip install ruff)</item>
      <item>eslint — JS/TS lint (npm i -D eslint)</item>
      <item>pytest --cov — Python coverage (pip install pytest-cov)</item>
      <item>c8 / nyc — JS/TS coverage (npm i -D c8)</item>
      <item>mutmut / stryker — mutation testing for critical modules (pip install mutmut / npm i -D @stryker-mutator/core)</item>
      <item>gitleaks — secret scanning; required in the quality gate (https://github.com/gitleaks/gitleaks)</item>
      <item>semgrep — pattern-based static analysis (https://semgrep.dev)</item>
      <item>trivy — container/SBOM vulnerability scan (https://aquasecurity.github.io/trivy)</item>
      <item>gh pr checks — read CI quality gate status (https://cli.github.com)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Services">
    <list>
      <item>SonarQube / SonarCloud — Web API for issues, quality gates, coverage; OSS and SaaS options.</item>
      <item>Codacy — REST API, multi-language analysis (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Code Climate — maintainability + test coverage, GitHub-native (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Codecov — coverage trend API, PR comments (SaaS).</item>
      <item>Sentry / OSS — defect-in-prod telemetry, API for events; rate-limits apply during spikes.</item>
      <item>BrowserStack — cross-browser test runs via API; physical device testing.</item>
      <item>TestRail — test case management, REST API; seat-priced.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-tune quality gates quarterly using lead-time and defect data — gates that are too strict kill velocity; gates that are too loose allow silent degradation.</statement>
      <rationale>Quality cost is U-shaped: the optimal gate tightness shifts as the codebase matures and team size changes. Quarterly calibration prevents ossification.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For agent-generated code, raise coverage bar to 90% and require mutation testing on critical modules — LLM-generated tests often pass coverage but miss edge cases.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs produce plausible-looking tests that assert tautologies; mutation testing reveals whether assertions actually catch defects.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="References">
    <list>
      <item>ISO 9001:2015 — quality management systems</item>
      <item>PMBoK 7th — Delivery Performance Domain</item>
      <item>W.E. Deming, "Out of the Crisis" (1986) — prevention over inspection</item>
      <item>Capers Jones, "Software Quality in 2024" — defect economics</item>
      <item>Google SRE Workbook, ch. 4 — SLOs and quality</item>
      <item>Sibling methodologies: change-control/, code-review/, usability-testing/</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
