<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-section-rules" title="Spec Section Rules and Traceability">
  <summary>Required 14 sections, persona rules, user story format, and FR traceability chain requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Required Sections">
    <rule>
      <statement>A full spec must include all 14 sections: Overview, Problem Statement, User Personas, User Stories, Functional Requirements, Non-Functional Requirements, Acceptance Criteria, Out of Scope, Assumptions and Constraints, Dependencies, Related Features, Recommended Skills, Open Questions, Appendix.</statement>
      <rationale>Omitting any section creates a predictable gap: no Personas → generic user stories; no Out of Scope → scope creep in every session; no Assumptions → conflicting implementations.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Problem Statement must answer: Who (target user group), Problem (what they face), Impact (business or user cost), Solution (high-level approach), Success Metric (how to measure the feature succeeded).</statement>
      <rationale>A problem statement without a success metric produces a feature with no clear done criterion. Agents and developers optimize toward undefined targets without it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Persona Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write 2-3 personas with name, role, goals, pain points, and usage context. Reference personas by name in user stories and acceptance criteria.</statement>
      <rationale>Named personas prevent "As a user" stories that apply to nobody specifically. Referencing them in AC forces scenario specificity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Persona defined in section 3 but never referenced in user stories or AC.</description>
      <reason>Orphan personas provide no filtering signal. If a persona is not referenced in at least one user story, either the persona is unnecessary or the user stories are too generic.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Traceability Chain">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every Functional Requirement must trace to at least one User Story (FR-X → US-Y). Every Acceptance Criterion must trace to at least one FR (AC-Z → FR-X). No FR may exist without a US parent. No AC may exist without an FR parent.</statement>
      <rationale>Orphan requirements indicate either gold-plating (FR with no user story) or untestable design (FR with no AC). The chain ensures every requirement serves a stated user need and has a verifiable completion check.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[### FR-001: Add item to cart
Traces to: US-001 (As Sarah, I want to add products to cart with one click)

**AC-001** (validates FR-001):
Given Sarah is on a product page,
When she clicks "Add to Cart",
Then the cart count increments by 1 and a confirmation toast appears.

**AC-002** (validates FR-001):
Given the product is out of stock,
When Sarah clicks "Add to Cart",
Then the button is disabled and shows "Out of Stock".]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Out of Scope Documentation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every Out of Scope item must include: feature name, one-sentence reason it is excluded, and a "when" (Phase N, v2, never). Do not include items without all three fields.</statement>
      <rationale>Items without explicit exclusion reasoning re-emerge in every planning session. The "when" prevents permanent exclusion from being confused with deferred scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
