<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-nfr-and-ac" title="NFR Measurability and Acceptance Criteria Coverage">
  <summary>NFR measurability rules, acceptance criteria coverage matrix, and agent-specific antipatterns for both.</summary>

  <section title="NFR Measurability">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every NFR must specify: quantifiable target, measurement approach (how to measure), and validation method (how to test). NFRs without quantifiable targets must be rejected and rewritten before spec approval.</statement>
      <rationale>"System should be fast" is not an NFR — it is a preference. Without a number, neither developers nor agents can know when the requirement is met.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[### NFR-001: Add to Cart Latency
**Requirement:** Add to cart operation SHALL complete in < 200ms at p95.
**Measurement:** Client-side total time from click to UI update (Performance API).
**Priority:** Must
**Validation:** Load test with 500 concurrent users, measure p95 latency.]]></code>
    </example>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent writes NFR as "The system should handle high traffic" or "Response times should be acceptable".</description>
      <reason>LLMs produce qualitative NFR language because they lack knowledge of the specific system's performance profile. Require the agent to propose a specific number and explicitly mark it [estimate] — then the human validates or corrects the target.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Acceptance Criteria Coverage">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each functional requirement, acceptance criteria must cover: happy path, at least one error case, at least one edge case (boundary condition or empty state). For security-sensitive FRs, add an unauthorized access scenario.</statement>
      <rationale>Specs with only happy path AC produce features that break on first error condition in production. The coverage matrix forces specification of failure behavior before implementation begins.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Use Given-When-Then format for all acceptance criteria. Avoid free-form prose AC. "Works correctly" is not an acceptance criterion.</statement>
      <rationale>Given-When-Then enforces testability. Each field maps directly to a test: Given = test setup, When = action, Then = assertion. Prose AC requires interpretation, causing inconsistent test coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>AC covers only the happy path for all FRs, with no error or edge cases.</description>
      <reason>Agents default to positive-case thinking. Explicitly require error scenarios for every FR that involves user input, external calls, or state transitions. Ask: "What happens when this fails?"</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Assumptions Documentation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document every assumption that, if wrong, would require a spec change. Format: "Assumption: [statement]. If wrong: [consequence]."</statement>
      <rationale>Hidden assumptions are the primary source of mid-development spec surprises. Making the "if wrong" consequence explicit accelerates discovery of invalid assumptions during review.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
