<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="predictive-analytics-pm Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for predictive-analytics-pm. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use a classical ML model (gradient boosting, Cox hazard, Prophet) for point forecasts and confidence intervals; use an LLM only for the plain-language analyst brief that accompanies the model output. Never use an LLM as the forecasting engine.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs asked "predict when this will finish" hallucinate confident dates without uncertainty quantification. Deterministic estimators produce calibrated probabilities that can be monitored for drift; LLM forecasts cannot be calibrated or monitored.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deploy only a model that beats naive baselines (last-3-sprint velocity, mean cycle time) on a holdout set with statistical significance. Measure calibration with Brier score; reject any model with Brier score above 0.20.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">An uncalibrated model emitting "70% likely to slip" with no empirical basis is worse than intuition — it provides false confidence and cannot be improved without calibration data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Retrain on a fixed monthly cadence AND on drift triggers (team composition change, process change, scope change). Track both; log every forecast with input snapshot for post-hoc audit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Concept drift makes yesterday's model stale within months of the first organizational change. Silent drift produces confident wrong forecasts that PM teams stop trusting — then stop using.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require human approval for any action triggered by a forecast: resource reallocation, scope pull, escalation, or replanning. Agents emit recommendations only — never autonomous actions on forecast output.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Auto-actioning a forecast creates feedback loops in the training data (the intervention changes the outcome, invalidating future calibration) and bypasses judgment calls that require organizational context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Aggregate all analytics at team or program level; refuse to generate per-person productivity metrics from issue data.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Per-person metrics from issue trackers are an HR and legal risk (GDPR, labor law, union agreements in some regions). They also incentivize gaming the data at the individual level, destroying the signal entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define the decision the forecast supports before training; if no decision changes with the forecast, do not build it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Forecasting without a decision context produces shelf-ware dashboards that stakeholders ignore.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start with naive baselines (last-3-sprints velocity, mean cycle time) — only ship a model that beats them on holdout, with statistical significance.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Naive baselines set the bar; a model that fails this test has no value to add.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Calibrate probabilistic outputs; report both the prediction and its reliability diagram each release.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stakeholders need to understand both the forecast and how much to trust it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always include feature attribution (SHAP) in stakeholder briefs; opaque scores destroy trust.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">PMs and executives need to understand the drivers behind a forecast to act on it with confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Retrain on a fixed cadence (monthly) AND on drift triggers; track both.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Regular retraining keeps the model synchronized with team evolution; drift triggers catch sudden changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Human-in-the-loop for any action — model recommends, human decides — especially for resource changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Organizational decisions require context and judgment that models cannot provide.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Aggregate at team or program level, not per individual; prevents misuse for performance management.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Individual metrics invite HR abuse and destroy psychological safety on teams.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Log every forecast with input snapshot for post-hoc audit; PM forecasts are revisited frequently.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Forecasts improve when you track what you predicted, what happened, and why. Audit logs enable retrospectives.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pair predictive output with value-stream-management flow metrics and dora-metrics for triangulation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Multiple signals strengthen forecasting confidence and catch model edge cases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document model assumptions in a model card; PMs and execs need to understand limits.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Model cards prevent overconfidence and set realistic expectations for forecast reliability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r16" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use dvc for dataset and model version control, mlflow for experiment tracking and model registry.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Reproducibility and version control prevent duplicate work and enable rollback on drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
