<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-antipatterns" title="Predictive Analytics in PM — Seven Antipatterns">
  <summary>The seven most common failure modes when applying ML-based forecasting to project management, from garbage-in data quality to per-person productivity abuse.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Garbage-in status fields — "In Progress" means "abandoned" or "waiting for review" depending on the team member.</description>
      <reason>Every metric computed from inconsistent status fields lies. A model trained on this data will forecast confidently based on noise. Data quality discipline is a prerequisite to any forecasting investment.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Concept drift ignored — model trained on Q1 team composition and process used in Q4 after three re-orgs and a process overhaul.</description>
      <reason>ML models learn the statistical regularities of a specific team and process. When the team or process changes significantly, the model's learned patterns are no longer valid. Silent drift produces increasingly wrong but equally confident forecasts.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Survivorship bias — training data includes only completed projects, excluding cancelled and silent-fail projects.</description>
      <reason>Cancelled projects carry the failure patterns the model most needs to learn. A dataset of completions only under-predicts cancellation risk and over-predicts completion probability.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Uncalibrated probabilities — model emits "70% likely to slip" without a calibration dataset to validate that claim.</description>
      <reason>An uncalibrated probability is an opinion dressed as a number. PM teams that make budget or scope decisions on uncalibrated confidence intervals will be systematically misled.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Causal claims from correlational features — "long descriptions correlate with overrun" → PM bans long descriptions.</description>
      <reason>Correlation in issue data is not causal. Intervening on a correlate without understanding the mechanism often removes a useful signal without changing the underlying cause.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Per-person productivity metrics emitted from issue data (velocity per developer, bug rate per engineer).</description>
      <reason>Individual-level metrics from trackers are an HR and legal risk, incentivize gaming (artificially inflating closed tickets), and destroy the team-level signal that makes forecasting valuable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Stale snapshot forecast — forecast generated yesterday from data a week old, presented as current to stakeholders.</description>
      <reason>PM data ages fast; a week-old snapshot misses the sprint that just closed, the risk that materialized, or the scope change that was approved. Every forecast must show a data-freshness timestamp.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
