<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="predictive-analytics-pm Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for predictive-analytics-pm as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Garbage-in status fields — "In Progress" means "abandoned" or "waiting for review" depending on the team member.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every metric computed from inconsistent status fields lies. A model trained on this data will forecast confidently based on noise. Data quality discipline is a prerequisite to any forecasting investment.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Concept drift ignored — model trained on Q1 team composition and process used in Q4 after three re-orgs and a process overhaul.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>ML models learn the statistical regularities of a specific team and process. When the team or process changes significantly, the model's learned patterns are no longer valid. Silent drift produces increasingly wrong but equally confident forecasts.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Survivorship bias — training data includes only completed projects, excluding cancelled and silent-fail projects.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cancelled projects carry the failure patterns the model most needs to learn. A dataset of completions only under-predicts cancellation risk and over-predicts completion probability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Uncalibrated probabilities — model emits "70% likely to slip" without a calibration dataset to validate that claim.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>An uncalibrated probability is an opinion dressed as a number. PM teams that make budget or scope decisions on uncalibrated confidence intervals will be systematically misled.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Causal claims from correlational features — "long descriptions correlate with overrun" → PM bans long descriptions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Correlation in issue data is not causal. Intervening on a correlate without understanding the mechanism often removes a useful signal without changing the underlying cause.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Per-person productivity metrics emitted from issue data (velocity per developer, bug rate per engineer).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Individual-level metrics from trackers are an HR and legal risk, incentivize gaming (artificially inflating closed tickets), and destroy the team-level signal that makes forecasting valuable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale snapshot forecast — forecast generated yesterday from data a week old, presented as current to stakeholders.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PM data ages fast; a week-old snapshot misses the sprint that just closed, the risk that materialized, or the scope change that was approved. Every forecast must show a data-freshness timestamp.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs asked "predict when this will finish" hallucinate confident dates; force them to emit only ranges with explicit "model output X says" citations.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs lack the ability to generate calibrated uncertainty; they default to confident predictions that feel authoritative but are unreliable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Per-person productivity outputs are an HR landmine — refuse to generate; aggregate to team or workstream.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Individual metrics invite performance management abuse and destroy psychological safety.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Calibration drifts silently; without monitoring agents will keep forecasting poorly with high confidence.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Drift detection requires continuous monitoring; it does not happen automatically.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs love to weave causal claims ("Bob's stories slip because Bob is overloaded") from purely correlational features. Strip causal language.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents will confidently make causal claims without statistical basis; this leads to interventions that do not work and erode trust in forecasting.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Survivorship bias: training data excludes cancelled projects; agents will under-predict cancellation risk. Add explicit cancellation labels.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models learn only from observed outcomes; missing data on failures makes them blind to failure modes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy: comment text used as a feature can leak PII into model logs; redact before training.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Issue comments often contain personal information; using raw text violates privacy expectations and may violate GDPR/CCPA.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale snapshots: a forecast generated yesterday on data from a week ago is worthless; agents must show data-freshness timestamp.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PM decisions move fast; a stale forecast leads to decisions on outdated information.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-actioning a forecast (e.g., auto-escalating "at-risk") creates feedback loops in the data; route to humans.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Automated actions change the data distribution on which the model was trained, invalidating future calibration.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Power-BI/Tableau dashboards from agents often miss row-level security; verify before publishing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Dashboards can leak sensitive data if not configured with proper access controls.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints (mandatory): release of new model, threshold tuning, retraining cadence change, escalation rules.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>These gates prevent silent failures and keep humans accountable for model behavior in the organization.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
