<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Win-Loss Quarterly PM Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Win-Loss Quarterly PM Template plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="minimum-15-wins-15-losses" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The quarterly synthesis MUST review ≥15 closed-won and ≥15 closed-lost deals; sub-15 sample sizes MUST defer the report.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sales Hacker win-loss methodology">Sub-15 sample produces anecdote-as-trend errors; 15 is the empirical floor where patterns separate from noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="interviews-with-buyers-not-reps" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Synthesis MUST include direct interviews with ≥5 buyers per quarter (won + lost mixed); rep-only data MUST be flagged as unverified.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bob Moesta — Demand-Side Sales">Reps systematically over-credit product strengths and under-credit price/process losses; buyer interviews are the only ground truth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="competitive-mention-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every loss synthesis MUST name the competitor that won the deal (or 'no decision') and the buyer-stated reason; opaque losses MUST be re-interviewed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sales Hacker win-loss methodology">Opaque losses produce competitor-blindness; named competitors + reasons are the input to positioning revisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="synthesis-must-recommend-actions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The report MUST end with 3-7 named actions (owners + due dates); descriptive-only reports MUST be returned for revision.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — win-loss audit 2025">Descriptive-only reports are decoration; the named-action requirement is the operational handoff.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="crm-data-cross-checked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CRM stage history MUST be cross-checked against rep narrative; discrepancies &gt; 30% MUST trigger a CRM-hygiene action.</statement>
      <rationale source="Salesforce field-research norms">Rep-narrative drift from CRM stage history is a leading indicator of forecast unreliability; the cross-check is the data-hygiene gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
