<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="journey-mapping">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Visualize user experience over time: stages, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points, opportunities. Ground every map cell in research data.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>journey-mapping</tag>
      <tag>user-experience</tag>
      <tag>touchpoint-analysis</tag>
      <tag>pain-points</tag>
      <tag>emotional-arc</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Customer Journey Mapping</title>

    <summary>Visualize the complete experience a user has with a product over time — stages, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points, and opportunities. Use to find cross-channel friction and align stakeholders on the current-state experience before designing improvements. Always ground every map cell in cited research; "no data" is a valid value.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Teams that optimize individual touchpoints miss the overall experience. Handoffs between channels and departments cause friction that no single team owns. A journey map makes the full arc visible in one artifact, surfacing pain points at stage transitions that cannot be seen from analytics alone. The emotional arc — where it dips sharply — shows where to invest redesign effort.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing or redesigning a multi-step flow (onboarding, checkout, support, offboarding)</item>
        <item>After collecting user interviews or analytics data revealing cross-touchpoint pain points</item>
        <item>Before a product discovery sprint to align stakeholders on the current-state experience</item>
        <item>Evaluating a new feature's impact on the broader experience, not just its own screen</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>No research data exists — a purely imagined journey map creates false consensus</item>
        <item>Single, isolated interaction with no multi-step journey</item>
        <item>Need to understand why users behave a certain way — use user interviews or usability testing instead</item>
        <item>Stakeholders want quantitative evidence — journey maps are qualitative synthesis, not metrics</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="eight-map-components">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every journey map must include all eight components: persona, stages, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points, and opportunities.</statement>
        <rationale>Omitting emotions produces an action log, not a journey map. Omitting opportunities produces a complaint document, not a design input. All eight components are required for the map to drive action.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Persona: who is taking the journey (specific, research-based, not a generic archetype)</item>
        <item>Stages: major phases of the experience (Awareness, Research, Purchase, Delivery, Use, Support)</item>
        <item>Actions: what the user does at each stage</item>
        <item>Touchpoints: where interaction happens (web, email, app, phone, in-store)</item>
        <item>Thoughts: what the user is thinking and asking at each stage</item>
        <item>Emotions: how the user feels (use 1-5 scale or emotional arc diagram)</item>
        <item>Pain points: friction and frustrations at each stage</item>
        <item>Opportunities: specific improvement ideas tied to pain points</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="journey-types">
      <list>
        <item>Current state: documents how things are today — use to find problems and build stakeholder consensus on what to fix</item>
        <item>Future state: documents the ideal experience — use as a design target after current state problems are understood</item>
        <item>Day-in-the-life: broader context beyond the product — use to understand competing demands on user attention</item>
        <item>Service blueprint: includes backstage processes — use when operational failures drive user pain points</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Label future-state maps explicitly as design proposals, not research findings.</statement>
        <rationale>Future-state maps generated from team imagination (not research) create false consensus that a designed experience matches user needs. The distinction must be visible on the map itself.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="research-grounding">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every map cell must cite a research artifact (interview ID, support ticket ID, analytics event); "no data" is a valid and required value when evidence is absent.</statement>
        <rationale>Ungrounded cells are team assumptions masquerading as research findings. Requiring citations forces explicit identification of gaps, which then become research priorities rather than invention prompts.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-1-define-scope">
      <rule>
        <statement>Map one persona and one journey per map; scope to a specific start and end point.</statement>
        <rationale>Combining two personas hides differences between their experiences, producing a map that represents neither accurately. A scope without defined endpoints produces maps with no clear beginning or resolution.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Well-scoped journey">
        <note>Scope: Sarah (mid-market buyer persona), purchase journey from first product discovery to post-purchase unboxing. Start: first ad impression. End: product first use.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="step-2-gather-research">
      <rule>
        <statement>Collect multi-source evidence before mapping: user interviews, observation, analytics, support tickets, surveys, and employee interviews from customer-facing roles.</statement>
        <rationale>Single-source maps are advocacy documents masquerading as research. Customer support staff see pain points daily that UX research misses — their input is mandatory, not optional.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-3-identify-stages">
      <rule>
        <statement>Break the journey into 4-8 major stages; name stages from the user's perspective, not the company's process names.</statement>
        <rationale>Company process names (Lead, Opportunity, Closed) reflect internal pipeline stages, not user experience stages. User-perspective names (Discovering, Evaluating, Deciding) keep the map focused on user experience, not operations.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="steps-4-5-map-actions-touchpoints-emotions">
      <rule>
        <statement>Map emotions with grounding in research evidence; never invent emotional states from team assumptions.</statement>
        <rationale>Invented emotional arcs produce maps that validate team assumptions rather than challenge them. LLMs and teams both smooth emotional arcs — real journeys have sharp dips. Prompt explicitly for variance when using agents.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-6-identify-pain-points-opportunities">
      <rule>
        <statement>The emotional arc dip is the primary signal for where to invest redesign effort; prioritize pain points at the sharpest drops.</statement>
        <rationale>Sharp emotional dips represent the highest concentration of user frustration. These stages have the most to gain from improvement and the most risk from neglect.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every opportunity in the Opportunities column must link to a backlog item or hypothesis — a map without downstream action is waste.</statement>
        <rationale>Journey maps created without action commitments become deck artifacts. The opportunities column is only valuable if it generates work.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-7-maintain-as-living-document">
      <rule>
        <statement>Attach a "last validated" date to every map; trigger a review when a major feature ships that affects the mapped journey.</statement>
        <rationale>Journey maps go stale quickly. A map from last quarter may contradict current analytics after a product change. Stale maps create false consensus about a user experience that no longer exists.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ecommerce-journey-example">
      <example type="good" title="E-commerce purchase journey with emotional arc and opportunities">
        <note>Stages: Discover → Research → Decide → Purchase → Receive → Use. Emotional arc: Curious (3) → Engaged (4) → Uncertain (2) → Anxious (2) → Impatient (2) → Excited or Disappointed (1-5). Sharpest drop: Purchase stage. Pain point: long checkout form, hidden fees revealed at last step. Opportunity: simplify checkout to single page, show total cost breakdown earlier. Evidence: P3 interview "I almost didn't finish because I didn't know what the final price was", Sentry error logs show 40% cart abandonment at payment page.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="workshop-format">
      <p>Duration: 2-4 hours. Participants: cross-functional team including customer support. Agenda: introduction and scope (15 min), review research (20 min), map stages (30 min), add actions and touchpoints (30 min), add emotions and thoughts (30 min), identify pain points (30 min), prioritize opportunities (30 min), next steps (15 min). Materials: large paper or whiteboard, sticky notes, markers, research summaries, persona reference.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="metrics-by-journey-stage">
      <list>
        <item>Awareness: reach, impressions, brand search volume</item>
        <item>Consideration: engagement rate, time on site, content downloads</item>
        <item>Purchase: conversion rate, cart abandonment rate, checkout completion</item>
        <item>Onboarding: activation rate, time-to-first-value</item>
        <item>Usage: retention rate, feature adoption, session frequency</item>
        <item>Support: resolution time, CSAT, first-contact resolution rate</item>
        <item>Loyalty: NPS, repeat purchase rate, referral rate</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agent synthesizes journey maps from structured research inputs: interview transcripts, support ticket exports, analytics funnel CSVs, NPS comments. Feed agent a corpus of evidence per stage. Agent outputs stage x row matrix. Agent identifies emotional arc and pain-point clusters from sentiment in source text. Human review mandatory before sharing with stakeholders — agent cannot validate whether emotional attributions match real user intent.</p>
      <reference path="templates/journey-map.md">Full journey map template: stage × row matrix</reference>
      <reference path="templates/stage-detail.md">Single stage deep-dive template</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent hallucinate emotions when no sentiment evidence exists in the input corpus</description>
        <reason>Always require "no data" as a valid cell value. Agents fill empty cells with plausible-sounding emotions that are invention, not research. Invented emotional arcs produce false consensus.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent smooths emotional arcs, producing a gentle curve rather than sharp dips</description>
        <reason>Real journeys have sharp emotional drops at friction points. Prompt explicitly: "identify variance and sharp drops, not average sentiment." Smooth arcs hide the most actionable insights.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Future-state map labeled as current-state research</description>
        <reason>Future-state maps generated by agents are design proposals, not research outputs. Label explicitly on the artifact: "Future State — Design Hypothesis (not validated with users)".</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/journey-map.md" purpose="Full journey map: stage × row matrix (actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points)"/>
      <template path="templates/stage-detail.md" purpose="Single stage deep-dive: user goal, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotional state, opportunities"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/journey-mapping-101/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/emotional-journey-map/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
