<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="project-integration">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>PM acts as integrator across all knowledge areas through single version-controlled integrated plan with cross-area impact analysis on every change and numeric threshold-driven status.</summary>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>integration-management</tag>
      <tag>change-control</tag>
      <tag>project-charter</tag>
      <tag>cross-functional</tag>
      <tag>status-tracking</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Project Integration Management</title>

    <summary>The PM acts as integrator across all knowledge areas (scope, schedule, cost, quality, risk, resources, communications, procurement) through a single version-controlled integrated plan. Every change request triggers cross-area impact analysis before approval; status colour is derived from numeric thresholds, not PM narrative; and closure is treated as integration's last mile — formal acceptance plus lessons learned plus archive.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Projects fail from silo management: scope changes approved without schedule updates, cost baselines drifting from schedule, risks without owners. Without integration, each area optimizes locally and the whole degrades. A machine-readable integrated plan with locked source-of-truth and automated threshold alerts catches cross-area drift before it compounds.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Programs with 2+ workstreams whose decisions interact (scope vs. schedule vs. cost vs. vendor).</item>
        <item>Initiation phase: drafting the project charter to authorize work and bind sponsor commitment.</item>
        <item>Change-heavy environments where every CR has cross-area impact simultaneously.</item>
        <item>Multi-team or multi-vendor delivery where local optimization harms whole-system performance.</item>
        <item>Project closure: final integration, lessons learned, formal acceptance, contract closeout.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-team, single-stream work with a stable backlog — Scrum or Kanban already integrates within the team.</item>
        <item>Short tactical engagements under 4 weeks with no inter-area trade-offs — overhead exceeds value.</item>
        <item>Pure research or discovery phases with no committed scope — wait until charter signal is real.</item>
        <item>Solo-developer projects — keep artifacts lightweight (one-page charter, weekly check); the integrator is one person.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="integration-role">
      <p>The PM acts as the cross-area integrator: every decision in one knowledge area must be assessed for impact on all others before approval. Silo management optimizes parts and sub-optimizes the whole. A scope CR approved without schedule and cost update creates a multi-week cascade of drift that is invisible until delivery fails.</p>
      <p>Integration coordinates: Scope, Schedule, Cost, Quality, Risk, Resources, Communications, Procurement. Each has a subsidiary plan; the integrated plan references all of them from a single YAML source-of-truth.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>The PM acts as the cross-area integrator: every decision in one knowledge area must be assessed for impact on all others before approval.</statement>
        <rationale>Silo management optimizes parts and sub-optimizes the whole. A scope CR approved without schedule and cost update creates a multi-week cascade of drift that is invisible until delivery fails.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="six-integration-activities">
      <p>Core project integration management activities across the project lifecycle:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Project Charter (Initiation) — authorize project, define high-level scope, bind sponsor commitment. Charter as code: sponsor approves via PR review.</item>
        <item>Project Plan (Planning) — integrate all subsidiary plans into one YAML referencing scope (WBS), schedule, cost, risks, quality, resources, comms, procurement baselines.</item>
        <item>Direct Work (Execution) — lead execution; ensure the plan governs, not informal decisions.</item>
        <item>Monitor and Control (Throughout) — track against integrated baselines; emit GREEN/YELLOW/RED from numeric thresholds, not PM narrative.</item>
        <item>Integrated Change Control (Throughout) — every CR triggers cross-area impact analysis before approval; decisions logged in decisions/ per ADR pattern.</item>
        <item>Close Project (Closure) — formal acceptance, lessons learned, archive, contract closeout. Closure is integration's last mile — do not let the team scatter before it completes.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="charter-elements">
      <p>Project charter as code defines authorization, high-level scope, success criteria, and sponsor commitment.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every SMART objective in the charter must cite a measurable success criterion; unknowns must be listed as TO_CONFIRM, not omitted.</statement>
        <rationale>Charter generators hallucinate constraints and assumptions to appear thorough. Forcing unknowns to surface as TO_CONFIRM creates a tracked open-question list.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="integrated-change-control">
      <p>Change control process that enforces cross-area impact analysis and decision logging.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-baseline only when scope/budget/contract changes — not when velocity slips. Re-baselining for slip masks chronic delivery problems.</statement>
        <rationale>Baseline changes are decisions, not corrections. Treating slip as a reason to re-baseline hides the root cause and makes EVM meaningless.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every approved CR requires a cross-area impact memo committed alongside the CR before implementation begins.</statement>
        <rationale>Second-order effects (a 2-week delay shifting dependencies onto a holiday, breaking a vendor deadline) only surface when impact is computed across all areas — not as a delta on duration alone.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Status colour declared GREEN/YELLOW/RED based on PM narrative rather than numeric threshold comparison.</description>
        <reason>Agents over-summarize: declaring "GREEN — on track" without numeric backing is the dominant integration failure. Colour must follow threshold arithmetic.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="integrated-plan-as-code">
      <p>Architecture for version-controlling the integrated project plan using YAML and git.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Single source of truth: one YAML file (integrated/plan.yaml) in the project repo; derivatives (slides, PDFs, dashboards) are generated — never hand-edited.</statement>
        <rationale>Manual edits to derivative documents diverge from the source within one week; agents that pull from the wrong derivative produce misleading status reports.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Charter (charter.md) lives in the same repo; sponsor approves via PR merge. A decisions/ directory holds one ADR-style entry per approved CR. This makes the program's decision history searchable.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <p>Specialized agents for different integration management tasks:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — drives integration setup as SDD tasks: TASK_charter, TASK_integrated_plan, TASK_change_control_process, TASK_status_dashboard, TASK_closure.</item>
        <item>charter-author-agent (model: opus) — drafts charter from kickoff inputs, drives sponsor sign-off, captures assumptions and constraints.</item>
        <item>change-impact-agent (model: sonnet) — given a CR, computes impact across scope/schedule/cost/quality/risk/resources from the integrated plan; emits a markdown impact memo.</item>
        <item>baseline-curator-agent (model: sonnet) — keeps the integrated plan consistent — flags scope without schedule, schedule without cost, risks without owners.</item>
        <item>status-reporter-agent (model: haiku) — renders the status report template from numeric inputs only — colour follows thresholds, never tone.</item>
        <item>closure-agent (model: sonnet) — runs the closure checklist, archives plans, captures lessons learned, generates final acceptance documentation.</item>
        <item>password-scrubber-agent — runs over charter/status/closure docs before distribution; integration artifacts are top leak paths.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="change-impact-prompt-pattern">
      <p>Strict markdown prompt pattern that forces numeric grounding and rejects vague recommendations:</p>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are the change-impact agent. Inputs:
1. Approved change request (CR-NN.md): scope description, requestor, priority.
2. integrated/plan.yaml: scope (WBS), schedule, cost, risks, quality, resources.
3. Threshold table: GREEN/YELLOW/RED triggers per dimension.

Emit STRICT MARKDOWN:
## Impact Analysis CR-NN
| Area | Current | Proposed | Delta | Status | Notes |
|------|---------|----------|-------|--------|-------|

## Recommendation
- decision: approve | reject | conditional
- conditions: [ ... ]
- new_baseline_required: true|false
- communications: [ stakeholders to notify ]

Rules:
- Numbers come from inputs; never invent.
- Status follows threshold table verbatim.
- Recommend reject if any dimension goes RED without a compensating trade-off.
- Cite at least one risk-register entry if risk delta is non-zero.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Common failure modes when agents conduct integration management:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent produces cross-area impact analysis that only covers the areas it has API access to.</description>
        <reason>An agent with only Jira access produces schedule-blind reports. Force an input audit: every knowledge area must appear in the impact memo or be explicitly marked "data unavailable".</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Closure declared complete with an empty lessons-learned file.</description>
        <reason>Agents skip lessons learned because there is no code change. Force the closure checklist to fail-close if the lessons file is empty.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Charter sign-off automated by the agent merging its own PR.</description>
        <reason>Charter sign-off is a governance decision requiring sponsor authority; the agent prepares the PR and the sponsor approves the merge.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <p>Mandatory human checkpoints: charter approval, baseline changes, CR approval, status colour shifts to RED, closure declaration.</p>
      <p>Decision log entries get duplicated by parallel agents — force a unique-ID generator and advisory lock. Integrated plans over 500 lines blow context; page by knowledge area, persist summaries, rehydrate.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Command-line tools for integration management automation:</p>
      <list>
        <item>git + branch protection — charter and integrated plan as code; PR gates sponsor sign-off.</item>
        <item>gh / glab — drive change-request issues, link to PRs that update baselines.</item>
        <item>yq / jq — read/patch integrated/plan.yaml; aggregate dependencies.</item>
        <item>python-docx / python-pptx / pandoc — render charter, status reports, closure docs to org-required formats.</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc) — render integration diagrams (scope → schedule → cost) and status dashboards.</item>
        <item>mpxj — read/write MS Project .mpp schedules from the integrated plan.</item>
        <item>taskjuggler / ganttproject-cli — compute critical path locally from YAML.</item>
        <item>dvc / lakeFS — version control for non-code deliverables (CAD, datasets) referenced from the plan.</item>
        <item>pre-commit — block edits to charter.md or baselines without rationale and sponsor reviewer.</item>
        <item>make / just — standardize "build status pack" / "render closure" tasks.</item>
      </list>
      <p>SaaS platforms with agent-friendly integration:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Microsoft Project + Project for the Web — dominant predictive tool; integrates with Teams + Power BI for status.</item>
        <item>Smartsheet — portfolio gantt + dashboards; common integration target.</item>
        <item>Asana (Portfolios) / ClickUp (Goals) / Monday — lightweight portfolio with built-in status fields.</item>
        <item>Jira (with Plans / Advanced Roadmaps) — common host; integrate via cross-project dashboards.</item>
        <item>Azure DevOps — hybrid host: portfolio Plans + team Boards + Pipelines.</item>
        <item>GitLab Premium/Ultimate (Roadmaps + Boards + Iterations) — single-pane integration alternative for engineering-heavy programs.</item>
        <item>ServiceNow SPM (formerly ITBM) — heavy enterprise PPM with full integration; required where governance is the constraint.</item>
        <item>Planview / Clarity / Sciforma — portfolio + EVM-grade tooling for large enterprises.</item>
        <item>Confluence / Notion / Coda — charter, decisions, status home; pair with the work-graph host.</item>
        <item>OpenProject / Redmine / Tuleap — self-hosted hosts for regulated/airgapped orgs.</item>
        <item>Power BI / Tableau / Looker — status dashboards aggregating across tools.</item>
        <item>Slack / MS Teams — status digest delivery; throttle to avoid noise.</item>
        <item>DocuSign / Adobe Sign — charter sign-off, formal acceptance.</item>
        <item>Box / SharePoint / Drive — repository for non-code deliverables; pair with dvc for versioning.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Single source of truth for the integrated plan (one YAML file, one repo). Derivatives (slides, docs, dashboards) are generated; never hand-edited.</statement>
        <rationale>Manual edits diverge within one week; agents pulling from wrong derivatives produce misleading status.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Charter as code: charter.md lives in the project repo, sponsor approves via PR review with signed commit. Amendments require a new PR, not a stealth edit.</statement>
        <rationale>Git history of charter changes is the audit trail for change authorization.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>One decision log per project (decisions/), one ADR-style entry per integrated change. Search-first cultures depend on this.</statement>
        <rationale>Decision rationale lost verbally; documented decisions become searchable corporate memory.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Status colour driven by numeric thresholds, never PM mood. Force the threshold table into the plan so the agent computes status, the human interprets it.</statement>
        <rationale>Narrative status is subjective and unreliable; threshold-driven status is deterministic and auditable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every change request triggers cross-area impact analysis before approval; the impact memo is committed alongside the CR.</statement>
        <rationale>Second-order effects only surface in cross-area analysis; single-area impact reviews hide integration risks.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run an integration check weekly: scope without schedule? schedule without cost? risks without owners? — automate and open issues.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated consistency checks catch silo drift in days rather than months.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>For solopreneurs: keep the artifact lightweight (one-page charter, weekly integration check), but keep it. Skipping integration is the most common solopreneur failure.</statement>
        <rationale>Even solo projects benefit from documented scope, schedule, risks, and decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Closure is integration's last mile — formal acceptance + lessons learned + archive happens once, not after the team scatters.</statement>
        <rationale>Delayed closure spreads knowledge loss and delays resource recovery.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep change-control velocity moderate — too few CRs hides chaos; too many drown the integrator. Aim for batched weekly review.</statement>
        <rationale>Emergency CR streams bypass integrated impact analysis; batching forces discipline while preserving responsiveness.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Train sponsors on what they sign — most integration failures are sponsor-driven (silent scope additions).</statement>
        <rationale>If sponsors do not understand the baseline they approved, every informal "can you just add X" becomes an untracked scope change.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="where-integration-fails">
      <p>Common failure modes and limitations:</p>
      <list>
        <item>"Integration" is the easiest dimension to skip on paper — every plan claims integration; few enforce it. Without a single source of truth, integration degrades to status theatre.</item>
        <item>Charter rot: charters get signed and forgotten. If the charter does not change when scope/budget change, downstream teams use a stale "north star".</item>
        <item>Change control without integration becomes whack-a-mole — scope CR approved, schedule and cost not updated, baselines drift apart.</item>
        <item>Knowledge-area silos at the PMO produce inconsistent plans (schedule from MS Project, cost from Excel, risk in Confluence) that drift within weeks.</item>
        <item>"Single source of truth" claims fail in practice when humans edit derivatives instead of the source — locked workflows are mandatory.</item>
        <item>Solopreneurs treat integration as an afterthought; the lightweight section is correct but rarely practiced.</item>
        <item>Status-report fatigue substitutes for actual integration decisions — colour codes without action are noise.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/charter.md" purpose="Project charter template with SMART objectives, success criteria, constraints, approval block"/>
      <template path="templates/status-report.md" purpose="Weekly status report template with GREEN/YELLOW/RED per knowledge area"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="templates/integration-status.py" purpose="Script: compute status colours from numeric YAML inputs via threshold ladders"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards/foundational/PMBOK"/>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/75939"/>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/74995"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
