<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Capacity-Fit Calculator Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five failure modes that quietly inflate the capacity number and cause sprint over-commitment, especially when an LLM is generating the sheet.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="high">
      <description>Ceremonies under-counted — only standup is subtracted, planning/refinement/retro forgotten.</description>
      <detector>ceremonies_hours &lt; 4h per person per 2-week sprint</detector>
      <repair>Inventory all ceremonies and meeting holds for the sprint. Typical floor for a Scrum team: 5-8h per person per 2-week sprint.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="high">
      <description>PTO calendar not pulled — assumes full headcount across all working days.</description>
      <detector>pto_hours = 0 across &gt; 50% of sprints in capacity-sheet AND team is &gt; 3 engineers</detector>
      <repair>Make PTO check a hard step in the pre-planning checklist. Pull from HR system or shared calendar. Zero-PTO weeks exist but are not the average.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="high">
      <description>Interrupt buffer set to 0 because "we're shielded this sprint."</description>
      <detector>interrupt_buffer_pct = 0 AND no documented separate on-call rotation</detector>
      <repair>Set buffer to default 15% minimum. The "shielded" assumption is consistently falsified. If genuinely on-call-isolated, document it once in capacity-sheet notes and reference each sprint.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Velocity baseline cherry-picked — highest of last 3 sprints used.</description>
      <detector>velocity_baseline equals the max of the last 3 sprints &gt;= 2 times in 6 sprints</detector>
      <repair>Use rolling-3-sprint median or mean, not max. Discuss why one sprint was an outlier instead of treating it as the new normal.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Story points converted to hours with an inflated conversion factor.</description>
      <detector>committed_velocity in hours is &gt; story_points × 6 (typical conversion 4-6h/point depending on team)</detector>
      <repair>Calibrate conversion from actual logged hours per point over the last 3 sprints. Avoid mixing point-based commitment with hour-based capacity unless the conversion is empirically stable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>LLM-generated capacity sheets must not invent terms. If asked to "estimate ceremonies" with no input, the model must return UNKNOWN and prompt the PM, not fabricate 2h/person. Calculator output without grounded inputs is forbidden.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>RED-band sprints require a named human sign-off line ("Risk accepted by [PM name] on [date] because [reason]"). The calculator can recommend the trim list; it cannot grant the risk acceptance.</p>
  </section>
</text>
