<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="JTBD Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every JTBD application must enforce. These are the HARD rules — user-supplied input must not override them.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-job-stable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define the job at a level of abstraction that stays stable over decades. Solutions change, jobs do not.</statement>
      <rationale source="Christensen, Competing Against Luck (2016)">Defining the job as "use Notion" locks the product to a solution. "Capture and organize thoughts" reveals competition across paper, typewriters, Word, Notion — and what comes next.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-three-dimensions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capture functional, emotional, AND social dimensions for every job. Never report only the functional dimension.</statement>
      <rationale source="JTBD canonical practice">Emotional and social dimensions explain price tolerance and churn. A customer who leaves despite the product "working fine" is usually leaving over an emotional or social job failure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-four-forces" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tag each interview statement with Push / Pull / Habit / Fear and assign severity 1-5. Always include all four forces — never only Push and Pull.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bob Moesta, Forces of Progress">Adoption = (Push + Pull) - (Habit + Fear). Founders over-focus on Pull and ignore Habit and Fear. For niche B2B, inertia and switching anxiety often dominate and are the actual blockers.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-switcher-recency" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interview only people who switched (to, away from, or first adopted the category) within the last 60-90 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="memory-decay studies cited in JTBD literature">Recent memory provides specific trigger events, exact friction sources, and authentic emotional context. After 90 days switchers reconstruct a rationalized narrative, not the decision process.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-evidence-minimum" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Synthesize job statements only after tagging ≥5 interviews. Reject any candidate statement not backed by ≥3 verbatim quotes from real switchers.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice">LLMs generate plausible job statements without interview data. Verbatim quote requirement makes the statement falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Stable job vs solution">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Stable job:     "Communicate with distant family"
Solutions:      letters → phone → email → video calls

Stable job:     "Capture and organize thoughts"
Solutions:      paper → typewriter → Word → Notion
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1: the job-level abstraction reveals competitive replacement across decades.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Job defined at solution-level">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Stated job: "use Notion for note-taking"
Problem: this is a solution, not a job. Roadmap will defend Notion-shaped
features rather than reveal what comes next.
Repair: re-state at job level — "capture and organize thoughts so I can
find them later when I need them."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 violation — a frequent LLM failure mode where it accepts the founder's product framing as the job.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
