<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Jobs To Be Done (Researcher) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Jobs To Be Done (Researcher) application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="recent-switchers-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interviews target switchers who moved within the last 90 days. Older switchers' memory of forces is degraded.</statement>
      <rationale source="Memory-decay research">Episodic memory of the switching moment degrades quickly; recent switchers reconstruct forces with higher fidelity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="four-forces-tagged" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every transcript tags Push / Pull / Habit / Fear forces. Missing any force category triggers an interview re-run probe.</statement>
      <rationale source="JTBD canon (Christensen)">All four forces operate during a switch; missing one signals an interview gap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="observable-switch-event" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each interview anchors on a single observable switch event (sign-up, cancel, tool change). Generic 'I started using X' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anchor-event discipline">Without observable events the interviewee reconstructs a plausible story, not the switch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="force-aggregation-rubric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Forces aggregate via the rubric (strength 1–5 × evidence count). Aggregated forces with strength &lt;3 don't make the hire/fire criteria.</statement>
      <rationale source="Force-aggregation practice">Without rubric the strongest narrative wins, not the strongest signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="hire-fire-criteria-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output ends with hire/fire criteria: under what conditions a customer hires this product, under what conditions they fire it.</statement>
      <rationale source="JTBD applied-output discipline">Without hire/fire criteria the JTBD output is theory, not product input.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
