<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-jtbd-concepts" title="JTBD Core Concepts">
  <summary>Core Jobs to Be Done concepts: the job vs. solution distinction, functional/emotional/social job dimensions, hiring and firing, and the Forces of Progress model.</summary>

  <section title="Job vs. Solution">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the job at a level of abstraction that stays stable over decades; solutions change, jobs do not.</statement>
      <rationale>Defining the job as "use Notion" locks the product to a solution. Defining it as "capture and organize thoughts" reveals how the job has been hired across paper, typewriters, Word, and Notion — and what comes next.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Job (stable): communicate with distant family. Solutions: letters, phone, email, video calls.</item>
      <item>Job (stable): capture and organize thoughts. Solutions: paper, typewriter, Word, Notion.</item>
      <item>Job (stable): get from A to B quickly. Solutions: horse, car, Uber, autonomous vehicle.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Job Dimensions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always capture functional, emotional, and social dimensions for every job; never report only the functional dimension.</statement>
      <rationale>Emotional and social dimensions often explain price tolerance and churn. A customer who leaves a product despite it working "fine" is usually leaving over an emotional or social job failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Functional: get something concrete done ("file my taxes correctly").</item>
      <item>Emotional: feel a certain way as a result ("feel in control of my finances").</item>
      <item>Social: how others perceive me because of this ("appear financially responsible").</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Forces of Progress">
    <rule>
      <statement>Adoption occurs when Push (current pain) + Pull (new solution appeal) exceeds Habit (comfort with old) + Fear (anxiety about new). Optimize for the dominant force pair.</statement>
      <rationale>Founders over-focus on Pull (making their product attractive) and ignore Habit and Fear. For niche B2B, inertia and switching anxiety often dominate and are the actual blockers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
CRM switch analysis:
Push: old CRM loses data, clunky UI (score: high)
Pull: new CRM has automation, mobile app (score: medium)
Habit: team knows the old system (score: high)
Fear: migration might lose contacts (score: high)

Insight: Pull is not the problem; address Habit and Fear with
a migration service and a rollback guarantee before promoting features.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Hiring and Firing">
    <p>Customers hire products when progress is needed and the current solution is inadequate. They fire products when the job is done, a better alternative exists, or the progress is no longer needed. Understanding the firing event is as important as understanding the hiring decision.</p>
  </section>
</text>
