<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-interview-and-job-map" title="Switcher Interview Method and Job Map">
  <summary>How to find and interview recent switchers, reconstruct the timeline, synthesize job statements, apply the 8-stage job map, and antipatterns to avoid.</summary>

  <section title="Switcher Interview Method">
    <rule>
      <statement>Interview people who switched to, switched away from, or first adopted your product category within the last 60-90 days. Memory decay after 90 days flattens the timeline.</statement>
      <rationale>Recent memory provides specific trigger events, exact sources of friction, and authentic emotional context. Older switchers reconstruct a rationalized narrative, not the actual decision process.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Reconstruct the full timeline from first thought to current use; capture the trigger moment ("first thought") explicitly — most product investments target the wrong timeline stage.</statement>
      <rationale>Acquisition efforts usually target Active Looking (evaluation) but the opportunity to influence the decision is in Passive Looking or earlier. The trigger moment reveals what caused the job to become active.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>First Thought: "When did you first think you needed something different?"</item>
      <item>Passive Looking: "What did you first look at? How did you hear about options?"</item>
      <item>Active Looking: "When did you start seriously evaluating? What criteria mattered?"</item>
      <item>The Switch: "Walk me through the moment you decided to switch."</item>
      <item>Consumption: "What happened when you started using the new solution?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Job Statement Synthesis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Synthesize job statements only after tagging at least 5 interviews; reject any statement not backed by at least 3 verbatim quotes from real switchers.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs generate plausible job statements without interview data. A statement must be testable: a stranger reading it should predict the customer's behavior in three scenarios.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Validated job statement (backed by 7 interviews):
"When I finish a client project,
 I want to send a professional invoice quickly,
 so I can get paid faster and move on to the next project."
Evidence quotes:
  - "I was losing 30 minutes per invoice fiddling with templates."
  - "The delay between sending and getting paid was stressing me out."
  - "I looked for anything that would let me send in under 2 minutes."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Job Map (8 Stages)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the 8-stage Job Map only to jobs with at least 3 distinct steps; forcing it onto simple jobs creates fake pain points.</statement>
      <rationale>The Job Map is a discovery tool, not a template. A simple job like "send an invoice" does not have 8 meaningful stages; artificially creating them wastes roadmap time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Define — determine what is needed; pain: unclear requirements.</item>
      <item>Locate — find options and information; pain: information overload.</item>
      <item>Prepare — get ready to execute; pain: setup complexity.</item>
      <item>Confirm — validate the choice; pain: doubt and missing information.</item>
      <item>Execute — do the core job; pain: friction and errors.</item>
      <item>Monitor — check progress; pain: lack of feedback.</item>
      <item>Modify — make adjustments; pain: limited flexibility.</item>
      <item>Conclude — finish the job; pain: unclear completion state.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Asking "what features should we add?" instead of "what are you trying to accomplish?"</description>
      <reason>Feature requests are solution guesses, not job statements. They reveal what customers think the solution should look like, not what progress they are trying to make.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Accepting "do nothing / spreadsheets" as the real competitor without evidence from interview transcripts.</description>
      <reason>This is a meme answer that LLMs auto-generate. Require explicit mentions of "spreadsheet" or "I do it manually" in actual interview transcripts before accepting it.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/job-statement.md">Job statement template with functional/emotional/social dimensions and competitive set</reference>
  <reference path="templates/jtbd-interview.md">Full interview guide: context, timeline questions, forces analysis, draft statement</reference>
  <reference path="templates/job-map.md">8-stage job map with pain and opportunity fields per stage</reference>
  <reference path="templates/force-aggregator.py">Python script: aggregates Push/Pull/Habit/Fear from tagged-transcript JSON files</reference>
</text>
