<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Hourly Rate Floor Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every rate-floor calculation must enforce. These prevent the most common pricing mistake: dividing target income by 2080 hours.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-utilization-below-100" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use billable utilization between 40% and 60% of available work hours. Reject any calculation that uses 100% utilization or unstated utilization. Default if no operator data: 50%.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brennan Dunn / Jonathan Stark casework, agency benchmarks">Real solo practices spend 40-60% of work hours on non-billable activities (sales, admin, learning, dead leads, sick days). 100%-utilization math systematically undercuts the floor by 1.7-2.5×.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-gross-up-taxes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Gross up target take-home income by jurisdiction-specific effective tax rate INCLUDING self-employment tax / NI / VAT-on-services if applicable. Forbidden: using marginal rate as effective rate.</statement>
      <rationale source="freelancer tax study">In the US, self-employment tax adds ~15.3% on top of income tax. In the UK, NI Class 4 adds ~9%. Operators using marginal rate alone under-gross-up by 8-15% of revenue.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-gross-up-overhead" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Add 12 months of business overhead (tools, insurance, healthcare, training, office, accounting) to the grossed-up income BEFORE dividing by billable hours. Healthcare and pension contributions are mandatory when no employer covers them.</statement>
      <rationale source="solo-operator P&amp;L analysis">Forgotten overhead averages $8k-$25k per year for typical solo dev / consultant. Excluding it sinks the floor below sustainability within 2 years.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-three-band-output" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Produce three numbers: bottom (walk-away threshold), floor (sustainable target), stretch (target with margin for investment + savings + bad-debt reserve). Reject single-number outputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="rate-negotiation practice">A single number anchors the operator to the wrong value during negotiation. Three bands give the operator a clear floor and a stretch goal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-geography-specific" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The calculation uses the operator's tax + healthcare + insurance jurisdiction, NOT the client's jurisdiction. A Portuguese freelancer billing a US client uses Portuguese effective rates.</statement>
      <rationale source="cross-border freelancer postmortems">Operators charging "US rates" but paying European taxes mistakenly assume they're earning US wages. Floor is anchored to the operator's actual tax + cost-of-living position.</rationale>
    </rule>

      <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Floor calculation with three bands">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Inputs:
  Target take-home (annual):        $80,000
  Effective tax rate (US, solo):    32% (income + SE tax)
  Required gross income:            $80,000 / (1 - 0.32) = $117,647
  Annual overhead (12 mo total):    $14,000 (tools $3k, healthcare $9k, accounting $2k)
  Required revenue:                 $117,647 + $14,000 = $131,647
  Available work hours/year:        2,000 (50 weeks × 40)
  Utilization:                      50% (1,000 billable hours)

Output bands:
  bottom:   $115/hr   (covers basic survival at 40% utilization)
  floor:    $132/hr   (target sustainable at 50% utilization)
  stretch:  $165/hr   (margin for savings + business reinvestment)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1-r5 applied. Three bands give the operator pricing flexibility.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="2080-hour fantasy math">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Naive calc: $80,000 / 2080 hrs = $38/hr  (rate quoted)
Reality: at 50% utilization, $38/hr × 1000 billable hrs = $38,000 gross,
         minus taxes ~$12k, minus overhead ~$14k = $12,000 take-home.
         15% of target.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 + r3 violation. 2080-hour math is the dominant solo-pricing failure mode.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
