<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stakeholder Conflict Mediation Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that turn an erupting conflict in a requirements meeting into a captured decision or a clean escalation.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>When two stakeholders openly disagree, the BA MUST verbally pause the broader review within 30 seconds (e.g., "let me pause us here — I want to make sure I capture this disagreement correctly"). Letting the conflict run uncapped past 30 seconds is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>Past the 30-second mark, the disagreement turns into argument, audiences harden, and reframe options collapse. Early pause is the only window where neutral framing is still accepted.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The BA MUST reframe the dispute back to a specific clause in the requirements doc, quoted verbatim, and pin the disagreement to one of: (a) interpretation of the clause, (b) priority of the clause, or (c) inclusion of the clause. Mediation does NOT continue until all parties confirm which of (a)(b)(c) is the disagreement.</statement>
      <rationale>Mediating an under-specified disagreement is impossible: stakeholders will keep widening scope. Pinning to a specific clause + a specific (a/b/c) tag is what makes the rest of the loop tractable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The BA MUST offer exactly three resolution paths: (1) decide here using a quick rubric, (2) defer to an async decision memo with a deadline, (3) escalate to the named project sponsor. The room chooses one before mediation moves further.</statement>
      <rationale>Three named paths force a meta-decision the room CAN make even when the substantive question is contested. Open-ended ("what should we do?") regresses immediately back into the original argument.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Whatever path the room picks, the next step MUST be written into the meeting notes verbatim before review resumes: who does what, by when, against which clause ID. The BA reads the entry aloud and waits for explicit verbal confirmation from each stakeholder in the dispute.</statement>
      <rationale>An unconfirmed verbal "let's do X" decays within 24h; stakeholders later remember different versions. Reading-and-confirming creates a shared, witnessed record before the chemical of resolution wears off.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>If the pause-reframe-isolate-propose loop fails to converge after two iterations on the same clause, the BA MUST escalate to the named project sponsor before the meeting ends — without negotiating a third iteration. The escalation message MUST cite both iterations' notes.</statement>
      <rationale>Three+ iterations on the same clause is a strong signal the BA does not have authority to resolve it. Continuing burns the meeting, the BA's credibility, and the rest of the agenda. A hard cap respects the project's escalation contract.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
[Meeting notes, 10:42]

Maria and Tomás began arguing on the discount-on-subscriptions clause.

BA: "Let me pause — Maria, Tomás, the clause we are on is REQ-114:
'Discount codes are applicable to subscription products.' Is the
disagreement about (a) interpretation, (b) priority, or (c) inclusion?"

Both: "(c) inclusion."

BA: "Three paths: decide here with a quick rubric, write a decision memo
due Friday, or escalate to Pedro (sponsor). Which?"

Decision: write a memo, owner Maria, due 2026-05-23, escalation if no
agreement to Pedro by 2026-05-24.

[Notes read back and confirmed by Maria, Tomás, BA.]

Review resumed at 10:46 on REQ-115.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Pause within 30s. Clause pinned to (c). Three paths offered. Written, read-back, confirmed. Total mediation: 4 minutes.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
[Meeting notes, 10:42]

Maria and Tomás argued about subscriptions for 25 minutes. Other attendees
got pulled in. We ran out of time and ended without covering REQ-115 to 130.

Action: "the team will resolve it offline."
      ]]></code>
      <note>No pause, no reframe, no isolation, no path proposal, no written confirm, no escalation. Meeting hostage; agenda lost; "offline" decay guaranteed.</note>
    </example>

  </section>
</text>
