<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SLO Burn Matrix — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every burn-decision matrix must satisfy. The rules ensure burn alerts produce action, not debate.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-explicit-categories" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The matrix uses EXPLICIT burn categories (fast-burn 1h window, fast-burn 6h window, slow-burn 24h, slow-burn 72h, near-exhaustion) AND service classes (user-facing critical, user-facing non-critical, async worker, batch, internal tool). At least 3 categories × 3 classes minimum.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Workbook multi-window multi-burn-rate; field experience">A two-cell matrix (fast vs slow) cannot capture the difference between a 1-hour blip and a sustained 3-day burn. The 3×3 floor produces meaningful action differentiation; sparser matrices collapse to "page someone".</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-action-per-cell" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each cell maps to a specific action from the enumerated set: `halt_canary`, `freeze_ship`, `focus_shift`, `accept`, `investigate`. Empty cells or "see PM" are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="decision-theory; SRE workbook on-call practices">An undefined cell becomes a live debate when the alert fires. Pre-decided actions remove that overhead. The named enum prevents inventive ad-hoc actions during incident pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each action has a named owner: the role that executes the action (e.g. `oncall_primary`, `release_manager`, `tech_lead`). Group owners ("the team") are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI clarity; incident-management practice">When the action is `halt_canary` and the action message lands in a shared channel, "the team" diffuses responsibility. The named role pulls the action — the person occupying that role at the time acts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-revert-criteria-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each action has explicit revert criteria: what must be true for the action to lift (e.g. ship freeze lifts when burn drops below slow-burn threshold for 24h AND postmortem actions tracked). Open-ended actions are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="incident-lifecycle practice; field experience">A ship freeze without revert criteria becomes a permanent culture; releases stop, then resume informally without trust. Explicit revert criteria make the action a finite project.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-audit-log" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every matrix-triggered action is written to an immutable audit log: alert id, matrix cell, action taken, owner, start time, revert time, notes. The log feeds the weekly burn review.</statement>
      <rationale source="postmortem evidence requirements; governance">Without an audit log, the matrix's effectiveness cannot be assessed. The log also defends the team when leadership asks "why did you freeze ships last Friday?" — the matrix entry, the alert, the named action.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Sample 3x3 matrix">
    <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
                       | fast-burn (1h)  | fast-burn (6h)  | slow-burn (72h)
-----------------------|-----------------|-----------------|------------------
user-facing critical   | halt_canary     | halt_canary +   | freeze_ship +
                       |                 | freeze_ship     | focus_shift
user-facing non-crit   | investigate     | halt_canary     | focus_shift
async worker           | investigate     | investigate     | accept (note in log)
    ]]></code>
  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Fast-burn on user-facing critical service">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
14:22 — burn alert fires: user-facing critical service consuming 2h-window
budget at 14x normal rate.
14:22 — matrix lookup: halt_canary action.
14:22 — alert manager pages oncall_primary AND release_manager.
14:24 — release manager halts the in-progress canary deploy.
14:25 — investigation begins; root cause: a config error in the latest deploy.
14:50 — rollback completes; burn rate returns to baseline.
15:10 — revert criteria met (rate &lt; threshold for 30 min); action closed.
Audit log: cell (fast-1h, user-facing critical) → halt_canary → success.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1-r5 all in play.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="No matrix; burn debated in real-time">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
14:22 — burn alert fires. Slack thread: "is this a big deal? should we
freeze deploys? what about the marketing launch tomorrow?" 45-minute
discussion. Decision: "let us watch it." By 17:00, burn has consumed
60% of the monthly budget.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r2 violated (no action), r3 violated (no owner). The team debates instead of acting.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
