<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-types-and-process" title="Survey Types, Design Process, and Standard UX Metrics">
  <summary>Survey typology, six-step survey design process, and the four standard UX measurement instruments (NPS, SUS, CSAT, SEQ).</summary>

  <section title="Survey Types">
    <list>
      <item>Satisfaction — measures user happiness with a product or experience (CSAT, NPS).</item>
      <item>Task-based — collects post-task feedback on ease and usability (SUS, SEQ).</item>
      <item>Preference — compares options or prioritizes features (A vs B, ranking).</item>
      <item>Exploratory — understands usage patterns and behaviors at scale.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Six-Step Survey Design Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define a specific, measurable research objective before writing any question; never start with question ideas and work backward to an objective.</statement>
      <rationale>Ill-formed objectives produce questions that collect data no one acts on; a clear objective constrains the question set and prevents survey bloat.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Define objective — what specific, measurable thing do you want to know?</item>
      <item>Step 2: Choose question types — multiple choice for fixed options, rating scale for intensity, ranking for prioritization, open-ended only for exploration.</item>
      <item>Step 3: Write questions — one concept per question, neutral wording, complete answer options.</item>
      <item>Step 4: Design flow — introduction + consent → screening → easy questions → core questions → demographics → thank you.</item>
      <item>Step 5: Pilot test with 5-10 people; time the median completion; fix any confusion before launch.</item>
      <item>Step 6: Analyze — calculate response rate, descriptive statistics on quantitative items, theme-code open-ended responses.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Standard UX Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use validated instruments verbatim — do not reword SUS, NPS, or UEQ items; any wording change invalidates benchmark comparability.</statement>
      <rationale>Benchmark databases (SUS mean=68, NPS range −100 to +100) are tied to exact wording; paraphrasing breaks the comparison.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>NPS: "How likely are you to recommend [X] to a friend or colleague?" (0-10). Score = % Promoters (9-10) minus % Detractors (0-6). Range: −100 to +100.</item>
      <item>SUS: 10 standardized alternating positive/negative items, 1-5 scale. Score = (pos_sum + neg_sum) × 2.5. Average = 68; above 80 = excellent; below 50 = poor.</item>
      <item>CSAT: "How satisfied are you with [X]?" (1-5 or 1-7). Score = (satisfied responses / total) × 100.</item>
      <item>SEQ: "Overall, how easy or difficult was this task?" (1-7, very difficult to very easy). Use after each task in usability testing. Benchmark = 5.5.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/survey_metrics.py">Deterministic NPS and SUS calculator from CSV</reference>
  </section>
</text>
