<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Survey Question Quality Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Rules for writing unbiased questions, maximizing response rate, and known failure modes when agents assist with survey work.</summary>

  <section title="Question Quality Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each question must address exactly one concept; split any question that could be answered differently if interpreted two ways.</statement>
      <rationale>Double-barreled questions ("speed and accuracy") produce uninterpretable data because the respondent cannot indicate which dimension drove their answer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep total survey completion time under 5 minutes (median respondent); cut questions if the pilot exceeds this threshold.</statement>
      <rationale>Surveys over 5 minutes see sharply elevated dropout and straight-lining (respondents select the same answer for all items to finish faster).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Place demographic questions at the end of the survey, not the beginning.</statement>
      <rationale>Opening with demographics signals the survey is about the respondent rather than the product, reducing engagement with core questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Randomize answer order on attitudinal items and Likert blocks to neutralize order and anchoring bias.</statement>
      <rationale>Fixed answer order produces systematic bias toward top or bottom options; randomization distributes this effect across respondents.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Response Rate Factors">
    <list>
      <item>Length — shorter surveys have higher completion rates; every additional question reduces response.</item>
      <item>Mobile-friendly format — many respondents complete on phone; fixed-width tables and non-tap-friendly controls cause abandonment.</item>
      <item>Clear stated purpose — respondents complete surveys that explain why their input matters.</item>
      <item>Mid-week, mid-day timing — Tuesday–Thursday, 10am–2pm local time consistently outperform other windows.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent invents a 7-point Likert scale when a 5-point was specified.</description>
      <reason>Scale changes invalidate benchmark comparability; constrain the agent to the exact scale defined in the research plan.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent codes open-ended responses and assigns confident themes to very short responses ("ok", emoji, single word).</description>
      <reason>LLMs hallucinate themes from sparse text; enforce a minimum word count before LLM coding and flag low-confidence items for human review.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent computes NPS or SUS via LLM completion rather than deterministic code.</description>
      <reason>LLMs make arithmetic errors and confuse metric formulas; use the provided Python calculator for all metric computations.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent treats high survey NPS as a signal that users will pay for the product.</description>
      <reason>Stated preferences overestimate willingness-to-pay by 2-4x; willingness-to-pay research requires separate conjoint or pricing studies, not a satisfaction survey.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Human Checkpoints">
    <list>
      <item>Instrument review by a researcher before launch — agent-drafted questions need bias check before fielding.</item>
      <item>Thematic-coding spot check: human reviews at least 10% of LLM-coded open-ended responses before finalizing themes.</item>
      <item>Non-English surveys: native-speaker review required, especially for SUS which is particularly sensitive to wording.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
