<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Survey Question Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Good and bad survey question examples with explanations of why each antipattern fails.</summary>

  <section title="Good Question Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Question: "How often do you use the search feature?"
Options:
  - Never
  - Less than once a week
  - 1-3 times per week
  - Daily
  - Multiple times per day]]></code>
      <note>Single concept, unambiguous options with no gaps or overlaps, no assumed direction.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Question: "How satisfied are you with [product]?"
Options:
  - Very dissatisfied
  - Dissatisfied
  - Neutral
  - Satisfied
  - Very satisfied]]></code>
      <note>Standard CSAT wording; symmetric scale from negative to positive; all five points labelled.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Question Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Double-barreled: "How satisfied are you with the speed and accuracy of search results?"</description>
      <reason>Two dimensions in one question — a user who finds search fast but inaccurate cannot give a meaningful answer. Split into two separate questions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Leading: "How much do you love our new feature?"</description>
      <reason>Presupposes positive sentiment; drives respondents toward positive answers regardless of actual experience. Neutral wording: "How would you rate the new feature?"</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Vague: "How often do you use it?"</description>
      <reason>"It" is undefined; "often" is undefined. Every respondent interprets the question differently, producing incomparable data.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Double negative: "Is there anything you don't dislike about the onboarding?"</description>
      <reason>Double negatives require cognitive parsing effort that introduces noise and errors in responses. Rewrite as a direct positive or negative question.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Survey Mistakes">
    <list>
      <item>Too long — target under 5 minutes; surveys over 10 minutes see 40%+ dropout.</item>
      <item>Too many open-ended questions — each open-ended adds analysis cost; limit to 1-2 per survey.</item>
      <item>No pilot test — unclear questions only become visible when real respondents encounter them.</item>
      <item>Wrong audience — sample that does not represent actual users produces misleading findings.</item>
      <item>No analysis plan — define how you will analyze results before fielding, not after; post-hoc fishing inflates false-positive rates.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
