<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="surveys Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for surveys as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Double-barreled: "How satisfied are you with the speed and accuracy of search results?"</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Two dimensions in one question — a user who finds search fast but inaccurate cannot give a meaningful answer. Split into two separate questions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Leading: "How much do you love our new feature?"</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Presupposes positive sentiment; drives respondents toward positive answers regardless of actual experience. Neutral wording: "How would you rate the new feature?"</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Vague: "How often do you use it?"</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"It" is undefined; "often" is undefined. Every respondent interprets the question differently, producing incomparable data.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Double negative: "Is there anything you don't dislike about the onboarding?"</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Double negatives require cognitive parsing effort that introduces noise and errors in responses. Rewrite as a direct positive or negative question.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Self-report bias: stated preferences differ from revealed behavior; survey results need triangulation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Users often report different behaviors than they actually exhibit. Surveys must be paired with behavioral analytics for validation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Survey fatigue: long surveys collapse response rate and inflate straight-lining (same answer all the way down).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Fatigue introduces systematic error. Keep surveys under 5 minutes and pilot-test timing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Sampling bias: who answers is rarely who you mean. Voluntary samples skew engaged + dissatisfied.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Survey respondents are self-selected. Compare respondent demographics to your user base to assess bias.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent invents a 7-point Likert scale when a 5-point was specified.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Scale changes invalidate benchmark comparability; constrain the agent to the exact scale defined in the research plan.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent codes open-ended responses and assigns confident themes to very short responses ("ok", emoji, single word).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs hallucinate themes from sparse text; enforce a minimum word count before LLM coding and flag low-confidence items for human review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent computes NPS or SUS via LLM completion rather than deterministic code.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs make arithmetic errors and confuse metric formulas; use the provided Python calculator for all metric computations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent treats high survey NPS as a signal that users will pay for the product.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Stated preferences overestimate willingness-to-pay by 2-4x; willingness-to-pay research requires separate conjoint or pricing studies, not a satisfaction survey.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
