<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-interaction-patterns" title="Multimodal VUI Interaction Patterns">
  <summary>Four multimodal interaction patterns, smart display card layout rules, fallback hierarchy requirements, and timeout standards.</summary>

  <section title="Four Interaction Patterns">
    <list>
      <item>Voice-initiated, screen-completed: search results, selections (user speaks query; screen shows results; user taps to select)</item>
      <item>Screen-initiated, voice-completed: form filling (user sees form; voice fills fields)</item>
      <item>Voice + visual feedback: confirmations, progress (voice command → visual confirmation shown + spoken summary)</item>
      <item>Voice navigation + visual content: information browsing (voice navigates between visual cards/sections)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Smart Display Design Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always provide a three-tier fallback hierarchy — primary (voice) → secondary (touch) → tertiary (keyboard if available).</statement>
      <rationale>Users who cannot speak need touch alternatives; users who cannot touch need keyboard. Designing primary-only leaves large user segments unable to complete interactions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Design the fallback hierarchy before the primary interaction — if touch is broken, voice is broken too for a large user segment.</statement>
      <rationale>Multimodal state sync failures often affect both voice and visual layers simultaneously. The fallback path must work independently of the primary path.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Timeout Standards">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set visual element timeouts to match displayed content complexity: list (10s), detail card (20s), multi-step form (60s). Minimum 10s for accessibility.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent-suggested timeouts are often too short for elderly users or users with cognitive disabilities. Accessibility-minimum values must be specified explicitly in the prompt.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Spoken Summary Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Spoken summaries must be shorter than visual content — users listening cannot process paragraph-length speech.</statement>
      <rationale>VUI users listening to confirmation speech cannot rewind. Visual content can be re-read; spoken content cannot. Keep summaries to 1–2 sentences maximum.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Voice input: "Show me recipes for pasta" → Visual: card carousel with 5 recipe images → Spoken: "I found 5 pasta recipes" → User taps to expand, speaks to navigate</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/apl-card-generator.py">Generate APL list card JSON for Amazon Echo Show</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-design-flow.txt">Haiku prompt: feature brief → multimodal interaction spec with fallback hierarchy</reference>
</text>
