<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="multimodal-vui-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for multimodal-vui-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>AI-generated flow spec misses state sync when user speaks while simultaneously touching.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multimodal state sync on simultaneous input is an edge case agent-generated specs routinely miss. Add it as an explicit review checklist item in every multimodal spec review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using Echo Show APL templates on Google Nest Hub without adaptation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>APL is Amazon-specific; Google uses Action Builder with Rich Responses and Canvas. Platform-specific templates require separate implementations. Simulator rendering also differs from actual hardware.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent-generated APL JSON using deprecated APL version features.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>APL evolves between versions. Without specifying the exact target APL version in the prompt, agents default to older patterns that fail on current firmware.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Confusing "fallback" (user cannot use primary input) with "error" (input understood but failed).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Fallback paths handle inability to use a modality; error paths handle understood-but-failed interactions. Conflating them produces flows where errors are handled with the wrong recovery mechanism.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Wake-word false positives disrupting visual UI experience.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>AI cannot solve wake-word false positive rate at the UX layer — this is a hardware problem. Design visual UI to be resilient to unexpected voice activation, with visible state indicators when VUI is active.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>VUI timeout set too short for complex visual content without accessibility consideration.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Default timeouts from agent-generated specs are typically optimized for average users. Elderly users and users with cognitive disabilities need at minimum 10s for simple responses, 60s for multi-step forms.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
