<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="automation-tooling" count="20" version="3.0" generated="2026-05-23">
  <description>L2 index of methodologies in the automation-tooling domain. The retriever reads this after picking automation-tooling from L1 domains.xml. Entries list slug + tier + summary; open the leaf AGENTS.md / content/*.xml for full payload.</description>
  <methodology slug="playwright-automation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/playwright-automation">
    <summary>Generates a Playwright test or scraping script using role-based locators, auto-wait, storageState auth reuse, and on-first-retry trace capture.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pnpm-package-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/pnpm-package-management">
    <summary>Produces a pnpm-managed Node.js project config (.npmrc + pnpm-workspace.yaml + package.json packageManager pin + CI workflow) enforcing frozen lockfile, no shameful hoist, and only-allow pnpm.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="practices-backend-languages" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/practices-backend-languages">
    <summary>Produces a backend service scaffold in Go/Rails/Laravel/Spring Boot/.NET/Rust enforcing the canonical layout, error model, DI shape, and async discipline for the chosen language.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="practices-django-coding" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/practices-django-coding">
    <summary>Produces Django app code that uses fat-model thin-view discipline, custom QuerySet managers, select_related/prefetch_related to kill N+1, atomic transactions on writes, and class-based views/DRF for HTTP boundaries.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="practices-frontend-components" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/practices-frontend-components">
    <summary>Produces a frontend component (React, Vue, Svelte, or Angular) following one-responsibility, typed props, accessibility-from-the-start, controlled-vs-uncontrolled separation, and CSS-isolation discipline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="practices-js-ts-stack" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/practices-js-ts-stack">
    <summary>Produces a JS/TS project baseline: strict tsconfig, ESLint flat config + Prettier, Vitest, exports map, ESM-only, type-checked CI step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="practices-python-ecosystem" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/practices-python-ecosystem">
    <summary>Produces a Python project baseline: pyproject.toml with ruff + mypy strict, uv/pip-tools lock, src/ layout, py.typed marker, pre-commit hooks, CI gate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="puppeteer-agent-workflow" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/puppeteer-agent-workflow">
    <summary>Produces a Puppeteer worker script that the agent invokes via Bash with a hard timeout, captures structured artifacts to disk, and never runs browser logic inline in the LLM turn.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="puppeteer-launch-setup" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/puppeteer-launch-setup">
    <summary>Produces a Puppeteer launch config + navigation wrapper with correct CI/Docker flags, pinned Chromium revision, finally-close discipline, and SPA-safe wait strategies.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="puppeteer-output-capture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/puppeteer-output-capture">
    <summary>Produces a Puppeteer capture script that takes screenshots (jpeg/webp quality 80 for high volume), PDFs (printBackground true + waitForSelector before pdf), and HAR (with secret scrubber).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="puppeteer-page-interaction" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/puppeteer-page-interaction">
    <summary>Produces a Puppeteer interaction layer using attribute-based selectors (data-testid/id/name), targeted waitForSelector instead of waitForTimeout, request interception for stable scraping, and form fills via type/select/check methods.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="puppeteer-session-management" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/puppeteer-session-management">
    <summary>Produces a Puppeteer session layer using userDataDir per logical identity, explicit cookie serialisation as a secondary mechanism, isolated browser contexts per parallel job, and a daemonised runner for long-lived sessions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="puppeteer-stealth-proxy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/puppeteer-stealth-proxy">
    <summary>Produces a Puppeteer stealth + proxy layer using one documented evasion stance (plugin or manual, never both), proxy rotation with circuit breaker on 4xx, and bounded retries.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="testing-backend-languages" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/testing-backend-languages">
    <summary>Produces a test suite scaffold per backend language using the idiomatic runner (RSpec/Pest/xUnit/tokio::test/JUnit slices) with the right scope discipline (no @SpringBootTest by default; no WebApplicationFactory by default;</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="testing-django-pytest" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/testing-django-pytest">
    <summary>Produces Django pytest tests using function style + @pytest.mark.django_db + factory_boy factories, parametrize for input variants, shallow mocks, and conftest.py that does not call ORM directly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="testing-js-ts-frontend" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/testing-js-ts-frontend">
    <summary>Produces frontend component tests using @testing-library + Vitest (or Jest), querying by accessible role/label/text, explicit imports from 'vitest' (or globals:true), no snapshot-by-default, and runner-pinned mock APIs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trunk-based-branch-by-abstraction" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/trunk-based-branch-by-abstraction">
    <summary>Produces a Branch-by-Abstraction plan that follows the five steps (Protocol → wrap old → implement new → flag-gated swap → remove old + collapse abstraction), with a step-5 cleanup ticket filed at step-1 merge time.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trunk-based-challenges" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/trunk-based-challenges">
    <summary>Produces a diagnostic report when trunk breaks repeatedly, applying an ordered checklist (gates → CI speed → flags → PR size → review SLA) and recommending the first failing fix before touching downstream symptoms.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trunk-based-ci-gates" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/trunk-based-ci-gates">
    <summary>Produces a CI configuration enforcing trunk-based gates: pre-commit hooks under 1s, CI under 10 minutes, branch protection with full required-status list, auto-revert on red trunk, and a verifier that the required-status list stays in sync with CI job names.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trunk-based-dev-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/automation-tooling/trunk-based-dev-patterns">
    <summary>Produces a trunk-based pattern plan using feature flags, branch by abstraction, and dark launching — with cleanup tickets, positive flag naming, &lt; 24h branch lifetimes, and &lt; 1% dark-launch ramp before scaling.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
