<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="PLG Optimization Tactics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six testable rules anchoring PLG optimization. Each pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="baseline-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every tactic in the backlog MUST declare the funnel metric it moves AND a current numeric baseline. Tactics without a baseline are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal PLG audit; cf. Reforge growth-loop teardowns">Tactics without baselines are theatre — there is no way to detect a lift. The baseline anchors the hypothesis to observable reality.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="prompt-at-80-percent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>In-product upgrade prompts MUST trigger at ≤ 80% of the relevant limit (storage, seats, projects). Prompts at 100% are forbidden — the user has already hit the wall.</statement>
      <rationale source="PostHog + Appcues case studies on upgrade-prompt timing">Prompts at 100% arrive after the user is blocked and frustrated; 80% gives the user time to act before the workflow breaks.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="no-first-session-prompt" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Zero upgrade prompts during the user's first session. Cap upgrade prompts to one per subsequent session. No prompts during a critical workflow or immediately after a recent dismissal.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenView 2024 PLG benchmarks">First-session prompts break trust before value is demonstrated; over-prompting trains users to dismiss everything.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="named-customer-copy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All upgrade copy MUST name a comparable customer, quantify the value (hours saved, projects unlocked, revenue captured), and name the specific plan. Two CTAs required: primary (upgrade) + secondary (see example or learn more).</statement>
      <rationale source="ProfitWell A/B copy tests, Reforge upgrade-copy library">Named customer + quantified benefit copies convert at 2-3× generic CTA text. Generic copy does not connect the user's current need to the plan's value.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="banned-cta-text" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Upgrade CTA text MUST NOT be "Upgrade Now", "Premium Plan", "Get More Features", "Unlock Premium", or any variant. Post-filter the copy generator and reject matches.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal copy lint Q1 2026">Generic phrases survive review because they sound professional; they do not differentiate plans or signal value.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="balanced-free-tier" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Free-tier limits MUST give enough surface to reach the Aha moment but include at least one natural upgrade trigger (usage, feature, user, or time limit). Limit changes ship only after finance + retention sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenView PLG report 2024; Stripe SaaS pricing guide">Too-generous tiers produce low conversion (users never hit limits); too-restrictive produce high abandonment. Limit changes are the highest-leverage decision and need human gating.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
