<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="PLG Optimization Tactics Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six antipatterns observed when LLMs apply PLG tactics catalogs. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="generic-saas-copy" severity="high">
      <symptom>Auto-generated upgrade copy drifts to "powerful features", "enterprise-grade", "premium experience". A/B variants are all interchangeable.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Internal copy lint Q1 2026">LLM falls back to high-frequency training tokens for upgrade contexts.</root-cause>
      <fix>Post-filter the generator against the banned-phrase list; auto-reject + regenerate when the named-customer + quantified-value pattern is absent.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="remove-all-limits" severity="high">
      <symptom>Agent recommends "remove all limits" or "extend trial to 60 days" to boost activation.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="PLG audit notes">LLM optimizes apparent activation by removing friction, ignoring the upgrade-trigger half of the balance.</root-cause>
      <fix>Pin the balanced-free-tier rule in the system prompt; require every limit-change tactic to name the upgrade-trigger it preserves.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="autonomous-free-tier-change" severity="high">
      <symptom>Agent ships a free-tier limit change directly because its ICE score is high.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Internal — change-control audit">Free-tier limits look like an in-product config but couple to revenue + retention.</root-cause>
      <fix>Gate every free-tier limit mutation behind finance + retention sign-off; agents emit a PR/ticket, never a live change.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="prompt-at-limit" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Generated Appcues / Pendo flow triggers the upgrade prompt at exactly the limit (100% usage), not before.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Appcues template defaults">Default flow templates use 100% triggers; the LLM copies the default without checking.</root-cause>
      <fix>Generated flows MUST set the trigger at ≤80% and include a unit test of the trigger condition.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="first-session-prompt" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Upgrade prompt fires on first session because the agent omits the session-count gate.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Internal — first-session prompt audit">Session-count is a behavioral signal the LLM doesn't naturally encode.</root-cause>
      <fix>Generated flows MUST include `session_count &gt;= 2` (or equivalent) as a hard precondition; validator rejects flows missing this gate.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="stale-pql-weights" severity="medium">
      <symptom>PQL scoring weights from last quarter's coefficients reused without re-fitting against current converted cohorts.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Internal — quarterly PLG review">LLM reuses the previously-seen weights as if they are constants.</root-cause>
      <fix>Require the agent to re-fit weights against the most recent converted cohort each quarter; record the fit date in the backlog.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
