<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Business Storytelling (Pyramid / SCQA / Pixar) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding storytelling. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="answer-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Narrative MUST lead with the claim within the first 2 sentences. Burying the answer is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Barbara Minto — The Pyramid Principle">Audience stops reading the moment their question is answered; delay erodes retention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="so-what-on-every-fact" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every fact MUST be paired with a 'so what' implication. Naked facts are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — exec-review audits">Facts without implications force the audience to infer the point themselves; the inference is often wrong.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pixar-causal-chain" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pixar narratives MUST use a strict causal 'because of that' chain: Once upon a time → every day → one day → because of that → because of that → until finally. Skipping links breaks reader cognition.</statement>
      <rationale source="Emma Coats — Pixar 22 storytelling rules">Causal chain is what produces the emotional resonance; non-causal narratives feel like lists.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="scqa-tension-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>SCQA narratives MUST make the Complication explicit and surprising. A weak Complication produces no tension.</statement>
      <rationale source="Barbara Minto — The Pyramid Principle">Without tension the reader has no reason to keep reading; weak Complication kills the arc.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="one-frame-per-piece" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An artefact MUST use exactly one framework (Pyramid OR SCQA OR Pixar). Mixing is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — copy-edit audits">Mixed frameworks read as draft scaffolding the author forgot to remove.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
