<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-frameworks" title="Pyramid Principle, SCQA, and Pixar storytelling frameworks">
  <summary>Three complementary structures for business narratives: Pyramid Principle for logic-driven documents, SCQA for building narrative tension, and Pixar for case studies and change stories.</summary>

  <section title="Pyramid Principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lead with the main point (answer/recommendation), then provide 2-4 supporting arguments, each backed by evidence. Arguments must be MECE: Mutually Exclusive (no overlap) and Collectively Exhaustive (nothing missing).</statement>
      <rationale>Busy readers get the answer immediately and can stop when satisfied. Bottom-up structure forces readers to process all evidence before reaching a conclusion they may reject.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Cloud migration proposal using Pyramid Principle</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
RECOMMENDATION: Migrate to cloud infrastructure by Q3.

ARGUMENT 1: 40% lower TCO
  Evidence: Internal TCO analysis vs current on-prem costs
  Evidence: Competitor benchmarks showing 35-45% savings

ARGUMENT 2: Eliminates current capacity ceiling
  Evidence: Current servers at 87% utilization peak
  Evidence: Projected 3x traffic growth in 18 months

ARGUMENT 3: Reduces deployment cycle from 2 weeks to 2 days
  Evidence: Deployment time comparison with cloud-native competitor
  Evidence: Developer survey: 68% cite deployment speed as top blocker
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Bottom-up structure — buries the answer</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Background: Our servers are aging...
Analysis: We compared three options...
Findings: Cloud showed cost savings...
Conclusion: We recommend migrating to cloud.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="SCQA Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Open with a Situation the audience accepts as true, introduce a Complication that creates tension, raise the Question that tension produces, then deliver the Answer. Never invent a complication where none exists.</statement>
      <rationale>SCQA creates narrative tension that makes the audience want the answer before it is given. Artificial complications undermine credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>SCQA for a product quality proposal</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
S: Our team ships 10 features per quarter — strong velocity.
C: But 30% of features have critical bugs in the first week, eroding customer trust.
Q: How do we maintain velocity while improving quality?
A: Implement automated testing with an 80% coverage gate before any feature ships.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/scqa.md">SCQA fill-in template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Pixar Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the Pixar structure for case studies and change initiative stories: Once upon a time [situation] / Every day [routine] / One day [change] / Because of that [consequence 1] / Because of that [consequence 2] / Until finally [resolution].</statement>
      <rationale>The cause-effect chain of "Because of that" forces specificity about what the intervention actually changed, unlike generic "before/after" formats.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Pixar framework applied to a process automation story</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Once upon a time, our team spent 10 hours/week on manual reporting.
Every day, they copy-pasted data between 5 spreadsheets.
One day, we implemented automated dashboards.
Because of that, reporting time dropped to 1 hour/week.
Because of that, the team redirected 9 hours to analysis instead of data entry.
Until finally, they identified $500K in cost savings in Q4.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/case-study.md">Case study template using Pixar structure</reference>
  </section>
</text>
