<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-elements" title="Hook techniques, concrete language, and the so-what test">
  <summary>Tactical elements that make stories land: opening hooks that create questions, concrete numbers over abstractions, and the so-what test that forces every data point to carry an implication.</summary>

  <section title="The so-what test">
    <rule>
      <statement>For every data point, state the implication explicitly. A statistic without a "so what" is incomplete. The implication must be specific to the audience's context, not generic.</statement>
      <rationale>Audiences cannot reliably infer implications from raw numbers. Stating the implication removes ambiguity and prevents misreading.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[We have 99.9% uptime.]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
99.9% uptime = fewer than 9 hours of downtime per year.
For our users: they will never see an error page during business hours.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Concrete vs abstract language">
    <rule>
      <statement>Replace abstract outcome language with specific measurements. Never use "improved efficiency", "better experience", or "enhanced performance" without a number attached.</statement>
      <rationale>Abstract language is unverifiable and unmemorable. Specific numbers are checkable and anchor the claim.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>"Improved efficiency" → "Cut processing time from 4 hours to 15 minutes"</item>
      <item>"Better customer experience" → "Reduced support tickets by 60%"</item>
      <item>"Enhanced security" → "Blocked 10,000 attacks last month"</item>
      <item>"Faster deploys" → "Deployment cycle: 2 weeks → 2 days"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Hook techniques">
    <rule>
      <statement>The first 30 seconds must create a question in the audience's mind. Use a surprising statistic, a question, a bold claim, a micro-story, or a contradiction — never start by introducing yourself or the agenda.</statement>
      <rationale>Audiences decide within the first 30 seconds whether to engage. An agenda introduction signals "you can tune out for now."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Surprising stat: "90% of startups fail in year 3. Here's what the 10% do differently."</item>
      <item>Question: "What if you could deploy without fear?"</item>
      <item>Bold claim: "Meetings are broken. I can prove it in 2 minutes."</item>
      <item>Micro-story: "Last Tuesday at 2am, our server crashed and no one knew for 4 hours."</item>
      <item>Contradiction: "The best code is no code."</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Analogy rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Analogies must map to a domain the specific audience already understands. Test the analogy domain before using it; an analogy from an unfamiliar domain adds confusion instead of clarity.</statement>
      <rationale>An analogy works only if the audience can instantly map the source domain to the target. A mismatched analogy creates a second explanation problem.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Microservices analogy for a business audience familiar with restaurants</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Think of microservices like a restaurant kitchen.
Instead of one chef doing everything, you have specialists:
prep cook, grill cook, plating cook.
If orders spike at the grill station, you add one more grill cook —
not another full chef who has to learn the whole kitchen.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Burying the lead — writing extensive context before the recommendation.</description>
    <reason>Decision-makers read the first paragraph and skim the rest. A buried recommendation is often missed entirely.</reason>
  </antipattern>
  <antipattern>
    <description>One data point per page rule violated — cramming multiple metrics on one slide.</description>
    <reason>Audiences can process one key point per visual; multiple points on one slide split attention and none land.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <reference path="templates/executive-summary.md">Executive summary template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/presentation-outline.md">Presentation outline: Hook to CTA</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-pyramid.txt">Prompt: apply Pyramid Principle to executive summary</reference>
</text>
