<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules">
  <rule testable="true">State the outcome in ONE sentence using the buyer's language and a measurable end-state — not deliverables, not activities (e.g. "A SOC2 Type 1 audit-ready evidence pack in 6 weeks", not "we do compliance consulting").</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Name one fixed price and one fixed timeline; any canvas with "starting at" or "depending on scope" is rejected — productize means commit, or it is not productized.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Write the scope-OUT list (5-10 bullets of what is explicitly NOT included) on the same page as the scope-IN list; scope-out absence is the #1 cause of margin death.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Document the delivery SOP as a numbered checklist with a name, day-by-day cadence, and the named person who owns each step; if you cannot name the owner, it is not productized.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Cite ≥3 prior deliveries of the same outcome with named clients (logos or anonymized initials), measurable result, and engagement duration; without proof you sell a promise, not a product.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Define one change-order policy: per-scope-out request, named flat fee or hourly addendum, and which item it adds to scope-in; "we'll see" voids the productization.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Set a margin floor and a per-engagement hour budget; if the SOP exceeds the budget by ≥20% in two sequential engagements, return to canvas — the offer is not productizable as scoped.</rule>
  <example>Freelance security consultant productizes "SOC2 Type 1 evidence pack" at $12,000 / 6 weeks. Scope-in: gap assessment, 38 policies authored, evidence collection runbook. Scope-out: penetration testing, employee training delivery, ongoing monitoring. SOP: weeks 1-2 gap analysis (lead consultant), weeks 3-4 policies (author + reviewer), weeks 5-6 evidence + audit prep call. Proof: 5 prior pack deliveries, all passing audit on first attempt. Change-order: $1,500 per added control family.</example>
</text>
