<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Help Users Recognise, Diagnose, Recover from Errors Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Help Users Recognise, Diagnose, Recover from Errors. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-plain-language" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Error messages are in plain language; codes appear as a secondary detail, not the primary message.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen Heuristic #9">Plain language reaches the user; codes alone reach only support staff.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-name-and-point" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Message names what went wrong and points at the offending input or step.</statement>
      <rationale source="Form-design practice">Generic 'invalid input' leaves users hunting for the cause.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-next-action" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every error suggests a concrete next action — retry, edit field, contact support — never a dead end.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen Heuristic #9">Dead-end errors push users into rage-clicks or abandonment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-preserve-input" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>On error, the user input is preserved; the form is not cleared.</statement>
      <rationale source="Form-design practice">Clearing input on error is a recurring high-severity complaint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-instrument-errors" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each error code is instrumented so support can correlate volume and severity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Observability practice">Unmeasured errors cannot be prioritised.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-error-recovery.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
