<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-concepts" title="Data Analysis — Core Concepts and Process">
  <summary>Data analysis components, five-step process, data element attributes, data modeling levels, six quality dimensions, and data rules taxonomy.</summary>

  <section title="What Data Analysis Examines">
    <p>Data Analysis in the BA context covers five questions:</p>
    <list>
      <item>What data the business needs — reports, screens, input, calculated, stored, shared.</item>
      <item>How data is structured — entities, attributes, relationships.</item>
      <item>Where data comes from and goes — sources, targets, integration paths.</item>
      <item>Data quality requirements — accuracy, completeness, consistency, timeliness, validity, uniqueness.</item>
      <item>Data relationships — cardinality, business rules, constraints.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 1: Identify Data Needs">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each data category, document the question it answers and its role in the system before defining attributes.</statement>
      <rationale>Starting with attributes before understanding the data's purpose produces dictionaries that capture fields nobody uses and miss fields everyone needs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>What information do users need? — Reports and screens (consumed data).</item>
      <item>What data is captured? — Input data (created by users or external systems).</item>
      <item>What data is calculated? — Derived data (computed from other fields).</item>
      <item>What data is stored persistently? — Domain entities.</item>
      <item>What data is shared with other systems? — Integration data with defined contracts.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Define Data Elements">
    <p>For each attribute, document all seven characteristics:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Name — clear, unique, business-facing name (not column name).</item>
      <item>Definition — business meaning in plain language.</item>
      <item>Type — text, number, date, boolean, enumeration.</item>
      <item>Format — specific format rules (e.g., ISO 8601 dates, E.164 phone numbers).</item>
      <item>Values — valid values or ranges; enumeration members.</item>
      <item>Source — where the data originates.</item>
      <item>Owner — who is responsible for data quality.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every number cited in a requirements document must carry a definition footnote: metric name, definition, source system, snapshot date.</statement>
      <rationale>Numbers travel without their definitions; within weeks a cited metric becomes folklore that different teams interpret differently, producing conflicting implementations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Data Modeling Levels">
    <list>
      <item>Conceptual — high-level entities and relationships. Audience: business stakeholders. No attributes.</item>
      <item>Logical — detailed attributes, data types, relationships, and business rules. Audience: BA and developers.</item>
      <item>Physical — tables, columns, indexes, constraints. Audience: database developers. Out of BA scope to author; BA reviews for alignment with logical model.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Six Data Quality Dimensions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assess all six quality dimensions before defining data requirements. Missing dimensions produce requirements that assume data quality the system does not have.</statement>
      <rationale>Systems built on inaccurate or inconsistent data inherit the data's defects; post-launch data quality remediation is significantly more expensive than pre-spec assessment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Accuracy — correct values. Measure: error rate. Target threshold: less than 2%.</item>
      <item>Completeness — all required data present. Measure: missing value percentage.</item>
      <item>Consistency — same values across systems. Measure: conflict count between sources.</item>
      <item>Timeliness — current and available. Measure: age of data against business SLA.</item>
      <item>Validity — conforms to business rules. Measure: invalid value percentage.</item>
      <item>Uniqueness — no duplicates. Measure: duplicate rate.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Data Rules">
    <list>
      <item>Validation — Email must contain @; phone must match format.</item>
      <item>Derivation — Total = Quantity x Price; Age = today - birth date.</item>
      <item>Default — Status defaults to "New" on creation.</item>
      <item>Constraint — Start date must be before end date.</item>
      <item>Uniqueness — CustomerID is unique; Email is unique per account.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
