<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Data Analysis — Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Customer entity example with attributes and business rules; data quality findings example; common antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Example: Customer Entity">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Entity: Customer. Owner: CRM team. Source: web registration and import.</note>
      <note>Attributes: CustomerID (Integer, required, auto-generated unique — immutable, system-assigned); FirstName (Text 50, required, not empty); LastName (Text 50, required, not empty); Email (Text 100, required, valid email format — unique across all customers); Phone (Text 20, optional, valid phone format); Status (Text 10, required, enumeration: Active/Inactive/Prospect — defaults to Prospect on creation); CreatedDate (DateTime, required, auto-set on creation).</note>
      <note>Business rules: DR-01: CustomerID is system-generated and immutable. DR-02: Email must be unique across all customers. DR-03: Status defaults to Prospect for new customers.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example: Data Quality Assessment Findings">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Assessment of Product Data. Sample size: 15,000 records. Snapshot: 2026-04-19.</note>
      <note>Accuracy: 3/5 — 8% of prices incorrect vs. catalog; root cause: manual price override without catalog sync.</note>
      <note>Completeness: 4/5 — 2% missing descriptions; root cause: bulk import without description field.</note>
      <note>Consistency: 2/5 — product names differ across CRM, ERP, and web catalog; root cause: no naming convention enforced at import.</note>
      <note>Timeliness: 5/5 — updated daily, within SLA.</note>
      <note>Validity: 4/5 — 1% with invalid category codes; root cause: legacy category codes not migrated.</note>
      <note>Uniqueness: 3/5 — 5% duplicate SKUs; root cause: multiple import channels with no deduplication.</note>
      <note>Priority issue: Consistency (score 2/5). Recommendation: establish and enforce product naming convention at all import channels before building the new product search feature.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No data dictionary — everyone defines data differently.</description>
      <reason>Without a shared data dictionary, different teams build against different definitions of the same entity; the inconsistency surfaces as data quality failures after go-live, not before.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping data quality assessment — assuming current data is correct.</description>
      <reason>Systems built on inaccurate or inconsistent data inherit the data's defects; pre-spec assessment is orders of magnitude cheaper than post-launch remediation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Technical-only data modeling without business definitions.</description>
      <reason>Column names and data types without business meanings produce a dictionary that developers can implement but stakeholders cannot validate; discrepancies appear only during UAT.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No data ownership assigned.</description>
      <reason>Without a named owner per entity, data quality degrades because nobody has authority or accountability to enforce rules or resolve conflicts between source systems.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring historical data — not considering how data will change over time.</description>
      <reason>Systems designed without archival, versioning, or audit-trail requirements discover these needs at scale after launch, requiring costly schema migrations.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
