<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="data-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for data-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>No data dictionary — everyone defines data differently.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a shared data dictionary, different teams build against different definitions of the same entity; the inconsistency surfaces as data quality failures after go-live, not before.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping data quality assessment — assuming current data is correct.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Systems built on inaccurate or inconsistent data inherit the data's defects; pre-spec assessment is orders of magnitude cheaper than post-launch remediation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Technical-only data modeling without business definitions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Column names and data types without business meanings produce a dictionary that developers can implement but stakeholders cannot validate; discrepancies appear only during UAT.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>No data ownership assigned.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a named owner per entity, data quality degrades because nobody has authority or accountability to enforce rules or resolve conflicts between source systems.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring historical data — not considering how data will change over time.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Systems designed without archival, versioning, or audit-trail requirements discover these needs at scale after launch, requiring costly schema migrations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
