<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="requirements-documentation">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Requirements documentation across hierarchy: business (why), stakeholder (needs), solution (functional/non-functional). SMART criteria, Given/When/Then AC, baseline for traceability.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>documentation</tag>
      <tag>babok</tag>
      <tag>acceptance-criteria</tag>
      <tag>specification</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Requirements Documentation</title>
    <summary>A structured methodology for documenting requirements across the hierarchy: business requirements (why), stakeholder requirements (user needs), and solution requirements (functional and non-functional). Uses SMART criteria, acceptance criteria in Given/When/Then form, and a requirements baseline to enable traceability, testing, and change control. Without documentation: requirements exist only in people's heads, different team members have different understanding, developers build the wrong thing, testing cannot verify, and changes cannot be tracked.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Requirements exist only in people's heads. Different team members have different understanding. Developers build the wrong thing because requirements were unclear. Testing cannot verify because there is nothing to test against. Changes cannot be tracked because there is no baseline.</p>
      <p>Without documentation: ambiguous requirements, misunderstandings between teams, no basis for testing, change control impossible.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Producing the canonical spec.md for an SDD feature: business requirements (BR), stakeholder requirements, functional requirements (FR), non-functional requirements (NFR), and acceptance criteria — all in one machine-readable document.</item>
        <item>Migrating loose Notion / Confluence / Google Doc requirement notes into a Markdown + YAML-frontmatter requirements/REQ-XXX.md repository that diff/grep/Git can manage.</item>
        <item>Generating a Business Requirements Document (BRD) for stakeholder sign-off when an SDD spec is too dense for non-technical readers — a parallel artefact, not a replacement.</item>
        <item>Translating user-story backlogs (Jira, Linear, GitHub Issues) into the standard REQ-XXX format for regulated review (audits, SOC2, ISO).</item>
        <item>Pairing with requirements-traceability, requirements-lifecycle, and requirements-validation to close the Document → Trace → Validate loop.</item>
        <item>Pre-development: enforcing structure before code. Acceptance criteria in Given/When/Then form become Playwright/pytest scaffolds via codegen.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo founder pre-PMF: a BRD is theatre when the spec changes weekly. Use opportunity-solution-trees plus living user stories.</item>
        <item>Pure ops tasks (cron edits, nginx vhost tweaks, infra rotations) — runbooks, not requirement docs.</item>
        <item>Discovery spikes whose deliverable is a learning, not a baseline — use research notes and a stop condition.</item>
        <item>When stakeholders refuse written sign-off — without an Approved gate, the document degrades to a status spreadsheet.</item>
        <item>One-off scripts where the cost of writing REQ-XXX exceeds the cost of just rewriting the script.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="requirements-hierarchy">
      <p>Business Requirements → Stakeholder Requirements → Solution Requirements (Functional Requirements + Non-Functional Requirements).</p>
      <list>
        <item>Business: Why are we doing this? Example: Increase revenue by 20%</item>
        <item>Stakeholder: What do users need? Example: Sales reps need to create quotes faster</item>
        <item>Functional: What should system do? Example: System shall calculate quote total</item>
        <item>Non-Functional: How should system perform? Example: Page loads in &lt; 2 seconds</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="step-1-choose-documentation-format">
      <list>
        <item>Text document: Traditional, detailed. Tools: Word, Confluence.</item>
        <item>User stories: Agile, iterative. Tools: Jira, Azure DevOps.</item>
        <item>Use cases: Interactions, flows. Tools: Word, draw.io.</item>
        <item>Models: Complex processes. Tools: Visio, Lucidchart.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="step-2-write-clear-requirements">
      <p>Good requirement characteristics (SMART):</p>
      <list>
        <item>Specific: Clear, unambiguous. Test: Only one interpretation.</item>
        <item>Measurable: Can verify completion. Test: Testable.</item>
        <item>Achievable: Technically feasible. Test: Can be built.</item>
        <item>Relevant: Traces to business need. Test: Has clear purpose.</item>
        <item>Time-bound: Has timeline context. Test: Delivery prioritized.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Writing tips:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Use active voice ("System shall..." not "It should be...")</item>
        <item>One requirement per statement</item>
        <item>Avoid subjective terms (fast, user-friendly, easy)</item>
        <item>Include acceptance criteria</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="step-3-document-functional-requirements">
      <p>Template:</p>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
**REQ-XXX:** [Requirement Name]

**Description:** The system shall [action] when [trigger].

**Rationale:** [Why this is needed]

**Source:** [Stakeholder or document]

**Priority:** [Must/Should/Could/Won't]

**Acceptance Criteria:**
1. Given [context], when [action], then [outcome]
2. Given [context], when [action], then [outcome]
      ]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="step-4-document-non-functional-requirements">
      <list>
        <item>Performance: Response time, throughput</item>
        <item>Scalability: User capacity, data volume</item>
        <item>Security: Authentication, authorization</item>
        <item>Usability: Ease of use, accessibility</item>
        <item>Reliability: Uptime, error handling</item>
        <item>Compatibility: Browsers, devices</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="step-5-organize-and-structure">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
1. Introduction
   1.1 Purpose
   1.2 Scope
   1.3 Definitions

2. Business Requirements
   2.1 Business objectives
   2.2 Success metrics

3. Stakeholder Requirements
   3.1 User types
   3.2 User needs

4. Solution Requirements
   4.1 Functional requirements
       4.1.1 Feature A
       4.1.2 Feature B
   4.2 Non-functional requirements
       4.2.1 Performance
       4.2.2 Security

5. Constraints and Assumptions
6. Appendices
      ]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="business-requirements-document-template">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Business Requirements Document: [Project Name]

**Version:** [X.X]
**Date:** [Date]
**Author:** [Name]
**Status:** [Draft/Review/Approved]

## 1. Executive Summary
[Brief overview of the initiative]

## 2. Business Context

### 2.1 Current State
[Description of current situation]

### 2.2 Problem Statement
[What problem we are solving]

### 2.3 Business Objectives
| Objective | Measure | Target |
|-----------|---------|--------|
| [Objective] | [KPI] | [Target] |

## 3. Scope

### 3.1 In Scope
- [Item 1]
- [Item 2]

### 3.2 Out of Scope
- [Exclusion 1]
- [Exclusion 2]

## 4. Stakeholders
| Stakeholder | Role | Interest |
|-------------|------|----------|
| [Name/Group] | [Role] | [What they need] |

## 5. Business Requirements

| ID | Requirement | Priority | Source |
|----|-------------|----------|--------|
| BR-01 | [Requirement] | Must | [Source] |
| BR-02 | [Requirement] | Should | [Source] |

## 6. Constraints
- [Constraint 1]
- [Constraint 2]

## 7. Assumptions
- [Assumption 1]
- [Assumption 2]

## 8. Dependencies
- [Dependency 1]
- [Dependency 2]

## Approval

| Role | Name | Signature | Date |
|------|------|-----------|------|
| Sponsor | | | |
| Business Owner | | | |
      ]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="user-story-template">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
**Story ID:** US-[XXX]
**Title:** [Short title]
**Epic:** [Parent epic]

## User Story
**As a** [user type]
**I want** [capability]
**So that** [benefit]

## Acceptance Criteria

**Scenario 1: [Name]**
- **Given** [precondition]
- **When** [action]
- **Then** [expected result]

**Scenario 2: [Name]**
- **Given** [precondition]
- **When** [action]
- **Then** [expected result]

## Additional Information
- **Priority:** [Must/Should/Could]
- **Estimate:** [Story points]
- **Dependencies:** [Related stories]
- **Notes:** [Additional context]
      ]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="example-functional-requirement">
      <example type="good" title="Example 1: Functional Requirement">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
**REQ-101: Quote Total Calculation**

**Description:** The system shall calculate the total quote amount by summing all line item amounts plus applicable taxes.

**Rationale:** Sales reps need accurate totals to provide quotes to customers.

**Source:** Sales Manager (Interview 2026-01-10)

**Priority:** Must

**Acceptance Criteria:**
1. Given a quote with multiple line items, when user clicks "Calculate", then total equals sum of all line amounts
2. Given applicable tax rate of 8%, when total is calculated, then tax amount equals total x 0.08
3. Given no line items, when user clicks "Calculate", then total displays as $0.00
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="example-non-functional-requirement">
      <example type="good" title="Example 2: Non-Functional Requirement">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
**NFR-015: Page Load Performance**

**Description:** All application pages shall load within 2 seconds under normal load conditions.

**Measure:** Time from user click to page fully rendered

**Target:** 95th percentile &lt; 2 seconds

**Conditions:**
- Normal load: Up to 500 concurrent users
- Network: Standard corporate LAN

**Verification:** Load testing with 500 virtual users
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <list>
        <item>Vague requirements - "System should be fast"</item>
        <item>No acceptance criteria - Cannot verify completion</item>
        <item>Implementation in requirements - Specifying how, not what</item>
        <item>Missing non-functional - Only documenting features</item>
        <item>No traceability - Cannot link to business need</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="where-it-fails-limitations">
      <p>Implementation leak. Agents producing FRs from elicitation transcripts repeatedly emit "the system shall use Postgres" — a how, not a what. README mistake #3 holds for LLMs in spades; lint for forbidden tokens (Postgres, React, Redis, S3, Lambda).</p>
      <p>Vagueness camouflaged as confidence. "System shall be fast" passes a generic LLM review because the model defaults to amiable. Force a measurable-or-reject gate (numeric threshold + unit + measurement method).</p>
      <p>NFR amnesia. LLMs over-index on functional requirements and silently drop NFRs (security, usability, accessibility, observability). Always run an NFR-coverage pass with an explicit category checklist.</p>
      <p>ID collisions. Parallel agents writing into the same requirements/ directory race on REQ-XXX numbering. Use a lock file or pre-allocate ranges per agent.</p>
      <p>AC explosion. Generating 12 Gherkin scenarios per FR makes the spec unmanageable. Cap at 3-5 scenarios per FR; defer edge cases to test-plan.</p>
      <p>Stale acceptance criteria. Once code ships, AC drift from production behaviour. Tie a pre-commit hook to spec.md so any FR edit re-flags downstream tests.</p>
      <p>One-doc-fits-all fallacy. A 200-page BRD nobody reads. Split: BRD for sponsors (5-10 pages), spec.md for builders, story cards for sprints. Same source, three views.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="quality-checklist">
      <p>Before finalizing requirements:</p>
      <checklist>
        <check>Each requirement has unique ID</check>
        <check>Requirements are testable</check>
        <check>No ambiguous terms (fast, easy, user-friendly)</check>
        <check>Acceptance criteria defined</check>
        <check>Priority assigned</check>
        <check>Source documented</check>
        <check>No conflicts between requirements</check>
        <check>Traces to business objective</check>
        <check>Reviewed by stakeholders</check>
      </checklist>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Treat the requirements set as a directory of small Markdown files (spec/REQ-XXX.md or requirements/REQ-XXX.md) with YAML frontmatter for id, type (BR / SR / FR / NFR), priority, source, state, traces_to. A documentation pipeline runs in four stages: (1) a draft agent (Sonnet) consumes elicitation notes / interview transcripts and emits one REQ-XXX file per atomic requirement; (2) a lint agent applies the SMART + INVEST + measurability rules and rejects vague tokens; (3) a coverage agent (Opus) checks that every business objective has at least one BR, every BR has at least one FR, every FR has at least one AC, every AC is testable; (4) a render agent assembles the BRD / spec.md / sprint-story views from the same source via Jinja or pandoc. /faion should refuse to advance a feature into in-progress/ until stages 1-3 pass.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Document requirements in machine-readable form (REQ-XXX.md with YAML frontmatter).</item>
        <item>Use Given/When/Then acceptance criteria; they become test scaffolds automatically.</item>
        <item>Enforce traceability: every FR must trace to at least one BR; every AC must be testable.</item>
        <item>Separate BRD (for sponsors) from spec.md (for builders); reuse the same source data.</item>
        <item>Cap acceptance criteria at 3-5 per FR; defer edge cases to test-plan.</item>
        <item>Run NFR coverage pass explicitly; LLMs default to functional requirements.</item>
        <item>Reject vague subjective terms (fast, easy); require measurable thresholds with units.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow-details">
      <p>Documentation pipeline in four stages: (1) Draft agent (Sonnet) consumes elicitation notes / interview transcripts and emits one REQ-XXX file per atomic requirement; (2) Lint agent applies SMART + INVEST + measurability rules and rejects vague tokens; (3) Coverage agent (Opus) checks that every business objective has at least one BR, every BR has at least one FR, every FR has at least one AC, every AC is testable; (4) Render agent assembles BRD / spec.md / sprint-story views from the same source via Jinja or pandoc. /faion should refuse to advance a feature into in-progress/ until stages 1-3 pass.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-sdd-executor-agent (owns per-feature spec.md lifecycle, drafts requirements as SDD tasks, produces commits per requirement batch, blocks done/ if AC missing), /faion (wires documentation pipeline as quality gate between backlog/ → todo/), brainstorm (diverge to surface NFR categories the draft missed like security, accessibility, locale, observability, performance, compliance; converge to keep only those that apply), password-scrubber-agent (pre-commit pass over requirements/ to catch credentials pasted from stakeholder transcripts), improver (periodic audit: scans done/ features for AC that drifted from production behaviour), custom ba-doc-drafter (sonnet, turns transcript snippets into REQ-XXX skeletons with rationale, source, AC stubs), custom ba-doc-linter (haiku, cheap rule-based pass: SMART regex, forbidden implementation tokens, ID uniqueness, frontmatter completeness).</p>
      <p>Prompt pattern — Draft (Stage 1, structured output): Inputs: transcript_chunk, feature_id, REQ-NNN. Emit YAML frontmatter + Markdown body matching templates.md. type ∈ {BR, SR, FR, NFR}, priority ∈ {Must, Should, Could, Won't}. Body MUST contain Description, Rationale, Source, Acceptance Criteria (Given/When/Then). No implementation tokens (Postgres|Redis|React|S3|Lambda|specific framework names). No subjective adjectives (fast|easy|user-friendly|intuitive) without numeric threshold. Output ONE requirement only. Lint (Stage 2): Score requirement against SMART + measurability + non-implementation. Output JSON: {req_id, smart:{S,M,A,R,T:pass|fail}, measurability:pass|fail, forbidden_tokens:[], subjective_terms:[], severity:high|med|low, fix_suggestions:&lt;=3 items}.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools: markdownlint-cli2 (lint REQ-XXX Markdown structure), vale (prose linter — banned-word lists for implementation/subjective terms), pandoc (render REQ-XXX → DOCX/PDF for stakeholder review), mkdocs + mkdocs-material (browseable requirements site from same Markdown source), gherkin-lint (validate Given/When/Then AC syntax), behave / pytest-bdd (execute AC as test scaffolds in Python), cucumber (same for JS/TS projects), yq (query/transform YAML frontmatter across many REQ files), gh issue create (mirror REQ-XXX into GitHub Issues for sprint use).</p>
      <p>Services: Jama Connect (SaaS, REST API OAuth, heavyweight regulated), ReqView (SaaS/desktop, OpenSpecTrace export, lightweight), IBM ENGINEERING DOORS Next (SaaS/on-prem, OSLC API), Modern Requirements4DevOps (SaaS, Azure DevOps API), Aha! (SaaS, REST + GraphQL, strong roadmap link), Notion (SaaS, REST API + databases, good for BRD), Confluence (SaaS, REST API, standard for BRDs), Linear (SaaS, GraphQL, best for sprint-story), Jira (SaaS, REST + JQL, heavy), GitHub Issues + Markdown specs (OSS, gh CLI + MCP, recommended for solo/agentic).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="references">
      <list>
        <item>BA Framework Guide v3 - Requirements Analysis and Design Definition</item>
        <item>BA industry Requirements Documentation Standards</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-selection-guidance">
      <list>
        <item>Gather and analyze requirements: sonnet — Complex reasoning about stakeholder needs</item>
        <item>Write acceptance criteria for features: sonnet — Requires testing perspective and detail</item>
        <item>Create process flow diagrams (BPMN): opus — Architecture and complex modeling decisions</item>
        <item>Format requirements in templates: haiku — Mechanical formatting and pattern application</item>
        <item>Validate requirements with stakeholders: sonnet — Needs reasoning and communication planning</item>
        <item>Perform gap analysis between states: opus — Strategic analysis and trade-off evaluation</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="next-steps">
      <p>After documentation: (1) Review with stakeholders, (2) Resolve conflicts and gaps, (3) Get sign-off, (4) Baseline requirements, (5) Connect to Requirements Traceability methodology.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Implementation leak: agents emit "use Postgres" instead of "persist data". Lint for framework names.</item>
        <item>Score inflation: agents default to "System shall be fast" without measurement. Force measurable-or-reject gate.</item>
        <item>NFR amnesia: agents over-index on FR and silently drop security/accessibility/performance. Use explicit checklist.</item>
        <item>ID collisions: parallel agents writing to same requirements/ directory race on numbering. Pre-allocate ranges or use lock file.</item>
        <item>Acceptance criteria explosion: agents generate 12 Gherkin scenarios. Cap at 3-5; defer to test-plan.</item>
        <item>Stale acceptance criteria: once code ships, AC drift. Tie pre-commit hook so FR edits re-flag tests.</item>
        <item>One-doc fallacy: a 200-page BRD nobody reads. Split per audience: BRD (sponsors), spec.md (builders), stories (sprints).</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/brd-template.md" purpose="Business Requirements Document template for stakeholder review"/>
      <template path="templates/user-story-template.md" purpose="User story with acceptance criteria in Given/When/Then format"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/standards-and-resources/babok/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
