<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="jobs-to-be-done Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for jobs-to-be-done. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Express every job as: "When [situation/trigger], I want to [action/motivation], so I can [outcome/expected result]." Capture all three components; a statement missing the situation is a feature request, not a job.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The situation anchors the job to a real trigger moment; without it, the statement describes an abstract desire that cannot be used to design a specific product experience.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every job has three dimensions: Functional (what task to accomplish), Emotional (how to feel), Social (how to be perceived). Capture all three; products that address only the functional dimension lose to products that also address emotional and social dimensions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Customers who feel satisfied functionally but anxious emotionally or embarrassed socially will churn or avoid the product in high-stakes situations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Identify the job, not the current solution; jobs persist across technology changes while solutions change. Compete at the job level, not the feature level.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Communicating distant family (job) has been done by letters, phone, email, and video calls — same job, radically different solutions. A product competing on features competes with current solutions; a product competing on the job owns the category across solution generations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For a customer to switch, Push + Pull must outweigh Habit + Fear: Push = current pain driving away from old solution; Pull = new solution's appeal; Habit = comfort with the old way; Fear = anxiety about the new. All four forces must be assessed to predict adoption.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Products with strong pull but ignoring habit and fear launch to crickets; the switching cost is the sum of habit disruption and anxiety, not just the price difference.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interview people who recently purchased, switched to a competitor, or started using a category — not long-tenured loyal customers. Recent switchers remember the decision; loyal customers have rationalized it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Memory of the decision process fades within weeks; loyal customers reconstruct a coherent narrative that omits the actual friction and anxiety that drove the switch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ask "what did you use before?" before asking about the current product — the previous solution reveals the job better than the new one.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The job is defined by what was inadequate, not by what the customer currently values. The switch happened because the old solution failed the job.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For complex jobs, map all 8 stages: Define, Locate, Prepare, Confirm, Execute, Monitor, Modify, Conclude. For each stage: customer goals, current pain points, opportunity for the product to help. Build the product around the highest-pain stages, not the core execution stage alone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Most products address the Execute stage well but abandon the customer at Locate, Prepare, and Confirm — which are often the highest-friction points and the real differentiator.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
