<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-jtbd-framework" title="JTBD Core Concepts">
  <summary>Job statement formula, three job dimensions, hiring/firing mechanics, and four forces of progress.</summary>

  <section title="Job Statement Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Express every job as: "When [situation/trigger], I want to [action/motivation], so I can [outcome/expected result]." Capture all three components; a statement missing the situation is a feature request, not a job.</statement>
      <rationale>The situation anchors the job to a real trigger moment; without it, the statement describes an abstract desire that cannot be used to design a specific product experience.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>When I finish a client project, I want to send a professional invoice quickly, so I can get paid faster and move on to the next project. All three components present: trigger (finish client project), action (send invoice quickly), outcome (get paid faster).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Three Job Dimensions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every job has three dimensions: Functional (what task to accomplish), Emotional (how to feel), Social (how to be perceived). Capture all three; products that address only the functional dimension lose to products that also address emotional and social dimensions.</statement>
      <rationale>Customers who feel satisfied functionally but anxious emotionally or embarrassed socially will churn or avoid the product in high-stakes situations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Invoicing software: Functional = file a professional invoice; Emotional = feel confident I will get paid; Social = appear to be a legitimate business. A product addressing all three wins over one that just sends invoices.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Jobs Are Stable; Solutions Evolve">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify the job, not the current solution; jobs persist across technology changes while solutions change. Compete at the job level, not the feature level.</statement>
      <rationale>Communicating distant family (job) has been done by letters, phone, email, and video calls — same job, radically different solutions. A product competing on features competes with current solutions; a product competing on the job owns the category across solution generations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Four Forces of Progress">
    <rule>
      <statement>For a customer to switch, Push + Pull must outweigh Habit + Fear: Push = current pain driving away from old solution; Pull = new solution's appeal; Habit = comfort with the old way; Fear = anxiety about the new. All four forces must be assessed to predict adoption.</statement>
      <rationale>Products with strong pull but ignoring habit and fear launch to crickets; the switching cost is the sum of habit disruption and anxiety, not just the price difference.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
