<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-interview-and-mapping" title="JTBD Interview Method and Job Mapping">
  <summary>Switcher interview technique, timeline reconstruction questions, 8-stage job map, and worked examples.</summary>

  <section title="Interview Recent Switchers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Interview people who recently purchased, switched to a competitor, or started using a category — not long-tenured loyal customers. Recent switchers remember the decision; loyal customers have rationalized it.</statement>
      <rationale>Memory of the decision process fades within weeks; loyal customers reconstruct a coherent narrative that omits the actual friction and anxiety that drove the switch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Ask "what did you use before?" before asking about the current product — the previous solution reveals the job better than the new one.</statement>
      <rationale>The job is defined by what was inadequate, not by what the customer currently values. The switch happened because the old solution failed the job.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Timeline Reconstruction Questions">
    <p>Reconstruct the decision timeline across six stages: First Thought (trigger), Passive Looking (awareness), Active Looking (evaluation), Decision (purchase), Consumption (usage), Satisfaction (review).</p>
    <p>Key questions: "When did you first think you needed something different?" / "What was happening in your life at that point?" / "What did you try before this?" / "What almost stopped you from switching?"</p>
  </section>

  <section title="8-Stage Job Map">
    <rule>
      <statement>For complex jobs, map all 8 stages: Define, Locate, Prepare, Confirm, Execute, Monitor, Modify, Conclude. For each stage: customer goals, current pain points, opportunity for the product to help. Build the product around the highest-pain stages, not the core execution stage alone.</statement>
      <rationale>Most products address the Execute stage well but abandon the customer at Locate, Prepare, and Confirm — which are often the highest-friction points and the real differentiator.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Classic Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Milkshake job (Christensen): Commuters buying milkshakes at 7am. Surface understanding: they want breakfast. JTBD: "When I have a long boring commute, I want something to do with my hand that lasts 20 minutes, so I can make the drive less boring." Real competition: donuts, bananas, bagels, podcasts. Implication: make milkshake thicker and chunkier — a product insight invisible from demographic analysis.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Online course JTBD: Surface = "learn Python." Real job: "When I am stuck in a dead-end job, I want to gain a skill that is in demand, so I can switch careers and earn more money." Real competition: bootcamps, MBA, networking for promotion, starting a business. A Python course competing on curriculum loses; one competing on career change wins.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Asking "what features do you want?" instead of "what are you trying to accomplish?"</description>
      <reason>Feature requests describe a solution hypothesis; job discovery requires understanding the progress the customer is trying to make, which is often different from what they explicitly request.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Building one job statement for all customers when different segments hire the product for different jobs.</description>
      <reason>A single product can be hired for multiple distinct jobs; conflating them into one statement produces positioning that speaks clearly to nobody.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/jtbd-interview.md">Interview guide for recent switchers</reference>
  <reference path="templates/job-map.md">8-stage job map template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-extract-statement.txt">LLM prompt to extract JTBD statement from transcript</reference>
</text>
