<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="instagram-growth">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>smm-manager</domain>
    <summary>Reels-first growth system for Instagram: post 1-2 Reels daily, engage 30 min/day, convert via DM triggers. Hook must work silent. Use 3-5 hashtags, track Reel reach % and engagement rate.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>instagram</tag>
      <tag>reels</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>dm-funnel</tag>
      <tag>social-media</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Instagram Growth Tactics</title>

    <summary>A Reels-first growth system for Instagram: post 1-2 Reels daily, run Stories daily, engage 30 minutes per day, and convert via DM triggers. The hook of a Reel must work with sound off. Use 3-5 hashtags only — 30-hashtag lists risk shadowban. Track Reel reach % and engagement rate, not follower count.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Instagram's algorithm distributes Reels via Explore to non-followers; feed posts do not get this treatment. Accounts that prioritize Reels with strong visual hooks (text overlay in the first 1-2 seconds) reach audiences 3-10x larger than their follower base.</p>
      <p>DM trigger campaigns ("DM me 'GUIDE'") convert 3-5x better than link-in-bio clicks for lead magnets because they start a conversation rather than sending traffic to a cold page.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Generating Reel script outlines (hook + 3-5 body points + CTA) for a content batch</item>
        <item>Drafting weekly caption batches across pillars (educational, BTS, testimonial, CTA)</item>
        <item>Writing DM trigger copy for lead generation posts</item>
        <item>Producing a weekly content calendar: Reels + Stories + carousels per the schedule</item>
        <item>Analyzing an Instagram Insights CSV export for top-performing content patterns</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Generating the Reel video itself — agent produces scripts, not video files</item>
        <item>Hashtag generation at scale (30 tags) — current safe range is 3-5 targeted tags</item>
        <item>Automated commenting on other accounts — Instagram detects bot-style engagement</item>
        <item>Audience analysis without an exported Insights CSV — agent cannot pull data directly</item>
        <item>Accounts with under 200 followers and no content history — build content foundation first</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="reels-as-primary-growth-engine">
      <rule>
        <statement>Prioritize Reels over static feed posts for reach goals. Reels are redistributed via Explore to non-followers; feed posts are not.</statement>
        <rationale>Explore distribution allows accounts to reach audiences 3-10x larger than their follower base. Static posts reach only existing followers.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>The hook of a Reel must work with the sound off: text overlay and visual action are mandatory in the first 1-2 seconds.</statement>
        <rationale>A large percentage of mobile users watch video without sound. A sound-dependent hook loses this audience in the first second.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use 3-5 highly relevant hashtags per post. Never use 30 hashtags — this pattern triggers shadowban risk.</statement>
        <rationale>Instagram's current algorithm gives no additional reach benefit beyond 5 hashtags. Large hashtag lists are a spam signal and can restrict distribution.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="weekly-posting-schedule">
      <list>
        <item>Monday: Educational tip — Reel</item>
        <item>Tuesday: Behind the scenes — Story + Reel</item>
        <item>Wednesday: Trend or entertainment — Reel</item>
        <item>Thursday: Value or tutorial — Reel + Carousel</item>
        <item>Friday: Engagement or fun — Reel + Story</item>
        <item>Saturday: User content or testimonial — Reel</item>
        <item>Sunday: Inspirational or story — Reel</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Post Stories daily. Use polls and question boxes daily rather than passive image stories — these are the highest-engagement Story formats.</statement>
        <rationale>Story polls and question boxes drive replies and DMs, which are the highest-value signals for relationship-building and conversion.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="dm-trigger-funnel">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use DM trigger campaigns ("DM me 'GUIDE' to get...") instead of link-in-bio for lead magnets. DM triggers convert 3-5x better than link-in-bio clicks.</statement>
        <rationale>A DM trigger starts a direct conversation with the lead. Link-in-bio sends traffic to a cold page with no relationship context.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Caption: "I built a 30-day content system that doubled my engagement. DM me 'SYSTEM' and I'll send it to you." This creates a warm DM conversation vs. a cold landing page visit.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using ManyChat or non-partner DM automation tools to send bulk automated replies.</description>
        <reason>Non-partner DM automation is against Instagram ToS and risks account suspension. Use only Meta-approved partner tools like ManyChat for keyword triggers.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="kpi-benchmarks">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Track Reel reach % (not just views), engagement rate, Story completion rate, and weekly follower growth rate as primary KPIs.</statement>
        <rationale>Raw view counts are misleading for small accounts. Reach % relative to follower count indicates whether Explore distribution is working.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Engagement rate: 1% = average, 3% = good, 6%+ = excellent</item>
        <item>Reel reach: 10% of followers = average, 30% = good, 100%+ = viral</item>
        <item>Story completion: 50% = average, 70% = good, 85%+ = excellent</item>
        <item>Follower growth: 1%/week = average, 5%/week = good, 10%+/week = excellent</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Only posting photos instead of Reels.</description>
        <reason>Photos reach only existing followers. Reels reach Explore audiences. Without Reels, organic growth stalls.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Inconsistent posting cadence — missing days or weeks.</description>
        <reason>Instagram's algorithm penalizes accounts with erratic posting patterns by reducing distribution. Batch-film content to maintain consistency.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Over-edited, heavily filtered content.</description>
        <reason>Raw, authentic content currently outperforms polished production on Instagram. Audience trust comes from authenticity, not production value.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No face on camera for personal brand accounts.</description>
        <reason>Accounts showing a real person consistently achieve higher engagement than faceless brand accounts in the same niche.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Not checking DMs twice daily.</description>
        <reason>DM conversations are the highest-conversion touchpoint on Instagram. Delayed responses lose leads that were ready to buy.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-limitations">
      <rule>
        <statement>Agent-generated Reel scripts must be reviewed for hook quality before filming. The first 1-3 seconds determine watch time; the agent cannot judge if a hook is compelling in delivery.</statement>
        <rationale>Script quality and on-camera delivery are separate skills. Agents produce structure; humans provide authenticity in delivery.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Instagram Graph API provides page-level insights only. Personal account insights require manual export from the Instagram app before agent analysis.</statement>
        <rationale>The API does not expose individual post performance for personal accounts. Agents cannot pull this data autonomously.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Use the agent for two tasks: (1) content batch production — given content pillars, ICP, and the weekly schedule template, produce 14 Reel script hooks + body points + CTAs, 7 Story prompt sequences, and 2-3 carousel outlines per week; (2) performance analysis — given an Instagram Insights CSV export, identify top-performing content types and suggest next week's pillar distribution adjustments. Human films, edits, and posts Reels; agent never touches the upload flow.</p>

      <p><term name="Recommended subagents">faion-sdd-executor-agent — execute weekly Instagram content production tasks from a spec; password-scrubber-agent — sanitize DM conversation exports before feeding into lead analysis</term></p>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-pattern">
      <p>Content generation prompt:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are an Instagram content strategist for <niche>. ICP: <icp>. Brand voice: <voice>.

Generate this week's Reel scripts:
- 2 educational tips (hook + 3 key points + CTA)
- 2 behind-the-scenes (narrative arc + authenticity note)
- 1 trend/entertainment (format suggestion + hook)
- 1 user testimonial (story structure)
- 1 inspirational (emotional hook + lesson)

Each script: hook line (max 5 words), body (3-5 bullet points), CTA (specific action), caption (150 chars max), 3 hashtags.
      ]]></code>

      <p>Analysis prompt:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Analyze this Instagram Insights export:
<csv_data>

Identify: (1) top 3 Reels by reach %, (2) common hook patterns in high performers, (3) best posting times by engagement, (4) Story completion drop-off points. Recommend content adjustments for next week.
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p><term name="CLI tools">instagrapi (Python) — Unofficial Instagram API: read insights, schedule posts (pip install instagrapi / https://instagrapi.readthedocs.io); later API — Scheduled posting for Reels, carousels, stories (https://developers.later.com); manychat API — DM automation flows (keyword triggers) (https://developers.manychat.com); ffmpeg — Batch video processing for Reel format compliance (apt install ffmpeg / https://ffmpeg.org); pillow — Auto-generate Story frames and carousel slide images (pip install pillow / https://pillow.readthedocs.io)</term></p>

      <p><term name="Services">Later (SaaS, agent-friendly REST API) — Best scheduling for Instagram Reels; visual planner; ManyChat (SaaS, agent-friendly API) — DM automation for keyword triggers; ToS-compliant approach; Meta Business Suite (SaaS, agent-friendly Graph API) — Official insights export; limited granularity; Canva (SaaS, agent-friendly Apps SDK) — Carousel slide and highlight cover generation; CapCut (SaaS, no API) — Reel editing; manual use; Hootsuite (SaaS, agent-friendly REST API) — Scheduling + analytics; more expensive than Later; Metricool (SaaS, agent-friendly REST API) — Cross-platform analytics including Instagram</term></p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>The hook of a Reel must work with the sound off — text overlay and visual action in the first 1-2 seconds are mandatory</item>
        <item>Reels get redistributed via Explore; feed posts do not — prioritize Reels over static posts for reach goals</item>
        <item>Story polls and question boxes are the highest-engagement Story formats; use them daily rather than passive image stories</item>
        <item>DM trigger campaigns ("DM me 'GUIDE'") convert 3-5x better than link-in-bio clicks for lead magnets — use them for every major value offer</item>
        <item>Post carousels as the second slide hook (a teaser image that implies more content) — carousel swipe rate is the key metric for feed reach</item>
        <item>Batch film content in 2-3 hour sessions weekly; editing and posting daily from scratch leads to inconsistency</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p><term name="Video production gap">Agent produces scripts and storyboards; the filming and editing step is entirely human — plan for this production time when generating volume</term></p>
      <p><term name="DM automation ToS risk">ManyChat-style automation is permitted under Instagram's official partner program, but non-partner tools (instagrapi DM sending) are against ToS and risk account suspension</term></p>
      <p><term name="Hashtag shadowban">Agent should never generate 30-hashtag lists; 3-5 highly relevant hashtags is the current safe range</term></p>
      <p><term name="Insights access">Instagram Graph API provides page-level insights only; personal account insights require manual export from the app</term></p>
      <p><term name="Algorithm drift">Reel distribution rules (audio usage, original audio vs trending audio) change frequently; agent recommendations reflect training data, not current algorithm state</term></p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/reel-script-batch.txt" purpose="Agent prompt: weekly Reel scripts (7 types, hook + body + CTA)"/>
      <template path="templates/carousel-slides.py" purpose="Generate 10-slide carousel text outline from topic + key points"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://about.instagram.com/blog/announcements/instagram-ranking-explained"/>
      <link href="https://creators.instagram.com/"/>
      <link href="https://later.com/blog/instagram-growth/"/>
      <link href="https://blog.hootsuite.com/how-to-get-more-instagram-followers/"/>
      <link href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/instagram-api"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
