<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Multi-Touch Attribution Modeling Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Multi-Touch Attribution Modeling MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="four-model-variants" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST cover first-touch + linear + position-based + time-decay. Single-model attribution is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Avinash Kaushik, Multi-channel funnels">Different channels favor different models; comparing four variants reveals channel mis-attribution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="warehouse-source-of-truth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Warehouse (BigQuery / Snowflake) MUST be the reconciled source of truth. Platform self-reports are inputs, not outputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="GA4 / BigQuery export documentation">Platform self-reports double-count and use different windows; only warehouse can dedup.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="variance-threshold" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Variance &gt; 15% between platform-reported / GA4 / warehouse MUST trigger investigation before budget decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cross-channel attribution audit Q4 2025">Above 15% indicates pixel misfire, dedup failure, or definition drift; acting on bad data destroys budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="dark-social-tracking" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Model MUST track 'direct/none' as a named channel and investigate sources (community / podcast / DM / referral).</statement>
      <rationale source="Chris Walker / B2B dark-social literature">30-50% of B2B pipeline is dark-social; ignoring it under-credits the channels that actually fed it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="monthly-reconciliation-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reconciliation MUST run monthly with named owner; quarterly is too slow, weekly is over-fit to noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational cadence — marketing analytics teams">Monthly catches drift before quarter-end budget meetings; weekly causes flip-flop reallocation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
