<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="AWS Well-Architected Framework Checklists (2025-2026) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for the WA checklist. Each rule pairs a binary check + an AWS-source rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="all-6-pillars-evaluated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The checklist MUST contain at least one item per pillar (OpEx, Security, Reliability, Performance, Cost, Sustainability). No pillar may be empty.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected Framework">Skipping a pillar means the workload has not been reviewed against it. The Sustainability pillar (added 2021) is the most-skipped — and the easiest to dismiss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="binary-items-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every item MUST be phrased as a binary pass/fail check. Items like 'review security posture' are forbidden; 'IAM root account MFA enabled' is allowed.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected Tool">Non-binary items defer the decision to the reviewer's gut — defeating the point of a checklist. Binary items make the review reproducible across reviewers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cli-verifiable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every item MUST name an AWS CLI / Config rule / Compute Optimizer call that verifies pass/fail. Items relying on human inspection are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Config / CLI docs">CLI-backed items can be wired into a nightly job for drift detection. Manual items decay between reviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="gap-severity-ranked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every failed item MUST carry a severity (HIGH / MED / LOW) based on impact + compliance scope. HIGH items block production launch.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected Tool">Without severity, remediation degenerates into 'fix everything' (impossible) or 'fix what I noticed' (random). Severity drives priority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="review-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An audit-clean workload MUST be re-reviewed at least quarterly. A new workload MUST have a clean checklist before its first production deployment.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected best-practice">Cloud environments drift; quarterly cadence catches drift before it becomes a CVE. Pre-prod gate prevents debt from entering production at all.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies If preconditions in AGENTS.md do not all hold, OR any Skip If trigger fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and pick a different one — applying the rules here on a mismatched input produces wrong output.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology guard">Methodology selection errors cascade. The cheapest place to abort is before any rule fires.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>