<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="generative-ui-design">
  <metadata>
    <tier>geek</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>AI generation (v0, Claude Artifacts, Galileo, Uizard) for rapid UI ideation: 3–5 variants, human critique, agent refinement loop. Zero-cost exploration forces early design decisions.</summary>
    <category>design-tools</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>generative-ai</tag>
      <tag>ui-design</tag>
      <tag>ideation</tag>
      <tag>variant-generation</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <languages>
      <language>none</language>
    </languages>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Generative UI Design</title>

    <summary>Methodology for using AI generation tools (v0 by Vercel, Claude Artifacts, Galileo, Uizard, Relume) to produce multiple UI variants rapidly in the ideation phase. The loop is: agent generates 3–5 variants → human selects and critiques → agent refines → human verifies accessibility → done. Generated output is a forcing function for critique, not a finished deliverable.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Blank-canvas paralysis and slow single-variant design cycles are the primary bottlenecks in early UI exploration. Generating 5–10 variants in parallel from a single brief reduces the cost of exploration to near-zero, surfaces the design space faster, and gives teams concrete artifacts to critique rather than abstract concepts to debate. Every variant must still be verified for accessibility and brand compliance before use.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Rapid ideation: generating 5–10 UI variants from a brief to explore design space</item>
        <item>Prototyping flows for investor demos or usability tests where visual polish is secondary</item>
        <item>Generating React/HTML component code from design descriptions (v0, Claude Artifacts)</item>
        <item>Reducing blank-canvas paralysis on new projects</item>
        <item>Creating low-fidelity wireframe sets across multiple screen sizes in parallel</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Brand-critical production interfaces — AI generation does not understand brand nuance reliably</item>
        <item>Accessibility-first projects — generative outputs routinely miss focus management, ARIA roles, contrast</item>
        <item>Design system contributions — generated components bypass token and variant governance</item>
        <item>When the design problem requires deep user research insight — generation amplifies assumptions</item>
        <item>Final developer handoff — generated code requires significant cleanup before production</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="tool-landscape">
      <p>Generative UI tools vary significantly in output quality, API availability, and suitability for agentic workflows.</p>
      <list>
        <item>v0 by Vercel — REST API for component generation; output is React/TSX; agent-callable</item>
        <item>Claude Artifacts — native in-context generation; interactive HTML/React; agent-callable</item>
        <item>Galileo AI — browser-only; no public API; image-based output (not editable component trees)</item>
        <item>Uizard — browser-based; no headless API; image-based output</item>
        <item>Relume — Figma plugin + browser; no API; optimized for marketing/SaaS site structure</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="generation-loop">
      <p>The core workflow is structured to maximize exploration and minimize wasted critique cycles.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Generate 3–5 variants per brief, not 1. Single-variant generation anchors the team too early and forecloses design space exploration.</statement>
        <rationale>The purpose of generative UI is to expand the option space cheaply. A single variant is no better than having a designer start from scratch — it still anchors the conversation to one direction.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Treat generated UI as a zero-cost rough draft. Critique aggressively; accept nothing without review.</statement>
        <rationale>Generated output that is accepted without critique carries forward AI defaults (generic aesthetics, missing accessibility, deprecated patterns) into production.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Correct generation loop">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1. Agent generates 3-5 variants (parallel calls, different style constraints)
2. Human selects variants, marks off-brand elements, flags a11y issues
3. Agent refines selected variant based on critique notes
4. Human runs axe-cli / accessibility audit on refined output
5. Human verifies against brand style guide
6. Approved → isolated branch; marked with AI-generated comment
        ]]></code>
        <note>This loop treats generation as the starting point for critique, not the endpoint.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Accepting the first generated variant without comparing to alternatives.</description>
        <reason>Single-variant acceptance forecloses the design space early, defeating the purpose of generative UI for exploration.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Merging generated output directly into production without manual review.</description>
        <reason>Generated code frequently contains API hallucinations, missing accessibility attributes, and composition violations that require manual cleanup.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="quality-rules">
      <p>Generated UI requires specific validation steps before any stakeholder presentation or production use.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run axe-cli or equivalent on all generated HTML before presenting to stakeholders.</statement>
        <rationale>Generated UIs that look accessible routinely have broken focus order, missing live regions, and contrast failures. Automated check is mandatory before any stakeholder presentation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pin design tokens explicitly in every generation prompt. Without them, AI defaults to generic Bootstrap-like aesthetics.</statement>
        <rationale>AI generation models have no brand knowledge; explicit token references (color names, type scale, spacing) are the only way to anchor output to the design system.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep generated components isolated from the production codebase until manually reviewed and refactored.</statement>
        <rationale>Generated code frequently uses deprecated APIs, missing responsive breakpoints, and incorrect composition patterns; direct merge without review introduces technical debt.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Mark all AI-generated components with a comment: "AI-generated — review before production".</statement>
        <rationale>Unmarked AI-generated code becomes invisible in the codebase; marking enables future audits and prevents accidental promotion to production.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Accessibility audit workflow">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
# Generate 3 variants
haiku_generate_variants(screen_brief="login screen", variants=["minimal", "warm", "dense"])

# Audit each variant
for variant in variants:
  axe_report = axe_cli.scan(variant.html)
  if axe_report.fails:
    print(f"Variant {variant} failed: {axe_report.fails}")
    agent_refine(variant, fixes=axe_report.fails)

# Final review
designer_approves(selected_variant)
        ]]></code>
        <note>Parallel generation + automated auditing + manual refinement captures the full loop.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Understanding what generative UI cannot do is as important as knowing what it can.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using Galileo or Uizard output as Figma-import-ready components.</description>
        <reason>Both produce image-based outputs, not editable component trees; importing into Figma requires manual rebuild from scratch.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using generative UI for design system contributions.</description>
        <reason>Generated components bypass token governance, variant structure, and composition rules; they require significant rework to meet design system standards.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Expecting AI-generated code to converge on novel interaction models.</description>
        <reason>Agents generating UI converge on modal patterns (cards, hero banners, nav bars) — novel interaction models are underrepresented in training data and rarely generated.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Assuming brand consistency will hold across multiple generation runs without anchoring.</description>
        <reason>Brand consistency degrades with each iteration; AI drifts from style guide without explicit anchoring via design tokens or reference images in prompts.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Claude subagents can orchestrate the full generation → critique → refinement loop programmatically.</p>

      <p>Subagents generate multiple UI variants from a single brief by running parallel generation calls with different style constraints (minimal, warm-approachable, information-dense). The agent produces structured React/HTML code or Figma-paste-ready specifications. Human curates: selects variants, marks off-brand elements, flags accessibility issues. A second agent pass refines the selected variant based on critique notes.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>haiku — high-volume variant generation (10+ options), design token application to boilerplate</item>
        <item>sonnet — complex multi-state component generation, critique synthesis, design brief interpretation</item>
      </list>

      <p>Agent gotchas when generating code:</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent generates code with library APIs that don't exist or are deprecated.</description>
        <reason>LLMs hallucinate library APIs, especially for newer React versions and niche component libraries; always test generated code in a sandbox before accepting.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating WCAG compliance prompts as sufficient for accessible output.</description>
        <reason>Generated code that targets WCAG compliance often has broken focus order and missing live regions; axe-cli audit is mandatory regardless of prompt instructions.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using "modern" or "clean" as style constraints without concrete references.</description>
        <reason>Abstract style terms mean different things every run; add specific style references (typography system, component library names, example URLs) for reproducible output.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Accepting agent-generated complex component trees without checking against design system composition rules.</description>
        <reason>Agents propose component nesting that violates design system composition rules silently; the output looks correct but breaks at the system level.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/batch-generate.py" purpose="Batch generate multiple UI variants via Claude API in parallel"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-ui-variants.txt" purpose="Prompt for generating 3 styled React component variants from a brief"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-ui-critique.txt" purpose="Prompt for auditing generated UI for WCAG, ARIA, and brand violations"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://v0.dev/docs"/>
      <link href="https://www.usegalileo.ai/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/generative-ui/"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/quickref/"/>
      <link href="https://uxtools.co/ai-design-survey/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
