<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Data-Driven Requirements Engineering Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the data-driven-requirements methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 1 (frame business question): Translate vague ask into measurable business question.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the frame business question gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 2 (capture baseline): Pull baseline metric snapshot with provenance.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the capture baseline gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 3 (set target): Define measurable target with direction + by_when.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the set target gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 4 (design instrumentation): Events, properties, dashboard ties; review with analytics-eng.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the design instrumentation gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 5 (post launch measure): Compare against target; trigger learn/iterate/kill decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the post launch measure gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for data-driven-requirements do not hold, do not apply this methodology; route to an alternative as the decision tree suggests.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Methodologies misapplied to wrong contexts create overhead without value; explicit skip preserves the agent's budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
