<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="sdd-document-templates">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd</domain>
    <summary>Copy-paste ready templates for Specification-Driven Development documents (constitution, spec, design, test-plan, implementation-plan, task, roadmap, memory). Optimized for LLM-assisted workflows with YAML frontmatter, structured tables, and clear cross-references.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>sdd</tag>
      <tag>templates</tag>
      <tag>documentation</tag>
      <tag>planning</tag>
      <tag>task-management</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-24</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>SDD Document Templates</title>

    <summary>Eight copy-paste templates for Specification-Driven Development: constitution (tech stack and constraints), spec (requirements and user stories), design (architecture and decisions), test-plan (verification per acceptance criterion), implementation-plan (task breakdown and order), task (single executable unit), roadmap (feature timeline and metrics), and memory (patterns and lessons). All templates use YAML frontmatter for machine-readable metadata and support LLM-assisted workflows.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Specification-Driven Development requires a consistent document structure across projects and teams. Without templates, each team invents its own format, forcing agents and humans to relearn document conventions per project. Templates reduce cognitive load and token overhead by establishing predictable structure.</p>
      <p>LLM-assisted development benefits from explicit YAML frontmatter, structured tables, and clear cross-references between documents. Templates encode these patterns upfront so agents can fill them mechanically and humans can validate content without deciphering structure.</p>
      <p>Document lifecycle (spec → design → test-plan → implementation-plan → task) creates traceability: bugs can be traced back to original requirements, refactoring can honor original intent, and validation confirms implementation matches specification. Templates enforce this chain by requiring forward references (task links to implementation-plan, which links to design, which links to spec).</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Starting a new project: generate constitution and roadmap before any code.</item>
        <item>Adding a feature: scaffold spec, design, test-plan, implementation-plan in one agent pass.</item>
        <item>When a human provides a rough feature description and wants a fully structured SDD folder immediately.</item>
        <item>When bootstrapping a project that will be executed by faion-sdd-executor-agent.</item>
        <item>Onboarding a new team to Specification-Driven Development; templates teach the format by example.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-file bug fixes or one-liner patches: no SDD overhead needed.</item>
        <item>Vibe-coding or rapid throwaway prototypes where specs will be discarded.</item>
        <item>When a feature already has complete SDD docs: check .aidocs/ first before re-generating.</item>
        <item>When constitution.md does not yet exist: create it first; templates depend on it for constraints.</item>
        <item>Projects where no one will read or maintain documentation: templates create false promise if abandoned.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="document-lifecycle">
      <p>The document lifecycle flows from project-level governance down to task-level execution:</p>

      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
constitution.md (once per project)
        |
        v
    roadmap.md (strategic timeline)
        |
        v
    spec.md  →  design.md  →  test-plan.md  →  implementation-plan.md  →  task.md (N)
        |           |               |                      |                   |
    "What to      "How to        "How to              "What tasks,         "Execute
     build"       build"         verify"              what order"          this now"
]]></code>

      <p>Constitution defines the tech stack and project-level constraints. Every spec, design, and task must reference it for consistency.</p>

      <p>For each feature: spec defines requirements (FR-X), design archives architecture decisions (AD-X), test-plan maps test cases to acceptance criteria, implementation-plan breaks work into tasks, and individual task files guide execution.</p>

      <p>Memory captures patterns and lessons after each phase, feeding back into future specifications and design decisions.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="template-selection-guide">
      <rule>
        <statement>Start every project with constitution.md. Define tech stack, coding standards, architectural constraints, and non-negotiable project principles before creating any feature spec.</statement>
        <rationale>Constitution is the reference for all downstream documents. Specs that violate constitution constraints must be rejected at review time. Without constitution, specs accumulate contradictory decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Create roadmap.md as the strategic overview: feature phases, success metrics, and timeline milestones. Link each roadmap phase to corresponding feature folders in .aidocs/.</statement>
        <rationale>Roadmap gives context to individual specs; specs give detail to roadmap. Bidirectional linking keeps strategic intent visible during tactical implementation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>For each feature: create spec.md first, then design.md (after spec review), test-plan.md, implementation-plan.md, then task.md files. Do not skip phases or generate them in parallel; each depends on the previous.</statement>
        <rationale>Phase dependencies are load-bearing. Design errors caught early are cheap. Design errors caught after implementation are expensive. Spec review gates design work; design review gates implementation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Create task.md files one per logical unit of work. Task MUST be completable within a 100k token context window (30k reading context + 50k implementation + 20k buffer). If task is larger, split it.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents execute tasks better in isolation. 100k-token tasks fit in context; larger tasks force token budgeting mid-execution, causing quality loss or truncation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Update memory.md after every task completion: record successful patterns, mistakes encountered, and key decisions made. Feed these observations into next feature specs.</statement>
        <rationale>Memory creates organizational learning. Without it, each feature repeats the same mistakes. With it, experience accumulates.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="llm-optimization-context-efficiency">
      <p>Templates are designed for LLM efficiency. Structure reduces token overhead; agents parse YAML frontmatter faster than prose headers; tables parse faster than prose lists.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every template uses YAML frontmatter for machine-readable metadata (version, status, dates, author). Agents read frontmatter before content to understand context.</statement>
        <rationale>YAML frontmatter is parse-once, low overhead. Agents can skip irrelevant docs by reading frontmatter only.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use structured tables (FR-X, AC, AD-X, test rows) instead of prose. Every specification MUST have a requirements table (FR-001 through FR-N); every design MUST have a decisions table (AD-001 through AD-N); every task MUST link back to implementation-plan rows.</statement>
        <rationale>Structured data is queryable and compressible. "FR-001: User can log in with email" compresses to ~10 tokens; the same requirement in prose uses 20+. Over a 5k-token document, structure saves ~1k tokens.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Cross-reference aggressively. Every task.md references implementation-plan row (TASK-NK-042 implements IP-row-3). Every implementation-plan row references design.md decisions (AD-007, AD-009). Every design decision references spec.md requirements (FR-X, AC-Y). Traceability links are not overhead; they are essential for validation and debugging.</statement>
        <rationale>Cross-references allow validation without re-reading parent docs. Agents can check "did we implement what the spec required?" by checking links, not by re-reading spec content.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Each document fits within 5k tokens (constitution and roadmap may be larger). Larger documents split into separate features or task folders. Long documents force context re-reading and token waste.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents reading 20k-token spec + 20k-token design + 5k implementation-plan spend 20k tokens on re-reading context before implementing. Shorter docs, more frequent reads reduce overhead.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="template-anatomy">
      <p>All templates use a consistent anatomy: YAML frontmatter, purpose statement, sections with rules and examples, cross-references, and related docs.</p>

      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
---
version: "1.0"
status: draft | review | approved
created: YYYY-MM-DD
updated: YYYY-MM-DD
author: Name
---

# [Document Title]

## Summary or Purpose
One paragraph explaining what this document is for.

## [Main Sections]
Content organized by role (spec: Requirements; design: Decisions; etc.)

## Cross-References
- Links to parent/sibling docs
- Links to related methodologies
- Links to external resources
]]></code>

      <rule>
        <statement>Frontmatter fields: version (semver), status (draft/review/approved), created, updated, author. Update "updated" and "status" every time the document changes.</statement>
        <rationale>Frontmatter allows agents to skip outdated drafts. Status gates prevent merging unapproved specs or designs.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every document links to its parent and siblings. Task.md links to implementation-plan.md (its parent), which links to design.md (its parent), which links to spec.md (its parent), which links to constitution.md and roadmap.md.</statement>
        <rationale>Linked documents enable traceability. An agent executing a task can walk the chain back to original requirements if needed.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>For humans: Review specs and designs for clarity and completeness before proceeding. Specs need human validation that requirements are correct; designs need human validation that architecture choices are sound.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents excel at filling forms and explaining decisions. Humans excel at judging correctness and catching logical errors.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>For LLMs: Be explicit. State assumptions, don't leave things implied. Use examples. Concrete examples beat abstract descriptions. Define vocabulary. Clarify domain-specific terms. Specify constraints. What NOT to do is as important as what to do.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents work better with explicit constraints. "Build a user login system" is vague; "build a stateless JWT login system that does NOT use sessions, stores tokens in localStorage, and handles refresh tokens with 15-minute expiry" is precise.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>For teams: All docs in git, alongside code. One roadmap, one backlog, no duplicates. Each feature folder is self-contained (spec + design + tests + tasks all in one place).</statement>
        <rationale>Git versioning allows rolling back specs if decisions prove wrong. Single source of truth prevents bifurcated documentation. Self-contained features enable parallel work across teams.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Delete empty placeholder sections rather than leaving them as TBD. LLMs treat TBD as real content and generate against it. Omit sections that don't apply to your project.</statement>
        <rationale>Concise documents are easier to read and cheaper to inject into prompts. Boilerplate hides real content.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Number FR-X, AC, AD-X, and task IDs sequentially and never reuse numbers within a project. Numbers act as immutable IDs: if FR-007 is deleted, the next requirement is FR-008, not a new FR-007.</statement>
        <rationale>Immutable IDs allow reliable cross-referencing. If IDs are reused, "see FR-007" becomes ambiguous.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="failure-modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Generating all documents in one pass without waiting for review gates.</description>
        <reason>Design errors compound if not caught early. Testing gaps don't surface until implementation. Reviews gate quality; skipping them trades short-term speed for long-term cost.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Task.md files generated without reading design.md; task scopes are mis-sized or misaligned.</description>
        <reason>Task generation requires design context. Agents without design create tasks that violate architecture or miss dependencies.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Feature folder naming collisions (feature-024-starter-kits) causing silent overwrites.</description>
        <reason>Agents don't detect existing folders by default. Always check .aidocs/ before creating new feature folders.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents skip the traceability check: tasks don't reference implementation-plan rows, rows don't reference design decisions.</description>
        <reason>Without traceability, executor agents lose context. Always verify that each task.md references the implementation-plan row and design AD.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Token budget estimates in implementation-plan become stale after context is loaded.</description>
        <reason>Reading 20k-token codebase evaporates budget fast. Add 20k buffer for agents reading large existing code.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents writing multiple files in one turn silently truncate later files when approaching context limits.</description>
        <reason>Generate documents in separate turns or verify file sizes before merging. Monitor agent output for truncation patterns.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="template-customization">
      <rule>
        <statement>Remove sections that don't apply to your project. Regulatory? Add it. Multi-tenant? Add it. Legacy integration? Add it. Generic boilerplate hides signal.</statement>
        <rationale>Every project is different. Templates are starting points, not straitjackets.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Add project-specific frontmatter fields if needed (e.g., "epic" linking to roadmap, "priority" for task ordering, "estimate" for complexity). Keep it minimal.</statement>
        <rationale>Custom frontmatter is cheap if kept minimal. It becomes a liability if it grows to 10+ fields — agents start omitting optional fields, and search becomes hard.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Store templates in version control and never edit the skeleton in-place. Copy the skeleton, fill it, then commit both. This allows rolling back template changes if they break downstream documents.</statement>
        <rationale>Templates are shared artifacts. Editing in-place breaks existing documents. Git history on templates prevents surprise breaks.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/constitution.md" purpose="Project tech stack, constraints, and principles. Read by every downstream document."/>
      <template path="templates/spec.md" purpose="Functional requirements (FR-X), acceptance criteria per requirement. Defines WHAT to build."/>
      <template path="templates/design.md" purpose="Architecture decisions (AD-X), data models, API contracts, trade-offs. Defines HOW to build."/>
      <template path="templates/test-plan.md" purpose="Test cases per acceptance criterion. Defines HOW to verify."/>
      <template path="templates/implementation-plan.md" purpose="Task breakdown, dependency order, complexity levels. Task routing."/>
      <template path="templates/task.md" purpose="Single executable unit. Inputs, outputs, acceptance criteria, constraints."/>
      <template path="templates/roadmap.md" purpose="Feature timeline, success metrics, release milestones. Strategic context."/>
      <template path="templates/memory.md" purpose="Patterns, mistakes, decisions. Organizational learning captured per phase."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.industrialempathy.com/posts/design-docs-at-google/"/>
      <link href="https://adr.github.io/"/>
      <link href="https://addyosmani.com/blog/ai-coding-workflow/"/>
      <ref slug="writing-specifications"/>
      <ref slug="design-doc-structure"/>
      <ref slug="writing-implementation-plans"/>
      <ref slug="task-creation-principles"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
