<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ops-financial-planning">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>Forward-looking financial methodology for solopreneurs: project cash flow, calculate runway, allocate profits via reinvestment framework, and run quarterly scenario reviews.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>financial-planning</tag>
      <tag>cash-flow</tag>
      <tag>runway</tag>
      <tag>reinvestment</tag>
      <tag>solopreneur</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>ops</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Financial Planning</title>

    <summary>Forward-looking financial methodology for solopreneurs: project cash flow (3-month and 12-month), calculate runway (cash / monthly burn), allocate profits using the reinvestment framework (reserve 20% first, then split reinvestment vs. owner pay by profit tier), and run quarterly scenario reviews with a base case and 20%-revenue-drop stress case.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Solopreneurs conflate owner draw with operating profit, causing invisible cash drain. Building the 12-month forecast bottom-up from known customer count and ARPU — not top-down from desired revenue — produces a grounded plan. The reinvestment framework (50/30/20 at under $5K profit, shifting to 30/50/20 above $15K) prevents both under-paying the owner and over-investing before the business is stable. A minimum 3-month runway protects against a single bad month becoming a crisis.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solopreneur has initial revenue and needs sustainable growth planning</item>
        <item>Product reaches breakeven; deciding how to allocate the first profits</item>
        <item>Runway drops below 6 months; need scenario modeling to prioritize cuts</item>
        <item>Quarterly review is due and projections need updating from real data</item>
        <item>Planning a pricing change or major spend decision (ads, contractor)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-revenue stage with no real data — use financial-basics methodology instead</item>
        <item>GAAP accounting or investor-grade reporting — requires a CPA, not an agent</item>
        <item>Complex equity or cap-table planning — use Carta or legal counsel</item>
        <item>Multi-entity corporate structures — agent assumptions do not hold</item>
        <item>Any automated payment or transfer decision — human approval required before execution</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="cash-flow-and-runway">
      <rule>
        <statement>Build the 12-month forecast bottom-up from known customer count and ARPU — not top-down from desired revenue.</statement>
        <rationale>Top-down forecasts start from a wish number and work backward. Bottom-up forecasts start from real customer data and produce grounded projections that identify actual growth gaps.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always inject real numbers as context before asking the agent to build projections. Agents will hallucinate specific financial figures if not given actual data.</statement>
        <rationale>Financial hallucinations in projections are silent failures — the output looks plausible but is based on fabricated inputs. Real data must be provided explicitly.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Agent prompt: "MRR = $8,500, monthly expenses = $4,200, cash balance = $22,000. Build a 3-month cash flow table. Flag if runway drops below 3 months." This gives the agent real numbers to work with.</note>
      </example>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Runway (months) = Cash on hand / Monthly burn rate. Minimum safe runway by stage: pre-revenue = 12+ months, early revenue = 6+ months, growing = 3+ months, profitable = 3+ months (emergency fund).</statement>
        <rationale>Runway is the primary financial safety metric. Below 3 months, a single bad month becomes an existential threat. The emergency fund (3x monthly expenses, separate account) is the profitable-stage equivalent.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run two scenarios each quarter: base case (flat growth) and stress case (20% revenue drop). Stress case sets minimum acceptable runway and spend floor.</statement>
        <rationale>A base-case-only plan has no resilience mechanism. The stress case forces identification of which expenses are cuttable and which are fixed, before the crisis occurs.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track CAC and LTV monthly alongside P&amp;L. A healthy margin with deteriorating LTV:CAC ratio signals future cash flow risk even when current numbers look good.</statement>
        <rationale>LTV:CAC deterioration predicts future revenue decline before it appears in the P&amp;L. Catching it early allows course correction.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="reinvestment-framework">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Lock a minimum 20% reserve before any discretionary spend. Adjust only after the emergency fund is fully funded (3x monthly expenses).</statement>
        <rationale>The reserve percentage is the only number that should never flex. It protects against cashflow surprises before addressing growth or owner compensation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Breakeven: 0% reinvest / 0% owner pay / 100% reserve</item>
        <item>Under $5K profit: 50% reinvest / 30% owner pay / 20% reserve</item>
        <item>$5-15K profit: 40% reinvest / 40% owner pay / 20% reserve</item>
        <item>Over $15K profit: 30% reinvest / 50% owner pay / 20% reserve</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Invest in this order: (1) retention, (2) conversion, (3) acquisition, (4) operations, (5) expansion. Never skip to acquisition before fixing retention.</statement>
        <rationale>Acquiring customers into a leaky bucket (high churn) burns cash without building an asset. Retention improvements compound; acquisition spend is consumed.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>1. Retention — product improvements, customer success</item>
        <item>2. Conversion — landing page optimization, onboarding</item>
        <item>3. Acquisition — ads, content marketing</item>
        <item>4. Operations — tools, automation</item>
        <item>5. Expansion — new features, products</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Conflating owner draw with operating profit.</description>
        <reason>Mixing them obscures true business health. Owner pay is a cost of the business. If the business cannot afford to pay the owner a market wage, it is not yet profitable.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Building a 12-month forecast from desired revenue rather than from known customer count and ARPU.</description>
        <reason>Top-down forecasts hide the actual growth gap. Bottom-up forecasts reveal exactly how many customers at what price are needed to hit the target.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Applying the reinvestment framework to an exceptional month with one-time revenue.</description>
        <reason>One-time payments skew the allocation. Non-recurring revenue must be flagged separately before applying tier thresholds; only recurring revenue determines the tier.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-guardrails">
      <rule>
        <statement>Agent must not trigger any automated payment, transfer, or pricing change. Human approval is required before any financial action based on agent output.</statement>
        <rationale>Financial decisions based on agent projections without human review can execute on hallucinated or misinterpreted data. The agent produces recommendations; humans execute.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>An agent is most useful here for building and refreshing structured projection tables from raw inputs (MRR, expense list, churn rate) and formatting a monthly review narrative. The agent should be given the current P&amp;L snapshot as context, then asked to produce the 3-month or 12-month cash flow table, flag runway risk, and output the reinvestment allocation using the framework tiers. Human review is required before any actual spend or distribution decision.</p>
      <p>Projections rely on assumed growth rates; agents cannot know market conditions. Variable-revenue businesses (courses, seasonal) need wider safety margins than the templates show. Agents cannot pull live bank/payment data unless given explicit tool access. Tax implications vary by jurisdiction — agent output is pre-tax unless context is provided.</p>
      <p>Agents will hallucinate specific financial figures if not given actual data — always inject real numbers as context, not ask the agent to estimate them. Currency and locale: specify currency symbol and decimal convention explicitly; agents default to USD and may misparse European-format numbers. Multi-currency businesses require explicit FX rate injection; agents should not look up live rates unless given a real-time tool. Agents should not store financial data between sessions without an explicit memory/persistence mechanism — each session needs fresh context. Human-in-loop checkpoint required before any automated payment, transfer, or pricing change triggered by agent output. Agents may apply the reinvestment framework mechanically without recognizing that exceptional months (e.g., one-time payments) skew the numbers — instruct agent to flag non-recurring revenue separately.</p>
      <prompt purpose="cash-flow-projection"><![CDATA[You are a financial planning assistant for a solopreneur SaaS.
Current state: MRR=$X, monthly expenses=$Y, cash=$Z.
Build a 3-month cash flow table and calculate runway.
Flag if runway drops below 3 months at any point.
Output: markdown table + one-paragraph risk summary.]]></prompt>
      <prompt purpose="reinvestment-allocation"><![CDATA[Given profit=$X this month, apply the reinvestment framework:
profit < $5K → 50% reinvest / 30% owner / 20% reserve.
Output allocation in dollars and a brief rationale.]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools: stripe-cli (Pull MRR and charge data locally — https://stripe.com/docs/stripe-cli); ledger / hledger (Plain-text accounting, cash flow queries — https://hledger.org); visidata (Inspect CSV exports from QuickBooks/Wave — https://www.visidata.org); python -m csv + pandas (Scripted monthly roll-up from export files — stdlib + pip).</p>
      <p>Services: Stripe (SaaS, Yes REST API — Revenue, MRR, churn data via API); Baremetrics (SaaS, Yes REST API — Pre-computed SaaS metrics: MRR, LTV, CAC); Wave (SaaS, Partial no public API — Export CSV; agent parses offline); QuickBooks Online (SaaS, Yes REST API OAuth2 — Full P&amp;L; requires OAuth flow, not trivial); ProfitWell (SaaS, Yes REST API — Subscription analytics, pricing intelligence); Mosaic (SaaS, Partial — FP&amp;A platform; API available on paid plans).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Always separate owner draw from operating profit before calculating reinvestment — mixing them obscures true business health</item>
        <item>Build the 12-month forecast bottom-up from known customer count and ARPU, not top-down from desired revenue</item>
        <item>Lock a minimum reserve percentage (20%) before any discretionary spend; adjust only after emergency fund is fully funded</item>
        <item>Track CAC and LTV monthly alongside P&amp;L — a healthy margin with deteriorating LTV:CAC signals future cash flow risk</item>
        <item>Run two scenarios each quarter: base case (flat growth) and stress case (20% revenue drop) — stress case sets minimum acceptable runway</item>
        <item>Annual budget should be set in Q4 for Q1 start; mid-year budget revisions need a written rationale to prevent drift</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/monthly-review.md" purpose="Monthly P&amp;L review: revenue, expenses, profitability, cash position, next focus"/>
      <template path="templates/annual-budget.md" purpose="Annual revenue forecast + expense budget by category and quarter"/>
      <template path="templates/stripe-runway.py" purpose="Pull MRR from Stripe API and calculate runway with warning threshold"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.saastr.com/financial-planning/"/>
      <link href="https://www.profitwell.com/recur/all/financial-metrics"/>
      <link href="https://baremetrics.com/resources"/>
      <link href="https://www.mosaic.tech/resources"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
