<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="reporting-basics Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for reporting-basics. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every widget must answer "which decision does this enable?" Strip widgets without an answer.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Widgets without a decision driver become status theater — pretty, ignored, never used for decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep top-level dashboards to ≤7 metrics; deeper detail lives one click down.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">More than 7 metrics overload cognitive bandwidth and dilute attention from the critical few.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tie green/yellow/red thresholds to the team's commitment, not industry averages.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generic thresholds produce misleading signals. A threshold is actionable only if the team can influence it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always show trend arrows next to absolute numbers; absolute alone is meaningless.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">50 open issues is either excellent (trending down from 100) or a disaster (trending up from 25). Context matters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mobile-test executive dashboards — they get read in elevators and Ubers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Executive dashboards will be viewed on smartphones; an untestable responsive design makes them useless at decision time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Version dashboard configs in git; treat schema changes like code reviews.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without version history, dashboards drift silently from reality. Git history provides the audit trail and rollback path.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Know your audience — tailor detail level and refresh cadence.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Executives need summary + trend; teams need real-time + blockers. One dashboard for all confuses everyone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lead with insights, not data. Dashboard title should be "On Track for Q2 Release" not "Velocity = 42".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Insights drive decisions; raw data requires interpretation and delays action.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include recommended actions in dashboard context, not just metrics.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Red status without a next step frustrates stakeholders. Always pair status with recommended action.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Regular cadence — build trust through consistency. Report at the same time, on the same channel, every period.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Inconsistent reporting trains stakeholders to ignore it. Consistency builds trust and habit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Review dashboard effectiveness quarterly: Are they read? Do they drive decisions? Retire stale dashboards.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dashboards degrade over time as business questions change. Quarterly audits prevent rot.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Avoid vanity metrics (velocity without context, MTTR without incident count). All metrics must drive a decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Vanity metrics optimize teams for the metric, not the outcome, and destroy the signal-to-noise ratio.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Real-time refresh is rarely needed and quietly burns API quota. Refresh team dashboards hourly, management daily, executive weekly.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Constant refresh adds no value past a certain cadence and multiplies data-source load.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
