<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="reporting-basics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for reporting-basics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs love to add charts. Constrain by max-widget count per audience.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>More widgets = more cognitive load; agents default to comprehensive over focused. Set a hard limit in the prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents will fabricate KPI formulas — require explicit data-source field names.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs invent plausible-sounding formulas without verifying against actual schema. Always pass the schema as input and validate the output.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Forecasting from velocity needs ≥6 sprints of data; agents will project from 1–2 if not constrained.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Insufficient data produces unreliable forecasts. Explicitly require minimum data window in the prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Avoid agents auto-filing Jira/Linear changes from dashboard rules; one bad rule cascades broadly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Programmatic actions from dashboard insights create feedback loops and can cause unintended bulk changes. Always route through human approval.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Ensure the agent labels each metric as leading or lagging; it conflates them silently.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Leading (velocity, WIP) vs lagging (escaped defects, rework) metrics serve different purposes. Agents often mix them without distinction, producing misleading dashboards.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Reports become "status theater": pretty, ignored, never drive decisions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Dashboards without clear decision points and audience alignment become ornamental. They must answer questions that stakeholders are actually asking.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Vanity metrics (velocity, MTTR-without-context) lead teams to optimize for the metric, not the outcome.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>When teams are measured on a metric, they optimize for it. Velocity without outcome context incentivizes inflated estimates; MTTR without incident severity incentivizes fast-but-incomplete fixes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Dashboards drift from reality once their data sources change schema.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Schema changes in issue trackers break dashboard queries silently. Version dashboard configs and re-validate after every schema change.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Executive dashboards over-aggregate; root-cause investigation still needs ticket-level access.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Aggregation loses signal. An executive dashboard that says "velocity is down" is useless without a path to investigate which issue category or assignee caused the drop.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Real-time refresh is rarely needed and quietly burns API quota.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The cost of constant polling is high; the value past a 1-hour cadence is low. Set refresh appropriately and monitor API usage.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
