<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-loop-types" title="Five Growth Loop Types">
  <summary>Five loop types with mechanisms, examples, and key metrics: viral, content, paid, network effect, supply-side.</summary>

  <section title="Loops vs Funnels">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design at least one growth loop before scaling acquisition spend; linear funnels require proportional spend increases to maintain growth, while loops compound output with each cycle.</statement>
      <rationale>A funnel ends when a user converts. A loop reinvests the output (referral, content, revenue) as new input for the next cycle. The efficiency difference compounds over 12+ months into an order-of-magnitude CAC advantage.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Viral Loop">
    <p>Mechanism: users invite other users directly. Flow: user signs up → uses product → invites friends → friends sign up → repeat. Key metric: viral coefficient (K-factor). Examples: Dropbox "get 500MB for each friend," WhatsApp (works better with contacts), Calendly (scheduling link is sent to others). K-factor above 1.0 = viral growth; below 1.0 = requires supplemental acquisition.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Loop">
    <p>Mechanism: users create content that attracts new users via search or sharing. Flow: user creates content → content indexed and shared → new user discovers → signs up → creates content → repeat. Key metrics: content created per user, SEO traffic from user-generated content. Examples: Pinterest (boards rank in Google), Quora (Q&amp;A ranks in search), YouTube (videos attract viewers who become creators).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Paid Loop">
    <p>Mechanism: revenue funds acquisition that generates more revenue. Flow: user pays → revenue → reinvest in ads → new user acquired → pays → repeat. Key metric: LTV:CAC ratio (must exceed 3:1 for sustainability). Examples: e-commerce (each sale funds more ads), SaaS (subscription revenue funds growth marketing). Requires positive unit economics before the loop is self-sustaining.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Network Effect Loop">
    <p>Mechanism: product becomes more valuable as more users join, reducing churn and attracting new users. Flow: user joins → product value increases → attracts more users → repeat. Key metrics: network density, engagement per user. Examples: LinkedIn, Uber (more drivers = shorter wait = more riders), Airbnb (more hosts = more options = more travelers).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Supply-Side Loop">
    <p>Mechanism: suppliers or creators attract demand, which attracts more suppliers. Flow: creator joins → creates supply → attracts consumers → revenue → more creators join → repeat. Key metrics: creator acquisition, creator retention. Examples: Substack (writers bring audience), Shopify (stores bring customers), App Store (developers attract users).</p>
  </section>
</text>
