<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-loop-design-and-measurement" title="Loop Design, Efficiency Calculation, and Loop Stack">
  <summary>Loop efficiency formula, how to find and fix the bottleneck, implementation phases, and the loop stack pattern.</summary>

  <section title="Loop Efficiency Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Calculate loop efficiency as the product of all step-conversion rates; an efficiency below 1.0 decays (requires external input), at 1.0 maintains, and above 1.0 compounds.</statement>
      <rationale>The efficiency number makes optimization priorities explicit. Without it, teams focus on the most visible step rather than the lowest-conversion step, which is the actual bottleneck.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Formula: loop efficiency = step-1-to-2 conversion × step-2-to-3 conversion × step-3-to-1 conversion. Example: 40% × 85% × 15% × 25% = 1.3% — this loop decays and needs supplemental acquisition to maintain growth. Users after 12 months = initial users × (efficiency ^ (365 / cycle time in days)).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Finding and Fixing the Bottleneck">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always identify and fix the step with the lowest conversion rate before optimizing any other step; the bottleneck determines the loop's ceiling efficiency.</statement>
      <rationale>Improving a non-bottleneck step produces negligible loop efficiency gains. If step 3-to-1 conversion is 3% and other steps are 60%+, doubling step 1-to-2 from 60% to 80% adds almost nothing; doubling step 3-to-1 from 3% to 6% doubles overall efficiency.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Implementation Phases">
    <p>Phase 1 — Identify (Week 1): list all ways users currently bring in other users, map natural sharing moments in the product, find user-created content, calculate current K-factor. Phase 2 — Design (Week 2): choose primary loop type, map all steps, measure conversion per step, identify bottleneck, design experiments. Phase 3 — Instrument (Week 3): set up per-step tracking, create dashboard, set baseline and targets. Phase 4 — Optimize (ongoing): run bottleneck experiments, track cycle time, track compounding effect.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Loop Stack Pattern">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build one primary loop until it produces measurable compounding before adding a secondary loop; operating two immature loops simultaneously dilutes focus and produces results from neither.</statement>
      <rationale>Each loop requires instrumentation, optimization experiments, and organizational attention. Slack's three-loop stack (viral, content, enterprise sales) was built sequentially over years, not launched simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Healthy loop stack example — Slack: Primary: viral (teams invite team members). Secondary: content (integrations attract search traffic). Third: enterprise paid (revenue funds outbound sales).</p>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/growth-loop-design.md">Loop design canvas template</reference>
</text>
