<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="product-launch Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for product-launch. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Launches MUST follow a T-8-to-T+2 timeline with a locked launch date 2 weeks out, treated as immovable. The timeline MUST include: positioning and messaging definition (T-8 to T-6), asset creation (T-6 to T-2), audience pre-build and partner coordination (T-6 to T-1), launch-day checklist with sequence steps (T-0), and post-launch monitoring (T+1 to T+7).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sliding the launch date erodes team trust and breaks partner commitments. A fixed timeline forces discipline in prioritization and prevents last-minute feature creep.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Launch dates MUST be Tuesday or Wednesday, mid-month, and MUST avoid US holidays and major industry events (re:Invent, Google I/O, WWDC weeks).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tuesday/Wednesday captures the full weekday attention cycle without weekend bleed-through. Mid-month avoids the monthly-billing noise. Industry event weeks fragment media attention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each launch MUST include a written asset checklist with rows for: landing page (with sign-up CTA), announcement email (with testimonials or social proof), product demo or screenshot walkthrough, Twitter/X thread (5-8 tweets), LinkedIn post, Product Hunt tagline and description (if applicable), press release or media kit, internal launch guide for the team, and API/technical documentation if applicable. Each row MUST name an owner and a "definition of done" (e.g., "landing page: reviewed by 2 external users, zero 404s, &lt;3 second load time").</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ownership eliminates blame-shifting. Explicit done criteria prevent scope creep and typo oversights. Missing a single asset (landing page screenshot, email subject line) tanks momentum.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Launches MUST include a channel-per-timing matrix with rows for: Product Hunt (T-0 12:01 AM PT), Twitter/X (T-0 morning, then Q1/Q2/Q3/Q4), LinkedIn (T-0 mid-day), email list (T-0 or T+1), press contacts (T-7 warm-up, T-0 embargo lift), and partner amplification (T+1 to T+3). Each row MUST specify: asset, timing, format (thread, single post, segment), CTA variant, and monitoring signal (mentions, retweets, signup spike).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Channel timing maximizes awareness. Product Hunt at T-0 00:01 captures early momentum; Twitter morning drives daylong conversation; LinkedIn reaches professionals mid-day; email converts warm leads. Staggered partner posts (T+1 to T+3) sustain long-tail traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Twitter/X MUST receive at least one post per day from T-0 to T+3 (the "3-day tail"). Posting only once at T-0 leaves the launch to die mid-afternoon.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Twitter's feed algorithm decays posts rapidly. Sustained posting (morning, mid-day, evening) keeps the launch visible. Q1/Q2/Q3/Q4 day posts remind followers and catch different timezones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each launch MUST define 3-5 success metrics before launch day, with targets set and realistic anchors derived from comparable launches. Metrics MUST include: awareness (impressions, reach, mentions), acquisition (signups, free-trial conversions), engagement (DAU, feature adoption at T+7), and long-term retention (retention at T+30). Targets MUST NOT be aspirational (100K signups for a solo founder) — they MUST be grounded in comparable product launches in the same category.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Pre-set targets prevent post-hoc celebration of mediocre numbers. Historical anchors (e.g., "similar SaaS products see 50-200 signups in week 1") ground expectations. Aspirational targets train teams to ignore reality and repeat failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every launch MUST include a pre-written rollback narrative (150-250 words) covering: what happened, why it happened, what the team is doing now, and when the launch resumes. The narrative MUST NOT appear on social or the website — it is a contingency held by the launch DRI. If a critical issue arises (data breach, massive bug, supply-chain failure), the DRI publishes it within 4 hours of identifying the issue, then takes the launch offline.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A prepared statement prevents panic tweets and preserves customer trust. Without it, teams scramble to craft a response mid-crisis and often say something wrong. Having it written in advance (when calm) means the response is thoughtful and buys time for the real fix.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The launch-day checklist MUST include: pre-launch checks (T-30 min: login to all systems, test asset links, verify analytics dashboards), go-live steps (T-0: deploy backend feature flag, publish landing page, submit to Product Hunt, email list blast), announcement sequence (T+0-6 hours: stagger social posts every 2 hours), monitoring (T+0-24 hours: Slack webhook posting signup and error metrics every 15 min), and EOD debrief (T+1: first pass on what worked, what didn't). One person is the launch DRI with kill-switch authority.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sequencing prevents accidentally publishing before the landing page is live or forgetting to turn on analytics. A single DRI prevents conflicting decisions during the chaos. Staggered posts keep momentum. Monitoring alerts the team to problems (error spike, checkout bug) in real time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>NO automatic social posts on launch day. All Twitter, LinkedIn, and email sends MUST pass through a human approval gate within 60 minutes of the scheduled time. Auto-publishing to social on launch day is a reputational landmine — typos, broken links, and offensive language go live before anyone catches them.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Humans catch visual issues (broken images, wrong screenshot), typos, and tone problems that LLMs miss. The 60-minute window is tight enough to maintain momentum but gives a human time to review and approve.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Within 48 hours of launch, the team MUST capture 5-10 customer testimonials (one-liner + name + company/role). Goodwill is highest when the product is fresh and novel; after 2 weeks, enthusiasm fades. These quotes go into future marketing (landing page, case studies, social proof).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Testimonials collected immediately are authentic and effusive. Testimonials requested weeks later are polished but generic and hard to get. Ask within 48 hours: "What was your biggest aha moment with [product]?"</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A 30-minute postmortem MUST run within 7 days of launch. Attendance: launch DRI, marketing, product, and engineering leads. Agenda: (1) What was the target vs. what we hit? (2) What surprised us (good or bad)? (3) What's one thing we'd do differently? Document and share with the team. If you wait more than a week, lessons evaporate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Lessons fade quickly. A structured postmortem within a week captures learnings while memory is fresh. Waiting a month means the insights are lost and the team repeats the same mistakes on the next launch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>LLM copy agents MUST NOT be allowed to use: revolutionary, game-changing, leverage, paradigm, seamless, robust, cutting-edge, disruptive, innovative. These words are red flags for inflation. Agents drafting marketing copy MUST operate under a banned-words list and a requirement for 2 human review rounds minimum.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs default to hype. A banned-words list and multi-round human review forces specificity. Actual benefits (speed, cost savings, simplicity) sell better than vague superlatives.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DO NOT let agents draft the post-launch retrospective from metrics alone. Force them to interview 3 customers first and incorporate qualitative feedback. Metrics-only retrospectives turn self-congratulatory and miss real user pain points.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Numbers can be spun. Hearing directly from users ("the onboarding was confusing" or "the pricing modal scared me away") reveals the actual story behind the metrics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The launch tech stack MUST include: one analytics tool (Plausible, Fathom, or Umami) for privacy-respecting launch-day metrics, one email service (Resend, Beehiiv, or ConvertKit) for announcement blasts, one link shortener or utm builder for tracking (Short.io, Bitly), and one monitoring tool (Sentry or Highlight.io) to catch errors on launch day.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Analytics is non-negotiable (you must watch traffic). Email is non-negotiable (you must contact the list). UTM tracking is non-negotiable (you must attribute signups to channels). Error monitoring is non-negotiable (you must catch bugs before customers report them). All of these have APIs, so agents can monitor and report in real time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
