<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-planning" title="Product Launch Planning: Timeline, Asset Checklist, and Positioning Rules">
  <summary>The T-8-to-T+2 launch planning timeline, required assets, channel matrix rules, and positioning principles.</summary>

  <section title="Launch Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose launch type before planning: soft launch (limited audience, low effort), beta launch (early adopters, medium effort), full launch (public, high effort), major release (existing users, medium effort). Each type drives a different asset set and timeline scope.</statement>
      <rationale>A full-launch playbook applied to a beta wastes preparation time. Matching type to scope prevents over-engineering small launches and under-preparing large ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="T-8 to T+2 Timeline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the launch date 2 weeks out and treat it as immovable. Sliding a launch once erodes team trust and breaks partner commitments.</statement>
      <rationale>Date slippage cascades to partner schedules, press embargoes, and pre-built social content. A locked date forces scope cuts instead of deadline cuts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the T-minus framework: T-8 weeks (strategy finalized), T-6 (asset creation begins), T-4 (audience building), T-2 (all assets ready), T-1 (final checks), T-Day (execute), T+1 (monitor), T+2 (retrospective).</statement>
      <rationale>Without a structured timeline, asset creation and coordination compress into the last 2 weeks, producing rushed copy, missed channels, and support unpreparedness.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Asset Checklist">
    <rule>
      <statement>Minimum viable launch requires: landing page, demo or screenshots, announcement email, social posts (per channel), basic documentation. No launch without all five. Assign an owner and due date to each asset at T-8.</statement>
      <rationale>The most common launch failure mode is assets discovered incomplete at T-0. Owner and due date at T-8 gives 7 weeks of remediation runway.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Channel Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tailor message to each channel — same copy across all channels underperforms. Schedule announcements in sequence: email list first (warm audience), then social, then directories/press.</statement>
      <rationale>Warm audiences convert first and create social proof for cold audiences. Reversing the sequence wastes the warm-audience advantage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Launch on Tuesday or Wednesday, mid-month. Avoid major industry events (Google I/O, AWS re:Invent, WWDC weeks) and US public holidays.</statement>
      <rationale>Thursday-Friday launches compete with end-of-week context-switching. Monday launches compete with inbox clearing. Mid-month avoids budget cycles and conference distractions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Positioning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write a rollback narrative (200-word post explaining why the launch was paused) before T-Day. If you never publish it, no harm done. Without it, the decision to pause is made under stress with no preparation.</statement>
      <rationale>Launch-day decisions made under stress produce poorly-framed communications. Pre-written rollback narrative is cheap insurance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-execution.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/launch-plan.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
