<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-execution" title="Product Launch Execution: Launch Day, Monitoring, Post-Launch, and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Launch-day sequencing rules, monitoring requirements, post-launch actions, and the antipatterns that waste launch momentum.</summary>

  <section title="Launch Day Sequencing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign a single launch DRI who can say no to feature creep in the last 72 hours. All other team members are in support mode. Kill switch is held by a human, not an automated agent.</statement>
      <rationale>Launch-day decisions require context the automation does not have. An agent that auto-rolls-back on Twitter snark or a minor error rate spike will rollback unnecessarily and create a worse PR situation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Verify core flows manually before flipping feature flags or sending any announcement. A broken user flow discovered after the email blast goes out cannot be recalled.</statement>
      <rationale>Launch-day bugs that appear before any announcement can be fixed quietly. Bugs discovered after the email blast require a public apology email.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Monitoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Monitor: server health, error rates, signup flow conversion, and support queue length throughout launch day. Set alert thresholds before launch — define the number that triggers human escalation.</statement>
      <rationale>Monitoring without pre-set thresholds means every small anomaly triggers a team-wide discussion. Pre-set thresholds route noise to silence and signal to humans.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/launch-pulse.sh">Bash script that polls signup and visitor metrics every 5 minutes and posts to a Slack webhook.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Post-Launch">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture testimonials within 48 hours of launch — that is when user goodwill peaks and permission to quote is highest.</statement>
      <rationale>Testimonial requests sent 2 weeks after launch produce lower response rates and more generic feedback. The window closes fast.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a 30-minute retrospective within 7 days of launch. Force the retrospective agent (if used) to interview at least 3 customers before drafting — metrics-only retrospectives produce self-congratulatory artifacts that hide real learnings.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-launch learnings evaporate rapidly as the team moves on. A 7-day hard deadline preserves institutional memory while it is still fresh.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-publishing to social channels on launch day without a human approval gate between agent draft and POST to the network.</description>
      <reason>A reputational error published automatically at launch moment has maximum visibility. Human approval gate between generation and publication is non-negotiable for launch-day content.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent copy uses "revolutionary", "game-changing", "seamless", "robust", "cutting-edge", or "leverage" in launch content.</description>
      <reason>These words are credibility destroyers with technical audiences and produce lower CTR. Banned-words list in the copy prompt prevents them.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Counting on press pickup as a launch pillar without backup channel strategy.</description>
      <reason>Press pickup is unpredictable. Launches that depend on it have a ~60% chance of falling flat on the primary channel. Community and email list are the only controllable channels.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-planning.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/launch-day-checklist.md"/>
    <link path="templates/launch-pulse.sh"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
