<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-plg-principles" title="PLG Core Principles and Metrics">
  <summary>Defines the four PLG principles, key 2026 metrics, onboarding best practices, and the evolution away from one-size-fits-all freemium.</summary>

  <section title="Core Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design for self-serve onboarding — users must activate without sales intervention.</statement>
      <rationale>Sales-assisted onboarding caps growth by CAC payback; self-serve scales with zero marginal cost per new user.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Optimize for Time-to-Value (TTV): the "aha moment" must be reachable in under 5 minutes for consumer products.</statement>
      <rationale>Users who do not experience value in the first session rarely return. TTV under 5 minutes is the industry threshold for consumer SaaS; developer products may allow more time for a first successful API call.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Build product virality — sharing and collaboration features must be intrinsic, not bolted on.</statement>
      <rationale>Invitations and shared artifacts are the lowest-CAC acquisition channel when they trigger naturally from product usage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Grow expansion revenue through usage, not sales calls — upsells must be triggered by hitting product limits.</statement>
      <rationale>NRR above 120% allows a PLG company to grow revenue even while acquiring fewer new logos.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Key PLG Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track Activation Rate (% of signups completing the frozen activation event) and set a target above 40%.</statement>
      <rationale>Activation rate is the primary leading indicator for D30 retention; if activated users do not retain materially better than non-activated, the activation definition is wrong.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Freeze the activation event definition in YAML, not in a dashboard; change only via PR with both PM and growth owner signing.</statement>
      <rationale>Dashboard-stored definitions change silently quarter by quarter, making trend comparisons meaningless and causing PQL inflation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Key metrics table: Activation Rate target &gt;40%; TTV target &lt;5 min; PQL tracking weekly; Expansion Revenue Rate target &gt;30% of total; NRR target &gt;120%.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Onboarding Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement SSO/social login at step one to reduce signup drop-off before users see any value.</statement>
      <rationale>Email-and-password forms at signup are the single highest-friction drop-off point in self-serve funnels.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use interactive product tours, not documentation links; apply progressive feature disclosure rather than a full feature dump.</statement>
      <rationale>Documentation links send users out of the product; a feature dump overwhelms new users and increases time-to-value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Segment onboarding paths by user persona; personalize from first signup, not after the first session.</statement>
      <rationale>One-size-fits-all onboarding fails all personas partially; a developer signing up has different activation triggers than a designer or a PM.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="PLG Evolution 2026">
    <p>One-size-fits-all freemium is declining. Tailored free tiers based on user personas, AI-driven personalization in onboarding, and hybrid PLG + sales-assist for enterprise accounts are the emerging patterns.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Ahrefs reached $40M ARR with 40 employees using pure PLG — the product itself was the sales motion.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Limiting the free tier on signup count rather than on usage that correlates with willingness-to-pay.</description>
      <reason>Throttling new users hurts top-of-funnel; throttle on the dimension that scales with value (API calls, seats, storage) to align free-tier limits with upgrade intent.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="templates/plg-definitions.yml">Frozen activation/PQL spec — the PM-to-growth contract</reference>
  </section>
</text>
