<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-led-growth Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-led-growth as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Activation metric drift: "Activation" gets redefined every quarter to make the chart go up. Without a frozen, written definition tied to retention, the number is decorative.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A metric that changes definition each quarter is decorative; the trend line means nothing because the denominator changed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Freemium cannibalization: Free tier eats paid usage when limits are wrong; PMs lack the pricing instrumentation to detect it (need cohort revenue, not signup count).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Track cohort revenue separately; throttling on usage that correlates with willingness-to-pay, not on signup count.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>PQL → sales hand-off rot: PQL definition is owned by PM, scoring lives in product analytics, but acted on by sales in CRM. Three systems out of sync equals silent loss of deals.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Route via webhook to CRM SDR queue, not Slack; create a durable, auditable record.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>One-size-fits-all onboarding: PLG playbooks assume one ICP; in reality multiple personas hit signup and a single tour fails all of them.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Segment onboarding paths by persona; personalize from first signup.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Vanity North Star: "Weekly active users" without a revenue link rewards engagement hacks (notifications, streaks) that hurt retention long-term.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Link every metric to revenue impact; optimize for NRR and D30 retention, not just DAU/WAU.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Time-to-value cliff: TTV less than 5 min only matters if the second session happens. PMs over-optimize first-run and lose D7 retention.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>D1 to D7 conversion is the real growth lever once TTV is sub-10-min.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>PLG equals no marketing: Without content/SEO funnel, PLG equals empty funnel; PMs ship features instead of fixing acquisition and blame product-market fit.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PLG is not acquisition; without inbound traffic the activation funnel optimizes an empty pipe.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Ownership ambiguity: Activation owned by PM, conversion owned by growth, retention shared with CS — gaps between handoffs are where churn lives.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Define clear hand-off contracts and owners for each stage of the funnel.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM "activation rate is great" hallucination: Agents will confidently restate a number without checking the time window.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force the agent to print the SQL/HogQL it ran and the row count it received before any commentary.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Drift between PQL spec and SQL: Agent edits the YAML but not the dbt model, or vice versa — funnel silently changes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>CI must verify spec-yaml hash matches model annotation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Funnel-drop hypothesis collapse: Single-agent runs converge on "improve onboarding copy."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use 3 agents with separate roles (data, customer voice, competitor) and force divergent hypotheses before merging.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Survivorship bias on retention cohorts: Agent reports "D30 retention is 60%" but excludes cohorts that have not aged 30 days.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force explicit cohort-age filter in every retention query.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>PQL inflation: Agent loosens PQL thresholds because count is too low.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Threshold changes are governance events; require a git diff review on plg-definitions.yml, never accept inline tweaks.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Expansion attribution: Agent credits expansion to the last feature shipped; usage growth has multi-week lag.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use a fixed attribution window per the spec, not "what feels recent."</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Hand-off prompt-injection risk: PQL spec lives in a YAML the sales agent reads; if untrusted user content lands there, it can hijack the sales action.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Treat the file as a contract, validate schema before any agent ingest.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Confidentiality leak in cohort exports: Cohort dumps include emails, plan tier, sometimes free-form survey text.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run password-scrubber-agent before sharing analytics output externally or with broad-access bots.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
