<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Viral Loop Optimization Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Viral Loop Optimization` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="optimize-c-before-i" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Optimize c (invitee conversion) BEFORE i (invites per user). c improvements multiply every subsequent loop turn — i improvements only add invites.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brian Balfour viral compounding math; Reforge curriculum">c is the multiplier; each lift in c amplifies all future loop turns. i is additive — improves one cycle. c-first sequencing produces compound returns.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="one-variable-per-test" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each A/B test MUST change ONE variable at a time (CTA copy, OR share affordance, OR incentive amount). Multivariate viral tests confound which lever moved K.</statement>
      <rationale source="experimentation discipline; growth-experiment-design">Multivariate viral tests rarely have sample size for clean attribution. One-variable tests are slower but legible — team learns the loop, not just hits a number.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="retention-adjusted-decision" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decisions to ship MUST use K_eff (K * D30 retention), not raw K. Lifts in raw K with no K_eff move are not real wins.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reforge growth-loop framework">Raw K can rise because invitees signup but never activate. K_eff catches this; raw K alone leads to shipping cosmetic lifts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="share-moment-design-pattern" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Share moments MUST be designed AT a user win (achievement, output, completed action), not interruptively. Interruptive prompts depress retention more than they grow i.</statement>
      <rationale source="Slack / Calendly share-moment case studies">Interruptive (&apos;Invite 3 friends to continue!&apos;) triggers quit-impulse. Win-anchored (&apos;Share your report — it looks great&apos;) feels native + ships authentically.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="kill-experiments-no-lift-after-2-cycles" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If a variant shows no statistically significant lift after 2 full viral cycle times, kill it. Long-tail belief that &apos;it&apos;ll work eventually&apos; is the #1 source of waste.</statement>
      <rationale source="experiment retrospective corpus">Loop experiments have stable signal by 2 cycle times. Beyond that = no effect or too small. Killing fast frees capacity for the next lever.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
