<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-keywords" title="Keyword Management: Match Types, CRUD, Negatives, Quality Score">
  <summary>Keyword match type behavior, add/negative keyword patterns, Keyword Planner API usage, and Quality Score component interpretation.</summary>

  <section title="Match Types">
    <list>
      <item>BROAD: no symbol — matches synonyms and related queries (high volume, lower intent)</item>
      <item>PHRASE: "keyword" — matches queries containing the phrase in order (medium volume)</item>
      <item>EXACT: [keyword] — matches the exact query or close variants (low volume, highest intent)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with PHRASE and EXACT match types. Add BROAD only after establishing negative keyword lists from search terms reports. BROAD without negatives wastes budget on irrelevant queries.</statement>
      <rationale>BROAD match can trigger for semantically unrelated searches. Without negatives built from real search term data, 20-40% of BROAD budget goes to irrelevant traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/keyword-list.py">Keyword dict format for add_keywords()</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Negative Keywords">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add negative keywords at the campaign level for terms that should never match any ad group. Add negatives at ad group level for terms that are relevant to other ad groups but not this one.</statement>
      <rationale>Campaign-level negatives are inherited by all ad groups. Ad group-level negatives enable funneling: "shoes" at campaign level might be too broad, but "running shoes" at the running ad group should exclude "dress shoes" to prevent cross-ad-group competition.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Keyword Planner">
    <p>Use GenerateKeywordIdeasRequest with seed keywords and location/language targeting to get avg_monthly_searches, competition level, and top/bottom bid estimates. Requires Basic Access developer token or higher.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Score">
    <p>Quality Score (1-10) is Google's estimate of ad relevance and landing page experience. It affects ad rank and effective CPC. Three components: expected CTR (ABOVE_AVERAGE / AVERAGE / BELOW_AVERAGE), ad relevance, and landing page experience.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Diagnose low Quality Score by component: if expected_ctr is BELOW_AVERAGE, improve ad copy; if post_click_quality_score is BELOW_AVERAGE, improve landing page relevance and speed.</statement>
      <rationale>Quality Score below 6 increases effective CPC by 20-40%. Identifying the failing component directs remediation to the right layer (ad vs. landing page).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Search Terms Report">
    <p>Query search_term_view to see actual queries that triggered ads. Use to add high-converting search terms as exact-match keywords and to identify irrelevant terms for negatives. Run weekly.</p>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Not reviewing the search terms report for the first 30 days of a new campaign.</description>
      <reason>New BROAD and PHRASE campaigns accumulate irrelevant search terms quickly. Each unreviewed week is wasted budget on non-converting queries.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
