<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="FinOps Framework">
  <summary>Three-phase Inform/Optimize/Operate cycle with expected savings per strategy and AI/ML workload cost patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Phase 1: Inform">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable billing exports (AWS CUR, GCP BigQuery, Azure Cost Management) with daily refresh. Target &gt;90% tag coverage for cost attribution.</statement>
      <rationale>You cannot optimize what you cannot see. 100% tag coverage is unrealistic due to untaggable resources; 90%+ is the mature target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Mandatory tags: Environment, Owner, Project, CostCenter. Enforce via SCP/Policy to block untagged resource creation.</statement>
      <rationale>Four tags enable attribution by env, person, product, and finance. SCPs prevent drift by requiring tags at creation time, not retroactively.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 2: Optimize">
    <p>Expected savings by strategy (2025 benchmarks):</p>
    <list>
      <item>Rightsizing — 15-30%</item>
      <item>Spot/Preemptible instances — 70-90%</item>
      <item>Reserved Instances / Savings Plans — 30-60%</item>
      <item>Storage lifecycle policies — 20-40%</item>
      <item>Idle resource termination — 10-25%</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Purchase Savings Plans only after 30+ days of usage data. Commit to 80% of baseline usage to maintain flexibility.</statement>
      <rationale>Committing to more than baseline usage results in unused commitments (negative ROI). 80% baseline leaves 20% buffer for workload changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 3: Operate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set budget alerts at 50%, 80%, 100%, and 120% thresholds. Include a forecasted-overage alert at 100%.</statement>
      <rationale>Multi-threshold alerts give teams early warning (50%) and escalation path (100%+). Forecasted alerts enable proactive action before the month ends.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Conduct weekly cost reviews at team level and monthly reviews with optimization action items and savings tracking.</statement>
      <rationale>Weekly cadence keeps cost accountability active; monthly review measures ROI and adjusts targets.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="AI/ML Cost Optimization">
    <rule>
      <statement>For training jobs: use Spot instances with checkpoint-based restart. Checkpoint every 100-500 steps to S3/GCS.</statement>
      <rationale>Spot instances cost 70-90% less than on-demand. Checkpointing ensures a spot interruption loses at most one checkpoint interval of work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# Training loop with S3 checkpointing
def train_with_checkpoints(model, optimizer, dataloader, checkpoint_interval=100):
    for epoch in range(num_epochs):
        for step, batch in enumerate(dataloader):
            # ... training logic ...
            if step % checkpoint_interval == 0:
                torch.save({
                    'epoch': epoch, 'step': step,
                    'model_state_dict': model.state_dict(),
                    'optimizer_state_dict': optimizer.state_dict(),
                }, f's3://checkpoints/model_{epoch}_{step}.pt')
]]></code>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>For inference: implement response caching (20-60% savings) and request batching. Evaluate model quantization (50% cost, 2x speed).</statement>
      <rationale>Inference at scale is dominated by repeated identical requests and underutilized GPU batch capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
