<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-checklist" title="FinOps Implementation Checklist">
  <summary>Ordered checklist for implementing FinOps Inform, Optimize, and Operate phases.</summary>

  <section title="INFORM Phase">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable detailed billing exports with daily refresh before starting any optimization work.</statement>
      <rationale>Optimization decisions made without current data cause savings estimates to be wrong and commitments to be over-purchased.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Enable AWS CUR / GCP BigQuery export / Azure Cost Management export</item>
      <item>Define mandatory tag schema: Environment, Owner, Project, CostCenter</item>
      <item>Implement tag enforcement policies (SCP/Policy) to block untagged launches</item>
      <item>Create untagged resource report and assign remediation owners</item>
      <item>Enable cloud-native anomaly detection with Slack/email routing</item>
      <item>Build team-level cost dashboards with daily/weekly reports</item>
      <item>Target &gt;80% tag coverage initially; &gt;90% at mature stage</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="OPTIMIZE Phase">
    <list>
      <item>Run weekly rightsizing analysis: flag instances with avg CPU &lt;20% or memory &lt;30%</item>
      <item>Identify idle instances (&gt;7 days &lt;5% CPU): schedule termination or stop</item>
      <item>Implement auto-shutdown tags for non-production resources</item>
      <item>Analyze 30+ days of usage before purchasing Savings Plans or Reserved Instances</item>
      <item>Delete orphaned snapshots, unattached EBS volumes, unused Elastic IPs</item>
      <item>Implement S3 lifecycle policies: Standard-IA at 30d, Glacier at 90d, Deep Archive at 365d</item>
      <item>For AI/ML training: migrate on-demand GPU to Spot with checkpointing</item>
      <item>For AI/ML inference: implement caching and batching before scaling GPU instances</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="OPERATE Phase">
    <rule>
      <statement>Establish per-team budgets with 50/80/100/120% alerts and a forecasted-overage alert. Review forecast accuracy monthly.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams that never see their costs have no incentive to optimize. Multi-threshold alerts create early warning before budgets are blown.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Set monthly/quarterly budgets per team and environment</item>
      <item>Configure budget alerts at 50%, 80%, 100%, 120% thresholds</item>
      <item>Add forecasted-overage alert at 100% (fires before month end)</item>
      <item>Conduct monthly cost reviews with action items and savings tracking</item>
      <item>Track cost per unit of work (cost per 100k tokens, cost per transaction)</item>
      <item>Automate tagging remediation for new untagged resources</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Maturity Levels">
    <list>
      <item>Crawl: basic visibility, initial tagging, manual reviews, reactive</item>
      <item>Walk: &gt;80% tags, regular reviews, some automation, proactive rightsizing</item>
      <item>Run: &gt;90% tags, automated optimization, real-time visibility, cost-aware culture</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
