<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ops-legal-basics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>Establish legal framework for SaaS: Terms of Service, Privacy Policy, and trademark registration. Know what you must have in place before accepting customers and what compliance gaps pose legal risk.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>legal</tag>
      <tag>terms-of-service</tag>
      <tag>privacy-policy</tag>
      <tag>trademark</tag>
      <tag>compliance</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Legal Fundamentals for Founders: ToS, Privacy, and Trademark Basics</title>
    <summary>Before accepting customers, you need three legal documents: Terms of Service that govern the relationship and limit your liability, a Privacy Policy that discloses how you collect and handle user data (required by GDPR, CCPA), and trademark registration to protect your brand name. A ToS must cover payment, billing cycles, intellectual property ownership, disclaimers, liability caps, termination, and governing law. A Privacy Policy must detail data collection, use, retention, user rights, and security. Trademark registration via the US Patent and Trademark Office protects your brand.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Without a ToS, you have no contractual protection: a customer can claim they never agreed to your pricing, dispute payment, demand refunds, or claim ownership of data. Without a Privacy Policy, you violate GDPR (EU users) and CCPA (California users) by default, exposing yourself to fines (GDPR penalties up to 4% of global revenue). Without trademark registration, competitors can use your brand name and you have no legal recourse.</p>
      <p>These three documents are non-negotiable minimum compliance for any online business with paying customers or user data. The cost to set them up (often $1-3k with a lawyer, or free with templates) is far less than the risk of operating without them.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before launching a SaaS product or accepting paying customers.</item>
        <item>Before collecting any user data (emails, usage logs, payment info).</item>
        <item>Before using your brand name publicly (product launch, press coverage, social media).</item>
        <item>When expanding into new markets or geographies (GDPR, CCPA, and local regulations vary).</item>
        <item>After receiving legal notice or a cease-and-desist from a competitor.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Free projects with no user data collection and no business intent (personal blog, hobby projects).</item>
        <item>Internal tools used only by your company and employees (no external users, no external data).</item>
        <item>Services exclusively for a single client under a custom contract (bespoke legal agreement replaces standard ToS).</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="terms-of-service">
      <p>A Terms of Service (ToS) is the contract between your company and your customers. It specifies what you offer, what you do not guarantee, what users can and cannot do, how payment works, who owns intellectual property, how you limit your liability, and how disputes are resolved.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>A SaaS Terms of Service MUST include nine sections: (1) Acceptance of Terms (using the service means agreement); (2) Description of Service (what you provide, what you don't guarantee); (3) User Responsibilities (acceptable use, account security, credentials); (4) Payment Terms (pricing, billing cycle, cancellation policy, automatic renewal notice required by law in many jurisdictions); (5) Intellectual Property (you own platform IP, customers own their data, you license user content for service operation); (6) Disclaimers (no warranty, service is "as is"); (7) Termination (how either party exits, data export/deletion rights); (8) Governing Law and Dispute Resolution (jurisdiction, arbitration vs. court); (9) Severability plus Entire Agreement (one bad clause does not void the whole agreement, written terms supersede verbal promises). Do not use a 50-page generic template; customize at minimum: Description of Service, Payment Terms, IP ownership, and Governing Law. Get lawyer review if you have paying customers or operate in regulated industries (fintech, healthcare).</statement>
        <rationale>A ToS is your protection against customer disputes. It establishes that the customer agreed to your terms, limits what you guarantee, caps your liability, and specifies how disputes are resolved. Automatic renewal notices and clear cancellation policies are required by law in most US states and the EU. IP sections clarify that you own the platform and customer owns their data, preventing claims that the customer owns your product or that you claim ownership of their content.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="ToS with key protections">
        <description>SaaS ToS includes: "The Service is provided 'as is' without warranty of any kind" (liability cap). "Customer's sole remedy for service failure is a refund of fees paid in the last 30 days" (liability limitation). "Customer may cancel at any time; automatic renewal requires 14 days' notice before the next billing cycle" (ROSCA compliance). "Termination includes 30-day data export period; data not exported is deleted" (GDPR Art. 17 compliance). These four clauses protect the company from unlimited claims while respecting customer and regulatory rights.</description>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Weak ToS">
        <description>ToS says "We provide this service and are not liable for anything." No description of what the service is, no payment terms, no IP clarification, no cancellation policy. A customer disputes a charge and the ToS provides no recourse because it is too vague to enforce.</description>
        <note>A vague ToS is often unenforceable. Specificity (what the service is, what you do guarantee vs. do not, how payment works, how to cancel) makes it enforceable in court.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Adopting a ToS that includes "no refunds, ever" or "company is not liable for any damages, including data loss or security breaches."</description>
        <reason>Absolute liability waivers are often unenforceable; courts may deem them unconscionable. Balancing customer protection (reasonable cancellation, data export rights) with company protection (reasonable liability caps, remedies) is the goal.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="privacy-policy">
      <p>A Privacy Policy discloses what personal data you collect, how you use it, how long you retain it, who you share it with, and what rights users have to access or delete their data. Privacy Policy is required by GDPR (EU), CCPA (California), and other regulations globally.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>A SaaS Privacy Policy MUST include nine sections: (1) Information Collected (what personal data, how it is collected: forms, cookies, analytics, third-party SDKs); (2) Use of Information (purpose of each data category, legal basis for processing: consent, contract, legitimate interest under GDPR); (3) Data Sharing (named third parties: processors, analytics, payment providers; purpose and legal basis for each); (4) Data Retention (how long each category is retained and why); (5) User Rights (right to access, correct, delete, port data per GDPR Art. 15-20; CCPA opt-out of sale); (6) Security (description of technical and organizational measures without specifics that aid attackers); (7) Cookies (types: essential, analytics, marketing; consent mechanism); (8) Children (age restriction statement, COPPA compliance if applicable); (9) Contact (controller identity: legal name plus address, DPO contact if required, effective date and version number). Ensure the policy matches your actual practices; inconsistency is a compliance violation. Update the policy any time you add a data processor, change retention periods, or add new data collection.</statement>
        <rationale>GDPR and CCPA require a Privacy Policy that is accurate, transparent, and gives users meaningful control over their data. The policy is the mechanism by which you obtain consent (if consent is your legal basis) and allow users to exercise their rights (access, deletion, portability). Inconsistency between your stated practices and actual practices is a violation and can result in fines. The policy is a living document; update it as your data practices change.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Privacy Policy with transparency">
        <description>Privacy Policy states: "We collect email, name, and usage events for contract fulfillment and product improvement. Legal basis: contract and legitimate interest. We share data with Stripe (payment processor, PII), Segment (analytics, usage events), and AWS (hosting, all data). Retention: account data retained while customer is active plus 30 days after deletion; usage logs retained for 1 year for analytics. Users may access, correct, delete, and export data via Settings or by contacting privacy@company.com; we respond within 30 days per GDPR. We do not sell data to third parties." This policy is transparent, names all processors, specifies legal bases, and clarifies user rights.</description>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Vague Privacy Policy">
        <description>Privacy Policy states: "We may collect data as needed and may share with third parties if required." No specificity on what data, why, how long, or user rights. A GDPR regulator investigating this company will find the policy inadequate because it provides no meaningful transparency.</description>
        <note>A vague policy is a compliance violation. Regulators expect specificity: what data, why, who, how long, and how to delete.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Stating "We use Google Analytics" without mentioning that Google Analytics transfers EU user data to the US, which requires either Standard Contractual Clauses or a Data Processing Agreement under GDPR.</description>
        <reason>Data transfers outside the EU are heavily regulated. If you do not have appropriate legal mechanisms in place, you are violating GDPR even if the Privacy Policy mentions Google Analytics. Transparency alone is not sufficient; you must also have legal agreements with processors.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="trademark-registration-and-brand-protection">
      <p>Trademark registration (via the US Patent and Trademark Office for US-based companies, WIPO for international) protects your brand name from competitors and gives you legal grounds to stop infringement. An unregistered trademark has some protection but is weak compared to a registered mark.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Before publicly launching a product (name, logo, tagline), search the USPTO TESS database (https://tess.uspto.gov/) to ensure no similar marks are registered in your class of goods/services. If the search is clear, file a trademark application via ttsdr.uspto.gov. For US-based companies, register in class 42 (software services) and any commercial class relevant to your business. Registration takes 6-12 months. Once registered, use registered symbol (R in circle) next to your brand name in marketing materials. Monitor the trademark every 3 years to renew. For international expansion, consider registering with WIPO (Madrid Protocol) to cover the EU, UK, and other key markets simultaneously.</statement>
        <rationale>A registered trademark gives you exclusive rights to your brand name in your class and provides grounds for legal action against competitors. Without registration, a competitor can use a confusingly similar name and you have limited legal recourse. Registration is a one-time cost ($225-400 per class in the US) and is inexpensive compared to the risk of a competitor outbidding you for your own brand name on Google or App Store.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Trademark registration workflow">
        <description>Founder plans to launch "FooBar" SaaS product. They search the USPTO TESS database and find no existing marks in class 42 (software) that conflict with "FooBar." They file a trademark application in class 42 (software services) on day 1 of launch. 8 months later, the trademark is registered. They add registered symbol to "FooBar" in all marketing materials. A year later, a competitor tries to launch "FooBar Analytics" and the registered trademark holder sends a cease-and-desist, which is effective because the trademark is registered.</description>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="No trademark search, brand collision">
        <description>Founder launches "Analytics Pro" without searching the trademark database. 6 months later, they discover a competitor already has a registered trademark for "Analytics Pro" and receives a cease-and-desist. The company has built brand equity in the name, but has no legal right to it. Rebranding costs $50k plus in lost brand equity and marketing rework.</description>
        <note>A $300 trademark search and filing at launch prevents expensive rebranding later.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Assuming that because you registered a domain name (example.com), your brand name is legally protected.</description>
        <reason>Domain registration and trademark registration are separate. Domain registration gives you the web address; trademark registration protects your brand name in commerce. You can have a domain without a trademark and vice versa.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="compliance-roadmap">
      <p>Legal compliance is staged: before customers, set up ToS and Privacy Policy; before public launch, register trademark; as you grow, add additional compliance layers (data processing agreements with vendors, SOC 2 audit for enterprise customers, international privacy compliance).</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Compliance roadmap: Pre-launch (before first paying customer): draft or obtain ToS and Privacy Policy, customize for your business model, ensure they match your actual practices. Before public launch: search and file trademark application. Less than 3 months of revenue: have a lawyer review your ToS and Privacy Policy (cost: $1-2k). Greater than $100k ARR or entering new markets: add Data Processing Agreements (DPAs) with all third-party vendors who access customer data, conduct a GDPR impact assessment if you have EU users, and consider SOC 2 audit. This staged approach prevents spending over $5k on legal before you have product-market fit, while ensuring you do not operate unprotected.</statement>
        <rationale>Early startups often spend too much on legal or too little. A staged approach balances protection with cash constraints: templates plus light customization for the first phase, then lawyer review once you have revenue and can justify the cost.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Staged legal compliance">
        <description>Pre-launch: founder uses a free SaaS template for ToS and Privacy Policy, customizes payment terms and data collection sections, posts on website. Launch: files trademark application. 3 months later ($15k ARR): hires lawyer for $1500 review, fixes gaps in Privacy Policy (clarified data retention, added DPA clause). 6 months later ($50k ARR): adds formal DPAs with Stripe, Google Analytics, and hosting provider. This staged approach cost approximately $2k and provided necessary protection at each phase without overinvesting early.</description>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hiring a law firm to write a complete legal package (ToS, Privacy Policy, DPA, NDA, employee handbook) before launch or with minimal revenue.</description>
        <reason>Pre-launch legal spending of $10k plus is usually wasteful because the business model and feature set are still changing. Customize a template first, then get lawyer review after you have paying customers and revenue to justify the cost.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/policy-sections.txt" purpose="Required sections checklist for Terms of Service and Privacy Policy: 9 sections each that cover payment, IP, data, retention, user rights, and compliance."/>
      <template path="templates/tsdr-status.py" purpose="Python utility to look up USPTO trademark status by serial number. Use to check the current registration status of a filed or registered trademark via the TSDR API."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.ushio.gov/tmlocal/casefiles/"/>
      <link href="https://gdpr-info.eu/"/>
      <link href="https://oag.ca.gov/privacy/ccpa"/>
      <link href="https://www.abanet.org/rpps/public/home"/>
      <ref slug="ops-legal-compliance"/>
      <ref slug="ops-tax-basics"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
