<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Supply Chain Security Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5+ testable rules grounding the methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale. Includes the skip-this-methodology rule that the decision-tree maps to.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-secret-scanning" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Secret scanning MUST run on every commit via pre-commit hook (Gitleaks or detect-secrets) AND in CI on the full history (`git fetch --unshallow`). When a secret lands on main, rewrite history with `git filter-repo` and rotate the credential immediately.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source: Gitleaks docs; faion-network security audit Q1 2026">Pre-commit catches secrets before they reach the remote. CI with full history catches secrets introduced by force-pushes, merge commits, or squash merges that bypass the hook. Rotation without history rewrite leaves the secret in the public git object store indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-lock-files" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use lock files (package-lock.json, poetry.lock, go.sum, Cargo.lock) for all dependency manifests. Commit lock files. Never add lock files to .gitignore.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source: npm / pip / cargo docs">Lock files pin the exact resolved dependency tree including transitive dependencies, preventing silent upgrades to vulnerable versions during CI installs. Without lock files, `npm install` today and tomorrow may resolve different packages.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-license-policy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>License policy: deny by default; maintain an allowlist of approved licenses (MIT, Apache-2.0, BSD-3-Clause, MPL-2.0). Reject GPL-3.0 and AGPL-3.0 for commercial projects unless legal sign-off is explicit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source: open-source licensing primer; SPDX">SCA tools struggle with vendored or unknown-license code; an explicit allowlist forces review rather than silent acceptance of copyleft licenses that can create legal obligations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-sbom-per-build" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Generate an SBOM (Syft or Trivy, SPDX or CycloneDX format) per build and store it as a release artefact. SBOM component-count regression vs prior build fails CI.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source: CISA Software Bill of Materials guidance">Without per-build SBOMs there is no audit trail for what shipped. Regression detection catches accidental dependency loss as well as malicious tree changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply Supply Chain Security to one repository per pass. Cross-repo passes MUST be split. Methodology MUST be skipped when there is no incident response path — adding more findings without a triage workflow makes the team blind, not safer.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 content-completion; faion-network failure-mode audit">Anti-conflation: batched passes lose per-repo context. Findings without triage create noise that erodes trust in the scanner.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
