<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="business-process-analysis Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for business-process-analysis. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before modeling any individual process, build a scoped inventory table with columns: process name, owner, priority, in-scope flag. Prioritize by nva_minutes_per_year and strategic fit; deep-model only the top decile.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Enterprise programs routinely discover 800+ processes; without a Pareto cut, documentation effort consumes more resources than the improvements deliver. The scorecard prevents portfolio bloat.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capture every workaround and exception, not just the official flow; record verbatim quotes from process participants for any anomaly in evidence/anomalies.md.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Shadow steps and workarounds are the actual process; documenting only the intended flow produces a diagram nobody recognizes and analysis based on fiction. Verbatim quotes prevent agent rewrites that erase institutional knowledge.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Classify every step as Value-Adding (VA), Business-Necessary (BN), or Non-Value-Adding (NVA); compute NVA percentage before proposing any improvement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Redesigning before quantifying NVA produces a wish list, not a business case. The NVA percentage anchors the expected-benefit calculation in Stage 4.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Produce a structured diff table (step | current actor | future actor | current system | future system | change type | risk | dependency) instead of a narrative description.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A narrative future state hides integration prerequisites; the diff table forces specificity and makes dependencies visible before implementation starts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not advance to Stage 5 without Stage 4 review by the portfolio agent (enterprise context) or process owner (project context); validation is a decision gate, not a formality.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Future-state designs based on incorrect process models or unverified business rules generate implementation work in the wrong direction; the stage gate catches these before any code is written.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run enterprise BPA as two-tier orchestration: a portfolio agent that maintains the inventory and governance artifacts, plus per-process agents (one invocation per in-scope process) applying the 5-stage loop.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A single agent attempting to model 100+ processes in one context produces shallow, hallucinated artifacts. The portfolio agent acts as coordinator - it assigns scope, enforces the BPMN standard, and rolls up metrics; per-process agents produce the deliverables.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Limit deep-modeling to the top decile by nva_minutes_per_year *strategic_fit; document all other processes at narrative depth (one paragraph each).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Full documentation of a 500-process landscape is unmaintainable; the Pareto principle applied to NVA impact identifies the 10% of processes delivering 80% of improvement value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decide level-of-detail (L1/L2/L3/L4), naming convention (verb-noun), pool/lane discipline, and message-flow rules before any modelling starts; put the rules in standards/bpmn-conventions.md and have every agent read them.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">BPMN files produced without a shared dialect are incompatible at the portfolio level; a governance board that approves diagrams with inconsistent conventions creates technical debt in the model repository.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat BPMN as code: source-control XML, run bpmnlint in CI, code-review changes, tag releases per programme milestone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">BPMN files without version history cannot answer "what changed and why?" - the audit trail required by ISO 9001 and SOX 404 auditors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Anchor to APQC PCF, SCOR, or eTOM as scaffolding, not law; for every deviation from the reference, capture rationale and competitive-differentiation hypothesis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Reference-model fundamentalism forces genuine differentiators into generic boxes, destroying competitive advantage documentation. The deviation log is the intellectual property of the BPA exercise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain a per-L2-process ownership decision log with entries: acquirer | target | hybrid | new, each citing a deal-thesis line; un-cited decisions are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">M&amp;A process decisions made without deal-thesis grounding reflect political convenience rather than value creation; the citation requirement enforces discipline and provides audit evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For ERP gap-fit analysis, follow: adopt-standard → configure → extend → build-custom → drop; document each gap with explicit decision type. Agents bias toward "build" - counter with explicit configure-first prompts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Every customization multiplies upgrade cost; the adopt/configure priority order ensures the lowest-cost option is evaluated before custom development is authorized.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
