<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process-stages" title="Business Process Analysis: Five-Stage Loop">
  <summary>Five-stage BPA loop for documenting current-state processes, classifying activity value, and designing measurable future-state improvements.</summary>

  <section title="Stage 1: Identify Processes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before modeling any individual process, build a scoped inventory table with columns: process name, owner, priority, in-scope flag. Prioritize by nva_minutes_per_year and strategic fit; deep-model only the top decile.</statement>
      <rationale>Enterprise programs routinely discover 800+ processes; without a Pareto cut, documentation effort consumes more resources than the improvements deliver. The scorecard prevents portfolio bloat.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/rank-portfolio.py">Ranks redesign/automation candidates from scorecard.csv by NVA x feasibility</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 2: Document Current State">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture every workaround and exception, not just the official flow; record verbatim quotes from process participants for any anomaly in evidence/anomalies.md.</statement>
      <rationale>Shadow steps and workarounds are the actual process; documenting only the intended flow produces a diagram nobody recognizes and analysis based on fiction. Verbatim quotes prevent agent rewrites that erase institutional knowledge.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Activities — what is done.</item>
      <item>Actors — who does it (person, role, or system).</item>
      <item>Inputs and outputs — data entering and leaving each step.</item>
      <item>Decisions and business rules — gateway logic with conditions.</item>
      <item>Systems used — applications touched at each step.</item>
      <item>Exceptions and workarounds — deviations from the official flow.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/process-documentation.md">Current-state process documentation template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 3: Analyze the Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every step as Value-Adding (VA), Business-Necessary (BN), or Non-Value-Adding (NVA); compute NVA percentage before proposing any improvement.</statement>
      <rationale>Redesigning before quantifying NVA produces a wish list, not a business case. The NVA percentage anchors the expected-benefit calculation in Stage 4.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Value analysis — which steps add direct customer or business value (VA), which are required but not directly valuable (BN, e.g., compliance), which are waste (NVA).</item>
      <item>Time analysis — where are delays; compute cycle time vs. touch time ratio.</item>
      <item>Cost analysis — cost per transaction at each step.</item>
      <item>Quality analysis — where errors occur and their rework cost.</item>
      <item>Pain point analysis — participant frustrations (captured from elicitation, not inferred).</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/process-analysis.md">Process analysis artifact template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 4: Design Future State">
    <rule>
      <statement>Produce a structured diff table (step | current actor | future actor | current system | future system | change type | risk | dependency) instead of a narrative description.</statement>
      <rationale>A narrative future state hides integration prerequisites; the diff table forces specificity and makes dependencies visible before implementation starts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Eliminate — remove NVA steps (e.g., redundant approvals, double-entry).</item>
      <item>Automate — replace manual steps with technology where ROI is positive.</item>
      <item>Parallelize — run sequential steps concurrently where data dependencies allow.</item>
      <item>Simplify — reduce decision complexity by raising thresholds or merging branches.</item>
      <item>Integrate — connect systems to eliminate manual handoffs.</item>
      <item>Standardize — enforce one consistent execution path to eliminate variation-driven rework.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage 5: Validate and Plan">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not advance to Stage 5 without Stage 4 review by the portfolio agent (enterprise context) or process owner (project context); validation is a decision gate, not a formality.</statement>
      <rationale>Future-state designs based on incorrect process models or unverified business rules generate implementation work in the wrong direction; the stage gate catches these before any code is written.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Review future state with process owners and affected stakeholders.</item>
      <item>Identify system requirements generated by the redesign.</item>
      <item>Define transition plan: how the organization moves from current to future state.</item>
      <item>Define success metrics: quantitative targets against current baseline.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Documenting the ideal process instead of the actual process.</description>
    <reason>Analysis of an ideal state produces improvements to a process nobody runs; the current-state documentation must reflect observed reality, not policy intent.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Skipping baseline metrics before redesigning.</description>
    <reason>Future-state benefits have no evidence anchor without volume, cycle time, and cost baselines; the business case is undefendable.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
