<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-enterprise-scale" title="Business Process Analysis: Enterprise Scale and Governance">
  <summary>Portfolio-agent orchestration pattern for enterprise BPA, BPMN governance, reference-framework alignment, and M&amp;A/ERP specializations.</summary>

  <section title="Portfolio-Agent Orchestration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run enterprise BPA as two-tier orchestration: a portfolio agent that maintains the inventory and governance artifacts, plus per-process agents (one invocation per in-scope process) applying the 5-stage loop.</statement>
      <rationale>A single agent attempting to model 100+ processes in one context produces shallow, hallucinated artifacts. The portfolio agent acts as coordinator — it assigns scope, enforces the BPMN standard, and rolls up metrics; per-process agents produce the deliverables.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit deep-modeling to the top decile by nva_minutes_per_year × strategic_fit; document all other processes at narrative depth (one paragraph each).</statement>
      <rationale>Full documentation of a 500-process landscape is unmaintainable; the Pareto principle applied to NVA impact identifies the 10% of processes delivering 80% of improvement value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/rank-portfolio.py">Ranks processes by NVA x feasibility composite score from scorecard.csv</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="BPMN Governance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Decide level-of-detail (L1/L2/L3/L4), naming convention (verb-noun), pool/lane discipline, and message-flow rules before any modelling starts; put the rules in standards/bpmn-conventions.md and have every agent read them.</statement>
      <rationale>BPMN files produced without a shared dialect are incompatible at the portfolio level; a governance board that approves diagrams with inconsistent conventions creates technical debt in the model repository.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat BPMN as code: source-control XML, run bpmnlint in CI, code-review changes, tag releases per programme milestone.</statement>
      <rationale>BPMN files without version history cannot answer "what changed and why?" — the audit trail required by ISO 9001 and SOX 404 auditors.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Reference Framework Alignment">
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor to APQC PCF, SCOR, or eTOM as scaffolding, not law; for every deviation from the reference, capture rationale and competitive-differentiation hypothesis.</statement>
      <rationale>Reference-model fundamentalism forces genuine differentiators into generic boxes, destroying competitive advantage documentation. The deviation log is the intellectual property of the BPA exercise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Lifting APQC PCF text verbatim as if it describes the actual company processes.</description>
      <reason>Reference processes are industry averages; the company's reality may differ significantly. Every reference-derived sentence must be tagged [reference] and reviewed by a human before publication.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="M&amp;A Specialization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain a per-L2-process ownership decision log with entries: acquirer | target | hybrid | new, each citing a deal-thesis line; un-cited decisions are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale>M&amp;A process decisions made without deal-thesis grounding reflect political convenience rather than value creation; the citation requirement enforces discipline and provides audit evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Portfolio agent kickoff prompt for M&amp;A integration enforces structured output without inventing process owners.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Inputs: acquirer-pcf.csv, target-pcf.csv, deal-thesis.md, integration-priorities.md.
Build the Process Portfolio Comparison artifact:
  - Map both inventories to APQC PCF Level 2.
  - For every PCF L2 row: acquirer_owner, target_owner,
    decision (adopt-acquirer | adopt-target | hybrid | new),
    rationale (cite deal-thesis line).
  - Flag any L2 with no owner on either side as "GAP — requires design".
  - Output: portfolio.csv + decisions-log.md. Do NOT model individual processes yet.]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="ERP Rollout Specialization">
    <rule>
      <statement>For ERP gap-fit analysis, follow: adopt-standard → configure → extend → build-custom → drop; document each gap with explicit decision type. Agents bias toward "build" — counter with explicit configure-first prompts.</statement>
      <rationale>Every customization multiplies upgrade cost; the adopt/configure priority order ensures the lowest-cost option is evaluated before custom development is authorized.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Cross-country process smoothing: treating a multi-jurisdiction process as one global flow.</description>
    <reason>Tax, payroll, and labor law vary significantly by country; a global process diagram that hides legal variants creates compliance risk and failed implementations.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
