<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Business Process Analysis — Enterprise Scale and Governance Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Antipatterns observed in real engagements applying business-process-analysis. Each entry pairs symptom + root cause + fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern id="apqc-verbatim" severity="high">
      <symptom>Lifting APQC PCF text verbatim as if it describes the actual company processes.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="BABOK v3 + field experience">Reference-model fundamentalism — author copy-pastes APQC text into the current-state model.</root-cause>
      <fix>Reference processes are industry averages; every reference-derived sentence must be tagged [reference] and reviewed before publication.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="ideal-not-actual" severity="high">
      <symptom>Documenting the ideal process instead of the actual process.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="BABOK v3 + field experience">Sponsor and BA describe the policy intent because nobody shadowed an operator.</root-cause>
      <fix>Current-state model must reflect observed reality; pair with frontline-validation-protocol two-operator rule.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="no-baseline" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Skipping baseline metrics before redesigning.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="BABOK v3 + field experience">Stakeholders pressure the BA to move to future-state design before measurement.</root-cause>
      <fix>Lock volume/cycle-time/cost baselines before any future-state work; Stage 4 is gated on baseline presence.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="portfolio-inflation" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Documenting 800 processes uniformly without a Pareto cut.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="BABOK v3 + field experience">Agent over-eagerly produces equal-depth artefacts for every inventory row.</root-cause>
      <fix>Apply r7: deep-model only top decile by nva_minutes_per_year × strategic_fit; narrative-document the rest.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="politics-shaped-diagram" severity="medium">
      <symptom>M&amp;A surviving entity's process documented as canonical even when target's is better.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="BABOK v3 + field experience">Power asymmetry in steering committee.</root-cause>
      <fix>Require ownership_decision citation back to deal-thesis line; un-cited decisions are blocked.</fix>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
