<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="business-process-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for business-process-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Lifting APQC PCF text verbatim as if it describes the actual company processes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Reference processes are industry averages; the company's reality may differ significantly. Every reference-derived sentence must be tagged [reference] and reviewed by a human before publication.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Documenting the ideal process instead of the actual process.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Analysis of an ideal state produces improvements to a process nobody runs; the current-state documentation must reflect observed reality, not policy intent.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping baseline metrics before redesigning.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Future-state benefits have no evidence anchor without volume, cycle time, and cost baselines; the business case is undefendable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-country process smoothing: treating a multi-jurisdiction process as one global flow.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tax, payroll, and labor law vary significantly by country; a global process diagram that hides legal variants creates compliance risk and failed implementations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Portfolio inflation without Pareto cut.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Enterprise programmes routinely "discover" 800+ processes; LLMs eagerly produce documentation for all of them. Without a Pareto cut, the artefact set is unmaintainable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Reference-model fundamentalism.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Forcing every business onto APQC PCF or SCOR distorts genuine differentiators. Reference frameworks are scaffolding, not law.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Governance theatre without instrumentation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A BPMN governance board produces standards nobody uses. The methodology cannot, by itself, prove adoption - instrumentation (audit trails, conformance checks) is required.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Politics-shaped diagrams in M&amp;A.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>In M&amp;A, the surviving entity's process is documented as canonical even when the acquired entity's is better. The methodology has no political guard-rails.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Static snapshot without maintenance cycle.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Enterprise process landscapes drift quarterly (re-orgs, system changes, regulation). A 6-month-old BPA is already stale unless actively maintained.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
