<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="ba" count="118">
  <methodology slug="acceptance-criteria" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-modeling/acceptance-criteria">
    <summary>Acceptance criteria (AC) define the exact conditions a requirement must satisfy to be accepted as complete.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="acceptance-criteria" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/acceptance-criteria">
    <summary>Explicit, testable conditions that define when a requirement is accepted as complete.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-discovery-call-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-modeling/agency-discovery-call-playbook">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for agency discovery call playbook that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agile-ba-frameworks" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/agile-ba-frameworks">
    <summary>A mapping of business analysis competencies onto Scrum ceremonies and scaled agile framework (SAFe) levels.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agile-ba-frameworks" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/agile-ba-frameworks">
    <summary>Maps BA competencies to agile frameworks (Scrum, SAFe, Disciplined Agile, IIBA Agile Extension) so an analyst can choose a canonical framework, audit adherence against the IIBA seven principles, and generate a framework-fit report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-ac-hallucination-checklist" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/business-analyst/ai-ac-hallucination-checklist">
    <summary>Concrete operating checklist covering ai ac hallucination checklist — the small set of items a practitioner runs every cycle so nothing high-leverage gets skipped.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-acceptance-criteria-generator-reviewer" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-modeling/ai-acceptance-criteria-generator-reviewer">
    <summary>Numeric scoring rubric for ai acceptance criteria generator reviewer that converts qualitative judgment into a comparable 0-100 (or 1-5 weighted) signal usable across cohorts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-assisted-requirements-elicitation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/ai-assisted-requirements-elicitation">
    <summary>BABOK-grounded methodology for BAs to use LLMs to draft user stories and acceptance criteria from elicitation artifacts, with hallucination guards for compliance domains.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-elicitation-prompt-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-modeling/ai-elicitation-prompt-patterns">
    <summary>Prompt-engineering pattern for ai elicitation prompt patterns — reusable prompt skeleton, parameter slots, and validation pass keyed to a concrete deliverable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-enabled-business-analysis" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/business-analyst/ai-enabled-business-analysis">
    <summary>A methodology for integrating AI tools into core BA workflows: requirements extraction from documents using NLP, stakeholder sentiment analysis, process discovery via process mining, and AI-accelerated BA documentation (acceptance criteria, gap analyses, RACI matrices).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-enabled-business-analysis" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/ba-core/ai-enabled-business-analysis">
    <summary>A methodology for integrating AI tools into core BA workflows: requirements extraction from documents using NLP, stakeholder sentiment analysis, process discovery via process mining, and AI-accelerated BA documentation (acceptance criteria, gap analyses, RACI matrices).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-story-truth-checklist" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/business-analyst/ai-story-truth-checklist">
    <summary>A discrete BA checklist that vets AI-generated user stories for plausibility-but-wrong shapes — invented personas, conflated jobs, fabricated metrics, missing edge cases — before they enter the backlog.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-transcript-to-traceable-requirement" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/ai-transcript-to-traceable-requirement">
    <summary>Ai Transcript to Traceable Requirement: codified business-analysis practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/Stakeholder interview: prep + run + capture' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-user-story-decomposition" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ai-user-story-decomposition">
    <summary>Ai User Story Decomposition: codified business-analysis practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/AI-assisted requirements discovery on a new outsource engagement' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ambiguity-contradiction-detector" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ambiguity-contradiction-detector">
    <summary>Ambiguity Contradiction Detector: codified business-analysis practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/AI-assisted requirements discovery on a new outsource engagement' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-governance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/ba-governance">
    <summary>Establishes decision rights, change control, and communication planning for requirements work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-onboarding-week-one-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-onboarding-week-one-template">
    <summary>Week-one onboarding checklist for a BA joining a new project — artefact pull, stakeholder discovery script, glossary intake, tooling setup — collapsed to a single five-day plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-planning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/ba-planning">
    <summary>A six-step framework that defines how BA work will be performed before requirements gathering begins: selecting plan-driven, change-driven, or hybrid approach based on context; building the stakeholder list; scheduling elicitation activities; specifying deliverables; and establishing governance (approver, change process, escalation path).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-planning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/ba-planning">
    <summary>BABOK Knowledge Area 1 defines the five seeding tasks that govern all BA work: plan BA approach, plan stakeholder engagement, plan BA governance, plan BA information management, and identify BA performance improvements.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-requirements-mgmt" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/ba-requirements-mgmt">
    <summary>This methodology covers three sub-disciplines of ongoing requirements stewardship: requirements maintenance (version control, attribute management, quality monitoring, archival strategy), change impact analysis (scope, effort, risk, stakeholder impact, decision support), and requirements architecture (viewpoints, decomposition, dependencies, completeness).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-standup-script-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-standup-script-template">
    <summary>Ba Standup Script Template: codified business-analysis practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/Daily standup: BA-side prep + run' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-strategic-partnership" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/ba-strategic-partnership">
    <summary>Evolve from requirements documentation to strategic partnership.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-strategic-partnership" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/ba-strategic-partnership">
    <summary>A per-artifact stance reviewer that scores requirements documents on six axes (problem_clarity, outcome_orientation, evidence_grounding, enterprise_scope, partner_voice, kill_criterion) and rewrites order-taker language as outcome statements tied to a named OKR.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-to-qa-handoff-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-to-qa-handoff-template">
    <summary>Ba to Qa Handoff Template: codified business-analysis practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/AI-assisted requirements discovery on a new outsource engagement' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-trends-summary" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/ba-trends-summary">
    <summary>Read-only routing index of the six dominant BA industry trends for 2025-2026 (AI-enabled decision making, outcome-driven strategy, responsible innovation, operational resilience, digital trust, sustainability integration).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-trends-summary" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/ba-trends-summary">
    <summary>Router for six BA trends (AI-enabled decisions, outcome strategy, responsible innovation, resilience, digital trust, sustainability) with concrete triggers, paste-ready prompt, checklist, and verification.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="benefit-sustainment-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/benefit-sustainment-checklist">
    <summary>Benefit Sustainment Checklist: codified business-analysis practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/Process improvement initiative (8 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="bid-no-bid-scoring-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/bid-no-bid-scoring-rubric">
    <summary>Bid No Bid Scoring Rubric: codified business-analysis practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/Pre-bid discovery for a fixed-price engagement (P4)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="bpmn-via-ai-then-human-review" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/bpmn-via-ai-then-human-review">
    <summary>Bpmn Via Ai Then Human Review: codified business-analysis practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/FinTech KYC engagement: regulatory-anchored requirements with compliance traceability' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="business-process-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-modeling/business-process-analysis">
    <summary>5-stage analysis cycle for understanding how work actually flows through an organization: identify processes → document current state (with source citations) → analyze (value/time/cost tables) → design future state (diff table, not prose) → validate with stakeholders.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="business-process-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/business-process-analysis">
    <summary>A five-stage methodology for documenting how work actually flows through an organization (current state), classifying each step as value-adding, business-necessary, or non-value-adding, and designing a measurable future state.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="change-request-impact-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/change-request-impact-rubric">
    <summary>Change Request Impact Rubric: codified business-analysis practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/Stakeholder-conflict facilitation and decision rationale capture' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-control-id-mapping" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/client-control-id-mapping">
    <summary>Client Control Id Mapping: codified ba practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/Compliance-Grade Feature Delivery (FinTech / HIPAA / PCI)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="compliance-checklist-by-domain" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/compliance-checklist-by-domain">
    <summary>Domain-indexed compliance checklist (GDPR / HIPAA / PSD2 / SOC2 / WCAG) BAs apply during requirements validation to catch missing non-functional and regulatory items before sign-off.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="compliance-traceability-pack" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/compliance-traceability-pack">
    <summary>Compliance Traceability Pack: codified ba practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/FinTech KYC engagement: regulatory-anchored requirements with compliance traceability' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contractor-brief-template-self-contained" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/contractor-brief-template-self-contained">
    <summary>Contractor Brief Template Self Contained: codified ba practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Subcontractor task brief generation' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cr-impact-memo-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/cr-impact-memo-template">
    <summary>Cr Impact Memo Template: codified ba practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/Change-request impact assessment' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cr-options-matrix-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/cr-options-matrix-template">
    <summary>Cr Options Matrix Template: codified ba practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/Major change-request impact assessment + re-baseline' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-modeling/data-analysis">
    <summary>A structured approach to identifying, defining, and documenting data needs before system development.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/data-analysis">
    <summary>Data Analysis in the BA context identifies what data the business needs, how it is structured, where it comes from and goes, its quality characteristics, and the rules governing it.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-driven-requirements" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/data-driven-requirements">
    <summary>An evidence-based approach to requirements definition that replaces opinion-driven prioritization with data analytics.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-driven-requirements" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/data-driven-requirements">
    <summary>Apply data analytics to requirements engineering.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-modeling/decision-analysis">
    <summary>Structured 6-step process for evaluating options against weighted criteria: define decision → identify options → define and lock criteria with weights → score options with evidence URLs per cell → sensitivity analysis (±20% weight Monte Carlo) → document rationale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/decision-analysis">
    <summary>A six-step structured evaluation framework: define decision, generate options, elicit weights individually then reconcile, route scoring by expertise, run sensitivity analysis, document with traceability.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-options-memo-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/decision-options-memo-template">
    <summary>Standardized "options memo" template BAs use to escalate decisions — option framing, cost-value-risk per option, recommendation, dissent acknowledgement, decision-required-by date.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-rationale-capture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/decision-rationale-capture">
    <summary>Decision Rationale Capture: codified ba practice that turns the recurring 'role-business-analyst/Stakeholder-conflict facilitation and decision rationale capture' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="definition-of-done-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/definition-of-done-library">
    <summary>Definition Of Done Library: codified ba practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Subcontractor task brief generation' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="definition-of-ready-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/definition-of-ready-checklist">
    <summary>Outsource-grade DoR checklist that gates a story before grooming — covering not just engineering readiness but also client-side dependencies (env access, data, regulator/legal/security sign-off).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="demo-recap-email-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/demo-recap-email-template">
    <summary>Demo Recap Email Template delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Client demo prep + run' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: P4 BAs run client demos every sprint; structured recap email cuts scope-creep risk and is a high-frequency</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="discovery-to-delivery-handover-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/discovery-to-delivery-handover-protocol">
    <summary>Discovery To Delivery Handover Protocol delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Pre-bid discovery for a fixed-price engagement (P4)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: In P4 shops, pre-sales BA is often not the delivery BA. Handove</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ecommerce-checkout-ba-pack" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ecommerce-checkout-ba-pack">
    <summary>Payment-method requirements (PCI-DSS scope), VAT rules per jurisdiction, fraud decision tables, cart-abandonment rules, returns flow — the vertical BA pack the corpus is missing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="elicitation-techniques" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/elicitation-techniques">
    <summary>Elicitation is the process of drawing out information from stakeholders about their needs, wants, and constraints — not just asking questions but using structured techniques to uncover stated and unstated requirements.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="elicitation-techniques" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/elicitation-techniques">
    <summary>A deterministic technique-selector for the 10 BABOK v3 elicitation techniques (interview, workshop, focus group, observation, survey, document analysis, prototyping, brainstorming, interface analysis, collaborative game).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="facilitation-anti-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/facilitation-anti-patterns">
    <summary>Catalogue of stakeholder-workshop anti-patterns (sponsor monologue, false consensus, first-speaker anchoring, parking-lot graveyard) with detection cues and live counter-moves so BAs can keep elicitation honest under sponsor pressure.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fintech-kyc-ba-pack" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/fintech-kyc-ba-pack">
    <summary>Fintech Kyc Ba Pack delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'FinTech KYC engagement: regulatory-anchored requirements with compliance traceability' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Brief asks for domain-specific BA packs. Faion's</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fixed-price-risk-loading-model" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/fixed-price-risk-loading-model">
    <summary>Fixed Price Risk Loading Model delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Pre-bid discovery for a fixed-price engagement (P4)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Geek-tier methodology: how to translate risk register into pricing buffe</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fixed-price-vs-tm-cr-pricing-playbook" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/fixed-price-vs-tm-cr-pricing-playbook">
    <summary>Change-request playbook for P4 outsource BAs at the BA/procurement boundary: classify each CR by contract type (fixed-price vs T&amp;M), apply absorb / negotiate-addendum / scope-swap decisions per category, and price the residual risk explicitly so neither side discovers cost surprises at handover.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-proposal-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/freelance-proposal-template">
    <summary>Freelance Proposal Template — testable methodology for requirements, vendor, compliance, contracts. BA acceptance-criteria + requirements-prioritization assume enterprise context. Freelancers need a 1-page proposal pattern that wraps scope, success criteria, price, exclusions, change-request in something signable in a week.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-discovery-call-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ba/freelancer-discovery-call-template">
    <summary>Freelancer Discovery Call Template — testable methodology for requirements, vendor, compliance, contracts. ba/elicitation-techniques is enterprise-flavored. Freelancer discovery is 30 min, one prospect, no formal stakeholder map — needs a stripped template with question bank pre-filled.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="frontline-validation-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/frontline-validation-protocol">
    <summary>A protocol for engaging frontline operators (shadowing, gemba walks, structured listening sessions) during process improvement, distinct from sponsor / SME elicitation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="glossary-management-as-code" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/glossary-management-as-code">
    <summary>Glossary Management As Code — testable methodology for requirements, vendor, compliance, contracts. No methodology for treating the domain glossary as a versioned artefact (YAML / JSON-LD), wired into requirements docs as authoritative references, validated by CI for term drift, exposed to the LLM for grounded retrieval. P4 BAs working across cultures + l...</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="glossary-management-living-doc" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/glossary-management-living-doc">
    <summary>Lifecycle methodology for a project glossary: intake, definition, conflict resolution, deprecation, propagation to dev/QA/support so the same term means the same thing everywhere.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="govtech-foia-ba-pack" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/govtech-foia-ba-pack">
    <summary>FOIA / records-retention requirements, WCAG AA, Section 508 / EN 301 549, procurement constraints — the vertical BA pack public-sector engagements need.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="healthtech-fhir-ba-pack" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ba/healthtech-fhir-ba-pack">
    <summary>FHIR resources (Patient, Encounter, Observation, Condition), HIPAA/GDPR overlap, IRB/consent flows, audit-trail requirements — the HealthTech vertical pack the corpus lacks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hipaa-baa-vendor-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/hipaa-baa-vendor-checklist">
    <summary>Hipaa Baa Vendor Checklist — testable methodology for requirements, vendor, compliance, contracts. Healthcare engagements need a vendor-side checklist that maps BAA obligations to system + process controls. Today faion has no HIPAA-specific guidance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="inbound-intake-qualification" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/inbound-intake-qualification">
    <summary>Inbound Intake Qualification — testable methodology for requirements, vendor, compliance, contracts. An auto-qualifying intake form + triage SOP that filters tire-kickers before a discovery call — current elicitation-techniques is too heavyweight for first contact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="interface-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-modeling/interface-analysis">
    <summary>Identifies, documents, and validates all connection points between a solution and external systems, users, hardware, or communication channels.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="interface-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/interface-analysis">
    <summary>Identifies and documents all boundaries and connections between a solution and external systems, users, hardware, and communication channels, then specifies data elements, protocols, frequency, volume, security, and error handling for each.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="interview-recording-redaction-pipeline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/interview-recording-redaction-pipeline">
    <summary>Interview Recording Redaction Pipeline — testable methodology for requirements, vendor, compliance, contracts. Modern BAs record + transcribe stakeholder calls but lack a documented PII redaction step before content lands in Confluence/Jira.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="knowledge-areas-detail" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/knowledge-areas-detail">
    <summary>Detailed reference for all six BABOK Knowledge Areas (KA-1 through KA-6): per-KA task table, key outputs, linked methodologies, and the canonical workflow sequence for greenfield engagements and change requests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="knowledge-areas-overview" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/knowledge-areas-overview">
    <summary>BABOK organizes BA work into six knowledge areas.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kpi-drift-alarm-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/kpi-drift-alarm-template">
    <summary>Kpi Drift Alarm Template — testable methodology for requirements, vendor, compliance, contracts. After a process-improvement rollout, benefits routinely decay. Need a templated approach to define drift thresholds and alarms (statistical control limits, monitoring frequency, escalation path).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="live-ticket-drafting-shared-screen-pattern" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/live-ticket-drafting-shared-screen-pattern">
    <summary>Live Ticket Drafting Shared Screen Pattern: codified ba practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/JIRA ticket scoping session with client PM' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="methodologies-detail" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/methodologies-detail">
    <summary>A catalog of 12 enterprise BA frameworks used in BABOK Knowledge Areas 1-6: governance, communication planning, elicitation preparation, requirements maintenance, change impact analysis, current state analysis, future state definition, risk analysis, change strategy planning, requirements architecture, solution options analysis, and solution limitation assessment.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="modern-ba-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/modern-ba-framework">
    <summary>A meta-framework for applying the six BABOK Knowledge Areas to modern delivery contexts: agile, AI/ML, cloud-native, platform engineering, and process-mining.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="modern-ba-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/modern-ba-framework">
    <summary>Select one primary BA reference framework (BABOK v3, BA Standard 2025, IREB CPRE, PMI-PBA, BCS Diploma, SAFe BA, Agile Extension to BABOK v2, SWEBOK v4) for an engagement before producing any artifact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="nda-msa-obligation-extractor" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/nda-msa-obligation-extractor">
    <summary>Nda Msa Obligation Extractor: codified ba practice that turns the recurring 'p4-outsource-specialist/Foreign-Client Engagement Bootstrap' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="process-mining-automation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/process-mining-automation">
    <summary>A data-driven methodology for discovering actual process execution from IT event logs and identifying automation candidates using objective scoring criteria.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="process-mining-automation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/process-mining-automation">
    <summary>Covers the fundamentals of process mining: discovery algorithms, event-log prerequisites, adoption gate criteria, and automation candidate assessment.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="process-mining-tool-shortlist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/process-mining-tool-shortlist">
    <summary>Process Mining Tool Shortlist — pinned shortlist for the business analyst: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so process improvement initiative (8 weeks) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="remote-workshop-toolkit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/remote-workshop-toolkit">
    <summary>Operating manual for remote and hybrid BA workshops — pre-reads, Miro/FigJam patterns, breakout protocol, time-zone splitting, on-camera ground rules, async pulses — so requirements work survives the lack of a shared room.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirement-quality-scorecard" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/requirement-quality-scorecard">
    <summary>Requirement Quality Scorecard — pinned scorecard for the business analyst: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so ai-assisted requirements discovery on a new outsource engagement stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-documentation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/requirements-documentation">
    <summary>A structured methodology for documenting requirements across the hierarchy: business requirements (why), stakeholder requirements (user needs), and solution requirements (functional and non-functional).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-documentation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/requirements-documentation">
    <summary>Produce sign-off-ready requirements sets (BRD + URS + SRS/FRD) aligned to a single locked standard (IEEE 830-1998 or ISO/IEC/IEEE 29148:2018).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-lifecycle" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/requirements-lifecycle">
    <summary>A governance framework for managing requirements from initial capture through implementation and verification.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-lifecycle" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/requirements-lifecycle">
    <summary>Requirements exist in multiple versions with unclear ownership, approved requirements change without process, and implementations diverge from documentation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-prioritization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/requirements-prioritization">
    <summary>BABOK-aligned methodology for BA-as-facilitator of multi-stakeholder prioritization.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-prioritization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/requirements-prioritization">
    <summary>All-Must MoSCoW, Confidence=100% RICE, and conference-room Kano produce false confidence in priority decisions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-traceability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/requirements-traceability">
    <summary>Requirements traceability links every artifact (business requirement, stakeholder requirement, solution requirement, design, code, test) to its origin and its downstream dependents, enabling forward coverage analysis (need → test) and backward justification (test → need).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-traceability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/requirements-traceability">
    <summary>Without typed traceability, changed requirements cause unknown downstream impact and auditors cannot verify completeness.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-validation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/requirements-validation">
    <summary>A four-stage process that confirms requirements build the right thing (not that they are built right).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-validation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/requirements-validation">
    <summary>BABOK Task 7.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-creep-email-language-pack" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/scope-creep-email-language-pack">
    <summary>Scope-Creep Email Language Pack: ready-to-paste polite-firm phrasings for the seven recurring scope-creep moments so founders stop reinventing each push-back.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-creep-firewall" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/scope-creep-firewall">
    <summary>Scope-Creep Firewall: an explicit per-engagement change-request methodology tuned for solo operators that converts incoming asks into typed change orders instead of absorbed work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-creep-parking-lot-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/scope-creep-parking-lot-protocol">
    <summary>Live-meeting protocol for absorbing client asks during demos and requirements reviews without litigating scope on the spot — capture in a structured parking lot, classify after the session, route per pre-agreed triage rules.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-drift-early-warning-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/scope-drift-early-warning-metrics">
    <summary>Five quantitative early-warning metrics — CR-volume velocity, AC-rewrite rate, story-split count, requirement-churn ratio, parking-lot age — with thresholds, dashboards, and trigger actions that catch scope drift weeks before a re-baseline becomes unavoidable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solution-assessment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/solution-assessment">
    <summary>A structured evaluation of a solution's ability to meet business need and deliver expected value, covering four assessment types and producing a recommendation at 30/60/90 days post-deployment.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solution-assessment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/solution-assessment">
    <summary>Evaluates a solution's ability to meet the business need and deliver expected value across four assessment types: design, implementation, deployment, and post-implementation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sow-template-with-traced-assumptions" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/sow-template-with-traced-assumptions">
    <summary>SoW template where every scope clause, exclusion, and price assumption traces by ID to a discovery artefact (interview note, doc reference, decision memo), so the BA can defend scope post-signature.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/stakeholder-analysis">
    <summary>A six-step methodology that identifies all parties affected by or influencing a change initiative, maps them on a 2x2 influence-vs-impact matrix (Manage Closely / Keep Satisfied / Keep Informed / Monitor), documents individual needs, concerns, and communication preferences, plans engagement cadence per quadrant, and stores the register as a YAML file in git so diffs become the relationship history.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/stakeholder-analysis">
    <summary>Identify parties affected by change initiatives, classify by influence and impact, document needs, and plan engagement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-conflict-facilitation-script" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/stakeholder-conflict-facilitation-script">
    <summary>Step-by-step facilitation script for a live stakeholder-conflict meeting — agenda, ground rules, position framing, decision rubric, and dissent-capture format — replacing soft-skill folklore with a codified process.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-conflict-mediation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/stakeholder-conflict-mediation">
    <summary>Live mediation playbook for stakeholder conflicts surfacing during requirements review meetings — pause-reframe-isolate-decide-confirm loop with a fallback escalation criterion when the room cannot converge.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/strategy-analysis">
    <summary>Four sequential KA-6 tasks — analyze current state, define future state, assess risks, define change strategy — each with a strict input/output contract.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis-business-need" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/strategy-analysis-business-need">
    <summary>Strategy Analysis starts by defining why change is needed.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis-change-strategy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/strategy-analysis-change-strategy">
    <summary>The change strategy determines how to close the prioritized gaps from the gap analysis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis-current-state" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/strategy-analysis-current-state">
    <summary>Before defining the future state, the BA must systematically inventory where the organization is today across six areas: business processes, organization structure, technology landscape, people and skills, data and information, and external factors.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis-future-state" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/strategy-analysis-future-state">
    <summary>The future state describes the desired outcome after the change: vision, measurable goals, required capabilities, target processes, and target technology.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis-gap-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/strategy-analysis-gap-analysis">
    <summary>Gap analysis identifies what must change by joining current-state measurements with future-state targets for each area.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/strategy-basics">
    <summary>Framework for understanding the existing environment, defining desired future state, assessing risks, and planning change strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-methods" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-core/strategy-methods">
    <summary>Toolkit for weighted multi-criteria scoring of solution options, limitation/defect assessment, and BABOK 50-technique lookup.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="traceability-auto-maintenance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/traceability-auto-maintenance">
    <summary>Keeps the requirements traceability matrix live as the backlog churns — tracker-API ingest, link-drift detection, weekly reconciliation, AI-assisted broken-link repair — so the matrix stays useful past sprint 4.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="traceability-matrix-template-csv" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/traceability-matrix-template-csv">
    <summary>Traceability Matrix Template Csv: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-business-analyst/Traceability matrix weekly refresh'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="traceability-tooling-comparison-jira-ado-polarion" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/traceability-tooling-comparison-jira-ado-polarion">
    <summary>Traceability Tooling Comparison Jira Ado Polarion: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-business-analyst/Requirements traceability across the full project lifecycle'.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="use-case-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-modeling/use-case-modeling">
    <summary>A technique for expressing functional requirements as actor-system interaction sequences.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="use-case-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/use-case-modeling">
    <summary>Use case modeling captures WHO interacts with a system, WHAT they do with it, and WHY — as a sequence of actor-system interactions that yields observable value.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-story-mapping" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/ba-modeling/user-story-mapping">
    <summary>Arranges user stories along two dimensions: horizontal (user journey activities and tasks in narrative verb-phrases) and vertical (priority from essential to nice-to-have).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-story-mapping" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/user-story-mapping">
    <summary>A two-dimensional arrangement of user stories along a horizontal user-journey axis (activities → tasks) and a vertical priority axis (essential → nice-to-have), producing a story map that reveals the complete user experience and enables slice-based release planning.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
