<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="ba" count="118" version="3.0" generated="2026-05-23">
  <description>L2 index of methodologies in the ba domain. The retriever reads this after picking ba from L1 domains.xml. Entries list slug + tier + summary; open the leaf AGENTS.md / content/*.xml for full payload.</description>
  <methodology slug="acceptance-criteria" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/acceptance-criteria">
    <summary>Explicit, testable Given-When-Then or rule-based criteria per user story with mapping to ≥1 test case and explicit edge / negative / non-functional coverage.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="acceptance-criteria-ba-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/acceptance-criteria-ba-modeling">
    <summary>Produces stable, testable acceptance criteria (Given/When/Then or rule-based) with cross-reference IDs (AC-FEATURE-NN) tying spec, test-plan, and CI report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agency-discovery-call-playbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/agency-discovery-call-playbook">
    <summary>Produces a 45-minute discovery-call playbook output: budget range, decision-maker, fit score, and next-step recommendation with verbatim quotes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agile-ba-frameworks" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/agile-ba-frameworks">
    <summary>Map BA competencies onto Scrum ceremonies + SAFe levels (Team / Program / Solution / Portfolio) — produces a `spec` of which BA activity fires when.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agile-ba-frameworks-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/agile-ba-frameworks-ba-core">
    <summary>Picks the right Agile-BA framework (Scrum-BA, SAFe-BA, Disciplined Agile, Dual-Track) for a given team shape + cadence + regulatory bar, with named per-sprint BA activities and IIBA Agile-Extension 7-principle fit-report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-ac-hallucination-checklist" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ai-ac-hallucination-checklist">
    <summary>Produces a per-story checklist that vets AI-generated acceptance criteria for plausible-but-wrong shapes: invented happy paths, missing edge cases, fabricated metrics, contradictory constraints, before ACs enter sprint.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-acceptance-criteria-generator-reviewer" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ai-acceptance-criteria-generator-reviewer">
    <summary>Reviewer rubric that scores LLM-drafted acceptance criteria across happy/negative/edge/perf/a11y dimensions and gates them on evidence + frozen weights.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-assisted-requirements-elicitation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ai-assisted-requirements-elicitation">
    <summary>BABOK-grounded methodology for BAs to draft user stories + AC from elicitation artifacts via LLM with hallucination guards (compliance-domain rules, evidence per claim).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-elicitation-prompt-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ai-elicitation-prompt-patterns">
    <summary>Reusable prompt-skeleton + slot library for BA elicitation tasks (interview prep, follow-up probes, paraphrase-back validation) with structural validation per call.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-enabled-business-analysis" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ai-enabled-business-analysis">
    <summary>Produces a methodology spec for the business-analyst role on AI-assisted workflows: governance, agentic-system specs, AI TRiSM compliance, and the BA-specific checklists feeding requirements / AC / story workflows.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-enabled-business-analysis-ba-core" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ai-enabled-business-analysis-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a methodology spec for AI-assisted BA workflows: requirements extraction via NLP, stakeholder sentiment analysis, process discovery, AI-accelerated BA docs, agentic system specs, with AI TRiSM compliance gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-story-truth-checklist" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ai-story-truth-checklist">
    <summary>Produces a per-story checklist that vets AI-generated user stories for plausible-but-wrong shapes: invented personas, conflated jobs, fabricated metrics, missing edge cases — before they enter the backlog.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-transcript-to-traceable-requirement" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ai-transcript-to-traceable-requirement">
    <summary>Produces a traceable requirement record from a stakeholder-interview transcript: requirement statement, source quote, stakeholder owner, ambiguity flag, and link to the verbatim moment in the transcript.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-user-story-decomposition" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ai-user-story-decomposition">
    <summary>Decomposes vague AI-product asks ('add chatbot', 'make it smart') into INVEST-compliant user stories with explicit AI-vs-deterministic boundary, eval criteria (precision/recall/cost/latency), fallback behavior, and golden-set seed.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ambiguity-contradiction-detector" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ambiguity-contradiction-detector">
    <summary>Scans a requirements doc against a closed checklist (vague quantifiers / undefined terms / contradictory ACs / missing edge-cases / unowned decisions) and emits a per-finding report with severity, evidence quote, and remediation owner.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-governance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-governance">
    <summary>Establishes decision rights (RACI), change-control workflow, and stakeholder communication plan for a requirements stream before requirements work starts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-onboarding-week-one-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-onboarding-week-one-template">
    <summary>Five-day, artefact-driven onboarding plan that gets a BA from "first commit" to "ready to write requirements" — day-level outputs committed to a week-one-pack/ folder.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-planning" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-planning">
    <summary>Pre-elicitation 6-step framework: select plan-driven/change-driven/hybrid, name stakeholders, schedule elicitation, define deliverables, set governance approver + change process + escalation path.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-planning-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-planning-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces five BABOK KA1 task artefacts (T1-T5) with named approvers, cadences, and lifecycles seeding all downstream BA work.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-requirements-mgmt" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-requirements-mgmt">
    <summary>Produces a requirements-management register (change-control, traceability, approval thresholds) governing how requirements evolve through the SDLC.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-standup-script-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-standup-script-template">
    <summary>3-bullet BA-specific standup script (clarifications-needed / AC-ready / blockers) replacing dev-style updates, captured as a typed daily artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-strategic-partnership" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-strategic-partnership">
    <summary>Evolution checklist that lifts a BA from documentation-only execution to strategic-partner stance — quarterly OKR co-ownership, business-case authorship, named sponsor mapping.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-strategic-partnership-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-strategic-partnership-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a stance review naming what BA-as-partner means in this engagement — decision rights, escalation paths, value contracts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-to-qa-handoff-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-to-qa-handoff-template">
    <summary>Sprint-end BA → QA handoff packet (story, AC count, fixture refs, edge cases, named QA owner) replacing ad-hoc verbal/Slack handoffs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-trends-summary" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-trends-summary">
    <summary>Read-only routing index of 2025-2026 BA trends (AI-enabled decisions, outcome-driven strategy, responsible innovation, operational resilience, digital trust, sustainability) mapped to internal methodology.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ba-trends-summary-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ba-trends-summary-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a quarterly checklist mapping current BA-discipline trends (AI-enabled, product-ops, value-stream) to concrete adoption decisions for the engagement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="benefit-sustainment-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/benefit-sustainment-checklist">
    <summary>Post-launch 90-day checklist verifying realized benefits match projected business case (metric, target, measured-value, variance, named owner).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="bid-no-bid-scoring-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/bid-no-bid-scoring-rubric">
    <summary>Pre-bid 0-100 weighted rubric across 6 dimensions (fit / margin / risk / timeline / team / strategic) with go/no-go threshold and named approver.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="bpmn-via-ai-then-human-review" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/bpmn-via-ai-then-human-review">
    <summary>Two-pass BPMN authoring: LLM drafts BPMN 2.0 XML from process transcript, named SME reviews + signs + commits — never AI-only commit.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="business-process-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/business-process-analysis">
    <summary>Five-stage BPA loop (identify → document → analyze → design → validate) under portfolio-agent orchestration that produces auditor-grade as-is/to-be process models with NVA-percentage baselines.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="business-process-analysis-ba-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/business-process-analysis-ba-modeling">
    <summary>5-stage analysis cycle that turns raw process evidence into a current-state map, a value/time/cost analysis, and a future-state diff ready for automation or redesign.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="change-request-impact-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/change-request-impact-rubric">
    <summary>Scores a Change Request by blast radius (requirements / AC / tests / regulatory clauses / dependent stories touched) and routes it to the correct approver (BA / PO / steering committee).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="client-control-id-mapping" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/client-control-id-mapping">
    <summary>Maps client-supplied compliance control IDs (HIPAA, PCI, SOX) to internal requirements + tests so an auditor can trace any control to passing evidence on demand.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="compliance-checklist-by-domain" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/compliance-checklist-by-domain">
    <summary>Domain-indexed compliance checklist (GDPR / HIPAA / PSD2 / SOC2 / WCAG) BAs apply during requirements validation to catch missing non-functional and regulatory items before sign-off.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="compliance-traceability-pack" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/compliance-traceability-pack">
    <summary>Produces a compliance traceability pack for a regulated BA engagement (KYC / FHIR / GDPR / SOC2): requirement-to-regulation map, evidence inventory, control owner table, audit-ready exports.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contractor-brief-template-self-contained" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/contractor-brief-template-self-contained">
    <summary>A self-contained contractor brief — context, deliverable spec, acceptance criteria, evidence checkpoints, rate + payment terms — that a subcontractor can execute without back-and-forth.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cr-impact-memo-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/cr-impact-memo-template">
    <summary>Standardised Change Request impact memo: scope delta, cost delta, schedule delta, risk delta, recommendation — produced by BA, signed by approver, attached to the CR record.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cr-options-matrix-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/cr-options-matrix-template">
    <summary>Major-CR options matrix: ≥2 viable responses (accept / reduce / defer / re-baseline) with cost / value / risk per option, recommendation, and approver routing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/data-analysis">
    <summary>BA-grade data analysis pipeline (purpose → elements → model → quality → rules) producing a data dictionary, six-dimension quality assessment, and validation/derivation/default/constraint/uniqueness rule set linked to requirements.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-analysis-ba-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/data-analysis-ba-modeling">
    <summary>Identify, define, and document data needs before system development — data dictionary, conceptual/logical model, quality dimensions, and business rules as a versioned contract.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-driven-requirements" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/data-driven-requirements">
    <summary>Evidence-based requirements pipeline: every requirement anchored to a business question, quantified baseline metric, measurable success target, and instrumentation plan that closes the loop after launch.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-driven-requirements-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/data-driven-requirements-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a requirements set derived from observed data signals (analytics, telemetry, support tickets) with explicit evidence trails per requirement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/decision-analysis">
    <summary>Six-step structured evaluation (define → generate → weight → score → sensitivity → document) yielding an auditable decision record with traceability to elicited requirements and reconciled stakeholder weights.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-analysis-ba-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/decision-analysis-ba-modeling">
    <summary>6-step decision-matrix process — define decision, options, weighted criteria locked pre-scoring, evidence-per-cell scores, sensitivity Monte Carlo, signed rationale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-options-memo-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/decision-options-memo-template">
    <summary>Standardised options memo BAs use to escalate decisions: option framing, cost-value-risk per option, recommendation, dissent acknowledgement, decision-required-by date.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-rationale-capture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/decision-rationale-capture">
    <summary>Captures decision rationale in a versioned record: decision, alternatives considered, evidence, dissent, named owner — so the program can answer 'why did we do X?' a year later.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="definition-of-done-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/definition-of-done-library">
    <summary>A library of canonical Definitions of Done by deliverable type (story / feature / release / contractor task) so BAs and POs can reuse battle-tested AC patterns instead of reinventing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="definition-of-ready-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/definition-of-ready-checklist">
    <summary>Outsource-grade DoR checklist gating stories before grooming: covers engineering readiness plus client-side dependencies (env access, data, regulator/legal/security sign-off).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="demo-recap-email-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/demo-recap-email-template">
    <summary>Sprint-demo recap email skeleton that pins decisions made, scope deltas, open items, and named follow-ups so the client cannot retroactively reinterpret the demo.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="discovery-to-delivery-handover-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/discovery-to-delivery-handover-protocol">
    <summary>Formal handover protocol from pre-sales discovery BA to delivery BA: artefact bundle, walkthrough script, signed acknowledgement, and post-handover hot-line.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ecommerce-checkout-ba-pack" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/ecommerce-checkout-ba-pack">
    <summary>Reusable BA pack for any e-commerce checkout: user-flow, edge-case catalogue, NFR thresholds, regulatory checklist, payment-provider integration spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="elicitation-techniques" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/elicitation-techniques">
    <summary>Triangulated elicitation pipeline (interview/workshop/observation/survey/prototype/focus-group/brainstorm) producing typed session artifacts and REQ stubs that cite ≥2 distinct techniques per requirement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="elicitation-techniques-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/elicitation-techniques-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a technique-to-session mapping selecting interview / workshop / survey / observation / document-analysis per information type and stakeholder count.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="facilitation-anti-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/facilitation-anti-patterns">
    <summary>Rubric of six facilitation anti-patterns BA workshops must catch in real time, with detection cues + named counter-moves that defuse without humiliation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fintech-kyc-ba-pack" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/fintech-kyc-ba-pack">
    <summary>Produces a domain-specific BA pack for a FinTech KYC engagement: regulation-anchored requirements (FATF / AML / CDD), compliance traceability, identity-evidence inventory, and PEP / sanctions-screen control map.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fixed-price-risk-loading-model" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/fixed-price-risk-loading-model">
    <summary>Produces a fixed-price risk loading model: risk-register-to-buffer translation, contingency tiers, hidden-cost classes, and a defensible bid number with explicit risk-pricing reasoning per category.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fixed-price-vs-tm-cr-pricing-playbook" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/fixed-price-vs-tm-cr-pricing-playbook">
    <summary>Produces a change-request playbook for P4 outsource BAs at the BA/procurement boundary: classify each CR by contract type (fixed-price vs T&amp;M), apply absorb / negotiate-addendum / scope-swap decisions, and price residual risk explicitly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelance-proposal-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/freelance-proposal-template">
    <summary>Solo / freelance proposal skeleton: scope envelope, assumptions, exclusions, payment milestones, change-request rate, anti-scope-creep language.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-discovery-call-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/freelancer-discovery-call-template">
    <summary>Generates a 30-minute freelancer discovery call template with a pre-filled question bank, a go/no-go scorecard, and a one-page proposal seed.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="frontline-validation-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/frontline-validation-protocol">
    <summary>Operator-grounded as-is validation: ≥2 frontline operators per variant via shadowing/gemba/listening-session, closed observation taxonomy, reconcile-not-replace synthesis blocking sponsor-pleasing model edits.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="glossary-management-as-code" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/glossary-management-as-code">
    <summary>Domain glossary kept as versioned YAML next to code: terms, definitions, synonyms, deprecated aliases, owner, last-reviewed date.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="glossary-management-living-doc" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/glossary-management-living-doc">
    <summary>Living-doc glossary lifecycle (intake → definition → conflict resolution → deprecation → propagation) producing a single-source-of-truth term registry with audit-able conflict-resolution records and term-usage hooks across docs/code/tests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="govtech-foia-ba-pack" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/govtech-foia-ba-pack">
    <summary>Produces a public-sector BA pack — FOIA/records-retention schedule, WCAG AA accessibility audit plan, procurement-clause review log, and comment-period buffer — that closes the design-time gaps that bite GovTech launches.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="healthtech-fhir-ba-pack" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/healthtech-fhir-ba-pack">
    <summary>Produces a HealthTech BA pack — FHIR resources (Patient, Encounter, Observation, Condition), HIPAA/GDPR overlap matrix, IRB/consent workflow, and audit-trail spec — so clinical features ship without a post-launch privacy incident.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hipaa-baa-vendor-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/hipaa-baa-vendor-checklist">
    <summary>Pre-engagement HIPAA Business Associate Agreement (BAA) checklist for every PHI-touching vendor: data flow, breach notification, sub-processor map, audit rights.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="inbound-intake-qualification" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/inbound-intake-qualification">
    <summary>Five-question qualification rubric for inbound consulting leads: budget, decider, timeline, scope clarity, fit; emits qualify / reject / discovery-call routing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="interface-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/interface-analysis">
    <summary>Per-interface specification pipeline (catalog → classify → specify → reconcile) producing the integration landscape: data elements, protocol, frequency, volume, security, error-handling per boundary.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="interface-analysis-ba-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/interface-analysis-ba-modeling">
    <summary>Inventory + contract analysis of every connection point (API, file, message bus, UI, hardware) with named owner, data shape, SLA, and error contract per interface.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="interview-recording-redaction-pipeline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/interview-recording-redaction-pipeline">
    <summary>Pipeline configuration for BA interview recordings: transcript generation, automated PII redaction, manual review checkpoint, retention policy, access log.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="knowledge-areas-detail" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/knowledge-areas-detail">
    <summary>Reference catalog for all six BABOK Knowledge Areas (KA-1..KA-6) producing a per-KA task table, canonical workflow sequence, and routing map back into the BA methodology library.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="knowledge-areas-overview" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/knowledge-areas-overview">
    <summary>One-page L1 routing index over BABOK's six Knowledge Areas (KA-1..KA-6) producing a triage decision: which KA owns the current ask + which methodology to load next.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="kpi-drift-alarm-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/kpi-drift-alarm-template">
    <summary>Lightweight KPI drift alarm: baseline window, deviation threshold, alert routing, suppression window, escalation path; runs against any time-series KPI.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="live-ticket-drafting-shared-screen-pattern" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/live-ticket-drafting-shared-screen-pattern">
    <summary>Pattern: BA drafts tickets live on a shared screen during elicitation, contributor signs off in-session, eliminating async clarification rounds.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="methodologies-detail" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/methodologies-detail">
    <summary>Catalog of 12 enterprise BA frameworks across KA-1..KA-6 with per-framework usage notes, deliverable templates, and trigger conditions for choosing each over its peers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="modern-ba-framework" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/modern-ba-framework">
    <summary>Perspective routing wrapper over BABOK that maps the ask to a perspective (agile, AI/ML, cloud-native, platform, BI, BizArch, BPM) and adapts KA tasks + deliverables accordingly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="modern-ba-framework-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/modern-ba-framework-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a framework-selection decision (BABOK / Lean BA / Product-Ops BA / Hybrid) with explicit fit criteria for the engagement context.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="nda-msa-obligation-extractor" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/nda-msa-obligation-extractor">
    <summary>Extracts obligations from NDAs and MSAs into a structured register: obligation, owner, trigger, deadline, evidence pointer, audit-ready.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="process-mining-automation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/process-mining-automation">
    <summary>Event-log driven process discovery + automation candidate scoring (volume × frequency × variance × rule-density) producing a ranked automation pipeline with RPA/IDP/orchestration verdict per candidate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="process-mining-automation-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/process-mining-automation-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces an automation-assessment report ranking discovered process variants by frequency × variance × cost and naming candidate automations with feasibility scores.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="process-mining-tool-shortlist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/process-mining-tool-shortlist">
    <summary>Decision-grade shortlist of process-mining tools (Celonis / UiPath PM / Disco / open-source) with weighted criteria, evidence anchors, and named owner.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="remote-workshop-toolkit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/remote-workshop-toolkit">
    <summary>Run-book for remote/hybrid BA workshops (pre-read floor, four-role breakouts, camera policy, time-zone split, async pulses) producing the workshop run-book + canvas templates + ground rules block.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirement-quality-scorecard" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirement-quality-scorecard">
    <summary>Deterministic scorecard for every requirement before baseline: atomicity, testability, traceability, value, ambiguity, completeness — 0/1/2 per axis with rules.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-documentation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirements-documentation">
    <summary>Hierarchical requirements documentation pipeline (BR → SH → SR with FR/NFR split) producing typed BR/SH/SR records with acceptance criteria, source citations, and version-controlled artifacts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-documentation-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirements-documentation-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces SRS / BRD / user-story documents conforming to a checked schema, with traceability IDs, acceptance criteria, and review state per requirement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-lifecycle" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirements-lifecycle">
    <summary>Per-requirement state machine (Draft → Approved → Implemented → Verified) with change-control gates, multi-role sign-off, and immutable version log producing audit-grade traceability of every status transition.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-lifecycle-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirements-lifecycle-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a lifecycle policy declaring states (draft / reviewed / approved / implemented / verified / retired), transitions, owners, and SLAs per requirement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-prioritization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirements-prioritization">
    <summary>Method-locked prioritization pipeline (MoSCoW / RICE / Kano / WSJF) with stakeholder weights, cost-coupled scoring, and decision-record output blocking method-shopping and HiPPO bias.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-prioritization-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirements-prioritization-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a ranked requirements table using MoSCoW / RICE / WSJF with explicit per-requirement scores, weights, and rationale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-traceability" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirements-traceability">
    <summary>Bidirectional RTM pipeline (forward coverage need→test, backward justification test→need) producing per-requirement trace records over consistent role vocabulary suitable for automated coverage analysis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-traceability-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirements-traceability-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a Requirements Traceability Matrix (RTM) linking each requirement forward to design / code / test / release artefacts and backward to source elicitation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-validation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirements-validation">
    <summary>Four-stage validation pipeline (correctness check → completeness check → technique match → segmented review) producing a sign-off pack with quality scores, dissent log, and explicit gate before baseline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="requirements-validation-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/requirements-validation-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a validation report confirming each requirement meets value-alignment, feasibility, and review criteria before sign-off.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-creep-email-language-pack" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/scope-creep-email-language-pack">
    <summary>Indexed pack of polite-firm push-back phrasings for 7 recurring scope-creep moments; the founder pastes from it instead of wording each reply.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-creep-firewall" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/scope-creep-firewall">
    <summary>Per-engagement intake-and-classify gate that converts every new ask into change-order, no-op, in-scope-clarified, or backlog — never silently absorbed.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-creep-parking-lot-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/scope-creep-parking-lot-protocol">
    <summary>Live-meeting protocol absorbing client asks (verbatim capture, visible canvas, no-live-judgement) with 24h triage SLA + 48h response SLA producing a triaged parking-lot artefact and response log.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-drift-early-warning-metrics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/scope-drift-early-warning-metrics">
    <summary>Five quantitative drift metrics (CR velocity, AC rewrite, story split, churn ratio, parking-lot age) with thresholds + named trigger actions catching scope drift weeks before re-baseline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solution-assessment" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/solution-assessment">
    <summary>Structured 4-type solution evaluation (design / implementation / deployment / post-implementation) with baseline-locked metrics, 30/60/90-day cadence, and accept-with-remediation-or-reject verdict.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solution-assessment-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/solution-assessment-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a post-implementation review comparing delivered solution against baselined requirements, value drivers, and KPIs with explicit gap callouts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sow-template-with-traced-assumptions" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/sow-template-with-traced-assumptions">
    <summary>Fixed-price SoW where every scope clause, exclusion, and pricing assumption carries an [A-NN] ID pointing at the discovery artefact that set it.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/stakeholder-analysis">
    <summary>Identifies and classifies stakeholders by power × interest, defines engagement strategy per quadrant, and produces a named RACI + communications plan that owners actually follow.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-analysis-ba-core" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/stakeholder-analysis-ba-core">
    <summary>Produces a stakeholder register + power/interest map + RACI matrix mapping who decides, contributes, signs off, and must be informed across the engagement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-conflict-facilitation-script" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/stakeholder-conflict-facilitation-script">
    <summary>60-minute structured five-phase meeting (frame → positions → rubric → decide → record dissent) that converts a requirement disagreement into a signed decision-log entry.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-conflict-mediation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/stakeholder-conflict-mediation">
    <summary>In-the-moment five-step loop (pause → reframe → isolate → propose → confirm) for the BA when a stakeholder conflict erupts mid-requirements-review.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/strategy-analysis">
    <summary>Produces a business-need statement + gap analysis + change strategy tying current state to future state with measurable closure plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis-business-need" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/strategy-analysis-business-need">
    <summary>Identifies and quantifies the business need behind an initiative — problem statement, evidence, success metric, and the question 'what if we do nothing?' — before any solutioning starts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis-change-strategy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/strategy-analysis-change-strategy">
    <summary>Bridges current and future state with a sequenced change strategy: solution options, transition states, organisational readiness checks, and a recommended path with cost-risk-time trade-offs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis-current-state" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/strategy-analysis-current-state">
    <summary>Documents the as-is environment — processes, systems, capabilities, pain points, constraints — with named owners and evidence so future-state and gap analysis have a real baseline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis-future-state" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/strategy-analysis-future-state">
    <summary>Defines the target to-be environment — processes, systems, capabilities, measurable outcomes, and design constraints — anchored to the business need and reachable from current state.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-analysis-gap-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/strategy-analysis-gap-analysis">
    <summary>Identifies the delta between current and future state — capability gaps, process gaps, system gaps — with severity and remediation owner, feeding the change strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/strategy-basics">
    <summary>Produces a glossary + decision-tree primer that grounds BA team vocabulary (mission, vision, OKR, SMART, strategy vs tactics) before any strategic artefact is authored.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strategy-methods" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/strategy-methods">
    <summary>Produces a method-selection record (Porter Five Forces / SWOT / Wardley / OST / Blue Ocean) with explicit fit criteria, scoring, and limitation register.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="traceability-auto-maintenance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/traceability-auto-maintenance">
    <summary>Automated traceability-graph maintenance: a daily job that scans tickets, commits, and tests; rebuilds the requirement-to-deliverable graph; emits broken-link alerts to a named owner.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="traceability-matrix-template-csv" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/traceability-matrix-template-csv">
    <summary>Ready-to-use CSV traceability matrix + Jira export script for weekly refresh; closes the gap between BA discovery and engineering execution.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="traceability-tooling-comparison-jira-ado-polarion" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/traceability-tooling-comparison-jira-ado-polarion">
    <summary>Comparison + setup-guide report for traceability tooling (Jira, Azure DevOps, Polarion, Confluence): link types, custom fields, trace gates, gotchas.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="use-case-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/use-case-modeling">
    <summary>Defines actor-goal-scenario use cases — main success path, alternate flows, exception flows, preconditions, postconditions — that downstream teams turn into stories, tests, and screens.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="use-case-modeling-ba-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/use-case-modeling-ba-modeling">
    <summary>Express functional requirements as named-actor → system interaction sequences (main scenario + alternative + exception flows) with preconditions, postconditions, and trigger per use case.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-story-mapping" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/user-story-mapping">
    <summary>Two-axis story map (user journey × release slices) producing a backlog with explicit walking-skeleton, MVP, and release-N horizons so teams ship value rather than features.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-story-mapping-ba-modeling" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ba/user-story-mapping-ba-modeling">
    <summary>Arrange stories along horizontal user-journey activities + vertical priority bands (R1 walking skeleton through R4 nice-to-have) as YAML-in-git for release planning.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
