<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Sprint Capacity From Complexity Tags Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that turn per-task complexity tags into a sprint slot commitment without any time estimate.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every task entering sprint planning MUST carry a `complexity` frontmatter value drawn from the closed set {XS, S, M, L, XL}. Untagged tasks are rejected from the sprint candidate pool, not silently defaulted.</statement>
      <rationale>Silent defaulting (e.g., "assume M") makes capacity math look fine but produces systematic over-commitment because triage rarely upgrades the silent tag. Forcing an explicit tag at intake keeps the signal honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The tag-to-slot mapping is FIXED for the team: XS=1, S=2, M=3, L=5, XL=8. The mapping MUST NOT be re-tuned mid-sprint or per developer. Drift goes into the completion factor, not the table.</statement>
      <rationale>Two moving parts (tag weights AND completion factors) make the model unfalsifiable. Pinning one constant table lets the rolling factor carry all learning — the model stays diagnosable when it misfires.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Per-developer capacity = `anchor_slots * rolling_completion_factor`, where `rolling_completion_factor` is the slot-weighted average of (slots completed / slots committed) over the previous 3 sprints, clamped to the range [0.5, 1.2]. Cold-start (no history) uses a factor of 0.7.</statement>
      <rationale>An unbounded rolling factor amplifies a single bad sprint into a doomed next sprint; clamping inside [0.5, 1.2] absorbs noise. The 0.7 cold-start factor is the historical median observed across faion-network telemetry — biased low because new teams underestimate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Sprint commitment MUST NOT exceed the sum of per-developer capacities. The planner MAY pull in extra XS/S tasks to the "stretch" bucket, but stretch slots do NOT count against the rolling completion factor.</statement>
      <rationale>Hard cap on committed slots stops the "we'll just push a bit more" drift that destroys the completion factor's signal. Segregating a stretch bucket gives slack without polluting the data.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>At sprint close, the team MUST log per-developer (`slots_committed`, `slots_completed`, `incomplete_task_ids`) into the sprint ledger. A sprint without this entry blocks the next planning session — no data, no plan.</statement>
      <rationale>The model is empirical: without per-sprint ledger entries the rolling factor decays into folklore. Making the ledger a planning-gate forces the team to keep the data fresh.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# Developer: alex
# History (3 sprints): committed [10, 12, 11], completed [9, 10, 10]
# rolling_completion_factor = (9+10+10) / (10+12+11) = 29/33 ≈ 0.879
# anchor_slots = 10
# capacity = 10 * 0.879 ≈ 8.8 → round down to 8 slots

candidate_tasks:
  - id: TASK_201, complexity: M  # 3 slots
  - id: TASK_202, complexity: S  # 2 slots
  - id: TASK_203, complexity: M  # 3 slots
# committed = 8 slots — at cap. STOP.

stretch_bucket:
  - id: TASK_210, complexity: XS  # not counted toward factor
      ]]></code>
      <note>Capacity is derived, not negotiated. Stretch is segregated so the rolling factor stays clean.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# Developer: alex — "feels confident this sprint"
# capacity: 15 slots (manual)
# committed: TASK_201 (M), TASK_202 (S), TASK_203 (M), TASK_204 (L), TASK_205 (M)
# total = 3+2+3+5+3 = 16 slots
# rationale: "we'll burn down faster"
      ]]></code>
      <note>Manual capacity override and over-commit — guarantees a missed sprint AND a corrupted factor for the next plan. Both forbidden by the rules.</note>
    </example>

  </section>
</text>
