<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Scope Change vs Scope Creep Detection Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the scope-change-vs-scope-creep-detection methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="signed-baseline-as-ground-truth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Classifier consumes exactly one signed baseline document (spec + AC + out-of-scope list). Multiple candidates or 'latest chat' are forbidden as ground truth.</statement>
      <rationale source="Change-control theory; ITIL configuration management">A classifier consulting shifting context produces shifting decisions; the signed baseline is the project's constitution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="four-outcome-routing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Classifier returns exactly one of: in_scope / legitimate_change / creep / ambiguous. Probabilistic continuous output is forbidden as routing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-theory; HCI clear-states principle">Continuous scores invite negotiation; discrete states are auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-citation-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every classifier decision MUST cite specific baseline lines (spec section, AC ID, out-of-scope clause). Decisions without citations are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="LLM-grounding practice; PMBoK traceability">Citations make the decision defensible to the requester; black-box verdicts collapse trust on the first false-positive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="human-override-with-log" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>PM (or named delegate) can override any classifier decision with a recorded reason. Override is logged; classifier must be retrained or rule-adjusted if override rate exceeds 20%.</statement>
      <rationale source="Human-in-the-loop ML practice">Un-overridable automation is tyranny; constantly overridden automation is decoration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="immutable-audit-trail" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every triage decision is written to an immutable audit log (ticket id, baseline version, citations, verdict, override, timestamp). Queryable at engagement close.</statement>
      <rationale source="Governance practice">Without audit trail, retro-claims of 'you accepted creep' or 'you blocked work' cannot be settled.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Spec / baseline is implicit or non-existent — define it first</item>
      <item>Vendor / data-residency restrictions prevent ticket text being sent to an LLM — use rules-only triage</item>
      <item>Team explicitly accepts 'everything is in-scope' (T&amp;M billing) — nothing to gate</item>
      <item>Ticket volume &lt;5/week — overhead exceeds benefit</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
