<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Scope Detection — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that make the classifier defensible (against the requester) and useful (to the PM). Skipping any one collapses the system into either rubber-stamping or harassment.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-signed-baseline-as-ground-truth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The classifier consumes exactly one signed baseline document (spec + AC + out-of-scope list). Multiple baseline candidates or "the latest discussion in chat" are forbidden as ground truth.</statement>
      <rationale source="change-control theory; ITIL configuration management">A classifier that consults shifting context produces shifting decisions. The signed baseline is the project's constitution; only co-signed amendments change it. Chat threads are inputs to amendment proposals, not ground truth.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-four-outcome-routing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The classifier returns exactly one of four outcomes: `in_scope`, `legitimate_change`, `creep`, `ambiguous`. Probabilistic continuous output is forbidden as the routing decision; if uncertain, return `ambiguous`.</statement>
      <rationale source="decision-theory; HCI principle of clear automation states">Continuous scores invite negotiation ("a 0.6 probability is good enough to ship"). Discrete states are auditable and produce consistent routing. The `ambiguous` state is the safety valve.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-evidence-citation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every classifier decision MUST cite specific baseline lines (spec section, AC ID, out-of-scope clause) that support the verdict. Decisions without citations are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="LLM-grounding practice; PMBOK traceability">Citations make the decision defensible to the requester. The requester can argue with citations; nobody can argue with a black-box "the AI says no". The citations also surface stale baselines (when the citation cannot be found).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-human-override" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The PM (or named delegate) can override any classifier decision with a recorded reason. Override is logged; classifier MUST be retrained or rule-adjusted if override rate exceeds 20% for any class.</statement>
      <rationale source="human-in-the-loop ML; field experience">An automation users cannot override is a tyranny. An automation that is constantly overridden is decoration. The 20% override threshold catches mis-calibration before it loses trust.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-audit-trail" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every triage decision is written to an immutable audit log: ticket id, baseline version, citations, classifier verdict, human override (if any), timestamp. The log MUST be queryable at engagement close for the postmortem.</statement>
      <rationale source="governance and compliance practice">Without an audit trail, retro-claims of "you accepted scope creep" or "you blocked legitimate work" cannot be settled. The log turns scope disputes into data.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Classifier output for a legitimate change">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
ticket_id: PROJ-1042
title: Add SSO via Okta for admin users
verdict: legitimate_change
confidence: 0.86
citations:
  - baseline_v1.2#spec.3.2  -- "Authentication shall use email+password"
  - baseline_v1.2#out-of-scope -- "SSO providers are out of scope for v1"
reasoning: |
  Ticket explicitly adds SSO, which is enumerated in out-of-scope. The request
  is legitimate (security improvement) but exceeds the signed baseline.
recommended_route: change_control
change_impact_draft: docs/changes/PROJ-1042-impact.md (auto-generated)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 (single baseline), r2 (single discrete outcome), r3 (citations), and produces the change-control hand-off material.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Classifier without citations or override">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
ticket_id: PROJ-1042
verdict: creep
confidence: 0.91
reasoning: "AI judges this is creep"
      ]]></code>
      <note>r3 violation (no citations). The requester cannot argue with the verdict; trust collapses on the first false-positive.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
