<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="vui-iot-integration Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the vui-iot-integration methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="logical-grouping-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Devices MUST be grouped into rooms, zones, and scenes with stable IDs. Per-device-only naming is forbidden for households with ≥5 devices.</statement>
      <rationale source="Matter spec; Home Assistant docs">Per-device naming forces users to memorize unique names; grouping leverages spatial reasoning.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="scene-and-routine-names" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Scenes and routines MUST have intuitive natural-language names (e.g., 'movie night', 'good morning'). Acronyms and IDs are forbidden as primary names.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HomeKit guidelines; Google Home guidelines">Voice users invoke by natural names; IDs and acronyms fail discoverability.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="partial-failure-feedback" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Multi-device commands MUST report per-device outcomes explicitly when any device fails ('Lights on; thermostat unreachable'). Silent partial failures are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Matter spec — partial-failure feedback">Silent failures hide broken state; users assume command succeeded and act on false belief.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="undo-support" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every voice routine MUST support 'undo' or 'reverse last action' for at least the previous command. Permanent state changes without undo are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HomeKit guidelines">Voice mistakes (wrong room, wrong device) need a single-command recovery path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="noise-robust-testing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Routines MUST be tested in noisy conditions (kitchen, TV, multiple speakers). Pure-quiet testing is forbidden as evidence.</statement>
      <rationale source="Voicebot.ai best practices">Smart-home contexts are noisy; quiet-only testing inflates real accuracy.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
