<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="vui-iot-integration Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for vui-iot-integration as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM-generated utterance lists drift to single phrasing; developers accept the first output without forcing variants.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Users speak in natural, varied language. Over-training on a single utterance produces cascading NLU failures.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents skip undo and partial-failure paths in the output, treating them as optional.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Voice-initiated multi-device changes are hard to reverse; undo and explicit partial-failure reporting are essential for user trust.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Vendor capability matrices are cached in the prompt or RAG without version pinning; matrices change between quarters.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Matter cluster IDs, Alexa capability interfaces, and Google Home traits evolve. Agents hallucinate unsupported utterances if the matrix is stale.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents auto-deploy a routine that touches locks, alarms, garage, or thermostat extremes without human approval.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Voice-initiated safety-critical actions need human verification to prevent accidents or unauthorized control.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Voice transcripts in vendor cloud are treated as ephemeral; agents echo full transcripts in logs or prompts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Transcripts are PII persisting on vendor cloud. Echoing them violates privacy and creates regulatory exposure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents hallucinate Matter cluster IDs without grounding via chip-tool discovery.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Matter cluster IDs are numeric and not intuitive. LLMs freely invent them; use chip-tool to ground truth.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
