<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-nielsen-five" title="The 5 Nielsen heuristics chosen for per-feature audit">
  <summary>Five of the ten Nielsen heuristics are concretely checkable per feature. The other five stay in education material because checking all 10 per feature is theatre.</summary>

  <section title="The five">
    <list>
      <item>N1 Visibility of system status — "the user always knows what the system is doing right now".</item>
      <item>N3 User control &amp; freedom — "the user can undo / cancel / exit without consequence".</item>
      <item>N4 Consistency &amp; standards — "the same word means the same thing across the feature and the rest of the app".</item>
      <item>N5 Error prevention — "the design makes the bad input hard to enter, not just hard to submit".</item>
      <item>N6 Recognition over recall — "the user does not have to remember information from one step to the next".</item>
    </list>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The Nielsen audit section in ui-ux-design.md MUST contain exactly these five rows. Adding rows for N2/N7/N8/N9/N10 is forbidden in this per-feature template.</statement>
      <rationale>Bounded checklists get done; long checklists get faked. Five is the empirical sweet spot.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Why these five (not the other five)">
    <p>N1, N3, N5, N6 catch the most common per-feature regressions (silent operations, no-cancel modals, validate-on-submit, wizards without breadcrumb context). N4 catches the cross-feature drift that explodes after enough small changes. The remaining five (match real world, error recovery, flexibility, aesthetic, help docs) are either site-wide concerns or rarely actionable per feature.</p>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Auditing all 10 per feature.</description>
    <reason>The author runs out of attention by N6 and the last four become "ok" without inspection. Five rows that are taken seriously beat ten rows that are not.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/03-norman-principles.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
