<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-template-sections" title="Required sections in ui-ux-design.md">
  <summary>Six sections in fixed order. The fillable template is provided in templates/ui-ux-design.md.tmpl.</summary>

  <section title="Section list">
    <list>
      <item>Intent — what the user is trying to accomplish, in one sentence.</item>
      <item>Layout — coarse description of element placement; a screenshot or wireframe is allowed but not required.</item>
      <item>States — table with one row per state: empty, loading, error, success, disabled. Each row describes the visible affordance.</item>
      <item>Nielsen audit — five rows (N1, N3, N4, N5, N6) per content/02-nielsen-five.xml. Each row: heuristic, finding, fix-or-noted-OK.</item>
      <item>Norman audit — two rows (affordance, feedback) per content/03-norman-principles.xml.</item>
      <item>Copy &amp; microcopy — exact strings for button labels, error messages, empty-state text, success messages.</item>
    </list>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The six sections MUST appear in this order. Empty sections are filled with "n/a" and a reason, never omitted.</statement>
      <rationale>Stable order + explicit n/a + reason makes the artefact diff-able across features.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="The States table is load-bearing">
    <p>Empty / loading / error / disabled are the states most often left unspecified, and they generate ~80% of post-launch UI bug reports. The table forces the author to name each one before code lands.</p>
    <antipattern>
      <description>States section with only "success" filled in.</description>
      <reason>The other four states will be improvised in code, inconsistently across pages.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/ui-ux-design.md.tmpl">Fillable Markdown template with the six sections and audit-row stubs.</reference>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-nielsen-five.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-norman-principles.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
