<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-risk-process" title="Risk Register — Six-Step Process">
  <summary>How to build and maintain a risk register: identify risks by category, analyze probability and impact, score on a 5x5 matrix, plan responses (threat and opportunity strategies), assign owners, and run weekly reviews.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Identify Risks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify both threats (negative risks) and opportunities (positive risks) across all four categories: Technical, External, Organizational, and Project Management.</statement>
      <rationale>Registers that capture only threats miss the opportunity to exploit or enhance favorable events. Systematic category coverage prevents blind spots from informal brainstorming.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Identification techniques: team brainstorming, expert interviews, checklist review, historical project analysis, SWOT analysis.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Analyze Probability and Impact">
    <p>Probability scale (1=Very Low to 5=Very High): VL &lt; 10%, L 10-30%, M 30-50%, H 50-70%, VH &gt; 70%.</p>
    <p>Impact scale (1=Very Low to 5=Very High): VL &lt; 5% budget/schedule, L 5-10%, M 10-20%, H 20-40%, VH &gt; 40% or project failure.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Calculate Risk Score">
    <rule>
      <statement>Compute Risk Score = Probability x Impact (1–25); prioritize as High (15–25), Medium (8–14), Low (1–7). Require per-axis rationale for every score to prevent clustering at Medium-Medium.</statement>
      <rationale>Without rationale, analysts default to Medium-Medium, compressing information and hiding true high-priority risks. Per-axis justification forces calibration and distributes scores.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every risk with a measurable trigger condition; without a trigger, the team cannot detect when the risk is activating.</statement>
      <rationale>Trigger-less risks stay academic. A trigger converts risk monitoring from a scheduled exercise to an event-driven alert.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Plan Responses">
    <p>For threats: Avoid (eliminate), Transfer (insurance/outsource), Mitigate (reduce P or I), Accept (contingency).</p>
    <p>For opportunities: Exploit (ensure it occurs), Share (partner), Enhance (increase probability), Accept (take benefit if it occurs).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every risk with score 8 or above must have a named strategy and a specific response action; "Accept" without a contingency is not a valid response for high-score risks.</statement>
      <rationale>The all-accept antipattern gives false comfort. High-score risks without funded contingency will hit the budget as unplanned crisis costs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Assign Owners">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign exactly one named owner per risk; "the team" is not an owner.</statement>
      <rationale>Shared ownership is no ownership. One owner is accountable for monitoring triggers, executing response if needed, and updating status.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Monitor and Update Weekly">
    <rule>
      <statement>Review risks weekly; add new entries, update scores as situation changes, and close risks with explicit outcome (materialized / passed / merged). Never delete a row.</statement>
      <rationale>Deletion destroys audit history and contingency calculation integrity. Closure with outcome preserves the record for lessons-learned and future project calibration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Weekly review agenda: new risks? scores changed? triggers activated? responses in progress? risks to close? top-5 still accurate?</p>
    <reference path="templates/risk-audit.py">Script that flags stale, high-priority, and no-owner risks from a CSV register.</reference>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/risk-register.md">Full register table template.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/risk-card.md">Individual risk card template.</reference>
</text>
