<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples-antipatterns" title="Risk Register — Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Worked examples for software project threats and opportunity risks, plus the five most common risk-register antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Examples — Threats">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Software project risk register (5 entries): Key developer leaves (M/H, score 12, Mitigate: document code + cross-train); Third-party API deprecated (L/VH, score 10, Accept: build abstraction layer + monitor); Scope creep (H/M, score 12, Avoid: change control process); Performance issues (M/M, score 9, Mitigate: early load testing); Budget cut (L/H, score 8, Accept: identify optional features). Each entry has an owner and a trigger condition.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Examples — Opportunities">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Opportunity risks tracked alongside threats: Early delivery possible (M/H, score 12, Enhance: fast-track critical path); Partnership offer (L/VH, score 10, Exploit: prioritize integration); Positive press coverage (M/M, score 9, Share: prepare press kit). Reviewing these at every weekly meeting doubles the register's value.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>One-time exercise — risks identified at kickoff, register never updated.</description>
      <reason>Project context evolves weekly; a static register reflects the world as it was, not as it is. Stale scores give false comfort and miss emerging threats entirely.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No owners — risks listed without a named accountable person.</description>
      <reason>Unowned risks are nobody's problem. When they activate, the team scrambles to find who should respond, costing days in crisis mode before a response is even designed.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>All-Accept strategy — every high-score risk marked "Accept" with no contingency funded.</description>
      <reason>Accept without contingency is wishful thinking. High-score risks that materialize hit the project budget as emergency overruns with no pre-approved response plan.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Missing positive risks — register covers only threats.</description>
      <reason>Opportunities that pass unnoticed are value left on the table. A threat-only register uses 50% of the risk management value.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Too vague — "Something might go wrong with the vendor" is not an actionable risk.</description>
      <reason>Vague descriptions prevent probability/impact analysis and make response planning impossible. Every risk needs a specific "what might happen and why" framing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
