<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="risk-register Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for risk-register as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>One-time exercise — risks identified at kickoff, register never updated.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Project context evolves weekly; a static register reflects the world as it was, not as it is. Stale scores give false comfort and miss emerging threats entirely.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>No owners — risks listed without a named accountable person.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unowned risks are nobody's problem. When they activate, the team scrambles to find who should respond, costing days in crisis mode before a response is even designed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>All-Accept strategy — every high-score risk marked "Accept" with no contingency funded.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Accept without contingency is wishful thinking. High-score risks that materialize hit the project budget as emergency overruns with no pre-approved response plan.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Missing positive risks — register covers only threats.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Opportunities that pass unnoticed are value left on the table. A threat-only register uses 50% of the risk management value.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Too vague — "Something might go wrong with the vendor" is not an actionable risk.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Vague descriptions prevent probability/impact analysis and make response planning impossible. Every risk needs a specific "what might happen and why" framing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
