<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-procedure" title="Regulatory Compliance 2026 Procedure" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6-step procedure to produce a defensible 2026 accessibility compliance report from surface inventory to published statement.</summary>

  <section title="Procedure">

    <step n="1" name="inventory-surfaces">
      <input>Product catalog, GTM market list, app-store metadata.</input>
      <action>List every public surface (web URLs, native bundle IDs, kiosk firmware, e-book ISBNs). For each, mark active jurisdictions (US, EU, ON, US-FED, UK, AU, JP). Output: `surfaces[]` array.</action>
      <output>Surface inventory with jurisdictions.</output>
      <decision-gate>If &lt;1 surface, this methodology does not apply — stop.</decision-gate>
    </step>

    <step n="2" name="map-to-regulations">
      <input>Surface inventory + jurisdiction list.</input>
      <action>For each (surface, jurisdiction) pair, attach the binding regulation (ADA Title II / EAA / AODA / Section-508 / UK-EQA / AU-DDA), required WCAG version + level, and effective deadline. Output: `regulations[]` array.</action>
      <output>Regulation matrix.</output>
      <decision-gate>If a surface has no regulation row in any active jurisdiction, note "non-public-accommodation" justification; never silently omit.</decision-gate>
    </step>

    <step n="3" name="run-conformance-testing">
      <input>Regulation matrix + current build.</input>
      <action>Run axe / pa11y / Lighthouse on every changed page (automated). Run manual keyboard + screen-reader sweep on critical journeys. Schedule at-least-one AT-user session per major release. Record results.</action>
      <output>Testing log (automated + manual + AT-user).</output>
      <decision-gate>If AT-user session missing this release cycle, downgrade conformance claim from "conformant" to "partial conformance with named gaps".</decision-gate>
    </step>

    <step n="4" name="draft-statement">
      <input>Testing log + regulation matrix.</input>
      <action>Fill `templates/accessibility-statement.md`: WCAG version + level (use 2.2 AA as design baseline), methodology checkboxes (automated / manual / at_user), feedback channels (≥1 email + 1 voice or form), remediation commitment timeline, last-updated date.</action>
      <output>Draft statement (Markdown).</output>
    </step>

    <step n="5" name="legal-review">
      <input>Draft statement + testing log + regulation matrix.</input>
      <action>Route to counsel. Counsel checks for over-statement, missing jurisdictions, overlay-mention, and remediation-commitment realism. Sign-off recorded against `report_date`.</action>
      <output>Statement approved for publication.</output>
      <decision-gate>If counsel refuses sign-off, return to step 3 or 4 and tighten the claim.</decision-gate>
    </step>

    <step n="6" name="publish-and-schedule-review">
      <input>Approved statement + remediation backlog.</input>
      <action>Publish to public URL. Run `scripts/validate-regulatory-compliance-2026.py` against the JSON report — must exit 0. Schedule next review (quarterly + per major release). File backlog items in tracker with WCAG SC IDs.</action>
      <output>Statement live; backlog tracked; calendar scheduled.</output>
    </step>

  </section>
</text>
