<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Recognition vs. Recall — Principles">
  <summary>Core cognitive distinction between recognition and recall, and four design principles that reduce memory load.</summary>

  <section title="Recognition vs. Recall">
    <p>Recognition: user sees options and chooses. Recall: user must remember without a cue. Recognition is always faster, more accurate, and more accessible across user populations.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer recognition-based UI patterns over recall-based ones whenever design permits.</statement>
      <rationale>Recall requires active memory retrieval, which fails under time pressure, cognitive load, infrequent use, and stress — all common in real product contexts. Recognition merely requires matching a visible stimulus to memory, which is far more reliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Menu selection (recognition) vs. command-line with syntax recall. Autocomplete (recognition) vs. blank search field (recall).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Four Design Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Make options visible: show common actions, do not hide them in menus or right-click contexts.</statement>
      <rationale>Hidden options require users to remember they exist and know where to look — double recall burden.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide context: keep relevant information visible across multi-step tasks.</statement>
      <rationale>When context disappears between steps, users must remember prior selections — a cross-screen recall burden that causes errors and backtracking.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use recognition aids: icons paired with text labels, thumbnails for files, previews for documents.</statement>
      <rationale>Icons alone require users to memorize icon meanings. Pairing with text labels converts recall to recognition at minimal space cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Support retrieval: implement recent items, search with autocomplete, and frequently-used-item lists.</statement>
      <rationale>Recent items surface what the user has already interacted with — zero recall required. Autocomplete shows candidates matching partial input, reducing the recall burden to a fragment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility Connection">
    <p>Recognition-based design disproportionately benefits: users with cognitive disabilities, older users, occasional users, users under stress or time pressure, and mobile users with divided attention. It is not a nice-to-have — it is a baseline accessibility requirement.</p>
  </section>
</text>
