<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-patterns" title="Recognition Aid Implementation Patterns">
  <summary>Concrete implementation patterns for reducing recall burden: visible options, contextual information, autocomplete, and recent items.</summary>

  <section title="Visible Options">
    <rule>
      <statement>Expose primary actions in a visible toolbar or navigation; reserve menus for secondary and infrequent actions.</statement>
      <rationale>Hidden menus require users to remember the menu exists and what it contains — double recall burden. Visible toolbars convert both to recognition.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Visible tabs for main sections of an app rather than a hamburger menu that hides all navigation behind a tap.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>All actions behind right-click context menu — users must remember right-click exists and recall what actions are available.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Contextual Information">
    <rule>
      <statement>In multi-step flows, show a persistent summary of all prior selections visible alongside the current step.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a context panel, users must remember what they entered on previous screens. A sidebar showing prior selections eliminates the most common cross-screen recall failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Checkout step 3 shows: Selected items, shipping address entered on step 1, and payment method selected on step 2 — all visible in a sidebar summary.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Labels and Tooltips">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every icon with a text label; use tooltips only in space-constrained areas where label cannot be shown inline.</statement>
      <rationale>Icon-only interfaces require users to memorize icon meanings. Text labels eliminate this entirely. Tooltips are acceptable fallback when screen space prevents inline labels.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep tooltips at 7 words or fewer; show them on hover with a 300ms delay to avoid noise.</statement>
      <rationale>Long tooltips that appear instantly become visual noise that users learn to ignore. Short, delayed tooltips are read when needed and dismissed otherwise.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Autocomplete and Recent Items">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add autocomplete to every search and command input; show at least 5 recent items immediately on focus.</statement>
      <rationale>Autocomplete is the single highest-ROI recognition aid. Search with suggestions converts blank-field recall to candidate recognition. Recent items list surfaces past actions without requiring memory retrieval.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Recent items must update immediately after use; a stale list is worse than no list.</statement>
      <rationale>A stale list teaches users the feature is unreliable, causing them to stop using it. Immediate update maintains trust and utility.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Progressive Disclosure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show essential options always; reveal advanced options on demand via expansion rather than hiding by default in menus users must discover.</statement>
      <rationale>Progressive disclosure reduces visual noise while keeping options discoverable through visible "More options" or "Advanced" controls — not hidden menus users must know to look for.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
