<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Recognition Over Recall Examples and Audit Patterns">
  <summary>Real-world good and bad examples, common mistakes, and agentic audit workflow with gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Good Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Google Search: recent searches shown on focus, autocomplete suggestions, "Did you mean" corrections, related searches. All are recognition aids that eliminate recall of prior queries.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>VS Code Command Palette (Ctrl+P): fuzzy search for commands, recent files shown, icons and labels in menus. Turns command recall into command recognition.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Spotify: album art thumbnails, recently played prominent on home screen, visual playlists. Users recognize what they want to play; they do not recall album names.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Bad Examples">
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"Enter product code: ___" — user must recall an arbitrary alphanumeric code. Better: product picker with images and names. Recognition replaces recall entirely.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Multi-step checkout where prior address entered on step 1 is not visible on step 3. User must recall what they typed. Better: summary sidebar showing all prior selections.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Toolbar with 12 icons and no labels. Users must memorize what each icon means. Better: icon + text label for all actions, tooltip fallback for space-constrained areas.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Icon-only toolbars where users must memorize icon meanings.</description>
      <reason>Icons without labels require recall of meaning. Even "universal" icons (save floppy disk, hamburger menu) are not universally recognized by all user populations.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Multi-step forms with no progress summary of prior selections.</description>
      <reason>Cross-screen recall burden is the most common form of heuristic #6 violation and is invisible in static design reviews — requires prototype testing to detect.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Audit Workflow">
    <p>Agent receives UI screen descriptions, wireframe annotations, or component specs. Applies recognition audit template per screen: identifies recall demands, hidden options, icon-only elements, missing autocomplete, and cross-screen context failures. Outputs structured findings with severity and recognition alternative per item.</p>
    <reference path="templates/recognition-audit.md">Recognition audit template for systematic per-screen review</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-audit.txt">LLM prompt for auditing a screen against this heuristic</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent flags all icon-only elements including universally understood icons (magnifying glass for search, X for close).</description>
      <reason>Provide agent a list of safe icon exceptions before running audit. Magnifying glass and X are recognized across all user populations and do not need labels.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent audits static wireframes and misses cross-screen recall failures.</description>
      <reason>Information visible on screen A but gone on screen B is a dynamic property. Note this limitation explicitly in audit output; require prototype testing to validate cross-screen context.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
