<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="recognition-over-recall Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for recognition-over-recall as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Icon-only toolbars where users must memorize icon meanings.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Icons without labels require recall of meaning. Even "universal" icons (save floppy disk, hamburger menu) are not universally recognized by all user populations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Multi-step forms with no progress summary of prior selections.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cross-screen recall burden is the most common form of heuristic #6 violation and is invisible in static design reviews — requires prototype testing to detect.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent flags all icon-only elements including universally understood icons (magnifying glass for search, X for close).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Provide agent a list of safe icon exceptions before running audit. Magnifying glass and X are recognized across all user populations and do not need labels.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent audits static wireframes and misses cross-screen recall failures.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Information visible on screen A but gone on screen B is a dynamic property. Note this limitation explicitly in audit output; require prototype testing to validate cross-screen context.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
