<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-taxonomy-and-naming" title="Token Taxonomy and Naming Convention">
  <summary>Three-layer token taxonomy and naming convention rules that keep design systems lean and maintainable.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Layer Taxonomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use exactly three layers — primitives, semantic, component — never four or more.</statement>
      <rationale>A fourth layer (e.g., sub-component variants) creates indirection depth that makes runtime debugging and visual diff verification impractical.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add component tokens only when a single component needs a documented exception to a semantic token; justify every component token in its `$description`.</statement>
      <rationale>Unjustified component tokens frequently duplicate semantic tokens and double the rename surface area on every rebrand.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Primitives — raw values: `color.blue.500 = #3B82F6`, `spacing.4 = 16px`.</item>
      <item>Semantic — purpose: `color.surface.primary`, `color.text.muted`, `spacing.component.button`.</item>
      <item>Component — exceptions only: `button.primary.bg`, `input.border.focus`.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Naming Convention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name tokens using `{category}.{property}.{variant}.{state}` dot-path notation; describe purpose, never appearance.</statement>
      <rationale>Appearance-based names (`blue-500`) encode the current design decision into every consumer; purpose-based names (`color.action.primary`) survive rebranding without consumer changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Purpose-describing token names</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
color.surface.primary
color.surface.primary.hover
color.text.muted
spacing.component.button
typography.heading.xl
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Appearance-encoding token names</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
blue-1
blue-500-hover
gray-light
button-16px
xl-text
]]></code>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit dot-path depth to 4 segments maximum (`category.property.variant.state`).</statement>
      <rationale>Deeper paths indicate a missing taxonomy layer or Cartesian explosion of variants; LLMs generate full state-variant grids nobody uses if not bounded.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Lean-First Principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a new token only when no existing semantic token covers the case; run a duplicate-value detector in CI.</statement>
      <rationale>Tokens with identical values under different names are a smell: either the existing token should be reused, or one of them is redundant.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a `$description` to every semantic token explaining why it exists, not what value it holds.</statement>
      <rationale>Future maintainers and LLMs read descriptions to decide whether to reuse or create a token; missing descriptions produce duplication.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/token-name-lint.py">Linter that flags names not matching convention and tokens with duplicate values.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
