<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-gotchas" title="Agent Pitfalls and Rename Guidance">
  <summary>Common agent-generated token organization mistakes, aliasing depth limits, and rename codemod guidance.</summary>

  <section title="Agent Pitfalls">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM generates full Cartesian product of state × variant tokens (`color.brand.primary.light.hover.disabled`).</description>
      <reason>Symmetric token trees balloon to hundreds of tokens; cap depth and require justification per token in the prompt. Most generated tokens are never referenced.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent suggests component tokens that duplicate existing semantic tokens.</description>
      <reason>Duplicate component tokens double the rename surface area and confuse consumers about which to use; require an explicit justification for each component token.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent prunes "unused" tokens automatically via static analysis.</description>
      <reason>Static analysis misses theming, runtime, per-tenant, and Storybook MDX references; auto-pruning causes silent regressions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent invents a naming convention name ("Carbon style", "MUI v6 style") without grounding in the project's actual convention.</description>
      <reason>Pin the convention regex in every agent prompt; confidently invented convention names produce non-compliant output.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Aliasing Depth">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce a maximum aliasing depth of 3 levels; validate in CI.</statement>
      <rationale>Aliasing depth beyond 3 makes runtime debugging require tracing through multiple files; visual diffs become the only verification method.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Rename Codemods">
    <rule>
      <statement>When renaming tokens, include MDX, Storybook configs, and JSON data files in the scan — not just TypeScript/JS/CSS.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents default to code-file globs and miss Storybook MDX stories, documentation JSON, and Figma plugin config files where token names appear as strings.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every rename with a Storybook visual diff to catch unreferenced usages that the text scan missed.</statement>
      <rationale>A renamed token with a surviving reference at the visual level indicates a scan gap; the visual diff catches what grep-based tools miss.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
