<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-analytics-framework" title="Product Analytics Framework and Implementation">
  <summary>Defines analytics maturity levels, AARRR metric categories, the 5-step implementation process, and dashboard type assignments per audience.</summary>

  <section title="Analytics Maturity Levels">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start at Level 2 (user segmentation) minimum; Level 1 (page views, signups) produces only vanity metrics that move with marketing spend.</statement>
      <rationale>Level 1 metrics answer "did something happen?" but not "who did it and why?"; product decisions require at minimum user-level segmentation to be actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Maturity levels: Level 1 Basic (what happened — page views, signups); Level 2 Intermediate (who did what — user segmentation); Level 3 Advanced (why and what if — funnels, cohorts); Level 4 Predictive (what will happen — ML, forecasting). Start at Level 2.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="AARRR Metric Categories">
    <p>Acquisition: visitors, signups, sources, conversion rates, cost per acquisition. Activation: onboarding completion, time to value, first key action. Engagement: DAU/WAU/MAU, session frequency, feature usage. Retention: D1/D7/D30 retention, cohort retention curves, churn rate. Revenue: MRR, ARPU, LTV, upgrade/downgrade rates, revenue per cohort.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="5-Step Implementation Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — Define key questions before touching instrumentation: what decisions will this data inform, what behavior are we trying to understand, and what is the minimum we need to track?</statement>
      <rationale>"Track everything" creates a data warehouse full of events nobody queries; decision-first tracking ensures every event has a named decision it will inform.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Create a tracking plan for each event: event name (standardized object_action format), trigger condition, properties captured, and named owner.</statement>
      <rationale>Events without named owners are unowned; "Product team" owns everything means nobody owns anything, and naming drift creates variant event names for the same action.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Use server-side tracking for critical events (payments, auth); client-side for UX insights. Encode this rule in the tracking plan per event, not in tribal memory.</statement>
      <rationale>Client-side tracking is unreliable for critical events (ad blockers, JS errors, offline); server-side tracking ensures payment and auth events are never lost. Hybrid tracking without per-event side assignment causes double-counting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Build dashboards by audience: exec summary (health at a glance), product health (core metrics for product team), feature deep-dive (per-feature owner), experiment (test results).</statement>
      <rationale>One dashboard for all audiences produces a dashboard nobody uses; audience-specific dashboards optimize for the decision the reader needs to make.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5 — Establish review rituals: daily glance at key metrics, weekly dashboard review with anomaly notes, monthly deep-dive, quarterly goal vs. actual planning.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a review cadence, dashboards accumulate without driving decisions — they become the "graveyard" the anti-patterns section documents.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Onboarding analysis finding a 62% drop-off at step 3 (connect data source) leads to a specific intervention: add sample data option to skip integration. This is a decision-first analytics outcome.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Tracking 40 events but having no written record of which decision each event informs. Result: dashboards nobody opens, no connection between metrics and product decisions.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/tracking-plan.md">Tracking plan template with user properties, events, and conversion events</reference>
</text>
