<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-analytics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-analytics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent inventing event names (e.g., user_signed_up) when the codebase uses signup_completed.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always pass the canonical event taxonomy in the agent system prompt and reject novel event names; hallucinated event names create schema gaps that are invisible until a dashboard shows zero data.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent SQL joining events to users to sessions without DISTINCT, producing triple-counted metrics.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Naive joins fanout rows; require count(distinct user_id) and gate queries via sqlfluff rules, or use a metrics layer (dbt-metrics, Cube) so agents cannot write raw fanout SQL.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent providing a single confident cause when asked "why did retention drop?"</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Funnels and cohorts answer "what" and "where," never "why"; force the agent to list 3+ candidate causes and the disambiguating query, never a single explanation without a cited experiment.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent comparing partial-cohort retention to mature-cohort retention.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents will compare D30 retention of a 6-week-old cohort to D7 of a 1-week-old one; readers misread it as a retention regression. Pin window length explicitly in every prompt and chart.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent using Z-score against last 7 days for anomaly detection.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Z-score against last 7 days flags every product launch as an anomaly. Use a 4-week trailing baseline with seasonal adjustment.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent pasting 50k rows of raw event tables into context.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Do not paste 50k rows into context. Pre-aggregate to ≤200 rows or use tool-use (function calling) to query the warehouse directly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent including raw event payloads (with emails, IPs, free-text) in LLM prompts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Product events leak PII; always aggregate or hash before any LLM call; run a password-scrubber-agent pass on any data before it enters a prompt context.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Engineer shipping new events without updating tracking-plan.md.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The cron drift-linter is the only sustainable fix; agents themselves drift if not constrained to the canonical taxonomy in the system prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent emitting chart specs against tables that do not exist.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pass the schema (or, better, a metrics-layer manifest) in the prompt and reject any chart referencing an unknown column.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>A/B readouts written by agents drop confidence intervals and SRM checks.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Template the readout (the README's Analysis Report) and require explicit p, n, CI, and SRM-pass fields, or fail the report.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
