<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="devops-platform-crossplane Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for devops-platform-crossplane. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Crossplane XRD MUST define both a composite type (XDatabase) and a claim type (Database). The claim is what developers interact with in their namespace. Compositions MUST embed security defaults that cannot be overridden by claim parameters — storageEncrypted: true, publiclyAccessible: false, and deleteProtection: false in non-production are non-negotiable platform defaults. Developers MUST NOT be able to set storageEncrypted: false through the claim API.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Security defaults embedded in the Composition layer are enforced at the platform level, not through policy review. This achieves near-100% security compliance (Netflix Wall-E model) by making insecure configurations impossible to request, not forbidden by policy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Platform Terraform modules MUST set cluster_endpoint_public_access = false and cluster_endpoint_private_access = true by default for all Kubernetes cluster modules. Public endpoint access MUST NOT be the default. Modules MUST output cluster_endpoint and cluster_certificate_authority_data for downstream consumption without requiring module consumers to access the provider state directly.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Public Kubernetes API endpoints are the most common misconfiguration leading to cluster compromise. Embedding the private-only default in the module means all EKS clusters provisioned through the platform golden path are secure by construction, not by policy reminder.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
