<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Asymmetric Churn Power Interview Protocol Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Asymmetric Churn Power Interview Protocol plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="churn-cohort-defined-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The protocol MUST define the churn cohort first (segment + time window + minimum usage threshold) before any interview is scheduled; ad-hoc cohorts MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Rob Fitzpatrick — The Mom Test">Ad-hoc churn cohorts mix signal (real PMF gaps) with noise (trial dropouts); the upfront definition is the structural sample frame.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="power-users-also-interviewed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For every 3 churn interviews, the protocol MUST also conduct 1 power-user interview; churn-only protocols MUST be reclassified.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sean Ellis — PMF survey methodology">Churn-only research describes the negative space; the asymmetric ratio (3:1) keeps the positive signal as comparator.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="open-questions-no-leading" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interview questions MUST be open-ended (no yes/no, no leading phrases like 'would you pay for…'); leading questions MUST be rewritten.</statement>
      <rationale source="Rob Fitzpatrick — The Mom Test">Leading questions produce confirmation; open questions surface unanticipated reasons.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="two-coders-tag-transcripts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every transcript MUST be coded by ≥2 independent coders with inter-coder agreement ≥0.7 (Cohen's kappa); single-coder protocols MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Saldaña — The Coding Manual for Qualitative Researchers">Single-coder tagging projects the coder's hypothesis; dual coding with kappa is the structural reliability gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="themes-must-name-evidence-counts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every reported theme MUST name the number of interviews it appeared in (e.g., 7/12); themes without evidence counts MUST be returned for revision.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — research synthesis audit">Theme-without-count obscures whether 'users want X' came from 1 or 11 interviews; counts make claims verifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
