<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="YouTube Strategy Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every YouTube Strategy application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-niche-positioning" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Channel MUST commit to a niche (audience + topic + angle) in one sentence. Generic channels are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Algorithm and audience both reward niche specificity; generic channels never break threshold.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-search-intent-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>First 20 videos MUST target search-intent keywords (tutorials, how-to). Pure discovery content is rejected before subscriber base.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Search videos compound for years; discovery videos depend on hot algorithm slots that small channels rarely earn.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-hook-first-structure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every video MUST land its hook in the first 15 seconds. Logo intros and 'before we start' preambles are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Retention curve drops sharply past 15 seconds; hook position determines reach.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-sustainable-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cadence MUST be sustainable for ≥6 months without burnout (≤1 video/week recommended for solos). Bi-weekly bursts are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">YouTube rewards consistency; burnout drops cause the algorithm to deprioritise the channel.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-thumbnail-title-pair" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each video MUST ship with thumbnail + title pair tested as a unit. Mismatched thumb/title pairs are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">CTR depends on thumb + title together; testing them independently misses the interaction effect.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
