<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-niche-and-formats" title="YouTube Niche and Video Formats">
  <summary>Niche formula, validation criteria, content pillars, and video format selection by goal.</summary>

  <section title="Niche Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the channel niche as: [Your expertise] + [Specific audience] + [Content format]. Validate all three axes before publishing.</statement>
      <rationale>YouTube's algorithm rewards consistent niche signals. Generalist channels struggle to build a loyal subscriber base because the algorithm cannot identify who to recommend the channel to.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS marketing + indie founders + tutorials and case studies. Specific expertise, identifiable audience, consistent format.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Marketing tips for everyone. No expertise specificity, no audience definition, no format constraint — the algorithm has no signal to optimize.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Niche Validation Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate a niche on four dimensions before committing: demand, differentiation, sustainability (100+ video ideas), and monetization path.</statement>
      <rationale>A niche with demand but no monetization path produces views without revenue. A niche with a product but no demand produces content nobody watches.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Demand: are people actively searching for this on YouTube?</item>
      <item>Competition: can you differentiate from existing channels in this niche?</item>
      <item>Sustainability: can you generate 100+ video ideas without forcing it?</item>
      <item>Monetization: is there a product, service, or course to sell to this audience?</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Pillars">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose 3-4 content pillars and map every video to at least one pillar. Do not publish videos outside the pillars.</statement>
      <rationale>Pillar discipline maintains the algorithm signal and subscriber expectations. Off-pillar videos fragment the audience and reduce subscriber conversion rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Educational: how-to, tutorials, explainers</item>
      <item>Entertainment: stories, commentary, opinion</item>
      <item>Inspiration: case studies, interviews, build-in-public</item>
      <item>Updates: news, trends, product announcements</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Video Formats by Goal">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize search-intent formats (tutorials, list videos) during the first 6-12 months. Switch to discovery formats (opinion, commentary) only after establishing a subscriber base.</statement>
      <rationale>Search-intent videos rank for queries indefinitely, compounding traffic. Discovery content depends on algorithmic push, which requires watch-time history to earn.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Tutorials (10-20 min): search traffic, authority building</item>
      <item>List videos (8-15 min): easy to produce, highly searchable</item>
      <item>Case studies (15-30 min): trust building, conversion</item>
      <item>Interviews (30-60 min): audience borrowing, relationship building</item>
      <item>Shorts (&lt;60 sec): top-of-funnel discovery, supplement long-form</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
