<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-video-structure" title="Video Structure and Optimization">
  <summary>Hook-first video structure, title and thumbnail rules, and description template.</summary>

  <section title="Video Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write the hook before the rest of the script. The first 30 seconds determine whether viewers stay; a strong hook doubles effective watch time.</statement>
      <rationale>YouTube's algorithm weights watch time and session time. A video with a poor hook that loses viewers in the first 30 seconds generates negative distribution signals regardless of total content quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>0:00-0:30 — Hook: grab attention, preview value (one of: question, promise, curiosity, contrarian)</item>
      <item>0:30-1:00 — Intro: who you are, credibility signal, agenda</item>
      <item>1:00-near end — Content: value delivery with chapter markers</item>
      <item>Near end — CTA: subscribe, watch next video, product link (30 sec max)</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Question hook: "Ever wondered why your YouTube videos get views but zero subscribers?" — creates tension, promises answer, audience self-selects.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Title Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure every title as: [Primary keyword] + [Benefit or outcome] + [Optional curiosity element]. Keep under 60 characters.</statement>
      <rationale>Title and thumbnail must be designed together as a single unit — the combination drives CTR. Keyword in the title signals search relevance; benefit + curiosity drives the click.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>"How to Get Your First 1000 Subscribers (What Actually Works)" — keyword first, outcome stated, curiosity parenthetical.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"My YouTube Journey Update #47" — no keyword, no benefit, no audience signal. Only works for established channels with loyal subscribers.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Thumbnail Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every thumbnail must be readable at 120x68 pixels (mobile thumbnail size) before publishing.</statement>
      <rationale>Most YouTube impressions appear at small thumbnail sizes on mobile. A thumbnail that only reads at large size is effectively invisible to the majority of the audience.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Face with expression (surprise, excitement) — highest CTR signal</item>
      <item>3-4 words maximum on the thumbnail</item>
      <item>Contrasting colors against YouTube's white/dark background</item>
      <item>Consistent style and branding across all thumbnails</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Description and Chapters">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add timestamp chapters to all videos above 8 minutes. YouTube surfaces individual chapters in search results, increasing impressions per video.</statement>
      <rationale>Chapter timestamps generate additional SERP appearances for each chapter heading, multiplying the indexable surface area of a single video.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/description.txt">YouTube description template with keyword hook, timestamps, resources, tags</reference>
  </section>
</text>
