<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="growth-youtube-strategy Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for growth-youtube-strategy as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Waiting for perfect production quality before publishing the first video.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The first 20 videos are the learning curve. Delaying publication delays the feedback needed to improve. Ship the first video this week.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Shooting Shorts-first with the intent to convert Shorts viewers to long-form subscribers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Shorts and long-form require separate optimization strategies. A Shorts-first strategy does not convert viewers to long-form subscribers effectively — audiences treat them as different products.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring keyword research and publishing based on personal interest rather than search demand.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without keyword research, videos are not discoverable via search. Search-intent videos generate traffic for years; opinion videos depend on algorithmic push the channel has not yet earned.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Making intros longer than 30 seconds before delivering any value.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Viewers drop off during extended intros. Every second spent on credentials before the hook is a lost viewer. State credentials in one sentence, then deliver the promised value immediately.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
