<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-metrics-and-mistakes" title="YouTube Metrics and Common Mistakes">
  <summary>Performance metric targets, publishing cadence rules, and common mistakes that kill channel growth.</summary>

  <section title="Key Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track CTR, average view duration percentage, and subscriber conversion rate as primary health signals — not absolute view counts.</statement>
      <rationale>Absolute view counts are a lagging indicator and depend on subscriber count. CTR and watch duration are leading indicators that predict algorithmic distribution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>CTR: 4% good, 8%+ great (below 4% → fix thumbnail or title)</item>
      <item>Average view duration: 40% good, 60%+ great (below 40% → fix hook or pacing)</item>
      <item>Subscriber conversion: 3% good, 8%+ great (below 3% → add subscribe CTA or improve value)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Publishing Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose a publishing cadence you can sustain for 12 months. A consistent weekly schedule outperforms an inconsistent aggressive schedule.</statement>
      <rationale>YouTube's algorithm uses publishing consistency as a trust signal. Channels that publish irregularly receive less algorithmic promotion than channels with consistent cadence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Minimum: 1 video/month — slow growth but sustainable</item>
      <item>Good: 1 video/week — standard for most creators</item>
      <item>Aggressive: 2-3 videos/week — fast growth, high effort</item>
      <item>Shorts: daily — supplemental, does not replace long-form</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Waiting for perfect production quality before publishing the first video.</description>
      <reason>The first 20 videos are the learning curve. Delaying publication delays the feedback needed to improve. Ship the first video this week.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Shooting Shorts-first with the intent to convert Shorts viewers to long-form subscribers.</description>
      <reason>Shorts and long-form require separate optimization strategies. A Shorts-first strategy does not convert viewers to long-form subscribers effectively — audiences treat them as different products.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring keyword research and publishing based on personal interest rather than search demand.</description>
      <reason>Without keyword research, videos are not discoverable via search. Search-intent videos generate traffic for years; opinion videos depend on algorithmic push the channel has not yet earned.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Making intros longer than 30 seconds before delivering any value.</description>
      <reason>Viewers drop off during extended intros. Every second spent on credentials before the hook is a lost viewer. State credentials in one sentence, then deliver the promised value immediately.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Cross-Promotion Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post the video link to email newsletter, Twitter, and LinkedIn within 2 hours of publishing.</statement>
      <rationale>External traffic in the first 24 hours is a strong positive algorithmic signal. Early external traffic tells YouTube the video has demand beyond its existing subscriber base.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
