<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="voice-ui-patterns">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Patterns for voice UI design: prompt rules, error recovery ladders, multimodal coordination, platform constraints (Alexa, Google, Siri), and key metrics.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>voice-ui</tag>
      <tag>vui</tag>
      <tag>conversation-design</tag>
      <tag>voice-agents</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Voice UI Patterns</title>
    <summary>Practical patterns for designing voice user interfaces: prompt writing rules, progressive error recovery (3-step ladder), multimodal voice+screen coordination, platform-specific constraints (Alexa, Google Actions, Siri), and key performance metrics. The core discipline is designing for the ear, not the eye — one idea per turn, concise confirmations only for high-stakes actions, and always providing an escape hatch.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>VUI fails when designed like a GUI: long prompts cause users to forget the start; identical error messages frustrate; missing escape hatches trap users. Empirical VUI research (NNG, Google, Amazon design guides) shows task completion drops sharply after 15 seconds of speech and more than 3-4 options per turn. Progressive error ladders and implicit confirmations for low-risk actions reduce abandonment.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing a new voice skill (Alexa, Google Action, Siri Shortcut, or custom voice bot).</item>
        <item>Producing prompt copy, error ladders, and confirmation patterns from a feature spec.</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing voice flow against NNG / Google / Amazon design guidelines.</item>
        <item>Designing multimodal (voice + screen) flows for display devices.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure text chatbots with no audio — use chatbot conversation-design playbooks instead.</item>
        <item>IVR with regulatory script requirements (banking, healthcare) — legal-mandated wording overrides UX guidance.</item>
        <item>Pre-product validation phase — design utterances on real user data, not imagined scripts.</item>
        <item>Languages with limited TTS quality where prosody coaching is futile.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="prompt-writing-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep each system turn to one idea; if there are two, ask twice or show the second on screen.</statement>
        <rationale>Users cannot re-read spoken output; two ideas in one turn cause the first to be forgotten by the time the second lands.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Confirm only high-stakes actions (money, deletion); use implicit acknowledgement for low-stakes actions.</statement>
        <rationale>Excessive confirmations train users to stop listening; every extra turn increases abandonment probability.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep spoken responses under 15 seconds (~120 words at 150 wpm). If more is needed, summarize and offer detail on request.</statement>
        <rationale>NNG research shows users zone out after 15 seconds of speech; offering detail preserves access without forcing it.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Provide an escape-hatch exit phrase on every node; users must always know how to quit.</statement>
        <rationale>Users trapped in a flow with no exit abandon the product, not just the task.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Concise implicit ack for low-stakes action">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[User: "Add milk"
System: "Added milk to your list."]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Verbose, unnecessary confirmation for low-stakes action">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[User: "Add milk"
System: "I have successfully added milk to your shopping list. Is there anything else you would like to add?"]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="High-stakes explicit confirmation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[User: "Send $500 to John"
System: "That's $500 to John Smith. Should I send it?"]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="progressive-error-recovery-ladder">
      <rule>
        <statement>Vary reprompts across error steps — never use identical wording at step 2 and step 3.</statement>
        <rationale>Repeating the same error message frustrates users who are already stuck; each step must add new information.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Three-step error ladder for slot capture">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Step 1: "Sorry, I didn't catch that. What city?"
Step 2: "I'm still having trouble. You can say a city name like 'New York' or 'Los Angeles'."
Step 3: "Let me help differently. Would you like to type the city instead, or speak to someone?"]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="multimodal-voice-screen-coordination">
      <rule>
        <statement>When voice and screen are both available, speak the top 3 items and show the full list on screen.</statement>
        <rationale>Listing more than 3-4 items verbally exceeds working memory; the screen handles the overflow without overwhelming the ear.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep canonical voice+screen pairs in a single JSON source, not parallel documents.</statement>
        <rationale>Parallel docs diverge; a screen that shows different options than the voice prompt confuses users and breaks multimodal trust.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Voice summarizes, screen shows detail">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Voice: "Here are your upcoming appointments."
Screen: [Shows full calendar with details the user can scan]
Voice: "Tap the one you want to reschedule."
Screen: [Each appointment is tappable]]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="context-preservation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Preserve conversation context across turns; handle follow-up references without asking users to repeat themselves.</statement>
        <rationale>Forgetting prior turn context is the leading cause of VUI frustration; users expect voice systems to behave like people.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Implicit update using prior context">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[User: "Set an alarm for 7 AM"
System: "Alarm set for 7 AM tomorrow."
User: "Make it 6:30"
System: "Updated to 6:30 AM."]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="platform-constraints">
      <rule>
        <statement>Respect the 8-second response time limit on Alexa; design flows so no single turn requires more processing.</statement>
        <rationale>Alexa kills skills that exceed the time limit; long async operations require progressive disclosure with intermediate acks.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Validate all SSML against the target platform's supported subset before shipping.</statement>
        <rationale>Siri ignores most SSML; Alexa and Google support overlapping but non-identical tag sets; invalid SSML silently degrades to flat TTS.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Alexa: 8-second response limit, custom wake word not allowed, APL/Card for visual companions, certification required.</item>
        <item>Google Actions: multi-surface support (phone/speaker/display), Dialogflow for NLU, rich response cards.</item>
        <item>Siri: limited to SiriKit intents + Shortcuts, HomePod integration, privacy-focused with minimal data sharing.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="performance-metrics">
      <rule>
        <statement>Track task completion rate, average turns per task, error rate, fallback rate, and 7-day retention; act on metrics individually.</statement>
        <rationale>Each metric reveals a different failure mode: high error rate indicates utterance coverage gaps; high turns per task indicates prompt complexity.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Task completion rate: target above 85%.</item>
        <item>Average turns per task: target below 3.</item>
        <item>Error rate: target below 15%.</item>
        <item>Fallback rate: target below 10%.</item>
        <item>User satisfaction (CSAT): target above 4.0/5.</item>
        <item>7-day retention: target above 40%.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track per-node abandonment; if any node exceeds 30%, the prompt fails users — rewrite before adding utterance variants.</statement>
        <rationale>Utterance variants fix recognition; a rewrite fixes comprehension. High abandonment means users understood the system but rejected it.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="accessibility">
      <rule>
        <statement>Provide a visual or text-input alternative for every voice interaction path.</statement>
        <rationale>Speech impediments, accents, quiet environments, and privacy concerns all make voice-only interfaces exclusionary.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not auto-deploy voice copy; stage rollouts because one bad utterance lands on all users simultaneously.</statement>
        <rationale>Voice copy ships instantly to all devices — no browser cache to clear, no app update to decline. The blast radius of a bad line is immediate and broad.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-pitfalls">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM-generated prompts default to verbose, apologetic tone.</description>
        <reason>Explicitly bound max word count and ban filler phrases ("I'd be happy to", "Just to confirm") in the system prompt — the model will not self-edit reliably.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Generated SSML includes tags rejected by the target platform.</description>
        <reason>Validate every generated SSML fragment against the platform's supported-tag list before shipping; unsupported tags render as silent drops or literal text.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>PII in transcripts sent to LLM for copy "improvement".</description>
        <reason>Redact sensitive slots before any LLM analysis call; build the sanitizer as a mandatory pipeline step, not an optional flag.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Use Claude as a "voice pattern librarian" that turns an intent spec into a full conversation graph: greeting, prompt copy, slot capture, confirmation, error ladder (3 steps), help, exit, repeat. A second linter pass scores each utterance on length (≤ 8 s), blame-free framing, example presence, and platform compliance. Output is exported as Voiceflow JSON, Alexa Skills Kit interaction model, or Dialogflow agent. Real-data improvement loop: anonymized analytics feed a "rotate variants" job that swaps fresh utterances when retention drops.</p>
      <list>
        <item>general-purpose Claude subagent — full conversation graph synthesis.</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — implement SDD tasks for the voice agent backend.</item>
        <item>A "voice-copy-reviewer" prompt — score / rewrite copy against length + tone rules.</item>
        <item>faion-improver skill — sustain weekly improvement loop on retention metrics.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>One idea per turn; if there are two, ask twice or show on screen.</item>
        <item>Vary reprompts — never identical at step 2 and step 3.</item>
        <item>Confirm only high-stakes actions (money, deletion); low-stakes get implicit ack.</item>
        <item>Provide an "escape hatch" exit on every node — users must always know how to quit.</item>
        <item>Localize prosody, not just words — politeness and pacing vary by language.</item>
        <item>Track per-node abandonment; &gt; 30% means the prompt fails users, not vice versa.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>ask-cli (Alexa Skills Kit CLI) — Author + simulate Alexa skills</item>
        <item>gactions — Google Actions / Conversational Actions</item>
        <item>dialogflow (gcloud) — Dialogflow CX agents from CLI</item>
        <item>voiceflow API — Export / version conversation graphs</item>
        <item>rasa shell / rasa test — Test OSS NLU + policy routing</item>
        <item>botium-cli — Cross-platform conversational regression</item>
        <item>ElevenLabs / Azure Speech CLI — Generate spoken samples for prosody review</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <list>
        <item>Voiceflow — SaaS; Yes (REST API); Best authoring + agent target</item>
        <item>Amazon Alexa Developer Console — SaaS; Yes (ASK CLI); Required for Alexa launch</item>
        <item>Google Dialogflow CX — SaaS; Yes (gRPC API); Rich state machine</item>
        <item>Apple Siri / SiriKit — OS framework; Limited; Intents extension only</item>
        <item>Rasa Open Source — OSS; Yes (REST + CLI); Self-hosted, full control</item>
        <item>Botpress — OSS + SaaS; Yes (CLI + REST); LLM-native chatbot platform</item>
        <item>Botium — OSS + SaaS; Yes; Conversational regression testing</item>
        <item>Dashbot / VoiceLabs — SaaS analytics; Yes (export API); Mine retention + drop-off</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/vui-lint.py" purpose="Linter that scores voice copy against length (8 s) and blame-free framing rules."/>
      <template path="templates/conversation-graph-prompt.txt" purpose="Prompt template for generating a full conversation graph from an intent spec."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://designguidelines.withgoogle.com/conversation/"/>
      <link href="https://developer.amazon.com/en-US/docs/alexa/alexa-design/get-started.html"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/voice-ux/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
