<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-approach-spectrum" title="Approach Selection: Spectrum, Dimensions, and Hybrid Patterns">
  <summary>The predictive-to-adaptive spectrum, six scoring dimensions for approach selection, and named hybrid patterns with their appropriate contexts.</summary>

  <section title="Selection Dimensions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score the project on all six dimensions before recommending an approach. Never recommend based on team preference or default to agile without scoring.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs have a heavy agile bias from training data. Unscored recommendations are PM preference, not project fit. Scoring creates an auditable decision record.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Requirement clarity — stable and well-defined favours predictive; evolving and emergent favours agile</item>
      <item>Stakeholder engagement — limited access favours predictive; highly engaged favours agile</item>
      <item>Risk tolerance — low (must work first time) favours predictive; high (can experiment) favours agile</item>
      <item>Team agility — less experienced favours predictive; self-organising favours agile</item>
      <item>Contract flexibility — fixed price/scope favours predictive; time and materials favours agile</item>
      <item>Regulatory burden — high (FDA, DoD, banking phase gates) favours predictive; low favours agile</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/approach-score.py">Six-dimension scoring script, outputs recommendation JSON</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Named Hybrid Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>When recommending "hybrid", always name the specific pattern. Generic "hybrid" in output must be rejected and re-prompted.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic hybrid recommendations produce mixed signals — teams implement waterfall with daily standups (overhead without benefit). A named pattern specifies which phase uses which method.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Water-Scrum-Fall: Plan phase (predictive) → Build phase (Scrum) → Deploy phase (predictive). Caps agile benefit — total cycle time is still long.</item>
      <item>Agile-discovery-then-predictive: Agile discovery phase to clarify requirements → Waterfall implementation once scope is locked. Good for fixed-price contracts with unclear initial scope.</item>
      <item>Predictive-governance-over-agile-execution: Phase gates and funding approvals are predictive; sprint execution within each phase is agile. Two reporting cadences — sprint review + phase gate.</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Hybrid for a $100K fixed-price contract over 4 months.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Phase 1: Discovery (2 weeks) — Agile
  - User story workshops, prototype key screens, finalise scope
Phase 2: Development (10 weeks) — Scrum
  - 5 two-week sprints, weekly client demos, backlog refinement
Phase 3: Deployment (2 weeks) — Predictive
  - Fixed test plan, staged rollout, documentation

Governance:
  - Monthly steering committee (predictive gate)
  - Weekly sprint reviews (agile cadence)
  - Change requests required for scope changes (predictive control)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agile-in-name-only: daily standups plus a waterfall plan.</description>
      <reason>Standups without a working sprint backlog and empirical planning produce the overhead of both methods with the benefit of neither.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Recommending agile on a fixed-price contract without a scope-envelope warning.</description>
      <reason>Fixed-price plus agile only works with a scope-envelope contract (range of stories, change budget, exit clauses). Without it, every backlog refinement is a contract dispute.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Adopting SAFe to fix a single-team velocity problem.</description>
      <reason>SAFe is a multi-team scaling framework. Applying it to a one-team problem adds PI planning, ARTs, and RTEs without solving the velocity root cause.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
