<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Launch Retro Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every launch retro must enforce. These keep the retro marketing-focused, data-anchored, and forward-actionable.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-marketing-not-eng-focus" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The retro covers five marketing sections: audience reaction, messaging fit, creative performance, channel ROI, lessons. Reject retros that collapse into engineering bug retrospectives — those belong in a separate incident retro.</statement>
      <rationale source="cross-functional retro practice">Mixed retros over-index on operational bugs (concrete) and under-discuss marketing dimensions (subjective). Separating them lets each function actually learn.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-data-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each section opens with a data pull: numbers BEFORE narrative. Reject sections where impressions are unstated and "I felt like" leads the discussion.</statement>
      <rationale source="retrospective effectiveness studies">Anecdote-first retros produce shared mythology, not improvement. Data-first retros produce calibrated learnings.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-blameless-tone" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use blameless language: "the messaging didn't resonate with segment X" not "Marketing failed at messaging." Reject retros with finger-pointing or post-hoc blame assignment.</statement>
      <rationale source="psychological-safety research (Edmondson)">Blame triggers defensiveness and stops information flow. Blameless retros surface 3-5× more actionable learning.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-keep-change-drop" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every section produces explicit keep / change / drop entries. Reject vague "we should think about X" outputs — every learning is bucketed.</statement>
      <rationale source="retro output design">Three-bucket categorization forces decisions; "we should think about" is a procrastination tag that never converts to action.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-one-committed-change" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each retro commits to exactly ONE change for the next launch, with three named owners (driver, reviewer, deadline-keeper). Reject retros that commit to 5+ changes (none gets done) or zero (nothing applied).</statement>
      <rationale source="learning-curve studies">One committed change converts at ~60%; five committed changes convert at ~5%. Constraining to one preserves the learning compound.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Data-first retro section">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
## Channel ROI

Data:
  PH:        listing #4 of day, 1,140 upvotes, 320 signups (8.6% click-to-signup)
  Twitter:   38 tweets, 1.2M impressions, 480 signups (cost: $0 organic)
  Email:     38k sent, 19% open, 4% click → 412 signups
  Podcast:   2 episodes, ~12k listens, ~80 signups (attribution rough)

Keep:       Twitter cohort posting — outperformed expectation by 2x
Change:     Move PH posting from 7am PT to 6am PT — next-day data showed
            6-7am as the highest-conversion window for the same listing tier
Drop:       Podcast cross-promo — attribution unclear AND cost was 14h prep
            for ~80 signups. ROI doesn't justify the slot next launch.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1, r2, r4 in a marketing-anchored section.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Vibes-first finger-pointing retro">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Honestly, marketing just didn't bring it. We should have hyped more.
The email blast was weak — Bob should have written better subject lines.
Next time we'll just do better."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2, r3, r4, r5 violations in two sentences. The retro produces zero actionable learning.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
