<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Launch Retro Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Launch Retro Template application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-five-marketing-sections" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Retro MUST cover exactly 5 sections: Audience reaction, Messaging fit, Creative performance, Channel ROI, Lessons. Engineering retro shape is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Marketing retros that copy engineering shape miss the message / creative / channel axes that drive launch outcome.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-before-after-metrics" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each section MUST surface a before/after metric pair. Vibes-only retros are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Without the metric pair the retro becomes opinion; metrics anchor the discussion to outcome.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-keep-change-drop-decisions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output MUST include explicit Keep / Change / Drop decisions per section. Open-ended notes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Without decisions the retro produces no behaviour change next launch.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-one-committed-change" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Retro MUST commit exactly one named change for the next launch with a named owner. Multi-change commitments are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">One change is the cap solo operators can actually execute; multi-change lists become aspirational.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-ninety-minute-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Session MUST cap at 90 minutes (60 facilitated + 30 write-up). Open-ended sessions are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Past 90 minutes the conversation loses focus; the cap forces decision discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
