<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="procurement-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Procurement framework: make-or-buy, SOW, contract type, vendor evaluation, negotiation, ongoing management. Mandatory clause checklist before signing contracts.</summary>
    <category>vendor-management</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>procurement</tag>
      <tag>vendor-management</tag>
      <tag>contracts</tag>
      <tag>sow</tag>
      <tag>vendor-evaluation</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Procurement Management Framework</title>

    <summary>Six-step framework for engaging external vendors: make-or-buy decision, Statement of Work (SOW) with explicit acceptance criteria, contract type selection (Fixed Price / T&amp;M / Cost Plus), weighted vendor evaluation, contract negotiation, and ongoing vendor management. Every contract must pass a mandatory clause checklist before signing.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Vague SOWs and "lowest price wins" decisions are the primary causes of vendor disputes, cost overruns, and project delays. A structured procurement process forces explicit scope definition, distributes risk appropriately via contract type, and creates an audit trail from requirements through payment. Missing clauses (IP assignment, DPA, termination-for-convenience) create legal exposure that surfaces only during disputes.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Defining a make-or-buy framework before engaging external vendors</item>
        <item>Drafting SOW, Master Services Agreement (MSA), or Data Processing Addendum (DPA) skeletons</item>
        <item>Running an RFI / RFP / RFQ process: vendor list, evaluation matrix, weighted scoring</item>
        <item>Selecting contract type for a defined scope and risk profile</item>
        <item>Vendor risk and security review (SOC 2, ISO 27001, GDPR DPA) intake</item>
        <item>Ongoing vendor management: SLA tracking, change requests, performance reviews</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Spot purchases under a PO threshold (e.g. under $5K) where formal procurement is overhead</item>
        <item>Highly regulated industries with established central procurement and legal teams — defer to org policy</item>
        <item>SaaS tools the engineering team can self-onboard with monthly billing (security review still needed, but not a full RFP)</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="make-or-buy-decision">
      <p>Frame the decision as an explicit comparison including "build internally" or "do nothing" as baseline options.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Always include the "build internally" or "do nothing" option as an explicit row in the evaluation matrix; otherwise procurement becomes a forced choice.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a baseline comparison, the decision optimizes vendor selection rather than whether to engage a vendor at all.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Factors favouring Make: full control needed, internal expertise sufficient, long-term strategic asset. Factors favouring Buy: faster time-to-capability, specialized expertise needed, risk transfer preferred.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="contract-type-selection">
      <p>Match contract structure to scope clarity and risk allocation.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Select contract type based on scope clarity and risk allocation: Fixed Price for well-defined scope (vendor bears cost risk); T&amp;M for unclear scope (buyer bears cost risk); Cost Plus for research or highly uncertain work (buyer bears all cost risk).</statement>
        <rationale>Mismatched contract type is the primary cause of cost overruns and disputes; variable scope on a fixed-price contract guarantees conflict.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>For T&amp;M contracts, enforce a hard cap and a weekly burn-rate report; trigger a change request at 70% of cap.</statement>
        <rationale>T&amp;M without a cap produces silent budget overruns; the 70% trigger provides time to re-scope or stop before the cap is hit.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Contract type selection">
        <note>Mobile app development with clear deliverables (design mockups, working app, source code, App Store approval, 95% crash-free): Fixed Price. Cloud infrastructure setup with evolving requirements: T&amp;M with $15K/mo cap and senior/junior rate card.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="sourcing-methods">
      <p>Choose RFI, RFP, RFQ, or sole source based on market maturity and scope clarity.</p>

      <p>RFI: gather market info before committing to a procurement. RFP: formal proposals with solutions (use for complex work). RFQ: price quotes for defined work (use when scope is clear). Sole source: direct engagement — requires documented justification.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Publish the scoring rubric with weights before proposals arrive. Retroactive weight changes after seeing proposals are bias laundering.</statement>
        <rationale>Pre-published weights force the evaluating team to commit to priorities before they are influenced by vendor positioning.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="mandatory-contract-clause-checklist">
      <p>Non-negotiable terms that must be present before execution.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every contract must include all of the following before signing: IP assignment, sub-processor disclosure, DPA (if PII involved), termination-for-convenience clause with reasonable notice, audit right, SLA with credits, indemnity including AI-output IP, warranty period. Reject any contract missing a clause; do not accept "TBD".</statement>
        <rationale>Missing clauses surface as disputes; an undiscovered IP gap or absent termination clause locks the buyer into a bad vendor indefinitely.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <reference path="templates/sow.md">Statement of Work template</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="ongoing-vendor-management">
      <p>Payment structures and performance monitoring after contract execution.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Tie payments to acceptance of deliverables, not calendar dates. Default structure: 25% at start, 50% at milestone, 25% at completion for Fixed Price.</statement>
        <rationale>Calendar-based payments reward delivery timing, not delivery quality; milestone-gated payments preserve leverage for final acceptance.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="weighted-scoring">
      <p>Structured vendor evaluation with sensitivity analysis.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Run a sensitivity analysis after scoring: re-score with each criterion weight shifted ±10%. If rank order flips, the choice is not robust — re-evaluate or document the trade-off explicitly.</statement>
        <rationale>A rank that changes under small weight variations means the decision is essentially arbitrary within the measured range; false precision hides this.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Weighted scoring example">
        <note>Five criteria: Technical Capability 25%, Relevant Experience 20%, Price 25%, Timeline 15%, Team Quality 10%, References 5%. Vendor A weighted score 86.5, Vendor B 84.5. Sensitivity: swapping price weight to 35% changes winner to Vendor B. Decision documented: technical quality prioritized over cost for this engagement.</note>
      </example>

      <reference path="templates/vendor-matrix.md">Vendor evaluation matrix template</reference>
      <reference path="scripts/vendor_score.py">Weighted scoring with sensitivity analysis</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="evaluation-anti-patterns">
      <p>Common procurement failures and failure modes.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Lowest price wins without quality and risk weighting.</description>
        <reason>Price-only selection consistently underestimates ramp-up cost, quality gap, and vendor management overhead; total cost of engagement typically exceeds a higher-priced reliable vendor.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Reference checks summarized from the vendor's own proposal.</description>
        <reason>Self-reported references are marketing; independent reference checks require contacting previous clients directly, not reading testimonials in the bid document.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Vague SOW accepted to start faster.</description>
        <reason>Every undefined deliverable becomes a dispute; a clear SOW is the single most important document in procurement — spending one week on it saves months of rework.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No change process defined in the contract.</description>
        <reason>Scope always evolves; without a written change process, every addition is either rejected or silently absorbed until someone notices the cost overrun.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>How to structure procurement tasks for agent orchestration.</p>

      <p>The agent is a structured-document generator and an evaluation calculator, not a negotiator. Useful surfaces: (1) draft SOW from a feature spec + acceptance criteria, (2) ingest vendor proposals (PDFs / Markdown) and produce a normalized comparison matrix, (3) compute weighted scores and surface dissents, (4) flag missing clauses against a checklist (IP, DPA, termination, audit, SLA, indemnity, AI-output rights). Every output goes to a human (PM, legal, finance) before sending to vendor.</p>

      <list>
        <item>A sow-author subagent — emits SOW skeleton from spec + acceptance criteria; validates against clause checklist.</item>
        <item>A proposal-normalizer subagent — reads vendor proposals (PDF/MD), outputs canonical JSON: price, timeline, team, references, assumptions.</item>
        <item>A vendor-scorer subagent — given normalized proposals + scoring rubric YAML, outputs weighted matrix + sensitivity analysis.</item>
        <item>A contract-clause-auditor — diff received contract against checklist; flag missing / weakened clauses.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="sow-author-prompt-pattern">
      <p>Template for generating Statement of Work documents.</p>

      <example type="good" title="SOW generation prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Inputs: feature_spec.md, acceptance_criteria.md, contract_type_preference="fixed-price",
data_classifications=["PII","financial"], jurisdictions=["EU","US"].

Output a SOW with sections:
1. Background / objective (≤ 5 lines).
2. Scope (in / out, bulleted).
3. Deliverables table (id, name, format, due).
4. Acceptance criteria per deliverable.
5. Timeline (milestone, date, payment %).
6. Assumptions and dependencies.
7. Required clauses checklist status:
   IP assignment, DPA, sub-processor list, audit right, SLA, indemnity (incl. AI),
   termination for cause, termination for convenience, change process, warranty.
   For each: [present | missing | weak] with line reference.

Reject and ask for input if any field unspecified. Do NOT invent dollar figures.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>Command-line utilities and integrations for procurement workflows.</p>

      <list>
        <item>pandoc — convert SOW Markdown → PDF / DOCX for vendor delivery (https://pandoc.org/)</item>
        <item>docusign-cli / dropbox-sign-cli — programmatic e-sign workflows (https://developers.docusign.com/)</item>
        <item>gh issue / jira-cli — procurement intake tickets (https://cli.github.com/)</item>
        <item>pdfplumber (Python) — extract structured fields from vendor PDFs (https://github.com/jsvine/pdfplumber)</item>
        <item>cuelang — validate SOW JSON schema (https://cuelang.org/)</item>
        <item>gpg — sign final contracts / NDA exchanges (https://gnupg.org/)</item>
        <item>git (procurement-as-code) — version control for SOW / MSA templates (https://git-scm.com/)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-platforms">
      <p>SaaS platforms for procurement automation and vendor management.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Coupa (SaaS P2P) — enterprise; heavyweight (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
        <item>SAP Ariba (SaaS P2P) — enterprise; SAP-aligned (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
        <item>Procurify (SaaS) — mid-market (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
        <item>Tropic (SaaS) — SaaS-spend negotiation focus (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
        <item>Vendr (SaaS) — SaaS procurement assistant (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
        <item>Sastrify / Cledara (SaaS) — SaaS cost + contract management (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
        <item>Ironclad / LinkSquares / Lexion (SaaS CLM) — contract lifecycle, AI clause review (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
        <item>DocuSign / Dropbox Sign / Adobe Sign (SaaS e-sign) — final signature step (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
        <item>Vanta / Drata / Whistic (SaaS vendor risk) — security questionnaire automation (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
        <item>OneTrust / TrustArc (SaaS privacy) — DPA + sub-processor inventory (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
        <item>Notion / Confluence (SaaS) — procurement docs hub (REST API agent-friendly)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="known-limitations">
      <p>Where the framework breaks and what to watch for.</p>

      <list>
        <item>"Lowest price wins" anti-pattern is hard to dislodge once finance owns scoring weights.</item>
        <item>SOW without acceptance criteria collapses into endless revisions.</item>
        <item>T&amp;M contracts without a cap or burn-rate alert produce silent budget overruns.</item>
        <item>IP / data-ownership clauses are hand-waved by both sides until a dispute reveals them.</item>
        <item>Termination clauses ("for convenience" with notice + transition) often missing — locks in bad vendors.</item>
        <item>Cross-border procurement adds tax, FX, and data-residency complexity that single-jurisdiction templates miss.</item>
        <item>AI/ML vendor procurement: training-data rights, model output IP, and indemnity for IP infringement are 2024-2026 hot zones; old templates don't cover them.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/sow.md" purpose="Statement of Work with scope, deliverables, acceptance criteria, timeline, assumptions"/>
      <template path="templates/vendor-matrix.md" purpose="Weighted evaluation matrix with scoring scale and recommendation sections"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/vendor_score.py" purpose="Weighted vendor scoring with sensitivity analysis; flags rank instability"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="pm-tool-selection"/>
      <ref slug="risk-management"/>
      <ref slug="cost-estimation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
