<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="strategy-analysis-current-state">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Assess current state across six areas (process, org, tech, people, data, external) using SWOT, PESTLE, capability mapping, and a stakeholder coverage matrix before gap analysis.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>strategy-analysis</tag>
      <tag>current-state</tag>
      <tag>swot</tag>
      <tag>pestle</tag>
      <tag>capability-mapping</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>strategy</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-business-need"/>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-future-state"/>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-gap-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="stakeholder-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="business-process-analysis"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Strategy Analysis: Current State Assessment</title>

    <summary>Before defining the future state, the BA must systematically inventory where the organization is today across six areas: business processes, organization structure, technology landscape, people and skills, data and information, and external factors. Each area requires evidence — not anecdote. A stakeholder coverage matrix gates sign-off: rows are the six areas, columns are stakeholder roles, cells confirm evidence exists and who provided it.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Current-state assessment by anecdote is the most reliable failure mode of strategy analysis. Process, tech, people, and data inventories are filled by interviewing whoever happened to attend the workshop; whole departments are missing. Without a stakeholder coverage matrix the current state is fiction.</p>
      <p>SWOT and PESTLE analyses that list generic items ("AI is rising") with no link to the org's specific exposure get ignored. Agents produce this by default; they must be forced to supply per-cell relevance_to_us with concrete impact and primary-source citations stamped retrieved_at.</p>
      <p>Understanding the starting point is prerequisite to any gap measurement: without a current-state baseline, gap deltas cannot be computed and future-state targets cannot be validated against reality.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>After the business need has been framed and signed by the sponsor — current-state work begins only then.</item>
        <item>Digital transformation programs where the current state spans process, tech, people, and data simultaneously — the six-area inventory is the minimum coverage.</item>
        <item>M&amp;A integration: the acquired entity's current state must be mapped in all six areas before Day-1 / Day-100 / Day-365 gap analysis.</item>
        <item>Regulatory-driven change: the regulator's audit will demand evidence for the current-state baseline, not assertions.</item>
        <item>Whenever SWOT or PESTLE is requested — run these inside the current-state pass, not standalone, so findings feed the gap analysis.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before the business need is signed off — current-state work done prematurely anchors the problem frame to the wrong starting point.</item>
        <item>Single-area tactical changes where one area (e.g. only technology) is affected — scope the inventory to the relevant areas only, but still use the coverage matrix for that area.</item>
        <item>Early-stage product discovery — use customer interviews and opportunity-solution-trees; current-state org assessment introduces premature structure.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="six-area-inventory">
      <p>The six areas to analyze in every current-state assessment are: business processes, organization structure, technology landscape, people and skills, data and information, and external factors. For each area, the BA must identify who owns it, what evidence exists (not what people say), and who has not yet been interviewed.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Current-state assessment MUST cover all six areas: business processes, organization structure, technology landscape, people and skills, data and information, and external factors. Skipping any one area MUST be documented as a known gap with an owner and a resolution plan.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping any one area is the most reliable failure mode of strategy analysis; the omitted area typically surfaces in the gap analysis as an unplanned dependency that delays delivery.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>A stakeholder coverage matrix MUST be produced before current-state sign-off. Rows are the six areas; columns are stakeholder roles; each cell records "interviewed: yes/no" and an evidence link. Empty rows block sign-off.</statement>
        <rationale>Without the matrix, the BA cannot demonstrate that the current state is representative rather than the view of the loudest voices in the room.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="swot-analysis">
      <p>SWOT (Strengths, Weaknesses, Opportunities, Threats) is an internal/external 2x2 covering the organization's current position. Run it as part of the current-state pass, not standalone. Each cell must carry evidence URLs and a confidence score. Generic cells are rejected.</p>
      <example type="good" title="SWOT with evidence — Customer Service Department">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Strengths:
- Experienced staff (avg 7 years tenure, HR data 2025-Q4)
- Strong customer loyalty (NPS 62, survey 2026-01, n=1400)
- Good product knowledge (pass rate 94% on cert exam, L&D records)

Weaknesses:
- Outdated CRM system (Salesforce Classic, EOL 2026-06, IT asset register)
- Long call handling times (avg 8.2 min vs industry 5.1 min, Gartner 2025)
- Limited self-service options (0 deflection rate, analytics 2026-Q1)

Opportunities:
- AI chatbot implementation (pilot reduced AHT 35% at Competitor A, press release 2025-11)
- Mobile app development (62% of inbound from mobile, GA data 2026-Q1)
- Data analytics for personalization (CRM holds 5y purchase history, untapped)

Threats:
- Competitor service improvements (Competitor B launched 24/7 chat, 2026-02)
- Rising customer expectations (KPMG CX Barometer 2025: 71% expect sub-4h resolution)
- Staff turnover (attrition 22% in 2025 vs sector avg 15%, HR data)
]]></code>
        <note>Each cell carries a primary source and date. Confidence is implicit in the source quality. Generic cells like "AI is disrupting industries" are absent.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>SWOT cells with generic items: "Technology is changing fast" or "Market is competitive".</description>
        <reason>No link to the org's specific exposure; output gets ignored in steering reviews. Force per-cell relevance_to_us with concrete impact quantified where possible.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="pestle-analysis">
      <p>PESTLE (Political, Economic, Social, Technological, Legal, Environmental) scans the external environment. Run as part of the current-state external-factors area. Each cell cites a primary source stamped retrieved_at. Evidence older than 90 days must be re-fetched before sign-off.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every PESTLE cell MUST cite a primary source (regulator publication, industry report, the org's own telemetry, financial filings) stamped retrieved_at. Cells citing secondary synthesis or agent-generated prose without a primary source MUST be flagged for re-elicitation.</statement>
        <rationale>Tech-landscape and PESTLE evidence go stale fast; vendor websites can plant favorable framing. Primary sources with dates allow the BA to defend the evidence under audit.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="capability-mapping">
      <p>Business capability mapping identifies what the organization CAN do today (not what it does or how). Capabilities are stable; processes change. Map current capabilities against the six areas to establish the baseline for gap analysis. For EA-heavy organizations, ArchiMate 3.x or LeanIX / Ardoq REST APIs can supply the capability model programmatically.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>The BA owns framing and judgment; agents own coverage, traceability, and artifact production. For the current-state phase, run an opus current-state-agent that walks the six areas and asks per area: who owns it, what evidence exists, who has not yet been interviewed. Output is a coverage matrix plus a backlog of elicitation gaps. Pair with pestle-agent and swot-agent for external/internal scans, each citing primary sources.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: brainstorm for divergence on capability gaps (prevents anchoring to the three most-visible problems); improver quarterly to re-open strategy analyses signed off 6-12 months ago and compare predicted vs. actual gap closure.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Generic PESTLE / SWOT: agents emit "AI is disrupting industries" cells with no link to the org's specific exposure. Force per-cell relevance_to_us field with concrete impact.</p>
      <p>Date-stale evidence: tech-landscape and PESTLE evidence go stale fast. Stamp retrieved_at on every cell; refuse evidence older than 90 days without re-fetching.</p>
      <p>Prompt-injected vendor copy: when PESTLE or current-state evidence is pulled from vendor websites, vendors can plant favorable framing. Strip suspicious instructions; prefer primary sources (filings, regulator publications, the org's own telemetry).</p>
      <p>Hallucinated stakeholders: given a sparse brief, agents invent names. Pass the actual stakeholder list as input; reject any name the agent invents.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools">
      <p>CLI tools useful in current-state work: mermaid-cli for current-state diagrams and capability maps; yq plus jq for reading strategy state stored as YAML/JSON; gh for pulling issues and repos as evidence for capability mapping; graphviz (dot) for capability map and gap dependency DAG when mermaid scaling breaks; pandas plus numpy for aggregating current-state metrics and computing gap deltas.</p>
      <p>Services: LeanIX (SaaS, EA) with REST API for capability and tech map; Ardoq (SaaS, EA) with REST API for strategy-to-capability traceability; Airtable (SaaS, REST) for cheap intake of stakeholder-by-area current-state evidence; miro or mural for live SWOT and capability mapping workshops with agents pre-seeding the board.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="references">
      <p>IIBA — BABOK Guide v3, Knowledge Area 6, section 6.1 Analyze Current State. Kaplan &amp; Norton — The Strategy-Focused Organization (current-state capability mapping discipline). Porter — Competitive Strategy (five-forces; feeds PESTLE-C and current-state external scan). The Open Group — TOGAF ADM phases A-B (Architecture Vision, Business Architecture) — alternative current/future-state framing for EA-heavy orgs. ArchiMate 3.x — modeling language for current/future-state when LeanIX / Bizzdesign / Ardoq is in use.</p>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-business-need"/>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-future-state"/>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-gap-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="stakeholder-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="business-process-analysis"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
