<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Cognitive Walkthrough Framework">
  <summary>The four questions, what each checks, common failure modes per question, and how cognitive walkthrough compares to heuristic evaluation.</summary>

  <section title="The Four Questions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Answer all four questions for every step in the action sequence. Do not skip any step, including steps the team considers "obvious". The most useful findings are often on steps the team assumed were trivial.</statement>
      <rationale>Expert familiarity with the interface causes teams to skip steps that new users routinely fail on. Systematically skipping "obvious" steps is how critical learnability failures survive to production.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Q1: Will the User Try to Achieve the Right Effect?">
    <rule>
      <statement>Q1 checks: Is the goal clear? Does the user know an action is needed? Is motivation present?</statement>
      <rationale>Users often do not know they are supposed to do something. If the task goal is not communicated, the user will not attempt the correct action regardless of how visible or labeled it is.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Common failure: user does not know something is required at this step.</item>
      <item>Common failure: user thinks they are done when they are not (premature success perception).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Q2: Will the User Notice the Correct Action?">
    <rule>
      <statement>Q2 checks: Is the control visible? Is it in the expected location? Does it stand out from competing elements?</statement>
      <rationale>Visibility failures are distinct from labeling failures. An action can be correctly labeled but invisible because it is below the fold, de-emphasized, or surrounded by too many competing options.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Common failure: action is below the fold or requires scrolling the user will not do.</item>
      <item>Common failure: control does not look interactive (no visual affordance).</item>
      <item>Common failure: too many competing options make the correct one non-salient.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Q3: Will the User Associate the Action With the Effect?">
    <rule>
      <statement>Q3 checks: Does the label match the user's mental model? Is the icon recognizable? Is the location consistent with conventions?</statement>
      <rationale>Labels are interpreted through the user's existing vocabulary, not the team's internal terminology. Domain jargon and feature names that the team uses daily are opaque to first-time users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Common failure: jargon in labels (internal product terminology, technical terms).</item>
      <item>Common failure: ambiguous icons without labels.</item>
      <item>Common failure: action placed where the user's mental model does not expect it.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Q4: Will the User See That Progress Is Being Made?">
    <rule>
      <statement>Q4 checks: Is there feedback after the action? Does the UI state change visibly? Is success communicated? Q4 requires the post-action screen, not just the pre-action screen.</statement>
      <rationale>Without feedback, users repeat actions or abandon the task. Missing loading indicators, silent failures, and unchanged UI states after successful actions all produce the same user behavior: uncertainty leading to abandonment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Common failure: no loading indicator for async operations.</item>
      <item>Common failure: page looks identical before and after a successful action.</item>
      <item>Common failure: error message not displayed or not visible.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Vs Heuristic Evaluation">
    <list>
      <item>Cognitive walkthrough: focuses on task completion by a new user; step-by-step task analysis; four specific questions per step; best for learnability and onboarding.</item>
      <item>Heuristic evaluation: focuses on broad usability principles; expert review against 10 heuristics; best for general usability issues including efficiency for expert users.</item>
      <item>Use both: they catch different issue classes. Pair cog walk for learnability with heuristic evaluation for efficiency.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
