<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Cognitive Walkthrough Examples">
  <summary>Two worked examples (sign-up flow and file upload) showing Q1-Q4 evaluation per step with identified issues and concrete fixes.</summary>

  <section title="Example 1: Sign-Up Flow">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Step: Click "Get Started" button. Persona: first-time user, no prior experience with the product.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Q1: Will try to achieve right effect? YES
  Evidence: Clear value proposition above button establishes goal.

Q2: Will notice correct action available? PARTIAL
  Evidence: Button is visible but competes with "Sign In" at equal visual weight.

Q3: Will associate action with effect? NO
  Evidence: "Get Started" is ambiguous — could mean sign up, take a demo, or browse.

Q4: Will see progress? YES
  Evidence: Clicking navigates to registration form — clear state change.

Issue: Q3 failure — "Get Started" label does not communicate sign-up intent.
Fix: Change label to "Create Free Account" — removes ambiguity, communicates both action and cost.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example 2: File Upload">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Step: Drag file to upload zone. Persona: first-time user familiar with desktop file management.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Q1: Will try to achieve right effect? PARTIAL
  Evidence: Users familiar with drag-drop will attempt; users who expect a browse button
  will look for it first and may not discover the drag zone.

Q2: Will notice correct action available? YES
  Evidence: Large, centered drop zone is visible and prominent.

Q3: Will associate action with effect? YES
  Evidence: Drop zone icon and "Drag files here" label clearly communicate the interaction.

Q4: Will see progress? NO
  Evidence: No upload progress indicator; no filename displayed during upload;
  page appears unchanged while upload runs.

Issue: Q4 failure — no feedback during file upload creates uncertainty and abandonment risk.
Fix: Add progress bar showing percentage and filename. Display "Uploading..." state
immediately on file drop before server confirmation.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Prompt Pattern">
    <rule>
      <statement>Evaluate one step at a time. Feed the agent (a) the persona description, (b) a screenshot of the current screen, (c) the intended next action. Require JSON output with Q1-Q4 answers, evidence citations, and a concrete fix for every No or Partial.</statement>
      <rationale>Multi-step context causes theme contamination — earlier step findings bias the agent's evaluation of later steps. Stateless per-step evaluation produces independent findings that can be merged without contamination.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Agent prompt template for one step evaluation.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are evaluating ONE step of a user task using the Cognitive Walkthrough method.

Persona: <<<one-paragraph first-time user persona>>>
Goal: <<<task goal>>>
Step <N> action: <<<exact intended action>>>
Screen: <attached image>

Answer ONLY in JSON:
{q1:{ans:"yes|no|partial", evidence:""},
 q2:{ans:"yes|no|partial", evidence:""},
 q3:{ans:"yes|no|partial", evidence:""},
 q4:{ans:"yes|no|partial", evidence:""},
 suggested_fix:""}.
For each "no" or "partial", evidence MUST quote a visible UI element
or explicitly state what is missing.
Do not assume capabilities the persona lacks.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
