<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-antipatterns" title="Cognitive Walkthrough Antipatterns">
  <summary>Five failure modes: power-user bias, skipping steps, omitting positive findings, vague issue statements, and missing fix recommendations.</summary>

  <section title="Power-User Bias">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Evaluating the interface as an experienced user or product expert instead of as a first-time user.</description>
      <reason>Teams know the intended flow, terminology, and visual hierarchy intimately. This knowledge makes Q2 and Q3 failures invisible — controls that experts instantly recognize are opaque to first-time users with different vocabularies and mental models. The walkthrough becomes a confirmation exercise, not an evaluation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define a concrete first-time user persona with specific tech-savviness level, prior tools used, and absence of product knowledge. Inject this persona into every evaluation prompt and forbid the evaluator from assuming capabilities the persona lacks.</statement>
      <rationale>Concrete personas prevent evaluators from defaulting to their own knowledge. Vague personas ("a typical user") produce vague evaluations that miss the specific knowledge gaps of the actual target audience.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skipping Steps">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Evaluating only the steps that seem complex or where problems are anticipated, and skipping steps the team assumes are obvious.</description>
      <reason>The steps a team assumes are obvious are precisely where first-time users fail — because the team's assumption of obviousness reflects expert familiarity, not user learnability. Skipping these steps misses high-value findings systematically.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Omitting Positive Findings">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Recording only "No" and "Partial" answers and not documenting steps where all four questions receive "Yes".</description>
      <reason>Positive findings identify what works and must not be changed. Without a record of positive Q1-Q4 answers, subsequent redesigns inadvertently remove successful elements while fixing failed ones.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Vague Issue Statements">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Documenting issues as general observations ("the button is confusing") without citing the specific UI element and which question it fails.</description>
      <reason>Vague issues cannot be acted on. A developer receiving "the button is confusing" does not know which button, which failure mode (visibility? labeling? feedback?), or what change would resolve it. The issue sits unresolved or is fixed incorrectly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every issue must cite: the step number, the specific UI element (quoted text or described element), the question it fails (Q1/Q2/Q3/Q4), and a concrete one-line fix suggestion.</statement>
      <rationale>Structured issue format makes walkthroughs actionable. Issues in this format can be filed directly as development tickets without interpretation by an intermediary.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Missing Fix Recommendations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Documenting findings without suggesting how to fix them, leaving interpretation entirely to the development team.</description>
      <reason>Findings without fixes get deprioritized because the team must first understand the issue deeply enough to devise a solution before they can estimate effort. Walkthrough findings with concrete fixes get resolved in the next sprint; findings without fixes get deferred.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
