<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="cog-walk-basics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for cog-walk-basics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Evaluating the interface as an experienced user or product expert instead of as a first-time user.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Teams know the intended flow, terminology, and visual hierarchy intimately. This knowledge makes Q2 and Q3 failures invisible — controls that experts instantly recognize are opaque to first-time users with different vocabularies and mental models. Define a concrete first-time user persona with specific tech-savviness level, prior tools used, and absence of product knowledge. Inject this persona into every evaluation prompt and forbid the evaluator from assuming capabilities the persona lacks.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Evaluating only the steps that seem complex or where problems are anticipated, skipping steps the team assumes are obvious.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The steps a team assumes are obvious are precisely where first-time users fail — because the team's assumption of obviousness reflects expert familiarity, not user learnability. Skipping these steps misses high-value findings systematically.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Recording only "No" and "Partial" answers and not documenting steps where all four questions receive "Yes".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Positive findings identify what works and must not be changed. Without a record of positive Q1-Q4 answers, subsequent redesigns inadvertently remove successful elements while fixing failed ones.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Documenting issues as general observations ("the button is confusing") without citing the specific UI element and which question it fails.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Vague issues cannot be acted on. Every issue must cite: the step number, the specific UI element (quoted text or described element), the question it fails (Q1/Q2/Q3/Q4), and a concrete one-line fix suggestion. Structured issue format makes walkthroughs actionable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Documenting findings without suggesting how to fix them, leaving interpretation entirely to the development team.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Findings without fixes get deprioritized because the team must first understand the issue deeply enough to devise a solution. Walkthrough findings with concrete fixes get resolved in the next sprint; findings without fixes get deferred.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Vision-LLMs over-recognize standard patterns ("That hamburger menu is obvious").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Inject the persona's tech-savviness explicitly and forbid assumptions. Agents conflate Q1 (motivation) with Q2 (visibility) — separate prompts per question reduce contamination.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Q4 needs the next screen too; static screenshots can't show absence of feedback.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Capture before+after pairs or animated GIFs. A locale mismatch where a Ukrainian-speaking persona walks an English-only UI fails Q3 by default — do not let the agent pretend it does not.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Severity inflation: agents tend to rank everything Medium.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a forced ranking: top 3 issues only at High; rest must be Medium or Low. Prototype screenshots may contain real names/emails in placeholder data — scrub before any vision call to a third-party API.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
