<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-capabilities" title="AIOps Core Capabilities, Architecture, and Tool Landscape">
  <summary>Five AIOps capabilities, data-flow architecture, tool comparison, 2025-2026 evolution trends, and success metrics with targets.</summary>

  <section title="Core Capabilities">
    <list>
      <item>Anomaly detection: identify deviations from normal using ML (Isolation Forest, Prophet, LSTM)</item>
      <item>Root cause analysis: determine failure origin via event correlation, causal graphs, topology analysis</item>
      <item>Predictive alerts: forecast failures before impact using time-series forecasting</item>
      <item>Auto-remediation: self-healing actions (restart, scale, rollback) with risk-based approval gates</item>
      <item>Capacity planning: resource demand forecasting using regression and seasonal decomposition</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Data-Flow Architecture">
    <p>AIOps requires unified telemetry collection before any ML or LLM analysis can be applied.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Data sources: metrics (Prometheus), logs (Fluent Bit), traces (Jaeger/OpenTelemetry), events (K8s), changes (Git/CD)</item>
      <item>Ingestion: OpenTelemetry Collector normalizes across sources into unified format</item>
      <item>Analysis: ML models for anomaly detection + LLM for incident summaries and runbook generation</item>
      <item>Action: auto-remediation scripts + human-approval gates + SOAR/ChatOps integration</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="2025-2026 Evolution Trends">
    <list>
      <item>LLM integration: natural language incident summaries, GenAI runbooks generated from topology + history</item>
      <item>Predictive operations: failures predicted and prevented before reaching production</item>
      <item>Hybrid workflows: AI recommends → humans approve → systems execute (not fully autonomous)</item>
      <item>Explainable AI: every auto-action logged with reasoning for audit trail</item>
      <item>SLO-aware detection: alerts based on error budget burn rate, not static thresholds</item>
      <item>Change-aware correlation: RCA considers recent deployments and config changes in root-cause ranking</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Auto-Remediation Risk Classification">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every auto-remediation action by risk level and require human approval for P1/P2 incidents.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-remediation without approval gates can cascade failures. A pod restart in response to an anomaly might be correct 95% of the time, but the 5% case could be a symptom of a wider outage requiring human coordination.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Low risk (auto-execute): pod restart on CrashLoopBackOff, HPA scale on CPU above 80%, cache flush on memory pressure</item>
      <item>Medium risk (notify + short timeout): node drain on unhealthy node, deployment rollback on error spike post-deploy</item>
      <item>High risk (require human approval): cluster-wide operations, cross-service changes, data-touching actions</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Success Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Anomaly precision: target above 60% after tuning (true incidents / total anomalies promoted)</item>
      <item>Auto-remediation rate: start above 15%, grow to above 40% over 6 months</item>
      <item>MTTR reduction: target above 50% improvement vs pre-AIOps baseline</item>
      <item>False positive rate: target below 20%</item>
      <item>Noise reduction: target above 80% (correlated alerts / raw alert count)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Minimum Platform Requirements (2026)">
    <list>
      <item>Native OpenTelemetry support (unified metrics, logs, traces)</item>
      <item>SLO-aware detection with error-budget burn-rate alerts</item>
      <item>Change-aware correlation (deployment and config change events in RCA)</item>
      <item>Service topology with automatic dependency discovery</item>
      <item>LLM/RAG integration for intelligent runbook generation</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
