<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="aiops Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for aiops. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Implement anomaly detection on a minimum 2+ weeks of baseline data. Start with Isolation Forest for general deviations, then layer Prophet for time-series patterns and LSTM for complex behaviors.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">ML models trained on insufficient data overfit to noise. Baseline collection reveals seasonality (weekly traffic patterns, release-day spikes) that must be factored into anomaly thresholds. Starting with Isolation Forest gives fast results; adding Prophet and LSTM incrementally prevents overwhelming the ops team with alerts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use dynamic thresholds connected to SLO error-budget burn rates, not static threshold values like "CPU &gt; 80%".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Static thresholds are orthogonal to business impact. A service burning error budget at 50%/day deserves immediate attention; one at 5%/day can wait. SLO-aware thresholds align operations with product commitments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>AIOps platform MUST ingest metrics, logs, traces, and change events through OpenTelemetry Collector into a single telemetry backend before any analysis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Siloed data sources prevent correlation. A metric spike in isolation is noise. Metrics + logs + traces + recent deployments together reveal the root cause. OpenTelemetry standardizes collection across all sources; your platform becomes language-agnostic and polyglot-ready.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Auto-remediation without approval gates MUST NOT execute on P1 or P2 incidents. Classify actions by risk level; require human approval matrix for medium and high-risk actions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Auto-remediation without oversight can cascade failures. A pod restart might fix 95% of anomalies but mask a symptom of a wider outage. High-risk actions (rolling back a deployment, draining a node) need human judgment. Medium-risk actions need a short timeout window (5-15 min) to escalate if human doesn't approve.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every auto-remediation action MUST log the reasoning (ML features, confidence score, context) for audit trail and postmortem learning.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Explainability is both a compliance requirement (SOC2, HIPAA) and a debugging necessity. If an auto-action caused harm, you need to know why the system thought it was correct. Logs enable postmortems and model retraining.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>RCA output MUST include (1) ranked probable causes with confidence percentages, (2) timeline of related events (deployments, config changes, metric spikes), (3) affected services and scope, (4) relevant logs and traces for human investigation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">On-call engineers need to make decisions in seconds. Ranked causes with confidence let them prioritize investigation. Timeline context (recent deploy? config change?) is often the answer. Scope tells them the blast radius. Logs/traces accelerate troubleshooting vs starting from scratch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before deploying anomaly detection, establish 2+ weeks of baseline data and map seasonality (weekly, monthly, release-day patterns). Target false positive rate &lt;20% before expanding to new services.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Models trained on insufficient data trigger false alerts that erode trust. Seasonality (weekend traffic drop, release-day spike) is often mistaken for anomalies. Starting with &lt;20% false positives ensures the ops team trusts the system enough to act on alerts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track anomaly precision, auto-remediation rate, MTTR, false positive rate, and noise reduction quarterly. If MTTR is not improving by &gt;30% within 3 months, re-examine the data-flow architecture and model selection.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AIOps is only valuable if it reduces MTTR and false alerts. If numbers aren't improving, the system is likely producing noise (overfitting, poor feature selection, wrong algorithm). Quarterly reviews force course-correction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Platforms without native OpenTelemetry, SLO-aware detection, and change correlation are not viable for modern production AIOps as of 2026.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">OpenTelemetry is the de facto standard for observability. SLO-aware detection aligns ops with product commitments. Change correlation is what distinguishes useful RCA from noise. These three are table-stakes for any platform.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>LLM integration MUST include prompt caching (for topology/history context) to reduce latency and cost. Every LLM-generated runbook must be marked as "auto-generated" and reviewed by on-call before execution.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs are fast but not infallible. Caching context (service topology, incident history) reduces API costs and latency. Marking auto-generated content prevents on-call from blindly following incorrect recommendations. Human review gates catch edge cases.</rationale>
    </rule>
  
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply the AIOps configuration to one platform deployment per pass. Skip this methodology entirely when (a) baseline data &lt; 14 days, (b) SLOs are not defined, or (c) explainability/audit requirements prevent ML-driven decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 content-completion; sibling methodology routing">Anti-conflation: AIOps configs are platform-bound; cross-platform configs hide model-tuning state. Pre-baseline AIOps generates false-positive floods.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
