<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-checklists" title="AIOps Implementation and Audit Checklists">
  <summary>Checklists for anomaly detection setup, RCA, incident management, auto-remediation policy, platform selection, and quarterly audit.</summary>

  <section title="Anomaly Detection Setup">
    <list>
      <item>Metrics coverage: CPU, memory, disk, network, latency, error rates all instrumented</item>
      <item>Log aggregation: centralized with structured (JSON) format</item>
      <item>Distributed tracing enabled across all services</item>
      <item>Establish 2+ weeks of baseline data before enabling ML alerts</item>
      <item>Map seasonality: weekly, monthly, and release-day patterns</item>
      <item>Select algorithm: Isolation Forest for general anomalies, Prophet for time-series, LSTM for complex patterns</item>
      <item>Use dynamic thresholds, not static; connect to SLO error-budget burn rates</item>
      <item>Target false positive rate below 20% before expanding alert coverage</item>
      <item>Define escalation paths for unacknowledged alerts</item>
      <item>Build feedback loop: process for teams to mark false positives for model retraining</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Root Cause Analysis Setup">
    <list>
      <item>Maintain up-to-date service dependency graph (topology)</item>
      <item>Track change events: deployments, config changes, feature flag flips</item>
      <item>Configure correlation window for event grouping (typically 5-30 minutes)</item>
      <item>Link APM traces to RCA findings</item>
      <item>Attach relevant logs and anomalous metrics to each incident</item>
      <item>Output ranked probable causes with confidence percentages</item>
      <item>Export RCA data for postmortem templates</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Auto-Remediation Policy">
    <list>
      <item>Define scope: explicit list of what can and cannot be auto-remediated</item>
      <item>Classify each action by risk level (low/medium/high)</item>
      <item>Set approval matrix: which roles can approve medium and high risk actions</item>
      <item>Define blast-radius limits: maximum impact of any single auto-action</item>
      <item>Set rate limits: maximum actions per time window per service</item>
      <item>Set cooldown periods: minimum time between same action on same target</item>
      <item>Require health verification after each auto-action (confirm improvement)</item>
      <item>Log all actions with context for audit trail</item>
      <item>Provide manual override to disable auto-remediation per service</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Quarterly Audit">
    <list>
      <item>MTTR trend: improving quarter-over-quarter?</item>
      <item>False positive rate: decreasing or stable?</item>
      <item>Auto-remediation rate: coverage expanding as planned?</item>
      <item>Concept drift: retrain models if prediction accuracy declining</item>
      <item>Runbook accuracy: do runbooks match current system topology?</item>
      <item>Feature relevance: are health-score inputs still predictive?</item>
      <item>Tool adoption: are teams using AIOps capabilities in incident response?</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
