<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="nodejs-patterns Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five antipatterns the scaffold spec must never produce. Each has a symptom, a root cause, and a fix the agent can apply mechanically.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <antipattern id="fm-1-error-handler-first">
      <symptom>Requests that throw return generic Express HTML error pages, never the JSON shape declared in the error_classes. Tests for 404 / 400 paths fail with HTML bodies.</symptom>
      <root-cause>errorHandler middleware was registered before app.use('/api', routes). Express middleware is order-sensitive: an earlier error handler never sees errors thrown by later middleware.</root-cause>
      <fix>Move app.use(errorHandler) to the last line of createApp(). The output contract forbids middleware_order with errorHandler before routes — validate-nodejs-patterns.py catches this automatically.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-2-listen-in-factory">
      <symptom>Test suite cannot run more than one test file in parallel; supertest reports EADDRINUSE; CI flakes randomly on port collisions.</symptom>
      <root-cause>createApp() calls app.listen(PORT) before returning. Every test file that imports createApp now binds a real socket, contending for the same port.</root-cause>
      <fix>Split into app.ts (export createApp(): Express, no listen) and server.ts (const app = createApp(); app.listen(config.PORT)). Tests import createApp() only.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-3-scattered-process-env">
      <symptom>Local dev runs fine; production crashes after the first request with "Cannot read property of undefined" inside a controller. No clear log line points at the missing env var.</symptom>
      <root-cause>process.env.SOMETHING is read inline inside a controller or service. The var was unset in the prod environment; the read returned undefined and was used as a string.</root-cause>
      <fix>Move all process.env reads into config/env.ts, parse with Zod (or equivalent), export a frozen config object. Importing modules get typed, validated values; missing vars fail the process at boot.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-4-missing-async-forward">
      <symptom>Process logs UnhandledPromiseRejection warnings; the response hangs until the client times out; the error handler never fires.</symptom>
      <root-cause>An async route handler threw, but it was registered as router.get('/', async (req, res) =&gt; {...}) without try/catch and without asyncHandler() wrapper. Express 4 does not forward async rejections to next().</root-cause>
      <fix>Wrap every async handler in asyncHandler(fn) (Promise.resolve(fn(...)).catch(next)). Add an ESLint rule (no-misused-promises) to block raw async handlers on routers.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-5-console-log-production">
      <symptom>Log aggregator (Loki / Datadog / CloudWatch) shows unstructured lines that cannot be filtered by requestId or statusCode. Some lines are missing entirely after a crash.</symptom>
      <root-cause>console.log is used inside handlers and services. Output is plain text on stdout, with no JSON shape and no flush-on-exit semantics.</root-cause>
      <fix>Replace every console.* call with logger.info / logger.error from utils/logger.ts. Add a SIGTERM handler that calls logger.flush() before process.exit(0).</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
