<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Discovery to Delivery Handover Protocol Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules with rationale + source for discovery-to-delivery-handover-protocol. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="artefact-bundle-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Handover MUST include nine artefacts: discovery report, SoW with redlines, assumption register, risk register, stakeholder map, glossary, integration list, NFR table, open questions log. Missing any artefact blocks handover.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 solution evaluation perspective">BABOK v3 solution evaluation perspective — applies to Discovery to Delivery Handover Protocol.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="walkthrough-not-email" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Handover MUST include a synchronous walkthrough session of at least 90 minutes with the delivery BA, the pre-sales BA, and the delivery PM; email-only handover is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Outsource handover failure-mode research">Outsource handover failure-mode research — applies to Discovery to Delivery Handover Protocol.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="signed-ack-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Delivery BA MUST sign a written acknowledgement that lists every artefact received and every assumption understood; the signed document is filed with the SoW.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract handover discipline">Contract handover discipline — applies to Discovery to Delivery Handover Protocol.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="hot-line-30-days" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-sales BA remains on a hot-line (named channel, defined SLA) for 30 calendar days post-handover; questions are logged and used to update the discovery playbook.</statement>
      <rationale source="Knowledge-transfer practice">Knowledge-transfer practice — applies to Discovery to Delivery Handover Protocol.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="assumption-disambig" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every assumption in the register MUST be either CONFIRMED (with client sign-off ref), CONDITIONAL (with named trigger), or UNVERIFIED (with mitigation plan); ambiguous 'noted' status is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Assumption-management research">Assumption-management research — applies to Discovery to Delivery Handover Protocol.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="delta-from-discovery" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any delta between discovery findings and delivery setup MUST be logged as a change request, not silently absorbed; deltas become input to the next QBR.</statement>
      <rationale source="Change control discipline">Change control discipline — applies to Discovery to Delivery Handover Protocol.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="client-side-introduction" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Within 5 business days of handover the delivery BA is introduced in writing to every named client-side stakeholder; ghost-introductions are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stakeholder management practice">Stakeholder management practice — applies to Discovery to Delivery Handover Protocol.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If there is no personnel change between discovery and delivery, return `skipped`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to Discovery to Delivery Handover Protocol.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
