<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="devops-aws-service-selection Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for devops-aws-service-selection. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every production architecture MUST be evaluated against all 6 Well-Architected pillars: Operational Excellence, Security, Reliability, Performance Efficiency, Cost Optimization, and Sustainability. The evaluation MUST produce a gap list with priority (High/Medium/Low) per pillar before the first production deployment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Skipping Well-Architected review at design time results in costly retrofits post-launch. Security and Reliability gaps are much cheaper to fix in Terraform before the first deployment than after data is in production.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Compute selection MUST follow this priority: tasks under 15 minutes → Lambda (arm64); container workloads without specific EKS requirements → Fargate; container workloads needing node-level control or service mesh → EKS with Graviton managed node groups; batch processing with fault tolerance → AWS Batch with Spot instances; ML inference → Inferentia2 or Graviton. EC2 is a last resort for legacy or specific OS requirements.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Lambda and Fargate eliminate node management, patching, and capacity planning. Graviton (arm64) costs 20% less than x86 at equivalent performance. Spot instances save up to 90% for interruption-tolerant batch workloads.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Database engine selection MUST be driven by access patterns: relational joins and complex queries → Aurora Serverless v2 PostgreSQL; key-value or document with known access patterns → DynamoDB on-demand; sub-millisecond cache → ElastiCache Serverless; graph relationships → Neptune; document store with mongo-compatible API → DocumentDB. Never default to RDS without evaluating DynamoDB first for new greenfield services.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">DynamoDB scales to millions of requests per second with single-digit millisecond latency at any scale, but only when access patterns fit the key-value model. Aurora Serverless v2 handles relational complexity but requires connection management via RDS Proxy at scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
