<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-experiment-types" title="Micro-MVP Experiment Types">
  <summary>Six micro-MVP experiment types mapped to effort range and what each one validates.</summary>

  <section title="Experiment Catalogue">
    <rule>
      <statement>Match the experiment type to the assumption category. Do not build a landing page to validate willingness-to-pay; use a smoke test instead.</statement>
      <rationale>Each experiment type has a different signal type. Using the wrong type wastes time and produces misleading data.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>Landing page (1 day): validates demand and messaging. Shows a description of the product and measures sign-up rate or email capture.</item>
      <item>Concierge (1 week): validates workflow and core value. Manually deliver the product's promise to 5–10 users to discover the real job-to-be-done.</item>
      <item>Wizard of Oz (days): validates UX and willingness-to-pay. Fake automated product backed by manual human fulfilment; users interact as if it is real.</item>
      <item>Video demo (hours): validates interest and virality. Record the product promise; measure views, shares, and comments before building anything.</item>
      <item>Fake door (hours): validates feature demand. Add a button or menu item for a feature that does not exist yet; measure click rate before building.</item>
      <item>Smoke test (days): validates price sensitivity and conversion. Offer the product for purchase; measure conversion at the target price point before delivering.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Dropbox Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Assumption: people want easy file sync across devices.</note>
      <note>Micro-MVP: a 3-minute video explaining the concept, posted online. No code written.</note>
      <note>Result: waitlist jumped from 5,000 to 75,000 overnight. Validated demand without building a single byte of sync infrastructure.</note>
      <note>Cost: video production time only.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
