<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Micro-MVP Process">
  <summary>Six-step process for designing, running, and acting on a micro-MVP experiment.</summary>

  <section title="The Six Steps">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1: Identify the riskiest assumption — the one belief, if wrong, that kills the product idea entirely.</statement>
      <rationale>Testing a secondary assumption first wastes time. Riskiest assumption first forces prioritisation by existential risk, not build convenience.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2: Design the smallest experiment that can falsify or confirm that single assumption. One assumption per experiment.</statement>
      <rationale>Multi-assumption experiments produce ambiguous results. If the experiment fails, you do not know which assumption was wrong.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3: Define success metrics before starting, not after seeing results. Specify the threshold that means "confirmed" vs "rejected".</statement>
      <rationale>Defining metrics after seeing results produces motivated reasoning. Pre-commitment makes the experiment falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4: Run the experiment in hours to days. If it takes longer than one week, it is not a micro-MVP — split or simplify.</statement>
      <rationale>Speed is the whole point. A week-long micro-MVP competes with a two-week sprint and loses the argument for the lighter method.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5: Analyse results against the pre-defined threshold. Binary outcome: confirmed or rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Avoiding a clear verdict extends limbo. Even a failed experiment is valuable — it redirects effort before a full build.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Step 6: Decide: pivot (change the assumption and test again), persevere (move to building), or test the next riskiest assumption.</statement>
      <rationale>One confirmed micro-MVP is not enough to build. Stack experiments until the top 2–3 existential assumptions are validated before committing to a sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running a micro-MVP for an assumption already validated by strong existing evidence.</description>
      <reason>Over-testing wastes time. Reserve micro-MVPs for genuinely uncertain assumptions; skip experiments where evidence already converges.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping the pre-defined success threshold and interpreting results after the fact.</description>
      <reason>Post-hoc interpretation always finds a way to confirm the hypothesis. Pre-commitment is what makes the experiment honest.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
