<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Terraform IaC Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Terraform IaC methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-workspace-per-env-layer" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each (environment, infra-layer) pair MUST be its own state workspace. prod-network, prod-data, prod-app, staging-network, etc. Cross-workspace dependencies via data sources or remote_state.</statement>
      <rationale source="Terraform Cloud workspace pattern">Mixed-env state lets a dev apply touch prod; blast radius must be physically isolated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-module-from-registry" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reusable patterns MUST come from a registry (Terraform Registry or private) with semver tags. Module callers reference version explicitly. Inline copy-paste forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="module ecosystem best practices">Modules in-place fork on first edit; registry + version enforces shared interface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-no-cross-env-modules" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A module MUST NOT switch behaviour on env name (no if env == 'prod'). Pass behaviour as variables; let callers compose.</statement>
      <rationale source="12-factor for IaC">Env conditionals couple modules to global state; variables keep modules pure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-refactor-via-moved" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Renames / re-parenting of resources MUST use moved blocks (TF &gt;=1.1). state rm + import is reserved for genuine state corruption + requires named owner approval.</statement>
      <rationale source="HashiCorp moved-block docs">moved blocks are reviewable + reversible; state surgery is destructive and bypasses review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-data-source-not-hard-id" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cross-workspace references MUST go through data sources or terraform_remote_state. Hard-coded resource IDs (vpc-abc123) forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Terraform composition patterns">Hard-coded IDs break on re-create; data sources self-heal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-blast-radius-documented" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each workspace MUST document its blast radius: which resources, which env, which downstream services depend on it. Document lives in workspace README.</statement>
      <rationale source="blast-radius-rules-for-multi-component-changes">Implicit blast radius surfaces only during incidents; documenting it lets reviewers reason about plans.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
