<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="viral-optimization">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>growth-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Optimize K-factor by decomposing into i (invites/user) and c (invitee conversion). Fix the weaker leg first. Requires measured baseline K and full event chain tracked.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>viral</tag>
      <tag>k-factor</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>referral</tag>
      <tag>experimentation</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Viral Loop Optimization</title>

    <summary>Viral loop optimization iterates on an existing measured K-factor by decomposing it into its two drivers — i (invites sent per user) and c (invitee conversion rate) — identifying the bottleneck, and running A/B tests on the weakest leg. Optimize c first (invite landing page) before optimizing i (share moments); every improvement to c multiplies all future loop turns.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>K-factor is a compound metric: K = i * c. A small improvement to the lower leg often has larger absolute impact than a large improvement to the higher one. Without funnel decomposition, optimization effort is directed by intuition rather than math. Cycle time is a secondary lever — halving cycle time roughly squares compounding over a quarter.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Product has a working invite/share path and a measured baseline K (even K = 0.05 is enough to start).</item>
        <item>Full event chain is tracked: invite_shown → invite_sent → invite_clicked → invitee_signup → invitee_active.</item>
        <item>A live A/B test framework is available (no code deploy needed to split variants).</item>
        <item>At least 5,000 weekly users entering the loop (otherwise sample size kills experiments).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF: optimizing K of a product nobody loves yields K = 0.0X times any multiplier — still nothing.</item>
        <item>B2B enterprise where sharing is gated by procurement or security — viral mechanics do not translate.</item>
        <item>Markets with strict anti-spam rules (regulated finance, medical, EU consumer) where contact-import is non-compliant.</item>
        <item>Products where the inviter's value requires the invitee to join but the invitee has no standalone reason — forced virality churns invitees fast.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="k-factor-formula">
      <p>Decompose K into i (avg invites sent per user) and c (invitee conversion rate = signups / invites sent) before deciding where to optimize; optimize c first.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Improving c lifts every future loop turn because all future invites benefit from higher conversion; improving i only increases volume into the current conversion rate.</statement>
        <rationale>K = i * c. A small improvement to the lower leg often has larger absolute impact than a large improvement to the higher one.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>K = i * c</item>
        <item>i = total invite_sent events / distinct active users in period</item>
        <item>c = invitee_signup events matched to invite tokens / total invite_sent events</item>
        <item>cycle_time = median days between invite_sent and invitee_signup</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cycle-time-lever">
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure cycle time (p50 days from invite_sent to invitee_signup) and treat it as a primary optimization lever alongside i and c.</statement>
        <rationale>K = 0.4 with 3-day cycle time beats K = 0.7 with 60-day cycle time over a quarter in compounding terms.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>reduce cycle time by: one-click mobile signup, pre-filled email, social login for invitees</item>
        <item>track cycle_time weekly; a sudden increase signals friction introduced in a signup change</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="funnel-metrics">
      <p>Track the full event chain at every stage:</p>
      <list>
        <item>invite_shown: % of active users who see the invite prompt</item>
        <item>invite_sent: % of users who actually send an invite (= share rate)</item>
        <item>invite_clicked: clicks on the invite link by recipients</item>
        <item>invitee_signup: recipients who complete signup</item>
        <item>invitee_active: invitees who reach the activation milestone within D7</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track invitee D30 retention separately from organic D30; if invitee retention is less than 50% of organic, the loop is poisoning the cohort.</statement>
        <rationale>Incentivized loops attract users who join for the reward, not the product; high K with low invitee retention grows the user count but collapses LTV.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="increasing-i-share-moments">
      <rule>
        <statement>Place the share prompt at peak-emotion moments (just completed a milestone, just discovered something great) — not in settings menus.</statement>
        <rationale>Share prompts in settings rely on users seeking them out; achievement-moment prompts capture naturally high intent and produce 3-5x higher share rates.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>achievement trigger (completed goal, hit milestone) → celebration modal with share button</item>
        <item>discovery trigger (found something valuable) → "share with a friend who'd love this"</item>
        <item>social trigger (want to connect) → "invite teammates to collaborate"</item>
        <item>help trigger (need someone else to use it) → collaborative feature invite</item>
      </list>
      <p>Tactics by difficulty and impact:</p>
      <list>
        <item>achievement triggers — easy / high impact</item>
        <item>multi-channel sharing (email, SMS, copy link) — medium / medium</item>
        <item>viral content (shareable badges, results images) — medium / high</item>
        <item>contact import (bulk invite) — hard / high (privacy constraints; iOS/Android blocked post-2021)</item>
        <item>team features that require collaboration — hard / very high</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="increasing-c-invite-landing">
      <rule>
        <statement>Personal invites ("Anna invited you to [Product]") beat brand invites by 20-40% on click and signup; implement with a single DB join on the referral token.</statement>
        <rationale>Named social proof reduces perceived spam risk and creates accountability, increasing click-through before the landing page is even reached.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>personalize invite landing: show inviter name + avatar + their activity context</item>
        <item>add social proof: "join N people using [Product]"</item>
        <item>one-click signup: Google/Apple SSO, pre-filled email from invite token</item>
        <item>show value before signup: preview of what the invitee will access</item>
        <item>mobile-optimize: reduce tap count to 3 or fewer from invite link to activated account</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Requiring signup to view shared content.</description>
        <reason>Forcing pre-signup registration drops invitee conversion by 40-60%; a preview wall converts better than a hard gate.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="incentive-design">
      <rule>
        <statement>Reward at value-realization (invitee reaches activation milestone), not at signup, to cut incentive fraud.</statement>
        <rationale>Signup-triggered rewards are easy to game with fake accounts; activation-triggered rewards require genuine engagement that fraud bots cannot mimic at scale.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>one-time reward: credit after invitee activates</item>
        <item>tiered multi-referral: 1 referral → small reward, 5 → bigger reward + badge, 10 → large reward + premium feature</item>
        <item>two-sided: both inviter and invitee receive reward — higher acceptance rate</item>
        <item>cap one-time rewards but tier multi-referral to capture power-referrers</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="fraud-detection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Instrument a fraud-checker subagent to review referrer-IP / device-graph anomalies before any reward is issued on a new incentive structure.</statement>
        <rationale>Incentivized loops attract self-referrers and bot signups; raw K looks great while real LTV plummets — optimizing without fraud feedback maximizes gameable referrals.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>self-referral: inviter and invitee share the same IP, device fingerprint, or email domain</item>
        <item>bot signups: invitee accounts with zero post-signup events within 24h</item>
        <item>reward farming: single user accumulates more than 10% of all rewards in the period</item>
        <item>velocity anomaly: single referrer sends 10x the median invite rate</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="quality-checks">
      <list>
        <item>invitee D7 retention vs organic D7 retention — flag if invitee is less than 50% of organic</item>
        <item>invitee LTV vs organic LTV at D90 — if less than 60%, incentive is attracting wrong users</item>
        <item>invitee-to-inviter conversion: what % of referred users also invite someone? — secondary K</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Anchor K-factor expectations to category benchmarks, not to case studies — consumer apps: K=0.1-0.3; B2B SaaS: K=0.05-0.2.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents over-cite Dropbox/Spotify Wrapped as if any product can replicate them; unrealistic K targets lead to dark-pattern share mechanics that backfire.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="review-cadence">
      <list>
        <item>weekly: check K-factor trend, invite funnel drop-offs, top referrers, plan next experiment</item>
        <item>monthly: cohort analysis of signups by source, retention of referred vs organic, fraud check, channel performance</item>
        <item>quarterly: review loop type effectiveness, major product change to improve virality, incentive structure, competitive analysis</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Redesign viral loop mechanics every 12-18 months; users learn the pattern and c decays as familiarity reduces novelty.</statement>
        <rationale>"Personalized invite" wins early then plateaus; design for refresh, not permanence.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Where this methodology fails or does not apply:</p>
      <list>
        <item>K is fragile to fraud: incentivized loops attract self-referrers and bot signups; "raw K" looks great while real LTV plummets</item>
        <item>Cycle time matters as much as K; K=0.4 with 3-day cycle beats K=0.7 with 60-day cycle in compounding</item>
        <item>Holdouts are hard to design — network effect of one variant can leak into the control via shared social graphs</item>
        <item>"Personalized invite" wins early then plateaus; users learn the pattern; expect decay</item>
        <item>One-click contact import is dead in iOS/Android post-2021 privacy changes</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF optimization of K of a product nobody loves yields still nothing</item>
        <item>B2B enterprise with procurement/security gates: viral mechanics do not translate</item>
        <item>Anti-spam regulated markets (finance, medical, EU consumer) where contact-import is non-compliant</item>
        <item>Products with forced virality (invitee has no standalone reason to join) churn invitees fast</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive viral optimization with subagents in a tight loop: agent reads K-funnel data, proposes 1-3 hypotheses ranked by Impact x Confidence x Ease, writes A/B-test specs from the experiment-spec template, drafts variant copy, then waits for human green-light before any code or live-channel change. After test maturity, agent runs significance check, summarizes lift, and proposes the next experiment.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>growth-marketer (sonnet) — funnel analysis, hypothesis generation, copy drafts</item>
        <item>data-analyst (sonnet) — K-factor decomposition (i, c, cycle time), invitee-LTV check</item>
        <item>experiment-designer (sonnet) — sample-size math, randomization unit, MDE calc</item>
        <item>fraud-checker (sonnet) — referrer-IP / device-graph anomaly review on referral incentives</item>
      </list>
      <example type="prompt">
        <note>Prompt pattern for K-factor analysis and experiment proposal</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Input: viral_funnel_30d.csv (impressions, sends, clicks, signups, activations by variant, by cohort)
Task: 1) compute i, c, K, cycle_time per cohort
      2) rank top 3 drop-offs by absolute user loss
      3) propose ONE A/B test per drop-off using ab-testing-setup template
Output: yaml with hypothesis, variant_spec, primary_metric, mde, sample_size, days_required
Forbidden: claiming a winner before n >= sample_size AND days >= 14
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools:</p>
      <list>
        <item>growthbook CLI — define experiments, push variant configs; npm i -g @growthbook/cli</item>
        <item>statsig CLI — experiment scaffolding, power calc; https://docs.statsig.com/cli</item>
        <item>posthog CLI — funnel + cohort export, feature flags; npm i -g posthog-node</item>
        <item>branch.io CLI — deferred-deeplink referral attribution; https://help.branch.io</item>
        <item>mixpanel-utils — bulk export of invite/conversion events; pip install mixpanel-utils</item>
      </list>
      <p>Services and apps:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Viral Loops (SaaS, REST+JS SDK) — templated referral campaigns; agent can draft/clone via API</item>
        <item>ReferralCandy (SaaS, REST API) — ecommerce referral, Shopify-native</item>
        <item>Friendbuy (SaaS, REST API) — two-sided referral with anti-fraud built in</item>
        <item>GrowSurf (SaaS, REST API) — waitlist + referral, lightweight</item>
        <item>Branch (SaaS, REST+SDKs) — cross-platform deferred deeplinks for invite attribution</item>
        <item>AppsFlyer / Adjust (SaaS, REST) — mobile attribution; needed for K on iOS/Android</item>
        <item>GrowthBook (OSS+SaaS, REST+GitOps) — A/B framework, agent can author experiments</item>
        <item>Statsig (SaaS, REST+SDKs) — experimentation; CUPED variance reduction</item>
        <item>Optimizely (SaaS, partial agent support) — not ideal for agent-driven experiment creation</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="k-factor-script">
      <p>K-factor decomposition script — compute K and cycle time from event stream CSV:</p>
      <example type="code">
        <note>k-factor.py — Input: events.csv columns: ts (datetime), type, inviter_id, ref_token. Output: i, c, K, cycle_time median.</note>
        <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# k_factor.py — compute K-factor and cycle time from event stream CSV
# Input: events.csv with columns: ts (datetime), type, inviter_id, ref_token
# Output: i, c, K, cycle_time median printed to stdout

import pandas as pd

ev = pd.read_csv("events.csv", parse_dates=["ts"])
inv = ev[ev.type == "invite_sent"]
sig = ev[ev.type == "invitee_signup"]

# Average invites per inviter
i = inv.groupby("inviter_id").size().mean()

# Conversion: signups matched to invite tokens
matched = sig.merge(inv, on="ref_token", suffixes=("_s", "_i"))
c = len(matched) / max(len(inv), 1)

# Cycle time: days from invite_sent to invitee_signup
cycle = (matched.ts_s - matched.ts_i).dt.days
K = i * c

print(f"i={i:.2f}  c={c:.2%}  K={K:.3f}  cycle_p50={cycle.median():.1f}d")

# Decay check: K by inviter cohort week
inv = inv.copy()
inv["cohort"] = inv.ts.dt.to_period("W")
print("\nInvite volume by cohort:")
print(inv.groupby("cohort").size().tail(8).to_string())
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="loop-projection-script">
      <example type="code">
        <note>loop_projection.py — naive viral loop compounding model. Shows whether assumed K + cycle time yields self-sustaining growth over a period.</note>
        <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# loop_projection.py — naive viral loop compounding model
# Shows whether assumed K + cycle time yields self-sustaining growth over a period

def project(starting_users: int, K: float, cycle_days: int, days: int) -> float:
    """
    K: viral coefficient (invites_per_user * conversion_rate) per cycle.
    Returns estimated total user count after `days` assuming no churn.
    """
    cycles = days / cycle_days
    if K >= 1:
        # Exponential growth
        return starting_users * (K ** cycles)
    # Geometric series sum (decaying contribution)
    total = starting_users * (1 - K ** (cycles + 1)) / (1 - K)
    return total


if __name__ == "__main__":
    print(f"{'K':>6}  {'cycle':>7}  {'180d users':>12}")
    print("-" * 30)
    for K in (0.05, 0.10, 0.20, 0.30, 0.50, 0.70, 1.00):
        n = project(1000, K, cycle_days=14, days=180)
        print(f"{K:>6.2f}  {'14d':>7}  {n:>12,.0f}")
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="experiment-spec-template">
      <example type="template">
        <note>experiment-spec.md — K-Factor experiment spec template (hypothesis, primary metric, MDE, variants, anti-fraud checks). Winner declared only when n >= sample_size AND days >= 14.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# K-Factor Experiment: [Name]

## Hypothesis
IF we [change to invite flow / landing page / incentive],
THEN K-factor will increase by [X%]
BECAUSE [mechanism: more share moments / higher conversion / shorter cycle].

## Target Metric
- Primary: K-factor (measured over 28-day rolling window)
- Secondary: i (invites/user), c (conversion rate), cycle_time_p50

## Variants
| Variant | Description |
|---------|-------------|
| Control | [Current state] |
| Treatment | [Proposed change — one change only] |

## Sample Size
- Weekly users entering loop: ______
- Baseline K: ______  (i=____, c=____)
- MDE relative: ____% on c or i (specify which leg)
- n_per_variant: ______  Duration: ______ days

## Anti-Fraud Checks
- [ ] Invitee D7 retention vs organic tracked separately
- [ ] Self-referral IP/device check configured
- [ ] Reward gate: activation required before reward issued

## Decision
Winner declared only when: n >= sample_size AND days >= 14
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Optimize c (invitee conversion) before i (invites sent) — improving the landing page lifts every future loop turn</item>
        <item>Personal invites ("Anna invited you") beat brand invites by 20-40% on click and signup; cost is one DB join</item>
        <item>Reward at value-realization, not at signup — cuts incentive fraud massively</item>
        <item>Track invitee D30 retention separately; if less than 50% of organic, the loop is poisoning the cohort</item>
        <item>Cap one-time rewards but tier multi-referral (5 referrals → bigger reward, 25 → premium tier) to capture power-referrers</item>
        <item>Move share moments to peak emotion (just-completed-a-thing), not to settings menus</item>
        <item>K = 0.4 with 3-day cycle beats K = 0.7 with 60-day cycle over a quarter — optimize cycle time too</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Agents cite "+125x improvement" case studies as if achievable — anchor to category K: consumer apps 0.1-0.3, B2B SaaS 0.05-0.2</item>
        <item>LLMs invent invite-copy claims ("join 50,000 people") that are factually wrong; require numeric claims as inputs, not produced</item>
        <item>Agent must check sample size and runtime against MDE before declaring a winner; otherwise it ships noise</item>
        <item>Two-sided incentives change unit economics — require pricing-reviewer approval for any new reward structure</item>
        <item>Contact-import ideas from LLMs often violate platform TOS or privacy law (CASL, GDPR, CCPA); filter at template stage</item>
        <item>Fraud detection is adversarial; agent optimizing without fraud feedback will recommend mechanics that maximize gameable referrals</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="references">
      <list>
        <item>Andrew Chen, "What's your viral loop?" — https://andrewchen.com/whats-your-viral-loop</item>
        <item>Adam Penenberg, "Viral Loop" (book, 2009)</item>
        <item>Reforge, "Growth Models" — https://www.reforge.com/blog/growth-loops</item>
        <item>Lenny Rachitsky, "How the biggest consumer apps got their first 1000 users" — https://www.lennysnewsletter.com</item>
        <item>Jonah Berger, "Contagious: Why Things Catch On" (book)</item>
        <item>Branch, "Mobile attribution for viral loops" — https://branch.io/blog</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </content>
</methodology>
