<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="viral-optimization">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>growth-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Viral loop optimization iterates on an existing measured K-factor by decomposing it into its two drivers — i (invites sent per user) and c (invitee conversion rate) — identifying the bottleneck, and running A/B tests on the weakest leg. Optimize c first (invite landing page) before optimizing i (share moments); every improvement to c multiplies all future loop turns.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>viral-loops</tag>
      <tag>k-factor</tag>
      <tag>optimization</tag>
      <tag>experimentation</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>viral</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Viral Loop Optimization</title>

    <summary>Viral loop optimization iterates on an existing measured K-factor by decomposing it into its two drivers — i (invites sent per user) and c (invitee conversion rate) — identifying the bottleneck, and running A/B tests on the weakest leg. Optimize c first (invite landing page) before optimizing i (share moments); every improvement to c multiplies all future loop turns.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>K-factor is a compound metric: K = i * c. A small improvement to the lower leg often has larger absolute impact than a large improvement to the higher one. Without funnel decomposition, optimization effort is directed by intuition rather than math. Cycle time is a secondary lever — halving cycle time roughly squares compounding over a quarter.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Product has a working invite/share path and a measured baseline K (even K = 0.05 is enough to start).</item>
        <item>Full event chain is tracked: invite_shown → invite_sent → invite_clicked → invitee_signup → invitee_active.</item>
        <item>A live A/B test framework is available (no code deploy needed to split variants).</item>
        <item>At least 5,000 weekly users entering the loop (otherwise sample size kills experiments).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF: optimizing K of a product nobody loves yields K = 0.0X times any multiplier — still nothing.</item>
        <item>B2B enterprise where sharing is gated by procurement or security — viral mechanics do not translate.</item>
        <item>Markets with strict anti-spam rules (regulated finance, EU consumer) where contact-import is non-compliant.</item>
        <item>Products where the inviter's value requires the invitee to join but the invitee has no standalone reason — forced virality churns invitees fast.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="k-factor-formula">
      <rule>
        <statement>Decompose K into i (avg invites sent per user) and c (invitee conversion rate = signups / invites sent) before deciding where to optimize; optimize c first.</statement>
        <rationale>Improving c lifts every future loop turn because all future invites benefit from higher conversion; improving i only increases volume into the current conversion rate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>K = i * c</item>
        <item>i = total invite_sent events / distinct active users in period</item>
        <item>c = invitee_signup events matched to invite tokens / total invite_sent events</item>
        <item>cycle_time = median days between invite_sent and invitee_signup</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cycle-time-lever">
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure cycle time (p50 days from invite_sent to invitee_signup) and treat it as a primary optimization lever alongside i and c.</statement>
        <rationale>K = 0.4 with 3-day cycle time beats K = 0.7 with 60-day cycle time over a quarter in compounding terms.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>reduce cycle time by: one-click mobile signup, pre-filled email, social login for invitees</item>
        <item>track cycle_time weekly; a sudden increase signals friction introduced in a signup change</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="funnel-metrics-to-track">
      <list>
        <item>invite_shown: % of active users who see the invite prompt</item>
        <item>invite_sent: % of users who actually send an invite (= share rate)</item>
        <item>invite_clicked: clicks on the invite link by recipients</item>
        <item>invitee_signup: recipients who complete signup</item>
        <item>invitee_active: invitees who reach the activation milestone within D7</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track invitee D30 retention separately from organic D30; if invitee retention is &lt;50% of organic, the loop is poisoning the cohort.</statement>
        <rationale>Incentivized loops attract users who join for the reward, not the product; high K with low invitee retention grows the user count but collapses LTV.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="increasing-i-share-moments">
      <rule>
        <statement>Place the share prompt at peak-emotion moments (just completed a milestone, just discovered something great) — not in settings menus.</statement>
        <rationale>Share prompts in settings rely on users seeking them out; achievement-moment prompts capture naturally high intent and produce 3–5x higher share rates.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>achievement trigger (completed goal, hit milestone) → celebration modal with share button</item>
        <item>discovery trigger (found something valuable) → "share with a friend who'd love this"</item>
        <item>social trigger (want to connect) → "invite teammates to collaborate"</item>
        <item>help trigger (need someone else to use it) → collaborative feature invite</item>
      </list>
      <p>Tactics by difficulty and impact:</p>
      <list>
        <item>achievement triggers — easy / high impact</item>
        <item>multi-channel sharing (email, SMS, copy link) — medium / medium</item>
        <item>viral content (shareable badges, results images) — medium / high</item>
        <item>contact import (bulk invite) — hard / high (privacy constraints; iOS/Android blocked post-2021)</item>
        <item>team features that require collaboration — hard / very high</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="increasing-c-invite-landing-page">
      <rule>
        <statement>Personal invites ("Anna invited you to [Product]") beat brand invites by 20–40% on click and signup; implement with a single DB join on the referral token.</statement>
        <rationale>Named social proof reduces perceived spam risk and creates accountability, increasing click-through before the landing page is even reached.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>personalize invite landing: show inviter name + avatar + their activity context</item>
        <item>add social proof: "join N people using [Product]"</item>
        <item>one-click signup: Google/Apple SSO, pre-filled email from invite token</item>
        <item>show value before signup: preview of what the invitee will access</item>
        <item>mobile-optimize: reduce tap count to ≤3 from invite link to activated account</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Requiring signup to view shared content.</description>
        <reason>Forcing pre-signup registration drops invitee conversion by 40–60%; a preview wall converts better than a hard gate.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="incentive-design">
      <rule>
        <statement>Reward at value-realization (invitee reaches activation milestone), not at signup, to cut incentive fraud.</statement>
        <rationale>Signup-triggered rewards are easy to game with fake accounts; activation-triggered rewards require genuine engagement that fraud bots cannot mimic at scale.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>one-time reward: $10 credit after invitee activates</item>
        <item>tiered multi-referral: 1 referral → $10, 5 → $50 + badge, 10 → $100 + premium feature</item>
        <item>two-sided: both inviter and invitee receive reward — higher acceptance rate</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="fraud-detection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Instrument a fraud-checker subagent to review referrer-IP / device-graph anomalies before any reward is issued on a new incentive structure.</statement>
        <rationale>Incentivized loops attract self-referrers and bot signups; raw K looks great while real LTV plummets — "optimizing" without fraud feedback maximizes gameable referrals.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>self-referral: inviter and invitee share the same IP, device fingerprint, or email domain</item>
        <item>bot signups: invitee accounts with zero post-signup events within 24h</item>
        <item>reward farming: single user accumulates &gt;10% of all rewards in the period</item>
        <item>velocity anomaly: single referrer sends 10x the median invite rate</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="quality-checks">
      <list>
        <item>invitee D7 retention vs organic D7 retention — flag if invitee is &lt;50% of organic</item>
        <item>invitee LTV vs organic LTV at D90 — if &lt;60%, incentive is attracting wrong users</item>
        <item>invitee-to-inviter conversion: what % of referred users also invite someone? — secondary K</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Anchor K-factor expectations to category benchmarks, not to the README's case study — consumer apps: K=0.1–0.3; B2B SaaS: K=0.05–0.2.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents over-cite Dropbox/Spotify Wrapped as if any product can replicate them; unrealistic K targets lead to dark-pattern share mechanics that backfire.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="review-cadence">
      <list>
        <item>weekly: check K-factor trend, invite funnel drop-offs, top referrers, plan next experiment</item>
        <item>monthly: cohort analysis of signups by source, retention of referred vs organic, fraud check, channel performance</item>
        <item>quarterly: review loop type effectiveness, major product change to improve virality, incentive structure, competitive analysis</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Redesign viral loop mechanics every 12–18 months; users learn the pattern and c decays as familiarity reduces novelty.</statement>
        <rationale>"Personalized invite" wins early then plateaus; design for refresh, not permanence.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/k-factor.py" purpose="K-factor decomposition from event stream CSV"/>
      <template path="templates/loop-projection.py" purpose="Naive compounding model for K + cycle time projection"/>
      <template path="templates/experiment-spec.md" purpose="K-factor experiment spec template (hypothesis, primary metric, MDE, variants)"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.forentrepreneurs.com/lessons-learnt-viral-marketing/"/>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/courses/growth-loops"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
