<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="WBS Core Principles">
  <summary>The four WBS principles: deliverable orientation, hierarchical decomposition, the 100% rule, and work-package criteria — and why each prevents a distinct planning failure mode.</summary>

  <section title="Deliverable Orientation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every WBS node name must be a noun (deliverable or sub-deliverable), never a verb or activity; verbs belong in the schedule, not the WBS.</statement>
      <rationale>Activity-oriented WBSs silently drift into Gantt charts, losing the deliverable focus that enables acceptance criteria, traceability, and cost rollup. A noun-named WBS forces the team to answer "what will exist?" before "what will we do?"</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Verb-led names: "Design database schema", "Implement user authentication", "Test payment integration". These are schedule activities, not deliverables.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Noun-led names: "Database schema", "User authentication module", "Payment integration". Completion of each produces a testable artifact.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Hierarchical Decomposition">
    <p>WBS levels follow a standard hierarchy:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Level 1 — Project (one node, the project name).</item>
      <item>Level 2 — Major deliverables (product components, project phases, or functional areas).</item>
      <item>Level 3 — Sub-deliverables within each major deliverable.</item>
      <item>Level 4 — Work packages: the lowest level, estimable and assignable.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit WBS depth to five levels maximum; branches deeper than five are over-decomposed and belong in the task list or schedule, not the WBS.</statement>
      <rationale>Over-decomposition produces a WBS that functions as a task list, losing its value as a high-level scope map. Level 5 work packages are typically under eight hours and cannot be meaningfully baselined or controlled at the WBS level.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="100% Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>At every level, the sum of child nodes must capture 100% of the parent's scope — no more, no less; verify by asking "if all children are complete, is the parent complete?"</statement>
      <rationale>100% rule violations are the primary cause of forgotten scope; missing items at any level create work that must be absorbed informally, driving schedule and cost overrun without appearing as a scope change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include a "Project Management" branch (e.g., 1.X) capturing planning, status reporting, stakeholder management, and project closure; projects that omit PM scope underestimate effort by 10-20%.</statement>
      <rationale>PM work is real work; not scoping it creates a structural underestimate that forces the PM to absorb costs from other work packages, distorting EVM indices and schedule performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Work Package Criteria">
    <p>A valid work package meets all four criteria:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Estimable — can be assigned a credible hours or days estimate (8-80 hour guideline).</item>
      <item>Assignable — can be delegated to one person or one team with clear accountability.</item>
      <item>Measurable — has a clear "done" criterion against which completion can be verified.</item>
      <item>Mutually exclusive — does not overlap with any sibling work package.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
