<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="WBS Creation Rules and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Rules for WBS dictionary discipline, ID stability after baseline lock, agentic decomposition, and the anti-patterns that destroy WBS traceability.</summary>

  <section title="WBS Dictionary">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write a WBS dictionary entry for every work package before locking the baseline; numbers without definitions confuse estimators and make acceptance criteria disputes inevitable.</statement>
      <rationale>WBS IDs become references in contracts, schedules, RTMs, and risk registers; without a dictionary, WBS-1.2.3 means different things to different readers, breaking traceability at every integration point.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Required dictionary fields per work package: WBS ID, name, description, deliverable (what is produced), acceptance criteria (how completion is verified), owner, predecessor WBS IDs, effort estimate, cost estimate.</p>
    <reference path="templates/wbs-dictionary-entry.md">WBS dictionary entry template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="ID Stability">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never renumber WBS IDs after baseline lock; mark removed nodes as "deprecated" and their ID as retired; IDs are referenced by contracts, schedules, and registers that cannot be retroactively updated.</statement>
      <rationale>Re-numbering after baseline creates a version mismatch: change requests reference WBS-1.2.3 which no longer exists in the current structure, making the audit trail unresolvable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the WBS at the work-package level for the baseline; detail below work-package level (individual tasks, sub-tasks) belongs in the schedule and can evolve without a scope change request.</statement>
      <rationale>Locking task-level detail in the WBS baseline makes minor scheduling adjustments into scope changes, which adds bureaucratic overhead without improving control.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic WBS Authoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>The WBS-authoring agent must produce noun-led names only; the system prompt must enforce this constraint because LLMs default to activity-oriented (verb-led) decomposition.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs are trained on project management content that mixes WBS and task-list formats; without explicit enforcement, the output looks like a schedule, not a WBS, and the deliverable focus is lost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>The agent must emit a coverage rationale per parent node ("this node is 100% covered by its children because...") to support the 100% rule verification that human reviewers cannot mechanically verify at scale.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated 100% rule checking is difficult without domain knowledge; the agent's coverage rationale shifts the verification burden to explaining its reasoning, which human reviewers can evaluate faster than checking completeness from scratch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/wbs_lint.py">WBS linter: detects verb-led names, depth violations, missing PM branch</reference>
    <reference path="templates/wbs-outline.md">WBS outline template in Markdown format</reference>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Inconsistent decomposition depth across branches — one branch detailed to level 5, another stays at level 2.</description>
      <reason>Inconsistent depth produces inconsistent work-package sizes; large packages are unestimable and hide dependencies, small packages add tracking overhead without control benefit. Aim for consistent 40-80 hour work packages across the WBS.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
