<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-value-and-models" title="Value Analysis and Pricing Models">
  <summary>How to calculate cost floor, measure customer value ceiling, use Van Westendorp surveys to find acceptable price range, and select the right pricing model.</summary>

  <section title="Value-Based Pricing Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set price at 10–20% of the measurable value delivered to customers. If your product saves $500/month, charge $50–100/month.</statement>
      <rationale>Cost-plus pricing ignores value and systematically underprices. Competitor-copying ignores differentiation. Value-based pricing anchors the conversation to ROI, which is why customers buy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cost Floor Calculation">
    <p>Sum fixed costs (hosting, tools, salaries), variable costs per customer (support time, API calls), and opportunity cost (your time at hourly rate x hours). This floor is the minimum viable price — below it, the business loses money.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Customer Value Ceiling">
    <p>Quantify value across four types: time saved (hours/month x customer's hourly rate), money saved (cost reduction vs. alternatives), money earned (revenue increase enabled), and risk reduced (cost of problems prevented). The ceiling is the maximum a rational customer would pay.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Van Westendorp Willingness-to-Pay Survey">
    <rule>
      <statement>Ask these four questions to find the acceptable price range: (1) Too expensive? (2) Expensive but worth considering? (3) A bargain? (4) So cheap it raises quality concerns? The optimal price is the intersection of "too cheap" and "expensive" responses.</statement>
      <rationale>Van Westendorp avoids anchoring bias (you don't suggest price points) and surfaces both the floor and ceiling from the buyer's perspective. Minimum sample: 30 target customers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pricing Model Selection">
    <list>
      <item>Flat rate — simple products with uniform value delivery. One price, all features.</item>
      <item>Tiered (Good/Better/Best) — feature differentiation exists; anchors the middle tier as the obvious choice.</item>
      <item>Usage-based — value delivery is variable (API calls, seats, volume). Pay-per-unit aligns cost with value received.</item>
      <item>Per-seat — team tools where value scales with users. Price per user per month.</item>
      <item>Freemium — high volume, low-touch; free tier generates leads, paid converts them.</item>
      <item>Hybrid (base + usage) — SaaS with variable infrastructure costs; base covers fixed, usage covers variable.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
