<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-tier-design" title="Tier Structure and Psychological Pricing">
  <summary>How to design tier structures (feature allocation, anchor tier), apply psychological pricing tactics, and read signals to raise or lower price.</summary>

  <section title="Recommended Tier Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design a maximum of 3–4 tiers. Label them by target persona outcome (Starter, Pro, Team), not by technical features (Basic, Advanced, Enterprise).</statement>
      <rationale>More than 4 options causes decision paralysis and lowers conversion. Persona labels help buyers self-select; feature labels force them to compare specs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Make the middle tier the obvious anchor: give it the name "Pro" or "Growth", badge it "Most Popular", and price it at your target revenue mix. Free/Basic should be limited enough to create genuine upgrade motivation.</statement>
      <rationale>Decoy pricing — the presence of a higher-priced option makes the middle look reasonable. "Most Popular" reduces social risk ("others have chosen this"). Free tier that gives too much removes the upgrade incentive.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Psychological Pricing Tactics">
    <list>
      <item>Charm pricing ($49 vs $50): left-digit effect makes the number feel significantly lower. Use for sub-$200 price points.</item>
      <item>Round pricing ($100, $500): signals premium quality. Use for high-end enterprise or luxury positioning.</item>
      <item>Anchor high: show the most expensive tier first (left to right), so middle and lower tiers feel affordable.</item>
      <item>Annual framing: present as "2 months free" rather than a percentage discount — tangible months feel more concrete than abstract percentages.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Price Adjustment Signals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Raise price when: conversion rate exceeds 5%, customers volunteer "this is cheap", no price objections appear in sales calls, or churn is below 2%/month.</statement>
      <rationale>High conversion at current price means willingness-to-pay is higher. You are leaving revenue on the table. Raise in 20–30% increments and re-measure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Lower price (or restructure tiers) when: conversion rate is below 1%, price objections appear in more than 30% of sales calls, or sales cycles are unusually long.</statement>
      <rationale>Below 1% conversion signals that price is above willingness-to-pay for this audience. Investigate whether the barrier is price or unclear value before lowering.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Tier Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Never changing prices after initial launch.</description>
      <reason>Market evolves. Costs change. Competitors adjust. Quarterly price review prevents gradual value misalignment.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hiding prices behind "contact us" for sub-$1K ARR products.</description>
      <reason>Friction and distrust. Buyers expect transparent pricing for self-serve products. "Contact us" signals the price will be painful or negotiated, which repels price-sensitive early adopters.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
