<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-experiment-types" title="Micro-MVP Experiment Types">
  <summary>Six micro-MVP types with effort, what each validates, and the conditions under which each is the right choice.</summary>

  <section title="Experiment Type Catalog">
    <rule>
      <statement>Landing page (1 day): validates demand and messaging. Use when the core question is "do people want this?" Measure: signup or waitlist conversion rate against a pre-registered threshold.</statement>
      <rationale>A landing page with a CTA isolates demand signal from product quality signal. The Dropbox 3-minute video generated a 75K waitlist from 5K overnight at cost of video production time only.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Concierge (1 week): validates workflow fit and value delivery. Use when the question is "does this process actually help users?" A human manually delivers the service. Measure: task completion rate, willingness to return.</statement>
      <rationale>Concierge MVPs reveal process failures before automating them. Automating a broken workflow is more expensive than discovering it is broken during manual delivery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Wizard of Oz (days): validates UX and willingness to pay. The user sees a polished interface; humans operate the backend manually. Limit to approximately 50 concurrent users before manual operation collapses.</statement>
      <rationale>Decouples UX validation from automation cost. Answers "would users pay for this experience?" without building the engine.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Video demo (hours): validates interest and virality. Use for consumer products where the value is immediately demonstrable. Measure: shares, comment sentiment, waitlist signups.</statement>
      <rationale>Video is the cheapest signal for "does this concept resonate?" not "does this work?" Do not use as a willingness-to-pay signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Fake door (hours): validates feature demand. Show a button or menu item for a non-existent feature. Measure: click-through rate. Requires ethical unwind: inform users the feature does not exist yet.</statement>
      <rationale>Fake doors measure intent, not interest. A user who clicks "Export to CSV" intended to use it. Plan the ethical unwind before launch — users who discover the deception lose trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Smoke test / Stripe Payment Link (days): validates price sensitivity and willingness to pay. Show a pricing page with a real checkout. The only reliable willingness-to-pay signal is the credit-card moment.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-reported willingness to pay (surveys) overstates actual behavior by 3-5x. A Stripe checkout with real money is the only honest signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <note>Dropbox: assumed people wanted easy file sync. Micro-MVP: 3-minute video explaining the concept. Result: waitlist from 5K to 75K overnight. Cost: only video production time. Validated demand before writing a single line of sync code.</note>
  </example>
  <example type="bad">
    <note>Running a concierge MVP beyond 50 concurrent users without automating anything. The team discovers it is now operating a service business, not validating a product hypothesis.</note>
  </example>
</text>
