<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Micro-MVP 6-Step Process">
  <summary>Sequential steps from identifying the riskiest assumption to the pivot/persevere/next-assumption decision.</summary>

  <section title="Process Steps">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — Identify the riskiest assumption. Rank assumptions by: (a) falsifiability — can it be tested cheaply? (b) impact if wrong — would the product fail? The riskiest assumption is high impact AND currently unverified.</statement>
      <rationale>Testing a low-impact assumption cheaply wastes a week. Testing an unfalsifiable assumption wastes indefinitely. The intersection of high-impact and falsifiable is where micro-MVPs produce the best ROI.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Design the smallest experiment to test that specific assumption. One assumption per experiment. Cap experiment cost at one week of work. If building it takes longer, decompose further.</statement>
      <rationale>Compound experiments yield ambiguous results. If the hypothesis is wrong, you cannot identify which assumption failed. Single-assumption experiments produce clean decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Pre-register the success criterion before building anything. Define the metric, threshold, minimum sample size, and traffic source. Commit this in a file or document before any traffic touches the asset.</statement>
      <rationale>Deciding the threshold after seeing the data is post-hoc rationalization. Pre-registration forces honesty about what "success" means before survivorship bias sets in.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Run the experiment. Duration: hours to days. Plan the ethical unwind before launch, especially for fake-door experiments collecting user data.</statement>
      <rationale>The ethical unwind (what happens to signups if the product is not built) must be planned before launch, not after. A 200-email waitlist with no follow-up is a trust violation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5 — Analyze results against the pre-registered criterion. Allow at most one extension of up to 7 additional days if the sample size is insufficient. After one extension, make a decision on available data.</statement>
      <rationale>Indefinite extensions are equivalent to not having a success criterion. The hard cap forces a decision even under uncertainty, which is the point of the experiment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 6 — Decide: pivot (assumption was wrong, try a different approach), persevere (assumption validated, build), or move to next assumption (this one is not the bottleneck). After three failed micro-MVPs on the same problem space, drop the problem space.</statement>
      <rationale>Three failed experiments on a problem space is evidence the problem is not worth solving, not that the experiments are poorly designed. Sunk-cost bias keeps teams iterating past the signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/experiment-preregistration.yaml">Pre-registration card with hypothesis, success criterion, and decision rule</reference>
</text>
