<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-antipatterns" title="Micro-MVP Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Failure modes that produce invalid learning or waste resources, with root causes.</summary>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Validation theatre: a beautifully designed landing page with no distribution plan. The page converts at 0.1% from cold ads but the team declares "validated."</description>
    <reason>The traffic source determines the signal quality more than the asset does. The same page hits 10% on Hacker News Show HN and 0.5% on cold ads. Require an explicit traffic source in the pre-registration before any asset is built.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Compound experiments: testing two assumptions simultaneously (e.g. demand AND price sensitivity on the same landing page).</description>
    <reason>When the hypothesis is wrong, you cannot identify which assumption failed. Single-assumption experiments produce actionable decisions; compound experiments produce ambiguous data that justifies continuing.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Post-hoc threshold setting: deciding whether the experiment "succeeded" after seeing the conversion data.</description>
    <reason>Survivorship bias makes any result look like it was close to success. Pre-registration removes the ability to move the goalposts after seeing the outcome.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Inflated asset bundle: building case studies, customer logos, and testimonials for a one-week experiment.</description>
    <reason>A micro-MVP needs a headline, sub-headline, three value-prop bullets, and a CTA. Additional content delays launch and adds signal noise. Cap copy explicitly.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Fake-door experiment with no ethical unwind plan. Users click "Get Early Access" and receive no follow-up.</description>
    <reason>Trust violation. Transparency is required: inform users the feature does not exist yet and offer them something real (a waitlist, a refund, a free trial). Plan this before launch.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Declaring "inconclusive, extend" after every failed experiment. Maximum one 7-day extension; then make a decision on available data.</description>
    <reason>Indefinite extensions are equivalent to having no success criterion. The purpose of the experiment is to produce a decision under uncertainty, not to wait for certainty.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
