<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="micro-mvps Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for micro-mvps as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Validation theatre: a beautifully designed landing page with no distribution plan. The page converts at 0.1% from cold ads but the team declares "validated."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The traffic source determines the signal quality more than the asset does. The same page hits 10% on Hacker News Show HN and 0.5% on cold ads. Require an explicit traffic source in the pre-registration before any asset is built.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Compound experiments: testing two assumptions simultaneously (e.g. demand AND price sensitivity on the same landing page).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>When the hypothesis is wrong, you cannot identify which assumption failed. Single-assumption experiments produce actionable decisions; compound experiments produce ambiguous data that justifies continuing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Post-hoc threshold setting: deciding whether the experiment "succeeded" after seeing the conversion data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Survivorship bias makes any result look like it was close to success. Pre-registration removes the ability to move the goalposts after seeing the outcome.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Inflated asset bundle: building case studies, customer logos, and testimonials for a one-week experiment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A micro-MVP needs a headline, sub-headline, three value-prop bullets, and a CTA. Additional content delays launch and adds signal noise. Cap copy explicitly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Fake-door experiment with no ethical unwind plan. Users click "Get Early Access" and receive no follow-up.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Trust violation. Transparency is required: inform users the feature does not exist yet and offer them something real (a waitlist, a refund, a free trial). Plan this before launch.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Declaring "inconclusive, extend" after every failed experiment. Maximum one 7-day extension; then make a decision on available data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Indefinite extensions are equivalent to having no success criterion. The purpose of the experiment is to produce a decision under uncertainty, not to wait for certainty.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs ship "validation theatre" — beautifully written landing pages with no real distribution plan. Force the prompt to include a traffic-source section.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Language models optimize for coherent prose, not distribution strategy. Without explicit prompting, they produce polished but untestable outputs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Models hallucinate plausible conversion-rate benchmarks ("industry standard is 8%"). Require citation or omit; otherwise the success criterion is anchored on fiction.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Plausible-sounding numbers get cached into decision-making even when unsourced.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents will inflate the asset bundle (case studies, logos, testimonials) for a 1-week experiment. Cap copy length explicitly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without constraints, models default to comprehensive design, not minimal validation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Post-experiment, agents have a strong bias to declare "inconclusive, extend." Force the decision rule with a hard cap (e.g. max 1 extension).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models optimize for narrative coherence; inconclusive results generate more coherent extended narratives than hard decisions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Human-in-loop checkpoint: pre-registration commit before any traffic touches the asset. Agents can draft, humans must approve.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-registration integrity requires human sign-off; agents cannot bind themselves to thresholds.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Human-in-loop checkpoint: ethical unwind plan must be human-signed, especially for fake-door experiments that collect data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Ethical compliance requires human accountability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Do not let the agent run the post-mortem alone — it tends to weave a coherent narrative regardless of result, masking learning.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models prioritize narrative closure over accurate causal inference.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
