<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="user-interviews">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>Conduct structured conversations with target customers via the Mom Test framework to understand problems, behaviors, and needs.</summary>
    <category>research</category>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>research</tag>
      <tag>interviews</tag>
      <tag>users</tag>
      <tag>discovery</tag>
      <tag>validation</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>User Interviews</title>

    <summary>Founders skip user interviews or conduct them poorly. Common issues: asking leading questions, pitching instead of listening, accepting "I would" instead of "I did", not reaching enough people, and lacking systematic analysis of findings. User interviews are structured conversations with target customers to understand their problems, behaviors, and needs. Apply the Mom Test principles: talk about their life not your idea, ask about specifics in the past not generics about the future, and talk less and listen more.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>The root cause of poor user research is having no framework for extracting honest, actionable insights. Teams revert to leading questions and pitch-mode under pressure. Recall bias leads respondents to reconstruct past behavior optimistically. Sample bias from warm-network recruits skews positive. Without systematic analysis, patterns don't emerge until too late.</p>
      <p>User interviews are the fastest way to surface latent jobs, pains, and current solutions before building. They bridge the gap between what people say they want and what they actually do. Conducted well, they expose contradictions and reveal problems you didn't know existed. The Mom Test framework prevents the universal failure mode: asking would you use this and accepting yes as validation when the person will never actually use it.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-MVP discovery to surface latent jobs, pains, and current solutions before committing to build.</item>
        <item>After launch when quantitative metrics show drop-off but root cause is unclear from data alone.</item>
        <item>Persona refinement and segmentation work to refine who your customers actually are.</item>
        <item>Pricing and packaging research when willingness to pay is unknown or varies by segment.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>For statistically significant claims. Interviews surface themes and patterns, not percentages. Use surveys after themes stabilize for larger sample.</item>
        <item>When you can already observe behavior via analytics or session recordings. Behavioral data trumps stated experience.</item>
        <item>For commodity or well-understood markets where interviews will repeat existing knowledge.</item>
        <item>As a substitute for behavioral validation. Interviews don't prove anyone will pay. They expose problems.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="mom-test-principles">
      <p>Rob Fitzpatrick's The Mom Test gives three principles for extracting truth from conversations. Talk about their life, not your idea. Ask about specifics in the past, not generics about the future. Talk less, listen more.</p>

      <p>Good vs Bad Questions. Bad: Would you use this? Good: How do you solve this now? Bad: Do you like this idea? Good: What did you try last time? Bad: How much would you pay? Good: What have you paid for solutions? Bad: Is this a problem? Good: Tell me about the last time this frustrated you.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every interview question must reference a past specific event, not a hypothetical future. Scan questions for would, imagine, hypothetically, do you think. If found, rewrite as past-tense behavioral.</statement>
        <rationale>Hypothetical questions elicit wishful thinking and what people think they should want. Specific past events reveal actual behavior and real constraints.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="interview-process">
      <p>Follow these five steps to conduct interviews that yield actionable insights. Skip any step and interviews become conversations or pitches instead of research.</p>

      <p>Step 1: Define Research Goals. Start with specific learning goals, not general curiosity. We want to learn: [Specific question about behavior]. [Specific question about pain points]. [Specific question about current solutions]. We'll know we're done when: [Criteria for enough interviews]. [Pattern threshold]. Example: We want to learn: How do freelancers currently bill clients? What alternatives have they tried? How much time do they spend on billing? We'll know we're done when we interview 10 different freelancers and see at least two clear billing patterns.</p>

      <p>Step 2: Recruit Participants. Different recruiting sources have different response rates and biases. LinkedIn (Cold DM, 5-10% response). Twitter or X (Reply plus DM, 10-20% response). Reddit (Post in niche subs, response varies). Communities (Slack or Discord, 20-30% response). Cold email (Find company emails, 2-5% response). Referrals (Ask interviewees for intros, 40%+ response). Warm-network recruits skew positive and homogeneous because they know you and want to help. Cold recruiting is harder and slower but produces cleaner data. Referrals from satisfied customers provide credibility and reach similar audiences without pure warm-network bias. Start with referrals, move to cold outreach for segment validation.</p>

      <p>Outreach template: Hi [Name], I'm researching [topic] and noticed you [relevant context]. Would you spare 20 minutes to share your experience with [problem]? No selling just trying to understand the problem better. Happy to share findings afterward or [offer incentive]. Best, [Your name].</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>End every interview with a referral ask: Do you know 2-3 other people who face similar challenges? Referrals dominate cold recruiting and reduce warm-network sample bias.</statement>
        <rationale>Warm-network recruits skew positive and homogeneous. Referrals from satisfied customers provide credibility and reach similar (but not identical) audiences.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Step 3: Prepare Interview Script. Structure interviews for 20-30 minutes and don't go longer than 30 because fatigue sets in. Warm-up (2-3 min) to build rapport and explain the format (Thanks for chatting. I'm researching X and trying to understand how people handle Y. This is not a sales call. Mind if I record? It stays confidential.). Context (3-5 min) to understand their situation (What's your role? What does a typical week look like? Where does this fit into your priorities?). Problem exploration (10-15 min) to dig into specific experiences (Walk me through the last time you dealt with X. What happened? How did you handle it? What was the hardest part? How often does this come up?). Solutions tried (5 min) to learn what they've used (What have you tried? How did that work? What do you use now? What do you like/dislike?). Wrap-up (2-3 min) to ask for referrals (Is there anything I should have asked? Do you know 2-3 others who face this?).</p>

      <p>Key question types for problem exploration. Open-ended: Walk me through how you handle X. Let them tell the story. Follow-up: Tell me more about that. Don't let vague answers slide. Specific: What happened last time? Ground them in a real past event. Quantifying: How often does this occur? Get frequency. Emotional: How did that make you feel? Understand the impact and frustration level.</p>

      <p>Step 4: Conduct the Interview. During the conversation, follow these practices. Do: Record (with permission). Take brief notes on emotions and reactions (excited, frustrated, confused). Follow their lead, not your script. Ask why five times to get to root cause (Why did that fail? Why did you choose X over Y? Why does this matter?). Sit with silence and let them think. Pauses are uncomfortable but they give people space to remember and think deeply. Don't: Pitch your solution. Correct or argue. Fill silences immediately. Ask multiple questions at once. Accept vague answers without clarification. Say yeah, yeah to confirm understanding when you should be listening.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Record plus transcribe everything (with consent). Memory after 4 interviews is worthless. Pre-prime transcription tools with a glossary of likely technical terms and proper nouns to reduce mis-attribution.</statement>
        <rationale>Recording prevents recall bias and provides exact quotes for synthesis. Transcription allows pattern detection across interviews without memory decay from interview fatigue.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Step 5: Analyze Findings. Systematic analysis turns raw interviews into actionable patterns. Analyze after each interview, then again after every 3 interviews. After each interview document key quotes, pain points with severity (1-5), current solutions, surprising insights, follow-up questions. After 5+ interviews perform pattern analysis showing finding, frequency (X of Y interviews), and confidence level.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Tag pains by severity AND frequency separately. High frequency plus low severity is noise. Low frequency plus extreme severity is opportunity.</statement>
        <rationale>Frequency and severity move independently. A problem appearing once but destroying workflow is more actionable than minor annoyance everyone mentions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <p>Asking Would you use this instead of How do you handle this now. Pitching instead of saving ideas for end. Only positive feedback instead of seeking pain. Leading questions instead of open-ended. Too few interviews when 10 minimum for patterns. No recording. Not asking for referrals. Immediate synthesis instead of waiting for patterns to emerge.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Leading questions and pitch-mode are universal failure modes for both humans and agents under pressure.</description>
        <reason>Default conversation patterns are social and confirmatory. Research requires deliberately breaking those patterns.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Recall bias: respondents reconstruct past behavior optimistically. Always ask for last specific instance.</description>
        <reason>Memory is constructive and optimistic. Specificity (dates, names, sequences) anchors recall to actual events.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>5-10 interviews is enough for thematic saturation only on narrow segments. Cross-segment work needs 10-15 per segment.</description>
        <reason>Homogeneous recruiting under-samples variation. Segment-specific insights require segment-specific interview volume.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Interview fatigue after 3-4 sessions in a day. Quality drops. Schedule with buffers.</description>
        <reason>Interviewer fatigue reduces active listening. Listening is the methodology; fatigue breaks it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Treat interviews as a four-stage pipeline: recruit (outreach drafting plus scheduling), conduct (script plus live note-taking with human leading), transcribe plus tag (Whisper plus LLM signal extraction), synthesize (cross-interview pattern analysis). Agents do not run live interviews. They prepare scripts, transcribe, and tag. Decision-making remains with the human.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents: recruit-writer (haiku) drafts personalized outreach DMs and emails using LinkedIn or X profile context. script-writer (sonnet) generates Mom Test-compliant scripts per segment and research goal. transcriber-tagger (sonnet) runs Whisper diarization and tags pains, jobs, solutions, quotes. pattern-synthesizer (sonnet) performs cross-interview thematic analysis with frequency counts. faion-persona-builder-agent (referenced in README) maintains persona deliverable.</p>

      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Role: script-writer.
Input: research_goals.md, segment_profile.md.
Output: 20-30 minute script with sections (warm-up, context, problem exploration, solutions tried, wrap-up).
Constraint: every problem-exploration question must reference past specific event; no hypotheticals; no would you.
Self-check: scan output for "would|imagine|hypothetically|do you think"; if any present, regenerate.
      ]]></code>

      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Role: transcriber-tagger.
Input: interview.wav (with diarization), segment_context.md.
Output JSON: pains array with quote, timestamp, severity 1-5. current_solutions array with tool and satisfaction. jobs_to_be_done array. red_flags array. referrals_offered.
Rule: never paraphrase pains. Verbatim quotes only.
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Record plus transcribe everything (with consent). Memory degrades after the 4th or 5th interview because human working memory overloads. You will misremember what people said and mix up quotes across interviews. Transcription prevents that and allows pattern detection.</item>
        <item>End every interview with: Who else should I talk to? Referrals dominate cold recruiting. They account for 40%+ response rate versus 5-10% for cold outreach. Referrals also break warm-network bias by expanding your circle.</item>
        <item>Synthesize after every 3 interviews, not at the end. Patterns inform follow-up scripts for remaining interviews. After 3 interviews, look for recurring pains, solutions, and jobs. Use those to refine your script. This iterative learning accelerates convergence.</item>
        <item>Pre-write the script with red-flag checks (would you, do you think) and reject any question that fails. Scan for hypothetical language before interviewing. One leading question ruins an otherwise good interview.</item>
        <item>Tag pains by severity AND frequency separately. High frequency plus low severity is noise that appears important but affects few. Low frequency plus extreme severity is opportunity that affects few acutely.</item>
        <item>Don't pitch your solution. If you must, save it for last 2 minutes and frame as here's what I'm playing with, what does it remind you of? Pitching early biases answers and people become polite instead of honest.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs naturally rephrase verbatim quotes into smoother prose. Explicitly forbid paraphrasing in prompts.</item>
        <item>Whisper struggles with proper nouns and technical jargon. Pre-prime with glossary of likely terms.</item>
        <item>Diarization fails on overlapping speech. Expect 5-10% mis-attribution. Cross-check before quoting.</item>
        <item>Cross-interview synthesis hallucinates frequency. Most users said X is fabricated. Require cited interview IDs per claim.</item>
        <item>Persona generation from under 8 interviews is statistically meaningless. Agents produce confident personas anyway.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoints: script approval before recruiting, synthesis review before persona work, referral chain audit for warm-only network bias.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="problem-validation"/>
      <ref slug="pain-point-research"/>
      <ref slug="persona-building"/>
      <ref slug="jobs-to-be-done"/>
      <ref slug="user-research-methods"/>
      <link href="https://www.momtestbook.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.steveportigal.com/books/interviewing-users"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/user-interviews/"/>
      <link href="https://www.continuous-discovery.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
