<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-focus-areas" title="PMBOK 8 Five Focus Areas">
  <summary>PMBOK 8 replaces Process Groups with five method-agnostic Focus Areas that organize the 40 non-prescriptive processes across any delivery lifecycle.</summary>

  <section title="Focus Area Definitions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map agile ceremonies to focus areas for stakeholders trained on PMBOK 6 — Sprint Planning → Planning, Sprint → Executing, Daily/Demo → Monitoring &amp; Controlling, Retro → Closing-of-iteration.</statement>
      <rationale>Provides a common vocabulary between agile teams and PMO leadership without forcing waterfall sequencing onto iterative work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Initiating">
      <p>Establish vision, purpose, and organizational alignment. Not just a kickoff meeting — includes business case, project charter, and sponsor sign-off.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Predictive: project charter, stakeholder register, business case</item>
        <item>Agile: vision statement, product goals, initial backlog seeding</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Planning">
      <p>Define the approach, build estimates, and identify risks. In agile, Planning recurs inside every sprint rather than once upfront.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Predictive: WBS, requirements baseline, schedule, budget, risk register</item>
        <item>Agile: backlog, user stories with acceptance criteria, sprint plan, release roadmap</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Executing">
      <p>Perform work to achieve objectives. The largest consumer of project effort; in agile this maps directly to sprint execution.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Predictive: work packages, procurement, resource coordination</item>
        <item>Agile: sprint development, integration, deployment automation</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Monitoring and Controlling">
      <p>Track performance, manage changes, and enable informed decisions. In agile, daily standups and demo reviews serve this function continuously.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Predictive: EVM, baseline comparison, change control log</item>
        <item>Agile: velocity tracking, burn-up charts, defect rate, demo feedback</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Closing">
      <p>Formal completion, lessons learned, and acceptance. The most frequently skipped focus area in continuous-flow product work.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Predictive: final reports, acceptance signatures, lessons-learned document</item>
        <item>Agile: sprint retrospective, release retrospective, knowledge transfer</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Block project archive until at least one Closing artifact (lessons-learned, formal acceptance, or retrospective summary) exists.</statement>
        <rationale>Without enforcement, Closing never happens in agile or product-mode work; lessons-learned vanish and the same mistakes repeat in the next project.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using focus areas as a glorified table of contents without the seven Performance Domains as the orthogonal axis.</description>
      <reason>Focus areas answer "when" (lifecycle position); without domains answering "what area," the framework produces empty section headers with no substance.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Placing the same artifact in multiple focus areas because boundaries are fuzzy.</description>
      <reason>Single-home tagging is required for analytics; double-counting inflates effort reporting and obscures where the team actually spends time.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating "40 non-prescriptive processes" as freedom to define 40 custom process names.</description>
      <reason>Without org-level standardization, each PM invents their own subset and inter-team audits become impossible.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/scaffold_focus_areas.sh">Creates docs/ tree with one folder and default artifacts per focus area</reference>
</text>
