<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-tailoring" title="Focus Area Tailoring and Domain Integration">
  <summary>Tailoring rules for focus areas by project type and size, orthogonal integration with seven performance domains, and subagent patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Tailoring by Project Type">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair focus areas with the seven Performance Domains on an orthogonal axis: focus areas answer "when in the lifecycle," domains answer "what area of work."</statement>
      <rationale>Used alone, focus areas produce empty section headers; used alone, domains produce concurrent work without a temporal anchor. Together they produce a complete project structure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Small Project (S)">
      <list>
        <item>Initiating: charter.md (1 page)</item>
        <item>Planning: spec.md + risk-register.md (light)</item>
        <item>Executing: status-reports/ folder</item>
        <item>Monitoring &amp; Controlling: metrics.md (minimal)</item>
        <item>Closing: lessons-learned.md (required even for small projects)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Medium Project (M)">
      <list>
        <item>Full artifact set per focus area; 3-5 documents each</item>
        <item>Explicit change log under Monitoring &amp; Controlling</item>
        <item>Formal acceptance document under Closing</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Regulated Project">
      <list>
        <item>All focus areas require documented artifacts regardless of team preferences</item>
        <item>Initiating must include business case, sponsor sign-off, and regulatory scope statement</item>
        <item>Closing requires auditable acceptance signature and archived project record</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Agile Team Mapping">
    <p>For agile teams who resist PMO framing, map ceremonies to focus areas to provide a common vocabulary with leadership:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Sprint Planning → Planning focus area</item>
      <item>Sprint Execution → Executing focus area</item>
      <item>Daily Standup + Sprint Demo → Monitoring &amp; Controlling focus area</item>
      <item>Sprint Retrospective → Closing focus area (iteration-level)</item>
      <item>Product Discovery → Initiating focus area (ongoing)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not double-document: if a sprint review serves Monitoring &amp; Controlling, do not require a separate M&amp;C report for the same period.</statement>
      <rationale>Double-documentation is the most common reason agile teams reject PMO frameworks; removing it increases adoption without reducing auditability.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Subagent Patterns">
    <section title="Focus-Area Scaffolder">
      <p>Generates a per-focus-area folder tree from project metadata (type, size, regulated flag).</p>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are focus-area-scaffolder. Inputs: project type (string), size (S/M/L), regulated (bool).
Output a Markdown directory tree under docs/ with one folder per focus area
(initiating, planning, executing, monitoring-controlling, closing). For each folder,
list 3-5 required documents tailored to the inputs. Mark optional with "(optional)".
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section title="Coverage Checker">
      <p>Scans a corpus, reports completeness per focus area, flags silently empty areas.</p>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are focus-area-coverage-checker. Scan <corpus>. For each focus area, report:
- Status: COVERED | PARTIAL | MISSING
- Evidence: list of documents found (or "none")
- Gap: what is missing for PARTIAL/MISSING
Do not infer coverage from document titles alone; verify content exists.
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/scaffold_focus_areas.sh">Creates docs/ tree with one folder and default artifacts per focus area</reference>
</text>
