<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Live Ticket Drafting (Shared-Screen Pattern) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules with rationale + source for live-ticket-drafting-shared-screen-pattern. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="draft-in-session" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ticket MUST be drafted in the shared screen during the elicitation session, not as a post-session write-up.</statement>
      <rationale source="Live-elicitation research">Live-elicitation research — applies to Live Ticket Drafting (Shared-Screen Pattern).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="contributor-signs-off-live" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each ticket MUST receive a verbal or chat sign-off from the contributor before the session ends; deferred sign-off is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reducing async clarification rounds">Reducing async clarification rounds — applies to Live Ticket Drafting (Shared-Screen Pattern).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="template-pre-filled" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>BA opens the session with a pre-filled ticket template (title, type, parent epic, AC shell); blank-canvas drafting wastes session time.</statement>
      <rationale source="Workshop-facilitation practice">Workshop-facilitation practice — applies to Live Ticket Drafting (Shared-Screen Pattern).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="each-ticket-bounded-time" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each ticket draft MUST be timeboxed (default 8 minutes); over-running triggers a 'park or commit' decision, not silent over-run.</statement>
      <rationale source="Time-boxed facilitation">Time-boxed facilitation — applies to Live Ticket Drafting (Shared-Screen Pattern).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ambiguity-marker-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If ambiguity remains, the ticket MUST contain an explicit `[NEEDS-CLARIFICATION]` marker plus the owner of the clarification; silent ambiguity forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Spec-Driven Development research">Spec-Driven Development research — applies to Live Ticket Drafting (Shared-Screen Pattern).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="post-session-summary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Session ends with a one-screen summary of all drafted tickets + their states (signed-off, needs-clarification, parked); summary persisted to engagement log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Session-closure discipline">Session-closure discipline — applies to Live Ticket Drafting (Shared-Screen Pattern).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="recording-or-minutes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Session is either recorded (with consent) or transcribed minutes are produced; pure verbal sign-off without artefact forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-trail discipline">Audit-trail discipline — applies to Live Ticket Drafting (Shared-Screen Pattern).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If contributors are async-only or screen-share is prohibited, return `skipped`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to Live Ticket Drafting (Shared-Screen Pattern).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
