<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Rate Increase Notice Template — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `rate-increase-notice-template` must enforce. The rules pin the discipline that turns a template from folklore into a reviewable, owned, version-controlled operating tool.</summary>

  <section title="Rules">
    <rule id="r1-fixed-shape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The rate increase notice template has a fixed section list with named headings. Practitioners fill sections; they do not invent new ones per use.</statement>
      <rationale source="Standardisation literature (Atul Gawande, The Checklist Manifesto) and information-architecture canon">Variable structure across instances destroys comparability and prevents future audit or aggregation. A fixed shape makes filled artefacts diff-able and reviewable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-evidence-fields" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every claim or recommendation in the template carries a citation field (link, ticket, transcript ID, or measurement). Unevidenced sections are flagged at review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Evidence-based delivery practice; Lean Startup validated-learning rules">Templates without evidence anchors decay into opinion-capture. Tagging evidence at fill-time makes the artefact defensible and reusable in retro / audit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-version-and-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The header carries `version`, `last_reviewed`, and a named owner. Templates without ownership age into untrusted folklore.</statement>
      <rationale source="Documentation-as-code practice; Diátaxis maintainability model">Templates ship as living docs. Anonymous templates rot because no one is on the hook for refresh. A named owner pins refresh accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-fill-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The fill budget is explicit: target ≤ 30 minutes for the technical freelancer. Templates that exceed it are split into a short variant + an extended variant.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cognitive-load research; field experience with operational templates">If filling the template costs more than the artefact yields, practitioners route around it. A budgeted template enforces leverage.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-reuse-marker" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each filled instance ends with a `decisions / actions / next-review` block. Templates without an action block are reading material, not operating tools.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-journal practice (Annie Duke, How To Decide); GTD next-action discipline">Plain-language, low-friction rate-increase letter that minimizes churn — neither pricing-strategy nor difficult-conversations gives the exact artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>
  
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If all Applies-If preconditions hold and no Skip-If disqualifier is present, execute the full procedure from `04-procedure.xml` and commit the artefact described in `02-output-contract.xml`.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's affirmative leaf; pairs the preconditions with the methodology's commit path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Skip-If condition is present (one-shot, &lt;3 instances/year, regulator override, missing owner), do NOT apply this methodology. Route to the sibling/upstream methodology named in `AGENTS.md` Related section.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's skip leaf; prevents over-application of a heavyweight artefact when the loop conditions do not hold.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
