<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-capture-process" title="Lessons Learned Capture Process">
  <summary>Rules for capturing lessons continuously with mandatory structured fields, 5-whys root cause, and session facilitation ground rules.</summary>

  <section title="Mandatory Structured Fields">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Reject any lesson submission that is missing a field or contains "TBD". Required: title (action-oriented, under 80 chars), project, date, category, impact_level with quantified effect, situation (facts only), root_cause (5-whys), lesson (generalizable, under 2 sentences), recommendation (action verb + owner_role + where_applied), evidence (artifact links).</statement>
      <rationale>Free-text lessons degrade to noise within months; structured fields enforce the information quality required for retrieval and application.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Reject "communication was bad" and any entry where symptom equals cause. Push back with: "go one level deeper — what specifically broke, and why?"</statement>
      <rationale>Vague entries produce vague recommendations; "improve communication" cannot be actioned or measured. A specific mechanism and fix can.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Quantify impact in dollars, days, defects, or incidents. "Saved time" is not a lesson; "avoided 12 dev-days of rework" is.</statement>
      <rationale>Quantified impact enables prioritization: a lesson that saved 12 dev-days should be in the kickoff checklist; one that saved 30 minutes should not be.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Continuous Capture Triggers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture lessons at each of these triggers, not only at project close-out: after each milestone, when a problem occurs, after a significant success, during retrospectives, at vendor handoffs, and at project closure.</statement>
      <rationale>End-of-project capture misses 60-80% of lessons; details are forgotten and the team has moved on. Continuous capture is the only way to preserve context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Technical lesson: chose a new framework without prior team experience. Impact: development took 40% longer (est. 12 dev-days lost). Root cause: excitement about technology + underestimated training time (5-why: why did scope of training not appear in estimates? — because new tech was not flagged as a risk during kickoff). Lesson: new technology adoption requires explicit training time in the WBS. Recommendation: when introducing unfamiliar tech, add 25% buffer to estimates + schedule dedicated training. Owner: PM. Where applied: planning checklist.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Session Ground Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run lessons-learned sessions blameless: focus on systems and processes, not individuals. Apply 5-whys and reject "human error" as a terminal cause.</statement>
      <rationale>Blame culture turns sessions into theater; people stop sharing real failures. Blameless sessions produce actionable root causes that can change the system rather than the person.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Session structure (75 min): opening + ground rules 5min, what worked 15min, what did not work 15min, root causes 15min, recommendations 15min, action items with owners 10min.</p>
  </section>
</text>
