<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="lessons-learned Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for lessons-learned. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reject any lesson submission that is missing a field or contains "TBD". Required: title (action-oriented, under 80 chars), project, date, category, impact_level with quantified effect, situation (facts only), root_cause (5-whys), lesson (generalizable, under 2 sentences), recommendation (action verb + owner_role + where_applied), evidence (artifact links).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Free-text lessons degrade to noise within months; structured fields enforce the information quality required for retrieval and application.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reject "communication was bad" and any entry where symptom equals cause. Push back with: "go one level deeper — what specifically broke, and why?"</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Vague entries produce vague recommendations; "improve communication" cannot be actioned or measured. A specific mechanism and fix can.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>At every project kickoff, retrieve relevant lessons by tag and similarity and insert them into the planning checklist. Track application rate: of last quarter's lessons, what percent triggered a documented process change? Target: above 50%.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Lessons that are captured but not applied provide zero value; the application rate is the only metric that distinguishes a knowledge system from a documentation exercise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If application rate falls below 30% for two consecutive quarters, declare the storage or retrieval system broken and redesign the workflow before adding more lessons.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Adding more lessons to an unused system increases storage cost without benefit; the constraint is retrieval and application, not volume.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
