<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-storage-application" title="Lessons Storage, Searchability, and Application">
  <summary>Requirements for a searchable, versioned lessons repository; application SLO definition; staleness expiry rules.</summary>

  <section title="Storage Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store lessons in a versioned repository (git or equivalent) with a controlled tag taxonomy. Inconsistent tags make lessons unfindable at kickoff retrieval.</statement>
      <rationale>A searchable corpus requires consistent categorization; without it, semantic search retrieves shallow matches and the repository becomes a graveyard.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a last_validated_on field to every lesson. Review tooling-specific lessons annually; expire at 24 months. Process and team lessons expire at 5 years. Mark expired lessons as archived, not deleted.</statement>
      <rationale>Tooling lessons go stale quickly as stacks change; recommending a deprecated approach is worse than no recommendation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Application SLO">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>At every project kickoff, retrieve relevant lessons by tag and similarity and insert them into the planning checklist. Track application rate: of last quarter's lessons, what percent triggered a documented process change? Target: above 50%.</statement>
      <rationale>Lessons that are captured but not applied provide zero value; the application rate is the only metric that distinguishes a knowledge system from a documentation exercise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>If application rate falls below 30% for two consecutive quarters, declare the storage or retrieval system broken and redesign the workflow before adding more lessons.</statement>
      <rationale>Adding more lessons to an unused system increases storage cost without benefit; the constraint is retrieval and application, not volume.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Lessons held only at project close-out.</description>
      <reason>Small, frequent lessons are forgotten over a multi-month project; by close-out only major events are recalled, and even those lose context details.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Lessons stored in a wiki without a tag taxonomy or search capability.</description>
      <reason>An unsearchable repository means lessons cannot be retrieved at kickoff; they effectively do not exist for the next project team.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Recommendations written as "consider Y" or "be more careful".</description>
      <reason>Vague recommendations cannot be actioned, measured, or assigned. Every recommendation requires an action verb, an owner role, and a point of application.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../procurement-management/">Vendor-specific lessons inform the approved-vendor list and next RFP criteria</link>
  </see-also>
</text>
