<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="value-proposition-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for value-proposition-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Building the canvas around features instead of customer jobs, pains, and gains.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The canvas becomes a product datasheet. Without customer-first framing, you miss what customers actually care about and build a feature list instead of value prop.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating one generic value prop that "works for everyone."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>One value prop per segment. Positioning that fits everyone fits no one. Explicit audience segmentation allows targeted positioning per segment.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Designing pain relievers and gain creators without research data on customer problems and desires.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The canvas becomes fiction. Every entry must cite interview data or JTBD research. Agents guessing pains produce plausible-sounding but untested hypotheses.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Leading with the product category or feature in the value prop ("AI-powered platform," "blockchain-based solution").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Customers don't buy categories or technologies; they buy outcomes. Feature-led copy reads as marketing jargon, not value.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Equating "Unlike X" with a real differentiator ("more user-friendly," "better support").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Weak differentiators. Every product claims to be user-friendly. Differentiators must be measurable, specific, and hard to copy ("flat pricing regardless of scale," "offline-first sync").</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Refreshing the value prop once and leaving it static.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Markets move. Yesterday's differentiator becomes table stakes. Quarterly refresh keeps positioning sharp; annual refresh is minimum discipline.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
