<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Service Ownership Map Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of service-ownership-map-template enforces. Each rule has a statement, a rationale anchored to industry practice, and a source citation.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every service has a named owning team — never 'shared' or 'TBD'; orphan services are resolved within 30 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="Team Topologies — Ownership chapter">Shared ownership = no ownership; orphan services accumulate incidents and stall improvements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every service entry links to: on-call rotation, SLO doc, runbook, dependency list.</statement>
      <rationale source="Spotify Backstage docs 2026">Missing links turn the map into a phone book; the value is the linked artefacts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map is version-controlled (Backstage catalog-info.yaml OR Markdown in repo) — never a wiki page.</statement>
      <rationale source="ThoughtWorks — Service catalogue post">Wiki pages drift; version-controlled maps diff like code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly audit: every service entry verified against reality; stale entries removed; new services added.</statement>
      <rationale source="Team Topologies practice">Unaudited maps decay to fiction in 6-12 months.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dependency graph is computed (or curated) and surfaced as part of incident response — 'what depends on this service?'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Spotify Backstage docs 2026">Without the dependency view, every incident asks the same question.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, skip this methodology and route to the adjacent one referenced in Related.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 skill-authoring conventions">A skip rule keeps the decision tree closed: every branch ends at a real rule id.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>