<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Shutdown Customer Email Pack Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules every product-shutdown email sequence must follow so the founder preserves trust capital instead of burning it.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The first announce email MUST be sent at least 30 days before service-off; shorter windows are forbidden unless legal or financial force majeure applies.</statement>
      <rationale>Indie shutdowns are recurring and almost always bespoke under pressure; a 30-day minimum gives customers time to export data, find replacements, and dispute charges without escalating to chargebacks. Anything shorter trades short-term comfort for permanent reputation damage.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The second email MUST contain a concrete refund OR migration offer — never "thanks for your support" without remedy. Refund window, formula, and migration target are stated explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale>The whole reason existing shutdown comms are bespoke is that founders avoid the refund decision; codifying it as a required slot removes the temptation to skip it. Refunds (or a credible migration) are the difference between "wound up gracefully" and "took my money and disappeared".</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Refund: we are refunding the unused remainder of your annual plan,
calculated as months_remaining / 12 × $X. You'll see it on the
original card within 7 business days. No action needed.

Or, if you'd rather migrate, we recommend <competitor> — they've
agreed to a 3-month free trial for users coming from us at
<migration-link>.]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The sequence MUST be exactly three emails — announce, refund/migrate-details, final thanks — sent at known intervals (T-30 days, T-14 days, T+1 day); silent disappearance after announce is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>Founders who send only the first email regularly lose 30%+ of the refund-eligible customers because they forget the deadline. A scheduled three-email cadence ensures customers cannot miss it through inattention.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every email MUST be sent from a named human (founder name + photo + signature), not noreply@ or a generic "team" alias.</statement>
      <rationale>The shutdown moment is exactly when the customer needs to know who is on the other end. A bare alias signals abandonment; a named human signals accountability and is the single biggest driver of future-product trust capital.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Copy MUST state the real reason for shutdown in plain language (no "exciting new chapter", no "rapid evolution of the market"); minimum one honest sentence on cause.</statement>
      <rationale>Customers can read corporate-speak and will resent being patronised at the moment they are losing the product. Honest cause framing — "didn't find product/market fit", "couldn't reach sustainable revenue" — is consistently rated by post-shutdown surveys as the single most respected element.</rationale>
      <example type="bad">
        <description>"After an exciting journey, we are evolving in a new direction and saying goodbye to the product you love."</description>
        <reason>This says nothing, dodges accountability, and tells the customer the founder thinks they are stupid.</reason>
      </example>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
