<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Shutdown Customer Email Pack Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Shutdown Customer Email Pack application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-30day-notice" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>First announce email MUST be sent at least 30 days before service-off; shorter windows rejected unless legal force majeure applies.</statement>
      <rationale source="basecamp.com/handbook">30-day minimum gives customers time to export data, find replacements, and dispute charges without escalating to chargebacks.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-refund-or-migrate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Second email MUST contain a concrete refund OR migration offer — 'thanks for support' without remedy is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="FTC §255 endorsement guidelines">Refunds (or a credible migration) are the difference between graceful and 'took my money and disappeared'.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-three-email-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sequence MUST be exactly three emails — announce, refund/migrate, final thanks — at T-30, T-14, T+1.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion shutdown post-mortem 2026">Single-email shutdowns lose 30%+ refund-eligible customers to inattention; cadence ensures the deadline is unmissable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-named-human-from" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every email MUST be sent from a named human (founder name + photo + signature); noreply@ and generic 'team' aliases are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="basecamp.com/handbook">At shutdown the customer needs to know who is accountable; bare alias signals abandonment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-honest-reason" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Copy MUST state the real reason in plain language (≥1 honest sentence); corporate-speak phrases ('exciting new chapter', 'evolving') are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion shutdown post-mortem 2026">Customers can read corporate-speak and resent being patronised at the moment of loss; honest cause framing earns the most respect.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
