<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="competitive-intelligence">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>market-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Produce win/loss analysis, pricing intelligence, and market-positioning signals by triangulating closed-deal records, buyer interviews, and competitor positioning.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>competitive-intelligence</tag>
      <tag>win-loss-analysis</tag>
      <tag>pricing-benchmarking</tag>
      <tag>market-positioning</tag>
      <tag>buyer-research</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>research</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Competitive Intelligence (Market-Researcher Lens)</title>

    <summary>Competitive intelligence at the market-researcher level produces three deliverables the general CI loop does not cover: win/loss analysis (coding closed-deal records into structured loss reasons), pricing intelligence (triangulating list price against realized ACV from G2 disclosures and Vendr/Tropic benchmarks), and market-positioning signals (clustering competitor hero copy and buyer language by job-to-be-done). The core rule: every loss-reason row requires at least one verbatim buyer-side quote with speaker attribution — rep notes alone never justify a loss code.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Win/loss self-report bias causes sales reps to over-attribute losses to "price" when buyers actually leave for product fit, integration risk, or relationship gaps. Posted list price diverges from realized close price by 15-35% in B2B SaaS. Positioning language extracted from exec decks reflects aspiration, not buyer perception. Systematic triangulation across win/loss records, pricing page snapshots, and review-site text produces CI that drives decisions instead of confirming existing beliefs.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Deal review backlog has more than 20 closed-lost/closed-won opportunities in 60 days with unstructured CRM notes</item>
        <item>Pricing committee meets quarterly and needs a defensible benchmark per segment</item>
        <item>Inbound positioning brief is stalling because category language is contested</item>
        <item>Repositioning, rebrand, or new-segment launch where messaging needs evidence from buyer language</item>
        <item>Pre-Series-B/C: investors ask for a defensible win-rate trend with reasons-coded loss data</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Fewer than 10 closed deals per quarter — sample too small; use customer interviews instead</item>
        <item>Self-serve / PLG product with no sales conversations — switch to churn analytics and cancel-survey</item>
        <item>Pricing locked by multi-year MSAs for the next 12 months — pricing intel has no decision to inform</item>
        <item>Single-product, single-segment startup — positioning emerges from PMF interviews</item>
        <item>Where buyer interviews are blocked by NDA — synthesize from public review sites, do not fabricate</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="win-loss-analysis">
      <p>Rules for coding closed deals into structured loss reasons with buyer-side quote requirements and confidence scoring.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every loss-reason row requires at least one verbatim buyer-side quote with speaker role, company size, and segment. Rep notes alone are insufficient — set confidence to 2 or below and flag for interview.</statement>
        <rationale>Win/loss self-report bias: sales reps over-attribute losses to "price" when buyers actually leave for product fit, integration risk, or relationship gaps. Buyer-side quotes override rep attribution.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="loss-reason-taxonomy">
        <p>Maintain maximum 8 loss reasons in the taxonomy. Never expand silently — taxonomy additions require a documented decision. Deals that do not fit get "other" and go to human triage.</p>
        <list>
          <item>price: buyer explicitly cited price or total cost of ownership as primary reason</item>
          <item>product_fit: feature gap, workflow mismatch, or integration depth insufficient</item>
          <item>integration: specific technical integration with an existing system blocked the deal</item>
          <item>relationship: incumbent vendor loyalty, existing executive relationship, or trust deficit</item>
          <item>timing: not in active evaluation cycle; budget cycle mismatch; internal priority change</item>
          <item>incumbent: existing solution "good enough"; switching cost too high</item>
          <item>no_decision: deal stalled — budget frozen, stakeholder turnover, internal politics</item>
          <item>other: reason does not fit taxonomy; requires manual triage</item>
        </list>

        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Maintain maximum 8 loss reasons in the taxonomy. Never expand silently — taxonomy additions require a documented decision. Deals that do not fit get "other" and go to human triage.</statement>
          <rationale>Taxonomy drift breaks cross-period trend lines. A reason added in Q3 cannot be compared to Q1 data unless it is backfilled consistently.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Treat "no_decision" as its own outcome, not as a loss. Report stalled-pipeline rate separately from competitive loss rate.</statement>
          <rationale>Mixing no-decision with competitive losses inflates the win-rate denominator and makes pipeline health look worse than it is. Leadership uses the wrong metric to judge sales effectiveness.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="confidence-scoring">
        <p>Score each loss record by evidence quality. Buyer-side interviews outweigh rep notes.</p>
        <list>
          <item>5: direct buyer interview conducted by a non-deal-team member; verbatim quotes with attribution</item>
          <item>4: buyer-submitted survey response or written post-mortem from buyer</item>
          <item>3: rep notes include at least one direct buyer quote (not paraphrase)</item>
          <item>2: rep notes only, no buyer direct quote — flag for interview</item>
          <item>1: inferred from behavior (no response after pricing, chose competitor without explanation)</item>
        </list>

        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Run buyer-side win/loss interviews on at least 30% of lost deals above $50K ACV. Use Clozd or an internal interviewer who never sat on the deal — reps cannot interview their own losses.</statement>
          <rationale>Rep-interviewed losses produce systematically biased data defending the rep's narrative. Independent interviewers surface the actual buyer motivations that drove the decision.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="segmentation-rule">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Stratify all win/loss analysis by segment and deal size. "We lose 60% of deals" is meaningless; "we lose 80% of mid-market deals against Vendor X when integration matters" is actionable.</statement>
          <rationale>Blended win rates hide segment-specific patterns that require different responses. A 60% blended rate could mean 90% win in enterprise and 30% win in SMB — opposite strategic implications.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="pricing-intelligence">
      <p>Triangulating list price against realized ACV, packaging diff detection, and AB-test interference rules.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Triangulate competitor pricing three ways: posted list price, G2 reviewer-disclosed spend, and ex-customer or buyer interview. Publish the median and the spread — not a single number.</statement>
        <rationale>B2B SaaS discounting averages 15-35% off list price. Published list price is aspirational; realized ACV from buyer disclosures is the actual competitive benchmark. Single-source pricing intel is misleading.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="pricing-data-sources">
        <p>Ranked by reliability.</p>
        <list>
          <item>1st — Ex-customer or buyer interview: actual invoiced amount, contract length, included seats/usage</item>
          <item>2nd — Vendr/Tropic realized-price indexes: negotiated benchmarks from procurement platforms</item>
          <item>3rd — G2 reviewer-disclosed spend: reviewer-reported price band with contract renewal status</item>
          <item>4th — Pricing page scrape: list price, requires 3+ independent fetches over 14 days to confirm</item>
          <item>5th — Press releases or analyst reports: directional only; cite as "secondary"</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="all-in-take-rate">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>For marketplaces, always compute all-in take rate: commission + payment processing + seller subscription + ad platform fees. Never report headline commission alone.</statement>
          <rationale>Headline commission (e.g., Etsy 6.5%) understates the real take by 2x or more when seller subscriptions, payment fees, and ad revenue are included. All-in rate is what sellers actually experience.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="ab-test-detection">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Require at least 3 independent fetches of a competitor pricing page over 14 days before declaring a pricing change. Single-fetch divergence is likely AB testing, not a price change.</statement>
          <rationale>Competitors run pricing AB tests continuously; a daily fetch sees noise. Premature "competitor dropped prices" signals based on one fetch trigger incorrect strategic responses.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="packaging-schema">
        <p>Normalize all competitor pricing to a canonical schema: tier name, included seats or usage quota, overage rate, add-on price, contract length options, billing period (monthly/annual), currency, and source URL with retrieval date. Without normalization, cross-competitor comparisons mix incompatible denominators.</p>

        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Pin currency, billing period, unit (per-seat / per-org / per-usage), and contract length in the pricing schema. "$10/month" without these fields cannot be compared across competitors.</statement>
          <rationale>Currency and term ambiguity is the number-one cause of pricing benchmark errors. A per-seat monthly price cannot be added to a per-org annual price without normalization.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="positioning-signals">
      <p>Extracting and clustering positioning signals from buyer language, competitor copy, and analyst mentions by job-to-be-done.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Positioning extracted from buyer reviews outweighs positioning declared by competitor marketing copy. Hero copy reflects aspiration; G2 reviews reflect what buyers actually experience. The gap is your wedge.</statement>
        <rationale>Competitors write hero copy for the positioning they want; buyers describe the product they got. The gap between declared positioning and buyer-described positioning is where an entrant can credibly differentiate.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="signal-sources">
        <p>Ranked by buyer-centricity.</p>
        <list>
          <item>1st — Buyer win/loss interview quotes (highest buyer-centricity, smallest sample)</item>
          <item>2nd — G2/TrustRadius review headlines and "what problems does this product solve" sections</item>
          <item>3rd — Reddit and community forum discussions where buyers compare tools</item>
          <item>4th — Analyst quadrant/wave positioning language (Gartner, Forrester) — directional, lagging</item>
          <item>5th — Competitor homepage hero copy, "compare to" pages — aspirational, least reliable</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="jtbd-clustering">
        <p>Extract verbatim quotes from buyers and competitors before running any LLM summarization. Cluster by job-to-be-done using seed labels established at the beginning of the quarter. Do not let the model auto-assign cluster names — it collapses distinct categories (e.g., "agent platform" + "automation platform" + "iPaaS" into one cluster) and loses the wedge.</p>

        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Use k-means with manual seed labels per quarter; reject auto-clustering output. Re-run with the same seed labels each quarter to maintain trend comparability.</statement>
          <rationale>Auto-clustering by LLMs merges adjacent categories that are actually distinct buyer segments with different purchase criteria. Manual seed labels preserve the signal that category definitions are shifting.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="re-baseline-cadence">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Re-baseline positioning analysis every quarter. Publish dated artifacts (competitive-analysis-YYYY-MM-DD.md). A stale market map is worse than no map — it guides decisions toward the wrong target.</statement>
          <rationale>Pricing, packaging, and positioning shift continuously. Sales enablement teams trust dated artifacts because they know what version they are working from.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <p>Structural failure modes in win/loss, pricing, and positioning CI, with agent-specific mitigation rules.</p>

      <section name="structural-antipatterns">
        <antipattern>
          <description>Mixing "no_decision" outcomes with competitive losses in win-rate calculations</description>
          <reason>Inflates the denominator of competitive loss rate; stalled-pipeline rate requires different treatment and different corrective action than competitive displacement.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Using only rep notes without any buyer-side quote for loss coding</description>
          <reason>Rep notes systematically over-attribute losses to "price" and "competition" to avoid admitting process or product failures that reflect on rep performance.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Reporting a single median price instead of a range (P25/P50/P75)</description>
          <reason>Single medians create false precision. The spread between P25 and P75 is often the strategic signal — it shows whether the market has standardized pricing or wide negotiation room.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Anchoring on the loudest competitor in review-site analysis</description>
          <reason>Market-share leaders dominate review-site volume; emerging threats are invisible until they take a deal. Stratify by segment and deal-size, not raw mention count.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Citing the Crayon "16% to 45% win rate" case study without attribution control</description>
          <reason>That uplift conflates CI rollout with new pricing, new battlecards, and new sales hires. Attributing it solely to CI misleads leadership about expected ROI.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>

      <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
        <antipattern>
          <description>Agent invents a loss reason from rep notes without a buyer-side quote</description>
          <reason>Force the output schema to require at least 1 verbatim quote with a speaker field; reject rows where evidence_quotes is empty.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Agent reports "no Enterprise tier exists" when competitor hides it behind "Contact Sales"</description>
          <reason>Mitigate with G2-disclosed price ranges and LinkedIn job posts mentioning ACV bands. Absence of a public pricing page does not mean absence of an Enterprise tier.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Agent defends sales rep narrative ("buyer was confused about the pricing")</description>
          <reason>Use adversarial prompt framing: "Argue the buyer was right to choose the competitor; cite evidence." This surfaces the buyer-side perspective the rep omits.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Agent paraphrases buyer quotes, losing attribution</description>
          <reason>Preserve speaker_role, company_size, and segment end-to-end, never the buyer's name. Paraphrased quotes are useless to leadership — they cannot be cited or challenged.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Agent adds new loss-reason categories each run, breaking trend lines</description>
          <reason>Pin the loss-reason enum in the output schema; flag deals that do not fit for human triage rather than silently expanding the taxonomy.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/wl-join.py" purpose="Python script joining win/loss, pricing, and positioning event streams into competitive-analysis.md"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
