<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-campaign-structure" title="Campaign Structure and Objective Selection">
  <summary>Three-tier Campaign → Ad Set → Ad model, objective-to-goal mapping, and CBO vs ad-set budget decision.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Tier Structure">
    <p>Campaign: defines objective. Ad Set: defines audience, placements, schedule, budget. Ad: defines creative and copy.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never mix objectives within a campaign — each campaign optimizes for exactly one objective signal.</statement>
      <rationale>Meta's delivery system is objective-aware at the campaign level; splitting objectives forces the algorithm to optimize for incompatible signals simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Objective Selection">
    <list>
      <item>Awareness → reach and impressions (brand, new markets)</item>
      <item>Traffic → link clicks or landing page views (content promotion)</item>
      <item>Engagement → post interactions (social proof building)</item>
      <item>Leads → Lead Instant Forms or website lead events</item>
      <item>App Installs → mobile install events</item>
      <item>Sales → Purchase pixel event or catalog sales</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>For revenue-driven campaigns, always choose Sales or Leads objective — never Traffic, even if conversion volume is low initially.</statement>
      <rationale>Traffic objective optimizes for the cheapest click, not the most likely buyer; this fills the funnel with high-bounce, low-intent visits that look good in CPCs but produce zero conversions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="CBO vs Ad-Set Budget">
    <list>
      <item>CBO (Campaign Budget Optimization) — Meta distributes across ad sets dynamically; best when testing multiple audiences with equal starting budgets</item>
      <item>Ad-Set Budget — fixed per ad set; use when one ad set must never be starved by others (e.g. retargeting)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with CBO at $20-50/day minimum and let Meta distribute; switch to ad-set budget only if a specific ad set is being chronically under-funded by CBO after 7+ days.</statement>
      <rationale>CBO with sufficient total budget finds efficient delivery faster than manual allocation; premature manual allocation forces sub-optimal fixed splits.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
