<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ads-meta-campaign-setup Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ads-meta-campaign-setup as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Running campaigns without a verified Meta Pixel.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>No conversion data means the delivery system cannot optimize — ads serve to random segments at maximum CPM with zero feedback loop.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Choosing Traffic objective when the actual goal is leads or purchases.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Traffic optimizes for cheap clicks; it finds audiences that click but don't convert, inflating CTR while producing zero revenue.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Using an audience under 100K for interest-based prospecting.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Audience exhaustion occurs within days; high frequency causes CPM inflation and ad fatigue before the algorithm can learn anything meaningful.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Launching with one ad per ad set.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>No creative variation means no optimization path — Meta cannot identify a winner and the campaign performance is limited to whatever the single creative happens to achieve.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Editing budgets, targeting, or bids during the first 3-7 days.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Resets the learning phase counter; the campaign re-enters unstable high-CPA delivery, negating any potential improvement from the edit.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Omitting UTM parameters from destination URLs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without UTMs, GA4 attributes Meta-driven sessions as direct traffic, making cross-channel ROAS comparison impossible.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
