<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-ads-and-launch" title="Ad Creation and Launch">
  <summary>Ad component requirements, minimum creative set, UTM parameters, and learning phase rules.</summary>

  <section title="Ad Components">
    <list>
      <item>Primary text: 125 characters shown without truncation; additional text behind "See more"</item>
      <item>Headline: 40 characters ideal</item>
      <item>Description: optional, appears below headline</item>
      <item>CTA button: required — Learn More, Sign Up, Shop Now, Get Quote, etc.</item>
      <item>Image or video: must match placement spec (see instagram-ads for specs)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Minimum Creative Set">
    <rule>
      <statement>Upload at least 3 ad variations per ad set covering different formats (image, video, carousel) — never launch with a single creative.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-creative ad sets cannot be optimized; Meta needs variation to identify which creative, format, or angle resonates with a given audience segment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="UTM Parameters">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add UTM parameters to all ad destination URLs before launch — never rely on Meta's internal attribution alone.</statement>
      <rationale>Meta attribution and GA4 attribution diverge by 20-50% due to view-through vs click-through differences; UTMs provide the GA4 ground truth needed for cross-platform comparison.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
?utm_source=facebook&utm_medium=paid-social&utm_campaign={{campaign.name}}&utm_content={{ad.name}}
      ]]></code>
      <note>Meta supports dynamic UTM parameters using {{campaign.name}}, {{adset.name}}, {{ad.name}} placeholders.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Learning Phase Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not edit ad sets, targeting, bids, or budgets during the first 3-7 days — any significant edit resets the learning phase counter.</statement>
      <rationale>The learning phase requires ~50 conversions to complete; editing forces a restart, extending the period of unstable, high-CPA delivery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/launch-checklist.md">Pre-launch checklist</reference>
  </section>
</text>
