<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="data-driven-requirements Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for data-driven-requirements as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Adoption-stage mismatch: a BA practice that pushes data-driven requirements before the org has a reliable warehouse.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tag the practice's maturity (see "Adoption gates") and don't skip stages. Requirements with placeholder baselines that nobody trusts fail faster than no requirements at all.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Definition drift: "active user" means three different things in three dashboards.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a metric catalog, two BAs pull contradicting baselines for the same KPI on the same day. Keep a single metrics.md before reaching for a metric layer.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Survivorship bias: heavy users skew the data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The cohort that already churned is invisible — the requirement looks well-justified and is solving the wrong problem. Slice baselines by ≥1 dimension (channel, plan, geo).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Single-source bias: pulling from one tool (just GA, just Mixpanel) inherits that tool's tracking gaps.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cross-check with the system of record (DB, Stripe, support tickets) before locking a baseline.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Confidence theater: stamping a number doesn't make it correct.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always include n, as_of, and source_url next to every baseline. A number without those three is gossip.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Causal claims from correlational data: "users of feature X retain 2x" almost never means "shipping X for everyone doubles retention."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Self-selection eats the effect. Add a causal_evidence_type field; observational claims must be hedged.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy/consent: requirements built on data the org cannot lawfully use under GDPR/CCPA.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Fail at legal review even when statistically sound. Restrict warehouse roles, and run a redaction-checker before commit.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Dashboard fixation: BAs start prioritizing what's easy to query (page views) over what matters (retained revenue).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tie every metric to one sentence about the business outcome it maps to. If the BA can't write that sentence, the KPI is vanity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs invent plausible KPI values without citation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force every cell to cite a source URL or query, and have a verifier agent re-run the query.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents collapse different metric definitions ("conversion", "completion", "purchase") into a single number.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Resolve names against metrics.md first. This blocks the most common silent failure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Date drift: an agent fetched a baseline last week and will reuse it forever.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add the freshness gate as a finalization step. Enforce as_of in the schema.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Vanity-metric capture: agents pick the easiest-to-query metric over the most-business-relevant one.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Constrain the schema to require a downstream business KPI (revenue, retention) and a "why this matters" sentence per requirement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Sycophancy: an agent finds data supporting whatever the question implies.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add a counter-evidence pass before finalization: "find the strongest signal that this requirement should NOT be built."</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy leak: agents may pull PII columns into the evidence section.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Restrict warehouse roles, and run a redaction-checker before commit.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Adoption-gate denial: agents will happily produce data-driven requirements at G1 with placeholder baselines.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hard-code the gate in the prompt: refuse to ship a requirement labeled "data-driven" if metrics.md has fewer than 3 KPIs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
