<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Sentry Supabase Vercel Wiring Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of `Sentry Supabase Vercel Wiring` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-three-runtimes-three-configs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Repo MUST contain three Sentry configs: `sentry.client.config.ts`, `sentry.server.config.ts`, `sentry.edge.config.ts`. Single-config setups miss edge-runtime errors (middleware, edge API routes). Missing any file = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sentry Next.js wiring patterns 2026">Next.js runs three different runtimes; Sentry's bundler-plugin emits separate transports. A single config silently drops edge-runtime errors — exactly where middleware-level auth fails.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-source-maps-via-vercel-build" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Source maps MUST upload via Sentry's Next.js bundler plugin during the Vercel build (NOT a post-deploy hook). `SENTRY_AUTH_TOKEN`, `SENTRY_ORG`, `SENTRY_PROJECT` MUST live in Vercel project env (NOT in committed code).</statement>
      <rationale source="Vercel + Sentry integration corpus">Post-deploy hooks race the first user error. Vercel build is the only place that has both the unminified bundle and the deploy ID; everything else is hope.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-supabase-auth-error-scrubbing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>`beforeSend` MUST scrub Supabase auth error payloads: strip `access_token`, `refresh_token`, `provider_token`, full email body, any `Authorization:` header echo.</statement>
      <rationale source="Supabase + Sentry incident review">Supabase client errors include the request that failed, which often contains the JWT. Sentry then becomes the leak. Scrubbing is mandatory, not optional.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-rls-error-classification" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Supabase `PGRST*` and `42501` (RLS denial) errors MUST be classified before sending to Sentry: legitimate denials tagged `level: warning`, unexpected denials tagged `level: error`, both with `meta.expected_rls` payload.</statement>
      <rationale source="Supabase observability patterns">Treating every RLS denial as an error floods Sentry with user-typo noise and hides the actual bugs. Classification is what makes Supabase + Sentry usable together.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-edge-sampling-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>`sentry.edge.config.ts` MUST set `tracesSampleRate` ≤ 0.1 (10%) regardless of client/server settings.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sentry quotas + edge-runtime">Solo plans have small spans quotas. Edge middleware runs on every request including bots — leaving sampling at 1.0 burns through monthly quota by lunchtime.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-ignore-noise-baseline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>`ignoreErrors` MUST include the baseline noise list: ResizeObserver loop limit, AbortError on navigation, NextRouter cancel, hydration mismatch from extensions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Next.js + Sentry noise patterns">Solo builders fight Sentry signal-to-noise for weeks before discovering the baseline list; codifying it saves the discovery cost and stops 'Sentry is useless' abandonment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
