<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Template Task Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every template-task application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-observable-ac" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Acceptance Criterion MUST be expressed as "Given X / When Y / Then Z" with Z being a code-verifiable or filesystem-observable outcome (HTTP status, exit code, file content match). Vague verbs ("works", "is smooth", "looks correct") are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cohn 'User Stories Applied', SDD execution research">Executor agents cannot verify vague criteria. Vague AC ship and then break in QA where the cost-to-fix is 10x.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-single-responsibility" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Objective MUST describe ONE responsibility. If the Objective sentence contains "and" joining two verbs (e.g., "create the endpoint AND write tests"), split into two TASK files. Tests for the implementation MAY live in the same task; cross-component changes MAY NOT.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD task-sizing research">Multi-responsibility tasks consistently exceed token budgets and create review bottlenecks. One-task-one-responsibility halves median time-to-merge.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-traces-to-spec" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every task MUST cite at least one FR-X (functional requirement from spec.md) and at least one AD-X (architectural decision from design.md) under "Requirements Coverage". Tasks without spec/design traces are forbidden — they indicate scope creep beyond the approved plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="Traceability matrix research, SDD audit data">Untraceable tasks accumulate as drift. The spec-design-task chain is the audit trail that lets the system explain what shipped and why.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-token-budget-realistic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Estimated Tokens MUST sum to ≤100k for a single task. Tests for Django viewsets / React components default to ≥30k; do not under-estimate test scope. If the realistic budget exceeds 100k, the task MUST be split before dispatch.</statement>
      <rationale source="Claude Code execution telemetry, SDD wave-orchestrator data">Tasks over 100k tokens hit context limits mid-execution, leaving the worktree in a broken state. A pre-dispatch split is cheaper than recovery.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-executor-sections-empty-at-dispatch" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The "Implementation" and "Summary" sections MUST be empty at dispatch time. They are filled by the executor at completion. A pre-filled Summary indicates the task was authored after-the-fact and the trace is fabricated.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD audit-integrity research">Pre-filled execution sections defeat the audit purpose. Empty sections at dispatch + filled at completion is the integrity invariant.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-00 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
