<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-template-rules" title="Task File Template: Rules and Fill Order">
  <summary>Rules for correctly creating TASK_NNN.md files: section responsibilities (creator vs executor), token budget enforcement, INVEST validation, lifecycle states, and anti-patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Section Responsibility Split">
    <rule>
      <statement>Task creator fills SDD References, Dependency Tree, Requirements Coverage, Objective, Dependencies, AC, Technical Approach, Files, and Estimated Tokens. Executor fills Implementation and Summary. Never pre-fill executor sections.</statement>
      <rationale>Pre-filled Implementation sections give the executor incorrect expectations and reduce quality — the executor follows the pre-fill rather than the actual codebase.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Creator fills: SDD References, Task Dependency Tree, Requirements Coverage, Objective, Dependencies, Acceptance Criteria, Technical Approach, Files, Estimated Tokens</item>
      <item>Executor fills: Implementation (Changes Made, Tests Added), Summary (Completed, Issues, Lessons)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Token Budget">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every task must have an Estimated Tokens breakdown, and the total must be under 100k tokens.</statement>
      <rationale>Tasks exceeding 100k tokens cause executor agents to run out of context mid-implementation, producing partial or inconsistent code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Token budget breakdown for a normal-complexity task</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
SDD Documents (constitution + spec + design): ~15k
Task Dependency Tree (done task summaries): ~10k
Research (read existing code patterns): ~25k
Implementation (actual coding): ~40k
Testing (writing tests): ~10k
TOTAL: ~100k
]]></code>
    </example>
    <list>
      <item>Simple task: &lt;30k tokens — single file, clear pattern</item>
      <item>Normal task: 30-60k tokens — multiple files, some decisions</item>
      <item>Complex task: 60-100k tokens — architecture decisions, research needed</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Requirements Coverage Section">
    <rule>
      <statement>Paste the full text of each FR-X and AD-X inline into the task file. Do not write "See spec.md" — the executor must not re-read the full SDD at runtime.</statement>
      <rationale>Each re-read of the full spec adds 10-30k tokens of context cost and risks the executor misreading a section out of context.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Objective Section">
    <rule>
      <statement>The Objective must be a single, measurable, agent-executable goal in 2-3 sentences. If the title contains "and", split the task.</statement>
      <rationale>Tasks with compound objectives are executed partially — agents complete the first part and mark done without attempting the second.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Compound objective — should be split</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Create User model with email validation and password hashing and add login endpoint.]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Single-responsibility objective</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Create User model with email field (Zod RFC 5322 validation) and password_hash field (bcrypt wrapper). Expose via UserRepository interface.]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Task Lifecycle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Task lifecycle is directory-based: todo/ → in-progress/ → done/. The Status field in the task header must match the directory. Never place a task in the wrong directory.</statement>
      <rationale>Executor agents check the directory, not the status field. A task in todo/ is picked up regardless of its header status.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Vague acceptance criteria: "system works correctly" or "user experience is smooth".</description>
      <reason>Executor agents cannot verify vague criteria. Every AC must have an observable, code-verifiable outcome.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Given-When-Then format used for background jobs (no "when" actor).</description>
      <reason>Use "Given / Triggered by / Then" variant for jobs with no user actor.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Estimated Tokens for test files set to &lt;10k.</description>
      <reason>Test files for Django viewsets or React components consistently run 30-40k tokens. Underestimating causes executor to run out of context before tests are complete.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/task.md">Complete TASK_NNN.md template with all required sections</reference>
  <reference path="templates/task-lifecycle.sh">Moves task file between lifecycle states with section header validation</reference>
</text>
