<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="template-task Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for template-task as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Vague acceptance criteria: "system works correctly" or "user experience is smooth".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Executor agents cannot verify vague criteria. Every AC must have an observable, code-verifiable outcome.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Given-When-Then format used for background jobs (no "when" actor).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use "Given / Triggered by / Then" variant for jobs with no user actor.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Estimated Tokens for test files set to &lt;10k.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Test files for Django viewsets or React components consistently run 30-40k tokens. Underestimating causes executor to run out of context before tests are complete.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Estimated Tokens field is advisory; executors often exceed it without enforcement.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Task files have no hard token limit enforced by the framework itself — context overflow happens at execution time.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Implementation and Summary sections are filled after execution — they are empty when task is dispatched, defeating their purpose as context for the executor.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>These sections capture execution results, not pre-execution context. They cannot be filled until the task is done.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Token estimation guide in template is Django/React-centric; other stacks have different baselines.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add stack-specific calibration to the token budget section for your tech stack.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Task states (todo → in-progress → done) are file-system directory states, not fields — template section is ambiguous.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The Status field in the task header and the directory must stay in sync manually; consider a hook to validate this.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>No field for "rollback" — when a task must be undone, there is no documented reversal procedure.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add a "Rollback" section for tasks that modify stable data or deployed services.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
