<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-prioritization-frameworks" title="Backlog Prioritization Frameworks">
  <summary>RICE scoring, MoSCoW classification, and Value vs Effort matrix — when to apply each.</summary>

  <section title="RICE Scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>RICE score = (Reach x Impact x Confidence) / Effort. Always flag agent-generated RICE scores with [estimate] — they are hypotheses until validated with real user data.</statement>
      <rationale>Reach and Impact require real user data the agent does not have. Agents systematically assign 100% Confidence; default to 50-80% for agent-generated scores and require justification for 100%.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[| Feature | Reach | Impact | Confidence | Effort | RICE Score | Notes |
|---------|-------|--------|------------|--------|------------|-------|
| Auth refactor | 8 [est] | 2 [est] | 80% [est] | 2 | 6.4 | estimate — needs user research |]]></code>
      <note>Every score tagged [est] so future readers (human and agent) know the data source.</note>
    </example>

    <rule>
      <statement>Use RICE for quarterly roadmap planning and data-driven feature comparison. Require at least Reach and Impact to be estimated before scoring.</statement>
      <rationale>RICE without Reach and Impact estimates is arbitrary ranking with extra steps. Skip RICE if user data is not available and use MoSCoW instead.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="MoSCoW Classification">
    <rule>
      <statement>Must items must not exceed 60% of total release scope. If everything is Must, require the team to demote items until the constraint is met.</statement>
      <rationale>Unrestricted Must lists defeat the purpose of MoSCoW. The 60% constraint forces genuine prioritization.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Document every Won't item with a one-sentence reason and a "when" (Phase 2, v2, never). The Won't-Do section in roadmap.md prevents the same items from being re-proposed in every grooming session.</statement>
      <rationale>Items without explicit exclusion reasoning re-emerge in every planning session, wasting grooming time on decisions already made.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Framework Selection">
    <list>
      <item>Quick sprint decisions or resource constraints: MoSCoW</item>
      <item>Quarterly roadmap with data available: RICE</item>
      <item>Small team, lightweight process: Value vs Effort 2x2 matrix</item>
      <item>Strategic theme identification across a large backlog: Outcome-Based (OKR-linked)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
