<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="backlog-grooming-roadmapping Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for backlog-grooming-roadmapping as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent-generated backlog items look certain and well-reasoned but are pure hypothesis.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs produce polished text that creates false confidence. Text quality does not equal idea quality. Always mark AI-generated items as hypothesis and require user validation before writing a spec.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent assigns 100% Confidence in RICE scores to almost all items.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents lack data to justify lower confidence, so they default to 100%. Require explicit justification for Confidence above 80% in agent-generated scores.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent assigns high RICE scores to technically interesting items regardless of business value.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents cannot distinguish strategic P0s from tactical P0s without explicit business context. Human must validate strategic feasibility before items move to todo/.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent adds items to backlog but never drops or archives old ones.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents reword and reorder but rarely delete. Backlogs grow unbounded without explicit cleanup instructions. Archive items older than 6 months with no progress to `.aidocs/backlog/.archive/`.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
