<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="product-discovery Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for product-discovery. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before designing any experiment, classify every assumption into exactly one of four risk types: Value (will customers use it?), Usability (can they figure it out?), Feasibility (can we build it?), Business Viability (does it work for the business?). Sort assumptions by risk type and severity before selecting methods.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Teams that skip risk classification default to testing easy assumptions (often Usability) while ignoring lethal ones (often Value or Business Viability). The classification forces the conversation about which risk would kill the idea if wrong.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Combine at least two Value-risk methods before concluding validation. Surveys alone are insufficient — users say one thing and do another.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-method value validation is the most common source of false positives in product discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use A/B testing only for optimization of existing surfaces, not for validating new concepts. For new concepts, prototype testing is the appropriate method.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A/B tests require sufficient traffic and a working implementation. Running them for concept validation burns engineering time that prototype testing avoids.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a technical spike before committing any assumption tagged feasibility=hi to delivery planning. A spike costs days; a wrong feasibility assumption costs a quarter.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Feasibility assumptions are the most underchecked risk type because engineers feel confident and PMs defer to them. A spike creates an explicit evidence artifact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always test the highest-severity assumption first, regardless of how easy a lower-severity test would be. The lethal risk is the one that would kill the idea if wrong; test it before investing in anything else.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Teams default to testing the most comfortable assumption. Explicit severity-first sorting overrides that bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>List every assumption the proposal makes — about user behaviour, willingness to pay, technical feasibility, and business model. No assumption is too obvious to list; obvious assumptions are often the ones that fail.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Undocumented assumptions cannot be validated. The act of listing them surfaces disagreements among team members before experiments are designed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sort assumptions by: severity (hi/md/lo) first, then effort to test (lo/md/hi) second. Focus the discovery sprint on the top 2-3 high-severity assumptions only.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Trying to validate all assumptions simultaneously dilutes effort. Discovery must converge on the assumptions that would kill the idea if wrong.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every experiment must specify: hypothesis ("If X then Y by Z%"), method, audience, sample size (with justification), duration, success threshold, and kill threshold. An experiment without a kill threshold cannot teach.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a pre-set kill threshold, confirmation bias wins — teams always find a way to interpret results as partial validation. Kill thresholds force honest decision-making.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Design experiments to falsify, not to confirm. For every proposed experiment, ask: "If this assumption is wrong, would this experiment catch it?" If no, redesign.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents and PMs default to confirmation-seeking designs. An explicit falsification test in the design step prevents the most common discovery error.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap at 1-2 active experiments per discovery cycle. Additional experiments go into a queue, not active execution.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Running too many experiments simultaneously makes causation impossible to attribute and splits team focus.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep experiments cheap: prototypes over code, scripts over services, fakes over builds. Never run production code during discovery.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Building during discovery defeats the cheap-fail principle. Production code creates sunk-cost pressure that biases the go/no-go decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document all learnings (including null results) in a research repository. Undocumented null results cause the same experiment to be run again in the next cycle.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Discovery without memory repeats itself. Null results are evidence; they are as valuable as positive results for constraining the solution space.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Final go/no-go is a human decision. The decision signals are: all critical risks addressed (Proceed), lethal risk not validated (Pivot or Kill), partial validation (More Discovery needed). Timebox "More Discovery" to prevent perpetual stalling.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs may flag Proceed on weak evidence because they cannot weigh business consequence. Human ownership of the final decision is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
