<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-risk-framework" title="Product Discovery Risk Framework: Four Risk Types and Technique Selection">
  <summary>The four risk types every product idea carries, discovery techniques mapped to each, and the rule for selecting experiments by severity.</summary>

  <section title="Four Risk Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before designing any experiment, classify every assumption into exactly one of four risk types: Value (will customers use it?), Usability (can they figure it out?), Feasibility (can we build it?), Business Viability (does it work for the business?). Sort assumptions by risk type and severity before selecting methods.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams that skip risk classification default to testing easy assumptions (often Usability) while ignoring lethal ones (often Value or Business Viability). The classification forces the conversation about which risk would kill the idea if wrong.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Value Risk Techniques">
    <p>Ordered by increasing effort and confidence: customer interviews (low effort, medium confidence), surveys (low effort, low confidence), fake-door tests (low effort, medium confidence), landing page tests (low effort, medium confidence), concierge MVP (medium effort, high confidence), Wizard of Oz (medium effort, high confidence).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Combine at least two Value-risk methods before concluding validation. Surveys alone are insufficient — users say one thing and do another.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-method value validation is the most common source of false positives in product discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Usability Risk Techniques">
    <p>Paper prototypes (low effort, low confidence), clickable prototypes (medium effort, medium confidence), moderated usability testing (medium effort, high confidence), A/B testing (high effort, very high confidence).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use A/B testing only for optimization of existing surfaces, not for validating new concepts. For new concepts, prototype testing is the appropriate method.</statement>
      <rationale>A/B tests require sufficient traffic and a working implementation. Running them for concept validation burns engineering time that prototype testing avoids.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Feasibility Risk Techniques">
    <p>Technical spike (low-medium effort, high confidence), architecture review (low effort, medium confidence), proof of concept (medium effort, high confidence), vendor evaluation (low effort, medium confidence).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a technical spike before committing any assumption tagged feasibility=hi to delivery planning. A spike costs days; a wrong feasibility assumption costs a quarter.</statement>
      <rationale>Feasibility assumptions are the most underchecked risk type because engineers feel confident and PMs defer to them. A spike creates an explicit evidence artifact.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Severity-First Selection Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always test the highest-severity assumption first, regardless of how easy a lower-severity test would be. The lethal risk is the one that would kill the idea if wrong; test it before investing in anything else.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams default to testing the most comfortable assumption. Explicit severity-first sorting overrides that bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Team has high-severity Value risk and medium-severity Usability risk. They run a usability test first because they have a prototype ready. Value assumption is never tested. Feature ships to zero adoption.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-process.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/experiment-report.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
