<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Product Discovery Process: Five Steps with Experiment Design Rules">
  <summary>The five-step discovery process from assumption mapping through a go/no-go decision, with rules for experiment design and antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Identify Assumptions">
    <rule>
      <statement>List every assumption the proposal makes — about user behaviour, willingness to pay, technical feasibility, and business model. No assumption is too obvious to list; obvious assumptions are often the ones that fail.</statement>
      <rationale>Undocumented assumptions cannot be validated. The act of listing them surfaces disagreements among team members before experiments are designed.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Prioritize Risks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Sort assumptions by: severity (hi/md/lo) first, then effort to test (lo/md/hi) second. Focus the discovery sprint on the top 2-3 high-severity assumptions only.</statement>
      <rationale>Trying to validate all assumptions simultaneously dilutes effort. Discovery must converge on the assumptions that would kill the idea if wrong.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Design Experiments">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every experiment must specify: hypothesis ("If X then Y by Z%"), method, audience, sample size (with justification), duration, success threshold, and kill threshold. An experiment without a kill threshold cannot teach.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a pre-set kill threshold, confirmation bias wins — teams always find a way to interpret results as partial validation. Kill thresholds force honest decision-making.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Design experiments to falsify, not to confirm. For every proposed experiment, ask: "If this assumption is wrong, would this experiment catch it?" If no, redesign.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents and PMs default to confirmation-seeking designs. An explicit falsification test in the design step prevents the most common discovery error.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap at 1-2 active experiments per discovery cycle. Additional experiments go into a queue, not active execution.</statement>
      <rationale>Running too many experiments simultaneously makes causation impossible to attribute and splits team focus.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/experiment-report.md">Experiment design and results template with all required fields.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/validate-experiment.py">Gate script that rejects experiments missing kill threshold, sample size, or power calculation.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Run and Learn">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep experiments cheap: prototypes over code, scripts over services, fakes over builds. Never run production code during discovery.</statement>
      <rationale>Building during discovery defeats the cheap-fail principle. Production code creates sunk-cost pressure that biases the go/no-go decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Document all learnings (including null results) in a research repository. Undocumented null results cause the same experiment to be run again in the next cycle.</statement>
      <rationale>Discovery without memory repeats itself. Null results are evidence; they are as valuable as positive results for constraining the solution space.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Decide">
    <rule>
      <statement>Final go/no-go is a human decision. The decision signals are: all critical risks addressed (Proceed), lethal risk not validated (Pivot or Kill), partial validation (More Discovery needed). Timebox "More Discovery" to prevent perpetual stalling.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs may flag Proceed on weak evidence because they cannot weigh business consequence. Human ownership of the final decision is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Discovery cycle extends beyond 4 weeks with the justification "we need more data".</description>
      <reason>Permanent stalling disguised as discovery is a decision avoidance pattern. Hard timeboxing forces the team to decide with the evidence at hand.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-risk-framework.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/discovery-kickoff.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
