<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Platform Team Charter Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of platform-team-charter-template enforces. Each rule has a statement, a rationale anchored to industry practice, and a source citation.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Charter names primary customer (other engineering teams) explicitly — not 'the business'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Team Topologies — Platform team chapter">Vague customers make scope decisions political; explicit customers enable product-team-style prioritisation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Charter ships with an anti-charter: enumerated work the platform team does NOT do.</statement>
      <rationale source="ThoughtWorks Platform Engineering blog">Without anti-charter, scope creep is inevitable; the team becomes a help desk for everyone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every paved-road service has a documented SLA (availability, support response) and a sunset criterion.</statement>
      <rationale source="Humanitec IDP report 2026">Services without SLA become unpredictable; without sunset criterion they accumulate as forever-debt.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Support model is tiered: self-service docs → office hours → on-call escalation. No 'just slack the platform team'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Spotify Tech Health Check">Unbounded slack-support consumes the team and erodes paved-road work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Success metrics are platform-health metrics (adoption, lead time, defect rate) — not vanity output metrics.</statement>
      <rationale source="DORA Accelerate">Vanity metrics (PRs shipped) reward busywork; health metrics reward outcome.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, skip this methodology and route to the adjacent one referenced in Related.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 skill-authoring conventions">A skip rule keeps the decision tree closed: every branch ends at a real rule id.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>