<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="terraform-modules-versioning">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>infrastructure-engineer</domain>
    <summary>Semantic versioning, version constraint syntax, CHANGELOG maintenance, and registry publication checklist for Terraform modules used by multiple consumers.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>terraform</tag>
      <tag>modules</tag>
      <tag>versioning</tag>
      <tag>semver</tag>
      <tag>registry</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>iac</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <languages>
      <language>hcl</language>
    </languages>
    <frameworks>
      <framework>terraform</framework>
    </frameworks>
    <related>
      <ref slug="terraform-modules-structure"/>
      <ref slug="terraform-modules-composition"/>
      <ref slug="terraform-basics"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Terraform Module Versioning</title>

    <summary>Published Terraform modules MUST use Semantic Versioning (SemVer) with Git tags, version constraints on every module source reference, and a maintained CHANGELOG.md. Without pinned version constraints, a module update can silently break all consumers on the next terraform init.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Terraform resolves module versions at init time. An unpinned module source (no version argument) fetches the latest commit on the default branch. If a breaking change is merged overnight, every pipeline that runs terraform init the next day picks it up — often during a production apply. Pinned version constraints make upgrades explicit and reviewable. SemVer communicates the impact of a release to consumers without requiring them to read every diff.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Authoring a module consumed by more than one caller (team-shared or registry module).</item>
        <item>Upgrading a module dependency — need to understand what constraint syntax is safe.</item>
        <item>Releasing a new module version — need the correct tag and CHANGELOG format.</item>
        <item>Setting up a new consumer module call — choosing the right version constraint operator.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Private local modules referenced by relative path (./modules/vpc) in a mono-repo — they have no separate release lifecycle.</item>
        <item>Single-team repos where the module author and all callers commit in the same branch — version pinning adds overhead without benefit.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="semver">
      <p>SemVer defines three version segments: MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH. For Terraform modules, the key distinction is whether a change requires consumers to update their module call.</p>

      <rules>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Major version bumps (X.0.0) MUST be used for any change that requires consumers to update variable names, remove previously supported variables, or change output names. A migration guide MUST accompany every major release.</statement>
          <rationale>Without a clear signal, consumers cannot distinguish a bug fix from a breaking change at a glance. Major bumps give teams a predictable gate for planning upgrades.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Minor version bumps (0.X.0) MUST be used for new optional variables, new outputs, or new resources that are backward-compatible. Existing callers MUST continue to work without modification.</statement>
          <rationale>Consumers who rely on ~&gt; constraints (see below) will pick up minor versions automatically. Breaking backward compatibility in a minor bump violates consumer expectations.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Patch version bumps (0.0.X) MUST be used for bug fixes that do not add new features or change behavior. No consumer code changes required.</statement>
          <rationale>Patch bumps signal safe auto-adoption for consumers using pessimistic constraints.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </rules>

      <example type="good" title="SemVer version decision table">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Change                                         → Version bump
----------------------------------------------------------
Rename variable `enable_nat` → `nat_enabled`  → MAJOR (2.0.0)
Remove deprecated output `subnet_id`           → MAJOR (2.0.0)
Add new optional variable `enable_ipv6`        → MINOR (1.1.0)
Add new output `ipv6_cidr_block`               → MINOR (1.1.0)
Fix NAT gateway depends_on race condition      → PATCH (1.0.1)
Update default instance type for cost          → PATCH (1.0.1)
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="version-constraints">
      <p>The version argument on a module source controls which releases Terraform will accept. Using the wrong operator is the most common cause of accidental breaking-change adoption.</p>

      <rules>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>All module source references that include a version argument MUST use the pessimistic constraint operator (~&gt;) to allow patch and minor updates within a major version, or an explicit range. The exact-pin operator (=) MUST only be used when a specific patch is known to fix a critical bug.</statement>
          <rationale>~&gt; 5.0 allows 5.0.1, 5.1.0, 5.9.9 but blocks 6.0.0 — safe for routine updates while blocking breaking changes. Exact pins require manual bumps for every patch release, increasing maintenance burden.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Registry and GitHub module sources MUST always include the version argument. Local path sources (./modules/X) MUST NOT include a version argument.</statement>
          <rationale>Local modules have no separate release lifecycle — the version argument is ignored and its presence misleads maintainers.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </rules>

      <example type="good" title="Version constraint examples">
        <code lang="hcl"><![CDATA[
# Registry module — pessimistic constraint (recommended)
module "vpc" {
  source  = "terraform-aws-modules/vpc/aws"
  version = "~> 5.0"      # >= 5.0.0, < 6.0.0
}

# Registry module — explicit range
module "s3" {
  source  = "terraform-aws-modules/s3-bucket/aws"
  version = ">= 4.0, < 5.0"
}

# GitHub module — pinned to exact tag (acceptable for external repos)
module "network" {
  source = "github.com/org/terraform-modules//network?ref=v1.2.3"
}

# Local module — no version argument
module "ecs" {
  source = "./modules/ecs"
}
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Unpinned module source">
        <code lang="hcl"><![CDATA[
# No version argument — fetches latest on every terraform init
module "vpc" {
  source = "terraform-aws-modules/vpc/aws"
}
]]></code>
        <note>Any breaking change merged to the upstream module HEAD will be adopted silently on the next terraform init, breaking the next plan or apply.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="changelog">
      <p>The CHANGELOG.md is the consumer-facing release log. It must be maintained as part of every release, not retroactively.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every published module MUST maintain a CHANGELOG.md in the module root. Each release MUST document: the version number, release date, and categorized changes (Added, Changed, Breaking Changes, Fixed, Deprecated, Removed). Breaking changes MUST be in their own section and include migration instructions.</statement>
        <rationale>Consumers deciding whether to upgrade need to evaluate impact without reading the full diff. A categorized CHANGELOG reduces the upgrade decision from O(diff) to O(CHANGELOG section).</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="CHANGELOG.md format">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Changelog

## [2.1.0] - 2025-01-15
### Added
- Support for IPv6 CIDR blocks
- New output `ipv6_cidr_block`

### Changed
- Default instance type updated to t3.medium

## [2.0.0] - 2024-11-01
### Breaking Changes
- Renamed variable `enable_nat` to `nat_gateway_enabled`
- Removed deprecated `single_nat_gateway` variable

### Migration
Replace in all module calls:
  enable_nat = true  →  nat_gateway_enabled = true
Remove any `single_nat_gateway` references.
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="release-checklist">
      <p>A release checklist prevents common omissions that break the registry sync or leave consumers without upgrade guidance.</p>

      <checklist>
        <check>Version follows SemVer — verify MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH classification against the change table.</check>
        <check>CHANGELOG.md updated with new version section before tagging.</check>
        <check>Breaking changes documented with migration guide (required for MAJOR bumps).</check>
        <check>README includes updated usage example matching new variable names.</check>
        <check>Git tag created with vX.Y.Z format (e.g., v2.1.0).</check>
        <check>Registry sync verified after tag push (Terraform Registry auto-syncs from GitHub tags).</check>
        <check>Team notified of breaking changes (major releases require consumer team awareness).</check>
        <check>Internal consumer modules updated if managed in the same repo.</check>
      </checklist>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="terraform-modules-structure"/>
      <ref slug="terraform-modules-composition"/>
      <link href="https://developer.hashicorp.com/terraform/tutorials/modules/pattern-module-creation"/>
      <link href="https://semver.org/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
