<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Ad Account Hygiene Checklist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Ad Account Hygiene Checklist MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="weekly-monthly-split" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Checklist MUST partition items into weekly (14 items) and monthly (8 items) cadences. Mixed-cadence checklists are skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational checklist practice">Items with mixed cadences confuse owners; explicit splits create a runnable ritual.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="per-platform-tag" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every item MUST tag platform (Google / Meta / LinkedIn / other). Cross-platform checklists invite skips.</statement>
      <rationale source="PPC operations practice">Platform-specific items skipped silently when not tagged; tagging surfaces them in audits.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="completion-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each completed item MUST log evidence (timestamp + reviewer + observation). Self-attestation alone is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-log practice">Self-attestation without evidence fails audits; evidence anchors trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="owner-per-item" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every item MUST have a named owner. Un-owned items default to 'no one' and skip silently.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene — PMBOK 7">Checklists with shared ownership collapse; explicit owner is the only enforcement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-with-reason" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skipped items MUST log a written reason in the audit log. Blank skips invalidate the cycle.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene">Silent skips are how drift creeps in; reasons surface patterns over quarters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
