<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-structure" title="Focus Group Structure, Composition, and Moderation Rules">
  <summary>When focus groups beat interviews, group composition rules, discussion guide structure, and moderation techniques.</summary>

  <section title="Method Choice">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use focus groups for attitude exploration, concept reactions, language discovery, and cross-segment comparison. Do not use them for usability testing, sensitive topics, individual behavior measurement, or final go/no-go decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Group dynamics are a feature for attitude exploration (diverse reactions surface quickly) and a bug for usability testing (participants suppress struggle when observed by peers). The method matches some research goals and actively harms others.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run minimum 2-3 groups per segment. Never report a finding from a single group.</statement>
      <rationale>A single group finding is anecdote, not pattern. Group composition, moderator dynamics, and random participant selection create too much session-level noise for any single group to be representative.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Group Composition">
    <rule>
      <statement>6-10 participants per group. Homogeneous enough for comfort (common frame of reference), diverse enough for variety (different perspectives). Run 2-4 groups total.</statement>
      <rationale>Below 6: insufficient dynamic diversity. Above 10: moderator cannot manage all voices; quieter participants get lost. Homogeneity enables candor; diversity enables range.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Screen aggressively for professional respondents (people who cycle across studies). Use live screener calls or short video tasks to verify participation quality.</statement>
      <rationale>Professional respondents give polished, rehearsed answers that do not represent real users. They are common on large panel platforms and inflate perceived consensus.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Discussion Guide Structure">
    <p>Standard 90-min structure: Opening 5 min (introductions, ground rules) → Warm-up 10 min (easy questions) → Core topics 40-60 min (3 topics maximum) → Concept reaction 15 min (if showing stimuli) → Wrap-up 5 min (summary, final thoughts).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Show concepts and stimuli only after the warm-up and initial topic exploration. Introducing stimuli too early biases the discussion toward reacting to your framing rather than expressing independent attitudes.</statement>
      <rationale>Pre-stimulus exploration captures the user's unprompted mental model. Introducing stimuli first anchors all subsequent discussion to the product frame, suppressing organic vocabulary and unprompted concerns.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Moderation Techniques">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture written first-impressions (silent post-it round) before group discussion to break anchoring on the first speaker's view. Then open the floor.</statement>
      <rationale>The first speaker's view anchors the whole group. Written capture before discussion preserves independent assessments that would otherwise be lost to social conformity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/discussion-guide.md">Full 90-min discussion guide template</reference>
  </section>
</text>
