<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-analysis" title="Focus Group Analysis: Themes, Cross-Group Comparison, and Reporting">
  <summary>Post-session pipeline, cross-group comparison framework, theme extraction rules, and reporting structure.</summary>

  <section title="Post-Session Pipeline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use speaker diarization on all focus group recordings. Without speaker labels, transcript analysis cannot identify dominant-participant skew or per-segment quote attribution.</statement>
      <rationale>Dominant participants can drive 40-60% of transcript volume. Without diarization, LLM theme extraction weights their views as group consensus. Diarization allows per-speaker filtering before analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a dissent prompt pass explicitly after the consensus pass: "What disagreement existed within this group?" LLMs are biased toward consensus narratives and collapse nuanced dissent into a single theme without explicit prompting.</statement>
      <rationale>Consensus-biased synthesis misses the finding that often matters most: the minority view, the segment-specific objection, the latent concern. Dissent prompting is the structural counter to this bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/postprocess.sh">Post-session pipeline: audio extract → diarize → theme extract</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Cross-Group Comparison">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag transcripts with both speaker ID and segment label before analysis. Filter synthesis prompts by segment to surface cross-group contrasts: shared themes, segment-unique themes, and contradictions.</statement>
      <rationale>Untagged cross-group analysis merges distinct segment signals and produces a false "global user" view. Segment filtering preserves the core value of running multiple groups.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Count unique speakers per theme, not utterance count, to assess theme strength. Polite agreement ("yeah, that's right") is not endorsement.</statement>
      <rationale>High utterance count from a single speaker inflates theme strength artificially. Unique-speaker count is the correct denominator: consensus = most participants expressed the theme independently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Reporting">
    <p>Report structure per finding: theme name → what we heard (summary) → representative verbatim quote with speaker type → implication for design or strategy.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Report per-group findings before cross-group synthesis. Never aggregate groups before documenting group-level patterns.</statement>
      <rationale>Early aggregation destroys segment signals. Cross-group synthesis must build on documented per-group patterns, not replace them.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
