<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="focus-groups Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for focus-groups as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Dominant participant drives the transcript and LLM analysis treats their views as group consensus.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without diarization and speaker-filtered analysis, a participant generating 50% of transcript volume gets 50% weight in theme extraction. Always diarize and compute unique-speaker-count per theme before any consensus claims.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Online groups analyzed without adjusting for the ~30% nonverbal signal loss versus in-person sessions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Zoom groups flatten energy, disagreement, and hesitation. Online findings should be framed as stated attitudes only, not as a proxy for in-person dynamics. Use smaller groups (4-6) and more structured activities to compensate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM theme extraction over-clusters nuanced disagreement into a single theme without explicit dissent prompting.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs trained on consensus-seeking corpora produce consensus-seeking summaries. Force dissent extraction with a separate pass: "What disagreements or tensions existed?" before merging with the consensus pass.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-generated themes form neat categories without an unclassified bucket.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every real focus group transcript contains messy, boundary-spanning material that resists clean categorization. Forcing 100% classification loses the material that often drives the most interesting insights. Always include a "messy/unclassified" bucket.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM-generated discussion guides over-rely on closed-ended probing questions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents produce grammatically correct but logically leading questions by default. Human researchers must rewrite at least 30% of probes for genuine openness before the guide is used.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
