<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cannibalization Detection SOP Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `Cannibalization Detection SOP` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="query-page-mapping-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The report MUST contain a Search-Console-sourced query → ranking-page mapping for the top 200 queries by clicks. Hand-collected mappings forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Search-Console-based audit practice 2024-2026">Hand-collected mappings miss the long-tail; SC-sourced data is the only complete picture of which page ranks for what.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="intent-overlap-scored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each cannibalization candidate MUST carry an intent-overlap score (0-3: distinct / partial / heavy / identical) with rationale. Distinct (0) candidates are dropped from the report.</statement>
      <rationale source="Intent-clustering SEO research 2024">Bare URL-overlap surfaces false positives; intent scoring filters out the legitimate dual-coverage cases.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="consolidation-or-deopt-recommended" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each surviving candidate MUST carry a recommendation: consolidate (one canonical, 301 the other) OR de-optimize (narrow the loser&apos;s intent). Hand-wave &apos;optimize&apos; recommendations are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="SEO consolidation audit corpus">Vague &apos;optimize&apos; recommendations stall execution; the binary consolidate-or-deopt forces a decision.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="named-redirect-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each consolidation recommendation MUST name the engineer who will deploy the 301 redirect and the date. Group handles forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal redirect-execution audit">Group-owned redirects rot at 80% within 60 days; named owner + date converts to ~70% execution rate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="baseline-traffic-snapshotted" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The report MUST snapshot baseline organic traffic (clicks, impressions, position) per affected URL before consolidation, with a 30-day post-consolidation check scheduled at report-sign-time.</statement>
      <rationale source="SEO migration validation practice">Without baseline snapshots, post-merge regression goes unmeasured; snapshot + 30-day check makes the win or loss visible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>