<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-service-selection" title="AWS Service Selection: Serverless vs Containers">
  <summary>Decision criteria for choosing Lambda, ECS/Fargate, or EKS, with a hybrid-by-default stance for 2025-2026.</summary>

  <section title="Compute Decision">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose Lambda when traffic is variable or spiky, execution is under 15 minutes, cold start is acceptable, and GPU is not required.</statement>
      <rationale>Lambda costs per invocation; idle time costs nothing. Containers cost per provisioned hour regardless of traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose containers (EKS/ECS/Fargate) for steady 24/7 workloads, long-running processes, GPU requirements, or when Kubernetes ecosystem is needed.</statement>
      <rationale>Reserved container capacity is cheaper than Lambda at high sustained throughput. GPU workloads require EC2-backed compute.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to a hybrid architecture: Lambda for event-driven and sporadic workloads, containers for always-on services.</statement>
      <rationale>78% of engineering teams run hybrid architectures. The question is which workload belongs where, not a binary choice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>E-commerce: EKS for the main web API (steady traffic), Lambda for order notifications (spiky), Step Functions for payment workflow (stateful).</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running all workloads as Lambda including a websocket server or ML inference service.</description>
      <reason>Lambda has a 15-minute timeout, no persistent connections, and no GPU support.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Container Orchestration Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose Fargate (ECS or EKS) when the team lacks Kubernetes expertise or wants to avoid node management overhead.</statement>
      <rationale>Fargate is fully managed; no patching, scaling, or capacity planning for nodes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose EKS when multi-cloud portability, Helm ecosystem, or advanced scheduling is required.</statement>
      <rationale>EKS uses standard Kubernetes APIs, enabling migration to other clouds or on-prem clusters.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Database Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use RDS Aurora for relational OLTP workloads; use DynamoDB for key-value or document access patterns requiring single-digit millisecond latency at any scale.</statement>
      <rationale>Aurora provides Aurora PostgreSQL compatibility with auto-scaling storage. DynamoDB avoids connection pooling limits at high concurrency.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Integration Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use EventBridge for decoupled cross-service routing; use Step Functions for stateful orchestration; use SQS for async buffering with retry; use SNS for fan-out notifications.</statement>
      <rationale>Each service solves a distinct coordination problem. Using SQS for routing or SNS for stateful workflows creates operational complexity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Well-Architected Pillars">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply all six Well-Architected pillars: Operational Excellence, Security, Reliability, Performance Efficiency, Cost Optimization, Sustainability.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping any pillar creates technical debt: missing Security leads to breaches; missing Cost Optimization leads to uncontrolled spend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to Graviton (ARM64) instances for all new compute resources; justify x86 explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale>Graviton provides 20% lower cost and comparable or better performance for most workloads.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
