<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-event-driven-patterns" title="AWS Event-Driven Architecture Patterns">
  <summary>EventBridge, Step Functions, SNS, and SQS integration patterns with error handling rules.</summary>

  <section title="EventBridge">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a custom event bus (not default) for application events; enable event archive with 30-day retention for replay capability.</statement>
      <rationale>The default event bus mixes AWS service events with application events. Archiving enables replay during outages.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always configure a dead-letter queue and retry policy on every EventBridge target rule.</statement>
      <rationale>Without DLQ, failed event deliveries are silently dropped. EventBridge retries up to 185 times over 24 hours by default.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="hcl"><![CDATA[
resource "aws_cloudwatch_event_target" "notify" {
  rule           = aws_cloudwatch_event_rule.order_created.name
  event_bus_name = aws_cloudwatch_event_bus.main.name
  target_id      = "notify-customer"
  arn            = aws_lambda_function.notify.arn

  dead_letter_config {
    arn = aws_sqs_queue.dlq.arn
  }

  retry_policy {
    maximum_event_age_in_seconds = 3600
    maximum_retry_attempts       = 3
  }
}
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="SQS vs SNS vs Step Functions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use SQS Standard for async decoupling with at-least-once delivery; use SQS FIFO when message ordering matters; use SNS for fan-out to multiple subscribers.</statement>
      <rationale>SQS provides buffering and retry; SNS delivers immediately to all subscribers without buffering.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Step Functions for workflows with more than 2 sequential steps, error handling, or human approval gates.</statement>
      <rationale>Chaining Lambda functions directly via code creates invisible retry logic and poor observability. Step Functions provides visual state machines with built-in retry/catch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using SNS as a queue replacement for a single consumer.</description>
      <reason>SNS has no retention — if the consumer is down, messages are lost. Use SQS for single-consumer reliable delivery.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Choreography vs Orchestration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use EventBridge choreography for loosely coupled, independently deployable services; use Step Functions orchestration for multi-step transactions requiring compensation (saga pattern).</statement>
      <rationale>Choreography reduces coupling but makes flow hard to trace. Orchestration centralizes visibility at the cost of coupling to the orchestrator.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
