<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="continuous-discovery-habits">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Weekly discovery cadence via Opportunity Solution Tree: classify nodes, score on reach×frequency×severity×addressability, test assumptions before building.</summary>
    <category>discovery</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>discovery</tag>
      <tag>product-trio</tag>
      <tag>opportunity-solution-tree</tag>
      <tag>torres</tag>
      <tag>customer-research</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="competitor-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="user-personas"/>
      <ref slug="portfolio-strategy"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Continuous Discovery Habits</title>

    <summary>Teresa Torres' framework: a product trio (PM + Design Lead + Tech Lead) runs weekly customer touchpoints and maps all signals into an Opportunity Solution Tree (OST). Every node is classified as outcome, opportunity, solution, or assumption test. Opportunities are scored on reach × frequency × severity × addressability. Selected opportunities spawn falsifiable assumption tests before any build. Discovery output traces to delivery via opp_id in SDD specs and PR titles.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Discovery as a one-time project kickoff produces roadmaps that miss user reality within weeks. A weekly cadence — at least one customer touchpoint per week — keeps the team continuously calibrated. The OST makes opportunity-to-solution tracing explicit and forces rejection of solution-shaped feature requests at intake. Without continuous discovery, shipped features frequently don't move the Outcome, and the team has no structured diagnosis path.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Active product with paying users where weekly discovery output must convert into roadmap moves</item>
        <item>Quarterly OKR cycle where each Outcome must trace to opportunities, then to assumption tests</item>
        <item>Backlog grooming: rejecting feature requests disguised as solutions and recasting as opportunities</item>
        <item>Roadmap negotiation where the OST provides a defensible structure for "why not feature X"</item>
        <item>Solo/small-team where agents fill discovery gaps by mining tickets, analytics, and sales calls</item>
        <item>Post-launch when shipped features aren't moving the Outcome — to diagnose the broken assumption</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF or zero-user products — no signal volume to support a weekly cadence; use customer-development or problem-validation first</item>
        <item>Crisis triage (active outage, churn cliff, security incident) — pause discovery, resume after</item>
        <item>Hardware / regulated medical / enterprise sales with 6–18 month cycles — adapt to monthly windows</item>
        <item>Stakeholder culture demanding validation from a single interview — pick a different framework</item>
        <item>Pure platform/infra teams whose users are other engineers — adapt with DX telemetry instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="ost-node-types">
      <p>Teresa Torres' OST structure, node classification rules, opportunity scoring model, weekly cadence, and anti-patterns to avoid.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Classify every OST node as one of: outcome, opportunity, solution, or assumption_test. Reject any node that doesn't fit cleanly into one type and re-prompt for the correct classification.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixed-type nodes (opportunity disguised as solution) cause the team to build solutions to problems nobody actually has. Strict classification at intake prevents this.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Reject inputs phrased as features ("add filter X", "redesign onboarding"). Re-prompt for the underlying customer need. Never add a solution node to the OST without a parent opportunity.</statement>
        <rationale>Feature requests are hypotheses about solutions, not observed customer needs. The OST forces the team to identify the need before evaluating solutions, which improves outcome probability.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="opportunity-scoring">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Score opportunities on (reach × frequency × severity × addressability), 1–5 each. Emit numeric scores and surface week-over-week deltas. Never score on gut feel.</statement>
        <rationale>Gut-feel prioritization produces roadmaps that bias toward vocal stakeholders. Numeric scoring with consistent dimensions makes the reasoning auditable and improvable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Cap visible opportunities per Outcome at 7 ± 2. Archive overflow to parked/. Larger trees become invisible and stop driving decisions.</statement>
        <rationale>Miller's Law: working memory holds 7 ± 2 items. OSTs with 30+ opportunities cause stakeholders to skip the tree entirely, defeating the purpose of the structure.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="assumption-testing">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every opportunity selected for build must spawn at least one falsifiable assumption test from: smoke test, fake door, prototype, Wizard of Oz, or concierge. "Ship and measure" is not a test.</statement>
        <rationale>Shipping without a pre-specified falsifiable test converts learning into luck. The test menu provides concrete low-cost options that generate evidence before a full build commitment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Never declare "validated." Use "tested" with explicit pass/fail criteria and a signal count (n_signals). Require n_signals &gt;= 5 for any claim of pattern recognition.</statement>
        <rationale>"Validated" is a banned word in Torres' framework. It implies certainty that a test cannot provide. "Tested" with explicit criteria is honest and actionable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="weekly-cadence">
      <p>Monday: review customer feedback queue. Tuesday: customer interview (30 min). Wednesday: analyze interview + behavioral data. Thursday: team sync, share insights. Friday: plan next week's discovery. Discovery capacity target: 15–20% of team capacity. Alert if below 10% for two consecutive weeks.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Tie discovery to delivery in tooling: opp_id in PR titles, in SDD spec front-matter, in commit trailers. Block PRs that touch specs without an opp_id reference.</statement>
        <rationale>Without tooling linkage, discovery and delivery decouple silently. The opp_id convention makes the learning loop visible in the delivery record.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="anti-patterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Discovery as one-time project kickoff: interviews only when building new features.</description>
        <reason>One-time discovery produces a roadmap calibrated to a single point in time. Weekly cadence keeps calibration continuous as customer behavior and market evolve.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>PM does all discovery alone; Design and Tech leads don't attend interviews.</description>
        <reason>Trio dilution causes Design and Tech to lose customer intuition. OST scoring anchors on PM bias rather than cross-functional perspective. Rotate which Lead reviews synthesis each week.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>OST rot: opportunities accumulate because agents add fast but humans prune slow.</description>
        <reason>Without a monthly archival pass, the tree becomes unsearchable in ~8 weeks. Schedule a monthly kill-list pass as mandatory, not optional.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>The product-planning loop sits downstream of research collection and upstream of delivery. Agents bridge the three:</p>

      <p>research-collection (upstream) → product-planning (this lens) → delivery (SDD). raw signals → tagged notes, ost-curator → opportunity-scorer → trio-deliberation, opportunity-solution-tree.md → spec.md (opp_id)</p>

      <p>In practice on this repo: faion-sdd-executor-agent consumes specs that cite opportunity IDs; the planning loop is what produces those IDs. Research subagents (researcher domain) feed the OST curator; planning subagents convert OST leaves into SDD backlog items. Use loop skill for cadence triggers and schedule skill for managed cron triggers.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Route via intake-classifier (haiku) before escalating to opus. Only trio deliberation warrants opus; classification is deterministic and cheap.</statement>
        <rationale>Running opus on every intake item is 10x the cost with no quality improvement for classification. The model tier should match the reasoning complexity of the task.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="subagent-roles-and-models">
      <p>intake-classifier (haiku, real-time): classifies requests as opportunity | solution | bug. ost-curator (sonnet, weekly): updates OST, dedupes. opportunity-scorer (sonnet, weekly): scores on reach x frequency x severity x addressability. assumption-designer (sonnet, per opportunity): designs falsifiable test plan. trio-deliberation-agent (opus, bi-weekly): build | test | park | kill with rationale. roadmap-synth (opus, monthly): kill list + doubled-down list. outcome-tracker (haiku, daily): outcome trend + flag if Outcome unchanged > 4 weeks. spec-linker (haiku, on PR open): verify opp_id in spec front-matter.</p>

      <p>Keep cheap models on collection and tagging; reserve opus for bi-weekly+ deliberation where reasoning across the full OST matters.</p>

      <p>Repo subagents to wire into this flow: faion-sdd-executor-agent — consumes specs that reference opp_id; this loop produces those IDs. skills/faion:brainstorm/ — invoke for diverge/converge when the trio cannot agree on which opportunity to test next. skills/faion:improver/ — invoke when outcome-tracker flags a stagnant Outcome (treat as a system-improvement session). skills/faion/knowledge/pro/research/researcher/continuous-discovery/ — upstream sibling for the research collection angle.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-pattern">
      <example type="good" title="Continuous Discovery Prompt Structure">
        <code lang="xml"><![CDATA[
<role>You are the {agent}. Continuous Discovery (Torres) -- product-planning lens.</role>
<inputs>
  <ost>{path to opportunity-solution-tree.md}</ost>
  <intake>{path to intake-queue.md}</intake>
  <outcomes>{path to outcomes-register.md}</outcomes>
  <delivered>{path to recent merged PRs with opp_id refs}</delivered>
  <segment_filter>{optional: limit to a user segment}</segment_filter>
</inputs>
<rules>
  - Classify every node as: outcome | opportunity | solution | assumption_test.
  - Reject inputs phrased as features; re-prompt for the underlying need.
  - Never declare "validated"; use "tested" with explicit pass/fail criteria.
  - Score opportunities with (reach * frequency * severity * addressability), 1-5 each.
  - Cap visible opportunities per Outcome at 7; archive overflow to parked/.
  - Output JSON matching {schema_path}; emit a markdown digest &lt;= 60 lines.
</rules>
<task>{cadence-specific instruction}</task>
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Intake-classifier passing "add filter X" through without explicit few-shot rejection examples.</description>
        <reason>Provide at least 10 few-shot rejections of solution-phrased requests in the classifier prompt. Without examples, the classifier will accept solution framing at the same rate as humans do without training.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>OST-curator aggressively deduping and merging opportunities that cross different Outcomes.</description>
        <reason>Require human review on any merge that crosses Outcome boundaries. Cross-Outcome merges lose the linkage between an opportunity and its parent Outcome metric.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Opportunity-scorer hallucinating reach numbers when analytics fetch fails.</description>
        <reason>Require a fetched_at timestamp and source URL in every score row. Reject scores without provenance rather than proceeding with fabricated numbers.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Trio-deliberation agent rubber-stamping the highest-scoring opportunity every run.</description>
        <reason>Force the agent to nominate a devil's-advocate alternative on every run. Without this, the deliberation reduces to a score-sorter rather than a reasoning process.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Outcome-tracker declaring improvement on noisy daily metrics after a single positive day.</description>
        <reason>Require a 2-week rolling window minimum before any Outcome status change. Single-day signals are noise at standard metric variance levels.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pin one Outcome at the OST root before any opportunity work; without a measurable Outcome, agents drift into solution mining.</item>
        <item>Force "opportunity vs solution" classification at intake; reject anything phrased as a feature and re-prompt for the underlying need (intake-classifier does this automatically).</item>
        <item>Cap visible opportunities per Outcome at 7 ± 2; agents archive overflow to a parked/ branch monthly. Larger trees become invisible.</item>
        <item>Score opportunities on (reach × frequency × severity × addressability), not gut feel; agents emit numeric scores and surface week-over-week deltas.</item>
        <item>Every opportunity selected for build must spawn at least one falsifiable assumption test from the menu: smoke test, fake door, prototype, Wizard of Oz, concierge. "Ship and measure" is not a test.</item>
        <item>Tie discovery to delivery in tooling: opp_id in PR titles, in SDD spec front-matter, in commit trailers. Spec-linker enforces this.</item>
        <item>Rotate the human reviewer of synthesis output weekly; agents anchor on prior patterns, humans catch curse-of-knowledge.</item>
        <item>Capacity rule: discovery 15–20%, tech debt 10–15%, delivery 65–75%. Track in outcomes-register.md; alert if discovery drops below 10% for two consecutive weeks.</item>
        <item>Monthly research-reviewer pass must produce a "kill list" alongside the doubled-down list; without pruning, OSTs collapse under their own weight.</item>
        <item>Token budget: weekly score + trio deliberation ≤ 30k tokens, monthly roadmap synth ≤ 80k. Pre-summarize per-day with haiku, feed summaries to opus.</item>
        <item>Privacy: never feed raw PII transcripts to a non-zero-retention model. Use ZDR-eligible Anthropic endpoints or strip PII pre-prompt.</item>
        <item>Single source of truth: pick Productboard OR Dovetail OR Notion as canonical OST home; mirror to the others. Dual-write breaks evidence linking.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-failure-modes">
      <list>
        <item>OST rot: opportunities accumulate because agents add fast and humans prune slow. Without a monthly archival pass the tree becomes unsearchable in ~8 weeks.</item>
        <item>Discovery-delivery decoupling: discovery output never traces to a PR or spec. Symptom: spec.md files have no opp_id references. Fix: require opportunity ID in PR title and SDD spec front-matter.</item>
        <item>"Solution mining" by stakeholders: requests arrive as "add filter X". If the intake agent does not classify and reject, the OST fills with solutions disguised as opportunities.</item>
        <item>Trio dilution: when only the PM attends interviews, Design and Tech leads lose intuition. Agents can simulate trio coverage, but the human PM must rotate which Lead reviews synthesis, otherwise OST scoring anchors on PM bias.</item>
        <item>Capacity over-allocation: 15–20% discovery is the canonical number; teams under PMF pressure drop to 5% and the OST silently dies.</item>
        <item>Recruiting infrastructure debt: weekly interviews require a recurring source (in-app prompt, customer panel, Userinterviews API). Without it cadence collapses by week 4.</item>
        <item>LLM synthesis hallucination: small-N pattern claims (N&lt;5) drift into "validated" language; require schema-level rejection of the word "validated" and an explicit n_signals ≥ threshold.</item>
        <item>Roadmap fatigue: 30+ opportunities make stakeholders skip the OST. Cap visible opportunities per Outcome at 7 ± 2; archive the rest under "parked".</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>claude (Claude Code) — Orchestrate subagents; one slash command per cadence (/discovery-intake, /discovery-score, /discovery-trio). https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/claude-code</item>
        <item>gh — Pull issues/PRs as intake signal; verify opp_id in PR titles. gh CLI</item>
        <item>linear CLI — Query feature requests + bug clusters; tag against OST nodes. https://developers.linear.app</item>
        <item>productboard CLI / API — Sync opportunities + insights bidirectionally. https://developer.productboard.com</item>
        <item>notion CLI — Mirror OST into team Notion; pull comments back as intake. https://developers.notion.com</item>
        <item>posthog / amplitude-cli — Outcome metric trend; feeds outcome-tracker. https://posthog.com/docs/api</item>
        <item>dovetail API — Pull tagged research notes as OST evidence. https://developers.dovetail.com</item>
        <item>cron / systemd-timer — Run cadence triggers; on NERO use loop/schedule skill. systemd timers, cron</item>
        <item>gh actions — Spec-linker: PR check that blocks merge if SDD spec lacks opp_id. https://docs.github.com/actions</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-integration-tools">
      <p>Productboard (SaaS, agent-friendly with REST + webhooks) — Native OST-shaped objects: Objectives → Drivers → Features. Insight linking is the killer feature for this lens. Dovetail (SaaS, REST API) — Source of evidence; OST nodes link to Dovetail tags. Magic AI summaries (2025+) reduce synth load. Notion (SaaS, REST API) — Cheapest OST home for solo PMs; database views handle the tree shape adequately. Airtable (SaaS, REST + scripting) — Lightweight insight DB if not on Dovetail; good for opportunity scoring tables. ProdPad (SaaS, REST API) — OST-friendly idea management; lighter than Productboard. Aha! (SaaS, REST, slow) — Roadmap-heavy; OST is bolted on, not native. Avoid if discovery-first. Cycle.app (SaaS, REST + GraphQL) — 2024+ entrant; opinionated continuous-discovery UX, AI synthesis built-in. Mixpanel / Amplitude / PostHog (SaaS / OSS, REST + SQL) — Outcome metric source for outcome-tracker. PostHog is self-hostable. Linear (SaaS, GraphQL) — Delivery-side; require opp_id in issue templates. Jira (SaaS, REST, verbose) — Same as Linear but heavier; agents need a custom field for opp_id. Trello / GitHub Projects (Free / SaaS, REST) — Solo-PM fallback if Productboard is overkill. ChartHop / Lattice (SaaS, limited) — OKR alignment to Outcomes — useful for outcome-tracker context. Userinterviews.com (SaaS, REST) — Recruiting infra (upstream); without it the cadence dies. Slack (SaaS, Webhooks + Bolt) — Trio deliberation channel; post weekly digest, capture decisions.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cadence-triggers-and-automation">
      <p>Cadence triggers (crontab -e or NERO schedule skill): */30 * * * * claude run /discovery-intake (classify new requests), 0 9 * * 1 claude run /discovery-score (weekly OST score), 0 10 * * 2,4 claude run /discovery-trio (bi-weekly trio deliberation), 0 11 1 * * claude run /discovery-roadmap-synth (monthly roadmap delta), 0 7 * * * claude run /discovery-outcome-track (daily outcome metric).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="references-and-related">
      <list>
        <item>Teresa Torres, Continuous Discovery Habits (2021) — canonical text. https://www.producttalk.org/continuous-discovery-habits/</item>
        <item>producttalk.org/podcast — 2025–2026 episodes on AI-augmented discovery and Claude Code integration.</item>
        <item>Marty Cagan, Inspired / Empowered — adjacent product-trio practices and outcome-driven roadmaps.</item>
        <item>Itamar Gilad, Evidence-Guided — opportunity scoring (RICE / ICE) variants compatible with OST scoring.</item>
        <item>Sibling methodology (this skill): ../competitive-positioning/methodology.xml, ../portfolio-strategy/methodology.xml.</item>
        <item>Upstream sibling (research lens): ../../../research/researcher/continuous-discovery/agent-integration.md.</item>
        <item>Upstream sibling (research lens): ../../../research/market-researcher/continuous-discovery/agent-integration.md.</item>
        <item>Related methodology: ../../../research/researcher/opportunity-solution-trees/agent-integration.md.</item>
        <item>Anthropic Claude Agent SDK — agents, structured outputs, scheduled triggers. https://docs.anthropic.com/en/api/agent-sdk</item>
        <item>Productboard "Insights → Drivers → Features" model — https://www.productboard.com</item>
        <item>Dovetail Magic AI synthesis (2025) — https://dovetail.com</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ost-schema.json" purpose="OST node schema: type, parent, evidence, score, status, linked_specs"/>
      <template path="templates/spec-opp-link.yml" purpose="GitHub Actions check: blocks PR merge if SDD spec lacks opp_id"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="competitor-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="user-personas"/>
      <ref slug="portfolio-strategy"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
