<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Opportunity Solution Trees Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Opportunity Solution Trees methodology. Every rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale, plus the universal skip-this-methodology gate.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="one-outcome-at-root" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every OST MUST have exactly one metric-based outcome at the root (name + current value + target).</statement>
      <rationale source="Teresa Torres, Continuous Discovery Habits">Opportunityless trees collapse into unordered wishlists; one outcome focuses discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="solutions-only-under-opportunities" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Solutions MUST hang off an opportunity node; no orphan solutions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Torres, OST chapter">Solutions without opportunities are feature requests, not discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="falsifiable-assumption-per-solution" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every solution node MUST spawn &gt;=1 falsifiable assumption with a named test type (smoke/fake-door/prototype/Mom-Test).</statement>
      <rationale source="Torres + internal — assumption register">Without falsifiability, solution work proceeds without grounding.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="numeric-scoring" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Opportunities MUST carry numeric scores: frequency (n observations), severity (1-5), addressability (H/M/L); composite displayed with week-over-week delta.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — OST scoring policy">Gut-feel prioritization is unauditable; deltas reveal urgency shifts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="depth-cap-four" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tree depth MUST NOT exceed 4 levels (outcome -&gt; sub-outcome -&gt; opportunity -&gt; solution).</statement>
      <rationale source="Torres + F-066 B5.7">Deeper trees signal under-decomposed nodes that should split into separate trees.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="monthly-kill-list" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every monthly review MUST emit a kill list (parked/dead opportunities) &gt;=1 entry after 4 weeks; without pruning OSTs collapse under their own weight.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Q4 2025 OST autopsy">Opportunities accumulate faster than they resolve; pruning keeps the tree iterable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only if all entries in `## Applies If` hold and none of `## Skip If` triggers; otherwise abort and route to the correct methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — decision tree minimum form">A misrouted methodology produces wrong-shape output; the explicit skip rule is the universal default branch from the decision tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
