<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Minimum Product Frameworks Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Selection matrix that chooses one of nine 'minimum product' frameworks (MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC) by market density × ICP × differentiator BEFORE the first spec.md exists.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="framework-decision-recorded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The chosen framework MUST be recorded as a decision-record (DR) with three signals: market density, buyer type, differentiator.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — startup post-mortem audit">Without a written DR, the team drifts to default-MVP regardless of fit; DR forces explicit signal evaluation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="nine-framework-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The matrix MUST evaluate all nine frameworks (MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC). Skipping a row produces invisible bias toward whichever framework the operator already knows.</statement>
      <rationale source="Henrik Kniberg / Marty Cagan minimum-product taxonomy">Familiar-framework bias is the dominant mis-pick; full-matrix forcing function neutralises it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="differentiator-test-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The DR MUST name what would prove the chosen differentiator (price -&gt; unit economics; experience -&gt; NPS+activation; capability -&gt; feature-eval win; distribution -&gt; channel CAC).</statement>
      <rationale source="Lean Startup hypothesis testing">Differentiators without proof gates degrade into marketing copy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="revisit-trigger-pre-registered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DR MUST list 2-3 quantitative triggers that would force a framework re-pick (activation &lt; X, churn &gt; Y, MRR flat 90 days).</statement>
      <rationale source="Lean Startup pivot/persevere triggers">Without triggers, sunk-cost keeps the wrong framework; pre-registered triggers force reassessment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="framework-not-product" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The framework choice describes HOW you ship, not WHAT you ship. Mixing them (e.g., 'MLP for X feature') is a category error.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — framework-misuse audit">Conflating framework with feature scope produces incoherent specs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — DR already exists &lt;=90 days; consulting/services; compliance-driven build; iteration on stable product), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
