<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-matrix" title="Nine Minimum Product Frameworks Matrix">
  <summary>Defines all nine frameworks with purpose and when-to-use, the decision matrix mapping market conditions to frameworks, and the key insight about crowded-market risk of defaulting to MVP.</summary>

  <section title="The Nine Frameworks">
    <list>
      <item>MVP (Minimum Viable Product): test core assumptions in a new market with an unvalidated idea.</item>
      <item>MLP (Minimum Lovable Product): create emotional connection in a crowded market requiring differentiation.</item>
      <item>MMP (Minimum Marketable Product): generate revenue in B2B or enterprise sales contexts where a sellable surface is required.</item>
      <item>MAC (Minimum Awesome Component): differentiate via one killer feature where feature-based differentiation is the strategic bet.</item>
      <item>RAT (Riskiest Assumption Test): validate the biggest risk in a high-uncertainty project before any full build.</item>
      <item>MDP (Minimum Delightful Product): exceed expectations in a premium positioning context where delight is the brand promise.</item>
      <item>MVA (Minimum Valuable Product): deliver measurable business value in enterprise or ROI-focused contexts.</item>
      <item>MFP (Minimum Functional Product): prove technical feasibility first in complex technology or infrastructure projects.</item>
      <item>SLC (Simple, Lovable, Complete): balance simplicity and polish in consumer apps where all three attributes are simultaneously required.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Decision Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the decision matrix: blue ocean unvalidated → MVP or RAT; red ocean many competitors → MLP or MAC; enterprise B2B → MMP or MVA; consumer emotion-driven → MLP or MDP; technical uncertainty → MFP then expand.</statement>
      <rationale>The default "MVP" is correct only in genuinely uncontested markets. In red oceans, users already have "good enough" alternatives — an MVP that is merely functional gives them no reason to switch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every framework choice must include two explicit exit criteria — one quantitative (metric + threshold + measurement window) and one disqualifying kill criterion — before scoping begins. Without exit criteria the framework is decorative.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams pick "MLP" because it sounds nicer than "MVP" without changing scope. The exit criteria are the only mechanism that enforces the actual definition of "done enough to advance."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick exactly one framework per scope cycle. "MVP+MLP hybrid" is a hedge that produces neither validation rigor nor delight investment. Force the choice, then re-pick on the next pivot.</statement>
      <rationale>Hybrid choices distribute effort across two conflicting optimization targets — speed-of-learning (MVP) and quality-of-experience (MLP) — and optimize for neither.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Crowded Market Insight">
    <rule>
      <statement>When 3+ "good enough" competitors exist, the default framework flips to MLP or SLC. In crowded markets, "viable" is table stakes — users will not switch for a product that merely works.</statement>
      <rationale>Users in crowded markets bear switching costs (data migration, habit change, team retraining). They will absorb those costs only for a product that is clearly better on an emotional or economic dimension, not merely functional.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Reflexively choosing MVP without checking competitor density, buyer type, or differentiator.</description>
      <reason>"Just build an MVP" is a 2010s default that does not generalize to 2026 categories where AI-assisted competitors can clone functional surfaces in weeks. Framework choice must be grounded in market evidence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
