<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-selection-process" title="Framework Selection Process and Limitations">
  <summary>Three-pass agentic selection workflow, framework hand-off contracts, common failure modes, and limitations of the nine-framework matrix.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Pass Selection Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pass 1 — Research: a market-researcher agent gathers competitor count, ICP, buyer type, switching cost, and risk profile into market-context.yml before the selection agent runs. Refuse to run the matrix if market-context.yml is missing or buyer is "unknown."</statement>
      <rationale>Agents lacking market context will default to MVP (training bias from 2010s startup canon). Requiring a completed market-context.yml as a pre-condition forces evidence-first selection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pass 2 — Selection: a PM agent applies the decision matrix to market-context.yml, scores all nine frameworks, and emits framework-choice.md with the chosen framework, the rejected ones, and two exit criteria. Score every framework before naming the winner.</statement>
      <rationale>Scoring rejected frameworks forces honest disagreement rationale and prevents post-hoc justification of a predetermined choice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pass 3 — Hand-off: the chosen framework's downstream methodology agent (mvp-scoping, mlp-planning, etc.) consumes framework-choice.md as its input contract. Abort and request re-pick if the choice file is older than 14 days or refers to a different framework.</statement>
      <rationale>Stale choice files decouple framework and scope; a sprint that starts with an outdated framework choice ships the wrong minimum product.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Re-Pick on Pivots">
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-run the matrix on every pivot — failed validation, missed activation target, or strategy shift. Append the new decision as a dated section in framework-choice.md; never rewrite history.</statement>
      <rationale>The pivot history is the most useful single input to next year's selection heuristics. Rewriting history destroys institutional memory about what conditions trigger which framework failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>MFP is a stepping stone, not a destination. Pre-commit the trigger that ends MFP (e.g., "first internal demo passes", "API latency &lt; 100ms at 1k RPS") before MFP work starts.</statement>
      <rationale>Without an explicit graduation trigger, teams stay in MFP indefinitely because "technical feasibility" is never fully resolved — there is always one more edge case.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Acronym soup as theatre: teams pick "MLP" because it sounds nicer than "MVP" without changing scope or adding exit criteria.</description>
      <reason>The framework name is irrelevant without a written exit criterion per framework. The choice is decorative unless it changes what gets built and when you stop.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Single-axis market read: using only blue/red ocean without considering buyer (B2B/consumer), distribution (PLG/sales-led), or regulatory load.</description>
      <reason>The nine-framework table under-specifies; in practice buyer type and distribution model often dominate the framework choice more than competitive density alone.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No cost dimension: all nine frameworks treated as equally expensive in the decision matrix.</description>
      <reason>MLP and MDP cost 2-4x MVP for polish budget; recommending MLP without surfacing the cost delta produces naive choices that surprise engineering in sprint planning.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/framework-choice.md">Versioned framework-choice document skeleton with chosen framework, rationale, exit criteria, and dated history.</reference>
  <reference path="scripts/pick-framework.sh">Bash + Python: rule-based first-pass selection from market-context.yml; writes framework-choice.md; commits to git.</reference>
</text>
