<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="minimum-product-frameworks Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for minimum-product-frameworks as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Reflexively choosing MVP without checking competitor density, buyer type, or differentiator.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"Just build an MVP" is a 2010s default that does not generalize to 2026 categories where AI-assisted competitors can clone functional surfaces in weeks. Framework choice must be grounded in market evidence.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Acronym soup as theatre: teams pick "MLP" because it sounds nicer than "MVP" without changing scope or adding exit criteria.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The framework name is irrelevant without a written exit criterion per framework. The choice is decorative unless it changes what gets built and when you stop.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Single-axis market read: using only blue/red ocean without considering buyer (B2B/consumer), distribution (PLG/sales-led), or regulatory load.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The nine-framework table under-specifies; in practice buyer type and distribution model often dominate the framework choice more than competitive density alone.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>No transition rule: README says "MFP then expand" but doesn't define what triggers the transition (metric? time? validation event?).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents will sit in MFP forever without an explicit graduation trigger and acceptance criteria.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>MAC ambiguity: "Minimum Awesome Component" overlaps heavily with MLP and SLC; in red oceans a MAC often is the lovable hook, double-counting the same scope.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The methodology doesn't fully disambiguate MAC from MLP; agents may conflate them without additional context about the category.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>MVA vs MMP overlap: Both target enterprise/ROI; the methodology doesn't disambiguate.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>In practice, MMP = sellable, MVA = measurable business value — agents conflate them without clear distinction.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>No cost dimension: all nine frameworks treated as equally expensive in the decision matrix.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>MLP and MDP cost 2-4x MVP for the polish budget; recommending MLP without surfacing the cost delta produces naive choices that surprise engineering in sprint planning.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Framework lock-in: Once "MLP" is in the deck, switching to RAT after a failed validation is socially expensive.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Methodology offers no de-escalation path. Re-picks should be reframed as learning, not failure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Survivorship-bias source: "MVP is suicide in 2026" is a strong claim drawn from crowded-SaaS storytelling; doesn't generalise to vertical SaaS, B2B niches, or dev-tools where MVPs still win.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The framework is weighted toward horizontal SaaS assumptions; vertical and deep-tech contexts may validate differently.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Acronym hallucination: LLMs invent extra frameworks (MUP, MEP, MWP) under prompt pressure.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Constrain to the exact 9-row enum; reject any output naming a framework outside the list.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Default-to-MVP drift: Any LLM trained on 2010s startup canon will pick MVP unless explicitly told to consider crowded-market evidence.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force the agent to print the matrix score per framework before naming the winner.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Crowded-market over-claim: Without competitor evidence, agents will declare every market "crowded" to justify MLP.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require competitor_count + named competitors in market-context.yml; refuse to pick if missing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Exit-criterion vagueness: Agents emit "good user feedback" or "high adoption" as exit criteria.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Validate that each criterion has a metric, a threshold, and a measurement window.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Framework-then-justify failure: Agent picks first, rationalises second.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mitigate by structured output: scores per framework BEFORE the chosen one, in a JSON schema the prompt enforces.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Confounding with mvp-scoping methodology: Agent jumps straight into in/out scope before picking the framework.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pipeline must enforce: choice file exists → only then scoping methodology runs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Pivot inertia: Agent re-confirms the original framework even when metrics scream pivot.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a structured "stay vs pivot" decision with rejection-reason for the rejected option.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>No human checkpoint on enterprise commitments: MMP/MVA implies sales contracts and SLAs — agents must not autonomously promote to these without a founder/PM sign-off step.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add a human gate before MMP/MVA selection goes live.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-18" severity="medium">
      <description>Hand-off contract drift: Downstream methodology agents read the choice file; if framework changes mid-cycle without re-running the downstream agent, scope and framework drift apart.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>CI: hash the choice file in the spec front-matter; mismatch fails the build.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-19" severity="medium">
      <description>2026-claim staleness: README says "in 2026 MVP is suicide in crowded markets" — agents will quote this verbatim in pitches.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Phrase it as a heuristic, not a law, to avoid over-confident decks.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
