<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="user-control-freedom Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for user-control-freedom. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every state-changing action that is technically reversible MUST provide undo. Undo MUST be available immediately after the action (in a toast notification with an [Undo] button or in the UI). Redo MUST be available after undo.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Undo is always better UX than a confirmation dialog because it avoids false positives (users confirming actions they definitely want) and allows quick recovery without friction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All forms and dialogs MUST have a visible [Cancel] button. Modals MUST be closeable via X button (top-right corner), Escape key, and clicking outside the modal. Multi-step processes MUST have a [Back] button at each step and an obvious [Exit] or [Cancel] at the top or bottom.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cancel buttons and exit paths prevent users from feeling trapped. Escape key and outside-click are platform conventions; not implementing them violates user expectations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Soft-delete patterns (trash with 30-day retention) MUST replace permanent-delete patterns. Users MUST be able to restore deleted items within the retention window. Only after the retention window expires (or on explicit permanent delete) should deletion be irreversible.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Soft delete removes the need for confirmation dialogs and is almost always the right choice for user data. Permanent deletion should be rare.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Confirmation dialogs MUST be reserved for truly irreversible or high-impact actions (e.g., permanent delete, account termination, unsaved changes in a complex form). Routine actions MUST NOT require confirmation. Do not show "Are you sure?" on every exit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Over-confirmation trains users to click OK blindly, reducing effectiveness of confirmation as a safety net. Confirmations should be rare enough that users actually read them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Implement undo at the granularity that makes sense for the action. Simple actions (single field change, delete one item) get single-level undo. Complex operations (bulk delete, form-wide changes) get multi-level undo with history if more than 10 actions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-level undo is the minimum. Multi-level undo (e.g., Google Docs) allows users to step back further if needed. Show undo history visually if the number of actions is large (more than 5-10).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All forms and modal dialogs MUST have a visible [Cancel] button. Cancel MUST discard unsaved changes and return to the previous state (or close the dialog). If the form has significant unsaved changes, warn the user before closing ("Discard changes?"), but use a soft warning (toast) not a full confirmation dialog.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Visible Cancel buttons make exiting obvious. Warning about unsaved changes prevents accidental loss, but soft warnings (toast) are less annoying than full modals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Multi-step processes (wizards, onboarding flows) MUST have a [Back] button at each step and an [Exit] or [Cancel] button visible throughout. Back MUST restore form state from the previous step—do not lose user input when navigating back.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Back navigation without state loss allows users to review and correct input. Losing input on back is a major UX failure and trains users to avoid back.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All modals and overlays MUST be closeable via: (1) X button in top-right corner, (2) Escape key, (3) clicking outside the modal on the background. All three methods MUST have the same effect: close the modal and return to the previous state without saving changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These are platform conventions. Users expect all three methods to work. Modals that cannot be closed via Escape or outside-click feel trapped and cause frustration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not hide primary actions behind modals or overlays. Do not require users to complete a flow to dismiss an overlay. Do not disable outside-click dismissal for critical modals (use confirmation only if the action is irreversible).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Forced modals (newsletters, upsells, login walls) with no obvious close teach users to close the tab instead of engaging. Reserving modals for critical, intentional actions makes them effective when they are used.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use confirmation dialogs ONLY for irreversible, high-impact actions: permanent delete, account termination, canceling a subscription, irreversible settings change. For all other actions, use undo instead. If a confirmation dialog is shown, it MUST explain the impact ("This action cannot be undone").</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Over-confirmation causes users to click OK without reading. Confirmations should be rare and meaningful. Undo is better UX than confirmation for most actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prefer soft-delete (trash / trash bin with retention) over hard-delete. Soft-delete: item moves to trash, user can restore within 30 days, after 30 days item is permanently deleted. Hard-delete should only be used when: (1) the action is irreversible by design (financial transaction), (2) the action is explicitly requested by the user after multiple confirmations, or (3) data retention policy requires immediate deletion.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Soft delete eliminates the need for confirmation dialogs and almost always improves UX. Users make mistakes; soft delete allows recovery without friction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Undo/Redo MUST be available via keyboard shortcut (Ctrl+Z / Cmd+Z for undo, Ctrl+Shift+Z / Cmd+Shift+Z for redo). Cancel and back buttons MUST be keyboard-accessible (Tab navigation, Enter activation). Escape key MUST close modals.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Keyboard users rely on shortcuts and Tab navigation. Escape closing modals is a platform convention. These must work for screen reader users and power users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Focus management in modals MUST trap focus within the modal (Tab cycles within the modal, not the background). When modal closes, focus MUST return to the element that triggered the modal (e.g., the button that opened it).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Screen reader users navigate via Tab and arrow keys. Focus trap prevents keyboard users from accidentally interacting with the background while a modal is open. Focus restoration allows users to continue from where they left off.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
