<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="User Control and Freedom Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding User Control and Freedom. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-undo-for-destructive" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every destructive action exposes either an immediate undo or a clearly labelled confirmation with a recoverable trash for at least 30 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen Heuristic #3">Without undo, users avoid the feature or pay a heavy mistake tax.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-clear-exit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Modals, multi-step flows, and full-screen takeovers carry an explicit close affordance — Esc, X icon, and back swipe — that does not lose entered data.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG and Material guidelines">Trapped states are a frequent rage-click trigger.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-no-double-confirm" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A single confirmation per destructive action is enough; cascading confirm dialogs train users to click through them.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Confirmation fatigue defeats the safety the dialog was supposed to provide.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-history-and-redo" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Where workflows support undo, they also support redo and a visible history so users can navigate the stack confidently.</statement>
      <rationale source="Adobe and Figma command-history patterns">Undo without redo punishes accidental over-undo.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-system-cancel-honoured" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pressing Esc, swiping back, or tapping the system back button always honours user intent — never silently committing pending changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG and Material guidelines">Silent commits on cancel violate user expectation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-user-control-freedom.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
