<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Requirement Quality Scorecard — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `requirement-quality-scorecard` must enforce. The rules pin the discipline that turns a scorecard from folklore into a reviewable, owned, version-controlled operating tool.</summary>

  <section title="Rules">
    <rule id="r1-named-dimensions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The scorecard has 4–7 named dimensions, each with an explicit 1–5 anchor description per score. &apos;Subjective overall&apos; is forbidden as a dimension.</statement>
      <rationale source="Behaviourally Anchored Rating Scale (BARS) literature; structured-interview research">Without anchored scales the same artefact scores 3 from one reviewer and 5 from another. Anchored 1–5 scales make inter-rater agreement measurable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-evidence-per-score" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each score carries one verbatim evidence pointer (quote, line, screenshot, metric). Scores without evidence are invalid and re-graded.</statement>
      <rationale source="Evidence-based delivery practice; assessment-validity literature">Unanchored scoring degrades to opinion. Tying score to evidence makes reviews defensible and audit-ready.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-aggregation-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Aggregate score is computed by a published rule (min, weighted sum, or veto-on-any-1). &apos;Reviewer&apos;s overall feeling&apos; is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kahneman, Noise (2021); structured-decision-making practice">Aggregation hides poor dimensions when reviewers compensate. A published rule makes the verdict reproducible and challengeable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-calibration-pass" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before the scorecard goes live, ≥2 reviewers score the same 5 artefacts and reconcile differences ≥ 2 points. Disagreements update the anchor descriptions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Inter-rater reliability methodology; assessment-development best practice">First-use of a scorecard surfaces ambiguous anchors. The calibration pass fixes them before the scorecard is used on real artefacts that matter.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-versioned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The scorecard carries `version` + `last_calibrated_at` + named owner. Stale calibration auto-expires after 6 months.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO 9001 document control; structured-assessment maintenance practice">BAs need a deterministic scorecard (atomicity, testability, traceability, value, ambiguity, completeness) they can run on every requirement before baseline. Today the corpus discusses these as principles inside prioritization / validation but provides no scoring artefact. P4 BAs handing to foreign clients need an objective quality signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
