<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Paid Ads Creative Library Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Paid Ads Creative Library MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="tag-taxonomy-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tag taxonomy MUST be fixed and documented (hook-type / offer / format / persona / funnel-stage). Free-form tags forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Library hygiene practice">Free-form tags decay into ungroupable chaos within a quarter; fixed taxonomy preserves searchability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="lineage-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every variant MUST record lineage_parent (previous asset_id) and what was changed. Lineage gaps invalidate iteration.</statement>
      <rationale source="Experiment ledger discipline">Without lineage, the team cannot answer 'what test was won'; ROI of changes becomes unattributable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="performance-feedback-loop" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every asset MUST surface live performance (CTR, CVR, CPA) at the asset row. Stale performance &gt; 7 days rejects the asset for new spend.</statement>
      <rationale source="Performance feedback loop literature">Stale performance drives ad-fatigue spend; live performance is the kill / scale signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="tag-on-upload" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tags MUST be applied at upload, not retroactively. Untagged assets are blocked from campaign upload.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — library audit 2025">Retroactive tagging never happens; blocking at upload is the only enforcement that works.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="deprecation-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Asset MUST be marked deprecated after 8 weeks live OR CTR drop &gt; 30% from peak. Deprecated assets blocked from new campaigns.</statement>
      <rationale source="Creative-fatigue cohort data">Creative fatigue is real and predictable; explicit deprecation prevents zombie spend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
