<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="feature-prioritization-rice">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>Score features as (Reach x Impact x Confidence) / Effort. Fixed scales for Impact and Confidence, engineer-owned Effort, strategic veto for one bet per quarter. Sort highest-to-lowest.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>prioritization</tag>
      <tag>rice</tag>
      <tag>scoring</tag>
      <tag>roadmap</tag>
      <tag>feature-ranking</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Feature Prioritization (RICE)</title>
    <summary>Score each candidate feature as (Reach x Impact x Confidence) / Effort. Reach = users affected per quarter (cite an analytics query or proxy metric). Impact = {3, 2, 1, 0.5, 0.25} only — do not add intermediate values. Confidence = 100%/80%/50% only — drop one tier for each unknown. Effort = person-months including design, dev, QA, and a 30% buffer for unknowns; engineers must own this column. Sort highest-to-lowest, sanity-check, then apply strategic veto for one bet that may rank lower but is the only path to differentiation.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Feature prioritization driven by gut or loudest voice (HiPPO) produces inconsistent decisions and scope creep. RICE forces stakeholders to debate quantified inputs rather than opinions, and the division by Effort surfaces effort-adjusted ROI that verbal discussion consistently misses. The fixed impact and confidence scales prevent score inflation and keep cross-feature comparison valid over time. Tracking post-ship actuals against estimates is the only mechanism that improves future confidence scores.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Comparing 5+ candidate features in a single quarter where reach and effort vary widely.</item>
        <item>Killing pet features: a numeric score forces debate on inputs, not opinions.</item>
        <item>Triaging a backlog after a discovery sprint produced more validated problems than capacity.</item>
        <item>Deciding between two features that both look "obviously valuable" — RICE exposes effort-adjusted ROI.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo founder with fewer than 3 candidates — overhead exceeds signal; pick by gut and ship.</item>
        <item>Hard-deadline regulatory or compliance work — there is no score; you ship or get fined.</item>
        <item>Discovery phase before reach and impact data exist — confidence will be 50% across the board and ranking is noise.</item>
        <item>Strategic bets / 0-to-1 features — RICE punishes high-effort items even when they are the only path to a moat.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="formula">
      <rule>
        <statement>RICE Score = (Reach x Impact x Confidence) / Effort. Higher score = higher priority. Never modify the formula structure — adding weights or exponents destroys cross-quarter comparability.</statement>
        <rationale>The formula's simplicity is its strength. Modifications make it impossible to compare scores across teams or quarters.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="reach">
      <rule>
        <statement>Reach = users affected per quarter. Every Reach value must cite the analytics query, dashboard, or proxy metric used to derive it. "Everyone" and "all users" are not valid values.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs fabricate plausible-looking Reach numbers. Requiring a citation makes fabrication detectable and forces the scorer to check actual data.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="impact">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use only the five standard values: 3 (massive), 2 (high), 1 (medium), 0.5 (low), 0.25 (minimal). Do not add intermediate values. Tie Impact to a specific user-facing metric (conversion, retention, activation).</statement>
        <rationale>Adding intermediate values (1.5, 0.75) destroys cross-feature comparability. The five-point scale forces meaningful distinctions. Impact=3 must be reserved for core differentiators; co-sign required.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Impact scored as 1.7 "because it's between medium and high." The intermediate value makes it impossible to compare this feature against others scored in prior quarters.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="confidence">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use only three values: 100% (shipped data on the same surface), 80% (some data, reasonable assumptions), 50% (opinions, limited data). Drop one tier for each unknown: no user research, technical unknowns, never done before, external dependencies.</statement>
        <rationale>100% Confidence is almost always wrong. Reserving it for shipped-data-only situations prevents the entire dataset from clustering at 80% which makes the factor meaningless.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="effort">
      <rule>
        <statement>Effort = person-months, including design, dev, QA, docs, and a 30% buffer for unknown integrations. Engineers must own the Effort column — PM estimates are systematically 2-3x too low.</statement>
        <rationale>Effort is the divisor; underestimating it inflates the score and produces a misleading priority ranking that collapses when sprint planning reveals actual capacity.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="formula-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Cross-team comparison using the same Reach unit: "Reach = 10K" means different things for free-tier vs paid-tier customers.</description>
        <reason>Comparing RICE scores across segments with different conversion rates mixes apples and oranges. Partition by segment before scoring.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Effort estimated by PM without engineering input, producing scores that look good until sprint planning.</description>
        <reason>PM effort estimates are optimistic by construction. Engineer ownership of the E column is structural, not optional.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="process-step-1-list-candidates">
      <rule>
        <statement>Gather all candidate features with a one-paragraph problem statement each before scoring begins. Score the problem statement, not the feature title.</statement>
        <rationale>Scoring vague feature titles produces vague scores. The problem statement forces the scorer to articulate who is affected and why, grounding the R and I estimates.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="process-step-2-score-each-factor">
      <rule>
        <statement>Score in batches of 8-10 items maximum. Quality drops sharply after 10. Randomize order within each batch and average two independent passes to prevent anchoring on the first item.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs anchor on the first item scored and bias subsequent scores relative to it. Randomization across passes neutralizes this effect.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Store raw R/I/C/E inputs and rationale alongside the final score. The score alone is unauditable; rationale enables future calibration.</statement>
        <rationale>Without stored rationale, post-ship actuals cannot be compared against estimates, making quarterly calibration impossible.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="process-step-3-calculate">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply the formula: (R x I x C) / E. Treat confidence as a decimal (80% = 0.8). Sort highest to lowest.</statement>
        <rationale>Treating confidence as a percentage (80) instead of a decimal (0.8) produces scores 100x larger and loses the relative weighting between confidence levels.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/rice-rank.sh">Bash script that reads a CSV and outputs sorted RICE scores with the computed column.</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="process-step-4-sanity-check">
      <rule>
        <statement>After sorting, ask: "Does this ranking feel wrong?" Investigate items where the gut diverges from the score — the score is probably right and the gut is anchored on a wrong assumption. Document the investigation.</statement>
        <rationale>Sanity checks catch data errors (wrong Reach unit, Effort in days instead of months). Documenting the investigation builds calibration discipline.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="process-step-5-strategic-veto">
      <rule>
        <statement>After sorting, the PM may promote one strategic bet that ranks lower than its score suggests. Document the veto rationale explicitly. Strategic veto is limited to one item per quarter.</statement>
        <rationale>RICE does not encode dependencies, sequencing, or strategic narrative. A single veto slot preserves the score discipline while allowing human judgment on moat-building investments.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="process-step-6-rescore-quarterly">
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-score the full backlog quarterly. Re-score individual features immediately when their underlying assumption is invalidated — not at the next quarterly cycle. Track post-ship actuals (real Reach, real Effort) to calibrate next quarter's estimates.</statement>
        <rationale>A score based on stale assumptions misleads roadmap planning. Immediate re-scoring on assumption change prevents cascading prioritization errors.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Re-scoring retroactively to "explain" why a shipped feature succeeded.</description>
        <reason>Retroactive scoring destroys the calibration data needed to improve future estimates. Keep original scores immutable; add actuals as a separate column.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations">
      <list>
        <item>Reach x Impact x Confidence is multiplicative, so one wrong factor (e.g. inflated reach) dominates the score.</item>
        <item>Confidence anchors on the loudest scorer; without a calibration step everyone defaults to 80%.</item>
        <item>Effort estimates from PMs are systematically 2-3x too low; engineers must own the E column.</item>
        <item>Score does not encode dependencies, sequencing, or strategic narrative — top-ranked feature may be useless without #4.</item>
        <item>Cross-team comparison breaks: "Reach = 10K" means different things for free-tier vs paid customers.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Have a discovery agent gather feature candidates with a one-paragraph problem statement each, then run a scoring agent that proposes R/I/C/E with explicit rationale per factor (cite analytics queries or research notes). A second reviewer agent challenges every Confidence greater than or equal to 80% and every Effort less than or equal to 1 month. Human approves the final ranking before it enters the roadmap. Re-run quarterly with a delta-only pass — only re-score items whose underlying assumptions changed.</p>
      <section name="recommended-subagents">
        <list>
          <item>faion-mlp-feature-proposer-agent — drafts initial R/I/C/E with rationale per factor.</item>
          <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — once a feature wins, hand it to SDD to break into spec/design/tasks.</item>
          <item>A custom rice-challenger Sonnet agent — single-purpose: read scores, attack confidence and effort claims, return revised proposal.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <prompt purpose="rice-scorer"><![CDATA[Given the feature candidates in <backlog>, for each compute RICE.
For Reach cite the analytics query or proxy metric.
For Impact pick from {3, 2, 1, 0.5, 0.25} and state which user-facing metric moves.
For Confidence drop one tier (100->80, 80->50) for each unknown.
For Effort use eng-weeks and add 30% buffer for unknown integrations.
Output as a markdown table sorted by score, plus a 2-line "why this ranks here" per row.]]></prompt>
      <prompt purpose="rice-challenger"><![CDATA[Review this RICE table. Find every Confidence >=80% with no cited evidence and propose a downgrade.
Find every Effort <1 month and ask the engineer-persona challenge questions.
Return a diff, not a rewrite.]]></prompt>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>gh issue list --json number,title,labels — Pull candidate features from GitHub issues for scoring. https://cli.github.com/manual/gh_issue_list</item>
        <item>linear-cli — Pull/push backlog from Linear, where RICE fields are first-class. https://github.com/evangodon/lr</item>
        <item>csvkit (csvsql) — Quick re-rank: csvsql --query "select *,(r*i*c)/e as rice from features.csv order by rice desc". https://csvkit.readthedocs.io</item>
        <item>qsv — Faster csvkit replacement for greater than 10K-row backlogs. https://github.com/jqnatividad/qsv</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli — Render priority bubble charts from RICE output. https://github.com/mermaid-js/mermaid-cli</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="services">
      <list>
        <item>ProductBoard (SaaS, Yes REST+webhooks) — Native RICE column; agent can POST score updates via API.</item>
        <item>Productlift (SaaS, Limited) — Cheap RICE-first board for solo PMs.</item>
        <item>Airfocus (SaaS, Yes REST API) — Configurable RICE matrix, supports custom factors.</item>
        <item>Linear (SaaS, Yes GraphQL API) — Add R/I/C/E as custom fields; agents update via GraphQL.</item>
        <item>Aha! (SaaS, Yes REST+webhooks) — Enterprise; RICE templates built-in.</item>
        <item>Notion (SaaS, Yes REST API) — DIY: database with formula column for RICE; cheap and scriptable.</item>
        <item>OpenProject (OSS, Yes REST API) — Self-host option for RICE custom fields.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Always store the raw R/I/C/E inputs alongside the score; the score alone is unauditable.</item>
        <item>Cap Confidence at 80% unless there is shipped data on the same surface — 100% is almost always wrong.</item>
        <item>Re-score a feature the moment its prerequisite assumption is invalidated, not at the next quarterly cycle.</item>
        <item>Keep the impact scale (3 / 2 / 1 / 0.5 / 0.25) — adding intermediate values destroys cross-feature comparability.</item>
        <item>Pair RICE with strategic veto: top-3 by score, then PM picks one strategic bet that may rank lower.</item>
        <item>Track post-ship actuals (real reach, real effort) to calibrate next quarter's estimates — this is the only way confidence improves.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs are confident bullshitters about Reach. Force a citation: every Reach value must reference a query, dashboard, or proxy metric, otherwise the agent fabricates numbers that look plausible.</item>
        <item>Effort estimation from an LLM with no access to the codebase is noise. Either feed it cloc output and a dependency graph, or have a human engineer fill that column.</item>
        <item>An agent will happily score 50 features in one pass; quality drops sharply after ~10. Batch in chunks of 8-10.</item>
        <item>The model anchors on the first feature it scores. Randomize order per pass and average two passes.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoint #1: before any feature with score greater than 2x the median is committed to roadmap, a human must validate Reach and Effort. These are the highest-leverage error sources.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoint #2: any feature where the agent assigned Impact = 3 must be co-signed — Impact=3 is reserved for differentiators.</item>
        <item>Don't let the agent re-score retroactively to "explain" why a shipped feature succeeded; that destroys the calibration data.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/rice-scorecard.md" purpose="RICE scoring table with notes per feature and rank."/>
      <template path="templates/rice-decision-record.md" purpose="Per-feature decision record: inputs, rationale, rank, and decision."/>
      <template path="templates/rice-rank.sh" purpose="Bash script: reads a CSV (name, reach, impact, confidence, effort) and outputs sorted RICE scores."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.intercom.com/blog/rice-simple-prioritization-for-product-managers/"/>
      <link href="https://www.productboard.com/glossary/rice-scoring-model/"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/how-the-best-product-managers-prioritize"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
