<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GCP Production Deployments Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>≥5 testable rules grounding the gcp methodology, each paired with rationale and source reference.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="autopilot-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use GKE Autopilot for new clusters unless workloads require GPU, privileged containers, custom node configs or Windows nodes.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Autopilot eliminates node-pool sizing, OS patching and kubelet tuning — 20-40 hours/month of toil.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="workload-identity-federation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Authenticate every external workload (GitHub Actions, GitLab, AWS, on-prem) via Workload Identity Federation and disable service-account key creation at org level.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Service-account keys are the leading cause of GCP credential exposure; WIF maps OIDC directly to IAM principals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-primitive-iam-roles" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never assign primitive IAM roles (Owner, Editor, Viewer) to service accounts; always use predefined or custom roles scoped to the resource.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Primitive roles span hundreds of permissions and are unauditable in any non-trivial breach review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="private-service-connect" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Private Service Connect (not VPC Peering) for instances without public IPs that need Google APIs, and add private DNS for googleapis.com and gcr.io.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">PSC scales to many projects without IP-range collisions; peering forces collision-free CIDR planning across the org.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cloud-run-sizing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set Cloud Run min-instances to 0 for cost-sensitive services and 1+ for latency-sensitive ones; tune concurrency to 80-100 for typical web apps and 1-10 for CPU-heavy work.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Cold starts (200ms-2s) are the dominant Cloud Run tail-latency factor; concurrency tuning bounds per-instance CPU contention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, do NOT run this methodology — return early with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree's negative branch must terminate cleanly without partial output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold AND scope is explicit, run the methodology end-to-end and produce the canonical artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree positive-branch terminus; aliases the apply-end-to-end verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
