<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="resource-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Identify required skills and quantities per work package, assess real availability capped at 75-80%, map to activities, and level overloads via delay/split/add/cut options.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>resource-planning</tag>
      <tag>capacity</tag>
      <tag>utilization</tag>
      <tag>team-management</tag>
      <tag>leveling</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>resource</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Resource Management</title>

    <summary>Identify required skills and quantities per work package, assess real availability (capped at 75-80% effective capacity), map resources to activities, level overloads via delay/split/add/cut options, and monitor utilization weekly against plan. Resources include human, physical, material, and financial — but human resource planning dominates and must never assume 100% capacity.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Bottlenecks from missing skills, uneven workload distribution, and schedule delays from unavailability trace back to plans built at 100% utilization that ignore meetings, interruptions, and PTO. Effective capacity for most knowledge workers is 75-80% of nominal hours; plans built above that ceiling always slip on the first sick week or sprint ceremony load.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Multi-team programs where the same engineers are claimed by 2+ projects</item>
        <item>Onboarding or offboarding wave shifting skill mix within 30-60 days</item>
        <item>Agency or consulting context billing by utilization</item>
        <item>Mid-project resource crisis (key person quit, contractor delayed)</item>
        <item>Capacity planning ahead of quarterly OKR commitments</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Stable single team under 8 people — informal allocation works; formal plans add overhead</item>
        <item>Pure agile teams committed to whole-team ownership — utilization tracking erodes psychological safety</item>
        <item>One-week sprint of throwaway research — over-planning waste</item>
        <item>Organisations where utilization % is used as a performance metric — creates burnout and gaming</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="resource-categories">
      <list>
        <item>Human: team members, contractors. Key considerations: skills, availability, cost, bus factor.</item>
        <item>Physical: equipment, facilities. Key considerations: location, capacity, scheduling lead time.</item>
        <item>Material: supplies, software licenses. Key considerations: lead time, inventory, renewal cycles.</item>
        <item>Financial: budget, cash flow. Key considerations: timing, approval process, EVM reconciliation.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Human resource planning dominates software and knowledge-work projects. The remaining sections focus on human resources unless otherwise stated.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="six-step-process">
      <list>
        <item>Step 1: Identify requirements — for each work package: what skills, how many people, how long, any special constraints.</item>
        <item>Step 2: Assess availability — current commitments, effective capacity (hours/week at 75-80%), skills and experience, cost rates.</item>
        <item>Step 3: Create resource plan — map resources to activities; produce a resource calendar grid by week and phase.</item>
        <item>Step 4: Level resources — resolve overloads: delay tasks (non-critical), split tasks, add resources, reduce scope, or extend timeline.</item>
        <item>Step 5: Develop the team — training, mentoring, team building, clear expectations, recognition.</item>
        <item>Step 6: Manage the team — track utilization vs. plan weekly; address performance, conflicts, and reassignments.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="effective-capacity-rule">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Plan to 75-80% effective capacity, never 100% — meetings, interruptions, and administrative overhead consume at least 20% of nominal hours.</statement>
        <rationale>Plans at 100% utilization collapse on the first sick week or sprint ceremony load, creating cascading delays. The 20% buffer is not slack — it is the cost of doing knowledge work in a real organisation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Utilization guidelines by zone: under 50% = underutilized; 50-75% = healthy with buffer; 75-85% = optimal for most roles; 85-100% = full capacity, burnout risk rising; above 100% = unsustainable, address immediately.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="leveling-techniques">
      <list>
        <item>Delay tasks: move non-critical-path tasks to later; no scope or cost impact.</item>
        <item>Split tasks: interrupt a task and resume later; useful when work can be paused safely.</item>
        <item>Add resources: requires budget and available skill; ramp-up cost is 2 weeks at 50% productivity for contractors.</item>
        <item>Reduce scope: cut features; requires sponsor approval and change control.</item>
        <item>Extend timeline: delay delivery date; requires sponsor approval and baseline update.</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>100% allocation plans that ignore meetings, email, ceremonies, and breaks.</description>
        <reason>These plans always slip on the first sick week or holiday; they create chronic delivery failures that look like execution problems but are actually planning failures.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="skill-and-bus-factor">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Cross-train at least one backup per critical skill; bus factor below 2 is a P1 risk.</statement>
        <rationale>A single-person dependency on a critical skill (database, security, deployment) is a project risk comparable to a high-probability technical risk — it should appear in the risk register.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-capacity-pipeline">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>A capacity-planner subagent ingests calendars (PTO, holidays), current Jira/Linear assignments, and skill tags from HR; produces a weekly availability matrix capped at 75% effective capacity.</statement>
        <rationale>Manual capacity planning is always stale; automated ingestion from authoritative sources (calendar + HR + tracker) produces a plan that updates as reality changes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>A leveler agent compares demand (committed work from WBS) vs. supply (availability matrix), surfaces overload weeks, and proposes options with cost impact. The PM selects; the agent updates the plan and notifies affected leads. Re-runs weekly on cron.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>capacity-planner — pulls PTO, ceremonies, current assignments → effective capacity per person per week (capped at 32h / 80% of 40h standard week).</item>
        <item>skill-matcher — matches required skills from WBS to people with skill-level scoring (skill_match × 0.6 + availability × 0.3 + cost_fit × 0.1).</item>
        <item>leveler — detects overload weeks, proposes mitigations (delay, split, add, cut scope) with cost and schedule impact per option.</item>
        <item>utilization-monitor — weekly delta vs. plan; flags drift greater than 15%; surfaces trend, not snapshot.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Capacity-planner prompt — hard cap at 80%, explicit subtraction logic:</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are a capacity-planner. Given calendar events {ical}, sprint commitments
{jira_issues}, recurring meetings {meetings}, return per-person weekly hours
available for project work. Cap at 32h/week (80% of 40). Subtract:
- PTO/holidays (full day = 8h)
- Recurring meetings (sum per week)
- Reserve 4h/week for interruption buffer
Output JSON {person, week, available_h, committed_h, free_h}.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Skill-matcher prompt — scoring formula prevents gut-feel assignments:</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are a skill-matcher. Given task {task} requiring {skills} at {level},
return ranked candidates from {team_roster.yaml}.
Score = skill_match * 0.6 + availability * 0.3 + cost_fit * 0.1.
Reject candidates with score < 0.5. Output JSON with score and rationale.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Calendar API pulls miss informal meetings, pair sessions, and debugging deep dives.</description>
        <reason>Structured calendar data only captures formally scheduled events; ask the person to confirm their actual available hours before using the raw calendar count for planning.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Allocation agent packs the calendar to 100% if uncapped.</description>
        <reason>Agents optimize for filling capacity; hard-cap at 80% effective in the prompt and the output schema to prevent burnout plans.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent auto-rebalances assignments mid-sprint.</description>
        <reason>Mid-sprint reassignments break WIP and disrupt flow. Schedule rebalancing only at sprint boundaries.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents read calendar subjects to assess meeting load.</description>
        <reason>Calendar subjects are often sensitive (layoff prep, performance review); redact subject lines before any LLM input, keep only duration and recurrence pattern.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <list>
        <item>Skill self-assessments inflate; use last-shipped-feature as ground truth for skill level.</item>
        <item>Hourly-rate fields in HR systems mix loaded and unloaded cost; document which rate EVM uses.</item>
        <item>Pulling PTO from HR APIs often hits permissioning issues; have a fallback "ask the EM" loop.</item>
        <item>Mandatory human checkpoints: resource plan approval, overload escalation to sponsor, contractor engagement, any assignment change that affects the critical path.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>gcalcli — read Google Calendar events for capacity (https://github.com/insanum/gcalcli)</item>
        <item>khal — CalDAV calendar queries (https://github.com/pimutils/khal)</item>
        <item>jira CLI — pull current assignments + estimates (https://github.com/ankitpokhrel/jira-cli)</item>
        <item>linear-cli — Linear capacity/load by user (npm)</item>
        <item>tempo (Jira plugin API) — worklog + capacity (https://apidocs.tempo.io)</item>
        <item>harvest API — time tracking + capacity (https://help.getharvest.com/api-v2)</item>
        <item>clockify API — free time tracking (https://docs.clockify.me/api)</item>
        <item>bamboohr API — HR data, PTO, headcount (https://documentation.bamboohr.com)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services">
      <list>
        <item>Float — resource scheduling, REST API; best for agency/consulting contexts (SaaS).</item>
        <item>Resource Guru — bookings + leave, REST API; WFH and holiday aware (SaaS).</item>
        <item>Forecast.it — AI scheduling, GraphQL; integrates with Harvest (SaaS).</item>
        <item>Runn — capacity planning, rich API; supports project + people views (SaaS).</item>
        <item>Microsoft Project for Web — Graph API, Azure AD; enterprise default on Microsoft estate (SaaS).</item>
        <item>OpenProject — self-host, REST API, Gantt + WBS native; for regulated environments (OSS).</item>
        <item>Tempo Planner — Jira-tied, plugin permissioning; useful when already on Jira ecosystem (SaaS).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Track skills with three levels (learning, proficient, mentor) and a last-used date — skill matrices encoded once go stale fast.</statement>
        <rationale>People grow and their skills change; a matrix without last-used dates produces assignments that mismatch actual capability within 6-12 months of authoring.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Resource plan must reconcile with schedule (CPM) and budget (EVM); update all three together when resource changes occur.</statement>
        <rationale>A resource change that does not propagate to schedule and cost creates invisible drift — the plan says on-time but the critical path has already slipped.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep a stretch bench — people with 10-20% slack who can absorb spikes without going over 80% effective capacity.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a stretch bench, every unplanned event (sick day, unexpected bug, scope addition) requires a formal escalation; a small buffer keeps velocity stable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="references">
      <list>
        <item>PMBoK 7th — Team Performance Domain</item>
        <item>DeMarco &amp; Lister, "Peopleware" — slack chapter on the cost of full utilization</item>
        <item>Allen Ward, "Lean Product and Process Development" — capacity utilization paradox</item>
        <item>Float blog, "The 70% rule for resource planning"</item>
        <item>Sibling methodologies: schedule-development/, cost-estimation/, earned-value-management/, raci-matrix/, procurement-management/</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/capacity.py" purpose="Compute effective hours per person per week from roster, PTO, and meeting load"/>
      <template path="templates/resource-plan.md" purpose="Resource plan with summary table, calendar grid, skill matrix, resource risks"/>
      <template path="templates/resource-request.md" purpose="Resource request form with role, skills, dates, justification, impact-if-not-filled"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
