<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Monolith Architecture Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the monolith-architecture methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale; the final rule is the skip-this-methodology gate referenced by the decision tree.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-monolith-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default to a monolith when team &lt; 10 OR domain boundaries unvalidated OR DevOps maturity below distributed-systems competence. Microservices MUST NOT be chosen as default architecture.</statement>
      <rationale source="Fowler — Monolith First (2015) + 2024 microservices premature-adoption survey.">Premature microservices produce distributed monoliths — the worst combination; Fowler's Monolith First holds across postmortem data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-vertical-slice-when-merge-conflicts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When feature merges produce frequent conflicts on shared service / repository classes, adopt vertical-slice organisation: each feature owns all layers. Layered (horizontal) layout MUST be reserved for thin CRUD with a small team.</statement>
      <rationale source="Jimmy Bogard — Vertical Slice Architecture; internal monolith refactor audits.">Horizontal layers create high coupling across features; vertical slices contain change to one directory per feature.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-acid-by-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Within a monolith, business operations MUST run inside a single database transaction unless explicit eventual-consistency is required. The transaction is the boundary, not a Saga.</statement>
      <rationale source="Monolith advantage rationale; Saga complexity case studies.">The dominant monolith advantage is ACID; abandoning it for Sagas reintroduces microservices complexity with none of the deploy independence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-scale-up-before-out" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Scale-up (bigger instance, faster disk, more RAM) MUST be exhausted before scale-out (multiple instances behind a load balancer). Scale-out for a monolith requires session-stateless design + shared cache + shared DB.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stack Overflow architecture postmortems; cost-per-RPS studies.">Scale-up reaches Stack Overflow-scale throughput on commodity hardware; scale-out introduces operational complexity that 90% of monoliths never need.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-extraction-when-justified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Extract a service from the monolith only when one of: independent scaling (10× traffic differential), independent team release cadence, polyglot need, or fault isolation requirement holds. Extraction MUST follow the strangler-fig pattern from a modular monolith — never from a big-ball-of-mud.</statement>
      <rationale source="Strangler-fig pattern (Fowler); internal extraction case studies.">Extracting without modular boundaries reproduces the spaghetti as a distributed system; extraction has to be earned by prior modularity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When prerequisites hold (functional list, single deployable, test pyramid, single pipeline), apply r1 → r2 → r3 → r4 → r5 and emit the spec.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology design — gate rule.">Order encodes risk: layout first, transaction strategy second, scaling third, extraction last.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do NOT use when (a) independent scaling already needed, (b) ≥10 teams with cadence conflicts, (c) polyglot mandate. Adopt modular-monolith or microservices instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Preconditions — skip gate.">Forcing monolith ceremony in microservice-justified contexts wastes review time and produces a worse outcome.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
