<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="vui-privacy-security Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the vui-privacy-security methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="transparency-before-capture" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Users MUST be informed BEFORE voice capture begins, with a clear, dated privacy notice listing what is recorded, where it is stored, retention, and how to delete.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 13/14; CCPA notice-at-collection">Post-hoc notices fail GDPR + CCPA; legal exposure is real.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="trust-indicators-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Recording state MUST be indicated visually (LED / icon) AND audibly (start/end chime). Silent recording is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG; W29 Article 29 WP opinion on smart devices">Without indicators, users cannot give informed consent at the moment of capture.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="step-up-auth-sensitive" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sensitive actions (payment, account change, health data access) MUST require step-up authentication beyond the initial voice session (PIN, biometric, second-factor).</statement>
      <rationale source="PSD2 SCA; HIPAA 164.312">Voice can be spoofed or shoulder-surfed; one-factor voice cannot protect sensitive actions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="pii-redact-at-boundary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Transcripts MUST be redacted of PII (names, account numbers, addresses, dates of birth, health terms) BEFORE leaving the device or being logged. Server-side redaction is insufficient as the only mechanism.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR data-minimisation principle">Once PII reaches a 3rd-party log, removal is hard or impossible; on-device redaction is the only reliable mitigation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="retention-and-deletion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST declare a retention period for transcripts (≤30 days for non-essential) AND a user-accessible 'delete my voice history' control. Indefinite retention is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 17 (right to erasure)">Users have legal right to delete; defaulting to indefinite retention violates the principle.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="minor-extra-protection" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If audience MAY include minors, additional protections (COPPA / GDPR Art. 8) MUST be declared: parental consent gate, no behavioural profiling, enhanced data-minimisation.</statement>
      <rationale source="COPPA 16 CFR 312; GDPR Art. 8">Minor data has heightened legal protections; default consumer flow does not meet them.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
