<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="VUI Privacy Principles and Trust Design">
  <summary>Core privacy principles for voice interfaces: transparency, control, minimization, security, deletion — plus trust indicators and step-up authentication rules for sensitive operations.</summary>

  <section title="Privacy Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Disclose data collection at the start of any session that captures voice data.</statement>
      <rationale>GDPR, HIPAA, CCPA, and BIPA require informed consent before biometric or health-related voice capture. Disclosure at session start prevents retroactive consent failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Collect only the voice data strictly required for the current task; do not retain beyond the session unless the user explicitly consents.</statement>
      <rationale>Data minimization limits regulatory exposure and reduces the blast radius of a transcript breach.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a "stop listening" command that is always available and honored within one utterance, backed by a hardware mute when possible.</statement>
      <rationale>Software-only stop commands fail when ASR is degraded. A hardware kill switch guarantees the user can always revoke capture regardless of model state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Allow users to access and delete their voice history at any time through a discoverable interface.</statement>
      <rationale>GDPR Article 17 (right to erasure) and CCPA deletion rights are non-negotiable in production deployments.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Trust Indicators">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show a visual indicator (light, icon) AND play an audio confirmation whenever the microphone is active.</statement>
      <rationale>Visual-only indicators exclude blind users; audio-only excludes deaf users. Both channels together cover the full user range and build consistent trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>LED ring glows amber during listening + chime plays on activation. "Stop listening" command tested and confirmed to silence both within 500ms.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Visual waveform animation only while listening. Blind users have no way to know capture is active; no hardware mute fallback.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Sensitive Operations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require step-up authentication (OTP, TOTP, biometric factor) before executing any destructive, financial, or identity-changing action via voice.</statement>
      <rationale>Voice authentication alone is too weak for high-value actions: voice cloning is accessible and speaker ID fails under noise. Step-up authentication adds a knowledge or possession factor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never repeat back full sensitive values the user provided; mask to last 4 digits or equivalent when confirming.</statement>
      <rationale>Repeating "your card number 4111 1111 1111 1111" in a shared space leaks the full number. Masking "the card ending 1111" preserves confirmation without exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Redact PII at the tool-call boundary, before any logging or persistence layer receives the data.</statement>
      <rationale>Tool-call payloads are often logged with full fidelity. Redacting at the boundary — not after persistence — is the only reliable prevention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/vui_privacy.py">Disclosure emitter and regex PII redactor for GDPR/HIPAA jurisdictions</reference>
  </section>
</text>
