<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="vui-privacy-security Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for vui-privacy-security as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Embedding real user PII or API secrets in the system prompt, treating it as private.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The system prompt is semi-public — adversaries extract it via creative jailbreaks. Any secrets or PII embedded in prompts will be leaked eventually.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Assuming "delete from our database" removes voice data from all persistence layers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cloud transcripts persist on third-party infrastructure (OpenAI, Google, AWS). Local deletion does not guarantee removal from provider storage unless Zero Data Retention is explicitly negotiated and documented in the DPIA.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Trusting voice speaker ID as sufficient authentication for high-value actions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Voice cloning is accessible and speaker ID fails under noise. Adversaries can bypass voice biometrics with clones; step-up with a knowledge or possession factor is mandatory for high-risk actions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Logging tool-call payloads without redacting PII at the boundary.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tool calls typically log request and response payloads in full. PII redaction must happen at the tool boundary before any persistence layer receives the data — not as a post-processing step.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
