<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="roadmap-design Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for roadmap-design. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose the format by uncertainty level first, then external-sharing requirement. High uncertainty + external sharing = outcome-based or Now-Next-Later (themes only). Low uncertainty + external sharing = timeline.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Format mismatch is the root cause of roadmap trust failures. A timeline roadmap in a high-uncertainty context creates commitments that cannot be kept, destroying stakeholder trust on every slip.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For a solo founder, the roadmap must fit on one screen. If it does not, it is a backlog with a roadmap header, not a roadmap.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A roadmap communicates strategic direction. Anything requiring scrolling has too much detail for strategic communication and too little for task execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 1 — Gather four inputs before touching the roadmap format: company/product vision, business goals for the period, user research insights, and technical constraints. Output: clear objectives for the roadmap period.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A roadmap without strategy inputs is a backlog sorted by recency. The objectives from this step are the connective tissue between every initiative and the business direction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 2 — Use the selection matrix as a deterministic first step. Do not let the audience or personal preference drive the format choice — let uncertainty level and external-sharing requirement drive it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Format chosen by audience preference produces a timeline roadmap for high-uncertainty work because stakeholders always want dates. The matrix overrides this bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 3 — Group all planned work into 3–5 themes. For each theme write: name, which objective it drives, why it is prioritised now, and 2–3 example initiatives. No theme should be orphaned from an objective.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Themes without objectives are backlog categories, not strategic groupings. The objective link is what prevents "Later" from becoming a permanent graveyard of low-priority features.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 4 — Assign each initiative a confidence level: High (committed and scoped), Medium (planned, needs scoping), Low (exploring, tentative). At least 30% of items must be Medium or Low — if everything is High, the labelling is decoration.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Uniform High confidence strips the signal from Now-Next-Later. Stakeholders learn to ignore confidence levels that are never Low, and the roadmap loses its communication function.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Limit Now to 5 initiatives maximum. Past 5, the team is effectively planning a backlog sprint, not a strategic now-horizon.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Teams can execute 3–5 significant initiatives in parallel before coordination costs outweigh benefits. More than 5 in Now signals that priorities have not been made.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 5 — For each horizon, document: why you chose these initiatives, what you are NOT doing and why, dependencies and risks, and how success will be measured. The "not doing" section is mandatory — it stops scope creep better than any priority list.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without explicit exclusions, every reasonable idea becomes a candidate for this quarter. The not-doing list also creates a retrospective record of scope decisions, which is invaluable for explaining past trade-offs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every initiative must link to one objective ID. Initiatives without an objective link are strategy leakage — remove them or create the missing objective.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Orphaned initiatives represent work that is in the plan without strategic justification. They accumulate over time and eventually dominate the roadmap without anyone being able to explain why.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Update cadence: monthly review of the initiative list, quarterly rewrite of the full document. Never rewrite the whole doc each sprint — that destroys the historical diff signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Quarter-to-quarter diffs are the primary retrospective artefact. Frequent complete rewrites make it impossible to see how the plan evolved or why certain items moved.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always include an "Explicitly Not Doing" section with reasons. It doubles as a future review log for stakeholder questions like "why didn't we build X?"</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stakeholders re-request excluded items constantly. A documented reason closes each request with a reference instead of reopening the debate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain two artefacts: internal roadmap (full detail: outcomes, owners, confidence, metrics) and external roadmap (themes and benefits only, no confidence levels, no owners, no metric targets). Sync via script, not copy-paste.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sharing confidence levels externally signals uncertainty in a way that customers interpret as incompetence. Sharing metric targets creates contractual expectations. Sharing owners exposes internal structure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
