<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-formats" title="Roadmap Format Selection">
  <summary>Four roadmap types with a selection matrix based on uncertainty, external-sharing needs, commitment level, and team maturity.</summary>

  <section title="Four Roadmap Types">
    <list>
      <item>Timeline roadmap: date-based, quarters or months, committed work. Use when: external sharing required with committed deliverables, low uncertainty, high team maturity.</item>
      <item>Now-Next-Later roadmap: priority sequence, no dates. Use when: internal or limited external sharing, medium uncertainty, any team maturity.</item>
      <item>Outcome-based roadmap: metric targets per theme. Use when: strategic alignment focus, high uncertainty, external sharing acceptable at theme level.</item>
      <item>Kanban roadmap: live work state. Use when: internal teams only, pure execution visibility, no strategic communication needed.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Selection Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose the format by uncertainty level first, then external-sharing requirement. High uncertainty + external sharing = outcome-based or Now-Next-Later (themes only). Low uncertainty + external sharing = timeline.</statement>
      <rationale>Format mismatch is the root cause of roadmap trust failures. A timeline roadmap in a high-uncertainty context creates commitments that cannot be kept, destroying stakeholder trust on every slip.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>Uncertainty high: outcome-based or Now-Next-Later</item>
      <item>Uncertainty medium: Now-Next-Later</item>
      <item>Uncertainty low: timeline or Kanban</item>
      <item>External sharing required: timeline (committed) or outcome/Now-Next-Later (theme level only)</item>
      <item>Internal only: any format</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Solo Founder Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>For a solo founder, the roadmap must fit on one screen. If it does not, it is a backlog with a roadmap header, not a roadmap.</statement>
      <rationale>A roadmap communicates strategic direction. Anything requiring scrolling has too much detail for strategic communication and too little for task execution. It serves neither purpose.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
