<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Roadmap Design Process">
  <summary>Five-step process from strategy input through stakeholder communication, including theme definition and confidence levels.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Start with Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Gather four inputs before touching the roadmap format: company/product vision, business goals for the period, user research insights, and technical constraints. Output: clear objectives for the roadmap period.</statement>
      <rationale>A roadmap without strategy inputs is a backlog sorted by recency. The objectives from this step are the connective tissue between every initiative and the business direction.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Choose the Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the selection matrix from content/01-formats.xml as a deterministic first step. Do not let the audience or personal preference drive the format choice — let uncertainty level and external-sharing requirement drive it.</statement>
      <rationale>Format chosen by audience preference produces a timeline roadmap for high-uncertainty work because stakeholders always want dates. The matrix overrides this bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Define Themes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Group all planned work into 3–5 themes. For each theme write: name, which objective it drives, why it is prioritised now, and 2–3 example initiatives. No theme should be orphaned from an objective.</statement>
      <rationale>Themes without objectives are backlog categories, not strategic groupings. The objective link is what prevents "Later" from becoming a permanent graveyard of low-priority features.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Populate Horizons with Confidence Levels">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign each initiative a confidence level: High (committed and scoped), Medium (planned, needs scoping), Low (exploring, tentative). At least 30% of items must be Medium or Low — if everything is High, the labelling is decoration.</statement>
      <rationale>Uniform High confidence strips the signal from Now-Next-Later. Stakeholders learn to ignore confidence levels that are never Low, and the roadmap loses its communication function.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Limit Now to 5 initiatives maximum. Past 5, the team is effectively planning a backlog sprint, not a strategic now-horizon.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams can execute 3–5 significant initiatives in parallel before coordination costs outweigh benefits. More than 5 in Now signals that priorities have not been made.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Add Context">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each horizon, document: why you chose these initiatives, what you are NOT doing and why, dependencies and risks, and how success will be measured. The "not doing" section is mandatory — it stops scope creep better than any priority list.</statement>
      <rationale>Without explicit exclusions, every reasonable idea becomes a candidate for this quarter. The not-doing list also creates a retrospective record of scope decisions, which is invaluable for explaining past trade-offs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/lint-roadmap.py">Automated validator for required keys, Now initiative count, not_doing field, and objective links</reference>
  </section>
</text>
