<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules" title="Roadmap Design Operational Rules">
  <summary>Concrete rules for roadmap maintenance, audience publishing, and agent-specific gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Maintenance Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every initiative must link to one objective ID. Initiatives without an objective link are strategy leakage — remove them or create the missing objective.</statement>
      <rationale>Orphaned initiatives represent work that is in the plan without strategic justification. They accumulate over time and eventually dominate the roadmap without anyone being able to explain why.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Update cadence: monthly review of the solution list, quarterly rewrite of the full document. Never rewrite the whole doc each sprint — that destroys the historical diff signal.</statement>
      <rationale>Quarter-to-quarter diffs are the primary retrospective artefact. Frequent complete rewrites make it impossible to see how the plan evolved or why certain items moved.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Always include an "Explicitly Not Doing" section with reasons. It doubles as a future review log for stakeholder questions like "why didn't we build X?"</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholders re-request excluded items constantly. A documented reason closes each request with a reference instead of reopening the debate. It also prevents reinventing the same prioritisation each quarter.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Audience Publishing Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain two artefacts: internal roadmap (full detail: outcomes, owners, confidence, metrics) and external roadmap (themes and benefits only, no confidence levels, no owners, no metric targets). Sync via script, not copy-paste.</statement>
      <rationale>Sharing confidence levels externally signals uncertainty in a way that customers interpret as incompetence. Sharing metric targets creates contractual expectations. Sharing owners exposes internal structure. Each audience needs a different abstraction level.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>Never let an agent ship the external roadmap without human review. Review for commitments, NDAs, and competitive signalling — LLMs cannot assess business risk context.</statement>
      <rationale>External roadmaps are marketing documents with legal and competitive implications. An LLM cannot assess NDA scope, competitive sensitivity, or contractual interpretation. Human checkpoint is mandatory before publication.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>When prompting an LLM for roadmap generation: force confidence distribution (now=mostly High, next=mostly Medium, later=mostly Low), cap themes at 3–5, cap Now initiatives at 5, mark not_doing as a required field.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs default to "everything is High confidence", produce 8+ themes, and silently drop the not-doing column because it produces no generative content. Explicit constraints in the prompt override these defaults.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>When the LLM is fed a previous quarter's roadmap as context, explicitly instruct it to identify what changed since the last review — otherwise it will simply restate the prior roadmap.</statement>
      <rationale>Models are trained to be helpful, which defaults to continuity. Without explicit change-detection instructions, the agent produces a cosmetically different version of the same document.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
