<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spatial-computing-overview">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Spatial computing (AR/VR/MR/XR) 2026 platform landscape and selection workflow: Vision Pro, Quest 3/3S, Android XR, HoloLens, Magic Leap 2.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>spatial-computing</tag>
      <tag>ar</tag>
      <tag>vr</tag>
      <tag>mr</tag>
      <tag>xr</tag>
      <tag>visionos</tag>
      <tag>android-xr</tag>
      <tag>quest</tag>
      <tag>platform-selection</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Spatial Computing Overview: Platform Landscape and Selection Workflow (2026)</title>
    <summary>Spatial computing blends digital content with physical space through AR, VR, and MR. This methodology gives an autonomous agent a concrete, paste-ready workflow to evaluate the 2026 platform landscape and produce a defensible platform-selection recommendation in a single pass.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Spatial computing represents a fundamental shift in how humans interact with digital information. Traditional 2D interfaces constrain content to rectangular screens; spatial interfaces distribute content across three dimensions, exploiting the human visual system's natural strengths in spatial reasoning and peripheral awareness. This enables richer information density, more intuitive interactions, and experiences that feel more natural than screen-based equivalents.</p>
      <p>The spatial computing market is experiencing rapid growth, with 87% headset adoption growth projected in 2026 and 40% of Global 2000 manufacturers implementing digital twins. An autonomous agent picking the wrong platform locks a team into the wrong SDK, the wrong input model, and the wrong distribution channel for 12+ months. This document provides the WHEN, the CHECKLIST, the COMMANDS, and the VERIFY steps so an agent can avoid that lock-in without human help.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>User asks: "Which XR/AR/VR/spatial platform should we build on?"</item>
        <item>User asks for a "spatial app", "Vision Pro app", "Quest app", "AR app", "MR app", or "headset app" without naming the platform.</item>
        <item>Task involves designing or scoping a new application targeting head-mounted displays (HMDs) in 2025/2026.</item>
        <item>Evaluating market opportunity, install base, or ecosystem before committing to an SDK.</item>
        <item>Planning a multiplatform XR strategy (e.g. WebXR + native + Unity).</item>
        <item>Translating a 2D mobile/web product to a spatial modality.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Optimizing existing 2D mobile/desktop applications — use standard mobile or desktop UX methodologies.</item>
        <item>Projects with no XR/AR/VR component or vision — this overview is not applicable.</item>
        <item>Pre-2024 legacy VR knowledge tasks — platforms and guidelines (visionOS, Horizon OS, Android XR) have changed; consult vendor docs directly.</item>
        <item>Internal hack-week prototypes with no commercial intent — the platform-selection overhead exceeds the value.</item>
        <item>Hardware engineering questions (optics, SLAM, compute) — out of scope; consult hardware specs.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="definitions">
      <p>Use these definitions verbatim when communicating with stakeholders. Confusing AR/VR/MR is the most common failure mode for non-XR teams.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Augmented Reality (AR): Digital content overlays the user's view of the physical world via phone, glasses, or pass-through; physical environment is primary context. Examples: ARKit, ARCore, Snap Lens.</item>
        <item>Virtual Reality (VR): Fully immersive digital environments replace physical view; total environmental control. Examples: Quest 3 immersive mode, PSVR2.</item>
        <item>Mixed Reality (MR): Digital and physical content coexist with occlusion and lighting interaction; digital objects appear grounded. Examples: Vision Pro pass-through, Quest 3 MR, HoloLens 2.</item>
        <item>Extended Reality (XR): Umbrella term covering AR + VR + MR. Use when modality is not yet decided.</item>
        <item>Spatial Computing: Apple-popularized term covering MR-first workflows where 2D apps and 3D content share the same volumetric canvas.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="market-context-2026">
      <p>Anchor numbers an agent should cite when justifying a platform recommendation. Use 2026 figures only; avoid pre-2024 forecasts.</p>
      <list>
        <item>AR/VR headset shipment growth: 87% YoY projected in 2026 (IDC class).</item>
        <item>Global 2000 manufacturers running production digital twins: 40%.</item>
        <item>Top consumer install base: Meta Quest line (~30M+ cumulative).</item>
        <item>Top premium/enterprise install base: Apple Vision Pro + Vision (next-gen) line.</item>
        <item>Emerging open ecosystem: Android XR (Samsung, Lenovo, XReal partners) launching at scale 2025-2026.</item>
        <item>Enterprise verticals leading adoption: manufacturing, training, medical, AEC, design visualization.</item>
        <item>Consumer verticals leading adoption: gaming, social, fitness, immersive video.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="platform-landscape-2026">
      <p>Snapshot of the five platforms an agent must consider. Treat any platform not on this list as niche or pre-production.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Apple Vision Pro / visionOS: premium MR; SwiftUI + RealityKit; eye+pinch input; App Store distribution; strongest for premium consumer + enterprise productivity.</item>
        <item>Meta Quest 3 / 3S / Horizon OS: consumer VR/MR leader; Unity + Unreal + native Android; controllers + hand tracking; Horizon Store + sideload; strongest for gaming, social, fitness.</item>
        <item>Android XR (Google + Samsung Galaxy XR): open Android-based MR; Jetpack XR + Unity OpenXR; hand + voice input; Play Store distribution; strongest for ecosystem scale + Android reuse.</item>
        <item>Microsoft HoloLens 2 (mature, no successor announced): enterprise MR; MRTK3 + Unity; hand + voice; tethered enterprise contracts; strongest for industrial, AEC, defense, frontline workers.</item>
        <item>Magic Leap 2: enterprise AR; Unity + WebXR; controller + hand; B2B contracts; strongest for medical, training, secure enterprise visualisation.</item>
      </list>
      <p>No single platform dominates across all segments. Vision Pro leads premium/enterprise productivity. Quest leads mainstream consumer. Android XR is rapidly scaling as the open alternative. HoloLens and Magic Leap dominate specific industrial verticals.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-model-selection">
      <p>When this methodology is applied by another LLM agent, route the work by complexity.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Haiku: apply the checklist to a single, well-scoped product brief.</item>
        <item>Sonnet: compare 2-3 platforms, weigh tradeoffs, produce the recommendation matrix.</item>
        <item>Opus: novel interaction paradigms, multi-year platform strategy, ambiguous markets.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <how-to>
      <p>Eight-step workflow. Execute sequentially; do not skip steps. Each step has a concrete output.</p>
      <step>1. Restate the brief in one sentence: "Build a [type] app for [audience] doing [task] in [environment]." If any slot is empty, ask the user before continuing.</step>
      <step>2. Classify modality: AR vs VR vs MR vs undecided XR. Use the Definitions section. Output one label.</step>
      <step>3. Classify market: premium-consumer, mainstream-consumer, prosumer, enterprise-productivity, industrial-frontline, or B2B-vertical. Output one label.</step>
      <step>4. Filter platforms using the Platform Selection Matrix below. Drop platforms that fail any hard constraint (budget, distribution, region, certification).</step>
      <step>5. Score the remaining 1-3 platforms against the Investment Considerations checklist (maturity, ecosystem, market size, technical fit). Output a 0-5 score per category.</step>
      <step>6. Produce a recommendation: primary platform, optional secondary platform, explicit rejected platforms with reasons.</step>
      <step>7. Emit the deliverable using the Recommendation Template below. Fill every field; do not leave placeholders.</step>
      <step>8. Run the Verify checklist. If any check fails, loop back to the failing step.</step>
    </how-to>
    <section name="platform-selection-matrix">
      <p>Decision lookup. Match the user's primary goal to the recommended platform and rationale.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Premium enterprise productivity, knowledge workers, design tools → Apple Vision Pro (visionOS, SwiftUI, RealityKit).</item>
        <item>Mainstream consumer gaming, social, fitness → Meta Quest 3 / 3S (Unity, Horizon OS).</item>
        <item>Open ecosystem, Android reuse, mass-market 2026+ → Android XR (Jetpack XR, OpenXR).</item>
        <item>Industrial frontline, AEC, hands-free workflows, secure enterprise → HoloLens 2 (MRTK3, Unity).</item>
        <item>Medical, defense, regulated training, B2B contracts → Magic Leap 2 (Unity, WebXR).</item>
        <item>Cross-platform, web-first, low commitment → WebXR (Three.js, Babylon.js, A-Frame) on Quest browser + Vision Safari + Android XR Chrome.</item>
        <item>Cross-platform native, single codebase → Unity OpenXR + per-platform shells.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <checklist>
      <check>Modality (AR/VR/MR/XR) is explicitly named in the brief.</check>
      <check>Target market segment is named (consumer/prosumer/enterprise/industrial).</check>
      <check>Hard constraints are listed: budget tier, distribution channel, certification (HIPAA, SOC2, ITAR), supported regions.</check>
      <check>Hand tracking, controllers, eye tracking, and voice input requirements are explicit.</check>
      <check>Pass-through MR vs full immersion is decided.</check>
      <check>Minimum supported FPS, resolution, and field-of-view targets are recorded.</check>
      <check>Network model is decided: offline, online-required, multiplayer, cloud-rendered.</check>
      <check>Localization and accessibility (captions, alt-input, comfort modes) are scoped.</check>
      <check>Monetization model is decided: paid, freemium, subscription, B2B contract.</check>
      <check>At least one rejected platform is documented with reasons (forces tradeoff thinking).</check>
      <check>Recommendation cites at least one 2026 market data point.</check>
      <check>Deliverable uses the Recommendation Template exactly.</check>
    </checklist>
    <section name="investment-considerations">
      <p>Score each candidate platform 0-5 on every dimension. Sum and rank.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Platform maturity: SDK stability, doc quality, update cadence, long-term roadmap signals from vendor.</item>
        <item>Developer ecosystem: active community, third-party assets, sample apps, funding/grant programs, learning resources.</item>
        <item>Market size: install base, growth rate, regional reach, monetization options (store, subs, B2B).</item>
        <item>Technical fit: required FPS, resolution, FOV, input modalities, sensors, on-device ML support, networking.</item>
        <item>Distribution: store policy, review timelines, sideload, MDM/enterprise distribution, certification cost.</item>
        <item>Cost: device price for end-users, dev hardware cost, SDK/license fees, store cut.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <commands>
      <command name="research-vision-pro">curl -s 'https://developer.apple.com/visionos/' | head -100</command>
      <command name="research-quest">curl -s 'https://developers.meta.com/horizon/' | head -100</command>
      <command name="research-android-xr">curl -s 'https://developers.google.com/xr' | head -100</command>
      <command name="research-hololens">curl -s 'https://learn.microsoft.com/windows/mixed-reality/' | head -100</command>
      <command name="research-magic-leap">curl -s 'https://developer.magicleap.cloud/' | head -100</command>
      <command name="webxr-spec">curl -s 'https://immersiveweb.dev/' | head -80</command>
      <command name="check-openxr">curl -s 'https://www.khronos.org/openxr/' | head -80</command>
      <command name="market-data">echo 'Cite IDC AR/VR Headset Tracker 2026 + Statista XR Market Size 2026 in the recommendation.'</command>
    </commands>
    <prompt purpose="platform-recommendation"><![CDATA[
You are a spatial computing platform analyst. Use the methodology
"spatial-computing-overview" verbatim.

INPUT
- Product brief: <ONE SENTENCE>
- Modality: <AR | VR | MR | XR-undecided>
- Market segment: <premium-consumer | mainstream-consumer | prosumer | enterprise-productivity | industrial-frontline | B2B-vertical>
- Hard constraints: <budget, distribution, certification, regions>
- Input requirements: <hands | controllers | eyes | voice | combinations>
- Network model: <offline | online | multiplayer | cloud-rendered>
- Monetization: <paid | freemium | subscription | B2B>

TASK
1. Filter the five 2026 platforms using the Platform Selection Matrix.
2. Score the surviving 1-3 platforms 0-5 on: maturity, ecosystem,
   market size, technical fit, distribution, cost.
3. Produce a Markdown recommendation using the Template below.
4. Cite at least one 2026 market data point.
5. List explicitly rejected platforms with one-line reasons.

CONSTRAINTS
- Use only 2025/2026 platform names and SDKs.
- No pre-2024 platform claims (e.g. no "Oculus Go", no "Magic Leap 1").
- No time estimates; use complexity labels (low/medium/high).
- No emojis.

OUTPUT
Markdown only, matching the Template.
]]></prompt>
    <template path="recommendation-template.md" purpose="Paste-ready Markdown deliverable agents must produce."/>
    <example type="good" title="Recommendation Template (paste into deliverable)">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Spatial Platform Recommendation: <product name>

## Brief
<one-sentence restatement>

## Classification
- Modality: <AR | VR | MR>
- Market segment: <segment>
- Hard constraints: <list>

## Candidates considered
| Platform | Maturity | Ecosystem | Market | Tech fit | Distribution | Cost | Total |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|
| Vision Pro | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | n/30 |
| Quest 3/3S | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | n/30 |
| Android XR | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | x/5 | n/30 |

## Recommendation
- Primary platform: <name + SDK>
- Secondary platform (optional): <name + SDK>
- Why: <2-4 sentences citing market data>

## Rejected platforms
- <name>: <one-line reason>
- <name>: <one-line reason>

## Open risks
- <risk 1>
- <risk 2>

## Next steps
- Build a 1-week prototype on <primary platform>.
- Validate input model (<hands/controllers/voice>) with 5 target users.
- Re-score after prototype if any tech-fit score was below 3.
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Insufficient recommendation (do not produce)">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
We should build for VR. Quest is popular. Let's start there.
]]></code>
      <note>Fails because: no modality justification, no market segment, no scores, no rejected alternatives, no constraints, no data point, no next steps.</note>
    </example>
    <rules>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always classify modality (AR/VR/MR) before recommending a platform.</statement>
        <rationale>Modality determines hardware, input, and SDK; skipping it produces ungrounded recommendations.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always document at least one rejected platform with a one-line reason.</statement>
        <rationale>Forces tradeoff thinking and prevents single-vendor bias.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always cite a 2025 or 2026 market data point in the recommendation body.</statement>
        <rationale>Anchors the recommendation to current ecosystem state, not stale forecasts.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Never recommend retired or pre-2024 platforms (Oculus Go, Magic Leap 1, Daydream, Hololens 1, etc.).</statement>
        <rationale>They are not supported in 2026 and lock the team into dead SDKs.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Prefer WebXR or Unity OpenXR when the brief demands cross-platform with no clear lead platform.</statement>
        <rationale>Reduces vendor lock-in until the team has signal from a prototype.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </rules>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Recommending a platform without naming the modality (AR vs VR vs MR).</description>
      <reason>Different modalities require different hardware, input models, comfort budgets, and SDKs; the recommendation is not actionable without the label.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Choosing a platform purely by install base without checking distribution constraints (enterprise MDM, region availability, certification).</description>
      <reason>Large install base on a closed store is irrelevant if the product cannot ship on it.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Mixing 2D-app reasoning ("just port the mobile app") into spatial recommendations.</description>
      <reason>Spatial UX requires depth, comfort, and input redesign; a port without rethink fails usability.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <verify>
      <step>1. Confirm the recommendation Markdown matches the Recommendation Template field-for-field.</step>
      <step>2. Confirm modality (AR/VR/MR) is named in the Classification section.</step>
      <step>3. Confirm at least one rejected platform appears with a reason.</step>
      <step>4. Confirm at least one 2025/2026 market data point is cited (install base, growth %, vertical adoption).</step>
      <step>5. Confirm scoring table has 6 columns and a total per row.</step>
      <step>6. Confirm no retired platforms appear (Oculus Go, ML1, Hololens 1, Daydream, Cardboard).</step>
      <step>7. Confirm input model and comfort/accessibility considerations are explicit.</step>
      <step>8. Confirm Next Steps proposes a time-boxed prototype on the primary platform.</step>
      <step>9. Confirm no time estimates appear; only complexity labels and prototype scope.</step>
      <step>10. If any check fails, return to the matching how-to step and regenerate.</step>
    </verify>
    <warning>Pre-2024 VR knowledge is misleading in 2026. Vision Pro, Quest 3/3S, Android XR, and Magic Leap 2 have replaced earlier devices and SDKs. Always confirm SDK names against vendor docs at the time of recommendation.</warning>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/designing-for-visionos">Apple visionOS Human Interface Guidelines</link>
      <link href="https://developers.meta.com/horizon/design/">Meta Horizon OS Design Guidelines</link>
      <link href="https://developers.google.com/xr">Android XR Developer Site</link>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/windows/mixed-reality/design/">Microsoft Mixed Reality Design</link>
      <link href="https://developer.magicleap.cloud/learn/guides">Magic Leap 2 Developer Guides</link>
      <link href="https://immersiveweb.dev/">WebXR Reference</link>
      <link href="https://www.khronos.org/openxr/">OpenXR Standard</link>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/spatial-computing">Interaction Design Foundation: Spatial Computing</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
