<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spatial-computing-overview">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Market overview and platform landscape for spatial computing (AR/VR/MR) in 2026. Key platforms: Apple Vision Pro, Meta Quest, Android XR, HoloLens, and Magic Leap.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>spatial-computing</tag>
      <tag>ar</tag>
      <tag>vr</tag>
      <tag>mr</tag>
      <tag>xr</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Spatial Computing Overview</title>
    <summary>Spatial computing blends digital content with physical space through AR (Augmented Reality), VR (Virtual Reality), and MR (Mixed Reality). Interfaces exist in three-dimensional space, not confined to rectangular screens.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Spatial computing represents a fundamental shift in how humans interact with digital information. Traditional 2D interfaces constrain content to rectangular screens; spatial interfaces distribute content across three dimensions, exploiting the human visual system's natural strengths in spatial reasoning and peripheral awareness. This enables richer information density, more intuitive interactions, and experiences that feel more natural than screen-based equivalents.</p>
      <p>The spatial computing market is experiencing rapid growth, with 87% headset adoption projected in 2026 and 40% of Global 2000 manufacturers implementing digital twins. Understanding the platform landscape and market dynamics is essential for product teams evaluating spatial opportunities.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing new applications for spatial platforms (Vision Pro, Quest, HoloLens).</item>
        <item>Evaluating market opportunity and platform selection for spatial experiences.</item>
        <item>Understanding the 2026 spatial computing landscape and key player positioning.</item>
        <item>Making platform investment decisions for teams building XR applications.</item>
        <item>Planning multiplatform strategies that span AR, VR, and MR modalities.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Optimizing existing 2D applications — use standard mobile or desktop design methodologies instead.</item>
        <item>Projects with no XR component or vision — spatial overview is not applicable.</item>
        <item>Legacy VR knowledge from pre-2024 eras — platforms and guidelines have evolved significantly.</item>
        <item>Internal prototypes or proof-of-concept work without commercial intent — market analysis overhead exceeds value.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="definition">
      <p>Spatial computing blends digital content with physical space through AR (Augmented Reality), VR (Virtual Reality), and MR (Mixed Reality). Interfaces exist in three-dimensional space, not confined to rectangular screens.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Augmented Reality (AR): Digital content overlays the user's view of the physical world; the physical environment is the primary context.</item>
        <item>Virtual Reality (VR): Fully immersive digital environments that replace the user's physical view; total environmental control.</item>
        <item>Mixed Reality (MR): Digital and physical content coexist and interact with occlusion; digital objects appear grounded in physical space.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="market-context-2026">
      <p>The spatial computing market is growing rapidly with significant platform diversity and consumer adoption acceleration.</p>
      <list>
        <item>AR/VR headset growth: 87% projected in 2026</item>
        <item>Global 2000 manufacturers with digital twins: 40%</item>
        <item>Key platforms: Apple Vision Pro, Meta Quest, Android XR</item>
      </list>
      <p>Market growth is driven by improvements in display resolution, field-of-view, battery life, and reduced cost. Enterprise adoption is accelerating in manufacturing, training, medical, and design visualization. Consumer adoption continues to concentrate in gaming and social experiences.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="platform-landscape">
      <p>The spatial computing ecosystem includes multiple competing platforms, each with distinct positioning and target markets.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Apple Vision Pro: Spatial computing platform; premium UX, enterprise focus, visionOS operating system, day-one enterprise partnerships</item>
        <item>Meta Quest: VR/MR hybrid; consumer adoption leader, strong social features, Android-based Horizon ecosystem</item>
        <item>Android XR: Open platform; ecosystem scale, broad device support, integration with Android phone ecosystem</item>
        <item>Microsoft HoloLens: MR specialist; enterprise and industrial applications, Windows integration, ruggedized hardware</item>
        <item>Magic Leap: AR focus; industrial applications and specialized use cases, enterprise training and visualization</item>
      </list>
      <p>No single platform dominates across all market segments. Vision Pro leads enterprise/premium consumer markets; Meta Quest leads mainstream consumer gaming; Android XR is rapidly scaling ecosystem support; HoloLens and Magic Leap dominate specific industrial verticals.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-selection">
      <p>When applying spatial computing methodologies, the choice of agent (model, system) depends on the task complexity and required reasoning depth.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Haiku model: Task execution; applying established spatial design methodologies to concrete problems and platform selection scenarios.</item>
        <item>Sonnet model: Design synthesis; comparing platforms, evaluating tradeoffs, recommending multiplatform architecture approaches.</item>
        <item>Opus model: Strategy and research; market analysis, long-term platform direction analysis, novel spatial interaction paradigm design.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="platform-comparison-matrix">
      <p>Platform selection depends on target market, deployment model, development budget, and feature requirements. No single platform is optimal for all scenarios.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Premium enterprise experience: Vision Pro (highest quality, established enterprise partnerships)</item>
        <item>Mainstream consumer gaming: Meta Quest (largest install base, social features, developer ecosystem)</item>
        <item>Open ecosystem scaling: Android XR (broad device support, Android integration, emerging platform)</item>
        <item>Industrial/specialized verticals: HoloLens, Magic Leap (vertical-specific applications, enterprise contracts)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="investment-considerations">
      <p>Teams evaluating spatial computing investments must consider platform maturity, developer ecosystem, market size, and technical requirements.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Platform maturity: Evaluate dev tools, documentation quality, SDK stability, update cadence, long-term viability</item>
        <item>Developer ecosystem: Check for active communities, third-party tools, asset stores, funding/support programs, sample applications</item>
        <item>Market size: Understand install base, growth projections, deployment scenarios, monetization options per platform, regional adoption</item>
        <item>Technical requirements: Review performance targets, network bandwidth, storage, localization, accessibility support per platform</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/designing-for-visionos">Apple Vision Pro Design Guidelines</link>
      <link href="https://developer.oculus.com/">Meta Quest Developer Center</link>
      <link href="https://developers.google.com/ar">Android XR Platform</link>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/spatial-computing">XR Design Principles</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
