<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="pm-certification-changes-2026">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>PMP exam ECO changes effective July 1, 2026. People 42%→33%, Process 50%→41%, Business Environment 8%→26%.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>pmp</tag>
      <tag>certification</tag>
      <tag>exam-changes</tag>
      <tag>2026</tag>
      <tag>domain-weights</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>PM Certification Exam Changes 2026</title>
    <summary>The PMP exam ECO (Examination Content Outline) changes effective July 1, 2026: People domain drops from 42% to 33%, Process drops from 50% to 41%, and Business Environment rises from 8% to 26%. The +18% shift requires new emphasis on business case development, benefits realization, strategic alignment, governance and compliance, sustainability, and tailoring.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Exam prep materials built for the 2021 ECO weight Business Environment at 8% — well below the new 26%. Candidates who study old outlines, training courses, or flashcard decks without updating them will be under-prepared for the largest weight area on the new exam. Materials must be rebuilt from the 2026 ECO PDF, not paraphrased from memory.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Preparing PMP/CAPM candidates for the July 1, 2026 exam revision.</item>
        <item>Updating internal PM training curricula or study-guide repos against the new domain weights.</item>
        <item>Building a study-companion agent that needs a current domain weight map.</item>
        <item>Auditing existing exam prep materials (Rita Mulcahy, PM PrepCast, internal decks) to find content gaps.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Candidates sitting before the July 1, 2026 cutover — the old outline is still authoritative.</item>
        <item>Non-PMI certifications (PRINCE2, IPMA, AgilePM, Scrum.org) — different bodies, different outlines.</item>
        <item>General PM coaching that is not exam-bound — exam weights distort real-world emphasis.</item>
        <item>Practitioners who already passed — this content is exam-shaped, not job-shaped.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="New Domain Weights (effective July 1, 2026)">
      <list>
        <item>People: 42% → 33% (−9%)</item>
        <item>Process: 50% → 41% (−9%)</item>
        <item>Business Environment: 8% → 26% (+18%)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Rebuild curriculum and study plans from the official 2026 ECO PDF, not from memory or legacy Rita Mulcahy / PM PrepCast outlines; domain weight drift is the most common gap in auto-generated study plans.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs and trainers fed old outlines (42/50/8) will silently produce materials weighted for the 2021 exam. A candidate spending 8% effort on Business Environment in 2026 is under-prepared for 26% of the exam.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="New Emphasis Areas (Business Environment +18%)">
      <list>
        <item>Business case development and benefits realization</item>
        <item>Strategic alignment of projects to organizational objectives</item>
        <item>Governance and compliance (regulatory, ethical, organizational)</item>
        <item>Sustainability considerations in project delivery</item>
        <item>Value delivery measurement and reporting</item>
        <item>Tailoring approaches to fit project context</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track candidate weak areas at the ECO enabler level, not the domain level; domain-level coaching is too coarse to direct effective study.</statement>
        <rationale>A candidate scoring 60% on Business Environment might score 90% on strategy and 30% on compliance. Domain-level visibility hides the real gap.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>A cert-curriculum-curator ingests the official 2026 ECO PDF plus PMBOK 7e / Agile Practice Guide / Process Groups Practice Guide, builds a topic graph (domain → task → enabler → study resources). A gap-analyzer diffs current course materials against the graph and outputs a missing-topic list. A mock-exam-author generates situational questions weighted to the new domain split, with rationales that cite source pages. A weak-area-coach reads candidate quiz history, identifies low-confidence enablers, and queues targeted drills. Human PMP-certified instructor reviews every mock question before it ships — never publish auto-generated PMP items unreviewed.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Recommended Subagents">
      <list>
        <item>cert-curriculum-curator (sonnet) — owns the ECO graph, reconciles drift versus PMI announcements.</item>
        <item>gap-analyzer (sonnet) — diffs internal materials against the 2026 ECO; emits missing-topic backlog.</item>
        <item>mock-exam-author (sonnet) — drafts situational questions, four answer choices, distractor design, source citation.</item>
        <item>weak-area-coach (haiku) — chats with candidate, picks next 5 questions from the bank by skill gap.</item>
        <item>policy-watch-agent (haiku, scheduled) — polls PMI announcements + PM Network blog for ECO addenda.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Prompt Pattern — Mock Exam Author">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a mock-exam-author. Generate ONE situational question for ECO domain
"Business Environment", task "T1 Plan and Manage Project Compliance", enabler
"identify regulatory requirements". Return STRICT JSON:
{ "stem": "...", "options": ["A","B","C","D"], "correct": "B",
  "rationale": "...", "source": "PMBOK 7e p.NN", "difficulty": "medium" }
Rules: scenario must be 4–6 sentences, distractors must be plausible PMI
language, no trick wording, no time-bound details that go stale.]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="Prompt Pattern — Gap Analyzer">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a gap-analyzer. Inputs: 2026 ECO graph (JSON) and our course outline
(markdown). Output a table of (domain, task, enabler, status, evidence_link)
where status ∈ {covered, partial, missing}. Cite specific course slides.]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="Key Limitations and Gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>The README is a single-page summary; it omits the actual ECO (Examination Content Outline) tasks/enablers per domain. Agents that quote percentages without ECO tasks produce shallow study plans.</description>
        <reason>Anchor to PMI Standard for Earned Value (2024), PMBOK 7e, Agile Practice Guide, and the published 2026 ECO PDF.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Sustainability" and "Tailoring" are PMI buzzwords; LLMs hallucinate plausible-sounding but non-PMI definitions.</description>
        <reason>Anchor content to authoritative PMI sources: PMBOK 7e, Agile Practice Guide, Process Groups Practice Guide.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Domain weights are not exam question counts; PMI uses scaled scoring per domain. Agents that promise "you must get 26% of Business Environment correct" are wrong.</description>
        <reason>PMI scaled scoring is not public. Use weights to allocate study effort, not to predict raw question distributions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Exam item bank evolves continuously after July 2026; static content goes stale within months of release.</description>
        <reason>Plan for ongoing revision. Treat curriculum as a living document, not a one-time PDF.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Regional language exams (UA, RU, ES, ZH) lag English by 1–3 quarters; weights are the same but examples differ.</description>
        <reason>Translate examples with PMI vocabulary, not literal translation. Maintain language parity.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Generating PMP mock questions with LLMs without human PMP-holder review before delivery.</description>
        <reason>LLMs invent plausible PMI vocabulary that does not appear in the ECO or source texts. Auto-generated PMP items distributed to candidates without review damage exam credibility and candidate preparation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating domain weights as direct question-count percentages.</description>
        <reason>PMI uses scaled scoring per domain; "26% Business Environment" does not mean 26% of raw questions map to that domain directly. Agents that promise specific question counts mislead candidates.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Applying the 2026 ECO to candidates sitting before July 1, 2026.</description>
        <reason>Pre-cutover candidates are tested on the 2021 outline; using the new weights for them introduces wrong material and creates confusion about what to prioritize.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools">
      <list>
        <item>pdftotext (poppler) — Extract ECO PDF for ingestion into curriculum graph</item>
        <item>pandoc — Convert course materials between markdown / docx / pptx for diffing</item>
        <item>jq / yq — Manipulate the ECO topic graph as JSON/YAML</item>
        <item>anki-cli / genanki (Python) — Generate flashcard decks from enabler list</item>
        <item>pytest — Run a test that validates every mock question has a source citation</item>
        <item>git + branch-per-cohort — Track curriculum versions per exam window</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Services and Apps">
      <list>
        <item>PMI.org (CCRS, exam scheduling) — Limited API; no public mock-exam API</item>
        <item>Pearson VUE — Exam delivery vendor; no agent integration</item>
        <item>PrepCast / PM Edu — Closed content; reference only</item>
        <item>Anki (AnkiWeb / AnkiConnect) — Local API for deck push from mock-exam-author</item>
        <item>Notion / Confluence — Host the ECO graph + study notes</item>
        <item>GitHub / GitLab — Curriculum repo, PR-based review of generated questions</item>
        <item>Quizlet — Sets API deprecated; avoid for new builds</item>
        <item>Kahoot / Mentimeter — Cohort live-quiz delivery during instructor-led sessions</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Anchor every generated question to a primary PMI source (PMBOK 7e, Agile Practice Guide, PfMP/PgMP standards) with page citation; reject questions without citations.</item>
        <item>Rebuild the ECO graph from the official 2026 PDF on each PMI revision announcement; never edit it by hand.</item>
        <item>Track candidate weak areas at the enabler level, not the domain level — domain-level coaching is too coarse.</item>
        <item>Human-review 100% of auto-generated mock items before they reach candidates; PMP brand exposure to bad items is a credibility risk.</item>
        <item>Maintain language parity for at least UA + EN if your audience is bilingual; translate stems with PMI vocabulary, not literal translation.</item>
        <item>Pair certification prep with a real-project simulation (kanban board, risk register, EVM exercise) so candidates do not become test-taker-only PMs.</item>
        <item>Sunset old (2021 outline) materials with a clear date stamp; do not silently overwrite — auditors and re-takers need both versions.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-agent Gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs invent PMI vocabulary that "sounds right" (e.g., "Strategic Tailoring Index").</description>
        <reason>Force a glossary check against PMBOK 7e index before accepting any term.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Domain weight drift: agents fed old outlines (42/50/8) will silently regress.</description>
        <reason>Pin the 33/41/26 weights in the system prompt, not a retrieval doc that can be evicted.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Business Environment" is the largest growth area and most under-represented in legacy material — quotas alone do not fix shallow content; require new examples per enabler, not paraphrases.</description>
        <reason>Invest in original content creation, not repackaging.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Distractor design is hard for LLMs — they often produce options that are obviously wrong or two-correct.</description>
        <reason>Run a self-critique pass on every generated question.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Region/language: same weights, different idioms. Translation agents that copy English idioms into UA/PT lose realism.</description>
        <reason>Employ bilingual PMI-certified reviewers for regional variants.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Citation hallucination: LLMs love fake page numbers. Validate citations by retrieving the cited PDF page text and checking for keyword overlap before publishing.</description>
        <reason>Build a validation hook into the publishing pipeline.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Never let an agent decide if a candidate is "ready"; emit readiness signals (sub-domain confidence, mock score trend) and let a human instructor make the call.</description>
        <reason>Preserve human judgment on certification decisions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>PDU/CCRS reporting: do not auto-submit PDUs on a candidate's behalf — PMI compliance issue; agents only draft.</description>
        <reason>Maintain audit trail and compliance responsibility with human instructors.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/score-session.py" purpose="Weighted exam-style session scorer using 2026 ECO domain weights (33/41/26)."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="pm-certification-alignment-2026"/>
      <ref slug="benefits-realization"/>
      <ref slug="value-stream-management"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/get-certified/certification-types/project-management-professional-pmp"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
