<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="elicitation-techniques Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for elicitation-techniques. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prepare a written interview guide with objectives, question types (open, closed, probing, clarifying), and pre-read materials. Send the guide 24 hours ahead.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Pre-reading produces 30-50% deeper sessions; unprepared stakeholders give surface-level answers that require follow-up interviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap interviews at 60 minutes. Past that, signal-to-noise collapses.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Fatigue produces unreliable notes and stakeholders disengage from the process.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use anonymous dot-voting or similar mechanisms to prevent the loudest voice from dominating. Record per-vote tallies, not names.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Workshop dynamics get hijacked without structured participation controls; consensus produced by loudest voice is not consensus.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap workshops at 90 minutes with a hard break.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Past 90 minutes, participant attention degrades and minutes become unreliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pair observation with at least one other technique (interview or document analysis) for every requirement area.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stated needs (interviews) differ from actual behavior (observation); skipping observation produces requirements that pass review and fail in production.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat every document-analysis claim as "as-documented" and cross-check against at least one observation or interview before promoting to a requirement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Documentation typically lags actual implementation by 6-18 months; as-documented state is not as-implemented state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Surveys with less than 30% response rate are not data — they are anecdotes. Flag response rate in the synthesis report.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Low-response-rate surveys mislead with statistical framing; the real finding is that the stakeholder group did not engage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Design with a target N and confidence interval before distributing. Pre-register the analysis plan to prevent post-hoc fishing.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Open-ended analysis produces artifacts that confirm pre-existing beliefs rather than surface new requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never use prototyping as the first elicitation technique. Use only after interviews and/or observation have produced candidate requirements.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Prototyping anchors stakeholders on the prototype's affordances; they stop imagining alternatives and stop surfacing underlying needs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every requirement must cite at least two distinct session IDs of different techniques before promotion from candidate to draft.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-source requirements lack triangulation; contradictions between sources are where the real requirements live.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capture consent in the frontmatter (`consent: true`, `consent_basis: email|signed|verbal+recorded`). No consent → no commit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stakeholder consent is a legal and ethical requirement; missing consent invalidates the entire session artifact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Redact PII at ingest, not later — Presidio / spaCy NER pass before the transcript hits git. Keep raw recordings outside the repo (S3 with lifecycle policy).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">PII in git is impossible to expunge; redact at the source, not in a post-hoc pass.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Distinguish *stated*, *observed*, and *inferred* needs in the synthesis output. Tag each REQ with its source tier; observed &gt; stated &gt; inferred for credibility.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The source of a requirement affects its credibility; inferred requirements without observation backing should be flagged for stakeholder validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cross-link every elicitation artifact to a `stakeholder-analysis/` ID and a `ba-planning/` deliverable; otherwise the corpus becomes unsearchable within a sprint.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Artifacts scattered across the project without cross-references become orphaned; linkage keeps them connected to the broader requirements lifecycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep an "open questions" log per session that the next session is expected to close. Track close-rate as a process metric.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unclosed questions are the leading cause of incomplete requirements; tracking them as a metric highlights discovery thoroughness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r16" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Recording retention policy lives next to the artifact (`retention: 365d`); a cron job purges past-due recordings and logs the deletion. GDPR-friendly by default.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Raw recordings contain sensitive information; automatic expiry is simpler than manual deletion and proves compliance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r17" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a "what did we miss" round at the end of every session — single highest-yield question, almost always uncovers an unspoken constraint.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">This one question consistently surfaces requirements that all other techniques missed; it is the most cost-effective discovery technique per minute spent.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
