<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-techniques" title="Elicitation Techniques Reference">
  <summary>Eight elicitation techniques with when-to-use, preparation, execution guidance, and a technique selection guide by information type.</summary>

  <section title="Interviews">
    <p>Purpose: gather detailed information from individuals. Best for deep understanding, sensitive topics, or stakeholders with unique knowledge.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Prepare a written interview guide with objectives, question types (open, closed, probing, clarifying), and pre-read materials. Send the guide 24 hours ahead.</statement>
      <rationale>Pre-reading produces 30-50% deeper sessions; unprepared stakeholders give surface-level answers that require follow-up interviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Open questions — explore: "Tell me about your process."</item>
      <item>Closed questions — confirm: "Do you use this daily?"</item>
      <item>Probing questions — dig deeper: "Why is that important?"</item>
      <item>Clarifying questions — ensure understanding: "So you mean...?"</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap interviews at 60 minutes. Past that, signal-to-noise collapses.</statement>
      <rationale>Fatigue produces unreliable notes and stakeholders disengage from the process.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Workshops">
    <p>Purpose: bring stakeholders together to build consensus on complex topics. Best when multiple perspectives are required.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use anonymous dot-voting or similar mechanisms to prevent the loudest voice from dominating. Record per-vote tallies, not names.</statement>
      <rationale>Workshop dynamics get hijacked without structured participation controls; consensus produced by loudest voice is not consensus.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap workshops at 90 minutes with a hard break.</statement>
      <rationale>Past 90 minutes, participant attention degrades and minutes become unreliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Observation">
    <p>Purpose: see how work is actually done, not how it is described. Captures what interviews miss.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Passive — watch without interaction; produces unbiased view of the current state.</item>
      <item>Active — ask questions while observing; captures the rationale behind each step.</item>
      <item>Participant — join in the work; produces the deepest understanding.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair observation with at least one other technique (interview or document analysis) for every requirement area.</statement>
      <rationale>Stated needs (interviews) differ from actual behavior (observation); skipping observation produces requirements that pass review and fail in production.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Document Analysis">
    <p>Purpose: extract requirements from existing materials — system documentation, process manuals, business rules, reports, regulations, previous project documents.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat every document-analysis claim as "as-documented" and cross-check against at least one observation or interview before promoting to a requirement.</statement>
      <rationale>Documentation typically lags actual implementation by 6-18 months; as-documented state is not as-implemented state.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Surveys and Questionnaires">
    <p>Purpose: gather quantitative or broad input from large or geographically distributed stakeholder groups.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Surveys with less than 30% response rate are not data — they are anecdotes. Flag response rate in the synthesis report.</statement>
      <rationale>Low-response-rate surveys mislead with statistical framing; the real finding is that the stakeholder group did not engage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Design with a target N and confidence interval before distributing. Pre-register the analysis plan to prevent post-hoc fishing.</statement>
      <rationale>Open-ended analysis produces artifacts that confirm pre-existing beliefs rather than surface new requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Prototyping">
    <p>Purpose: validate understanding through tangible examples. Use only after divergent elicitation.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Paper — low fidelity, quick concept validation.</item>
      <item>Wireframe — low-medium fidelity, layout and flow.</item>
      <item>Mockup — medium-high fidelity, visual design.</item>
      <item>Working prototype — high fidelity, functional validation.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use prototyping as the first elicitation technique. Use only after interviews and/or observation have produced candidate requirements.</statement>
      <rationale>Prototyping anchors stakeholders on the prototype's affordances; they stop imagining alternatives and stop surfacing underlying needs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Focus Groups">
    <p>Purpose: gather user perspectives on a topic from a group with similar characteristics. Best for validating assumptions about user segments.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Brainstorming">
    <p>Purpose: generate ideas rapidly in a group setting. Best at the start of a discovery phase.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Technique Selection Guide">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every requirement must cite at least two distinct session IDs of different techniques before promotion from candidate to draft.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-source requirements lack triangulation; contradictions between sources are where the real requirements live.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Understand current process → Observation + Interview.</item>
      <item>Gather broad input → Survey + Focus group.</item>
      <item>Build consensus → Workshop.</item>
      <item>Validate design → Prototyping.</item>
      <item>Understand documentation → Document analysis.</item>
      <item>Generate ideas → Brainstorming workshop.</item>
      <item>Deep dive with expert → Interview.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
