<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Elicitation Techniques — Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Requirements discovery interview example, process mapping workshop example, and common elicitation antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Example: Requirements Discovery Interview">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Stakeholder: Customer Service Manager. Objective: understand current pain points and information needs.</note>
      <note>Questions: (1) "Walk me through a typical customer inquiry." [process understanding — open] (2) "What are the most common issues your team faces?" [pain points — open] (3) "What information do you wish you had access to?" [needs — probing] (4) "How do you measure success?" [metrics — closed] (5) "What would ideal look like?" [vision — open]</note>
      <note>Insights gathered: average call takes 12 minutes (7 minutes searching for info); 3 different systems checked per call; no visibility into order status; customer satisfaction declining. Each insight becomes a candidate requirement with this session_id as source citation.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example: Process Mapping Workshop">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Objective: map current order fulfillment process. Participants: order entry, warehouse, shipping, customer service teams.</note>
      <note>Activities: each team presents their steps (15 min each) → group maps end-to-end flow (45 min) → identify handoff points and issues (20 min) → dot-vote to prioritize pain points (15 min).</note>
      <note>Output: current state process map, list of 12 pain points, top 3 priorities. Each pain point becomes a candidate requirement citing this workshop session_id and the team that raised it.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Leading questions in interview guides — "Don't you think the system is too slow?" or "Wouldn't it be better if...?"</description>
      <reason>Leading questions suggest the answer and confirm pre-existing assumptions; they produce requirements that reflect the BA's beliefs, not the stakeholder's actual needs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using prototyping as the first elicitation technique before any interviews or observation.</description>
      <reason>Prototyping anchors stakeholders on the prototype's affordances; they stop imagining alternatives and stop surfacing underlying needs, producing requirements shaped by the prototype rather than by the problem.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating document analysis as sufficient on its own without observation or interviews.</description>
      <reason>Documentation typically lags actual implementation by 6-18 months; as-documented state is not as-implemented state and not where real requirements live.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Surveys with less than 30% response rate reported as representative data.</description>
      <reason>Low-response surveys are anecdotes with statistical framing; they mislead stakeholders about the breadth of the finding and produce requirements that serve the responding minority.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Scheduling too many elicitation sessions without preparation — wasting stakeholder time.</description>
      <reason>Stakeholder time is the scarcest resource in elicitation; unprepared sessions burn goodwill and produce shallow answers that require follow-up sessions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Single-technique elicitation — relying only on interviews without observation or document analysis.</description>
      <reason>Single-source requirements lack triangulation; stated needs (interviews) differ systematically from actual behavior (observation), and the gap is where the most valuable requirements live.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
