<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="elicitation-techniques Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for elicitation-techniques as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Stated needs ≠ actual needs. Interviews capture what people say they do; observation captures what they actually do. Skipping observation produces requirements that pass review and fail in production.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pair interviews with observation to close the stated-vs-actual gap. Single-technique programs will miss this.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Workshop dynamics get hijacked by the loudest voice. Without dot-voting or anonymous input the loudest stakeholder's view is recorded as "consensus".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use anonymous voting mechanisms (Miro / FigJam / physical dots) to distribute voice equitably. Record per-vote tallies, not attributions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Surveys with less than 30% response rate are not data, they are anecdotes with statistics applied — the README does not flag this.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Flag response rate in the synthesis report. If &lt; 30%, call it "anecdotal feedback" not "survey results."</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Document analysis surfaces the *as-documented* state, which is usually 6-18 months behind the *as-implemented* state. Pair with observation or it lies.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always cross-check document claims against at least one observation or interview. Documentation is a starting point, not the source of truth.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Prototyping anchors stakeholders on the prototype's affordances; they stop imagining alternatives. Use only after divergent elicitation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Prototyping is a validation technique, not an ideation technique. Run interviews/observation first; use prototypes to test, not explore.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Recordings + transcripts contain PII, salaries, performance complaints, customer names. Without a retention policy the elicitation archive becomes a compliance liability.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Redact PII at ingest (Presidio / spaCy). Keep raw recordings outside git with a lifecycle expiry (365 days). Comply by default.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Single-technique programs miss requirements. Triangulation (≥2 techniques per area) is the empirical fix; the README mentions it but does not enforce it.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Block requirement promotion to draft until ≥2 session_ids of different techniques are cited. Make triangulation a gate, not a suggestion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM-driven "interviews via chatbot" suppress emotional / non-verbal signal — sarcasm, hesitation, eye-rolls — which often carry the real requirement.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Humans run live sessions. Agents prepare guides, transcribe, synthesise. Never delegate the human conversation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Hallucinated stakeholders: synthesis agents invent plausible quotes ("the CFO said...") when none exists. Forbid any REQ without a `session_id + line_range` citation; reject outputs that fail the regex check.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Validate every REQ citation against the actual transcript before persisting. Spot-check 10% manually.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Leading-question generation: prep agents bias toward confirmation ("How much do you love feature X?"). Lint the guide for "don't you", "wouldn't", "isn't it true", and superlatives in question stems before sending.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run a heuristic linter on the generated guide. Flag leading phrasing; human approves before distribution.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Transcription drift: Whisper hallucinates fluent text on silence / cross-talk. Always keep timestamps and require the synthesizer to cite line ranges; spot-check 10% manually.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Never trust STT output as-is. Require line-range citations; spot-check against audio. Preserve timestamps for correlation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>PII echo: agents quote redacted spans back in summaries because the redaction was only on the transcript copy, not on the indexed embeddings. Redact at the embedding source, not just at view time.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Redact before any LLM ingests the text. Hash or replace sensitive fields in the raw transcript, not just in the summary view.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Sentiment flattening: LLM summaries strip frustration, sarcasm, hesitation. Preserve emotional markers in the transcript (`[long pause]`, `[laughs]`) and require the synthesizer to surface them as a separate "tone" field.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Preserve [long pause] and similar markers in the transcript. Require the agent to emit a "tone" field separately; humans review for missed signals.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Workshop minute generation tends toward consensus narrative. Force the agent to also emit a `dissents` list with named (or pseudonymised) speakers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generate minutes with explicit `dissents` section. Name speakers (or use pseudonyms for anonymity) for accountability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Survey design agents balance question types but ignore Likert-scale calibration (5-point vs. 7-point, label asymmetry). Cap the agent to a known-good template; humans approve the final scale.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Never let agents invent the Likert scale. Use a pre-approved template with consistent labeling.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Document-analysis agents over-trust outdated docs. Require every "as-is" claim from a document to be cross-checked against ≥1 observation or interview.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tag document-derived claims as "as-documented" and require cross-check before promotion to requirement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Prototyping prompts: agents propose hi-fi prototypes too early because the corpus is full of them. Constrain to paper / wireframe at the divergent stage; promote fidelity only after stakeholder validation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Constrain the prompt: "at this stage, only paper or wireframe fidelity." Enforce fidelity gatekeeping in the orchestration layer.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-18" severity="medium">
      <description>Token budget: long workshops produce 10-20k-token transcripts. Chunk per agenda item with overlap, not arbitrary windows; otherwise the synthesizer loses speaker context across chunks.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Chunk by agenda item, not by token count. Preserve overlap between chunks for context continuity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-19" severity="medium">
      <description>Multi-language sessions: BA in Ukrainian, stakeholder in English mid-session — STT systems silently drop the minority language. Configure language hints per speaker; verify turn-by-turn.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Configure STT with language hints per speaker. Spot-check output for silently-dropped languages.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
