<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ar-design-patterns Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ar-design-patterns as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Outdoor lighting variability breaks plane detection and color matching, especially on Quest passthrough. Objects that look correct indoors look washed out or saturated in sunlight.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Outdoor lighting varies by time of day, cloud cover, and reflection. Dynamic lighting estimation cannot keep up. Solution: test in target lighting conditions or use unlit, high-saturation shaders for outdoor AR.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Object recognition is brittle outside trained classes. Agents hallucinate that "object recognition works like human vision" but trained models only recognize the exact classes they were trained on.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>CoreML / ARCore Augmented Images require custom training per object class. Generic object detection (YOLO) on mobile is too slow. Solution: define a closed set of recognizable objects and test extensively before shipping.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Battery drain: continuous tracking + render at 60 fps drains a phone in 30-45 minutes. AR is power-hungry.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>GPU and IMU tracking run continuously. Solution: cap session duration, provide clear battery warnings, and optimize render loops (use LOD, cull off-screen objects, reduce geometry count).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy: AR cameras capture bystanders without consent. This raises red flags in EU (GDPR), CA (CCPA), and Israel (Privacy Law) jurisdictions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>AR requires camera access, and any recording includes background people. Solution: clearly disclose camera recording, provide a "do not record" affordance in shared sessions, and avoid persistent capture.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-platform parity (ARKit ↔ ARCore ↔ WebXR) is partial. Agents over-promise feature equivalence but ARKit's scene mesh, ARCore's depth sensing, and WebXR's anchors are not equivalent.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each platform has different sensor hardware and SDKs. Feature parity requires per-platform implementation. Solution: define a core feature set and gracefully degrade on platforms that don't support it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Cybersickness from misaligned overlays at &gt;70ms latency. High latency between head movement and visual update causes nausea.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The human brain expects motion-to-photon latency under 70ms. Mobile ARCore/ARKit typically achieve 50-100ms, but network latency, per-frame render time, or poor frame pacing breaks this. Solution: target 90 fps on high-end devices, profile end-to-end latency, and implement frame pacing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents conflate ARKit world tracking with ARCore. Features like "scene mesh" are not equivalent across platforms.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>ARKit (iOS) has scene mesh understanding; ARCore (Android) has depth sensing. Different capabilities, different APIs. Solution: test on each target platform.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs hallucinate Reality Composer Pro APIs. Ground via current Apple sample code, not guesses.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Reality Composer Pro is newer and less well-documented in training data. Solution: provide agents with Apple's sample code or Reality Composer documentation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents underestimate device thermal throttling. Ship with low-poly + LOD by default.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>60 fps AR on a phone can cause the device to thermally throttle after 15 minutes. Solution: profile on target devices, use LOD meshes, and cap frame rate if needed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Camera + microphone permissions are PII gates. Agents must produce a privacy disclosure string.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Requesting camera/microphone access is a trust breach. Users expect clear privacy disclosures. Solution: generate privacy policy text and obtain explicit user consent.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Bystander capture: agent must include a "do not record" affordance in shared sessions. Recording bystanders without consent is illegal in many jurisdictions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Any AR app with camera access may record bystanders. Solution: provide explicit "recording off" toggle and legal disclaimers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Never let an agent auto-publish AR content for kids without COPPA/GDPR-K review. AR for children has special legal and ethical constraints.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>COPPA (USA) and GDPR Article 8 (EU) restrict collection from children under 13/16. Solution: block auto-publish for kid-targeting content and require legal review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
