<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Continuous Discovery Habits Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Continuous Discovery Habits plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="product-trio-must-attend" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Discovery touchpoints MUST be attended by the full trio (PM + Design Lead + Tech Lead); PM-only touchpoints MUST be reclassified as 'sales calls'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Teresa Torres — Continuous Discovery Habits (2021)">Single-discipline attendance produces single-discipline interpretation; the trio constraint is the structural gate against discovery silos.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="weekly-customer-touchpoint" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The trio MUST hold ≥1 customer touchpoint per week; weeks without a touchpoint MUST be logged as discovery debt.</statement>
      <rationale source="Teresa Torres — Continuous Discovery Habits (2021)">Sub-weekly cadence loses signal freshness; the weekly rhythm is the minimum for compound learning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ost-is-source-of-truth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every spec MUST link to an opportunity node in the Opportunity Solution Tree (OST); orphan specs MUST be rejected at backlog grooming.</statement>
      <rationale source="Teresa Torres — Continuous Discovery Habits (2021)">Orphan specs drift from desired outcomes; the OST link is the only durable trace from outcome to feature.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="assumption-tests-precede-build" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each candidate solution MUST identify its top-3 risky assumptions and run cheap tests on them before any production build.</statement>
      <rationale source="Teresa Torres — Continuous Discovery Habits (2021)">Building on untested assumptions is the dominant cause of low-impact features; assumption tests are the cheapest filter.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-feature-without-opportunity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Features without a corresponding opportunity in the OST MUST be deferred; 'leadership wants this' is not an opportunity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Marty Cagan — Empowered (2020)">Top-down feature insertion bypasses discovery and is the leading cause of shipped-but-unused features; the OST link is the structural gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
