<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="continuous-discovery-habits Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for continuous-discovery-habits. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Classify every OST node as one of: outcome, opportunity, solution, or assumption_test. Reject any node that doesn't fit cleanly into one type and re-prompt for the correct classification.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixed-type nodes (opportunity disguised as solution) cause the team to build solutions to problems nobody actually has. Strict classification at intake prevents this.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reject inputs phrased as features ("add filter X", "redesign onboarding"). Re-prompt for the underlying customer need. Never add a solution node to the OST without a parent opportunity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Feature requests are hypotheses about solutions, not observed customer needs. The OST forces the team to identify the need before evaluating solutions, which improves outcome probability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score opportunities on (reach × frequency × severity × addressability), 1–5 each. Emit numeric scores and surface week-over-week deltas. Never score on gut feel.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Gut-feel prioritization produces roadmaps that bias toward vocal stakeholders. Numeric scoring with consistent dimensions makes the reasoning auditable and improvable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap visible opportunities per Outcome at 7 ± 2. Archive overflow to parked/. Larger trees become invisible and stop driving decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Miller's Law: working memory holds 7 ± 2 items. OSTs with 30+ opportunities cause stakeholders to skip the tree entirely, defeating the purpose of the structure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every opportunity selected for build must spawn at least one falsifiable assumption test from: smoke test, fake door, prototype, Wizard of Oz, or concierge. "Ship and measure" is not a test.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Shipping without a pre-specified falsifiable test converts learning into luck. The test menu provides concrete low-cost options that generate evidence before a full build commitment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never declare "validated." Use "tested" with explicit pass/fail criteria and a signal count (n_signals). Require n_signals &gt;= 5 for any claim of pattern recognition.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">"Validated" is a banned word in Torres' framework. It implies certainty that a test cannot provide. "Tested" with explicit criteria is honest and actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tie discovery to delivery in tooling: opp_id in PR titles, in SDD spec front-matter, in commit trailers. Block PRs that touch specs without an opp_id reference.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without tooling linkage, discovery and delivery decouple silently. The opp_id convention makes the learning loop visible in the delivery record.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Route via intake-classifier (haiku) before escalating to opus. Only trio deliberation warrants opus; classification is deterministic and cheap.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Running opus on every intake item is 10x the cost with no quality improvement for classification. The model tier should match the reasoning complexity of the task.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
