<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-ost-model" title="Opportunity Solution Tree and Weekly Discovery Cadence">
  <summary>Teresa Torres' OST structure, node classification rules, opportunity scoring model, weekly cadence, and anti-patterns to avoid.</summary>

  <section title="OST Node Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every OST node as one of: outcome, opportunity, solution, or assumption_test. Reject any node that doesn't fit cleanly into one type and re-prompt for the correct classification.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixed-type nodes (opportunity disguised as solution) cause the team to build solutions to problems nobody actually has. Strict classification at intake prevents this.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Reject inputs phrased as features ("add filter X", "redesign onboarding"). Re-prompt for the underlying customer need. Never add a solution node to the OST without a parent opportunity.</statement>
      <rationale>Feature requests are hypotheses about solutions, not observed customer needs. The OST forces the team to identify the need before evaluating solutions, which improves outcome probability.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Opportunity Scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score opportunities on (reach × frequency × severity × addressability), 1–5 each. Emit numeric scores and surface week-over-week deltas. Never score on gut feel.</statement>
      <rationale>Gut-feel prioritization produces roadmaps that bias toward vocal stakeholders. Numeric scoring with consistent dimensions makes the reasoning auditable and improvable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Cap visible opportunities per Outcome at 7 ± 2. Archive overflow to parked/. Larger trees become invisible and stop driving decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Miller's Law: working memory holds 7 ± 2 items. OSTs with 30+ opportunities cause stakeholders to skip the tree entirely, defeating the purpose of the structure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Assumption Testing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every opportunity selected for build must spawn at least one falsifiable assumption test from: smoke test, fake door, prototype, Wizard of Oz, or concierge. "Ship and measure" is not a test.</statement>
      <rationale>Shipping without a pre-specified falsifiable test converts learning into luck. The test menu provides concrete low-cost options that generate evidence before a full build commitment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Never declare "validated." Use "tested" with explicit pass/fail criteria and a signal count (n_signals). Require n_signals &gt;= 5 for any claim of pattern recognition.</statement>
      <rationale>"Validated" is a banned word in Torres' framework. It implies certainty that a test cannot provide. "Tested" with explicit criteria is honest and actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Weekly Cadence">
    <p>Monday: review customer feedback queue. Tuesday: customer interview (30 min). Wednesday: analyze interview + behavioral data. Thursday: team sync, share insights. Friday: plan next week's discovery. Discovery capacity target: 15–20% of team capacity. Alert if below 10% for two consecutive weeks.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Tie discovery to delivery in tooling: opp_id in PR titles, in SDD spec front-matter, in commit trailers. Block PRs that touch specs without an opp_id reference.</statement>
      <rationale>Without tooling linkage, discovery and delivery decouple silently. The opp_id convention makes the learning loop visible in the delivery record.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Discovery as one-time project kickoff: interviews only when building new features.</description>
      <reason>One-time discovery produces a roadmap calibrated to a single point in time. Weekly cadence keeps calibration continuous as customer behavior and market evolve.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>PM does all discovery alone; Design and Tech leads don't attend interviews.</description>
      <reason>Trio dilution causes Design and Tech to lose customer intuition. OST scoring anchors on PM bias rather than cross-functional perspective. Rotate which Lead reviews synthesis each week.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>OST rot: opportunities accumulate because agents add fast but humans prune slow.</description>
      <reason>Without a monthly archival pass, the tree becomes unsearchable in ~8 weeks. Schedule a monthly kill-list pass as mandatory, not optional.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/ost-schema.json">OST node schema: type, parent, evidence, score, status, linked_specs</reference>
  <reference path="templates/spec-opp-link.yml">GitHub Actions check blocking PRs without opp_id in SDD spec</reference>
</text>
