<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="continuous-discovery-habits Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for continuous-discovery-habits as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Discovery as one-time project kickoff: interviews only when building new features.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>One-time discovery produces a roadmap calibrated to a single point in time. Weekly cadence keeps calibration continuous as customer behavior and market evolve.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>PM does all discovery alone; Design and Tech leads don't attend interviews.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Trio dilution causes Design and Tech to lose customer intuition. OST scoring anchors on PM bias rather than cross-functional perspective. Rotate which Lead reviews synthesis each week.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>OST rot: opportunities accumulate because agents add fast but humans prune slow.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a monthly archival pass, the tree becomes unsearchable in ~8 weeks. Schedule a monthly kill-list pass as mandatory, not optional.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Intake-classifier passing "add filter X" through without explicit few-shot rejection examples.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Provide at least 10 few-shot rejections of solution-phrased requests in the classifier prompt. Without examples, the classifier will accept solution framing at the same rate as humans do without training.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>OST-curator aggressively deduping and merging opportunities that cross different Outcomes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require human review on any merge that crosses Outcome boundaries. Cross-Outcome merges lose the linkage between an opportunity and its parent Outcome metric.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Opportunity-scorer hallucinating reach numbers when analytics fetch fails.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require a fetched_at timestamp and source URL in every score row. Reject scores without provenance rather than proceeding with fabricated numbers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Trio-deliberation agent rubber-stamping the highest-scoring opportunity every run.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force the agent to nominate a devil's-advocate alternative on every run. Without this, the deliberation reduces to a score-sorter rather than a reasoning process.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Outcome-tracker declaring improvement on noisy daily metrics after a single positive day.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require a 2-week rolling window minimum before any Outcome status change. Single-day signals are noise at standard metric variance levels.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
