<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-iot-vui-patterns" title="VUI + IoT — Command Patterns and Multi-Device Coordination">
  <summary>Command taxonomy for smart home voice control, multi-device coordination flow design, partial failure handling, and best practice rules for coherent IoT voice UX.</summary>

  <section title="Command Pattern Taxonomy">
    <list>
      <item>Direct control: single device command — "Turn off the lights" → one device, immediate execution</item>
      <item>Scene activation: named routine triggering multiple devices — "Goodnight" → lights off, thermostat set, doors locked</item>
      <item>Status query: read device state — "Is the front door locked?" → returns current state, no action</item>
      <item>Conditional: state-triggered automation — "Turn on the AC when I get home" → registers a geofence trigger</item>
      <item>Scheduled: time-triggered action — "Turn off the lights at 11 PM" → registers a timer</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Design scene names to be discoverable by voice: short, memorable, natural-language phrases that match how users talk about activities ("Movie time", "Goodnight", "I'm leaving") rather than technical labels ("Mode 3", "Preset B").</statement>
      <rationale>Scene names that match natural speech patterns are recalled and used; technical labels are forgotten and users revert to device-by-device control, defeating the purpose of scenes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Multi-Device Coordination">
    <rule>
      <statement>After a multi-device command, confirm all executed actions in a single summary response — not a separate confirmation per device. If some actions failed, report the failures explicitly in the same summary.</statement>
      <rationale>Per-device confirmations are verbose and slow; a single summary is faster and still provides the information needed to detect partial failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
User: "I'm leaving"
System executes: lock doors, lights off, thermostat set to 68F, arm security

VUI response: "Home secured. Doors locked, lights off, thermostat set to 68.
              Have a good day."

Partial failure response: "Mostly done. Doors locked and lights off, but
                          the thermostat didn't respond. Check the app."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Partial failure is reported without alarming language; the user gets actionable next step (check the app).</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never report a multi-device scene as fully complete when one or more devices failed silently. Always surface partial failures to the user.</statement>
      <rationale>Silent partial failures leave the home in an unexpected state — an armed security system with an unlocked thermostat is a minor annoyance; a silent failure to lock doors is a safety issue.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Undo and Recovery">
    <rule>
      <statement>Support "undo" for the most recent multi-device action by voice command ("Undo that" or "Never mind") within a 30-second window. After 30 seconds, provide a scene command that reverses the previous state.</statement>
      <rationale>Users issue voice commands in ambient contexts without full attention; immediate undo significantly reduces the frustration of misrecognized commands that change multiple devices.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For conditional and scheduled commands, always read back the registered automation with specifics before confirming: "Turning on the AC at 3:30 PM when you arrive home. Say 'cancel' to remove it."</statement>
      <rationale>Future-state commands are easy to misset; reading back the specifics catches time zone errors, wrong device references, and misrecognized conditions before they execute.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Device Grouping Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Group devices by room and by function — not by technical ID. Users say "the kitchen lights", not "device-group-14". Design the schema to match room names as they appear on floor plans or as users naturally refer to spaces.</statement>
      <rationale>Device naming that does not match natural spatial language requires users to remember a separate naming convention, reducing adoption and satisfaction.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
