<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-database-design" title="Notion Database Design for Agile PM">
  <summary>Projects and Tasks database schemas, relation and rollup field patterns, and formula examples for sprint metrics.</summary>

  <section title="Core Design Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a single Tasks database with Sprint as a relation field; never create a new database per sprint.</statement>
      <rationale>Per-sprint databases fragment task history and prevent cross-sprint velocity computation; a single Tasks database with a Sprint relation supports all views and rollups without data migration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep each task as a separate database page, not as a sub-bullet inside a sprint document.</statement>
      <rationale>Only database pages are queryable via the Notion API; sub-bullets cannot be filtered, sorted, or updated by agents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit database properties to 15–20 maximum; archive unused properties rather than accumulating them.</statement>
      <rationale>Complex formulas and many properties slow Notion database loading; unused properties add visual noise and agent confusion.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Tasks Database Schema">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tasks database required properties: Task (title), Status (status type — not select), Priority (select: Urgent/High/Medium/Low), Assignee (person), Project (relation), Sprint (relation), Estimate (number), Due Date (date), Tags (multi_select), Blocked By (self-relation).</statement>
      <rationale>Status type (vs select) enables Notion's built-in kanban grouping; self-relation on Blocked By enables dependency tracking without a separate database.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using select property type for Status instead of the native status type.</description>
      <reason>Select type loses Notion's built-in grouping behavior (not_started/in_progress/complete) that kanban and board views rely on.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Relations and Rollups">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use bidirectional relations between Tasks and Projects; add rollup properties on Projects for: task count, completed task count, and total estimate sum.</statement>
      <rationale>Bidirectional relations allow navigation both ways; rollups give Projects a live progress indicator without formulas that break when relations change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Projects database rollup: "Completed Tasks" — relation: Tasks, property: Status, calculation: Count values, filter: Done. This gives live completion count per project.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Useful Formulas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use formulas for derived display fields only (days until due, overdue flag, priority emoji) — never use formulas for metrics that require cross-database aggregation.</statement>
      <rationale>Notion formulas cannot aggregate across databases; cross-database metrics require relation + rollup chains, which are more reliable and auto-update.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="javascript"><![CDATA[
// Days until due
if(empty(prop("Due Date")), "No due date",
  dateBetween(prop("Due Date"), now(), "days") + " days")

// Overdue check (returns boolean)
if(empty(prop("Due Date")), false,
  and(prop("Status") != "Done", prop("Due Date") < now()))
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
