<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-views-automations" title="Notion Views and Automations">
  <summary>Board, table, timeline, and calendar view configurations; native automation patterns; Zapier/n8n integration.</summary>

  <section title="Essential Views">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create four purpose-driven views per database: Board (sprint execution, group by Status), Table (all tasks, sort by priority), Timeline (roadmap, group by Project), Calendar (deadlines, filter: Status not Done).</statement>
      <rationale>Each view serves a distinct PM function; proliferating views with overlapping purposes creates confusion about which view is authoritative.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Board view: filter Sprint = Current Sprint, group by Status, show Assignee/Priority/Estimate/Due Date properties on cards.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Creating a new view for every sprint or team member.</description>
      <reason>Views multiply without a governance policy; use filters on shared views instead of creating per-person or per-sprint views.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Native Automations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use native Notion automations only for property-triggered actions: set Completion Date when Status is Done, notify Assignee when Priority is Urgent, set Status to Backlog on page creation.</statement>
      <rationale>Native automations are limited to property triggers — they cannot run on a schedule. For time-based jobs (daily standup digest, sprint closure), use n8n, Make, or a cron-based agent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never delete sprint pages — archive them by setting a Status property to "Completed". Deleted sprint pages break any task's Sprint relation field that pointed to them.</statement>
      <rationale>Notion relation fields that point to deleted pages become null silently; rollup properties that count sprint tasks stop working. Archived pages preserve all existing relations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="External Automation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use n8n (self-hostable) or Make for time-triggered Notion workflows: daily standup digest (query tasks in sprint where Status = Blocked or In Progress → post to Slack), sprint closure (compute metrics → fill Sprint page).</statement>
      <rationale>n8n is compatible with the NERO stack and can be self-hosted; it handles the Notion API rate limit (3 req/sec) with built-in retry logic.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
