<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="work-breakdown-structure">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Hierarchical decomposition of project scope into noun-led work packages, each assignable to one owner, estimable in 8–80 hours, with 100% rule ensuring no overlap or gaps.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>wbs</tag>
      <tag>scope-management</tag>
      <tag>work-packages</tag>
      <tag>project-decomposition</tag>
      <tag>baseline</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <category>planning</category>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Work Breakdown Structure (WBS)</title>
    <summary>A hierarchical decomposition of total project scope into deliverable-oriented (noun-led) work packages. Each leaf is assignable to one owner, estimable in 8–80 hours, and produces a tangible output. The 100% rule requires every parent to equal the sum of its children with no overlap or gaps.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Without structured scope decomposition, projects face invisible scope creep, missed deliverables discovered late, and inaccurate estimates from unclear work. WBS establishes a reusable scope-baseline artefact that integrates with cost, schedule, and EVM — and gives every work item a stable ID traceable across contracts, schedules, and change requests.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Establishing a contractual scope baseline for fixed-bid or government-style work.</item>
        <item>Cost estimation for proposals where each work package needs an hours/$ line.</item>
        <item>Programs spanning multiple teams or vendors needing a single ID schema (1.2.3) for integration.</item>
        <item>Compliance or audit contexts where every deliverable must be traceable to a parent objective.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Backlog-driven product teams — the product backlog plus epics already plays the WBS role.</item>
        <item>Discovery or R&amp;D where deliverables are emergent and unknowable up front.</item>
        <item>Sub-2-week tasks — a checklist or kanban swimlane suffices.</item>
        <item>Steady-state operations work — use a service catalog, not a WBS.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Step 1: Start with Major Deliverables">
      <rule>
        <statement>Begin with noun-led major deliverables (working software, documentation, training materials, infrastructure), not activities or phases.</statement>
        <rationale>WBS shows WHAT is delivered, not HOW or WHEN. Verb-led entries (Design, Build, Test) create Gantt disguised as WBS and lose the deliverable focus.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Step 2: Decompose to Work Packages">
      <rule>
        <statement>Decompose each deliverable until every leaf satisfies all four work-package criteria: assignable to one person or team, estimable in 8–80 hours, measurable completion, and produces a tangible output.</statement>
        <rationale>The 8–80h rule prevents both over-decomposition (tasks too small to track) and under-decomposition (tasks too large to estimate reliably). It is the single most practical heuristic for stopping decomposition at the right level.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Depth maximum: 5 levels. Beyond level 5, the WBS becomes a schedule and should move to the activity list.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Step 3: Create the WBS Dictionary">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write a dictionary entry for every work package: ID, name, description (inclusions and exclusions), acceptance criteria, owner, estimate, and dependencies.</statement>
        <rationale>Without acceptance criteria in the dictionary, Definition-of-Done is ambiguous downstream. Dictionary entries dated more than 90 days are suspect and should be refreshed.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/wbs-dictionary-entry.md">WBS dictionary entry form for a single work package.</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="Step 4: Validate with the 100% Rule">
      <rule>
        <statement>At every parent node, the children must represent exactly 100% of the parent scope — no overlap, no gaps.</statement>
        <rationale>Silent 100%-rule violations leave scope holes that surface as missed deliverables late in execution. Validate explicitly at every parent; do not assume.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Development (100%) = Frontend (40%) + Backend (35%) + Integration (25%). Each child is mutually exclusive; together they cover all of development scope.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Verb-led leaf: "2.1 Design the auth flow" instead of "2.1 Auth Flow Design".</description>
        <reason>Verb-led names shift focus from deliverable to activity, making the WBS function as a Gantt rather than a scope baseline.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Baseline and Maintenance Rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Lock the WBS at level 3–4 as the scope baseline; post-baseline changes go through Change Control with a new WBS ID — never reuse or renumber removed IDs.</statement>
        <rationale>Downstream artefacts (contracts, schedules, EVM) reference WBS IDs. Renumbering destroys traceability and invalidates contract line items.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Examples and Common Antipatterns">
      <p>MVP Launch WBS (8 weeks): 1.0 Planning (define scope, timeline, resources), 2.0 Core Features (auth, dashboard, core workflow, settings), 3.0 Quality (testing, bug fixes, performance), 4.0 Launch (production deploy, monitoring, announcement). Each parent covers 100% of its domain; leaves are nouns (not verbs), each estimable in under a week.</p>
      <p>Online Course (solopreneur): 1.0 Content Creation (outline, scripts, recording, worksheets), 2.0 Platform Setup (Teachable account, course structure, payment integration), 3.0 Marketing (sales page, email sequence, social promo), 4.0 Launch (beta testers, feedback iteration, public launch). Single-owner work packages, each producing a tangible deliverable.</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Too detailed too early — decomposing to day-level tasks before scope is stable.</description>
        <reason>Early over-decomposition wastes planning effort; scope changes at the leaf level cascade into massive re-planning. Start high-level; add detail when the next planning horizon is confirmed.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Verb-based names: "2.1 Design authentication" instead of "2.1 Authentication Design".</description>
        <reason>WBS shows WHAT is delivered, not HOW. Verb-led names convert the WBS into a task list, losing the deliverable-traceability that makes WBS useful for scope control and contract management.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Missing the 100% rule — parent A has children B and C that together cover only 80% of A's scope.</description>
        <reason>The silent 20% gap becomes "out-of-scope" later, causing missed deliverables or unapproved change requests that surprise the customer.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No WBS dictionary — leaf names exist without acceptance criteria or ownership.</description>
        <reason>Without a dictionary, estimates are guesses and Definition-of-Done is negotiated at delivery time, which always favors the side that did not do the work.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating WBS as a schedule — adding start/end dates and sequencing to WBS nodes.</description>
        <reason>WBS shows WHAT, not WHEN. Mixing schedule information into the WBS entangles scope baseline with time baseline; a single schedule change forces WBS re-publication.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow and Integration">
      <p>This methodology overlaps `wbs-creation`; the difference is emphasis on the WBS as a reusable scope-baseline artefact integrated with cost, schedule, and EVM. A subagent is effective at: drafting the hierarchy from charter+requirements, mirroring leaf packages into Jira/issue-tracker as `wbs-id` labelled items, validating coverage against the requirements traceability matrix, and detecting drift when PR diffs touch areas outside the baseline. Humans approve the baseline lock and any post-baseline changes (which become CRs).</p>
      <p>Drifts into a Gantt activity list when teams treat verbs as deliverables. 100% rule violations stay invisible without explicit coverage rationale per parent. Inconsistent depth between branches makes rollups misleading. WBS dictionary is the high-value, low-completion artefact; without it estimates are guesses. Locked baselines vs reality: WBS can become fiction when scope shifts but baseline is not refreshed.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Recommended Subagent Patterns">
      <p>Decompose &lt;scope statement&gt;. Output WBS as YAML with id, name (noun), deliverable, acceptance_criteria, owner, est_hours, predecessors[]. Enforce: leaf packages 8-80h; depth &lt;= 5; include 1.0 Project Management. For every parent emit a one-line "100% coverage rationale".</p>
      <p>Cross-check this WBS against the requirements list. Output: {wbs_id: [requirement_ids]} mapping. List orphans: requirements_without_wbs[], wbs_without_requirements[].</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Tools and Services">
      <p>CLI tools include mermaid-cli for rendering WBS as graph TD or mindmap, markmap-cli to convert outline to interactive mindmap, pandoc for outline to DOCX/PDF for sponsor review, jira-cli for bulk-creating issues from WBS leaves with ID labels, gh for GitHub equivalent (leaves as issues, parent label as milestone), and dot (Graphviz) for tree visualizations from wbs.dot.</p>
      <p>Services supporting WBS include Microsoft Project / Project for the Web (SaaS with Graph API, native WBS column with rollup), Smartsheet (SaaS with REST API and hierarchy + rollup formulas), OpenProject (OSS / SaaS with REST API for free-tier WBS + Gantt), Asana with hierarchy (SaaS with REST API, Project → section → task as 3-level WBS), Notion / Coda hierarchical DB (SaaS with REST API, best for SDD repos and solo PMs), Jira Advanced Roadmaps (SaaS with REST API, Initiative → Epic → Story as proxy WBS), and WBS Schedule Pro (Desktop with strong graphical decomposition but no API).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Number nodes with stable IDs (1.2.3); never reuse a removed number — mark deprecated.</item>
        <item>Pair every leaf with acceptance criteria so downstream Definition-of-Done is unambiguous.</item>
        <item>Validate the 100% rule explicitly at every parent; do not assume.</item>
        <item>Lock the WBS at level 3–4 for the baseline; finer detail evolves through schedule and CRs.</item>
        <item>Mirror the WBS in your tracker (Jira/Linear/GitHub) so team work always rolls up to a baseline ID.</item>
        <item>Refresh the WBS dictionary at every major change; entries dated &gt;90 days are suspect.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-Agent Gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Models default to verb-led names (activity-oriented). Pin "noun-led names only" in the system prompt.</item>
        <item>Estimates produced cold are ±100% — feed analogous-project data into the prompt.</item>
        <item>LLMs over-decompose; cap depth and leaf hours explicitly in the schema.</item>
        <item>Do not let the agent renumber after baseline; downstream artefacts (contracts, schedules, EVM) reference the IDs.</item>
        <item>Agent-generated dictionaries read generic; require the agent to extract acceptance criteria from source requirements verbatim.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoints: (1) draft review, (2) 100%-rule validation per parent, (3) baseline lock with sponsor signoff, (4) any post-baseline change → goes through Change Control.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/wbs-outline.md" purpose="Hierarchical WBS template for six standard project phases (PM, Requirements, Design, Development, Testing, Deployment)."/>
      <template path="templates/wbs-dictionary-entry.md" purpose="WBS dictionary entry form: ID, parent, description, acceptance criteria, owner, estimate, dependencies, deliverable."/>
      <template path="templates/wbs-check.py" purpose="Lint script enforcing noun-led names, max depth 5, and 8–80 hours per leaf."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards/foundational/pmbok"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards/practice-standards-work-breakdown-structures"/>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Work_breakdown_structure"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
