<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Contextual Inquiry Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules anchoring the contextual-inquiry methodology, each grounded in a source.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="master-apprentice-frame" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Researcher MUST adopt master-apprentice stance: user explains the work; researcher questions to understand, never to advise. Suggestion-giving during the session is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Beyer &amp; Holtzblatt — Contextual Design">Suggesting solutions contaminates observation; master-apprentice preserves the user's actual workflow.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="observe-in-environment" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Session MUST happen in the user's environment (office, factory floor, hospital, home) — not a lab.</statement>
      <rationale source="Beyer &amp; Holtzblatt">Environment shapes workflow; lab settings strip context that produces breakdowns and workarounds.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="verbatim-quotes-with-ids" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Notes MUST capture verbatim quotes tied to participant ID + timestamp; paraphrased summaries alone are insufficient.</statement>
      <rationale source="Beyer &amp; Holtzblatt">Verbatim quotes ground later affinity diagrams + persona work; paraphrases lose nuance and inject researcher bias.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="interpretation-session-within-48h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interpretation session MUST run within 48 hours of the field session with &gt;=2 researchers.</statement>
      <rationale source="Beyer &amp; Holtzblatt">Memory decays fast; same-week interpretation captures non-verbal cues + context invisible in raw notes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="informed-consent-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Written informed consent MUST cover observation, recording, photo/screen capture, anonymisation, retention period; no session without signed consent.</statement>
      <rationale source="ESOMAR / IRB guidance">Legal + ethical baseline; missing consent invalidates the data and exposes the org.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Skip-If preconditions hold, the methodology MUST be skipped and the caller routed to the linked alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="self">Applying this machinery to the wrong workflow burns tokens without producing a usable artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
