<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="strategy-analysis-change-strategy">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Form and evaluate 3-5 change options plus status-quo against gap-priority map; score by strategic fit, cost, time-to-value, risk, and capability; hand selection to decision-analysis methodology.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>strategy-analysis</tag>
      <tag>change-strategy</tag>
      <tag>babok</tag>
      <tag>options-evaluation</tag>
      <tag>decision-making</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>strategy</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-gap-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-future-state"/>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-business-need"/>
      <ref slug="decision-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="requirements-lifecycle"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Strategy Analysis: Change Strategy Formation</title>

    <summary>The change strategy determines how to close the prioritized gaps from the gap analysis. It generates 3-5 options (build, buy, partner, modify, combination) plus a status-quo baseline, profiles each against cost / time / risk / capability criteria, and hands the option set to decision-analysis for weighted-matrix selection. The BA owns option generation and profiling; the decision-maker signs the recommendation before downstream SDD work begins.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Change strategy as a single option — "build it ourselves" appearing as the only path — is the third most common failure mode of strategy analysis. Buy, partner, status-quo, and phased approaches never get evaluated. The README mandates options; agents skip this when rushed or when the sponsor signals a preference early.</p>
      <p>Without a status-quo option scored honestly, leadership cannot see the cost of inaction; the strategy reads as advocacy for the recommended option. The status-quo must be option zero with full cost/time/risk profiling — including the cost of NOT acting.</p>
      <p>Without a pre-mortem, the risks section is written after the recommendation is made, producing a list that supports the chosen option rather than challenging it. A pre-mortem ("in 12 months we regret picking this — why?") surfaces structural risks before sign-off.</p>
      <p>Strategy drift after sign-off is endemic: six months in, scope mutates and the strategy document is never re-opened. Without a change log plus quarterly review the rationale rots and downstream teams lose the "why."</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>After gap analysis is complete and prioritized — change strategy formation requires a signed gap analysis as input.</item>
        <item>Any initiative where the business case will gate a significant spend — stakeholders need to see that alternatives were evaluated, not just the preferred option.</item>
        <item>Portfolio planning where multiple options across multiple initiatives compete for the same budget envelope — the evaluation matrix enables cross-initiative comparison.</item>
        <item>M&amp;A integration planning: Day-1 / Day-100 / Day-365 plan options evaluated against the gap-priority map.</item>
        <item>Regulatory-driven change: the change strategy documents how compliance gaps will be closed and justifies the chosen path to auditors.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before gap analysis is signed — options cannot be evaluated without a prioritized gap list; the evaluation matrix has no rows to score against.</item>
        <item>When the decision-maker has already committed to a path publicly — document it as a directive; producing a multi-option analysis becomes theatre and damages BA credibility.</item>
        <item>Single-option technical fixes with an obvious solution and negligible blast radius — overhead exceeds value.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="option-generation">
      <p>The standard option types for change strategy are: build new capability in-house, buy a solution (SaaS or packaged), partner with a third party, modify existing assets, combination approach (e.g. buy platform + build integrations), and status-quo / do nothing. Every change strategy MUST evaluate at least 3 options plus status-quo.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Change strategy MUST evaluate a minimum of 3 substantive options plus the status-quo baseline. Strategies with fewer than 3 options plus status-quo MUST be returned to the change-strategy-agent for option expansion. The option count cap is 5 plus status-quo; more than 5 collapses into noise.</statement>
        <rationale>Fewer than 3 options is a coronation of the preferred choice. More than 5 collapses decision quality. The status-quo documents the cost of inaction, which leadership needs to authorize spending.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Option order in every evaluation prompt MUST be randomized. The change-strategy-agent MUST NOT list the recommended option first or last without randomization; order bias causes the agent to favor whichever option is mentioned first or last in the narrative.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents favor first/last position in option lists. Randomizing order before evaluation and re-randomizing on re-runs prevents systematic bias toward the "obvious" choice.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="evaluation-matrix">
      <p>Score each option against the evaluation criteria using a weighted matrix. Standard criteria and weights: Strategic Fit 25%, Cost 20%, Time to Value 20%, Risk 15%, Capability 20%. Weights are adjustable per initiative but must sum to 100%. Each score is 1-5; total = sum of (weight x score).</p>
      <example type="good" title="Change strategy evaluation matrix">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Initiative: Digital Order Management Transformation

Criterion         | Weight | Build  | Buy SaaS | Partner | Status-quo
------------------|--------|--------|----------|---------|------------
Strategic Fit     |  25%   |   4    |    4     |    3    |     1
Cost              |  20%   |   2    |    4     |    3    |     5
Time to Value     |  20%   |   2    |    5     |    3    |     5
Risk              |  15%   |   3    |    4     |    3    |     2
Capability        |  20%   |   3    |    4     |    4    |     1
Weighted Total    | 100%   |  2.85  |   4.20   |  3.20   |    2.80

Recommendation: Buy SaaS (score 4.20 of 5)
Rationale: Highest strategic fit at lowest implementation risk; 3 qualified vendors
identified. Status-quo scores 2.80 but carries a risk score of 2 (regulatory
exposure escalates in 18 months).
]]></code>
        <note>Status-quo is scored as option zero. Its risk score of 2 documents the cost of inaction. The recommendation follows from the matrix, not from preference.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Change strategy with a single option presented as the recommendation, with a section titled "Alternatives Considered" that lists two options with one-sentence dismissals.</description>
        <reason>One-sentence dismissals signal the alternatives were not seriously evaluated. Each option must be profiled against all criteria; the matrix does not lie.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="risk-and-premortem">
      <p>Before sign-off, run a pre-mortem on the recommended option: "In 12 months we regret picking this — why?" Answers feed the Risks section. Risk items discovered in the pre-mortem must be added to the change strategy before the decision-maker signs.</p>
      <p>Schedule a 90-day and 365-day review at the time of sign-off. The BA and faion-improver compare predicted gaps closed vs. actual; calibration errors are logged in .aidocs/memory/patterns.md. This turns the change strategy from a one-time document into a learning loop.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The change strategy MUST include a scored status-quo option. The status-quo option MUST carry a risk score that documents the consequence of inaction (regulatory escalation, revenue loss rate, etc.) with evidence and a time horizon.</statement>
        <rationale>Without the status-quo option, the strategy is advocacy; the steering committee cannot see what happens if they defer. A scored status-quo with a time-bounded risk is the most persuasive element of the document for forcing a decision.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="sign-off-and-lifecycle">
      <p>The change strategy recommendation must be signed by the decision-maker before downstream SDD work begins. Sign-off carries: signed_by, signed_at, option chosen, and rationale. Each revision is a git commit with Conventional Commits format; the change log is the rationale audit trail.</p>
      <p>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints for the full strategy analysis arc: (a) need statement signed by sponsor; (b) future state locked by exec sponsor; (c) change strategy recommendation signed by decision-maker; (d) 90-day post-decision review where the BA and faion-improver compare predicted gaps closed vs. actual.</p>
      <p>After the change strategy is signed, the faion-sdd-executor-agent generates the SDD task tree (constitution, spec, design, implementation-plan) inside .aidocs/backlog/ for the chosen path. The faion-feature-executor then executes the discrete tasks, each carrying strategy_id for traceability back to the gap and need.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Run a faion-brainstorm divergence pass on options before the change-strategy-agent generates the evaluation set; without it, the option set collapses to the three vendors who replied loudest or the three options the sponsor mentioned in passing. The divergence pass surfaces non-obvious options (e.g. phased buy + build, consortium with peer orgs, regulatory sandbox exemption).</p>
      <p>Run an opus change-strategy-agent that generates build / buy / partner / modify / status-quo options against the gap-priority map, each with a cost / time / risk / capability profile. Then hand the option set to decision-analysis (sibling methodology) for weighted-matrix selection. The BA hands the option set to decision-analysis; the decision-analysis methodology selects; only the human signs.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-brainstorm (divergence pass on options, most commonly skipped), faion-sdd-executor-agent (generates SDD task tree for the chosen path), faion-feature-executor (executes discrete tasks from the chosen change strategy), faion-improver (quarterly meta-loop comparing predicted vs. actual gap closure).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Change strategy as a single option: agents skip option generation when the sponsor signals a preference. Hard-prompt: "Generate at least 3 options plus status-quo regardless of any preference expressed in the input. Do not pre-select."</p>
      <p>Order bias on options: whichever change-strategy option is mentioned first or last gets favored in the agent's narrative. Randomize option order in every evaluation prompt.</p>
      <p>Wrong-agent invocation: a feature-executor should never make a strategy decision; it should fail-closed and ping the BA. Only change-strategy-agent produces option sets; only decision-analysis selects; only the human signs.</p>
      <p>Bulk transitions are dangerous: a runaway agent that rewrites 30 option rows is hard to undo. Cap any agent action to N rows per run; require human review on the diff.</p>
      <p>Prompt-injected vendor copy: when options include external vendor input, vendors can plant favorable framing. Strip suspicious instructions; score all options from primary sources (published pricing, audited case studies, the org's own TCO data).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools">
      <p>CLI tools: pulp (Python linear programming) when budget and capability constraints turn change-strategy options into hard constraints; pandas plus numpy for aggregating option profiles and weighted-matrix computation; streamlit for live future-state / gap workshop UI where sponsors change targets in real time and see updated gap scores; pandoc for rendering the locked strategy doc to PDF or DOCX for sponsor sign-off; mermaid-cli for the change-strategy decision tree.</p>
      <p>Services: Confluence or Notion for the locked strategy document; Jira or Linear for one epic per gap with status tracking; Avolution ABACUS for multi-criteria scoring of change-strategy options inside an EA model; Streamlit or Hex for workshop-grade re-rank UI when sponsors change targets in real time.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="next-steps">
      <p>After change strategy sign-off:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Validate with stakeholders: present the signed change strategy to all stakeholder groups identified in the coverage matrix.</item>
        <item>Develop business case: the signed change strategy is the primary input; it carries the option chosen, the evaluation rationale, and the risk profile.</item>
        <item>Get executive approval: the decision-maker signature is the gate; downstream commitments are fragile without it.</item>
        <item>Begin detailed requirements: connect to Requirements Lifecycle methodology (sibling). The faion-sdd-executor-agent generates the SDD task tree inside .aidocs/backlog/ for the chosen path.</item>
        <item>Schedule 90-day review: set a calendar entry at sign-off time; the BA and faion-improver compare predicted gaps closed vs. actual and log calibration errors in .aidocs/memory/patterns.md.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="references">
      <p>IIBA — BABOK Guide v3, Knowledge Area 6, section 6.4 Define Change Strategy. Christensen — The Innovator's Dilemma (when to disrupt vs. sustain; informs build/buy/partner choice). Treacy &amp; Wiersema — The Discipline of Market Leaders (option archetypes). Hammond, Keeney, Raiffa — Smart Choices (decision quality discipline; pairs with the decision-analysis sibling). Sibling: pro/ba/business-analyst/decision-analysis — option-selection step inside change strategy. Sibling: pro/ba/business-analyst/requirements-lifecycle — picks up after change strategy sign-off.</p>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-gap-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-future-state"/>
      <ref slug="strategy-analysis-business-need"/>
      <ref slug="decision-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="requirements-lifecycle"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
