<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Chaos Engineering Practice for Infra Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of chaos-engineering-practice-for-infra enforces. Each rule has a statement, a rationale anchored to industry practice, and a source citation.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every experiment ships with a written hypothesis stating the expected steady-state behaviour and the predicted observable on failure.</statement>
      <rationale source="Principles of Chaos Engineering 2020">Without a hypothesis, an experiment is just sabotage; with one, the outcome teaches whether the mental model is correct.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every experiment has bounded blast radius — explicit list of affected services / users / regions — and exec sign-off for production-wide scope.</statement>
      <rationale source="Netflix Chaos Monkey postmortem 2024">Unbounded chaos is incident; bounded chaos is learning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every experiment has automated abort criteria tied to SLO thresholds; tripping the abort halts the experiment without human intervention.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS FIS abort condition docs 2026">Manual aborts are slow; automated aborts make chaos production-safe.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every learning is converted to a regression test (synthetic check, alert, or automated chaos run) so the system can never regress silently.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gremlin Chaos Maturity Model">Without conversion, learnings rot in postmortems and recur 18 months later.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Experiments run on a cadence (e.g. weekly small + quarterly GameDay), not just when incidents prompt them.</statement>
      <rationale source="Principles of Chaos Engineering 2020 — Run experiments in production">Cadence builds muscle memory across the team; one-off experiments do not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, skip this methodology and route to the adjacent one referenced in Related.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 skill-authoring conventions">A skip rule keeps the decision tree closed: every branch ends at a real rule id.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>