<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="design-doc-structure">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd-planning</domain>
    <summary>Design document structure bridging spec (what) to implementation (how) via architecture decisions, file tables, and traceability matrix from FR to AD to files.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>design-document</tag>
      <tag>architecture</tag>
      <tag>traceability</tag>
      <tag>specification</tag>
      <tag>sdd</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Design Document Structure</title>

    <summary>A design document answers "HOW are we building this?" — it bridges spec (what) and code (impl). The canonical structure is: reference docs, overview, FR/AD traceability matrix, architectural decisions (AD-X) with alternatives and consequences, file change table (CREATE/MODIFY), data models, API contracts, security, performance, testing strategy, and migration plan. Every file change must trace to an FR and an AD.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without a design document, executor agents make local decisions that break overall architecture, generate files not required by any FR, and produce API contracts that drift from spec ACs. The FR → AD traceability matrix is the quality gate: if every FR has an AD, and every file change traces to both, the implementation is complete by construction. Human reviewers need only check the AD alternatives and consequences sections — the rest is verifiable.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>After `spec.md` is approved and before writing the implementation plan</item>
        <item>Feature has non-trivial architectural decisions: schema, API contracts, auth, caching</item>
        <item>Code will be written by an agent executor — design.md is the authoritative file-creation instruction</item>
        <item>Feature spans multiple files or services requiring explicit data flow definition</item>
        <item>Security or performance concern exists — these sections create explicit review targets</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-file, single-concern changes with no architectural decisions (waste)</item>
        <item>`spec.md` is still Draft — design decisions cannot be made until requirements are stable</item>
        <item>Internal refactors with no API/schema changes — write an ADR instead</item>
        <item>Spike/research tasks: output is an ADR or updated spec, not a design doc</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="document-role-and-hierarchy">
      <p>A design document sits in the middle of the specification-to-implementation chain. Spec answers: WHAT to build and WHY. Design answers: HOW to build it. Implementation plan answers: in what ORDER, by whom.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Spec (specification): question=What to build? Audience=stakeholders, PMs. Content=requirements, AC. Output=FR-X, NFR-X.</item>
        <item>Design (design doc): question=How to build it? Audience=developers, agents. Content=architecture, APIs. Output=AD-X, file list.</item>
        <item>Impl Plan: question=In what order? Audience=developers, agents. Content=tasks, estimates. Output=TASK-XXX list.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Document Hierarchy: CONSTITUTION (project-wide) → informs SPEC (feature) → informs DESIGN (feature) → informs IMPL PLAN → TASKS</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>A design document must exist and be approved before the implementation plan is written.</statement>
        <rationale>The file change table in design.md is the input to task decomposition in the implementation plan. Without an approved design, the implementation plan has no authoritative file list, and tasks will be created for files that may not be needed.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="required-sections">
      <p>Canonical section list for design.md v2.0:</p>

      <list>
        <item>Reference Documents: links to spec, constitution, related designs</item>
        <item>Overview: 2-3 sentence technical approach summary</item>
        <item>Spec Coverage: FR-X → AD-X traceability matrix</item>
        <item>Architectural Decisions: AD-X with context, decision, rationale, alternatives, consequences</item>
        <item>File Structure: CREATE/MODIFY table with FR and AD traces per row</item>
        <item>Data Models: TypeScript types + SQL DDL (kept separate — they often diverge)</item>
        <item>API Contracts: endpoints with OpenAPI-style request/response</item>
        <item>Dependencies: packages with versions, external services</item>
        <item>Security Considerations: specific threats with mitigations</item>
        <item>Performance Considerations: strategies with targets</item>
        <item>Testing Strategy: unit, integration, E2E targets</item>
        <item>Migration Strategy: if applicable — data migration + rollback plan</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="authoring-checklist-phase-1-preparation">
      <list>
        <item>Read spec.md completely and extract all FR-X and NFR-X IDs</item>
        <item>Review constitution.md for tech stack and patterns</item>
        <item>Identify reference documents to link (spec, constitution, related designs)</item>
        <item>Confirm spec status is Approved (not Draft)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="authoring-checklist-phase-2-architecture-decisions">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Write AD-X entries before filling the file structure table — decisions should drive file layout, not the reverse.</statement>
        <rationale>When the file table is written first, decisions are reverse-engineered from assumed files. Writing ADs first ensures every file in the table exists because of a decision, not because of a pattern the agent knows.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Create at least one AD-X per 2-3 FR-X requirements</item>
        <item>For each AD-X: write Context (why decision is needed)</item>
        <item>For each AD-X: list at least 2 rejected alternatives with concrete rejection reasons</item>
        <item>For each AD-X: state Decision clearly</item>
        <item>For each AD-X: document Consequences (positive and negative)</item>
        <item>Trace each AD to FR-X / NFR-X</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="authoring-checklist-phase-3-file-structure">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every row in the file change table must have both an FR trace and an AD trace; rows with missing traces indicate gold-plating.</statement>
        <rationale>File structure tables include files the agent assumes will be needed from training patterns (index.ts barrel exports, __init__.py files) that are not required by any FR. These produce unnecessary tasks in the implementation plan.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>List all CREATE files with description, FR trace, AD trace</item>
        <item>List all MODIFY files with scope of change, FR trace, AD trace</item>
        <item>Include test file structure alongside source files</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="authoring-checklist-phase-4-data-and-api">
      <list>
        <item>Define TypeScript interfaces / Pydantic models</item>
        <item>Write SQL DDL separately from TypeScript — they often diverge</item>
        <item>Document all table relationships and indexes</item>
        <item>Document API endpoints with OpenAPI-style request/response JSON</item>
        <item>Define all error response schemas (not just happy path)</item>
        <item>Reference contracts.md for existing API patterns (do not redefine)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="authoring-checklist-phase-5-security-and-performance">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Mark security mitigations with the specific threat they address (SQL injection, CSRF, privilege escalation); generic "use HTTPS" entries provide no actionable guidance.</statement>
        <rationale>Security sections written as vague checklists are skipped during code review. Specific threat + specific mitigation creates a testable requirement that reviewers can verify in code.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Security: auth approach, input validation rules, encryption decisions</item>
        <item>Performance: caching strategy with targets, query optimization, scaling approach</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="quality-gate">
      <list>
        <item>Every FR-X from spec has at least one AD-X in design</item>
        <item>Every NFR-X addressed in security/performance sections</item>
        <item>Every file in file-structure table has FR and AD traces</item>
        <item>All API endpoints have error response schemas</item>
        <item>Data models complete (TypeScript + SQL DDL)</item>
        <item>Dependencies listed with versions</item>
        <item>Spec Coverage matrix 100% complete</item>
        <item>Status: design.md set to Review (human sets to Approved)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="traceability-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>FR-X IDs in spec are non-consecutive (FR-001, FR-003, no FR-002); agent copies them without verifying completeness.</description>
        <reason>Gaps in FR numbering propagate silently into the design traceability matrix. The coverage matrix shows FR-001 and FR-003 covered but misses FR-002 as absent. Run: grep -oP 'FR-\d+' spec.md | sort -u before starting design.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>API contracts in design.md are aspirational and not validated against AC scenarios.</description>
        <reason>An AC that requires a 422 response code may have no corresponding error schema in the design. Contract tests (Dredd) will fail. Cross-reference each AC error scenario against the API contract error responses.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="ad-x-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Alternatives Considered section lists three options that sound reasonable but were never actually evaluated.</description>
        <reason>This is the highest-hallucination-risk section of design.md. Agents produce fluent-sounding alternative evaluations from training data. Only list alternatives that were genuinely considered for this specific project. Prompt: "only list alternatives you can justify with project-specific reasons."</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Consequences section is omitted from AD-X entries.</description>
        <reason>Agents frequently skip Consequences because it requires acknowledging trade-offs. Without it, future agents or developers have no basis for understanding why a different approach wasn't chosen. Enforce via reviewer checklist.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="file-table-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>File structure table includes barrel export files, __init__.py, index.ts stubs not required by any FR.</description>
        <reason>These produce unnecessary tasks in the implementation plan that consume token budget without delivering FR value. Every file in the table must trace to an FR. Files needed only for structural reasons belong in a separate "scaffolding" note.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>File structure table becomes wrong as implementation evolves; design.md is not updated.</description>
        <reason>Agents executing tasks discover additional files needed. If design.md is not updated, it becomes misleading for subsequent tasks. Either update design.md as implementation reveals new files, or freeze it and document deviations in task summaries.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="process-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent marks design.md status as Approved after completing it.</description>
        <reason>Design status change from Review to Approved must be a human action. Agents set Draft → Review; humans set Review → Approved. Never let an agent mark its own design as Approved.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Design phase starts before spec.md is approved.</description>
        <reason>Design decisions are based on shifting requirements. When spec changes after design is started, the FR → AD coverage matrix must be rebuilt from scratch. Gate strictly on spec.md status: Approved before starting design.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>An agent generates design.md in one pass after loading spec.md and constitution.md. It derives architectural decisions (AD-X) by mapping each FR-X to one or more decisions, then fills the file structure table from those decisions. API contracts are generated from FR-X endpoint requirements. The human reviews the AD-X alternatives and consequences sections — these require domain judgment. The agent then self-validates using the design quality gate checklist before marking the document as `Review`. Human sets `Approved`.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Recommended subagent prompt pattern">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Write a design document for feature: <feature-name>.

Inputs:
- spec.md: <paste spec content>
- constitution.md relevant sections: <paste>

Instructions:
1. For each FR-X in the spec, create one or more AD-X that implement it.
2. Build the file structure table: every CREATE or MODIFY entry must trace to an FR and AD.
3. For API endpoints, use OpenAPI-style request/response documentation.
4. For each AD-X, list at least 2 rejected alternatives with concrete rejection reasons.
5. Fill security and performance sections with specific mitigations tied to FR-X.
6. Run the design quality gate checklist internally; list any failed items as Open Questions.
Status: Draft.
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Reviewer subagent checklist">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Review this design document for completeness.
Check: (1) every FR-X from spec has at least one AD-X, (2) every file in file-structure
table traces to an FR and AD, (3) all API endpoints have error response schemas,
(4) security section addresses auth and input validation.
Output: gap table only. Do not rewrite the document.
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-external-services">
      <p>Tools for validation and documentation rendering:</p>

      <commands>
        <command name="markdownlint">Validates heading structure, table format, link syntax in design.md</command>
        <command name="swagger-cli">Validates inline OpenAPI YAML blocks if extracted from design.md</command>
        <command name="vale">Prose style linting — enforces "SHALL" language in requirement statements</command>
        <command name="ripgrep">Traceability audit: rg 'FR-\d+' design.md vs rg 'FR-\d+' spec.md</command>
      </commands>

      <list>
        <item>GitHub / GitLab PR — Design doc review via PR; inline comments on specific AD-X sections</item>
        <item>Backstage TechDocs — Renders design.md as browsable technical documentation</item>
        <item>Miro / FigJam — Used for component diagram sketches referenced in design.md appendix</item>
        <item>dbdiagram.io — Data model diagrams; embed SVG export in design.md appendix</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Write AD-X entries before filling the file structure table — decisions should drive file layout, not the other way around</item>
        <item>Every rejected alternative in AD-X must state a concrete rejection reason tied to the project's constitution, NFRs, or constraints — "too complex" is not a concrete reason</item>
        <item>The file structure table is the implementation plan's predecessor: every file listed here becomes a task in the implementation plan; keep it precise</item>
        <item>Separate data models (TypeScript interface) from database schemas (SQL DDL) — they often diverge and agents conflate them</item>
        <item>Mark security mitigations with the specific threat they address (SQL injection, CSRF, privilege escalation) — generic "use HTTPS" entries provide no value</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Known limitations when using design documents:</p>

      <list>
        <item>The FR → AD-X traceability matrix requires that the spec's FR-X IDs are stable; specs revised after design is started invalidate the coverage matrix and require full re-sync</item>
        <item>File structure tables become wrong as implementation evolves — agents executing tasks may discover additional files needed; design.md must be updated or it becomes misleading</item>
        <item>API contracts in design.md are prose/JSON, not machine-validated — they can drift from actual implementation without Dredd/Pact enforcement in CI</item>
        <item>"Alternatives Considered" sections require genuine exploration; agents will generate plausible-sounding alternatives that were never actually evaluated</item>
        <item>Security and performance sections are easily written as vague checklists; without specific targets and owners, they provide no actionable guidance</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/design-template.md" purpose="Canonical design.md v2.0 template with all sections and placeholder text."/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/design-quality-gate.sh" purpose="Verify every spec FR appears in design; check file table traces to FR and AD."/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.industrialempathy.com/posts/design-docs-at-google/"/>
      <link href="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt"/>
      <link href="https://c4model.com/"/>
      <link href="https://adr.github.io/"/>
      <link href="https://swagger.io/specification/"/>
      <ref slug="design-doc-examples"/>
      <ref slug="design-doc-writing-process"/>
      <ref slug="writing-specifications"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
