<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-function-design" title="AWS Lambda Function Design">
  <summary>Handler structure rules, idempotency pattern, cold start optimization strategies, and layer management.</summary>

  <section title="Handler Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Initialize all SDK clients, database connections, and static configuration outside the handler function; keep the handler itself to business logic only.</statement>
      <rationale>Code outside the handler runs once per execution environment (cold start). Code inside the handler runs on every invocation. Since August 2025, INIT phase is billed at the same rate as invocation duration — every unnecessary re-initialization now has a direct cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
import boto3

# Initialize once outside handler
dynamodb = boto3.resource('dynamodb')
table = dynamodb.Table('my-table')

def handler(event, context):
    # Business logic only here
    if not validate(event):
        return {'statusCode': 400, 'body': 'Invalid input'}
    result = process(event, table)
    return {'statusCode': 200, 'body': result}
]]></code>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use ARM64 (Graviton2) architecture for all new Lambda functions; justify x86_64 explicitly (e.g., native x86 binary dependencies).</statement>
      <rationale>Graviton2 provides 20% lower cost per GB-second at comparable or better performance for most workloads. No code changes required for Python, Node.js, or Java runtimes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cold Start Optimization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable SnapStart for Java 11+, Python 3.12+, and .NET 8 functions to reduce cold starts by 58-94%; ensure initialization code is safe to snapshot (no unique IDs or time-sensitive data in INIT phase).</statement>
      <rationale>SnapStart restores a pre-initialized execution environment snapshot instead of running INIT from scratch. Snapshots expire after 14 days of inactivity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Provisioned Concurrency only for strict p99 latency requirements (under 100ms); cost is 3x reserved concurrency — for 50 functions × 5 provisioned, estimated $19,000/year vs $50/month without.</statement>
      <rationale>Provisioned Concurrency eliminates cold starts entirely by keeping environments warm 24/7. It is appropriate only when SnapStart does not meet latency targets and the cost is justified by SLA requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Idempotency">
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement idempotency for all Lambda functions that process business transactions; use a composite idempotency key derived from the event payload and store results with TTL.</statement>
      <rationale>Lambda can be invoked more than once for the same event due to retries. Without idempotency, duplicate charges, duplicate database inserts, or duplicate notification sends result.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Lambda Layers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use layers for shared dependencies across functions (pandas, boto3 extensions, custom utilities); limit to 5 layers per function; pin layer versions to specific ARNs in production.</statement>
      <rationale>Layers reduce deployment package size and allow dependency updates without redeploying all functions. Unpinned layers can introduce unexpected changes when a new version is published.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Initializing boto3 clients, database connections, or external API clients inside the handler function.</description>
      <reason>Connection setup runs on every invocation, multiplying latency and cost. With INIT phase billed since August 2025, functions with heavy initialization inside the handler pay double.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
