<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="dora-metrics Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for dora-metrics. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Measure all four DORA metrics as a set — throughput (Deployment Frequency + Lead Time) and stability (Change Failure Rate + MTTR) together reveal the full delivery health picture.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Optimizing only throughput metrics drives risky large batches; only stability metrics drives slow but safe delivery. Elite performers achieve high scores on all four simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track trends, not absolute values — week-over-week improvement matters more than hitting exact elite thresholds.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Teams in different domains (embedded, banking) have structural constraints that prevent elite Deployment Frequency; improvement trajectory predicts organizational outcomes better than absolute tier.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Add Reliability (SLO achievement rate) as a fifth metric alongside the four core DORA metrics.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">DORA 2025 research shows SLO achievement and error budget consumption predict organizational outcomes independently of the four delivery metrics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Monitor batch size when using AI code generation tools; expect a ~7% reduction in delivery stability with heavy AI adoption.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI-generated code encourages larger commits and pull requests, which violates the small-batch principle underlying elite DORA performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Automate metric collection from CI/CD pipelines — never rely on manual reporting.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Manual reporting introduces lag and bias; teams under pressure stop updating it. Automated collection from deployment events is the only reliable baseline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define "production deployment" precisely before collecting data: successful deploy to prod environment, not staging.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ambiguous definition inflates Deployment Frequency when staging deployments are counted. The signal must reflect real user impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mark deployments as rollback or hotfix at emit time, not retroactively, so Change Failure Rate is accurate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Retroactive classification is inconsistent across team members; the CI/CD pipeline knows at deploy time whether the trigger was a hotfix branch or rollback workflow.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Link incident records to the deployment that caused them; Mean Time to Restore without deployment linkage cannot distinguish release-caused incidents from infrastructure failures.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Only release-caused incidents contribute to Change Failure Rate. Infrastructure-only incidents belong in reliability/SLO tracking, not Change Failure Rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Export deployment events to a Prometheus-compatible endpoint or PostgreSQL from every CI/CD pipeline immediately after each successful deploy.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Post-hoc scraping of CI/CD logs is fragile; emit events at the point of deployment where all metadata (commit SHA, timestamp, is_rollback) is available.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Review DORA metrics in team retrospectives, never in performance reviews of individual engineers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Using DORA metrics to evaluate individuals causes gaming (smaller commits, avoided deployments, suppressed incident reports) that destroys the signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set weekly automated reports; alert on degradation (not on absolute low values) during the first 90 days of collection.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">First 90 days establishes baseline. Early alerting on low absolute values discourages teams before the baseline is known.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
