<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="requirements-traceability Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for requirements-traceability. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use exactly these five link roles and reject any other string at lint time: satisfies (child fulfils parent need, vertical down), derives (peer requirement logically derived from another, horizontal), implements (design/code realises a requirement, vertical down), verifies (test proves requirement satisfied, vertical up from test), conflicts (two requirements cannot both hold, horizontal — requires resolution).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a closed vocabulary the matrix becomes lossy within a quarter; humans and LLMs both conflate satisfies vs verifies vs derives causing coverage errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track three gates independently: forward (BR → TC, target ≥95%), backward (TC → BR, target 100%), horizontal consistency (zero cycles, zero unresolved conflicts). Never collapse to a single percentage — it hides the failure mode.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Forward coverage is mechanical; backward breaks when tests exist for non-functional concerns with no explicit requirement; horizontal is where consistency bugs hide.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Generate the RTM deterministically from frontmatter-typed links in source artifacts; never hand-edit the matrix file.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hand-edited matrices decay within 2-3 sprints; a generator makes the matrix a build product, not a maintenance burden.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include only artifact types where ownership changes hands: BR, SR, FR, D (design), TC (test case). UI strings, log lines, and helper code are leaves on a TC, not matrix nodes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Too-granular matrices become unreadable and mask the real traceability signal in noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Switch from a table to a graph view (DAG with role-coloured edges) when the node count exceeds 50.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">An O(n*m) cell table is unreadable beyond approximately 50 requirements; mermaid-cli renders the same data as a navigable DAG.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every proposed link must carry a verbatim quote from both source and target artifacts; reject any link where evidence cannot be quoted from both sides.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hallucinated links are the number-one LLM failure mode in traceability; quoted evidence forces real reading and blocks fabrication.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Limit each subagent to one of four jobs; agents must never touch the matrix file directly — only source artifact frontmatter: (1) propose typed links with quoted evidence and confidence, (2) detect orphans (no parent or no child), (3) detect cycles and horizontal conflicts, (4) impact analysis on a change request.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixing jobs produces runaway agents that bulk-modify the matrix; separating them enables human review of each pass's diff before regeneration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap any agent run at 20 link edits; require human review of the diff before the generator regenerates the matrix. Lock the source set with a git SHA at run start; reject the run if the SHA moves before merge.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Bulk-operation runaway and stale corpus errors are the top failure modes; capping scope and locking baseline prevent silent data loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track three gates independently and never collapse to a single percentage. Forward coverage (BR → TC): target ≥95%, measured as (tested requirements / total requirements). Backward coverage (TC → BR): target 100%, measured as (linked tests / total tests). Horizontal consistency: target zero unresolved conflicts and zero cycles in derived/relates links.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Collapsing to a single percentage hides failure modes. Forward coverage is mechanical; backward breaks when tests exist for non-functional concerns with no explicit requirement; horizontal is where consistency bugs hide.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include only artifact types where ownership changes hands: BR (Business Requirement), SR (Stakeholder Requirement), FR (Functional Requirement), D (Design), TC (Test Case). UI strings, log lines, and helper code are leaves on a TC, not matrix nodes. Aim for 20-100 nodes in the matrix; above 50 nodes, switch to a graph view (DAG with role-coloured edges) rather than a table.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Too-granular matrices become unreadable and mask the real traceability signal in noise. Too-coarse and you lose linkage precision. An O(n*m) cell table is unreadable beyond ~50 requirements; mermaid-cli renders the same data as a navigable DAG.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
