<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-link-model" title="Requirements Traceability — Link Model and Coverage Gates">
  <summary>Five typed link roles, three coverage directions with separate gates, granularity rules, and when to switch from table to graph view.</summary>

  <section title="Five Link Roles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use exactly these five link roles and reject any other string at lint time: satisfies (child fulfils parent need, vertical down), derives (peer requirement logically derived from another, horizontal), implements (design/code realises a requirement, vertical down), verifies (test proves requirement satisfied, vertical up from test), conflicts (two requirements cannot both hold, horizontal — requires resolution).</statement>
      <rationale>Without a closed vocabulary the matrix becomes lossy within a quarter; humans and LLMs both conflate satisfies vs verifies vs derives causing coverage errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Three Coverage Gates">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track three gates independently: forward (BR → TC, target ≥ 95%), backward (TC → BR, target 100%), horizontal consistency (zero cycles, zero unresolved conflicts). Never collapse to a single percentage — it hides the failure mode.</statement>
      <rationale>Forward coverage is mechanical; backward breaks when tests exist for non-functional concerns with no explicit requirement; horizontal is where consistency bugs hide.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate the RTM deterministically from frontmatter-typed links in source artifacts; never hand-edit the matrix file.</statement>
      <rationale>Hand-edited matrices decay within 2-3 sprints; a generator makes the matrix a build product, not a maintenance burden.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Granularity and Node Set">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include only artifact types where ownership changes hands: BR, SR, FR, D (design), TC (test case). UI strings, log lines, and helper code are leaves on a TC, not matrix nodes.</statement>
      <rationale>Too-granular matrices become unreadable and mask the real traceability signal in noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Switch from a table to a graph view (DAG with role-coloured edges) when the node count exceeds 50.</statement>
      <rationale>An O(n*m) cell table is unreadable beyond approximately 50 requirements; mermaid-cli renders the same data as a navigable DAG.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Evidence Requirement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every proposed link must carry a verbatim quote from both source and target artifacts; reject any link where evidence cannot be quoted from both sides.</statement>
      <rationale>Hallucinated links are the number-one LLM failure mode in traceability; quoted evidence forces real reading and blocks fabrication.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>100% forward coverage achieved with one tautological test per requirement.</description>
      <reason>Coverage metric gaming; pair with AC-density, mutation testing, or independent reviewer sampling.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Horizontal trace blindness — only vertical links (forward/backward) are tracked.</description>
      <reason>The horizontal axis (derives, conflicts) is where consistency bugs hide and is rarely matrixed by default.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Baselining an RTM during volatile discovery.</description>
      <reason>Formal baselines imply a contract; baselining in flux is theatre and creates change-control overhead for items that should still be under discovery.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/rtm-template.md">RTM table with forward, backward, and orphan coverage sections</reference>
  <reference path="templates/rtm_min.py">Minimum-viable generator and pre-commit hook configuration</reference>
</text>
