<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="requirements-traceability Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for requirements-traceability as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>100% forward coverage achieved with one tautological test per requirement.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Coverage metric gaming; pair with AC-density, mutation testing, or independent reviewer sampling. A tautological test is one that passes automatically by design, offering no real validation of the requirement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Horizontal trace blindness — only vertical links (forward/backward) are tracked.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The horizontal axis (derives, conflicts) is where consistency bugs hide and is rarely matrixed by default. Missing horizontal links means derived requirements can diverge silently from parent requirements.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Baselining an RTM during volatile discovery.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Formal baselines imply a contract; baselining in flux is theatre and creates change-control overhead for items that should still be under discovery. Baseline only after Approved state.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Hand-edited matrix maintained as a spreadsheet instead of generated from source frontmatter.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hand-edited matrices decay within 2-3 sprints; a generator makes the matrix a build product, not a maintenance burden. Every manual update is an opportunity for drift.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Hallucinated links — agent proposes a link but cannot quote evidence from both artifacts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require verbatim quote from source AND target; auto-reject confidence below 0.9; never accept a link the model proposes but cannot quote.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Role conflation — agent confuses satisfies with verifies or derives.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Restate the full five-role vocabulary in the system prompt every turn; do not rely on the model retaining it across turns.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Forward bias — agent readily generates BR → FR links and misses TC → REQ (backward) and FR ↔ FR (horizontal).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run three separate passes, one per direction; combine results before human review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Bulk operation runaway — agent edits 500 links in one call with no diff review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cap any agent run at 20 link edits; require human review of the diff before the generator regenerates the matrix.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale corpus during long agent runs — links point to artifacts that changed after run start.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Lock the source set with a git SHA at run start; reject the run if the SHA moves before merge.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
