<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-metrics" title="Meta Ads Metrics: Definitions, Formulas, Benchmarks, Diagnostic Tree">
  <summary>Key Meta Ads metrics, their formulas, what they diagnose, and a decision tree for tracing high CPA to its root cause.</summary>

  <section title="Metric Hierarchy">
    <p>Metrics form a diagnostic chain: CPM reveals audience competitiveness, CTR reveals creative + audience fit, CVR reveals landing page effectiveness, CPA reveals overall acquisition efficiency, ROAS reveals revenue return.</p>
    <list>
      <item>CPM = (Spend / Impressions) × 1000 — cost to reach 1,000 people; high CPM signals competitive audience or low relevance score.</item>
      <item>CTR = (Clicks / Impressions) × 100 — percentage of people who clicked; below 0.5% indicates creative or audience mismatch.</item>
      <item>CPC = Spend / Clicks — cost per click; derivative of CPM and CTR.</item>
      <item>CVR = (Conversions / Clicks) × 100 — landing page conversion rate; below 1% indicates a landing page problem.</item>
      <item>CPA = Spend / Conversions — cost per acquisition; the primary optimization target.</item>
      <item>ROAS = Revenue / Spend — overall return; below 2x means the campaign is losing money at average margins.</item>
      <item>Frequency = Impressions / Reach — average times a person saw the ad; above 3 signals audience fatigue.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Benchmarks">
    <p>Industry-wide averages for Meta Ads across sectors. Use as orientation, not gospel — benchmarks vary by vertical, offer, and funnel stage.</p>
    <list>
      <item>CTR: below 0.5% = poor, 0.8-1.2% = average, above 1.5% = good.</item>
      <item>CVR: below 1% = poor, 2-3% = average, above 5% = good.</item>
      <item>Frequency: above 3 = high fatigue risk, 1.5-2.5 = healthy, below 1.5 = good.</item>
      <item>ROAS: below 2 = losing, 2-3 = average, above 4 = good.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Diagnostic Decision Tree">
    <rule>
      <statement>Diagnose high CPA by walking the metric chain: check CTR first, then CVR, then CPM, then frequency.</statement>
      <rationale>Each metric isolates one stage of the funnel. Jumping to creative changes when the problem is a landing page wastes production budget. The chain prevents misdiagnosis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>CPA rose from $10 to $18 over two weeks. Diagnosis via metric chain.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
High CPA?
├── CTR stable at 1.2%  → creative is not the issue
├── CVR dropped 4% → 2.5%  → landing page problem
├── CPM stable  → audience is not the issue
└── Frequency rose 1.8 → 3.2  → audience fatigue, secondary issue

Actions:
1. A/B test landing page (primary fix)
2. Expand audience or add new lookalike (secondary fix)
3. Refresh creative to reduce frequency impact
4. Exclude recent converters
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Changing the creative when CVR is the low metric.</description>
      <reason>CTR is a creative metric; CVR is a landing page metric. Producing new ads when the click-to-conversion rate is broken wastes creative budget and delays the actual fix.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Column Presets">
    <p>Create four saved column presets in Ads Manager: Overview (spend, impressions, reach, frequency, CTR, CPA, ROAS), Prospecting (CTR, CPC, CPA, CVR), Retargeting (ROAS, CVR, frequency), Creative Testing (CTR, 3-second video view rate, thumb-stop rate, cost per result).</p>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-reporting-workflow.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/weekly-report.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
