<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-reporting-workflow" title="Reporting Cadence, Breakdowns, and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Daily, weekly, and monthly reporting cadence; breakdown analysis to find segment winners; custom report types; and antipatterns to avoid.</summary>

  <section title="Reporting Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Check spend pacing and errors daily; run full performance analysis weekly; review trends and reallocate budget monthly.</statement>
      <rationale>Daily checking of full metrics is noise — algorithmic variance within a day can show apparent swings that average out over a week. Weekly analysis has enough data for decisions. Monthly reviews catch slow-moving trends that weekly snapshots miss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Daily (5 min): spend pacing vs. budget, delivery errors, any metric changes over 30%.</item>
      <item>Weekly (30-60 min): full metric review, breakdown analysis, optimization decisions, creative refresh planning.</item>
      <item>Monthly (90 min): ROAS/CPA trend analysis, audience performance comparison, budget reallocation, strategy adjustments.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Breakdown Analysis">
    <p>Breakdowns expose which segment of your audience or placement is driving performance. Key dimensions: Age, Gender, Placement (Feed/Stories/Reels/Audience Network), Platform (Facebook/Instagram), Device (mobile/desktop), Time of day, Region.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>After identifying a breakdown winner, create a dedicated campaign or ad set for that segment rather than relying on the algorithm to favor it.</statement>
      <rationale>Meta's algorithm will spend across the full audience even when one segment converts 3× better. Isolating the winner gives it dedicated budget and prevents the budget being diluted into lower-performing segments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Instagram Stories placement converts at 2× lower CPA than Facebook Feed. Isolate and scale.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Before: One ad set, auto-placements, CPA $18 average
After: Separate ad set for Instagram Stories only, CPA $9
Result: 50% CPA reduction by isolating winning placement
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Budget Reallocation Decision">
    <rule>
      <statement>Scale campaigns beating target CPA; hold campaigns within 20% of target; test new creative or audience on campaigns above 20% over target; pause campaigns above 50% over target after a fair test period.</statement>
      <rationale>Budget reallocation is the primary lever for improving account efficiency without changing the product or offer. Clear numeric thresholds prevent emotional decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running weekly analysis on vanity metrics (likes, reach, impressions).</description>
      <reason>Vanity metrics do not correlate with revenue. Optimizing for reach at the expense of CPA produces popular ads that lose money.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Comparing performance across periods with different external conditions (holidays, launches, seasonality).</description>
      <reason>A 30% CPA increase week-over-week may be a Black Friday effect, not a campaign issue. Compare same-day-of-week, same-week-of-year, or use a holdout cell to isolate platform effects.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Producing a report with no action items.</description>
      <reason>A report without decisions is overhead. Every weekly analysis must produce at least one concrete action: scale, pause, test new creative, refresh audience.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-metrics.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/weekly-report.md"/>
    <link path="templates/creative-analysis.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
