<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ads-meta-reporting Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ads-meta-reporting as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Changing the creative when CVR is the low metric.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>CTR is a creative metric; CVR is a landing page metric. Producing new ads when the click-to-conversion rate is broken wastes creative budget and delays the actual fix.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Running weekly analysis on vanity metrics (likes, reach, impressions).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Vanity metrics do not correlate with revenue. Optimizing for reach at the expense of CPA produces popular ads that lose money.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Comparing performance across periods with different external conditions (holidays, launches, seasonality).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A 30% CPA increase week-over-week may be a Black Friday effect, not a campaign issue. Compare same-day-of-week, same-week-of-year, or use a holdout cell to isolate platform effects.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Producing a report with no action items.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A report without decisions is overhead. Every weekly analysis must produce at least one concrete action: scale, pause, test new creative, refresh audience.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
