<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ads-retargeting">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>ppc-manager</domain>
    <summary>Full-funnel retargeting: segment visitors by intent, tailor messaging per stage, apply frequency caps, exclude recent converters. Delivers 40-70% lower CPA than cold prospecting.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>retargeting</tag>
      <tag>remarketing</tag>
      <tag>funnel</tag>
      <tag>audiences</tag>
      <tag>conversion-optimization</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Retargeting</title>
    <summary>Full-funnel retargeting strategy: segment past visitors by intent (all visitors → blog readers → product viewers → pricing viewers → cart abandoners), tailor ad messaging to each segment's stage, apply frequency caps to prevent fatigue, and always exclude recent converters from acquisition campaigns. Retargeting should be 20-30% of total ad spend and delivers 40-70% lower CPA versus cold prospecting.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>97% of website visitors leave without converting. Retargeting recovers that spend by showing relevant ads to people who already know the brand — they convert at 2-4x the rate of cold traffic. The key is segmentation: showing a brand reminder to a cart abandoner, or a broad awareness ad to a pricing-page visitor, wastes the intent signal. Messaging must match where the person is in the funnel.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Any campaign where a pixel is installed and website audience segments are large enough (1,000+).</item>
        <item>After launching prospecting campaigns to recover non-converters.</item>
        <item>Building sequential ad sequences (reminder → benefits → social proof → urgency).</item>
        <item>Upselling or cross-selling to past purchasers.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before the pixel is installed and events are verified — audiences won't populate.</item>
        <item>Audience size under 1,000 — Meta/Google will throttle delivery; build up traffic first.</item>
        <item>When ad fatigue is already high (frequency &gt;5 and CTR declining) — pause and refresh creative.</item>
        <item>For purely brand-awareness campaigns with no conversion goal — retargeting requires a defined conversion event.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Tracking Prerequisites">
      <rule>
        <statement>Install and verify all platform pixels before building retargeting audiences; audiences require at least 1,000 members to serve on Meta.</statement>
        <rationale>Pixel events populate retroactively only from installation date. Starting campaigns before pixel installation means waiting months for audiences to build. Verifying events in advance prevents silent failures where audiences appear populated but track wrong users.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Standard events to fire for retargeting: PageView (all pages), ViewContent (product/feature pages), InitiateCheckout or AddPaymentInfo (checkout funnel), Purchase or Lead (conversion events), custom events for scroll depth, video views, form starts.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Meta: Meta Pixel plus Conversions API (CAPI) for server-side reliability.</item>
        <item>Google: Google Tag plus Remarketing tag plus conversion tracking.</item>
        <item>LinkedIn: LinkedIn Insight Tag.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Audience Segments by Intent">
      <p>Segment visitors by behavioral signals that indicate where they are in the decision process. Higher intent = shorter window = higher budget allocation per person reached.</p>
      <list>
        <item>All visitors (180 days): low intent, broad reach. Message: brand reminder, value proposition.</item>
        <item>Blog readers (60 days): low-medium intent. Message: related content, expertise signals.</item>
        <item>Product/feature page viewers (30 days): medium intent. Message: product benefits, demo offer.</item>
        <item>Pricing page viewers (14 days): high intent. Message: objection handling, comparison, discount.</item>
        <item>Cart abandoners / checkout starters (7 days): very high intent. Message: urgency, free shipping, limited offer.</item>
        <item>Past customers (180 days): warm — upsell or cross-sell. Message: new products, loyalty offer, upgrade.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Each higher-intent segment should exclude all lower-intent segments from the same person to prevent duplicate targeting and budget waste.</statement>
        <rationale>A pricing-page visitor is also an all-visitor. Without exclusion they appear in both ad sets and receive both messages, receiving duplicate impressions and consuming double the frequency budget.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Budget Allocation">
      <p>Retargeting should represent 20-30% of total ad spend. Budget scales with audience size: under 1,000 users → $5-10/day; 1,000-5,000 → $10-25/day; 5,000-20,000 → $25-50/day; 20,000+ → $50-100/day. Higher intent = higher CPA tolerance because conversion probability is higher.</p>
      <p>Performance benchmarks versus cold prospecting: CTR 2-3x higher, CVR 2-4x higher, CPA 40-70% lower, ROAS 2-4x higher.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Segment-to-Message Mapping">
      <rule>
        <statement>Match ad message to the segment's decision stage; do not show the same ad to all retargeting audiences.</statement>
        <rationale>A cart abandoner who is 10 minutes from converting needs urgency and a discount; showing them a brand awareness ad resets the conversation and loses the sale. Message relevance to intent stage is the primary lever that makes retargeting outperform cold traffic.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Message progression from low to high intent — each message addresses the specific friction at that stage.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
All visitors (awareness):
"Still thinking about [solving problem]?
Here's why [Product] might be the answer. → Learn More"

Product viewers (consideration):
"[Product] helps [audience] achieve [outcome].
See how teams like yours use it. → Watch Demo"

Pricing viewers (high intent):
"Ready to get started?
Use code WELCOME for 20% off your first month. → Start Free Trial"

Cart abandoners (urgent):
"You left something behind!
Complete your order and get free shipping today. → Complete Order"
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="Sequential Retargeting">
      <p>Sequential retargeting shows different ads to the same person over a defined time window, telling a story across multiple touchpoints. This counters the diminishing returns of repeatedly showing the same ad.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Day 1-3: Reminder — what they viewed, product/feature in focus.</item>
        <item>Day 4-7: Benefits — what they are missing, value proposition reinforcement.</item>
        <item>Day 8-14: Social proof — testimonials, case studies, user numbers.</item>
        <item>Day 14+: Urgency — last chance, discount, expiring offer.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Frequency Caps">
      <rule>
        <statement>Set frequency caps: 3 per week for all-visitor segments, 5 per week for high-intent segments, up to 7 per week for cart abandoners in the first week only.</statement>
        <rationale>Frequency above 5 for warm audiences produces negative ad experiences (reported ads, hides, unfollows) and elevates CPM without increasing conversion probability. Cart abandoners tolerate slightly higher frequency in the first week before the intent window closes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Fatigue signals: CTR declining week-over-week, frequency above 5, negative feedback increasing. When fatigue appears: refresh creative (new hook/visual) rather than expanding audience — the issue is creative, not audience fit.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Exclusion Windows">
      <rule>
        <statement>Exclude purchasers for 30-90 days from acquisition campaigns; re-engage them with upsell messaging after the exclusion window.</statement>
        <rationale>Showing acquisition ads to recent purchasers generates negative sentiment (they just bought and are now being sold to again) and inflates conversion metrics with zero net-new customer value.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running retargeting for only cart abandoners and ignoring the rest of the funnel.</description>
        <reason>Full-funnel retargeting captures the majority of non-converting visitors at every intent level. Cart abandoners represent less than 5% of traffic; building retargeting only for them ignores 95% of the recoverable opportunity.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Integration &amp; Automation">
      <p>Standing up multi-platform retargeting (Meta + Google + LinkedIn) from a single source-of-truth event spec. Maintain segmented retargeting audiences (visitors → product viewers → cart abandoners) and rotate creative on a schedule to avoid fatigue.</p>
      <p>Auto-pause retargeting ad sets when frequency exceeds caps or CTR drops a configured threshold. Manage sequential retargeting playbooks (Day 1-3 reminder → Day 4-7 benefit → Day 8-14 social proof → Day 14+ urgency) driven by audience-membership windows.</p>
      <p>Reconcile pixel data with server-side CAPI / Enhanced Conversions to recover post-iOS losses. The retargeting agent owns three loops: (1) event-spec sync — reads a YAML/JSON event taxonomy and verifies pixel + CAPI fire on each route via headless Playwright; (2) audience builder — reads a segment matrix and upserts platform audiences with deterministic naming; (3) campaign runtime — monitors frequency, CTR decay, and exclusion drift, pausing or rotating creative when thresholds trip.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Known Limitations &amp; Gotchas">
      <p>Pixel-only retargeting on iOS Safari/14.5+ ATT loses 40-70% of audience. Without CAPI, agent will report shrinking audience sizes month over month with no obvious cause.</p>
      <p>Frequency caps in Meta apply per ad set, not per user across the campaign — naive agent setup leads to one user seeing 5 ad sets × 3/week = 15 impressions.</p>
      <p>Visitors last 180 days auto-decays daily. Audience sizes look smaller on Mondays after weekend visit drops; agent alerts on size drops will false-positive.</p>
      <p>Cross-domain tracking (subdomain → main, app → web) requires explicit pixel config; missing it splits retargeting pools.</p>
      <p>GDPR / ePrivacy: EU/UK users without consent must be excluded; if Consent Mode v2 not wired, agent uploading email lists violates lawful basis.</p>
      <p>Meta's frequency field is over a 7-day rolling window, not lifetime. Agents that compare lifetime frequency to a 7-day cap will pause everything.</p>
      <p>Cart abandoner audiences need time_window of 1-7 days for urgency, but Meta defaults new audiences to 30 days. Agent must explicitly set retention_days.</p>
      <p>Customer Match in Google Ads needs greater than or equal to 1000 matched users to activate; smaller lists upload OK but never serve. Agent must check match_rate after upload.</p>
      <p>LinkedIn Matched Audience refresh is async with no callback; agent should poll status, not assume immediate availability.</p>
      <p>iOS users may show in audience size but never receive impressions. Do not tune frequency caps based on audience size alone — use delivery insights.</p>
      <p>Sequential retargeting requires audience exclusions across stages (Day 4-7 ad set excludes Day 1-3 audience). Easy to break when cloning campaigns; agent must verify exclusion graph after any campaign duplication.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices for Retargeting">
      <p>Adopt one event spec (Segment-style) and fan out to Meta + Google + LinkedIn from the same payload. Drift across platforms is the #1 retargeting bug.</p>
      <p>Always pair pixel + CAPI with event_id. Without it, dedupe fails and ROAS attribution is double-counted.</p>
      <p>Frequency caps belong at the campaign level, not ad set, on Meta where Reach &amp; Frequency objective allows it. Always exclude purchasers (90-180d window) at the campaign level. Codify the exclusion audience IDs in a registry; agents must verify the exclusion is attached after every save.</p>
      <p>Refresh creative every 14-21 days. Use a creative queue table (status: approved / live / retired) the agent can read. Run retargeting at 20-30% of total spend. Higher means acquisition starves; lower means leaving warm leads on the table.</p>
      <p>Need approximately 10k monthly visitors before retargeting moves the needle; below that, allocate 100% to acquisition. Long sales cycles (6+ months B2B enterprise): retargeting fatigue beats benefit; better off using account-based outreach.</p>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/retargeting-audiences.md" purpose="Full audience setup table (website, engagement, customer, exclusions)."/>
      <template path="templates/retargeting-campaign-structure.md" purpose="Campaign/ad-set structure for 3-tier funnel retargeting."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="ads-meta-reporting"/>
      <ref slug="ads-meta-targeting"/>
      <link href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/marketing-api/conversions-api"/>
      <link href="https://www.facebook.com/business/help/1474662202748341"/>
      <link href="https://support.google.com/google-ads/answer/2453998"/>
      <link href="https://support.google.com/google-ads/answer/9888656"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/linkedin/marketing/integrations/ads-reporting/matched-audiences"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
