<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="dora-metrics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>devops-engineer</domain>
    <summary>DORA metrics measure delivery performance: Deployment Frequency, Lead Time, Change Failure Rate, MTTR, Reliability. Elite teams deploy 973x more frequently and recover 6570x faster.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>dora</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>software-delivery</tag>
      <tag>performance-measurement</tag>
      <tag>deployment-frequency</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>DORA Metrics</title>

    <summary>Five DORA metrics measure software delivery performance: Deployment Frequency, Lead Time for Changes, Change Failure Rate, Time to Restore Service (MTTR), and Reliability (SLO compliance). Elite teams deploy 973x more frequently and recover 6570x faster than low performers. Measure all five together — high frequency with high CFR signals process problems, not success.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>DORA research proved throughput and stability are not a trade-off: elite teams excel at both. Tracking these metrics exposes bottlenecks (long PR review time, flaky tests, manual approvals) and creates a feedback loop for continuous improvement. Used punitively, they backfire — teams game metrics instead of improving systems.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Establishing baseline software delivery performance for a team or service</item>
        <item>Identifying delivery bottlenecks (where does lead time accumulate?)</item>
        <item>Evaluating impact of process changes (did trunk-based dev improve deploy frequency?)</item>
        <item>Building engineering dashboards for leadership aligned to business outcomes</item>
        <item>Assessing AI tooling adoption impact on delivery stability (2025: AI improves throughput but increases CFR)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Individual performance reviews — DORA measures team/system outcomes, not individuals</item>
        <item>Comparing teams without context — team size, domain complexity, and tech debt differ</item>
        <item>Single-metric focus — optimize one metric without watching others (e.g., deploy frequency up but CFR up too)</item>
        <item>Fewer than 30 days of data — baselines are meaningless without sufficient history</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="metric-overview">
      <p>DORA metrics measure software delivery performance across two dimensions: throughput (how fast) and stability (how safe). Elite teams deploy 973x more frequently and recover 6570x faster than low performers. High throughput and high stability are not a trade-off — elite teams achieve both simultaneously.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure all five metrics together. Never optimize one in isolation: high deployment frequency with rising CFR signals a process problem, not improvement.</statement>
        <rationale>DORA research shows that teams gaming single metrics (e.g., deploying more often without fixing quality) regress on stability. The five metrics form an interdependent system.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="deployment-frequency">
      <p>How often code is successfully deployed to production. Measures throughput.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Elite: multiple times per day (on-demand)</item>
        <item>High: weekly to monthly</item>
        <item>Medium: monthly to 6 months</item>
        <item>Low: less than once every 6 months</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure production deployments only. Do not count deploys to dev/staging environments.</statement>
        <rationale>Staging deployments are not customer-impacting. Mixing them inflates the metric and masks the actual delivery frequency visible to users.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="lead-time-for-changes">
      <p>Median time from a code commit being merged to that commit running in production. Measures throughput.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Elite: less than 1 hour</item>
        <item>High: 1 day to 1 week</item>
        <item>Medium: 1 to 6 months</item>
        <item>Low: more than 6 months</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure from merge commit timestamp to production deployment timestamp. Use median, not mean — outliers from feature flags or delayed releases distort mean values.</statement>
        <rationale>Median is resistant to outliers caused by long-running feature branches or scheduled release windows that do not represent normal delivery flow.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="change-failure-rate">
      <p>Percentage of production deployments that result in a degraded service requiring remediation (hotfix, rollback, patch). Measures stability.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Elite: 0–15%</item>
        <item>High: 16–30%</item>
        <item>Medium: 31–45%</item>
        <item>Low: greater than 45%</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Correlate incidents with deployments within a 24-hour window. A deployment that causes an incident within 24 hours counts as a failed change.</statement>
        <rationale>The 24-hour window captures both immediate failures and delayed manifestations (e.g., memory leaks) while excluding pre-existing issues unrelated to the release.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="time-to-restore-service-mttr">
      <p>Median time from when an incident starts affecting users to when the service is fully restored. Measures stability.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Elite: less than 1 hour</item>
        <item>High: less than 1 day</item>
        <item>Medium: 1 day to 1 week</item>
        <item>Low: more than 1 week</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="reliability-fifth-metric">
      <p>Added in 2023. Measures whether the team meets its own reliability targets (SLOs). Not a single number — it is a boolean: did the service meet its SLO targets this period?</p>
      <list>
        <item>Elite: consistently exceeds SLO targets</item>
        <item>High: meets SLO targets</item>
        <item>Medium: partially meets targets</item>
        <item>Low: below targets</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Define explicit SLO targets (availability, latency P99, error rate) before tracking Reliability. Without targets, the metric cannot be evaluated.</statement>
        <rationale>Reliability requires a defined threshold. Teams that have not defined SLOs cannot meaningfully track whether they are meeting them.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="data-collection-sources">
      <rule>
        <statement>Automate data collection from CI/CD pipelines, version control, and incident management. Never collect DORA metrics manually — manual data degrades within weeks as teams skip updates.</statement>
        <rationale>Manual data collection introduces selection bias (teams report favorable metrics) and sustains a maintenance burden that eventually leads to abandonment. Automated collection from event sources is authoritative and continuous.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Deployment Frequency: CI/CD pipeline success events (GitHub Actions, GitLab CI, ArgoCD PostSync hooks)</item>
        <item>Lead Time: merge commit timestamp + deployment event timestamp from VCS and CI</item>
        <item>Change Failure Rate: incident management events (PagerDuty, Opsgenie) correlated with deployment events within 24h</item>
        <item>MTTR: incident open/close timestamps from PagerDuty, Opsgenie, or ServiceNow</item>
        <item>Reliability: SLO compliance from Prometheus (availability, error rate, latency P99)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="tooling-options">
      <list>
        <item>Sleuth: purpose-built DORA tracking; connects to GitHub/GitLab, PagerDuty, Jira; best for DORA-focused teams</item>
        <item>LinearB: DORA plus engineering productivity metrics; good for teams wanting broader metrics</item>
        <item>Faros AI: custom metrics and data warehousing; best for data-driven teams building custom pipelines</item>
        <item>GitHub Insights: built-in for GitHub users; covers Deployment Frequency and Lead Time natively</item>
        <item>GitLab Value Stream Analytics: built-in for GitLab users; covers all four original DORA metrics</item>
        <item>Custom Prometheus + Grafana: full control, requires custom event tracking pipeline; best when data stays on-prem</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="minimum-viable-setup">
      <p>Start with Deployment Frequency and Lead Time — both come from CI/CD data already collected. Add CFR after 30 days once you have an incident correlation baseline. Add MTTR when incident management tooling is connected.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Wait 30 days before committing to Savings Plans or Reserved Instances based on DORA data. Wait 30 days before reporting DORA baselines to leadership.</statement>
        <rationale>Fewer than 30 days of data yields unreliable baselines. Seasonal variations, sprint cycles, and deployment windows need multiple samples to produce a representative median.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using DORA metrics for individual performance reviews or team comparison without context.</description>
        <reason>DORA measures team/system outcomes, not individual contribution. Teams with different domain complexity, technical debt, or size have incomparable baseline metrics. Punitive use causes gaming: teams split large deployments into trivial changes to inflate Deployment Frequency.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Optimizing Deployment Frequency without watching Change Failure Rate.</description>
        <reason>Deploying more often with inadequate test coverage raises CFR. High-frequency + high-CFR = more outages, not better delivery. The metrics must be tracked and improved together.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Setting targets based on industry benchmarks without establishing your own baseline first.</description>
        <reason>An organization at Low performance cannot jump to Elite. Setting unrealistic targets creates pressure to game metrics rather than improve systems. Set targets as 20-30% improvement from current baseline, not as absolute Elite thresholds.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-tooling-impact-2025">
      <p>The 2025 DORA Report found that AI adoption improves throughput metrics (faster code generation, review) but increases delivery instability (higher CFR). Teams must invest in seven capabilities to capture AI value without degrading stability:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Internal data accessible to AI systems</item>
        <item>Working in small batches</item>
        <item>Continuous integration with fast feedback</item>
        <item>Trunk-based development</item>
        <item>Comprehensive test automation</item>
        <item>Deployment automation</item>
        <item>Monitoring and observability</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="lead-time-calculator">
      <example type="good" title="Lead Time Calculator in Python">
        <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# lead_time_calculator.py — commit-to-deploy median over a period
import subprocess
from datetime import datetime

def calculate_lead_time(repo_path: str, deploy_sha: str) -> dict:
    merge_info = subprocess.run(
        ["git", "log", "-1", "--format=%H|%aI", deploy_sha],
        cwd=repo_path, capture_output=True, text=True
    )
    deploy_sha, deploy_time = merge_info.stdout.strip().split("|")
    deploy_dt = datetime.fromisoformat(deploy_time)

    first_commit = subprocess.run(
        ["git", "log", "--reverse", "--format=%H|%aI", f"{deploy_sha}~10..{deploy_sha}"],
        cwd=repo_path, capture_output=True, text=True
    )
    commits = first_commit.stdout.strip().split("\n")
    if commits and commits[0]:
        _, first_time = commits[0].split("|")
        first_dt = datetime.fromisoformat(first_time)
        lead_time = (deploy_dt - first_dt).total_seconds()
    else:
        lead_time = 0

    return {
        "deploy_sha": deploy_sha,
        "lead_time_seconds": lead_time,
        "lead_time_hours": lead_time / 3600
    }
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="change-failure-rate-calculator">
      <example type="good" title="CFR Calculator in Python">
        <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# cfr_calculator.py — correlate incidents with deployments
from datetime import datetime, timedelta
from typing import List, Dict

def calculate_cfr(
    deployments: List[Dict],
    incidents: List[Dict],
    correlation_window_hours: int = 24
) -> Dict:
    window = timedelta(hours=correlation_window_hours)
    failed_deployments = set()

    for incident in incidents:
        incident_time = datetime.fromisoformat(incident["timestamp"])
        service = incident["service"]
        for deploy in deployments:
            if deploy["service"] != service:
                continue
            deploy_time = datetime.fromisoformat(deploy["timestamp"])
            if 0 <= (incident_time - deploy_time).total_seconds() <= window.total_seconds():
                failed_deployments.add((deploy["sha"], deploy["timestamp"]))

    total = len(deployments)
    failed = len(failed_deployments)
    return {
        "total_deployments": total,
        "failed_deployments": failed,
        "change_failure_rate": (failed / total * 100) if total > 0 else 0,
    }
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="mttr-calculator">
      <example type="good" title="MTTR Calculator in Python">
        <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# mttr_calculator.py
from datetime import datetime
from typing import List, Dict
import statistics

def calculate_mttr(incidents: List[Dict]) -> Dict:
    resolution_times = []
    for incident in incidents:
        if not incident.get("resolved_at"):
            continue
        created = datetime.fromisoformat(incident["created_at"])
        resolved = datetime.fromisoformat(incident["resolved_at"])
        resolution_times.append((resolved - created).total_seconds() / 60)

    return {
        "total_incidents": len(incidents),
        "resolved_incidents": len(resolution_times),
        "mttr_minutes": statistics.mean(resolution_times) if resolution_times else 0,
        "mttr_median_minutes": statistics.median(resolution_times) if resolution_times else 0,
    }
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="promql-queries-for-dora-dashboard">
      <example type="good" title="PromQL Queries for DORA Metrics">
        <code lang="promql"><![CDATA[
# Deployment Frequency: deployments per day
sum(increase(deployment_total[1d])) by (service)

# Change Failure Rate: failed deploys / total
sum(deployment_total{status="failed"}) / sum(deployment_total) * 100

# MTTR: average incident duration in minutes
avg(incident_duration_seconds) / 60

# Reliability: 30-day availability
avg_over_time(up{job="myapp"}[30d]) * 100

# Error budget remaining (99.9% SLO)
((1 - 0.999) - (sum(rate(http_requests_total{status=~"5.."}[30d]))
  / sum(rate(http_requests_total[30d])))) / (1 - 0.999) * 100
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="github-actions-deployment-event-recording">
      <example type="good" title="Record Deployment Events in GitHub Actions">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# .github/workflows/deploy.yml
- name: Record Deployment
  if: success()
  run: |
    curl -X POST "https://metrics-api.example.com/deployments" \
      -H "Authorization: Bearer ${{ secrets.METRICS_TOKEN }}" \
      -H "Content-Type: application/json" \
      -d '{
        "service": "${{ github.repository }}",
        "commit": "${{ github.sha }}",
        "timestamp": "${{ github.event.head_commit.timestamp }}",
        "status": "success"
      }'
]]></code>
        <p>Record both success and failure events. Failure events are required for CFR calculation.</p>
      </example>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/deployment-event.json" purpose="JSON schema for deployment event records"/>
      <template path="templates/incident-event.json" purpose="JSON schema for incident event records"/>
      <template path="templates/dora-config.yaml" purpose="DORA metrics collection config (services, targets, data sources)"/>
      <template path="templates/weekly-report.md" purpose="Weekly DORA report template with all five metrics and action items"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-dora-analysis.txt" purpose="LLM prompt for analyzing DORA metric data"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
