<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-dashboard-config" title="Tool-Specific Dashboard Configuration">
  <summary>Widget configurations for Jira gadgets, Linear views, ClickUp widgets, and portfolio dashboards.</summary>

  <section title="Core Setup Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the metric schema in a config file before building widgets; validate every query manually three times with real data before scheduling automated delivery.</statement>
      <rationale>Metric definitions that change after widgets are built break all dependent dashboards simultaneously; manual validation catches JQL/filter errors before they produce misleading automated reports.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Building widgets first and defining what they measure later.</description>
      <reason>Widget reconfiguration after team adoption requires re-education and creates inconsistent historical data.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Jira Dashboard">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use these core Jira gadgets: Sprint Burndown (agile-burndown-chart), Sprint Health, Created vs Resolved (2D filter), Priority distribution (pie chart), and a Filter Results table for personal open issues.</statement>
      <rationale>These five gadgets answer the four PM questions: how is the sprint progressing, what is the quality trend, what is the workload, and what are my personal actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Linear Dashboard">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Linear's built-in Insights for cycle velocity, issue completion, bug count, and team workload — do not try to replicate these with external tools.</statement>
      <rationale>Linear computes these metrics from its internal data model; external queries miss in-progress partial completions and cycle rollover handling.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Portfolio Dashboard">
    <rule>
      <statement>Portfolio dashboards must include: status overview (all projects, health indicator), delivery confidence (on-time %), resource utilization, burnup chart (quarterly scope), and risk summary (top 5 by impact).</statement>
      <rationale>Executive stakeholders need a single screen that answers: are we on track, are resources sufficient, and what risks require escalation — without opening individual project boards.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/portfolio-dashboard.yaml">Portfolio dashboard widget layout configuration</reference>
  </section>
</text>
