<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="AWS Multi-Account Landing Zone Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules every application of `AWS Multi-Account Landing Zone` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="ou-hierarchy-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>OU hierarchy MUST include at minimum: Security, Infrastructure, Workloads (Prod / Non-Prod / Sandbox sub-OUs), Suspended. Mixed prod / non-prod in a single OU is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Landing Zone Accelerator; CIS Benchmark">Mixed OUs break SCP scoping; clear hierarchy makes guardrails crisp.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="control-tower-or-equivalent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>LZ MUST use AWS Control Tower OR a homegrown LZ Accelerator + AWS Config + GuardDuty + Security Hub + CloudTrail org-trail. Ad-hoc accounts without baseline are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Control Tower docs; AWS LZ Accelerator">Manual baselines drift; Control Tower / LZA enforces baseline on every new account.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="scp-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Org root SCP MUST deny: leave-org, disable-CloudTrail, disable-GuardDuty, modify-root, public-S3 (regulated OUs). Tested against canary OU first.</statement>
      <rationale source="CIS AWS Benchmark; AWS SCP docs">Without SCPs, compromised admin = compromised everything; SCPs are the org-level guardrail.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="identity-center-permission-sets" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Human access MUST flow through IAM Identity Center permission sets, mapped to AD / Okta groups. Per-account IAM users forbidden for humans.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Identity Center; CIS Benchmark">Per-account IAM users = key sprawl + offboarding gap; SSO permission sets centralise.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="logging-audit-accounts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dedicated `log-archive` and `audit` accounts MUST receive CloudTrail org-trail logs, Config recordings, GuardDuty findings, Security Hub aggregation. Cross-account access tightly scoped.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS LZ best practices">Co-locating logs with workloads makes log tampering trivial; isolated accounts are the auditor-friendly pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="account-vending-automated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>New account creation MUST go through automated vending (Control Tower Account Factory, Service Catalog Custom AFT, or equivalent). Console-clicked accounts forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Control Tower Account Factory; AFT docs">Manual accounts skip baseline; automated vending applies guardrails + tags + network hooks consistently.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="network-hub-pattern" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Multi-account networking MUST use Transit Gateway (or AWS Cloud WAN) hub-and-spoke from a Network account; flat per-account VPC peering forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Transit Gateway docs; LZ Accelerator">Full-mesh VPC peering scales O(n²) and breaks at ~20 accounts; TGW hub gives O(n).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>