<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-knowledge-areas" title="BABOK Six Knowledge Areas">
  <summary>Purpose, key tasks, outputs, and linked methodologies for all six BABOK Knowledge Areas.</summary>

  <section title="KA-1: Business Analysis Planning and Monitoring">
    <p>Purpose: plan how BA work will be done and track performance.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Plan BA Approach — define how BA will be performed; output: BA approach document.</item>
      <item>Plan Stakeholder Engagement — identify and plan work with stakeholders; output: stakeholder engagement approach.</item>
      <item>Plan Governance — define decision-making for requirements; output: governance approach.</item>
      <item>Plan Information Management — define how BA info is stored and accessed; output: information management approach.</item>
      <item>Identify Improvements — assess BA performance, recommend improvements.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Linked methodologies: ba-planning, stakeholder-analysis.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="KA-2: Elicitation and Collaboration">
    <p>Purpose: draw out information from stakeholders and confirm results.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Prepare for Elicitation — understand scope, select techniques; output: elicitation activity plan.</item>
      <item>Conduct Elicitation — draw out relevant information; output: elicitation results (unconfirmed).</item>
      <item>Confirm Results — verify understanding with stakeholders; output: elicitation results (confirmed).</item>
      <item>Communicate BA Information — ensure shared understanding.</item>
      <item>Manage Collaboration — encourage stakeholders to work together.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Linked methodologies: elicitation-techniques. Techniques: interviews, workshops, observation, surveys, document analysis, prototyping, brainstorming, focus groups.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="KA-3: Requirements Lifecycle Management">
    <p>Purpose: manage requirements through their full lifecycle.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Trace Requirements — ensure alignment at different levels; output: requirements (traced).</item>
      <item>Maintain Requirements — keep accurate and consistent; output: requirements (maintained).</item>
      <item>Prioritize Requirements — rank by importance; output: requirements (prioritized).</item>
      <item>Assess Changes — evaluate proposed changes; output: change assessment.</item>
      <item>Approve Requirements — obtain agreement; output: requirements (approved).</item>
    </list>
    <p>Linked methodologies: requirements-traceability, requirements-lifecycle, requirements-prioritization. Outputs: traceability matrix, requirements baseline, change impact analysis.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="KA-4: Strategy Analysis">
    <p>Purpose: understand the current state and define the change strategy to achieve the future state.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Analyze Current State — understand existing environment; output: current state description.</item>
      <item>Define Future State — define goals and objectives; output: future state description.</item>
      <item>Assess Risks — identify uncertainties; output: risk assessment results.</item>
      <item>Define Change Strategy — develop approach to achieve future state; output: change strategy.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Linked methodologies: strategy-analysis. Techniques: gap analysis, SWOT, business model canvas, capability assessment, risk analysis.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="KA-5: Requirements Analysis and Design Definition">
    <p>Purpose: structure, specify, model, verify, and validate requirements; define design options.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Specify and Model Requirements — output: requirements (specified/modeled).</item>
      <item>Verify Requirements — ensure quality standards met; output: requirements (verified).</item>
      <item>Validate Requirements — ensure alignment with business goals; output: requirements (validated).</item>
      <item>Define Requirements Architecture — ensure requirements support each other.</item>
      <item>Define Design Options — define solution approaches.</item>
      <item>Analyze Value and Recommend — assess options, recommend solution.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Linked methodologies: use-case-modeling, user-story-mapping, data-analysis, business-process-analysis, decision-analysis, interface-analysis, requirements-validation, acceptance-criteria, requirements-documentation.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="KA-6: Solution Evaluation">
    <p>Purpose: assess solution performance and the value it delivers.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Measure Solution Performance — define how performance is measured; output: performance measures.</item>
      <item>Analyze Performance Measures — examine data against expected value; output: performance analysis.</item>
      <item>Assess Solution Limitations — investigate problems and causes; output: solution limitations.</item>
      <item>Assess Enterprise Limitations — investigate enterprise factor impacts.</item>
      <item>Recommend Actions — identify actions to increase value; output: value improvement recommendations.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Linked methodologies: solution-assessment. Outputs: performance metrics, value realization report, improvement recommendations, lessons learned.</p>
  </section>
</text>
