<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="design-docs-big-tech Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for design-docs-big-tech. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always include "do nothing" as Alternative 1 in the alternatives section.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sometimes the best decision is not to build. Forcing this option ensures the author justifies why building is worth the cost and risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write in narrative prose, no bullet points, maximum 6 pages; supporting data goes in an unlimited appendix.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dense prose forces the author to synthesize; bullets permit loose thinking. Every word must carry information.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use the lightest template that fits the change scope; do not over-engineer the process.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Uber evolved from simple RFCs to tiered ERDs precisely because heavyweight process for lightweight changes slows teams without adding value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Separate the RFC (consensus-reaching) from the ADR (decision-recording); do not conflate the two jobs in one document.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">An RFC trying to reach consensus and record the decision simultaneously produces a document that does neither well. The RFC is collaborative and iterative; the ADR is the immutable record.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Match document weight to change scope; write before coding, never after.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Post-implementation documentation defeats the purpose — design docs exist to catch issues when changes are still cheap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use LLMs for initial structure, alternative brainstorming, and prose refinement; require human validation for every technical accuracy claim.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs generate plausible but technically inaccurate design docs when system-specific context is absent. Technical accuracy is the one dimension where LLM effectiveness is Low-Medium.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Limit LLM-generated alternatives to 2-3 concrete options; agents over-generate when not constrained.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">5+ alternatives overwhelm reviewers and dilute focus. The value is in comparing 2-3 realistic options, not exhaustively listing all possibilities.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
