<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-when-and-patterns" title="When to Write Design Docs and LLM Assistance Patterns">
  <summary>Decision table for when a design doc is required; LLM assistance effectiveness by task type; common mistakes; and agent-specific gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="When to Write">
    <rule>
      <statement>Match document weight to change scope; write before coding, never after.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-implementation documentation defeats the purpose — design docs exist to catch issues when changes are still cheap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Bug fix: no doc needed</item>
      <item>Small feature (1-2 days): optional 1-pager, team only</item>
      <item>Medium feature (1-2 weeks): standard design doc, team + stakeholders</item>
      <item>Large feature (1+ month): detailed RFC, cross-team review</item>
      <item>Architecture change: RFC + ADR, company-wide</item>
      <item>New service or system: full design doc, architecture review</item>
      <item>API changes affecting consumers: yes</item>
      <item>Database schema changes: yes</item>
      <item>Security-sensitive changes: yes</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM Assistance Effectiveness">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use LLMs for initial structure, alternative brainstorming, and prose refinement; require human validation for every technical accuracy claim.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs generate plausible but technically inaccurate design docs when system-specific context is absent. Technical accuracy is the one dimension where LLM effectiveness is Low-Medium.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>High LLM effectiveness: initial structure from requirements, prose refinement, alternative brainstorming</item>
      <item>Medium-High: risk identification, surface edge cases</item>
      <item>Low-Medium: technical accuracy (requires expert validation)</item>
      <item>Not applicable: organizational context, team history, stakeholder preferences, proprietary technology</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit LLM-generated alternatives to 2-3 concrete options; agents over-generate when not constrained.</statement>
      <rationale>5+ alternatives overwhelm reviewers and dilute focus. The value is in comparing 2-3 realistic options, not exhaustively listing all possibilities.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using the design doc as a spec — conflating "why/how" with "what".</description>
      <reason>Design doc answers HOW; spec answers WHAT. Mixing them produces a document that does neither well and forces readers to untangle intent from implementation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No alternatives section — only the chosen solution is documented.</description>
      <reason>Reviewers question judgment when they cannot see what was rejected. Future engineers re-litigate the decision because the reasoning is invisible.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Writing the design doc after implementation begins.</description>
      <reason>Defeats the primary purpose. Architectural issues caught post-implementation cost orders of magnitude more to fix than issues caught at the design stage.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Too many approvers — more than 10 participants.</description>
      <reason>Consensus gridlock; the review process takes longer than the implementation. Google and Amazon both observe this threshold empirically.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No "do nothing" option in alternatives.</description>
      <reason>Without the baseline, reviewers always ask "why not just leave it as is?" Include it to pre-empt the question and force the author to justify the build decision.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/prompt-design-doc.txt">LLM prompts for generating and reviewing design docs</reference>
</text>
