<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Annual Planning Process — Framework">
  <summary>Five-stage planning process: Reflect, Envision, Strategize, Plan, Execute — with cadence, priority constraints, and strategic questions.</summary>

  <section title="Process stages">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap annual priorities at exactly 3. If more than 3 priorities are proposed, refuse to proceed until one is dropped. Do not silently accept a 4th priority.</statement>
      <rationale>More than 3 annual priorities dilutes focus to the point where nothing compounds. The constraint is the mechanism that makes the plan actionable. LLMs default to 7-item lists; the cap must be enforced in prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Reflect: pull full-year metrics, identify wins/challenges/surprises, produce year-in-review with cited data</item>
      <item>Envision: write a vivid 12-month vision statement — what you will have, why it matters, what success feels like (founder writes, agent critiques)</item>
      <item>Strategize: select 3 strategic priorities; for each, answer: what is the biggest constraint on growth? what would 10x the business? what should you stop doing?</item>
      <item>Plan: break annual goals into quarterly milestones, monthly focus areas, and weekly task trees (cascade only to month — weekly/daily emerge from context)</item>
      <item>Execute: run weekly (30 min), monthly (2 hours), quarterly (half-day), and annual (1-2 days) reviews on fixed calendar dates</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Planning calendar">
    <rule>
      <statement>Schedule all four review cadences (weekly, monthly, quarterly, annual) on the calendar before the year starts. Agent holds the slot but humans must show up; agent must not skip a human review even if metrics look fine.</statement>
      <rationale>Cadence drift — monthly check-ins compressed to Slack messages, quarterly reviews skipped — is the primary cause of plans becoming irrelevant by Q2. Calendar commitment is the only reliable mechanism.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Week 1 of December: begin annual review</item>
      <item>Week 2 of December: finish review, start next-year planning</item>
      <item>Weeks 3-4 of December: finalize annual plan</item>
      <item>Week 1 of January: Q1 detailed planning</item>
      <item>End of each quarter: quarterly review</item>
      <item>First week of each month: monthly check-in</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Key results criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every key result must have: a numeric target with unit and date, a current baseline, a measurable data source available at reporting time, and a kill-switch (when do we stop this initiative?) and a leading indicator (what changes first if we are wrong?).</statement>
      <rationale>KRs without these fields cannot be scored objectively. "Improve customer experience meaningfully" is decoration. "Increase NPS from 32 to 45 by Q3, measured monthly via Delighted" is a KR.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the metric layer (which tool is the source of truth for each KR) at the start of the year. Lock definitions before Q1 starts and never silently change them mid-year.</statement>
      <rationale>Goal scoring against shifting definitions is misleading. "Customer" in January must mean the same thing in December.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/monthly-checkin.py"/>
    <link path="../ops-annual-planning-templates/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
