<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Annual Planning Process — Worked Examples">
  <summary>SaaS and info-product annual plan examples with quarterly breakdowns and goal-metric pairs.</summary>

  <section title="SaaS annual plan">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Vision: reach $100K ARR with sustainable solo operation. Annual goals: ARR $50K to $100K, customers 100 to 200, churn 5% to 3%. Quarterly breakdown: Q1 improve retention (reduce churn to 3%); Q2 double down on content marketing; Q3 launch premium tier; Q4 optimize and scale ads. Each quarter has one primary theme and 2-3 key results with numeric targets.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Info-product annual plan">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Vision: build evergreen course business with $200K revenue. Annual goals: revenue $80K to $200K, courses 1 to 3, email list 5K to 15K. Quarterly breakdown: Q1 launch course #2; Q2 build email list to 10K; Q3 launch course #3; Q4 evergreen funnel optimization. The quarterly sequence respects dependencies — list-building (Q2) before launch (Q3).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common planning mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Plan has 6 annual priorities and no "not doing this year" list.</description>
      <reason>Six priorities means nothing is prioritized. Without a stop-doing list, the founder keeps all existing commitments plus adds new ones. Compounding never happens.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Quarterly plan decomposes into daily task lists generated in January.</description>
      <reason>Daily tasks from January are stale by March. Cascade only to monthly level; weekly and daily plans emerge from current context, not annual planning.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Year-in-review contains only wins. Churned customers and missed targets are not mentioned.</description>
      <reason>Survivorship bias in annual reviews produces optimistic plans that ignore the mechanisms of past failure. Year-in-review must include lost-deal and churned-customer themes.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Annual plan has financial and product goals but no personal goals (energy, satisfaction, burnout).</description>
      <reason>Founder burnout kills the plan. A solopreneur's sustainability is a business risk, not a soft concern.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
