<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="architecture" count="64" version="3.0" generated="2026-05-25">
  <description>L2 index of methodologies in the architecture domain. The retriever reads this after picking architecture from L1 domains.xml. Entries list slug + tier + summary; open the leaf meta.json / content/*.xml for full payload.</description>
  <methodology slug="adr-for-client-arb-review-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/adr-for-client-arb-review-template">
    <summary>ADR template variant designed for client architecture-review-board (ARB) approval \u2014 names the approver up-front, captures regime constraints, redaction policy, and review-date binding.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="adr-reversibility-tagging" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/adr-reversibility-tagging">
    <summary>Tags every ADR with one-way-door vs two-way-door reversibility so review depth and approval gates match the cost of being wrong.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="adr-staleness-audit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/adr-staleness-audit">
    <summary>Quarterly audit pass that walks every accepted/proposed ADR through a 4-signal rubric (code reality match, stakeholder presence, reversal triggers fired, external context change) and moves each to accepted/superseded/deprecated/re-open.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-agent-perimeter-policy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/ai-agent-perimeter-policy">
    <summary>Translates client NDA/MSA data-handling clauses into a per-engagement AI-agent guardrail config \u2014 allowed-tools list, MCP allow-list, telemetry/log overrides, embedding-provider restrictions, audit cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="api-gateway-graphql" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/api-gateway-graphql">
    <summary>GraphQL federation via Apollo Router creates a unified supergraph from independently deployed domain subgraphs with depth/complexity limits and CI-validated composition.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="api-gateway-observability" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/api-gateway-observability">
    <summary>Three pillars at the gateway edge: Prometheus metrics, structured access logs with correlation ID, and W3C-context OpenTelemetry traces.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="api-gateway-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/api-gateway-patterns">
    <summary>Selects the gateway pattern (edge / BFF / per-service / no gateway) and the product (Kong / Traefik / Envoy / APIGW / Apollo Router) based on workload, team, and platform constraints.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="api-gateway-resilience" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/api-gateway-resilience">
    <summary>Multi-level rate limiting, circuit breakers, exponential-backoff retries with idempotency, and tiered timeouts at the gateway layer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="api-gateway-security" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/api-gateway-security">
    <summary>Layered gateway security: TLS termination at the edge, authentication (API keys, JWT, OAuth 2), authorization, secure headers, and WAF integration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="arch-health-weekly-report-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/arch-health-weekly-report-template">
    <summary>Weekly arch-health report: hot-spots, debt deltas, risk register movement, one decision-needed item.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="arch-pattern-clean" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/arch-pattern-clean">
    <summary>Dependencies point inward through concentric circles: Domain (Entities) at the center, then Application (Use Cases), then Interface Adapters, then Frameworks and Drivers at the outside.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="arch-pattern-ddd" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/arch-pattern-ddd">
    <summary>Tackles complexity in the heart of software by building a shared model between developers and domain experts using bounded contexts, aggregates, and ubiquitous language.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="arch-pattern-hexagonal" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/arch-pattern-hexagonal">
    <summary>Application core is isolated from the outside world through ports (interfaces) and adapters (implementations); both inbound and outbound concerns are pluggable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="arch-pattern-onion" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/arch-pattern-onion">
    <summary>All coupling points toward the center: Domain Model -&gt; Domain Services -&gt; Application Services -&gt; Infrastructure / UI / Tests at the outermost layer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="architect-mentoring-curriculum" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/architect-mentoring-curriculum">
    <summary>Produces a 6-month mentoring curriculum for staff engineers transitioning into architect roles.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="architect-pr-review-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/architect-pr-review-checklist">
    <summary>Tier-appropriate PR review checklist for the architectural surface; also serves as the solo dev's self-review checklist for AI-generated code.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="architecture-decision-records" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/architecture-decision-records">
    <summary>Captures one architecturally significant decision per ADR with Context, Decision, Consequences, Alternatives. Lock format; CI-enforce; treat as first-class artefacts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="architecture-proposal-document-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/architecture-proposal-document-template">
    <summary>Produces an architecture proposal: problem, constraints, options, decision, consequences, rollback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="architecture-review-meeting-facilitation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/architecture-review-meeting-facilitation">
    <summary>Playbook step to facilitate the weekly architecture review: pre-read, deliberation rules, decision capture, follow-up.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="behavioral-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/behavioral-patterns">
    <summary>Nine GoF behavioral patterns (Strategy, Observer, Command, State, Chain of Responsibility, Template Method, Mediator, Iterator, Visitor) for controlling object communication at runtime.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="c4-model" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/c4-model">
    <summary>Hierarchical diagrams at four levels: System Context, Containers, Components, Code. Locked toolchain (Structurizr / Mermaid / PlantUML) and per-level audience.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="caching-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/caching-architecture">
    <summary>Design multi-layer caching (browser → CDN → API gateway → application → database) using the correct pattern per data type: cache-aside, read-through, write-through, write-behind, or write-around.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/cloud-architecture">
    <summary>Well-Architected-Framework-bound cloud-native design pass \u2014 six pillars (operational excellence, security, reliability, performance, cost, sustainability), provider selection, landing zone, VPC, zero-trust, FinOps, DR \u2014 emitting an ADR + IaC scaffold before any cloud resource is created.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="container-orchestration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/container-orchestration">
    <summary>Kubernetes pod / Deployment / autoscaling / security manifest patterns \u2014 declarative model, probes, resource requests, PSS, network policies \u2014 emitted as a pre-merge manifest checklist that catches OOM, CrashLoopBackOff, ImagePullBackOff, and unready-pod traffic before production.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="creational-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/creational-patterns">
    <summary>Six GoF creational patterns (Factory Method, Abstract Factory, Builder, Prototype, Singleton, Object Pool) and DI for object creation that increases flexibility and reuse.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-modeling" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/data-modeling">
    <summary>Build any persistent schema in three sequential passes: conceptual (entities/relationships) → logical (attributes, keys, 3NF, tech-agnostic) → physical (tables, types, indexes, engine-specific).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-pipeline-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/data-pipeline-design">
    <summary>Pipeline design pass \u2014 medallion bronze/silver/gold tiers, idempotent tasks, DLQs, orchestrator choice (Airflow / Dagster), schema-evolution gates, data-quality validation \u2014 emitting a pipeline spec + orchestrator DAG skeleton.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="database-selection" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/database-selection">
    <summary>Framework for choosing among 100+ databases by access pattern, consistency need, scale envelope, and operational fit; output is a documented selection ADR.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-tree-architecture-style" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/decision-tree-architecture-style">
    <summary>Choose between Monolith, Modular Monolith, and Microservices based on team size, DevOps maturity, and deployment-frequency requirements.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-tree-build-vs-buy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/decision-tree-build-vs-buy">
    <summary>Decide whether to build custom software or buy/adopt a commercial solution by scoring strategic differentiation, TCO, time-to-value, and vendor lock-in.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-tree-cloud-provider" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/decision-tree-cloud-provider">
    <summary>Routes a workload to AWS, Azure, GCP, or none-of-the-above by walking existing-investment, workload-type, and budget-sensitivity branches; emits a provider+runner-up ADR.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-tree-process" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/decision-tree-process">
    <summary>Six-phase architecture decision process (problem, options, trade-off, validation, ADR, implementation) that emits a complete decision report with weighted matrix + ADR + rollback plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-tree-tech-stack" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/decision-tree-tech-stack">
    <summary>Picks a backend language + framework + datastore by walking team-expertise, performance-need, ecosystem-fit, and hiring-supply branches; emits a stack ADR with rejected alternatives.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="distributed-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/distributed-patterns">
    <summary>Pattern-selection methodology for distributed systems \u2014 Saga (choreography vs orchestration), CQRS, Event Sourcing, Outbox, 2PC/Saga/TCC tradeoffs, Circuit Breaker, Bulkhead, Retry-with-jitter, Idempotency, Leader Election, Rate Limiting \u2014 emitting a per-decision ADR that pins the chosen pattern + its rejected alternatives.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="event-driven-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/event-driven-architecture">
    <summary>Event-driven architecture pattern selection \u2014 async broker (Kafka / RabbitMQ / SQS), idempotent consumers, past-tense event naming, saga choreography vs orchestration, replay capability \u2014 emitting an ADR + per-event contract that pins the chosen pattern.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="microservices-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/microservices-architecture">
    <summary>Microservice decomposition decision pass \u2014 DDD subdomains, volatility-based extraction, Strangler-Fig migration, database-per-service, communication patterns, anti-patterns \u2014 emitting an ADR per extraction and a service-map that pins ownership + contracts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="modular-monolith" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/modular-monolith">
    <summary>Single-deployable architecture with strict module boundaries: one bounded context per module, schema-per-module, public-API-only calls, import-linter enforced in CI.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="monolith-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/monolith-architecture">
    <summary>Single-deployable architecture (Monolith First): vertical-slice or layered internal layout, ACID transactions, single deploy pipeline; ships when team ≤10 and boundaries unclear.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-tenancy-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/multi-tenancy-patterns">
    <summary>Decision framework for SaaS multi-tenancy isolation \u2014 shared-everything / schema-per-tenant / DB-per-tenant / hybrid \u2014 with quantified blast-radius math, cost economics, compliance scoping, and migration paths between models.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="observability-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/observability-architecture">
    <summary>Three-pillar observability design pass \u2014 metrics, logs, traces with SLI/SLO/error-budget instrumentation, OpenTelemetry collector pipelines, sampling strategy, multi-burn-rate alerting, tiered retention \u2014 emitting a per-service observability spec + collector config.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="one-way-door-flagging-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/one-way-door-flagging-protocol">
    <summary>Decision-time protocol that tags every architecture decision as one-way-door or two-way-door at the ADR header, routes one-way doors through a heavier review path (48h cooldown + devil's-advocate reviewer + rollback estimate), and reviews misclassifications quarterly for calibration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="patterns-overview" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/patterns-overview">
    <summary>Routes a design problem to a GoF (creational / structural / behavioural) or cloud-native pattern (CQRS, Saga, Circuit Breaker) using problem-signal triggers; emits a pattern-selection ADR.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="performance-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/performance-architecture">
    <summary>Defines numeric SLO targets, caching layers, database optimisation tactics, and load-test gates for a service; ships a performance spec + k6 baseline + scaling triggers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="quality-attributes" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/quality-attributes">
    <summary>Captures non-functional requirements (NFRs) as ISO-25010 quality scenarios with stimulus-response measurements, prioritised by ATAM utility tree; emits NFR spec + SLI/SLO doc.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="quality-attributes-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/quality-attributes-analysis">
    <summary>Systematic QAA pass binding NFRs to structural decisions \u2014 ISO/IEC 25010:2023 characteristics, 6-part quality-attribute scenarios, utility tree with (Importance, Difficulty) scoring, ATAM-style tradeoff analysis \u2014 every (H,H) scenario gates an executable fitness function in CI.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="readiness-matrix-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/readiness-matrix-template">
    <summary>Service \u00d7 runbook \u00d7 owner \u00d7 alert \u00d7 DR-tier matrix used for the weekly 30-minute pre-incident readiness review; output is a committed, signed-off readiness snapshot.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reliability-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/reliability-architecture">
    <summary>Reliability design pass binding availability targets to structural decisions \u2014 SLI/SLO/error-budget definitions, fault-tolerance pattern selection (circuit breaker / retry / bulkhead / timeout), graceful degradation tiers, health checks, chaos plan, DR strategy with RPO/RTO and 3-2-1 backups \u2014 emitting a per-service reliability spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-adr-pack" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/security-adr-pack">
    <summary>Pre-authored bundle of five canonical security ADR stubs (auth, encryption, secrets, isolation, residency) that turns a security-by-design audit from blank-page work into a fill-in-choices exercise.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/security-architecture">
    <summary>Zero-Trust, defence-in-depth architecture spec: identity + authZ matrix, secrets handling, OWASP ASVS L2 controls, threat-model, and incident-response gates. Output: security spec + STRIDE diagram.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-by-design-feature-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/security-by-design-feature-checklist">
    <summary>STRIDE-lite per-feature threat-model checklist that runs during a normal design review and produces a 1-page feature-stm.md attached to the design doc.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serverless-architecture-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/serverless-architecture-patterns">
    <summary>Routes a workload to the right serverless composition (API Gateway+Lambda, EventBridge, Step Functions, SQS fan-out) and emits a pattern ADR with cost + cold-start trade-offs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serverless-cold-start-optimization" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/serverless-cold-start-optimization">
    <summary>Cold-start mitigation spec for FaaS: runtime + memory + bundle-size + provisioned concurrency / SnapStart choice, with measured before/after p99 numbers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serverless-cost-optimization" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/serverless-cost-optimization">
    <summary>Cost-reduction report for a serverless workload: memory right-sizing, batching, downstream call reduction, idle-PC removal; ships before/after spend + break-even RPS vs containers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serverless-foundations" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/serverless-foundations">
    <summary>Foundational checklist for adopting serverless: execution model, statelessness, event sources, observability, vendor lock-in awareness, and IaC discipline. Output: yes/no checklist with rationale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serverless-iac-and-templates" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/serverless-iac-and-templates">
    <summary>IaC blueprint for a serverless stack: SAM / CDK / Serverless Framework / Pulumi / Terraform choice, parameterised template with env-aware stages, deployment pipeline, drift detection.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="structural-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/structural-patterns">
    <summary>Selects a GoF structural pattern (Adapter, Bridge, Composite, Decorator, Facade, Proxy, Flyweight) from concrete symptom signals; emits ADR with cost + alternative + ban on stacking &gt;2 decorators.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="system-design-process" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/system-design-process">
    <summary>Five-phase process (Understand → Scope → Design → Validate → Document) turning a product brief into a buildable architecture package: requirements, NFR back-of-envelope, C4 L1+L2, and ADRs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-build-vs-buy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/trade-off-build-vs-buy">
    <summary>Decides Build / Buy / Hybrid by scoring strategic differentiation, 3-year TCO, time-to-value, vendor lock-in, and integration cost. Emits ADR with quantified rationale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-decision-matrix" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/trade-off-decision-matrix">
    <summary>Builds a stakeholder-weighted decision matrix: criteria + weights (sum = 100%), evidence-backed scores per option, conflict identification, and computed weighted totals.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-decision-methods" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/trade-off-decision-methods">
    <summary>Routes the decision to the right method (Weighted Matrix, ATAM, Cost of Delay, Wardley, Real Options) based on number of options, stakeholder breadth, reversibility, and uncertainty.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-quality-attributes" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/trade-off-quality-attributes">
    <summary>ATAM-style trade-off analysis between competing quality attributes (perf, security, cost, maintainability, availability): scenario-pair conflicts, sensitivity points, and resolution rules.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-stakeholder-communication" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/trade-off-stakeholder-communication">
    <summary>Generates a stakeholder-tailored trade-off briefing that preserves the key risk for every audience (exec, PM, engineer, ops) and writes the ADR Consequences section.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-technical-debt" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/trade-off-technical-debt">
    <summary>Classifies a piece of technical debt on the Fowler quadrant, sizes the 15-20% debt budget, and emits a debt item with explicit repayment trigger.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="workflows" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/architecture/workflows">
    <summary>Picks one of seven canonical architecture workflows (system-design, review, ADR, tech-eval, ATAM/CBAM, Strangler migration, design-doc review) and emits its named step sequence + role assignments.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
