<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="architecture" count="59">
  <methodology slug="adr-for-client-arb-review-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/adr-for-client-arb-review-template">
    <summary>Reusable template for adr for client arb review template that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="adr-reversibility-tagging" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/adr-reversibility-tagging">
    <summary>Tags every ADR with one-way-door vs. two-way-door reversibility so review depth and approval gates match the cost of being wrong.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="adr-staleness-audit" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/adr-staleness-audit">
    <summary>Quarterly audit cadence and rubric for marking ADRs accepted / superseded / deprecated / re-open based on staleness signals.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-agent-perimeter-policy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/ai-agent-perimeter-policy">
    <summary>Translates client NDA/MSA clauses on data residency and confidentiality into per-engagement AI-agent guardrails (no embeddings of client code, no logs to provider X, no MCP servers from list Y).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="api-gateway-graphql" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/api-gateway-graphql">
    <summary>GraphQL federation via Apollo Router creates a unified supergraph from independently deployed domain subgraphs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="api-gateway-observability" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/api-gateway-observability">
    <summary>API gateway observability covers three pillars: metrics (request rate, latency percentiles, error rate, circuit breaker state, rate limit hits) exported via Prometheus; structured access logging with correlation ID, consumer identity, and upstream latency; and distributed tracing via OpenTelemetry with W3C trace context propagation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="api-gateway-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/api-gateway-patterns">
    <summary>An API gateway is a single entry point for all client requests to backend services, acting as a reverse proxy for cross-cutting concerns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="api-gateway-resilience" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/api-gateway-resilience">
    <summary>Resilience at the gateway layer means applying multi-level rate limiting to prevent abuse, circuit breakers to stop cascading failures, retries with exponential backoff to absorb transient errors, and tiered timeouts matched to backend SLAs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="api-gateway-security" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/api-gateway-security">
    <summary>API gateway security layers: TLS termination at the edge, authentication (API keys, JWT, OAuth 2.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="arch-pattern-clean" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/arch-pattern-clean">
    <summary>Dependencies point inward through concentric circles: Domain (Entities) at the center, then Application (Use Cases), then Interface Adapters, then Frameworks and Drivers at the outside.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="arch-pattern-ddd" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/arch-pattern-ddd">
    <summary>Eric Evans (2003) defined DDD as a way to tackle complexity in the heart of software by building a shared model between developers and domain experts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="arch-pattern-hexagonal" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/arch-pattern-hexagonal">
    <summary>The application core is isolated from the outside world through ports (interfaces) and adapters (implementations).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="arch-pattern-onion" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/arch-pattern-onion">
    <summary>Jeffrey Palermo (2008) formalised Onion Architecture: all coupling points toward the center.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="architect-pr-review-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/architect-pr-review-checklist">
    <summary>Tier-appropriate PR review checklist for the architectural surface — distinct from generic peer code review; also serves as the solo dev's self-review checklist for AI-generated code.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="architecture-decision-records" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/architecture-decision-records">
    <summary>An Architecture Decision Record (ADR) is a short document capturing one architecturally significant decision: Context (why the decision was needed), Decision (what was decided), Consequences (trade-offs accepted), and Alternatives (options rejected with reasons).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="behavioral-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/behavioral-patterns">
    <summary>Nine GoF behavioral patterns for controlling how objects communicate and distribute responsibilities at runtime.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="c4-model" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/c4-model">
    <summary>The C4 model is a hierarchical diagramming approach for software architecture: Context (system + users + external systems), Containers (deployable units + technology choices), Components (internal structure of one container), and Code (class diagrams, usually auto-generated).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="caching-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/caching-architecture">
    <summary>Design multi-layer caching strategies (browser → CDN → API gateway → application → database) using the correct pattern per data type: cache-aside, read-through, write-through, write-behind, or write-around.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cloud-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/cloud-architecture">
    <summary>Best practices for designing cloud-native applications using the Well-Architected Framework (six pillars: operational excellence, security, reliability, performance efficiency, cost optimisation, sustainability).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="container-orchestration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/container-orchestration">
    <summary>Kubernetes declarative model (desired state reconciliation) enables self-healing, horizontal scaling, and zero-downtime deployments — but misconfigured resource requests cause OOM kills and poor scheduling, missing liveness/readiness probes cause traffic to reach broken pods, and over-privileged service accounts create security blast radius.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="creational-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/creational-patterns">
    <summary>Object creation mechanisms that increase flexibility and reuse.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-modeling" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/data-modeling">
    <summary>Build any persistent schema in three sequential passes: conceptual (entities/relationships in business terms) → logical (attributes, keys, cardinality, normalized to 3NF, technology-agnostic) → physical (tables, exact data types, indexes, partitions, engine-specific constraints).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="data-pipeline-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/data-pipeline-design">
    <summary>Poor pipeline design causes data quality failures that propagate silently into dashboards and ML models.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="database-selection" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/database-selection">
    <summary>Framework for choosing among 100+ databases.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-tree-architecture-style" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/decision-tree-architecture-style">
    <summary>Use this decision tree to choose between Monolith, Modular Monolith, and Microservices based on team size, DevOps maturity, and deployment frequency.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-tree-build-vs-buy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/decision-tree-build-vs-buy">
    <summary>Use this decision tree to decide whether to build custom software or buy/adopt a commercial solution.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-tree-cloud-provider" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/decision-tree-cloud-provider">
    <summary>Walk this decision tree to choose between AWS, Azure, and GCP.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-tree-process" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/decision-tree-process">
    <summary>Six-phase process for making architecture decisions systematically: (1) problem definition, (2) options generation, (3) trade-off analysis, (4) technical and stakeholder validation, (5) ADR documentation, (6) implementation planning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-tree-tech-stack" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/decision-tree-tech-stack">
    <summary>Walk this decision tree to select frontend frameworks, backend languages, and mobile platforms.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="distributed-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/distributed-patterns">
    <summary>Patterns for data consistency, fault tolerance, and coordination in distributed systems.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="event-driven-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/event-driven-architecture">
    <summary>Event-Driven Architecture (EDA) structures inter-service communication as asynchronous events flowing through a broker (Kafka, RabbitMQ, SQS) rather than synchronous HTTP calls.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="microservices-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/microservices-architecture">
    <summary>Decomposing applications into independently deployable services around business capabilities.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="modular-monolith" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/modular-monolith">
    <summary>A modular monolith is a single deployable unit with strict module boundaries: each module maps to one bounded context, exposes only a public API, owns its database schema, and never directly imports internals of another module.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="monolith-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/monolith-architecture">
    <summary>A monolith is a single deployable unit containing all application functionality.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-tenancy-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/multi-tenancy-patterns">
    <summary>Decision framework for SaaS multi-tenancy isolation — shared-everything vs schema-per-tenant vs DB-per-tenant — with tenant-isolation guarantees, blast-radius math, and migration paths between models.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="observability-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/observability-architecture">
    <summary>Designing the three-pillar observability stack (metrics, logs, traces) so engineers can answer "why is this broken?" not just "is it broken?".</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="one-way-door-flagging-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/one-way-door-flagging-protocol">
    <summary>An explicit decision-time protocol that flags each architecture choice as one-way-door (irreversible within 6 months without significant cost) vs two-way-door, gating one-way doors behind a heavier review path while letting two-way doors ship at velocity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="patterns-overview" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/patterns-overview">
    <summary>Design patterns are language-agnostic solutions to recurring software design problems, grouped into three GoF categories (Creational, Structural, Behavioral) plus Architectural and Distributed/Cloud-Native patterns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="performance-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/performance-architecture">
    <summary>Design systems to meet explicit SLO targets (p50/p95/p99, throughput, error rate, availability) by addressing all five layers: client, CDN/edge, load balancer, application, and data.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="quality-attributes" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/quality-attributes">
    <summary>Identify, prioritize, and document non-functional requirements (NFRs) using ISO 25010 quality characteristics, scenario-driven specification, SLI/SLO definitions, and ATAM-style trade-off analysis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="quality-attributes-analysis" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/quality-attributes-analysis">
    <summary>Quality Attributes Analysis (QAA) is the systematic process of identifying, prioritizing, and binding non-functional requirements (NFRs) to architectural decisions using ISO/IEC 25010:2023 characteristics, 6-part quality attribute scenarios, utility trees with (Importance, Difficulty) scoring, and ATAM-style trade-off analysis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reliability-architecture" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/reliability-architecture">
    <summary>Designing systems that maintain availability targets, recover from failures, and degrade gracefully under stress.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="security-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/security-architecture">
    <summary>Designing secure systems with defense in depth, Zero Trust principles, and modern authentication/authorization patterns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serverless-architecture-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/serverless-architecture-patterns">
    <summary>Six core serverless patterns — API backend, event processing, saga/orchestration, fan-out/fan-in, CQRS with event sourcing, and edge computing — plus the most common anti-patterns and real-world examples from e-commerce, data pipelines, SaaS multi-tenant, and document processing use cases.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serverless-cold-start-optimization" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/serverless-cold-start-optimization">
    <summary>Cold starts occur when a new Lambda function instance is created (no warm container exists).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serverless-cost-optimization" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/serverless-cost-optimization">
    <summary>Lambda cost equals Requests + (Duration × Memory) + Data Transfer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serverless-foundations" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/serverless-foundations">
    <summary>Serverless computing abstracts infrastructure management, allowing developers to focus on code.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="serverless-iac-and-templates" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/serverless-iac-and-templates">
    <summary>Framework selection guide (SAM for AWS-native simplicity, Serverless Framework for multi-cloud plugins, SST for TypeScript full-stack DX, CDK for complex type-safe infra) plus production-ready templates for REST APIs, SQS event processing, Step Functions workflows, scheduled jobs, and Lambda handlers (Python Powertools and TypeScript).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="service-mesh" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/service-mesh">
    <summary>Infrastructure layer for secure, observable service-to-service communication in microservices.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="strangler-fig-playbook-vendor" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/dev/software-architect/strangler-fig-playbook-vendor">
    <summary>End-to-end strangler-fig migration playbook framed for vendor delivery — slice picking, traffic shifting, fallback semantics, exit criteria.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="structural-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/structural-patterns">
    <summary>Structural patterns define how classes and objects are composed into larger structures using inheritance and object composition.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="system-design-process" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/system-design-process">
    <summary>A five-phase process (Understand → Scope → Design → Validate → Document) for turning a product brief into a buildable architecture package: requirements list, NFR targets with numeric back-of-envelope estimates, C4 diagrams (L1+L2 minimum), and ADRs per non-obvious decision.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-build-vs-buy" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/trade-off-build-vs-buy">
    <summary>Evaluate whether to build a capability in-house, buy a vendor solution, or adopt a hybrid approach.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-decision-matrix" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/trade-off-decision-matrix">
    <summary>Build a weighted decision matrix to compare 3-5 architecture options across scored criteria.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-decision-methods" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/trade-off-decision-methods">
    <summary>Structured evaluation methods for architecture trade-offs, from the full ATAM workshop (3-4 days, Type 1 irreversible decisions) to lightweight alternatives (Mini-ATAM, TARA, LAAAM) for sprint-level choices.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-quality-attributes" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/trade-off-quality-attributes">
    <summary>Quality attributes often conflict: improving one typically degrades another.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-stakeholder-communication" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/trade-off-stakeholder-communication">
    <summary>Architecture trade-offs must be communicated differently to executives, product managers, engineers, and operations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="trade-off-technical-debt" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/trade-off-technical-debt">
    <summary>Technical debt is the implied cost of rework caused by choosing an easier but limited solution now instead of a better approach that would take longer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="workflows" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/dev/software-architect/workflows">
    <summary>Seven repeatable workflow types for architecture activities: system design, architecture review, ADR creation, technology evaluation, ATAM/CBAM assessment, migration planning (Strangler Fig), and design-document review.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
