<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Risk Register Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the risk-register methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="exactly-one-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every risk has exactly one named individual as owner; 'the team' is not valid.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI risk standard">Risks without a single owner are observed, not managed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="trigger-observable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every trigger must be an observable signal — a metric, log event, or date — not a subjective phrase.</statement>
      <rationale source="Risk-monitoring practice">Unobservable triggers cannot be monitored; risks activate without warning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="accept-requires-contingency" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Accept strategy entry must include contingency_amount or contingency_plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="Risk-budgeting practice">Accept without a contingency is denial dressed as a strategy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="score-integrity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Risk score must equal probability_level × impact_level; stored score must match computed value.</statement>
      <rationale source="Register hygiene">Score integrity is required for heatmap accuracy and prioritisation correctness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="opportunity-quota" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include at least one opportunity (positive risk) for every ten threats.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — register-bias audits">Sponsor approval rates rise when upside is visible; LLMs drop opportunities by default.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="calibrated-impact-scale" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Calibrate the impact scale with a project-specific reference point before scoring.</statement>
      <rationale source="Risk-assessment practice">Uncalibrated scales produce inconsistent scores across assessors and over time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="risk-driven-contingency" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Risk-driven contingency (sum of P × cost_impact per open risk) must replace flat-percentage reserves for any project with an active register.</statement>
      <rationale source="EVM / risk budgeting">Flat reserves systematically over- or under-fund based on risk profile.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Pure-Scrum teams already tracking risks as backlog impediments</item>
      <item>Tasks under 1 week with a single owner</item>
      <item>Pre-discovery R&amp;D where uncertainty is the work — use a learning log</item>
      <item>Risks already covered by a separate risk system (GDPR, security)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
