<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ops-dashboard-setup">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>growth-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Framework for centralizing business metrics into a single, actionable view. Dashboard design principles, metric selection, data connections, and reporting cadences.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>dashboard</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>reporting</tag>
      <tag>kpis</tag>
      <tag>business-operations</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Dashboard Setup</title>

    <summary>A framework for centralizing business metrics into a single, actionable view. Covers dashboard design principles, metric selection (5-10 max), data source connections, and reporting cadences (daily pulse, weekly review, monthly report). The core rule: every metric on a dashboard must be one you can act on — lagging vanity metrics belong in archives, not on the dashboard.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Metrics scattered across tools (Stripe, Google Analytics, CRM, product analytics) create decision lag. A single dashboard surface reduces time-to-insight from hours to seconds, enables pattern detection across correlated metrics (e.g., CAC vs LTV), and makes weekly reviews actionable rather than archaeological.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>No single view of business health exists across revenue, customers, and marketing</item>
        <item>Weekly review meetings waste time hunting for numbers across tools</item>
        <item>Setting up a new SaaS or product business that needs an initial metrics system</item>
        <item>Quarterly planning requires trend visibility across multiple metric categories</item>
        <item>Switching analytics tools and need to rebuild reporting infrastructure</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Business has fewer than 10 customers — a simple spreadsheet outperforms a dashboard</item>
        <item>Metrics are undefined or inconsistently tracked — fix data collection first</item>
        <item>No one will review the dashboard regularly — a stale dashboard is worse than none</item>
        <item>Dashboard tool requires data warehouse setup that hasn't been built yet</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="core-design-principles">
      <rule>
        <statement>Include 5-10 key metrics maximum on any single dashboard. A dashboard with 30 metrics is a report, not a decision tool.</statement>
        <rationale>Too many metrics dilute attention. A dashboard should answer the question "is my business healthy today?" in under 5 seconds. More than 10 metrics prevents this glance-level assessment.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Glanceable: status visible in 5 seconds without analysis</item>
        <item>Focused: 5-10 key metrics maximum</item>
        <item>Current: real-time or daily updates (not monthly)</item>
        <item>Actionable: only metrics you can directly influence</item>
        <item>Comparative: show trend vs prior period, not just point-in-time value</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="dashboard-types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Build separate dashboards for daily pulse, weekly review, and monthly report — each has a different audience, update frequency, and decision type.</statement>
        <rationale>A daily dashboard optimized for speed cannot serve monthly analysis. Combining them produces a hybrid that does neither well.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Daily pulse: quick health check, real-time or daily updates, 5-7 metrics</item>
        <item>Weekly review: trend analysis, weekly update, 10-12 metrics</item>
        <item>Monthly report: full analysis, monthly update, full metric set</item>
        <item>Real-time: live monitoring for time-sensitive operations</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="metric-selection-criteria">
      <rule>
        <statement>Include only metrics that pass the actionability test: if this metric changes 20% in the wrong direction, what specifically would you do differently?</statement>
        <rationale>Lagging vanity metrics (total pageviews, total followers) feel important but produce no decision. Actionable metrics (conversion rate, CAC, churn rate) map to specific interventions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="revenue-metrics">
      <list>
        <item>MRR (Monthly Recurring Revenue): total recurring revenue normalized to a month</item>
        <item>MRR Growth: (current MRR - prior MRR) / prior MRR × 100%</item>
        <item>New MRR: revenue from new customers this month</item>
        <item>Churned MRR: revenue lost from canceled customers</item>
        <item>Expansion MRR: additional revenue from upgrades and add-ons</item>
        <item>Net New MRR: New MRR + Expansion MRR - Churned MRR</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="customer-metrics">
      <list>
        <item>Total customers: count of active paying customers</item>
        <item>New customers: signups that converted to paid this month</item>
        <item>Churned customers: customers who canceled this month</item>
        <item>Churn rate: churned / total at start of period × 100%</item>
        <item>LTV (Lifetime Value): ARPU / monthly churn rate</item>
        <item>CAC (Customer Acquisition Cost): total sales + marketing spend / new customers</item>
        <item>LTV:CAC ratio: target 3:1 minimum, 8:1 healthy for SaaS</item>
        <item>CAC payback period: CAC / (ARPU × gross margin) in months</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="marketing-funnel-metrics">
      <list>
        <item>Organic visitors: monthly visits from search and direct</item>
        <item>Signup rate: signups / visitors × 100% (target: 2-5%)</item>
        <item>Activation rate: activated users / signups × 100% (target: 40%+)</item>
        <item>Trial-to-paid conversion: paid conversions / trial starts × 100% (target: 20-40%)</item>
        <item>Cost per acquisition (CPA): spend / conversions per channel</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track each funnel metric per acquisition channel (organic, paid, referral, direct). Channel-level metrics reveal where to invest; blended metrics hide the signal.</statement>
        <rationale>A 3% overall conversion rate may be 8% for organic and 0.5% for paid. Blended metrics would suggest the paid channel is contributing; channel breakdown reveals it is destroying ROI.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="reporting-cadence">
      <rule>
        <statement>Review dashboards on a fixed cadence: daily pulse check (2 min), weekly review (30 min), monthly report (2 hours). Skip reviews create metric blindspots.</statement>
        <rationale>The purpose of a dashboard is to catch problems early. A dashboard reviewed monthly catches problems a month after they start. A dashboard reviewed daily catches them on day 2.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Daily: pulse check — is anything broken? (revenue, signups, errors)</item>
        <item>Weekly: trend review — are key metrics moving in the right direction?</item>
        <item>Monthly: full analysis — channel performance, cohort comparison, targets vs actuals</item>
        <item>Quarterly: target reset — update benchmarks based on current trajectory</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="alert-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Set automated alerts for metric deviations greater than 20% from the 7-day rolling average. Alert on drops, not just on targets.</statement>
        <rationale>Target-based alerts ("below $X MRR") miss sudden drops that remain above target. Deviation-based alerts catch anomalies regardless of absolute level.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/monthly-metrics-tracker.md" purpose="Spreadsheet structure: revenue, customers, unit economics, marketing"/>
      <template path="templates/dashboard-spec.md" purpose="Dashboard specification: purpose, audience, metrics, visualizations"/>
      <template path="templates/monthly-report.md" purpose="Monthly report template: executive summary, KPIs, channel performance"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
