<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="FinOps — Reserved Instances / Savings Plans Commitment Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the fco-commitment-pricing methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced by the decision tree.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="3-month-baseline-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Commitment recommendation MUST be backed by at least 3 months of utilization baseline; commitments made on &lt; 3 months data are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS FinOps best practices, FinOps Foundation framework">Insufficient baseline produces over-commitment that locks in waste for 1-3 years; the 3-month floor is the empirical minimum.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="convertible-for-uncertainty" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When workload mix may shift (instance family change, region change) within the commitment term, plan MUST select Convertible RIs / Compute Savings Plan rather than Standard RIs.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS docs — RI types">Standard RIs are non-modifiable; convertibles exchange flexibility for ~3pp lower discount.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="cover-base-not-peak" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Commitment MUST cover the BASE load (e.g. p25 hourly utilization), NOT peak; over-commitment of peak yields unused-commitment waste.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps Foundation framework">Commitments are paid whether utilized or not; covering peak guarantees waste during the long tail when usage is below peak.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="utilization-alert-80pct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plan MUST emit a metric `commitment_utilization_pct` and alert when it drops below 80% for 7 consecutive days.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Cost Explorer docs, FinOps Foundation">Unused commitment is real cash burn; the alert is the only mechanism to detect drift before the term ends.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="staggered-renewal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Commitment terms MUST be staggered (not all expiring same month); a single-renewal-cliff exposes the team to pricing risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS FinOps best practices">Coincident expirations leave the team renegotiating at provider-favorable timing; staggered terms smooth the negotiation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the workload is bursty or pre-product, this methodology MUST be skipped — apply `fco-spot-instances` or wait for stability.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps Foundation framework">Commitments require predictability; without it, the discount is overwhelmed by unused-commitment waste.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
