<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="mlp-planning Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for mlp-planning as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Adding more features instead of polishing existing ones when retention is low.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>More features increase scope without addressing the quality gap. Users who left due to rough UX won't return for more features with the same rough UX.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping MVP validation and going straight to MLP polish.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Polish on an unvalidated core value is expensive waste. Validate the job-to-be-done first, then polish the delivery.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Surface-level polish (color changes, fonts) without addressing interaction quality.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cosmetic polish without fixing interaction friction does not move retention or NPS.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Generic delight not tailored to the specific audience.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Confetti on task completion delights consumer app users; it annoys enterprise finance users in the same moment. Delight must match emotional context.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Adding Layer 4 delight without completing Layers 1–3.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Delight on top of unreliable or unusable flows increases frustration. Users notice the inconsistency more than the charm.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Declaring MLP using vibes instead of remeasured retention and NPS.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without before/after metrics the team will declare MLP based on internal demos, then be surprised when retention is unchanged.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
