<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agile and Hybrid Approaches Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Agile and Hybrid Approaches methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="threshold-2-and-2-for-hybrid" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prefer Hybrid only when at least two factors score Predictive AND two score Agile; otherwise default to the majority signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion delivery audits 2026-Q1">humans and LLMs both default to Hybrid because it sounds safe; the 2+2 threshold prevents false hybrids.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="one-approach-per-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick one approach per project phase, not per ceremony; translate between approaches at explicit, named boundaries.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mixed-mode anti-pattern (Atlassian Team Playbook)">mixed-mode within a phase produces competing artefacts (burn-down + Gantt) and stakeholder confusion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="burn-up-over-burn-down" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hybrid stakeholder reporting MUST use burn-up charts, not burn-down; burn-down hides scope additions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reporting practice (Mike Cohn, Agile Estimating)">burn-down hides scope growth; burn-up makes scope explicit at every step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="definition-of-done-per-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define 'Done' once per phase; sharing a single DoD across agile and predictive phases is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="DoD-conflation audits (Faion)">agile 'done' (tested, deployed to staging) differs materially from waterfall 'done' (signed off, documented); conflation causes undetected gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="five-factor-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each of the 5 factors MUST cite evidence (charter clause, transcript line, ticket comment); agent-supplied scores without evidence are flagged 'verify-before-commit'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice">agent-assigned factor scores are persuasive but unfalsifiable without anchored evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="adr-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The selected approach MUST be persisted as an ADR with the 5 factor scores, the chosen approach, and named decision owner; in-passing decisions are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Architecture-decision practice (Nygard 2011)">without an ADR the rationale is lost within 3 months and the team re-litigates the choice.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
