<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-selection" title="Approach Selection Framework">
  <summary>A five-factor decision framework for choosing between Predictive, Agile, and Hybrid delivery approaches.</summary>

  <section title="Approach Spectrum">
    <p>Delivery approaches span a continuous spectrum from fully Predictive (requirements fixed early, sequential phases, big-bang delivery) to fully Adaptive (requirements evolve, iterative sprints, incremental delivery). Hybrid picks a point on the spectrum per project phase.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-Factor Decision Matrix">
    <p>Score each factor as P (Predictive), H (Hybrid), or A (Agile). If 4+ factors score P, choose Predictive. If 4+ score A, choose Agile. Otherwise choose Hybrid.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer Hybrid only when at least two answers point to Predictive AND two point to Agile; otherwise default to the majority signal.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs and humans both default to Hybrid because it sounds safe; the 2+2 threshold prevents false hybrids from sloppy analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Factor 1: Requirements Clarity">
      <list>
        <item>P — Clear, stable, fully documented before work starts</item>
        <item>H — Partially known; core stable, details emerging</item>
        <item>A — Unclear, evolving, discovered through feedback</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Factor 2: Stakeholder Availability">
      <list>
        <item>P — Limited access; prefer formal scheduled reviews</item>
        <item>H — Regular scheduled meetings achievable</item>
        <item>A — Highly engaged; available for frequent collaboration</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Factor 3: Risk Tolerance">
      <list>
        <item>P — Low; must work first time, failure is costly</item>
        <item>H — Medium; can absorb some iteration</item>
        <item>A — High; can experiment and pivot based on feedback</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Factor 4: Team Experience">
      <list>
        <item>P — Less experienced; benefits from clear direction</item>
        <item>H — Mixed experience levels</item>
        <item>A — Self-organizing; comfortable with ambiguity</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Factor 5: Contract Type">
      <list>
        <item>P — Fixed price, fixed scope</item>
        <item>H — Fixed price, flexible scope (phase gates)</item>
        <item>A — Time and materials or value-based</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="When Each Approach Applies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick one approach per project phase, not per ceremony; translate between approaches at explicit, named boundaries.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixed-mode approaches within a single phase produce competing artifacts (burn-down + Gantt) and stakeholder confusion without providing the benefits of either model.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running daily standups alongside Gantt chart updates for the same work.</description>
      <reason>Doubles reporting burden without improving either predictability or agility; the team serves the tools instead of the tools serving the team.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Calling a process "Hybrid" because it uses some agile terminology while keeping all waterfall gates.</description>
      <reason>"Agile in name only" loses the feedback-loop benefit of agile without gaining the predictability of predictive; worst of both worlds.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/pick_approach.py">Reads a YAML answer file and outputs the recommended approach with scores</reference>
</text>
