<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-hybrid-patterns" title="Hybrid Patterns, Scrum, and Kanban">
  <summary>Three hybrid delivery patterns, Scrum event and role reference, Kanban principles, and common methodology mistakes.</summary>

  <section title="Three Hybrid Patterns">
    <section title="Water-Scrum-Fall">
      <p>Predictive planning phase → Scrum execution sprints → Predictive deployment phase. Useful for fixed-price contracts with agile development requirements.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Plan phase: fixed scope, contract baseline, WBS</item>
        <item>Build phase: 2-week sprints, weekly demos, backlog refinement</item>
        <item>Deploy phase: fixed test plan, staged rollout, documentation</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Agile Development + Predictive Governance">
      <p>Sprints for work execution, phase gates for funding and approval decisions. Common in enterprises requiring board approval at each investment stage.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Predictive Core + Agile Discovery">
      <p>Agile discovery phase identifies and validates requirements, then hands off to waterfall implementation. Useful when requirements are unknown but delivery must be fixed-cost.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Define "Done" once per phase; hybrid teams sharing a single Definition of Done across agile and predictive phases produce inconsistent quality gates.</statement>
        <rationale>Agile "done" (tested, deployed to staging) differs materially from waterfall "done" (signed off, documented); conflation causes undetected gaps at handoff.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Scrum Reference">
    <section title="Scrum Events">
      <list>
        <item>Sprint Planning (2-4 hours): plan sprint work against capacity</item>
        <item>Daily Scrum (15 min): sync, surface blockers</item>
        <item>Sprint Review (1-2 hours): demo to stakeholders, collect feedback</item>
        <item>Sprint Retrospective (1-2 hours): improve process</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Scrum Roles">
      <list>
        <item>Product Owner: what to build, priority, backlog ownership</item>
        <item>Scrum Master: process health, impediment removal</item>
        <item>Developers: how to build, delivery commitment</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Kanban Principles">
    <list>
      <item>Visualize workflow — make work visible on a board</item>
      <item>Limit WIP — cap items in each column to expose bottlenecks</item>
      <item>Manage flow — optimize throughput, not utilization</item>
      <item>Make policies explicit — document column entry/exit criteria</item>
      <item>Continuous improvement — retrospect on flow metrics, not sprint events</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use burn-up over burn-down for hybrid stakeholder reporting; burn-down hides scope additions.</statement>
      <rationale>When scope is added mid-sprint, burn-down charts appear on track while total work grows invisibly; burn-up charts make scope growth explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Dogmatic adherence to one methodology ("We MUST do pure Scrum").</description>
      <reason>No single approach fits all project types; forcing a misfit approach causes ceremony theater without the benefits of either model.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Maintaining both burn-down charts AND traditional Gantt for the same work.</description>
      <reason>Doubles reporting burden without improving visibility; teams serve the tools instead of the tools serving the team.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Discovery → Implementation handoff without an explicit translation boundary.</description>
      <reason>Bakes in a translation tax (agile artifacts → waterfall inputs) that grows larger over time and is difficult to remove once established.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/sprint-plan.md">Sprint planning template with goal, capacity, backlog, dependencies, risks</reference>
  <reference path="templates/kanban-board.md">Kanban board template with WIP limits per column</reference>
</text>
