<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="agile-hybrid-approaches Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for agile-hybrid-approaches as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Running daily standups alongside Gantt chart updates for the same work.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Doubles reporting burden without improving either predictability or agility; the team serves the tools instead of the tools serving the team.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Calling a process "Hybrid" because it uses some agile terminology while keeping all waterfall gates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"Agile in name only" loses the feedback-loop benefit of agile without gaining the predictability of predictive; worst of both worlds.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Dogmatic adherence to one methodology ("We MUST do pure Scrum").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>No single approach fits all project types; forcing a misfit approach causes ceremony theater without the benefits of either model.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Maintaining both burn-down charts AND traditional Gantt for the same work.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Doubles reporting burden without improving visibility; teams serve the tools instead of the tools serving the team.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Discovery → Implementation handoff without an explicit translation boundary.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Bakes in a translation tax (agile artifacts → waterfall inputs) that grows larger over time and is difficult to remove once established.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
