<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Edge and CDN Strategy Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Edge and CDN Strategy application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-edge-platform-decision-axes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose edge platform on three axes: (a) compute runtime (V8 isolates / containers / Wasm), (b) cold-start behavior, (c) origin proximity. Pick ONE, do not multi-cloud edge.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Edge platforms compose poorly; multi-edge multiplies the failure modes without proportional benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-cache-key-includes-vary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cache key = path + query (allowlist) + Accept-Encoding + Vary headers. Wildcards in keys cause silent cache poisoning.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Cache key design is the #1 CDN bug source; explicit allowlist prevents poisoning + leakage.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-origin-shield-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Origin shield (intermediate cache layer) is mandatory for any service with ≥1k req/min to origin. Shields reduce origin load 50-90%.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Without shield, traffic spikes hit origin; shield is the cheapest insurance against origin overload.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-edge-auth-not-bypass" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Edge auth (JWT verification, signed cookies) supplements origin auth; never replaces. Origin must independently validate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Edge can be bypassed (direct origin requests); double validation is the only safe pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-purge-strategy-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Purge strategy: targeted purge per object &gt; tag-based purge &gt; wildcard purge &gt; full purge. Wildcard purges should require approval.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Full purges cause global cache stampedes; explicit hierarchy prevents accidental DDoS-on-self.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>