<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ada-title-ii-compliance-2026">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>US state/local government compliance: WCAG 2.1 AA by April 24 2026 (large) / April 26 2027 (small). Covers websites, apps, PDFs, multimedia, forms under 28 CFR Part 35.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>compliance</tag>
      <tag>ada</tag>
      <tag>government</tag>
      <tag>wcag</tag>
      <tag>legal</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>compliance</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>ADA Title II Compliance 2026</title>

    <summary>A compliance methodology for US state and local government digital services required to meet WCAG 2.1 Level AA under the DOJ final rule (28 CFR Part 35, effective April 24 2024), with large-entity deadline April 24 2026 and smaller-entity deadline April 26 2027. Non-compliant government digital services expose entities to DOJ enforcement, private litigation, and remediation costs that multiply when retrofitted post-launch.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Non-compliant government digital services expose entities to DOJ enforcement, private litigation, and remediation costs that multiply when retrofitted post-launch. The rule covers all public-facing websites, mobile apps, multimedia, PDFs, and interactive forms — not just the homepage. Proactive audit and remediation roadmap before the deadline is far cheaper than reactive remediation under complaint investigation.</p>
      <p>The rule mandates WCAG 2.1 Level AA, pinned to a specific standard by 28 CFR Part 35. Compliance is not optional for covered entities; the deadline is a hard legal requirement with exposure to DOJ enforcement actions and private lawsuits under Title II.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>US state, local, or territorial government digital services covered by 28 CFR Part 35.</item>
        <item>Public universities, transit systems, libraries, courts, agency portals.</item>
        <item>SaaS vendors whose product is delivered to a covered entity under contract.</item>
        <item>Deadline planning: large entities (population 50K+) by April 24 2026; smaller by April 26 2027.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Private-sector commercial sites — ADA Title III applies (different standard and remediation triggers).</item>
        <item>Federal government — Section 508 / ICT Refresh applies instead.</item>
        <item>Employee-facing internal tools at private employers — Title I applies.</item>
        <item>Non-covered entity marketing sites — out of scope for Title II.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="scope-and-coverage">
      <p>Legal scope, compliance deadlines, and the full list of digital content types covered by 28 CFR Part 35 (DOJ final rule, April 24 2024).</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Apply this methodology only to public entities under 28 CFR Part 35: US state, local, and territorial governments and their contractors delivering digital services on their behalf.</statement>
        <rationale>Title II scope is narrower than ADA Title III (private sector); applying Title II requirements to private commercial sites misstates the legal obligation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Covered: state and local government agencies, public universities, transit authorities, libraries, court systems, public utility portals.</item>
        <item>Covered as vendor: SaaS or custom software delivered to a covered entity under contract.</item>
        <item>Not covered by Title II: federal government (Section 508 applies), private-sector commercial sites (Title III), private employer internal tools (Title I).</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Implement WCAG 2.1 Level AA — not 2.2 — as the required standard; apply 2.2 success criteria only as recommended enhancements.</statement>
        <rationale>The DOJ final rule pins to WCAG 2.1 AA. Auto-applying 2.2 SCs as required misrepresents the legal standard and may misprioritize remediation effort.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="deadlines-and-entities">
      <p>Compliance deadlines vary by entity size:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Large entities (population 50,000 or more): April 24 2026.</item>
        <item>Smaller entities: April 26 2027.</item>
        <item>Special district governments: April 26 2027.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="covered-content-types">
      <p>The rule covers all digital content types the entity delivers:</p>
      <list>
        <item>All public-facing websites and web applications.</item>
        <item>Mobile applications (native iOS, Android, and web-based).</item>
        <item>Multimedia content: video (captions required), audio (transcripts), accessible media players.</item>
        <item>PDF documents, Word, Excel, and PowerPoint files created by or for the covered entity.</item>
        <item>Interactive forms.</item>
        <item>Third-party content embedded in covered entity sites (can still trigger compliance obligation).</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not assume archived content is exempt; the archived-content exemption requires: unaltered, clearly marked as archived, not used for current agency activity.</statement>
        <rationale>The exemption is intentionally narrow; pre-existing PDFs must still be remediated on request even if created before the deadline.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not advise clients to use the "undue burden" defense without legal counsel; it is far narrower under Title II than Title III.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents lack the legal standing and financial-analysis capability to make undue-burden determinations; premature reliance creates litigation exposure.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="six-step-compliance-workflow">
      <p>Six-step workflow from digital inventory to conformance documentation, with agent responsibilities and human checkpoints.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Crawl and tag every digital surface (web pages, mobile apps, PDFs, multimedia, forms, third-party widgets) before running any accessibility tests.</statement>
        <rationale>Unknown surfaces cannot be remediated; inventory gaps produce incomplete VPAT documentation and ongoing litigation risk.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run automated tools (axe-core, Pa11y) first, then add manual checkpoints for captions, audio descriptions, accessible PDFs, and keyboard-only navigation.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated tools catch approximately 30-40% of WCAG failures; captions, audio descriptions, and PDF tagging require human or specialized tool review.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Prioritize high-traffic, high-impact pages first; document remediation priority and owner for every issue found.</statement>
        <rationale>Remediation resources are finite; demonstrating good-faith prioritized effort matters under DOJ enforcement review.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Wire automated accessibility checks into CI/CD pipelines so regressions are caught at pull-request time, not post-launch.</statement>
        <rationale>Manual-only monitoring cannot scale; new content and code changes continuously introduce new violations.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Produce a VPAT 2.5 INT or ACR for each covered product; legal counsel must sign off on conformance claims and undue-burden assertions — never delegate these to an agent.</statement>
        <rationale>VPAT/ACR conformance statements carry legal weight; incorrect agent-generated claims increase enforcement and litigation risk.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="implementation-checklist">
      <p>Remediation implementation steps:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Add captions to all video content; provide audio descriptions for visual-only information.</item>
        <item>Tag all PDFs with proper heading structure, alt text, and reading order.</item>
        <item>Ensure all forms have programmatic labels, error identification, and error suggestions.</item>
        <item>Verify keyboard navigation order, focus visibility, and skip-nav links.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-rules-and-limitations">
      <p>Testable agent rules and known limitation flags that prevent common compliance errors.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Reference WCAG 2.1 AA as the required standard in all remediation guidance; flag WCAG 2.2 additions as recommended, not required.</statement>
        <rationale>The DOJ rule is pinned to WCAG 2.1 AA; conflating it with 2.2 creates inaccurate compliance assessments.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent auto-applies WCAG 2.2 success criteria as required under Title II.</description>
        <reason>WCAG 2.2 SCs are not part of the DOJ final rule; marking them required overstates the legal obligation.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent marks pre-existing PDFs as exempt from all accessibility requirements.</description>
        <reason>Pre-existing PDFs must still be remediated on request even if created before the compliance deadline; the exemption is not blanket.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent claims embedded third-party content is not in scope for the covered entity.</description>
        <reason>Third-party content embedded in a covered entity's site can still trigger the covered entity's compliance obligation.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent drafts an undue-burden claim without legal and financial analysis.</description>
        <reason>Undue-burden defenses under Title II require entity-level financial analysis; an agent lacks the standing and data to make this determination.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="human-checkpoints">
      <list>
        <item>Legal counsel must review and sign VPAT/ACR conformance statements.</item>
        <item>Manual AT (assistive technology) walkthroughs by a qualified evaluator are required for captions, audio descriptions, and complex form interactions.</item>
        <item>Validation with real AT users (screen reader, voice control, switch access) before declaring compliance.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools for Title II compliance auditing:</p>
      <list>
        <item>axe-core / axe-core-cli: WCAG 2.1 AA automated scan (deque.com/axe)</item>
        <item>pa11y-ci: CI-friendly site-wide scan (pa11y.org)</item>
        <item>pdfix-cli / pac: PDF accessibility check (PDF/UA) (pdfix.net, pac.pdf-accessibility.org)</item>
        <item>ffmpeg + whisper.cpp: Caption generation pipeline (ffmpeg.org, github.com/ggerganov/whisper.cpp)</item>
        <item>wcag-em-report-tool: W3C evaluation methodology report (github.com/w3c/wcag-em-report-tool)</item>
        <item>lighthouse-ci: Per-route a11y + performance (github.com/GoogleChrome/lighthouse-ci)</item>
        <item>iframe-tester (custom): Detect and audit third-party embeds</item>
      </list>

      <p>SaaS services for government accessibility compliance:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Deque axe DevTools / Auditor: Industry default for state/local agencies. REST API, CI plugins.</item>
        <item>Siteimprove: Strong inventory + tracking, popular with .gov. REST API.</item>
        <item>Level Access: VPAT generation, training. REST API.</item>
        <item>TPGi (ARC, JAWS Inspect): Manual + automated; AT-vendor advantage. REST API.</item>
        <item>Allyant (CommonLook): PDF/UA remediation specialist. REST API.</item>
        <item>3Play Media / Rev: Captions, audio description, transcripts. REST API.</item>
        <item>Civic Plus / Granicus: Require vendor a11y attestation. Partial agent support.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Inventory first, fix second — you cannot remediate what you have not catalogued.</item>
        <item>Prioritize by traffic and by service-criticality (benefits applications, court forms, transit alerts).</item>
        <item>Treat third-party widgets as in-scope — get vendor VPATs and contractually require remediation.</item>
        <item>Build accessibility into procurement: every new SaaS must ship a current VPAT 2.5.</item>
        <item>Train content authors on document accessibility — most violations originate in CMS uploads.</item>
        <item>Maintain a public accessibility statement with feedback channel (a Title II expectation).</item>
        <item>Re-audit after every major content release; baseline drifts within weeks.</item>
        <item>Avoid overlay widgets; DOJ guidance is skeptical of them. Refuse to recommend overlays as remediation.</item>
        <item>Accessibility statement: do not claim "fully conformant" — use "we conform to WCAG 2.1 AA except for…" with known issues list.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://federalregister.gov/documents/2024/04/24/2024-07758"/>
      <link href="https://ada.gov/notices/2024/04/08/web-rule/"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG21/"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/act/"/>
      <link href="https://www.itic.org/policy/accessibility/vpat"/>
      <link href="https://section508.gov/test/"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/ARIA/apg/"/>
      <ref slug="accessibility-evaluation"/>
      <ref slug="accessibility-first-design"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
