<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-aida-structure" title="AIDA Landing Page Structure: Section-by-Section Rules">
  <summary>Rules for each AIDA section: hero, problem agitation, solution/benefits, how-it-works, social proof, FAQ, and final CTA.</summary>

  <section title="Hero Section (Above the Fold)">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Hero must include: headline (6-12 words, benefit not feature), subheadline (expands with specificity), product visual, one CTA button, and a social proof line ("Trusted by X users").</statement>
      <rationale>Visitors decide in 5 seconds whether to scroll. Every missing element reduces the probability they continue. The social proof line directly below the CTA button increases CVR by 10-15%.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Headline formula: [Outcome] + [Timeframe] + [Without Pain Point]. Write 10 variations before selecting the final one.</statement>
      <rationale>The first headline written is rarely the best. Forcing 10 variations surfaces options that use more specific language and stronger benefit framing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Headline: "Build your SaaS in 2 weeks without writing backend code" — outcome (build SaaS), timeframe (2 weeks), without pain (no backend code).</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Headline: "The AI-Powered Platform for Modern Developers" — no outcome, no timeframe, no pain addressed. This describes what the product is, not what it does for the user.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Social Proof">
    <rule>
      <statement>Testimonial formula: "[Specific result achieved] in [timeframe]. Before [product], I struggled with [problem]. Now [positive outcome]." — [Name], [Title] at [Company].</statement>
      <rationale>Generic testimonials ("Great product!") add no conversion value. Specific results with numbers and named individuals are credible and benchmarkable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Social proof effectiveness order: customer logos (B2B) > testimonials with photos > case studies > numbers ("50K users") > press mentions > ratings.</statement>
      <rationale>Logos borrow institutional credibility. Named testimonials borrow personal credibility. Anonymous numbers are least credible because they cannot be verified.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent-polished testimonials with fabricated specifics (company names, exact numbers not from the original quote).</description>
      <reason>Fabricated testimonials are FTC violations and destroy trust when discovered. Agent should format and polish real quotes, never invent specifics.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="FAQ Section">
    <rule>
      <statement>FAQ must address conversion objections, not product questions. "Can I cancel anytime?" and "Is my data secure?" convert better than "How do I import my data?"</statement>
      <rationale>At the FAQ stage, visitors are close to converting but have unresolved concerns. Answering usage questions serves existing users; answering objections serves prospects.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Final CTA">
    <rule>
      <statement>Repeat the main CTA with: benefit reminder, risk reversal (30-day money-back, no credit card, free trial), and urgency if appropriate.</statement>
      <rationale>Visitors who scroll to the bottom are high-intent but may have lingering hesitation. Risk reversal removes the last friction at the decision moment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/saas-page-structure.md">Full SaaS landing page section order with placeholder content for all AIDA elements</reference>
    <reference path="templates/audit-checklist.md">Conversion checklist to score above-fold, copy, trust, and technical elements</reference>
  </section>
</text>
