<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="AIDA-Structured Landing Page Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every AIDA-Structured Landing Page application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-headline-formula" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Headline MUST follow [Outcome] + [Timeframe] + [Without Pain]. Generic 'welcome' or product-name headlines are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Headline carries ~80% of conversion impact; formulaic outcome headlines outperform creative ones.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-aida-sections-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Page MUST be structured as Attention / Interest / Desire / Action sections in order. Random-order sections are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">AIDA structure mirrors decision sequence; out-of-order reads as advertorial.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-one-cta-per-section" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each section MUST have exactly one CTA; multi-CTA sections are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Multiple CTAs in one section halve click-through; the constraint forces hierarchy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-social-proof-below-cta" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Social proof element MUST sit below the primary CTA. Above-CTA placement is rejected as decoration.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Below-CTA placement adds 10-15% CVR; above-CTA placement leaks scroll attention before the ask.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-mobile-first-fold" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Above-the-fold MUST render the headline + primary CTA on mobile (375px wide). Mobile-broken folds are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Mobile traffic is majority; a desktop-only fold breaks the primary conversion on most sessions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
