<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-copy-rules" title="Landing Page Copy Rules, So What Test, and Common Mistakes">
  <summary>Headline formula application, feature-to-benefit conversion test, copy quality rules, and failure modes to avoid.</summary>

  <section title="Feature-to-Benefit Conversion">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the "So what?" test to every feature statement. Ask "So what?" until the answer describes a user outcome, then use that as the copy.</statement>
      <rationale>Features describe what the product does. Benefits describe what the user gets. Customers buy outcomes, not capabilities. The "So what?" chain forces outcome-focused language.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Feature: "AI-powered" → "So what?" → "Get answers in seconds, not hours." Feature: "99.9% uptime" → "So what?" → "Never lose a sale to downtime."</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Agent must be constrained to 3 most differentiating benefits, ignoring the rest. Without this constraint, agents list all features and dilute the message.</statement>
      <rationale>A page that tries to communicate 10 benefits communicates zero. Constraint forces prioritization of the benefits that match the ICP's most urgent pain.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Copy Quality Rules">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Use numbers everywhere: "40% improvement" beats "significant improvement". "Trusted by 5,000 users" beats "trusted by thousands". Specificity is credibility.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague claims are unverifiable and dismissed by skeptical visitors. Specific numbers signal that the claim is based on measurement, not marketing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>FAQ generation without a real list of customer objections produces questions the target audience does not actually ask. Source FAQ from support tickets and sales calls.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents will generate plausible-sounding FAQs that do not match actual conversion blockers. Real objections come from real conversations, not from inference.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Multiple CTAs on the same page section.</description>
      <reason>Multiple CTAs create decision paralysis and split attention. Each section must have one primary action. Secondary CTAs belong in the footer or nav only.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Generic hero headline that could apply to any product in the category.</description>
      <reason>Generic headlines do not differentiate the product from competitors. Specificity in the ICP pain and the outcome is required to stop the scroll.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No mobile preview before launch.</description>
      <reason>Over 50% of landing page traffic is mobile. Above-the-fold elements on mobile differ significantly from desktop. Agent audits do not catch visual layout issues on small screens.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Page load over 3 seconds.</description>
      <reason>Each second of load time past 2 seconds reduces conversion rate by approximately 4.4%. This is a technical issue (images, CDN, JS bloat), not a copy issue — run Lighthouse.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Briefing Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Agent must receive: product name, one-sentence description, ICP definition, top 3 pain points, key benefits (not features), real social proof, and CTA goal before generating copy.</statement>
      <rationale>Without specific ICP pain language, agent copy sounds like every other SaaS landing page. The quality of the brief determines the quality of the output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-full-copy.txt">Agent prompt for complete AIDA landing page copy from ICP brief</reference>
    <reference path="templates/audit-score.py">Score landing page sections against conversion checklist criteria</reference>
  </section>
</text>
