<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="growth-landing-page-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for growth-landing-page-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent-polished testimonials with fabricated specifics (company names, exact numbers not from the original quote).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Fabricated testimonials are FTC violations and destroy trust when discovered. Agent should format and polish real quotes, never invent specifics.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Multiple CTAs on the same page section.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multiple CTAs create decision paralysis and split attention. Each section must have one primary action. Secondary CTAs belong in the footer or nav only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Generic hero headline that could apply to any product in the category.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generic headlines do not differentiate the product from competitors. Specificity in the ICP pain and the outcome is required to stop the scroll.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>No mobile preview before launch.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Over 50% of landing page traffic is mobile. Above-the-fold elements on mobile differ significantly from desktop. Agent audits do not catch visual layout issues on small screens.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Page load over 3 seconds.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each second of load time past 2 seconds reduces conversion rate by approximately 4.4%. This is a technical issue (images, CDN, JS bloat), not a copy issue — run Lighthouse to identify slow resources and optimize before final page launch.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
