<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-tracking" title="UTM Structure, Conversion Events, and Weekly Optimization Routine">
  <summary>UTM parameter naming convention, the 5 essential conversion events to track, and the weekly optimization cadence for managing active campaigns.</summary>

  <section title="UTM Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use consistent UTM parameters on every paid link. Inconsistent UTM naming makes attribution analysis unreliable across campaigns.</statement>
      <rationale>When utm_source values vary (meta vs Meta vs facebook), GA4 aggregates them as separate sources and understates channel performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>?utm_source=meta&amp;utm_medium=paid&amp;utm_campaign=summer-sale-2026&amp;utm_content=video-v1. Use lowercase, hyphens not underscores, consistent source names per channel.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Essential Conversion Events">
    <list>
      <item>1. Page View — baseline traffic measurement</item>
      <item>2. Lead — signup or form submission</item>
      <item>3. Trial Start — product trial initiated</item>
      <item>4. Purchase — transaction completed</item>
      <item>5. Subscription — recurring revenue started</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement server-side Conversion API in addition to pixel tracking. Pixel data degrades with ad blockers and iOS privacy changes; server-side fills the gap.</statement>
      <rationale>Without server-side tracking, Meta and Google can miss 20-40% of conversions, causing the algorithm to optimize on incomplete signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Weekly Optimization Routine">
    <list>
      <item>Monday: review last week's CPA, ROAS, CTR by campaign and ad set</item>
      <item>Tuesday: pause underperformers, increase budget on winners by 20-30%</item>
      <item>Wednesday: create new ad variations based on winning angles</item>
      <item>Thursday: test new audience segments</item>
      <item>Friday: analyze and document learnings; plan next week</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Increasing campaign budget by more than 30% in a single adjustment.</description>
      <reason>Large budget increases (50%+) trigger the platform learning phase, resetting algorithm optimization and causing temporary CPA spikes.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>CTR (Clicks / Impressions): target 1%+ for healthy ad relevance</item>
      <item>CPC (Cost / Clicks): varies by platform and industry</item>
      <item>CVR (Conversions / Clicks): target 2-5%</item>
      <item>CPA (Cost / Conversions): must be below LTV/3</item>
      <item>ROAS (Revenue / Ad Spend): target 3:1 minimum</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/weekly-ads-report.md">Weekly ads performance report template</reference>
</text>
