<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Churn Cohort Analysis Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Churn Cohort Analysis application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-cohort-by-activation-status" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Split churn cohorts by activation status (activated within 7 days, activated 8-30 days, never activated). Each segment has a different churn curve.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Aggregate churn hides 2-4 distinct curves; segmentation reveals the actual problem.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-leading-indicators" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Identify ≥2 behavioral leading indicators (e.g., login frequency drop, feature stop-use, support ticket spike) that predict churn ≥14 days ahead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Cancellations are lagging signals; intervene only on leading.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-save-flow-with-control" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every save-flow tested has a hold-out control group (≥10% of at-risk cohort). Without control, you cannot tell if the save-flow worked or the user would have stayed anyway.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Selection bias in save-flows: users who answer save-emails are pre-disposed to stay; control isolates effect.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-90-day-lookback" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use a 90-day lookback window for cohort comparison. Shorter windows (30 days) over-fit recent churn waves; longer (180+) blurs the signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Industry default; 90 days is the sweet spot for SaaS churn analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-document-segments-quarterly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document the active cohort segments + their churn rates in a quarterly memo. Trends only emerge with 3-4 quarters of stable definitions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Segment definitions drift silently; quarterly snapshots create comparability over time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Skip-If clause from AGENTS.md fires OR any precondition fails, STOP applying this methodology and route to the correct one. Producing an artefact when the methodology does not apply is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network skill-authoring docs">Mis-application is the most common methodology-routing failure observed in audits. An explicit STOP rule prevents the agent from synthesizing outputs for the wrong instrument.</rationale>
    </rule>


  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>