<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-rasa-framework" title="RASA Framework, Listening Levels, and Reflective Listening">
  <summary>The RASA model (Receive, Appreciate, Summarize, Ask), the five empathic listening levels, and the reflective listening formula for communicating both content and emotional understanding.</summary>

  <section title="RASA Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Work through all four RASA steps in every substantive conversation: Receive (full attention), Appreciate (acknowledgment), Summarize (reflect back), Ask (open follow-up).</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping Summarize is the most common failure — without paraphrasing, the speaker cannot confirm their message was understood and will either repeat or withhold detail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Requirements session with a skeptical stakeholder.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
R: No phone, eye contact, note-taking only.
A: "I see", nods, "Go on..."
S: "So if I understand you, the current process takes 4 hours
    because the data export step is manual — is that right?"
A: "Can you walk me through what happens after the export?"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Open vs Closed Questions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use What, How, and Tell-me-about openers instead of Is, Do, or Did — closed questions produce yes/no answers that close down exploration.</statement>
      <rationale>Open questions give the speaker control of the answer scope, which surfaces information the interviewer did not know to ask about.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Is the system slow?"
"Do you like the design?"
"Did that cause a problem?"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"How does the system perform under load?"
"What do you think about the design?"
"How did that affect your team?"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Empathic Listening Levels">
    <rule>
      <statement>Target Level 5 (Empathic) in high-stakes conversations: understand both the content of what is said and the emotional state of the speaker.</statement>
      <rationale>Levels 1-4 process words; Level 5 processes meaning and feeling. Decision-makers and clients operating under stress communicate 40-60% of their actual concern through emotional register, not explicit words.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Level 1 — Ignoring: not listening at all</item>
      <item>Level 2 — Pretending: "uh-huh" with no engagement</item>
      <item>Level 3 — Selective: hearing only parts while forming a reply</item>
      <item>Level 4 — Attentive: focusing on words, taking notes</item>
      <item>Level 5 — Empathic: understanding feeling AND content</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Reflective Listening Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reflect both content and feeling using the formula: "It sounds like you're [FEELING] because [CONTENT]."</statement>
      <rationale>Naming the feeling signals that you are operating at Level 5; the speaker either confirms (and feels understood) or corrects (providing higher-quality signal).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"It sounds like you're frustrated because the deadline keeps moving."
"It seems like you're excited about this new approach."
"I hear that you're concerned about the budget implications."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Mirroring Technique">
    <rule>
      <statement>Mirror by repeating the last 1-3 words of the speaker's sentence as a question — do not add interpretation.</statement>
      <rationale>Mirroring is the lowest-friction technique that produces the highest elaboration rate. It signals attention without leading the speaker toward a particular answer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Speaker: "We're really struggling with the deployment process."
You: "The deployment process?"
Speaker: [elaborates with root cause and context]
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
