<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-techniques-and-barriers" title="Silence, Paraphrasing, Barriers, and Agent Workflow">
  <summary>The silence technique, paraphrasing patterns, the five primary listening barriers with fixes, and agent workflow patterns for scaffolding active listening.</summary>

  <section title="Silence Technique">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pause 3-5 seconds after the speaker finishes before responding — do not fill silence immediately.</statement>
      <rationale>People add the most important information after the first pause. Immediate response signals that you were waiting to speak, not listening.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Paraphrasing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Paraphrase at least once per conversation using: "If I understand correctly, you mean..."</statement>
      <rationale>Paraphrasing forces the listener to synthesize rather than just hear, and gives the speaker an explicit correction opportunity before assumptions harden.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Barriers and Fixes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify and neutralize the five common barriers before entering a high-stakes listening situation.</statement>
      <rationale>Each barrier converts a potential Level 5 interaction into Level 3 or lower, degrading information quality and trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Planning response — fix: commit to understanding before forming any reply</item>
      <item>Judging — fix: suspend judgment until the speaker has fully finished</item>
      <item>Interrupting — fix: wait 2 seconds after they stop before speaking</item>
      <item>Advising prematurely — fix: ask "Do you want advice or just to vent?" before offering solutions</item>
      <item>Distractions — fix: remove phone, close laptop before the conversation begins</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Workflow Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use agents for pre-conversation scaffolding and post-conversation analysis, not live listening execution.</statement>
      <rationale>Active listening is fundamentally reactive to real-time emotional signals. Agents can generate question scripts and annotate transcripts, but cannot adapt in real time to tone or body language.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Two-pass agent workflow for a requirements session.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Pass 1 (before): Generate RASA-structured question flow for the session goal.
  - Output: Receive-phase opener, Appreciate phrases, Summarize starters, 5 open Ask questions.
  - Constraint: no yes/no questions, no "Is..." or "Do you..." openers.

Pass 2 (after): Annotate transcript with RASA labels.
  - Flag: closed questions used by interviewer
  - Flag: interviewer word-share > 20% in any 3-turn window
  - Flag: Summarize step skipped
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-rasa-question-flow.txt">Prompt template for generating a RASA question flow</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-transcript-annotation.txt">Prompt template for post-session transcript annotation</reference>
    <reference path="templates/speaker-ratio.py">Python snippet to measure interviewer word-share</reference>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Generating empathic reflection statements without knowing the interviewee's emotional context.</description>
    <reason>Statements like "It sounds like you're frustrated..." land as condescending or inaccurate when the person was calm. Reflection statements must respond to observed signals, not be pre-generated.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Using "What" or "How" openers for questions that still embed assumptions.</description>
    <reason>"What problems did you have with X?" assumes X caused problems. Check every open question for embedded assumptions before the session.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
