<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Active Listening Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed in real deployments. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="pre-generated-empathy" severity="high">
      <symptom>Generated script opens with "It sounds like you're frustrated..." before the speaker has said anything. Interviewee reads it as condescending and shuts down.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Internal — coaching transcripts review">Author treated reflective statements as openers; reflective statements are reactive, not generative.</root-cause>
      <fix>Mark reflective_prompts as response-only in the script. Generate them as templates with FEELING + CONTENT slots to be filled live, not pre-baked.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="closed-questions-disguised" severity="high">
      <symptom>Generated question opens with "What" but embeds an assumption: "What problems did X cause?" forcing the speaker to accept the framing.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Internal — interview audits Q1 2026">Open-opener test is purely lexical and misses semantic assumption-loading.</root-cause>
      <fix>Run an assumption-extraction pass: any "What X did Y" reformatted to "Walk me through Y" or "Tell me about Y" with no presupposition.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="live-execution-by-agent" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Team configures an agent to run a live customer interview using the RASA script. Agent cannot read tone, misses silence cues, output feels robotic.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="faion-network skill-authoring docs">Active listening is fundamentally reactive to real-time emotional signal; agents cannot adapt to body language or tone.</root-cause>
      <fix>Restrict agent role to (a) pre-conversation script generation, (b) post-conversation transcript annotation. A human runs the live conversation.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="skipped-summarize" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Script lists Receive, Appreciate, Ask but skips Summarize starters. Interviewer talks past misunderstandings; speakers repeat themselves.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Center for Creative Leadership — RASA Framework">Author abridged RASA to "what feels productive" — Ask seems substantive, Summarize seems redundant.</root-cause>
      <fix>Validator rejects scripts without ≥3 summarize_starters. Post-pass transcript annotator flags interviews where Summarize labels are absent.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
