<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="07-done-gate" title="in-progress → done gate (delegated)">
  <summary>The promotion-gate methodology gates TWO lifecycle transitions. The `backlog → todo` gate is covered by 01-04 + 06. The `in-progress → done` gate is delegated to the readiness-checklist methodology and enforces additional quality gates.</summary>

  <section title="Delegation rule">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>For `in-progress → done` transitions, this methodology delegates to `readiness-checklist`. The readiness.md file MUST exist and every item ticked with evidence before the feature can be moved.</statement>
      <rationale>The done-gate has 10 items with conditional applicability (API tests, Playwright, UI heuristics). Replicating that logic here would drift; single source of truth lives in readiness-checklist.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Additional quality-gate items enforced at the done gate">
    <list>
      <item>API tests pass — REQUIRED when the feature touched backend code (any file under backend source tree).</item>
      <item>Playwright positive AND negative cases pass — REQUIRED when the feature has a user-facing flow.</item>
      <item>Surface-coupling check — REQUIRED when the feature added a new public surface (skill trigger, API path, CLI flag, exported name).</item>
    </list>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The reviewer MUST verify which conditionals apply by inspecting the git diff, NOT by accepting the developer's self-assessment.</statement>
      <rationale>The author has a blind spot for what counts as "user-facing" or "public surface". The diff is the source of truth.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="What fails the done gate">
    <antipattern>
      <description>readiness.md exists but several items are blank or marked "n/a" without justification.</description>
      <reason>Blank ≠ pass. The done gate is binary; blanks block.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>API tests skipped because "the change was small" although a backend file changed.</description>
      <reason>The conditional is on the diff, not on the developer's estimate of impact.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="../readiness-checklist/AGENTS.md">Canonical 10-item readiness checklist; this gate consumes it.</reference>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-core-rules.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
