<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-charter" title="Project Charter: Elements, SMART Criteria, Version Control">
  <summary>Rules for authoring a project charter that is legally valid as a contractual artifact, version-controlled, and re-baselined only through approved change requests.</summary>

  <section title="Required Charter Elements">
    <rule>
      <statement>A project charter must include: project purpose, SMART objectives, high-level scope (in/out), named success criteria with baseline and target, key stakeholders with roles, PM authority level, and high-level budget and timeline. Missing any element makes the charter unenforceable.</statement>
      <rationale>Charters without measurable success criteria degenerate into "on time, on budget, on scope" — meaningless without baselines. Every element must be present before formal authorization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Success criteria must be SMART: specific metric, current baseline, target value, and by-date. Reject "improve customer satisfaction" — require "NPS from 32 to 45 by Q3 2026".</statement>
      <rationale>Vague success criteria enable scope creep and make project closure decisions impossible. Every criterion must answer: how will we know we succeeded?</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Charter Version Control">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store the charter in git as charter.yaml, signed (Signed-off-by or digital signature reference), and tagged baseline-v1 at authorization. Re-baseline only via approved change requests with sponsor sign-off recorded in git history.</statement>
      <rationale>Charters that drift from reality without version history cannot be audited. A PDF filed and never reconciled is not a controlled document.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-baseline triggers: scope change greater than 10%, schedule slip greater than 15%, cost overrun greater than 10%, or sponsor change. Anything below these thresholds is managed via the change log without a full re-baseline.</statement>
      <rationale>Frequent re-baselines reset performance measurement and hide variance history. Reserve re-baselining for genuine scope shifts that make the original baseline meaningless.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent drafts charter with fabricated stakeholder names, dollar figures, and milestone dates.</description>
      <reason>All numeric and named values must come from explicit input fields; never let the agent infer or fill in charter data from context. Charter hallucinations become contractual commitments.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent edits a charter mid-flight without a change request reference.</description>
      <reason>Charter freeze is a governance discipline. Enforce with branch protection and CODEOWNERS; any edit without an approved CR ID in the commit message is rejected.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
