<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="project-integration Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for project-integration. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A project charter must include: project purpose, SMART objectives, high-level scope (in/out), named success criteria with baseline and target, key stakeholders with roles, PM authority level, and high-level budget and timeline. Missing any element makes the charter unenforceable.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Charters without measurable success criteria degenerate into "on time, on budget, on scope" — meaningless without baselines. Every element must be present before formal authorization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Success criteria must be SMART: specific metric, current baseline, target value, and by-date. Reject "improve customer satisfaction" — require "NPS from 32 to 45 by Q3 2026".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Vague success criteria enable scope creep and make project closure decisions impossible. Every criterion must answer: how will we know we succeeded?</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store the charter in git as charter.yaml, signed (Signed-off-by or digital signature reference), and tagged baseline-v1 at authorization. Re-baseline only via approved change requests with sponsor sign-off recorded in git history.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Charters that drift from reality without version history cannot be audited. A PDF filed and never reconciled is not a controlled document.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-baseline triggers: scope change greater than 10%, schedule slip greater than 15%, cost overrun greater than 10%, or sponsor change. Anything below these thresholds is managed via the change log without a full re-baseline.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Frequent re-baselines reset performance measurement and hide variance history. Reserve re-baselining for genuine scope shifts that make the original baseline meaningless.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Compute RAG from measurable thresholds, never from opinion. Schedule: GREEN if SPI &gt;= 0.95, YELLOW 0.85-0.95, RED below 0.85. Cost: GREEN if CPI &gt;= 0.95, YELLOW 0.85-0.95, RED below 0.85. Overall: worst single dimension.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opinion-based status defaults to GREEN because pessimistic framing is rarer in training data and in human psychology. Threshold-based computation removes the bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Missing data is YELLOW with reason, not GREEN. If a required metric is null, surface it as a gap rather than assuming everything is on track.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs return GREEN when data is absent; the correct response is to flag the missing input as a monitoring gap requiring investigation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every change request must traverse all 8 component plans (scope, schedule, cost, quality, risk, resources, comms, procurement) and emit an impact matrix before approval. Standalone scope edits without schedule and cost re-estimates are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Silo approval of scope changes is the primary mechanism by which integration fails. A scope addition that "won't affect timeline" always affects timeline — the PM just hasn't computed it yet.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run change control as a PR: CR description, cross-area impact matrix, baseline patch proposal, sponsor approval, merge tagged baseline-vN+1. Every baseline change must have a unique CR ID and immutable diff in git history.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Audit trails are mandatory in regulated programs. A git-based change control system provides immutable history with timestamps and approvers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agents have zero authority to approve baseline changes. The agent proposes baseline patches; the sponsor or change board approves via their recorded sign-off before merge.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Autonomous baseline changes by agents constitute an audit risk and a governance failure. Human approval is non-negotiable for any change touching cost or schedule baselines.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
