<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-status-and-change" title="Status Reporting and Integrated Change Control">
  <summary>Deterministic RAG computation rules from EVM metrics, change control workflow as git PRs, and integration antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="RAG Computation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Compute RAG from measurable thresholds, never from opinion. Schedule: GREEN if SPI &gt;= 0.95, YELLOW 0.85-0.95, RED below 0.85. Cost: GREEN if CPI &gt;= 0.95, YELLOW 0.85-0.95, RED below 0.85. Overall: worst single dimension.</statement>
      <rationale>Opinion-based status defaults to GREEN because pessimistic framing is rarer in training data and in human psychology. Threshold-based computation removes the bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Missing data is YELLOW with reason, not GREEN. If a required metric is null, surface it as a gap rather than assuming everything is on track.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs return GREEN when data is absent; the correct response is to flag the missing input as a monitoring gap requiring investigation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/status-rag.py">Deterministic RAG from EVM + risk YAML baselines</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Integrated Change Control">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every change request must traverse all 8 component plans (scope, schedule, cost, quality, risk, resources, comms, procurement) and emit an impact matrix before approval. Standalone scope edits without schedule and cost re-estimates are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Silo approval of scope changes is the primary mechanism by which integration fails. A scope addition that "won't affect timeline" always affects timeline — the PM just hasn't computed it yet.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run change control as a PR: CR description, cross-area impact matrix, baseline patch proposal, sponsor approval, merge tagged baseline-vN+1. Every baseline change must have a unique CR ID and immutable diff in git history.</statement>
      <rationale>Audit trails are mandatory in regulated programs. A git-based change control system provides immutable history with timestamps and approvers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Agents have zero authority to approve baseline changes. The agent proposes baseline patches; the sponsor or change board approves via their recorded sign-off before merge.</statement>
      <rationale>Autonomous baseline changes by agents constitute an audit risk and a governance failure. Human approval is non-negotiable for any change touching cost or schedule baselines.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Component plans in heterogeneous tools (Jira for tasks, Smartsheet for schedule, Excel for budget) without a normalised export layer.</description>
      <reason>Without a common format, the integration agent cannot compute cross-area impact. Require each plan owner to export to a canonical YAML schema at each status cycle.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Status report generation that leaks vendor pricing, customer names, or employee performance into a shared report.</description>
      <reason>Component plans often contain commercially sensitive and personally identifiable information. Run a scrubber on the integration report before publishing to broad channels.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
