<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="project-integration Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for project-integration as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent drafts charter with fabricated stakeholder names, dollar figures, and milestone dates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>All numeric and named values must come from explicit input fields; never let the agent infer or fill in charter data from context. Charter hallucinations become contractual commitments.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent edits a charter mid-flight without a change request reference.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Charter freeze is a governance discipline. Enforce with branch protection and CODEOWNERS; any edit without an approved CR ID in the commit message is rejected.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Component plans in heterogeneous tools (Jira for tasks, Smartsheet for schedule, Excel for budget) without a normalised export layer.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a common format, the integration agent cannot compute cross-area impact. Require each plan owner to export to a canonical YAML schema at each status cycle.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Status report generation that leaks vendor pricing, customer names, or employee performance into a shared report.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Component plans often contain commercially sensitive and personally identifiable information. Run a scrubber on the integration report before publishing to broad channels.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Charters drift from reality if not version-controlled; many orgs sign a PDF, file it, and never reconcile against the live plan.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Version control with git tags enables audits and baseline resets. A PDF filed once and never updated is a liability in regulated programs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Integrated change control becomes a bottleneck when CAB / CCB meets infrequently — agile tempo collides with waterfall governance.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Async PR-based change control with async approval (e.g., 24-hour approval SLA) scales better than synchronous CAB meetings.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs producing status reports tend toward "GREEN washing" unless forced to compute RAG from quantitative inputs (variance thresholds).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Threshold-based RAG computation is the only reliable antidote to LLM optimism bias in status reporting.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>The PM-as-integrator model assumes the PM has access; in matrix orgs functional managers gate visibility and the integration view is incomplete.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Integration requires transparency across all 8 areas. Matrix orgs need a central repository (git, Confluence, SharePoint) where all plans are visible to the PM role, not just to function leads.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Charter "success criteria" often degenerate into "on time, on budget, on scope" — meaningless without baselines and measurable outcomes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Success criteria must be SMART and tied to business value, not just schedule/cost/scope conformance. "NPS 45 by Q3" is measurable; "increase revenue" is not.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
