<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Sprint Goal Formula Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Sprint Goal Formula application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="three-parts-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every sprint goal MUST contain three named parts: (a) outcome — verb + user/system change, (b) boundary — explicit in/out scope edge, (c) measure — verifiable signal. Any goal missing a part fails the planning gate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scrum Guide 2020 §Sprint Goal">Scrum Guide 2020 §Sprint Goal — anchors Sprint Goal Formula rule `three-parts-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="single-sentence-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The sprint goal MUST fit in one sentence ≤30 words. If it cannot, the sprint is targeting two goals and MUST be split or de-scoped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Compactness-as-recitability research">Compactness-as-recitability research — anchors Sprint Goal Formula rule `single-sentence-cap`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="binary-scope-filter" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mid-sprint scope additions MUST be graded with the binary test: &apos;does this advance the outcome inside the boundary?&apos;. &apos;Maybe / sort of&apos; counts as no.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sprint goal field guides">Sprint goal field guides — anchors Sprint Goal Formula rule `binary-scope-filter`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="binary-review-grade" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>At sprint review, the measure portion MUST be evaluated pass or fail — no partial credit. A failed measure triggers a retro root-cause discussion as the first agenda item.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scrum review discipline">Scrum review discipline — anchors Sprint Goal Formula rule `binary-review-grade`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-two-concurrent-goals" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A team MUST NOT commit to two concurrent sprint goals. Two genuinely independent outcomes = over-allocation; PM MUST descope or escalate staffing before sprint start.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-throat-to-choke practice">Single-throat-to-choke practice — anchors Sprint Goal Formula rule `no-two-concurrent-goals`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
