<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="audience-segmentation">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>user-researcher</domain>
    <summary>A structured process to divide a market into distinct groups using two to three differentiating dimensions, score each against weighted attractiveness criteria, and select at most one primary target.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>segmentation</tag>
      <tag>targeting</tag>
      <tag>marketing-strategy</tag>
      <tag>product-strategy</tag>
      <tag>positioning</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Audience Segmentation</title>
    <summary>A structured process to divide a potential market into distinct, mutually exclusive groups using two to three differentiating dimensions (demographic, behavioural, psychographic, or needs-based), score each segment against six weighted attractiveness criteria, and select at most one primary target for pre-traction products. Segments are maintained as YAML/JSON for reproducible quarterly re-scoring.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>"Everyone is our customer" erodes paid-acquisition efficiency and message resonance. Segmentation makes targeting trade-offs explicit and falsifiable: by scoring Size, Growth, Reachability, Profitability, Fit, and Competition with fixed weights, teams can defend their choice of primary segment without relying on intuition. Demographic-only segmentation is the most common failure mode — it yields lookalikes that do not predict purchase.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch positioning when the team is debating which buyer to target first.</item>
        <item>Post-launch when "everyone is our customer" is eroding paid-acquisition efficiency.</item>
        <item>Pricing-tier design that needs distinct buying behaviours and willingness-to-pay levels.</item>
        <item>Pivoting into a new market where the prior segmentation no longer maps.</item>
        <item>Product-tier or product-line decisions (free/pro/enterprise; consumer/SMB/mid-market).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-traction MVPs with fewer than 50 customers — use one persona, not segment matrices.</item>
        <item>Strict niche businesses where the entire ICP fits one segment by design.</item>
        <item>Account-based sales motions where named accounts replace segmentation.</item>
        <item>Ephemeral campaigns — A/B-test creatives instead.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="segmentation-types">
      <p>Use at most two or three dimensions per segmentation; denser matrices are unreadable in stakeholder conversations. Combine quantitative (firmographics, behavioural) and qualitative (needs, attitudes) dimensions — pure quant misses messaging insights.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Demographic: age, income, occupation, company size, industry. Best for B2B targeting and pricing tiers.</item>
        <item>Behavioural: usage frequency, purchase history, feature usage, engagement level, buying stage. Best for retention and product development.</item>
        <item>Psychographic: values, attitudes, lifestyle, motivations. Best for messaging and brand positioning.</item>
        <item>Needs-based: problem severity, current solution, budget, speed priority, support needs. Best for product tiers and pricing strategy.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="five-step-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Gather data from CRM, analytics, survey responses, and sales conversations; choose two to three dimensions that maximise inter-segment variance and minimise intra-segment variance.</statement>
        <rationale>Dimensions chosen without variance analysis produce segments that look different but behave the same — they do not guide distinct go-to-market or product decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Validate segment size against an addressable population (LinkedIn audience estimate, paid-ads reach, list-rental quote); theoretical size means nothing without addressability evidence.</statement>
        <rationale>Segments that are not addressable via any channel are worthless regardless of their size on paper.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Ensure mutually exclusive segments: every customer should fit one and only one segment after rules apply. Orphans signal definition gaps.</statement>
        <rationale>Overlapping segments prevent attribution and make channel and pricing decisions ambiguous.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include a do-not-target segment with explicit reasoning (low LTV, high CAC, support-cost-heavy). Pair the top segment with one channel and one message.</statement>
        <rationale>Without an explicit do-not-target definition, teams waste acquisition budget on low-ROI users.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="attractiveness-scoring-rubric">
      <p>Score each segment 1-5 on six criteria; apply fixed weights to produce a weighted total. Re-score quarterly using the same rubric weights; weight changes must be flagged as a methodology change.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Size (20%): how many people or companies are in this segment?</item>
        <item>Growth (15%): is the segment growing as a share of the market?</item>
        <item>Reachability (20%): can we access them economically via existing channels?</item>
        <item>Profitability (20%): will they pay enough to sustain the business model?</item>
        <item>Fit (15%): do our strengths match this segment's needs?</item>
        <item>Competition (10%): how crowded is this segment currently?</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Flag any score with no evidence; do not accept agent-generated segment sizes ("estimated 200K SMBs in NYC") without a cited source.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs invent segment sizes that are decorative; unsupported numbers give false precision to strategic decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="worked-crm-tool-example">
      <p>CRM tool segmentation: dimensions = team size x sales complexity. Decision: focus on Agency segment.</p>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Dimensions: Team size (Solo, 2-5, 6-20, 20+) x Sales complexity (Transactional, Consultative)

| Segment     | Profile               | Primary Need         | WTP     | Weighted Score |
|-------------|-----------------------|----------------------|---------|----------------|
| Freelancer  | Solo x Transactional  | Simple pipeline      | $9/mo   | 2.8            |
| Agency      | 2-5 x Consultative    | Deal tracking        | $29/mo  | 4.1            |
| Startup     | 6-20 x Transactional  | Automation, reporting| $49/mo  | 3.5            |
| Enterprise  | 20+ x Consultative    | Custom, integrations | Custom  | 2.2 (reach)    |

Decision: Focus on Agency — highest weighted score; high WTP, underserved, reachable via design communities.
Do-not-target: Enterprise (reachability = 1; sales cycle exceeds runway).
]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="worked-online-course-example">
      <p>Online course segmentation: dimensions = learning goal x time available.</p>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Dimensions: Goal (Career change, Skill upgrade, Hobby) x Time (<5h/wk, 5-10h, 10+h)

| Segment          | Profile                | Key Trait                  | WTP    |
|------------------|------------------------|----------------------------|--------|
| Career Changers  | Career change x 10+h   | Committed, outcome-focused | $400+  |
| Upskilling Pros  | Upgrade x 5-10h        | Busy, pays for time savings | $150+  |
| Hobbyists        | Hobby x <5h            | Fun-focused, price-sensitive| $30    |

Decision: Focus on Upskilling Pros — pays for time savings, reachable via LinkedIn and newsletters.
]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Producing eight micro-segments using five dimensions without a cap.</description>
        <reason>Segments beyond four become unmanageable; force a two to three dimension cap and merge the long tail into a do-not-target group.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Demographic-only segmentation (age, gender, location) for a B2B product.</description>
        <reason>Demographics predict lookup, not purchase; B2B requires industry, employee count, and role as primary axes, with needs-based dimensions second.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Behavioural-clustering agent over-fits to one outlier whale customer, creating a segment of one.</description>
        <reason>Require feature standardisation and scree-plot evidence for k before accepting cluster results.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Reverse-ETL bot syncing segments to ad platforms without an approval gate.</description>
        <reason>Agents merging segments to paid media without a kill switch can exhaust ad budgets in hours; require human approval before production activation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Use agents to ingest CRM, analytics, and survey data; propose candidate segmentation dimensions; score segments against attractiveness criteria from this methodology; emit profile cards. Decisions about which segment to pursue belong to humans (commercial trade-offs). Agents should never propose a target without addressability evidence and a sizing range. Maintain segments as a structured artefact (YAML/JSON) so re-scoring is reproducible quarter-over-quarter.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-persona-builder-agent — produces persona-grade detail per chosen segment.</item>
        <item>A dimension-finder subagent: runs feature-importance / variance analysis on CRM/analytics features to surface the two most differentiating axes.</item>
        <item>brainstorm — diverges on candidate segment names + needs framings, converges on at most four mutually exclusive segments.</item>
        <item>A scorer subagent: applies the weighted criteria (Size 20, Growth 15, Reachability 20, Profitability 20, Fit 15, Competition 10) consistently across segments.</item>
        <item>improver — quarterly refresh against fresh data.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Prompt patterns:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Given the attached CRM export (`crm.csv`) with fields `[plan, mrr, signup_source, employee_count, industry, churn_30, feature_use_score]`, propose two candidate dimensions that maximise inter-segment variance and minimise intra-segment variance. Show a confusion matrix for each. Output as `dimensions.json`.
]]></code>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Given segments `[A, B, C]` and the attractiveness rubric below, score each 1-5 per criterion with one-line justification. Compute weighted total. Flag any score with no evidence.
]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools for segmentation analysis and activation:</p>
      <list>
        <item>dbt — Cohort and segment SQL pipelines. Docs: https://docs.getdbt.com</item>
        <item>Posthog / Amplitude / Mixpanel APIs — Behavioural-segment cohorts. Docs: https://posthog.com / https://amplitude.com/docs/apis</item>
        <item>HubSpot / Salesforce CLI — CRM segment ops. Docs: https://developers.hubspot.com / https://developer.salesforce.com</item>
        <item>Segment / RudderStack — CDP routing per segment. Docs: https://segment.com / https://www.rudderstack.com</item>
        <item>pandas + scikit-learn — k-means / hierarchical clustering for segmentation. Install: pip install pandas scikit-learn</item>
        <item>kmodes — Categorical-variable clustering. Install: pip install kmodes</item>
        <item>Notion / Airtable API — Segment library. Docs: https://developers.notion.com</item>
        <item>Census / Hightouch — Reverse-ETL segments to ad/email tools. Docs: https://www.getcensus.com / https://hightouch.com</item>
        <item>Crayon / Klue (if exposed) — Competitive intel per segment. Docs: https://www.crayon.co / https://klue.com</item>
      </list>
      <p>Services and applications:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Segment / RudderStack (SaaS/OSS) — CDP for segment-driven activation. Agent-friendly via REST + SDK.</item>
        <item>Census / Hightouch (SaaS) — Reverse-ETL to ad platforms. Agent-friendly via REST.</item>
        <item>HubSpot / Salesforce (SaaS) — CRM as segment ground truth. Agent-friendly via REST.</item>
        <item>Posthog / Amplitude / Mixpanel (SaaS) — Behavioural data. Agent-friendly via REST.</item>
        <item>Apollo.io / ZoomInfo (SaaS) — B2B firmographic enrichment. Agent-friendly via REST.</item>
        <item>Clearbit (now HubSpot) (SaaS) — Firmographic data on sign-ups. Agent-friendly via REST.</item>
        <item>SurveyMonkey / Typeform (SaaS) — Psychographic survey delivery. Agent-friendly via REST.</item>
        <item>Forsta / Qualtrics (SaaS) — Enterprise segmentation studies. Agent-friendly via REST.</item>
        <item>Productboard (SaaS) — Segment ↔ feature roadmap link. Agent-friendly via REST.</item>
        <item>Crayon / Klue (SaaS) — Competitive density per segment. Agent-friendly via REST.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pick two dimensions, not five — anything denser is unreadable in stakeholder conversations.</item>
        <item>Combine quantitative (firmographics, behavioural) and qualitative (needs, attitudes); pure quant misses messaging insights.</item>
        <item>Validate segment size against an addressable population (LinkedIn audience, paid-ads reach, list rentals); theoretical size means nothing.</item>
        <item>Always include a "do-not-target" segment with explicit reasoning (low LTV, high CAC, support-cost-heavy).</item>
        <item>Pair the top segment with one channel and one message; if you can't pick one, the segment is too broad.</item>
        <item>Re-score quarterly using the same rubric weights; weight changes must be flagged as a methodology change.</item>
        <item>Sanity-check exclusivity: every customer should fit one and only one segment after rules apply; orphans signal definition gaps.</item>
        <item>Map segments to existing personas explicitly; the two artefacts must agree.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations-and-gotchas">
      <p>Segment definitions decay; behavioural segments especially shift in 6-12 months as products and competitors evolve.</p>
      <p>2x2 matrices give clean visuals but oversimplify multi-dimensional reality; don't over-trust them.</p>
      <p>Demographic-only segmentation is the most common failure mode — yields lookalikes that don't predict purchase.</p>
      <p>Segments that are not addressable (no channel reaches them economically) are worthless regardless of theoretical size.</p>
      <p>Mutually exclusive segmentation in B2B is hard: a contact may be both "decision maker" and "user".</p>
      <p>Agents asked to "find segments" without constraints often output 8 micro-segments by demographics; force a 2-3 dimension cap.</p>
      <p>LLMs invent segment sizes ("estimated 200K SMBs in NYC") that are decorative; demand a source for any quantitative claim.</p>
      <p>Behavioural-clustering agents over-fit to noisy features (e.g., one outlier whale); require feature standardisation and scree-plot evidence for k.</p>
      <p>B2B segmentation generated from B2C tropes (lifestyle, age) misses fit/firmographics; force industry, employee_count, role as priors.</p>
      <p>Reverse-ETL bots syncing segments to ad tools without a kill switch can blow ad budgets; require approval gating in production.</p>
      <p>Agents merging "current solution" responses across surveys conflate competitors with substitutes; clarify in the prompt.</p>
      <p>When proposing the final target, agents tend to pick the largest segment; force a weighted-score table so reachability and fit aren't ignored.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="k-means-clustering-script">
      <p>Inline behavioural-segment k-means (deterministic seed for reproducibility):</p>
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# segment.py — k-means on usage features, emits segments.json
import json, pandas as pd
from sklearn.preprocessing import StandardScaler
from sklearn.cluster import KMeans

df = pd.read_csv("usage.csv")  # cols: customer_id, mrr, dau_w, feat_score, seats
features = ["mrr", "dau_w", "feat_score", "seats"]
X = StandardScaler().fit_transform(df[features])

km = KMeans(n_clusters=4, n_init=20, random_state=42).fit(X)
df["segment"] = km.labels_

profile = (
    df.groupby("segment")[features]
      .agg(["mean", "median", "count"])
      .round(2)
      .to_dict()
)
out = {
    "n_segments": 4,
    "feature_importance": dict(zip(features, km.cluster_centers_.var(axis=0).tolist())),
    "profile": profile,
}
with open("segments.json", "w") as f:
    json.dump(out, f, indent=2)
]]></code>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/segmentation-analysis.md" purpose="Full segmentation analysis doc with scoring table and target strategy."/>
      <template path="templates/segment-profile-card.md" purpose="Single-segment profile card for stakeholder communication."/>
      <template path="templates/segment.py" purpose="k-means clustering on usage features, emits segments.json."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.bain.com/insights/management-tools-customer-segmentation/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
