<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Gumroad Ops Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed in indie Gumroad operations. Each pairs symptom + root cause + fix keyed to a methodology rule.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="fm-cover-blur" severity="high">
      <symptom>Listing cover renders blurry on the Gumroad product page and on social previews; conversion rate &lt; 1%.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Gumroad image-pipeline behaviour">Cover uploaded at &lt;1280×720; Gumroad upscales it for the product hero, producing visible artefacts.</root-cause>
      <fix>Re-export cover at ≥1600×900 PNG. Verify via the validator (r1 + listing.cover_width_px / cover_height_px checks). Push and re-snapshot Open Graph.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-double-vat" severity="high">
      <symptom>EU buyer reports being charged VAT twice — once by Gumroad checkout, once on the founder's separate invoice. Refund request + complaint email.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="MoR misunderstanding">Founder kept the pre-Gumroad invoicing flow active even after enabling Gumroad as Merchant of Record.</root-cause>
      <fix>Disable the parallel VAT invoice for Gumroad-source orders. Gumroad's receipt is the legal invoice. Issue refund for the duplicate VAT; apology email. Rule r2.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-license-bypass" severity="high">
      <symptom>Software pirated 48h after launch — same hard-coded key appears in cracked builds on GitHub.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="License API not enabled">License key embedded in the binary; no online validation.</root-cause>
      <fix>Wire Gumroad License API: `POST /v2/licenses/verify` at startup + daily. Revoke compromised keys. Re-issue per-buyer keys via Gumroad. Rule r3.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-affiliate-link-broken" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Affiliate complains their tracked clicks show 0 conversions despite known sales; affiliate quits the program.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Gumroad affiliate parameter handling">Founder's checkout URL drops the `?affiliate=` parameter when redirecting through their own landing page.</root-cause>
      <fix>Preserve affiliate query params through every hop. Test the affiliate flow end-to-end before announcing the program. Set commission_pct in [30, 50] per r4 to keep affiliates engaged.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
