<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="wcag-22-compliance">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>WCAG 2.2 compliance baseline by 2025/2026: focus visibility, target size 24x24px, drag alternatives, accessible authentication, and six new success criteria.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>wcag</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
      <tag>compliance</tag>
      <tag>a11y</tag>
      <tag>standards</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-24</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>WCAG 2.2 Compliance</title>
    <summary>WCAG 2.2 released October 2023, baseline compliance standard by 2025-2026. Covers nine new success criteria including focus visibility, target size, drag alternatives, and accessible authentication.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>WCAG 2.2 introduces nine new success criteria targeting modern interaction patterns (dragging, authentication, help consistency) and real-world failures that earlier versions missed. It is the global baseline compliance standard by 2025-2026 for government and enterprise procurements. Automated scanners catch only 30-40% of issues; manual validation and assistive-technology testing remain essential.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Validating a web product against WCAG 2.2 AA — the global baseline by 2025/2026.</item>
        <item>Adding a CI gate that flags new violations of the nine WCAG 2.2 success criteria added on top of 2.1.</item>
        <item>Auditing focus visibility, target size, dragging, accessible authentication, redundant entry, consistent help.</item>
        <item>Preparing VPAT 2.5 / ACR conformance documentation.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Native mobile-only apps without web surfaces — defer to platform a11y APIs (UIAccessibility, Android a11y).</item>
        <item>Internal tooling with a documented narrow user pool that does not include disabled users (rare; document the decision).</item>
        <item>WCAG 3.0 silver-bullet conversations — 3.0 is still working draft; do not retire 2.2 baselines.</item>
        <item>Pure visual design review — heuristics and cognitive walkthrough cover that better.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="What's New in WCAG 2.2">
      <p>Nine new success criteria released October 2023 as part of the WCAG 2.2 recommendation.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>All nine new WCAG 2.2 success criteria are considered baseline accessibility requirements and must be tested before launch.</statement>
        <rationale>Each new SC targets a real-world failure mode that earlier versions missed. Together they address focus indicators, target size, modern interaction patterns, and authentication barriers.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[WCAG 2.2 New Success Criteria:

2.4.11 Focus Not Obscured (Min) — AA
  Focus indicator must be at least partially visible.

2.4.12 Focus Not Obscured (Enhanced) — AAA
  Focus indicator fully visible.

2.4.13 Focus Appearance — AAA
  2px minimum focus indicator.

2.5.7 Dragging Movements — AA
  All drag actions have non-drag alternative.

2.5.8 Target Size (Minimum) — AA
  24x24 CSS pixels minimum.

3.2.6 Consistent Help — A
  Help mechanism in same location across pages.

3.3.7 Redundant Entry — A
  Don't ask for same info twice.

3.3.8 Accessible Authentication (Min) — AA
  No cognitive function tests for login.

3.3.9 Accessible Authentication (Enhanced) — AAA
  No object/image recognition for login.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="Target Size Requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>All interactive targets must be at least 24x24 CSS pixels minimum, or 44x44 CSS pixels for touch targets (recommended).</statement>
        <rationale>Users with motor control difficulties require larger targets; 24x24 is the minimum; 44x44 is best practice for mobile and touch interfaces.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="css"><![CDATA[/* Minimum 24x24px */
.button {
  min-width: 24px;
  min-height: 24px;
  /* Or 44x44px for touch targets (recommended) */
}]]></code>
      </example>
      <note>Target size is computed including spacing exception; agents must read the SC carefully to avoid over-reporting.</note>
    </section>
    <section name="Dragging Alternatives">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every drag action must have a non-drag alternative control. Ship the non-drag alternative first; add drag as enhancement only after keyboard/pointer alternatives exist.</statement>
        <rationale>Drag-only interfaces exclude users with motor disabilities, tremors, and alternative input devices. Non-drag alternatives must be discoverable, not hidden.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Drag Action | Alternative Required
------------|--------------------
Drag to reorder list | Up/down buttons
Drag to resize panel | Input field for value
Drag to select area | Click corners + shift-click
Drag to zoom map | + / - buttons]]></code>
      </example>
      <note>Drag alternatives often added as hidden controls that fail "discoverability" — passes scanner, fails users.</note>
    </section>
    <section name="Focus Visibility">
      <rule>
        <statement>Document focus styles in design tokens (`--focus-ring-width`, `--focus-ring-color`) so 2.4.11/12/13 stay consistent across the site. Never use `outline: none` without a custom focus indicator.</statement>
        <rationale>Default browser focus indicators vary; custom focus styles must be consistently visible, have sufficient contrast, and not be obscured by sticky headers or other UI.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <note>Focus visibility depends on z-index and sticky headers at runtime — needs viewport + keyboard simulation testing. Automated scanners miss z-index violations.</note>
    </section>
    <section name="Accessible Authentication">
      <rule>
        <statement>Authentication mechanisms must not require cognitive function tests (math, memory, recitation) or object/image recognition. Test authentication with no copy/paste, no autofill — captcha patterns now fail 3.3.8/9.</statement>
        <rationale>Users with cognitive disabilities cannot reliably complete CAPTCHA or memory-based authentication. Allow login with username/password, biometric, or passkeys; never gatekeep with cognitive tests.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <note>WCAG 3.0 guidance on authentication is still evolving; 2.2 baseline is the current standard.</note>
    </section>
    <section name="Consistent Help">
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep the "Help" link or contact mechanism in identical position site-wide (usually footer or persistent header). Cross-page reasoning is required to validate this — single-page scanners miss it.</statement>
        <rationale>Users need to locate help quickly; moving it between pages adds cognitive load and breaks discoverability expectations.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Limitations of Automation">
      <list>
        <item>Automated scanners catch ~30-40% of WCAG issues; manual + assistive-tech testing still required.</item>
        <item>"Accessible Authentication (Min)" and "Consistent Help" need cross-page reasoning — single-page scanners miss them.</item>
        <item>"Focus Not Obscured" depends on z-index / sticky headers at runtime — needs viewport + keyboard simulation.</item>
        <item>Drag alternatives often added as hidden controls that fail "discoverability" — passes scanner, fails users.</item>
        <item>Target size 24x24 CSS px is computed including spacing exception — agents misread the SC.</item>
        <item>Color-contrast checks fail on gradients and images-of-text — need pixel sampling, not CSS reads.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>Use a subagent to run axe-core / Pa11y / Lighthouse on each route, parse violations, and triage them against WCAG 2.2 SC IDs. A second agent walks new SCs (2.4.11, 2.4.12, 2.4.13, 2.5.7, 2.5.8, 3.2.6, 3.3.7, 3.3.8, 3.3.9) by writing Playwright keyboard scripts that inspect focus rect, target size, drag alternatives. A human reviews authentication and help-consistency findings.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>`faion-usability-agent` — manual SC evaluation, screen-reader walk-throughs.</item>
        <item>`faion-sdd-executor-agent` — patches code, adds CI a11y gates, runs axe in Playwright.</item>
        <item>`faion-ux-researcher-agent` — recruits AT users for validation.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools">
      <list>
        <item>`axe-core` / `@axe-core/cli` — rule engine, ~57% of WCAG covered. Install: `npm i -g @axe-core/cli`; deque.com/axe</item>
        <item>`pa11y` / `pa11y-ci` — headless WCAG scan, CI-friendly. Install: `npm i -g pa11y-ci`; pa11y.org</item>
        <item>Lighthouse CI — full audit incl. a11y subset. Install: `npm i -g @lhci/cli`</item>
        <item>`nu html-validator` — catches HTML errors that break a11y trees. validator.github.io/validator</item>
        <item>`wcag-em-report-tool` — W3C evaluation report builder. github.com/w3c/wcag-em-report-tool</item>
        <item>`playwright` + `@axe-core/playwright` — stateful, route-by-route a11y in CI. playwright.dev</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Services">
      <list>
        <item>Deque axe DevTools — SaaS+OSS, REST API, Pro tier adds Intelligent Guided Tests for 2.2 SCs.</item>
        <item>Siteimprove — SaaS, REST API for crawl results, enterprise-grade tracking.</item>
        <item>Tenon.io — SaaS, REST API, strong color-contrast logic.</item>
        <item>Stark — SaaS plugin, Figma plugin first, API for some plans, good for design-time checks.</item>
        <item>TPGi ARC — SaaS, REST API, manual + automated hybrid.</item>
        <item>Avoid: Equally AI / accessiBe overlays — they often regress UX, not a substitute for fixes.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Run automated scans on every PR; fail on any new 2.2 SC violation, warn on existing.</item>
        <item>Pair each automated check with one human AT walkthrough per release on top user flows.</item>
        <item>Document focus styles in tokens (`--focus-ring-width`, `--focus-ring-color`) so 2.4.11/12/13 stay consistent.</item>
        <item>For drag interactions, ship the non-drag alternative first; add drag as enhancement.</item>
        <item>Keep "Help" link in identical position site-wide (3.2.6) — usually footer or persistent header.</item>
        <item>Test authentication with no copy/paste, no autofill — many "captcha" patterns now fail 3.3.8/9.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI Agent Gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM assumes "accessible" means "alt text added"; 2.2 is mostly about interaction quality.</description>
        <reason>Accessibility spans semantic structure, keyboard navigation, focus management, cognitive load, color contrast, and more. Alt text is one small piece.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent misses focus-indicator regressions caused by `outline: none` in design tokens.</description>
        <reason>Linting for `outline: none` without a paired custom focus indicator is essential; agents often remove outlines and forget to add custom styles.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>`aria-hidden` and `inert` get over-applied; agent must verify keyboard reachability after applying.</description>
        <reason>These attributes hide content from assistive tech; over-applying them removes keyboard access to interactive elements.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Color-contrast checks fail on gradients and images-of-text — agent reads CSS only.</description>
        <reason>Pixel-level sampling is needed for gradient contrast; CSS reads cannot infer rendered colors. Images-of-text need OCR + contrast analysis.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Target-size SC: agent does not include the spacing exception; over-reports icon buttons.</description>
        <reason>The SC allows spacing around the target; if 24x24 includes padding, it passes. Agents must read the full SC text.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent ships an "overlay/widget" as a fix.</description>
        <reason>Never let an agent ship an overlay or JavaScript "accessibility tool" as a fix — they usually make things worse. Flag and refuse.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG22/"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/"/>
      <link href="https://deque.com/blog/whats-new-in-wcag-2-2/"/>
      <link href="https://tpgi.com/wcag-2-2-and-what-it-means-for-you/"/>
      <link href="https://itic.org/policy/accessibility/vpat"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/dequelabs/axe-core"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
