<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Docker Compose Core Rules">
  <summary>Concrete rules for writing production-safe Compose files: healthchecks, network isolation, volumes, resource limits, and log rotation.</summary>

  <section title="Service Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Omit the top-level `version:` field. Modern Compose V2 ignores it; it causes version-mismatch rejections with older tooling.</statement>
      <rationale>The Compose spec no longer requires a version field. Including it creates confusion and can block valid files in some older CI tools.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set `container_name` explicitly on every service so log queries and exec commands use a stable name.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a fixed name, Compose generates names from project + service + index, which changes across recreations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set `restart: unless-stopped` (staging) or `restart: always` (production) on every long-running service.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a restart policy, a crashed container stays down until manually restarted.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Health Checks and Dependencies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define a `healthcheck` on every service that is referenced by another service's `depends_on` with `condition: service_healthy`. If healthcheck is absent, the condition is silently ignored and the dependent starts immediately.</statement>
      <rationale>Race conditions on startup (app tries to connect to DB before it is ready) are the leading cause of intermittent Compose failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
services:
  db:
    image: postgres:16-alpine
    healthcheck:
      test: ["CMD-SHELL", "pg_isready -U ${DB_USER} -d ${DB_NAME}"]
      interval: 10s
      timeout: 5s
      retries: 5
      start_period: 30s

  app:
    depends_on:
      db:
        condition: service_healthy
]]></code>
      <note>The app waits until pg_isready returns 0 before starting.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using `depends_on: [db]` without a condition or healthcheck.</description>
      <reason>This only controls start order, not readiness. The app starts the moment the db container process is launched, not when Postgres is accepting connections.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Networking">
    <rule>
      <statement>Bind exposed ports to `127.0.0.1:HOST_PORT:CONTAINER_PORT` for services that must not be publicly reachable. Docker rewrites iptables directly and bypasses UFW.</statement>
      <rationale>A port bound to `0.0.0.0` is reachable from the internet regardless of UFW rules, because Docker inserts ACCEPT rules before UFW's DROP rules.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark backend networks as `internal: true` so containers on that network cannot reach the internet directly.</statement>
      <rationale>Limits blast radius of a compromised container — it cannot exfiltrate data or download payloads.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
networks:
  frontend:
    driver: bridge
  backend:
    driver: bridge
    internal: true

services:
  db:
    networks: [backend]
    ports:
      - "127.0.0.1:5432:5432"
  app:
    networks: [frontend, backend]
    ports:
      - "80:8000"
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Volumes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use named volumes for all persistent data in production. Bind mounts are only for config files (`:ro`) or development source sync.</statement>
      <rationale>Named volumes are managed by Docker, survive container recreation, and have better performance on Linux than bind mounts on macOS/Windows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using a bind mount for database data: `- ./pgdata:/var/lib/postgresql/data`</description>
      <reason>Bind mounts expose the host filesystem to the container, have permission issues (container UID vs host UID mismatch), and perform poorly on non-Linux hosts.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Resource Limits and Logging">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set `deploy.resources.limits.memory` and `.cpus` on every service. Without limits a runaway container can OOM-kill the host.</statement>
      <rationale>Docker on Linux applies cgroup limits only when they are declared; no limit means unbounded resource use.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure log rotation on every service: `driver: json-file` with `max-size: "10m"` and `max-file: "3"`. Without rotation, container logs fill the disk indefinitely.</statement>
      <rationale>The default json-file driver writes unbounded logs to `/var/lib/docker/containers/`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
services:
  app:
    deploy:
      resources:
        limits:
          memory: 512M
          cpus: "1.0"
        reservations:
          memory: 128M
    logging:
      driver: json-file
      options:
        max-size: "10m"
        max-file: "3"
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Secrets and Environment">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store all secrets in `.env` (gitignored). Commit only `.env.example` with placeholder values. Never put plaintext secrets in the compose file's `environment:` block.</statement>
      <rationale>`docker compose config` and `docker inspect` expose `environment:` values in plain text.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use profiles (`profiles: [dev]`) for optional services (adminer, mailhog, monitoring) so `docker compose up -d` starts only the production set.</statement>
      <rationale>Eliminates the need for separate compose files for dev vs prod optional services.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/base-service.yml">Generic service template</link>
    <link path="templates/postgres.yml">PostgreSQL service template</link>
  </see-also>
</text>
