<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="BA Week-One Onboarding Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every Week-One pack must satisfy. Each rule is enforced by the Day-5 validator; failure means the BA is not yet "ready to write requirements."</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-artefact-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Day 1 produces a flat inventory of every existing project artefact (file, ticket, channel, board, repo) with: source URL, last-modified date, and a 10-word summary. The inventory is the single source for the rest of the week — interviews never replace it.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK §3.1.4 Plan Business Analysis Information Management">Skipping the artefact pull leads to BAs re-asking what is already written, which burns stakeholder trust and surfaces only what stakeholders remember (recency-biased).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-named-stakeholders" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The stakeholders.md file MUST list each stakeholder with: full name, role, decision authority (Approve / Consult / Inform / None), preferred channel, and a one-line "what they care about." A stakeholder marked "TBD" or "the client team" is a failure.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK §10.43 Stakeholder List, Map, or Personas">Anonymous stakeholder groups produce vague requirements; named owners produce decisions. RACI-like authority labels prevent the BA from chasing sign-off from someone who cannot grant it.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-glossary-written-down" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Day 3 produces glossary.md with >= 15 domain terms. Each entry has: term, definition, source (interview/document/observed usage), and a flag if the definition was contested between stakeholders.</statement>
      <rationale source="IREB CPRE-FL §2.5 Glossary">Conflicting term usage is the highest-frequency source of late-stage requirements rework. A written glossary forces the conflict into the open during week one, where it is cheap to resolve.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-process-baseline-diagram" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Day 4 produces processes.md containing at least one BPMN-style or swimlane diagram of the as-is core business process. Pure text descriptions are not acceptable. The diagram must label each lane with a named owner from stakeholders.md.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK §10.34 Process Modelling">A diagram exposes handoff points that a prose description hides. Tying lanes to stakeholders also reveals process ownership gaps (lanes nobody owns) before requirements work begins.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-gap-memo" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Day 5 produces risks.md with: top 5 known gaps (info missing for requirements), top 5 risks (with likelihood + impact 1-3), and explicit "open questions for the PM" with owner and required-by date. The memo is signed off by the BA's engagement manager in writing (PR comment, email, Slack ack with timestamp).</statement>
      <rationale source="Standish Group CHAOS reports">Projects without a documented gap memo at start consistently underestimate discovery scope. The signed gap memo also protects the BA against scope creep allegations later: "this risk was logged on Day 5."</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Stakeholder line that passes r2">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
| Name | Role | Authority | Channel | Cares about |
|------|------|-----------|---------|-------------|
| Maria Lopes | VP Operations | Approve | Email + Tue 10:00 sync | Reducing manual order entry by 50% |
      ]]></code>
      <note>Named, authority labelled, single concrete care-about. The BA can now route a scope question to a real human with known authority.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Stakeholder line that fails r2">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
| Name | Role | Authority | Channel | Cares about |
|------|------|-----------|---------|-------------|
| Client Ops Team | TBD | TBD | TBD | TBD |
      ]]></code>
      <note>Three "TBD" + group name. The BA has effectively no stakeholder for the most critical role. The pack must reject this row.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
