<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="quality-management Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for quality-management. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store the quality plan in git as quality-plan.yaml with explicit threshold values: {metric, op (&gt;=|&lt;=), value}. Use CODEOWNERS to gate changes; the quality owner is named per workstream, not "the team".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Narrative quality plans are not enforced at gate time. A YAML threshold file is machine-readable by the gate script and human-readable in PR reviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track Cost-of-Quality explicitly: prevention costs (linting, type checking, code review), appraisal costs (testing, audits), internal-failure costs (rework, retests), and external-failure costs (production incidents, churn). CoQ trend reveals the true ROI of prevention investment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Teams under-invest in prevention because failure cost is invisible until it happens. Making it a tracked metric changes the investment decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DoD items must be measurable, not narrative. "Code compiles" is measurable; "code is high quality" is not. Every DoD item must have a testable evidence source: CI run URL, coverage report line, scan result file.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Narrative DoD items are passed on honour, not on evidence. Gate agents require a concrete evidence source to emit pass/fail; "high quality" cannot be grounded.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define DoD per artifact type: story, feature, release. A story DoD and a release DoD have different criteria. Do not use one DoD for everything.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Applying release-level criteria to every story creates overhead that teams bypass. Applying story-level criteria to releases misses integration and deployment checks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prevention beats detection: invest in linters, type checkers, design contracts, and generative testing before adding manual review steps. Every category of bug that can be caught by a tool should be caught by a tool.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Manual review catches fewer than 40% of defects in typical software; automated static analysis with well-configured rules catches the majority of structural defects at near-zero marginal cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run an escape-defect retrospective for every production defect rated S1 or S2. Output is a quality plan amendment — a new threshold, rule, or gate — not blame assignment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">S1/S2 escapes signal a gap in the gate chain. Without a systematic amendment process, the same class of defect escapes again.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quality gate decisions (release / hold / abort) require human approval. The gate script computes PASS/FAIL from thresholds; the agent emits a recommendation with evidence; a named human approves the release decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Automated quality gate execution is appropriate for blocking merges; releasing to production requires human accountability that no automated system can substitute.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every gate run must produce an immutable artifact with timestamp, inputs (CI run IDs, tool versions, threshold file version), and output (PASS/FAIL per criterion with evidence URLs). Audit evidence must be traceable, not curated post-hoc.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Regulated programs (ISO, SOC 2, FDA) require evidence that the gate was run correctly at the time of release. Post-hoc evidence curation creates regulatory liability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every defect must be triaged against one severity rubric defined in quality-plan.yaml. Reject severity assignments made without reference to the rubric. Auto-close of duplicates requires human review — the agent recommends, the human merges.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents inflate severity to be "safe" (everything S2/S3) or deflate to avoid escalation. A calibrated rubric with examples for each severity level is the only reliable anchor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Defect reports must include steps-to-reproduce grounded on actual logs or traces. Agents must refuse to fabricate reproduction steps from description alone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Invented repro steps cannot be executed, blocking triage and fix verification. Grounding on actual artefacts (logs, traces, screenshots) is a non-negotiable quality gate on the defect report itself.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
