<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-plan-and-assurance" title="Quality Plan, Definition of Done, and Assurance">
  <summary>Rules for authoring a quality plan with measurable thresholds, writing a useful Definition of Done, and running effective quality assurance activities.</summary>

  <section title="Quality Plan">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store the quality plan in git as quality-plan.yaml with explicit threshold values: {metric, op (&gt;=|&lt;=), value}. Use CODEOWNERS to gate changes; the quality owner is named per workstream, not "the team".</statement>
      <rationale>Narrative quality plans are not enforced at gate time. A YAML threshold file is machine-readable by the gate script and human-readable in PR reviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track Cost-of-Quality explicitly: prevention costs (linting, type checking, code review), appraisal costs (testing, audits), internal-failure costs (rework, retests), and external-failure costs (production incidents, churn). CoQ trend reveals the true ROI of prevention investment.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams under-invest in prevention because failure cost is invisible until it happens. Making it a tracked metric changes the investment decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Definition of Done">
    <rule>
      <statement>DoD items must be measurable, not narrative. "Code compiles" is measurable; "code is high quality" is not. Every DoD item must have a testable evidence source: CI run URL, coverage report line, scan result file.</statement>
      <rationale>Narrative DoD items are passed on honour, not on evidence. Gate agents require a concrete evidence source to emit pass/fail; "high quality" cannot be grounded.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define DoD per artifact type: story, feature, release. A story DoD and a release DoD have different criteria. Do not use one DoD for everything.</statement>
      <rationale>Applying release-level criteria to every story creates overhead that teams bypass. Applying story-level criteria to releases misses integration and deployment checks.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Assurance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prevention beats detection: invest in linters, type checkers, design contracts, and generative testing before adding manual review steps. Every category of bug that can be caught by a tool should be caught by a tool.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual review catches fewer than 40% of defects in typical software; automated static analysis with well-configured rules catches the majority of structural defects at near-zero marginal cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run an escape-defect retrospective for every production defect rated S1 or S2. Output is a quality plan amendment — a new threshold, rule, or gate — not blame assignment.</statement>
      <rationale>S1/S2 escapes signal a gap in the gate chain. Without a systematic amendment process, the same class of defect escapes again.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
