<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="quality-management Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for quality-management as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Process metric becomes a gaming target (Goodhart's Law): teams hit the coverage percentage by testing trivial code paths while leaving critical paths untested.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Rotate which metrics gate vs. which inform; a metric used as a gate for more than two cycles is at risk of being gamed. Supplement coverage percentage with mutation testing or branch coverage.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent writing "evidence" for a DoD item without a traceable artefact source.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Fabricated evidence creates audit liability. Every pass assertion must point to an immutable artefact URL (CI run, report file, scan SARIF). Refuse to pass any criterion without a concrete source.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Defect logs sent to a third-party LLM without PII scrubbing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Defect logs routinely contain user IDs, email addresses, payment data, and health information. Scrub before sending to any external model.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Conflates Cost-of-Quality (prevention + appraisal + failure) with mere QA budget; teams under-invest in prevention because failure cost is invisible.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Separate the budget lines: prevention (linting, type checking, design review), appraisal (testing, scanning, audits), internal failure (rework, retests), external failure (production incidents, churn). Track CoQ trend to show ROI.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Definition of Done is a checkbox cargo cult unless tied to measurable acceptance criteria and runtime evidence (test coverage, security scan, perf baseline).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every DoD item must have a testable evidence source. If you cannot automate it or point to a concrete artefact, remove it from DoD and move it to "nice to have".</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>"Quality is everyone's job" → in practice no one owns it; missing named QA owner per workstream is a common failure.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Name a quality owner per workstream and codify in CODEOWNERS. Quality is everyone's job only if someone is explicitly responsible.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Static checklists rot; programs accumulate dozens of checklists that nobody updates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Version quality-plan.yaml in git with branch protection. Checklist updates are PRs, not email updates.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs grading "code quality" produce confident but inconsistent verdicts; deterministic linters and SAST beat narrative review for pass/fail gates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use linters, type checkers, and SAST for pass/fail gates. Use LLMs for recommendations and patterns, but not for gate decisions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>UAT sign-off cannot substitute for production telemetry; defects escape UAT every release.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>UAT is a gate on requirements conformance. Production telemetry (error rate, latency p99, SLOs) is a separate gate. Both are mandatory.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents reading test reports skip the parts they cannot interpret (binary blobs, large logs); always pre-process to structured JSON before prompt.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Binary output is agent-unfriendly. Transform test reports to JSON before feeding to an agent.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Defect triage agents over-merge duplicates because of surface similarity; require &gt;0.85 embedding cosine + matching environment before auto-link.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Over-merging duplicates erases signal from the bug tracker. Require high confidence (multiple signals) before suggesting a duplicate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Severity inflation: agents rate everything S2/S3 to be "safe"; force a calibration set with examples in the prompt.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A severity rubric with concrete examples (S1: production down, customer impact; S2: feature broken, workaround exists; S3: cosmetic) is the only anchor.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents writing defect reports invent reproduction steps; ground on actual logs/traces and refuse to fabricate steps.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Invented repro steps cannot be executed. Quality gates must reject fabricated evidence.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy: defect logs frequently leak PII (user IDs, emails, payment data); scrub before sending to a third-party model.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PII in defect logs is a data breach risk and audit liability. Scrub before feeding to any external model.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Audit-prep agents producing "evidence" without traceable source create regulatory liability; every evidence claim must point to an immutable artifact.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Fabricated audit evidence is worse than no evidence. Every claim must have a traceable source (CI run, report file, scan SARIF with timestamp).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-closing duplicates without human review erases information; agent recommends, human merges.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Auto-merge of duplicates can hide important signal (different root cause, different severity, different environment). Require human review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Coverage hallucination: agents claim coverage that exceeds the actual report; always trust the file, not the LLM summary.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents invent metrics. Coverage comes from the report file, not from the LLM paraphrase. Cross-check every metric against the source file.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
