<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="backlog-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-operations</domain>
    <summary>Methodology for maintaining a prioritized, healthy backlog that connects work items to product goals. Applies the DEEP principle (Detailed-top, Emergent-bottom, Estimated, Prioritized) and INVEST criteria for story quality. Weekly grooming, regular cleanup, and a clear "ready" definition prevent backlogs from becoming unactionable dumping grounds.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>backlog</tag>
      <tag>prioritization</tag>
      <tag>product-operations</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>grooming</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Backlog Management</title>
    <summary>Methodology for maintaining a prioritized, healthy backlog that connects work items to product goals. Applies the DEEP principle (Detailed-top, Emergent-bottom, Estimated, Prioritized) and INVEST criteria for story quality. Weekly grooming, regular cleanup, and a clear "ready" definition prevent backlogs from becoming unactionable dumping grounds.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Backlogs treated as storage accumulate hundreds of items with no clear ordering, vague requirements, and stale entries. This silently kills velocity: sprint planning becomes negotiation theater, engineers start without clear acceptance criteria, and important work competes with noise. A healthy backlog — 2-4 sprints of ready items, under 10% stale, over 80% with acceptance criteria — makes planning fast and execution clear.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Backlog has more than 100 items and "next sprint" is unclear or untrusted.</item>
        <item>Pre-grooming session: classify new items, flag stale ones for archive.</item>
        <item>After SDD spec/design lands: decompose into INVEST stories with acceptance criteria.</item>
        <item>Cross-project rollup: same person owns 5+ backlogs across Linear/Jira/GitHub Projects.</item>
        <item>Migrating between trackers (Trello to Linear, GitHub Issues to Jira).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo founder with fewer than 30 items — a Markdown file beats agent automation.</item>
        <item>Backlog is a wishlist with no commitment system — fix process before adding agents.</item>
        <item>Compliance-bound product (medical, aviation) where every state change needs human signoff and audit trail.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="backlog-health-principles">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Apply DEEP to the backlog as a whole: top items Detailed, bottom items Emergent, all items Estimated, all items Prioritized.</statement>
        <rationale>A backlog uniformly detailed at all depths wastes refinement effort on items that will never be built. DEEP matches detail depth to proximity to execution.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Apply INVEST to every individual item before marking it Ready: Independent, Negotiable, Valuable, Estimable, Small, Testable.</statement>
        <rationale>Items that fail INVEST block sprint planning — engineers cannot estimate or test them without more work, causing last-minute scope changes.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="backlog-structure">
      <list>
        <item>Ready (Next Sprint) — Detailed, estimated, acceptance criteria present, no blockers</item>
        <item>Upcoming (1-3 sprints) — Defined, some detail, rough estimate</item>
        <item>Backlog (Future) — Ideas, rough description, not yet refined</item>
        <item>Icebox (Maybe/Later) — Parked, low priority, revisit quarterly</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Maintain 2-4 sprints worth of Ready items, fewer than 100 total items (or grouped), and fewer than 10% stale items.</statement>
        <rationale>These three targets are the minimal health indicators. Below 2 Ready sprints causes planning panic; above 100 ungrouped items means signal is buried in noise; above 10% stale means the backlog is a graveyard.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="backlog-item-quality">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every Ready item must have: clear user value, acceptance criteria (Given/When/Then format), size estimate, priority rank, and documented dependencies or none.</statement>
        <rationale>Items reaching sprint planning without acceptance criteria cause in-sprint scope debates. Given/When/Then forces specificity that "user can do X" does not.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Vague item title like "Better search" or "Fix dashboard".</description>
        <reason>Vague titles require a conversation to decode intent. Reformulate as "Add autocomplete to product search" — action-oriented, scoped, estimable.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <example type="good" title="Properly refined backlog item">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Title: Add autocomplete to product search
As a customer
I want to see suggestions as I type
So that I find products faster

Acceptance Criteria:
- Given 2+ characters typed, when user pauses 300ms, then top 5 suggestions appear
- Given a suggestion is shown, when user clicks it, then product detail page opens
- Given mobile viewport, when autocomplete is active, then keyboard does not obscure results

Estimate: M (3-5 days)
Priority: P2 — high-usage path
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="grooming-process">
      <list>
        <item>Step 1: Capture — accept items from any source, categorize type (feature/bug/debt/research), defer evaluation</item>
        <item>Step 2: Groom (weekly, 1-2h) — review new items, refine top items, re-prioritize on new learning, archive stale</item>
        <item>Step 3: Prioritize — apply RICE or MoSCoW, re-rank when new information arrives or goals change</item>
        <item>Step 4: Refine top-of-backlog — break into smaller stories, add AC, clarify requirements, estimate, identify deps</item>
        <item>Step 5: Cleanup — delete duplicates, archive items untouched for 6+ months, merge related items</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Archive items untouched for 6+ months AND with no roadmap link. Timestamp alone is not sufficient for stale detection.</statement>
        <rationale>Valid items can be dormant; cross-check with linked customer requests and roadmap before archiving.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-workflow">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Agents draft; humans commit. Never grant write-scoped tokens to autonomous agents on live trackers.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent-applied edits to live tickets in front of users is jarring and error-prone. Route through PR-style changeset or staging branch for human review.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Triage agent (nightly): classify new items, draft story format, propose priority — outputs draft only</item>
        <item>Health-check agent (weekly): compute counts, age distribution, AC coverage %, stale candidates</item>
        <item>Groomer agent (synchronous, during session): assists refinement of top-20 items under human approval</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM-rewritten user stories that paraphrase the original request.</description>
        <reason>Original requestor wording is signal; agent paraphrasing destroys it. Keep original text under a Raw Request section in every item.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent-generated estimates without team-historical priors.</description>
        <reason>T-shirt sizing without calibration against past delivery is dart-throwing. Bootstrap from last 30 closed items before trusting agent estimates.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-merging "similar" items based on semantic similarity alone.</description>
        <reason>Wrong merges destroy audit trail and lose distinct customer requests. Require 0.9+ similarity score AND human accept before merging.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="priority-limit-rule">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>If more than 20% of the backlog is already P1, refuse to propose new P1 items until the proportion drops.</statement>
        <rationale>P1 inflation means nothing is P1. The label loses its forcing function for sprint ordering.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow-detail">
      <p>Three-pass workflow: (1) Triage agent runs nightly on new items: classify (feature/bug/debt/research), enrich with template, draft AC, propose priority — outputs draft, never auto-applies. (2) Health-check agent runs weekly, produces backlog health report (counts, age distribution, AC coverage %, stale candidates). (3) Groomer agent assists synchronous grooming: takes top-20 items, asks clarifying questions, refines in-place under human approval. Production rule: agents draft, humans commit. Use Linear/Jira/GitHub APIs to apply changes through PRs/changesets, never direct mutation.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>backlog-triage — sonnet, classifies + drafts story format from raw request.</item>
        <item>backlog-health — haiku, computes metrics from API export.</item>
        <item>backlog-groomer — opus during real grooming session (multi-turn dialogue).</item>
        <item>task-creator-agent (already in repo faion-task-creator-agent) — decomposes spec → tasks.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Prompt pattern for triage:</p>
      <prompt purpose="backlog-triage"><![CDATA[
Raw request: {customer/team text}
Existing similar items: {top-3 by embedding similarity}
Output (do NOT auto-create):
- merge_candidate: {id or null with reasoning}
- story: As a {user}, I want {action}, so that {benefit}
- acceptance_criteria: 3-5 Given/When/Then
- size_estimate: XS/S/M/L/XL with rationale
- priority_proposal: P1/P2/P3 with criteria-based reasoning
- raw_request_preserved: {original text verbatim}
      ]]></prompt>
      <p>Prompt pattern for health-check:</p>
      <prompt purpose="backlog-health-check"><![CDATA[
Backlog export {linear-export.json}.
Compute: total, by_status, by_type, age_buckets (0-30, 30-90, 90-180, 180+),
ac_coverage_pct, stale_candidates (180+ days no activity AND no
roadmap link). Return health report against targets:
ready=10-20, stale<10%, ac_coverage>80%.
      ]]></prompt>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>linear-cli (community) — Linear backlog ops (npm i -g @linear/sdk)</item>
        <item>gh issue / gh project — GitHub Issues + Projects v2 (https://cli.github.com)</item>
        <item>jira-cli (Atlassian) — Jira read/write (https://github.com/ankitpokhrel/jira-cli)</item>
        <item>notion-cli — Notion-as-tracker (https://github.com/jevakallio/notion-cli)</item>
        <item>trello-cli — Trello migration source (OSS, npm)</item>
        <item>claude Skill tool — Drive sub-agents (https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/claude-code)</item>
        <item>jq + csvkit — Health-metric computation (system)</item>
        <item>embedding-cli (sentence-transformers) — Duplicate detection (pip install sentence-transformers)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-platforms">
      <list>
        <item>Linear (SaaS, Excellent) — GraphQL API, OAuth + PAT, webhooks. Best agent fit.</item>
        <item>Jira Cloud (SaaS, Yes) — REST + Forge; complex permissions; agent must scope tightly.</item>
        <item>GitHub Projects v2 (SaaS, Yes (GraphQL)) — Free for open source; tightly couples to repo.</item>
        <item>Notion (SaaS, Yes) — Backlog-as-database; weaker for sprint mechanics.</item>
        <item>ClickUp (SaaS, Yes) — API stable; verbose payloads.</item>
        <item>Shortcut (SaaS, Yes) — Simple REST; smaller ecosystem.</item>
        <item>Trello (SaaS, Yes) — Card-based; common migration source.</item>
        <item>Plane.so (OSS, Yes) — Linear-clone, self-host; webhooks; agent-friendly.</item>
        <item>Backlog.com (SaaS, Limited) — Niche; older API.</item>
        <item>Asana (SaaS, Yes) — Heavy-weight; project-centric.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Agents draft, humans commit: every AI-proposed change goes through human approval. Never grant write-scoped tokens to autonomous agents.</item>
        <item>Preserve raw requests verbatim: agent rewrites lose nuance; keep Raw Request section.</item>
        <item>DEEP not deep: top 10 items detailed, bottom 100 one-liner — resist the urge to AC-everything.</item>
        <item>Ready definition is binary, not vibe: scope clear, AC present, estimated, no blockers — agent enforces this gate before sprint planning.</item>
        <item>Stale = no activity AND no link: timestamp alone is noise; cross-check with roadmap/customer linkage.</item>
        <item>Estimate calibration with team baseline: agents need 20 past completed items as priors, otherwise they all-S everything.</item>
        <item>One source of truth: don't sync Linear ↔ Jira ↔ Notion bidirectionally — pick one canonical, others are read-only views.</item>
        <item>Limit "P1": if everything is P1, nothing is. Agent should refuse to propose P1 if more than 20% of backlog is already P1.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>API rate limits — Linear 1500 req/h, Jira tighter. Agents that re-pull on every action will throttle.</item>
        <item>LLMs invent customer types that match the wording — "as a power user", "as an admin" — when the raw request says nothing about role. Force quoting the request.</item>
        <item>Estimates without team-historical priors are dart-throws. Always bootstrap from last 30 closed items.</item>
        <item>Auto-merge bug: agents merging "similar" items lose distinct user voices; require 0.9+ similarity AND human accept.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoint: prioritization is product-strategy territory. Agents propose; humans (PM/founder) decide.</item>
        <item>LLMs add fake dependencies ("blocked by X" with no evidence). Require source ticket or remove the field.</item>
        <item>Agent-applied edits to live tickets in front of users is jarring; route through staging branch / PR-style changeset.</item>
        <item>Token-cost trap: weekly full backlog scan on 1k+ items is expensive. Embedding-cluster first, then LLM only on changed clusters.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/backlog-health-check.md" purpose="Snapshot by status/type with health metrics table and action checklist."/>
      <template path="templates/grooming-agenda.md" purpose="Session template: new item triage, top-of-backlog review, refinement, estimates, cleanup."/>
      <template path="templates/backlog-item.md" purpose="Story template with user story, Given/When/Then AC, size, priority, dependencies, links."/>
    </templates>
    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/backlog-health.sh" purpose="Linear API pull + Claude health report + stale candidate extraction, designed for weekly cron."/>
    </scripts>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.amazon.com/Agile-Estimating-Planning-Mike-Cohn/dp/0131479415"/>
      <link href="https://www.amazon.com/INSPIRED-Create-Tech-Products-Customers/dp/1119387507"/>
      <link href="https://linear.app/docs/api"/>
      <link href="https://docs.github.com/en/issues/planning-and-tracking-with-projects"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/ankitpokhrel/jira-cli"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
