<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="contextual-inquiry Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for contextual-inquiry. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conduct the session in the user's actual work environment, not a lab or meeting room.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Context principle: removing the user from their environment removes the environmental triggers, physical artifacts, and interruptions that shape real behavior.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat the user as the expert and the researcher as the apprentice (learner). Use the opening script to establish this frame before observation begins.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Partnership principle: the master-apprentice model reduces observer-effect distortion. Users perform naturally when they are the acknowledged authority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Share interpretations aloud during the session and invite corrections: "So it seems like... Did I understand correctly?"</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Interpretation principle: researchers form wrong mental models continuously. Surfacing and correcting them in-session prevents compounded misinterpretations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enter each session with clear research questions. The observation guide must specify which aspects of work to observe and what questions to answer.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Focus principle: without a defined lens, sessions produce unfocused notes. Clear focus enables selective attention without missing key phenomena.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Record these seven data types for every session: actions taken, tools used, artifacts created or used, physical environment description, interruptions, workarounds, and frustrations expressed verbally.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Comprehensive capture prevents the most common loss: workarounds and physical artifacts that hold the real workflow are easy to overlook.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mark inferences as inferences in notes from the very first session. Write observed vs inferred in separate fields; retroactive separation after analysis is impossible.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixing observed and inferred data produces false confidence in downstream analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define focus areas, recruit 4-8 participants for one focus area, obtain organizational permission, prepare recording equipment, and create an observation guide before the first session.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">4-8 sessions is the sweet spot for one focus area — enough to find patterns across participants without spending more sessions than new insights warrant.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a 1-hour pilot before the real round to fix observation-guide weaknesses. The second guide is always better.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Guides written before observation contain leading questions and missing focus areas that only become visible when used in the field.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Watch silently first, then ask about specific observed actions: "Why did you do that?" Never suggest improvements or express surprise at workarounds during the session.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Premature suggestions and expressed surprise alter behavior immediately.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capture artifacts physically (photos with consent). Workflows rarely live entirely on screens; paper notes, whiteboard scribbles, and handwritten forms are primary data.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Remote CI variants cannot capture physical artifacts, which is a significant data loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Debrief within 30 minutes of each session, while peripheral memory is intact. Audio recording does not replace immediate debrief.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Peripheral memory (environmental details, emotional tone, gestural context) decays within hours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After all sessions: identify patterns using affinity diagrams, sequence models, and cultural models.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-session insights are anecdotes. Cross-session analysis transforms observations into findings.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When in-person access is not possible, use screen share plus webcam to capture some environmental context; supplement with self-documentation or diary study. Always acknowledge that remote CI loses physical artifacts and reduces environmental signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Remote CI captures ~60-70% of the signal of in-person CI. The loss is concentrated in physical artifacts, peripheral activities, and environmental triggers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Time-boxed sessions (1-2 h) miss low-frequency tasks (monthly close, quarterly audits) and emergencies. Sample for role, shift, seniority, and edge-case variation — not statistical validity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Contextual inquiry is not a representative sample; it is a qualitative deep dive. Selecting for variation ensures the findings cover the range of work patterns, not just the most common ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Observer effect is real; participants perform their work for the researcher, missing the messy reality. Master-apprentice framing assumes a single expert; team-based work needs a different choreography.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Acknowledging observer effect and adapting method for team settings are part of rigorous CI practice. Design-by-observation without acknowledging these limits produces false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r16" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a 1-hour pilot before the real round to fix observation-guide weaknesses; the second guide is always better.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Guides written before observation contain leading questions and missing focus areas that only become visible when used in the field.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r17" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capture artifacts physically (photos with consent) — workflows rarely live entirely on screens.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Paper notes, whiteboard scribbles, and handwritten forms are primary data that screen-only capture misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r18" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mark inferences as inferences in notes from the very first session; retroactive separation of observed vs inferred is impossible.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixing observed and inferred data produces false confidence. Downstream agents and designers treat both as equally grounded unless the distinction is explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r19" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Debrief within 30 minutes of the session, while peripheral memory is intact. Audio recording does not replace this.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Peripheral memory (environmental details, emotional tone, gestural context) decays within hours. Recordings capture only what the microphone picked up.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r20" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sample for variation, not statistical validity: include shifts, regions, seniority, edge-case roles. 4-8 sessions is the sweet spot for one focus area.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Contextual inquiry finds patterns across variation. Selecting only typical users produces findings that miss the edge cases that break system assumptions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r21" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Share interim findings with participants ("member checking") to catch misinterpretations before downstream design work commits to them.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Researchers form incorrect interpretations even with shared-interpretation protocol. Participant validation is the final check before findings become design inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r22" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat workarounds as system-design signals, not user errors. The fact that someone keeps paper notes is the finding.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Workarounds reveal where the designed system diverges from how work actually happens. Treating them as errors misses the most valuable design signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
