<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Contextual Inquiry: Four Principles and Observation Rules">
  <summary>Defines the four core principles (context, partnership, interpretation, focus) and rules for what to capture during a session.</summary>

  <section title="Four Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Conduct the session in the user's actual work environment, not a lab or meeting room.</statement>
      <rationale>Context principle: removing the user from their environment removes the environmental triggers, physical artifacts, and interruptions that shape real behavior.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the user as the expert and the researcher as the apprentice (learner). Use the opening script to establish this frame before observation begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Partnership principle: the master-apprentice model reduces observer-effect distortion. Users perform naturally when they are the acknowledged authority, not the subject under evaluation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Share interpretations aloud during the session and invite corrections: "So it seems like... Did I understand correctly?"</statement>
      <rationale>Interpretation principle: researchers form wrong mental models continuously. Surfacing and correcting them in-session prevents compounded misinterpretations in analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enter each session with clear research questions. The observation guide must specify which aspects of work to observe and what questions to answer.</statement>
      <rationale>Focus principle: without a defined lens, sessions produce unfocused notes that are expensive to analyze. Clear focus enables selective attention without missing key phenomena.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="What to Capture">
    <rule>
      <statement>Record these seven data types for every session: actions taken, tools used, artifacts created or used, physical environment description, interruptions, workarounds, and frustrations expressed verbally.</statement>
      <rationale>Comprehensive capture prevents the most common loss: workarounds and physical artifacts (sticky notes, paper forms) that hold the real workflow are easy to overlook when focused only on screen interactions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark inferences as inferences in notes from the very first session. Write observed vs inferred in separate fields; retroactive separation after analysis is impossible.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing observed and inferred data produces false confidence. Downstream agents and designers treat both as equally grounded unless the distinction is explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Opening Script">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Opening frame that establishes master-apprentice model without leading the user.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"I'm here to learn how you do your work. You're the expert.
I'll watch and ask questions. Please do your work as normally
as possible. If you explain something I don't understand,
I'll ask. If I interpret something wrong, please correct me."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
