<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Contextual Inquiry: Six-Step Process">
  <summary>The six operational steps: prepare, introduce, observe-and-interview, capture data, debrief, and cross-session analysis.</summary>

  <section title="Prepare">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define focus areas (which aspects of work to observe), recruit 4-8 participants for one focus area, obtain organizational permission, prepare recording equipment, and create an observation guide before the first session.</statement>
      <rationale>4-8 sessions is the sweet spot for one focus area — enough to find patterns across participants without spending more sessions than new insights warrant.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a 1-hour pilot before the real round to fix observation-guide weaknesses. The second guide is always better.</statement>
      <rationale>Guides written before observation contain leading questions and missing focus areas that only become visible when used in the field.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Observe and Interview">
    <rule>
      <statement>Watch silently first, then ask about specific observed actions: "Why did you do that?" Never suggest improvements or express surprise at workarounds during the session.</statement>
      <rationale>Premature suggestions and expressed surprise alter behavior immediately. The session value depends on observing what the user actually does, not what they think they should do with a researcher watching.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture artifacts physically (photos with consent). Workflows rarely live entirely on screens; paper notes, whiteboard scribbles, and handwritten forms are primary data.</statement>
      <rationale>Remote CI variants cannot capture physical artifacts, which is a significant data loss. In-person sessions must compensate by actively documenting the physical environment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Debrief">
    <rule>
      <statement>Debrief within 30 minutes of each session, while peripheral memory is intact. Audio recording does not replace immediate debrief — peripheral observations and interpretive reactions are not on the recording.</statement>
      <rationale>Peripheral memory (environmental details, emotional tone, gestural context) decays within hours. Recordings capture only what the microphone picked up.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cross-Session Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>After all sessions: identify patterns using affinity diagrams (cluster observations across participants by theme), sequence models (map workflow steps, decisions, artifacts, handoffs), and cultural models (power dynamics, informal processes, values).</statement>
      <rationale>Single-session insights are anecdotes. Cross-session analysis transforms observations into findings. Skipping analysis leaves data in notebooks with no downstream value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Share interim findings with participants ("member checking") to catch misinterpretations before downstream design work commits to them.</statement>
      <rationale>Researchers form incorrect interpretations even with shared-interpretation protocol. Participant validation is the final check before findings become design inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/observation-guide.md">Pre-session guide template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/session-notes.md">Structured session notes template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/ci-row-schema.py">Observation row dataclass for cross-session analysis</reference>
</text>
