<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-analysis" title="Contextual Inquiry: Analysis Methods and Remote Adaptations">
  <summary>Affinity diagramming, sequence and cultural modeling, remote CI adaptations, limitations, and agent-specific failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Remote Adaptations">
    <rule>
      <statement>When in-person access is not possible, use screen share plus webcam to capture some environmental context; supplement with self-documentation (user records themselves working) or diary study. Always acknowledge that remote CI loses physical artifacts and reduces environmental signal.</statement>
      <rationale>Remote CI captures ~60-70% of the signal of in-person CI. The loss is concentrated in physical artifacts, peripheral activities, and environmental triggers — often the most important findings.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Time-boxed sessions (1-2 h) miss low-frequency tasks (monthly close, quarterly audits) and emergencies. Sample for role, shift, seniority, and edge-case variation — not statistical validity.</statement>
      <rationale>Contextual inquiry is not a representative sample; it is a qualitative deep dive. Selecting for variation ensures the findings cover the range of work patterns, not just the most common ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent-Specific Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never substitute an LLM-simulated user for a real participant. "Synthetic CI" produces convincing fiction with no environmental signal.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs have no sensory access to real workplaces. Any "observation" they produce is extrapolation from training data, not from the actual environment being studied.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLMs paraphrase quotes silently when summarizing transcripts.</description>
      <reason>Lock the tagging agent to verbatim mode: any string in the output not present verbatim in the source transcript is a hallucination. Reject paraphrases for the quote field.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Privacy: observation sessions capture bystanders, screen contents, and dictation not belonging to the participant.</description>
      <reason>Redact non-participant PII using a tool like presidio before any LLM ingestion. Remote CI screen recordings often include private windows — pre-trim before sharing with any third-party tool.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent ranks participant competence, labeling "wrong" workflows as user error.</description>
      <reason>The finding is always that the system does not fit real work. An agent that judges the workflow as incorrect misses the most valuable signal: workarounds reveal system design failures.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="scripts/observation_tagger_prompt.txt">LLM prompt for extracting structured observation rows from transcripts</reference>
</text>
