<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="contextual-inquiry Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for contextual-inquiry as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs paraphrase quotes silently when summarizing transcripts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Lock the tagging agent to verbatim mode: any string in the output not present verbatim in the source transcript is a hallucination. Reject paraphrases for the quote field.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy: observation sessions capture bystanders, screen contents, and dictation not belonging to the participant.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Redact non-participant PII using a tool like presidio before any LLM ingestion. Remote CI screen recordings often include private windows — pre-trim before sharing with any third-party tool.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent ranks participant competence, labeling "wrong" workflows as user error.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The finding is always that the system does not fit real work. An agent that judges the workflow as incorrect misses the most valuable signal: workarounds reveal system design failures.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Never substitute an LLM-simulated user for a real participant ("synthetic CI").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs have no sensory access to real workplaces. Any "observation" they produce is extrapolation from training data, not from the actual environment being studied.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
