<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-concepts" title="ArgoCD GitOps Concepts">
  <summary>Core resources (Application, Project, ApplicationSet), sync strategies, and hub-spoke vs distributed architecture.</summary>

  <section title="Core Resources">
    <list>
      <item>Application: ArgoCD CR defining source Git repo/path/revision and destination cluster/namespace; the fundamental unit of deployment</item>
      <item>AppProject: logical grouping with RBAC, allowed source repos, allowed destination clusters/namespaces; scope per team</item>
      <item>ApplicationSet: template that generates multiple Applications from a generator (Git directory, matrix, cluster list, PR)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never create Applications manually in the UI for production — manage all Application manifests in Git (App of Apps or ApplicationSet pattern).</statement>
      <rationale>Manually created Applications cannot be version-controlled or reviewed. A deleted ArgoCD instance with manual Applications means starting from scratch.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Sync Strategies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable selfHeal: true on all environments to prevent configuration drift; use syncWindows to restrict automated syncs to maintenance windows for production.</statement>
      <rationale>Without self-heal, a manual kubectl apply in production creates drift that is invisible until the next sync. Self-heal corrects this within seconds. syncWindows prevent ArgoCD from syncing production during incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Development: automated: true, selfHeal: true, prune: true — maximum agility</item>
      <item>Staging: automated: true, selfHeal: true, prune: true — same as dev</item>
      <item>Production: automated: false (manual sync gate), selfHeal: true, prune: false (explicit prune confirmation)</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
spec:
  syncPolicy:
    automated:
      selfHeal: true
      prune: false    # require explicit prune for resource deletion
    syncOptions:
      - CreateNamespace=true
      - ServerSideApply=true
      - ApplyOutOfSyncOnly=true
    retry:
      limit: 3
      backoff:
        duration: 5s
        factor: 2
        maxDuration: 3m
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Architecture Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use folders to model environments, not branches — one repository with overlays/ for each environment is simpler than branch-per-environment.</statement>
      <rationale>Branch-per-environment requires cherry-picking changes across branches and makes diff between environments difficult. Folder-per-environment shows environment differences as a clear Kustomize overlay diff.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Hub-and-spoke: single ArgoCD controls multiple clusters — single pane of glass, but network connectivity required and single point of failure</item>
      <item>Distributed: ArgoCD per cluster — isolated failure domains but more instances to manage and no centralized view</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Storing Kubernetes Secrets directly in the GitOps repository, even base64-encoded.</description>
      <reason>Base64 is not encryption. Anyone with repo read access gets all credentials. Use External Secrets Operator, Sealed Secrets, or Vault integration instead.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="templates/application.yaml">ArgoCD Application manifest with auto-sync and self-heal</reference>
    <reference path="templates/applicationset-matrix.yaml">ApplicationSet for multi-env multi-cluster deployment</reference>
  </section>
</text>
