<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-configuration" title="ArgoCD Configuration Patterns">
  <summary>Repository structure with Kustomize, RBAC via Projects, sync waves, hooks, notifications, and sync windows.</summary>

  <section title="Repository Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate the GitOps config repository from the application source code repository — never mix Dockerfiles and Kubernetes manifests in the same repo.</statement>
      <rationale>Application CI pushes image tag updates to the config repo. If they share a repo, the image build triggers another pipeline that triggers another build — infinite loop.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
kubernetes-manifests/         # GitOps repo
├── apps/
│   └── my-app/
│       ├── base/
│       │   ├── kustomization.yaml
│       │   ├── deployment.yaml
│       │   └── service.yaml
│       └── overlays/
│           ├── staging/      # patches: image tag, replicas
│           └── production/   # patches: image tag, replicas, HPA
├── infrastructure/
│   ├── cert-manager/
│   └── external-secrets/
└── argocd/
    ├── projects/
    └── applicationsets/
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="RBAC via Projects">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create an AppProject per team with explicit sourceRepos, destinations, and roles — do not deploy all applications to the default project.</statement>
      <rationale>The default project has no restrictions. An AppProject scopes a team to their repos and namespaces, preventing accidental or malicious cross-team deployments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/appproject.yaml">AppProject with RBAC for a team</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Sync Waves and Hooks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use sync-wave annotations to order resource creation within a sync: namespaces and CRDs at wave -1, ConfigMaps and Secrets at wave 0, Deployments at wave 1, Ingress at wave 2.</statement>
      <rationale>Without sync waves, ArgoCD applies all resources simultaneously. A Deployment that depends on a CRD fails if the CRD has not been installed yet.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# Namespace — created first
metadata:
  annotations:
    argocd.argoproj.io/sync-wave: "-1"
---
# Database migration Job — before app starts
metadata:
  annotations:
    argocd.argoproj.io/hook: PreSync
    argocd.argoproj.io/hook-delete-policy: HookSucceeded
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Notifications">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure notifications for on-sync-failed and on-health-degraded triggers at minimum; send to both Slack and a ticketing system for production.</statement>
      <rationale>Sync failures without notification go undetected. ArgoCD self-heals configuration drift but cannot fix broken images or missing dependencies — human alert is required.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Required triggers: on-sync-failed, on-health-degraded, on-deployed (for production audit trail)</item>
      <item>Optional: on-sync-running (noisy for high-velocity teams), on-sync-succeeded</item>
      <item>Notification channels: Slack for operational, GitHub/GitLab status for PR gates, email for compliance</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
