<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="personas">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Research-based fictional characters representing key user types that distill observed goals, behaviors, frustrations, and usage context into shared team artifacts for design decisions.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>personas</tag>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>user-modeling</tag>
      <tag>qualitative-analysis</tag>
      <tag>design-decisions</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Personas</title>
    <summary>Personas are research-based fictional characters representing key user types. Each persona distills observed goals, behaviors, frustrations, and usage context from real data into a shared team artifact that makes design decisions answerable: "Would Sarah want this?" Without them, teams design for themselves.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Teams without shared user models debate features as opinion battles with no resolution mechanism. Personas give every design and prioritization discussion a concrete reference: a named character with documented goals and pain points sourced from research. The artifact only carries signal when grounded in data — proto-personas and research-based personas serve different phases, but both must be explicit about their evidence basis.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Synthesizing interview, survey, analytics, and support-ticket data into 3-5 representative user types.</item>
        <item>Aligning a team that disagrees about who the primary user is.</item>
        <item>Bootstrapping proto-personas before research with explicit assumptions to validate.</item>
        <item>Re-validating outdated personas after a product pivot or new market entry.</item>
        <item>Writing user stories, A/B hypotheses, and onboarding flows that reference a consistent user identity.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Marketing-only segmentation (psychographics, ad targeting) — those need separate marketing-persona models.</item>
        <item>Single-user products (internal tools with one stakeholder) where a persona adds zero signal.</item>
        <item>Teams with no plan to reference personas in design reviews — building them as posters wastes effort.</item>
        <item>High-stakes regulated domains (medical devices, aerospace) where formal user-task analysis supersedes lightweight personas.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="persona-types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Choose persona type based on research maturity: research-based when data exists, proto-personas before data collection, provisional when assumptions must be made explicit.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing types without labeling them leads teams to treat assumptions as validated findings. Each type has a different confidence level and different update trigger.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Type comparison: research-based (data from interviews, surveys, analytics — most reliable); provisional (assumptions to validate — explicit uncertainty); proto-personas (team's current understanding — quick alignment before research).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="required-elements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every persona must include: name, demographics (context), goals (what they want to achieve), frustrations (pain points), behaviors (how they act), a representative quote sourced from real data, and usage context (when/where/devices).</statement>
        <rationale>Demographics-only personas are useless for design decisions. Goals and behaviors are the decision-making levers; demographics are context only.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Limit primary personas to 3-5. Each must represent a distinct combination of goals, behaviors, and context — not a demographic variant of an existing persona.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams cannot remember more than 5 personas. Too many personas dilutes focus; team members fall back to designing for whoever they imagined first.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="creation-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Conduct research first (interviews primary; surveys, analytics, support tickets, sales input as supplements), then identify behavioral clusters, then create personas, then validate with stakeholders.</statement>
        <rationale>Personas created without research reinforce team assumptions. The research-to-clustering-to-artifact sequence ensures claims trace back to evidence.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Step 1: gather data from multiple sources. Step 2: look for clusters sharing similar goals, behaviors, pain points, and context. Step 3: draft personas with evidence citations. Step 4: validate with stakeholders and team members. Step 5: share across the organization and reference in design decisions.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every Goal, Frustration, and Behavior field must cite at least one evidence ID from source data. Mark inferences explicitly as [INFERENCE]. Do not invent quotes — use verbatim quotes from identified participants (anonymized IDs).</statement>
        <rationale>Evidence-free inferences are indistinguishable from opinions. Evidence IDs allow audits and rebuild trust when stakeholders challenge findings.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="validation-and-lifecycle">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap evidence-free inferences at 20% per persona. Refresh research-based personas after every product pivot or new market entry; refresh proto-personas after the first 5 user interviews close.</statement>
        <rationale>Personas decay as products and markets evolve. A stale persona actively misleads: teams make confident decisions based on a user type that no longer exists.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="design-reviews">
      <rule>
        <statement>In every design review, frame feature questions against specific primary personas by name: "Would Sarah understand this view?" and "How does this help Sarah's goal of quick insights?"</statement>
        <rationale>Abstract user references ("the user") invite everyone to project their own model. Named persona references force the conversation onto documented, shared evidence.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="user-stories">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write user stories using the persona name as the subject: "As Sarah, I want to see a performance summary so that I can quickly prepare for meetings."</statement>
        <rationale>Persona-sourced stories are auditable: if the story cannot be traced to a goal or frustration in the persona, it may be a hidden assumption masquerading as a user need.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="prioritization">
      <rule>
        <statement>When prioritizing features, state which persona is served and at what tier: "This feature helps Sarah (primary) but not Tom (secondary). Prioritize for Sarah."</statement>
        <rationale>Without explicit persona mapping, prioritization debates have no resolution mechanism beyond seniority or volume.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Maintain a "non-persona" alongside each primary persona set — an explicit statement of who the product is NOT for. Use it to reject features in reviews.</statement>
        <rationale>Saying no in design reviews requires negative space. A non-persona makes the rejection grounded and depersonalized.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="jtbd-connection">
      <p>Personas and Jobs-to-be-Done are complementary, not competing: persona answers WHO is using the product; JTBD answers WHAT job they are hiring it for. Example: Sarah (persona) hires the dashboard (product) to make her look informed in leadership meetings (job). Pairing them enables both empathy and precise value-proposition scoping.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="persistence-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep personas as living Markdown in a research repository (not PDFs). Diff history shows when assumptions change. Reference the same persona in user stories, A/B test hypotheses, and onboarding flows.</statement>
        <rationale>PDF personas become posters. Posters do not affect decisions. Version-controlled files allow the team to audit drift and trace which research wave updated which field.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="bad-persona-signs">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Nobody uses the personas after creation.</description>
        <reason>Personas built without a plan for integration into design reviews, user stories, and prioritization are posters. Usage only follows if the team commits to referencing them in rituals.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Personas consist only of demographic data (age, role, location) with no goals, behaviors, or frustrations.</description>
        <reason>Demographics tell you nothing about what to build. Goals and behaviors are the design levers; demographic data is context at best.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>More than 5-6 primary personas exist for a single product.</description>
        <reason>Teams cannot hold more than ~5 personas in working memory. Excess personas cause designers to default to their own mental model because the persona set is too large to use.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Personas were created once and never updated despite product pivots or new markets.</description>
        <reason>Stale personas mislead. A persona describing a 2021 user in a product that has since expanded to a new geography is worse than no persona — it is confident misinformation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="process-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Personas created from team assumptions without any user research.</description>
        <reason>Assumption-based personas reinforce existing biases rather than revealing user reality. They feel validated because they look like real personas.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Quote fields contain synthesized, "voicey" paraphrases invented by the author rather than verbatim participant quotes.</description>
        <reason>Synthetic quotes tank credibility at first audit and are indistinguishable from hallucination. Use verbatim quotes with anonymous participant IDs only.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-specific-failures">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM generates plausible quotes and demographics without grounding them in source transcripts.</description>
        <reason>LLMs hallucinate fluent, contextually appropriate-sounding quotes. Locking the drafter to evidence-only mode and rejecting outputs with quotes not in the source corpus prevents this.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Persona names and photos encode demographic stereotypes (always-female-marketer, always-male-CTO).</description>
        <reason>Stereotype-encoded personas bias design decisions and are embarrassing in stakeholder reviews. Audit the persona set for diversity and rotate names and photos per update cycle.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent merges research data from different markets or locales into a single persona without explicit instruction.</description>
        <reason>Cultural assumptions embedded in one-market data (US tech-comfortable manager) do not transfer across markets. Segment by locale first, create personas second.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>LLMs are excellent at clustering qualitative data and drafting persona prose; they are weak at deciding which clusters matter. Use an analysis agent to read tagged interview transcripts and propose 6-10 clusters with evidence; a curation agent (with human review) selects the 3-5 personas to keep; a drafting agent fills the persona template citing source quotes verbatim. Persist evidence links — every claim in the persona should map to a transcript span.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: interview-clusterer (sonnet; ingests tagged transcripts, returns clusters with goal/behavior/pain themes and evidence quotes); persona-drafter (haiku; fills persona template from a cluster definition + evidence pack); persona-validator (sonnet; reviews a persona for evidence coverage, anti-pattern detection (just-demographics, made-up quotes), and JTBD linkage); proto-persona-author (haiku; produces lightweight proto-personas with explicit "assumption" tags).</p>
      <p>Prompt pattern: You are persona-drafter. Inputs: cluster_summary, evidence_quotes_with_source_ids. Produce a persona using the template. Every Goal, Frustration, and Behavior MUST cite at least one evidence_id. Mark inferences with [INFERENCE]. Do NOT invent quotes — pick the most representative quote_id for the Quote field. Output: markdown + JSON {evidence_map: {field -&gt; [evidence_ids]}}.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>dovetail CLI / API — Tag and cluster interview transcripts (dovetail.com/api). condens API — Research repo with thematic tagging (condens.io). marvinapp (Marvin) — Qualitative analysis with API (heymarvin.com). whisperx — Transcribe interviews locally (github.com/m-bain/whisperX). openai-whisper — OSS transcription (github.com/openai/whisper). airtable-cli / notion-cli — Persona library storage and updates (airtable.com / notion.so). pandoc — Convert persona markdown to slides/PDF for stakeholders (pandoc.org).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <p>Dovetail (SaaS, Yes — REST + Insights API): Industry standard for research repos. Condens (SaaS, Yes — REST): Smaller player, strong tagging. Marvin (SaaS, Yes — REST): AI-assisted theming. Notably (SaaS, Yes — REST): AI-native research repo. UserTesting (SaaS, Yes — REST): Source of recorded sessions. Maze (SaaS, Yes — REST): Survey + tree test data into personas. Airtable / Notion (SaaS, Yes — REST): Lightweight persona library hosting.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Cap evidence-free inferences at 20 % per persona and tag them explicitly. Anything more, the persona is fiction. Pair every persona with a "non-persona" (someone the product is explicitly NOT for). Saying no in design reviews requires negative space. Keep personas as living markdown in a research repo, not as PDFs. Diff history shows when assumptions change. Use the same persona in user stories, A/B test hypotheses, and onboarding flows. If it never re-appears, you built a poster. Cite real quotes verbatim with attribution to anonymous IDs. Synthesized "voicey" quotes tank credibility on first audit. Refresh research-based personas at least once per major release; refresh proto-personas the moment the first 5 user interviews close.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>LLMs hallucinate plausible quotes and demographics. Lock the drafter to evidence-only mode and reject outputs with quotes not present in the source corpus. Cluster quality depends on tagging consistency. Run an inter-rater check on tags before clustering — agents amplify tag noise. Persona "names + photos" risk encoding stereotypes (always-female-marketer, always-male-CTO). Audit the set for diversity and rotate per-update. Proto-personas drift toward team biases. Force the author agent to surface 3+ assumptions per proto and link each to a planned validation method. Beware the "synthetic users" pitch — generating personas purely from LLM imagination yields fluent fiction with no signal. Real research is required. Never let the agent merge research data from different markets/locales into a single persona without explicit instruction; segment first, persona-fy second. Persona files referenced in prompt context can balloon. Keep a one-paragraph persona summary for prompt injection and link to the full doc by URL/ID.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="references">
      <p>Alan Cooper, "About Face" (4th ed.) and "The Inmates Are Running the Asylum". Mulder &amp; Yaar, "The User Is Always Right". Kim Goodwin, "Designing for the Digital Age" (research-based persona method). Nielsen Norman Group — "Personas: Practice and Theory" (nngroup.com/articles/persona/). Interaction Design Foundation — Personas guide. Lean UX (Gothelf &amp; Seiden) for proto-persona practice.</p>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/persona-template.md" purpose="Full research-based persona document structure"/>
      <template path="templates/proto-persona-template.md" purpose="Lightweight proto-persona with explicit assumption fields"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-persona-drafter.txt" purpose="LLM prompt for evidence-constrained persona drafting"/>
    </templates>
    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/persona_evidence_check.py" purpose="Verify every persona claim cites an evidence ID; fail if quote lacks source"/>
    </scripts>
  </content>
</methodology>
