<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="accessibility-first-design Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for accessibility-first-design. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enforce a minimum contrast ratio of 4.5:1 for body text and 3:1 for large text (18pt+), UI components, and focus indicators; embed these thresholds in design tokens so non-compliant primitives cannot be exported.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">WCAG 2.2 SC 1.4.3 and 1.4.11 define these ratios. Encoding them in tokens prevents a designer from accidentally choosing a brand color that fails at the theme level before any component is built.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never use color as the sole indicator of meaning; pair every color signal with a shape, label, or pattern.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Approximately 8% of males have color vision deficiency. Color-only signals (red = error) are invisible to this population and fail WCAG SC 1.4.1.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set minimum interactive element size to 44x44 CSS pixels (or platform equivalent); ensure sufficient spacing between adjacent targets so misfire probability is low.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">WCAG 2.2 SC 2.5.8 (Target Size, Minimum) formalizes this. Spacing matters independently of size — clustered 44px targets still cause misfires for users with motor impairments or tremor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Make focus indicators visible with at least 3:1 contrast against the adjacent background; never rely on browser defaults which often fail this threshold.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">WCAG 2.2 SC 2.4.11 (Focus Appearance, Minimum) requires a visible focus ring. Browser defaults (thin dotted outline) are often invisible on colored backgrounds.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Specify heading level (H1-H6), landmark roles (nav, main, header, footer), and ARIA labels in design handoff annotations; do not leave semantic decisions to developer interpretation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Developers recreate heading hierarchies inconsistently without explicit annotation. Screen reader users navigate by headings; a flat or misordered hierarchy breaks the primary navigation pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include pause/stop controls for all auto-playing animations longer than 5 seconds; respect prefers-reduced-motion at the CSS level.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">WCAG 2.2 SC 2.2.2 (Pause, Stop, Hide) and 2.3.3 (Animation from Interactions) protect users with vestibular disorders and cognitive disabilities from motion that prevents reading or causes nausea.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never apply automated contrast or target-size fixes without designer review; fixes often break visual hierarchy (e.g., darkening a brand color to pass AA).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Automated fixes optimize for the accessibility metric, not for design intent. A darkened brand primary may pass contrast but invalidate the brand. Fixes must be flagged for designer decision, not silently applied.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track accessibility issues found at design stage versus handoff stage versus production; the ratio of design-stage finds to later-stage finds is the shift-left KPI.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">If most finds are in production rather than design, the design-phase process is not working. The KPI makes the shift-left investment visible and improvable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
