<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-press-coverage Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-press-coverage. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start with Tier 3 niche blogs and newsletters; build a coverage record before approaching Tier 1 publications.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tier 1 journalists (TechCrunch, NYT, Wired) receive hundreds of pitches daily. Without prior coverage, there is no social proof of newsworthiness. A few Tier 3 mentions establish credibility and provide links to cite when pitching upward. Pitching Tier 1 first before any coverage history means competing on equal footing with well-known companies.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never auto-pitch Tier 1 journalists; research manually and pitch individually with journalist-specific personalization.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tier 1 reporters will blacklist senders on the first templated email. Agent-drafted pitches that open with generic flattery ("Loved your piece on X") are immediately identified as templated and deleted. Each pitch must cite a specific non-obvious insight from a recent article by URL.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Identify a specific news angle before writing any pitch; a product announcement without an angle is not news.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Journalists publish stories that serve their readers. "We launched a product" is not a story — it is a press release. "Bootstrapped founder reached $1M ARR by rejecting VC advice" is a story because it carries a lesson, a protagonist, and a surprising outcome. Without an angle, no pitch volume will earn coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep pitches under 150 words; subject line under 8 words; cite one specific article by the journalist; offer three concrete assets; end with one clear CTA.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Journalists do not read long pitches. The pitch must communicate the story value before the reader decides to scroll. Citing a specific article proves research; offering concrete assets (founder access, exclusive data, customer stories) makes the journalist's job easier.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Respond to all coverage — positive and negative — within 24 hours with acknowledgment; never dispute factual errors publicly without first contacting the journalist privately.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Journalists remember how companies respond to their coverage. Gracious acknowledgment of positive coverage builds the relationship; private fact-correction maintains credibility. Public disputes burn the relationship permanently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
