<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-journalist-targeting" title="Press Coverage: Journalist Targeting and Research">
  <summary>Tiered approach to identifying and researching journalists: start with Tier 3 niche outlets to build coverage history before pitching Tier 1, and build journalist profiles before writing any pitch.</summary>

  <section title="Media Tier Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with Tier 3 niche blogs and newsletters; build a coverage record before approaching Tier 1 publications.</statement>
      <rationale>Tier 1 journalists (TechCrunch, NYT, Wired) receive hundreds of pitches daily. Without prior coverage, there is no social proof of newsworthiness. A few Tier 3 mentions establish credibility and provide links to cite when pitching upward. Pitching Tier 1 first before any coverage history means competing on equal footing with well-known companies.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Tier 1: TechCrunch, Wired, NYT, Forbes — major news, funding rounds, data-driven exclusives only.</item>
      <item>Tier 2: Industry publications, vertical blogs — product launches, features, milestones.</item>
      <item>Tier 3: Niche newsletters, podcasts, community blogs — any relevant news, relationship-building.</item>
      <item>HARO alternatives: Qwoted, Featured (formerly Terkel), SourceBottle, JustReachOut — respond to journalist queries as source.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never auto-pitch Tier 1 journalists; research manually and pitch individually with journalist-specific personalization.</statement>
      <rationale>Tier 1 reporters will blacklist senders on the first templated email. Agent-drafted pitches that open with generic flattery ("Loved your piece on X") are immediately identified as templated and deleted. Each pitch must cite a specific non-obvious insight from a recent article by URL.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Finding Journalists">
    <list>
      <item>Twitter/X search: "[Publication] + [beat keyword]" to find reporters covering your space.</item>
      <item>Publication website: browse relevant sections and note bylines on recent articles in your category.</item>
      <item>Similar coverage: search for articles about direct competitors and identify who wrote them.</item>
      <item>HARO alternatives: subscribe to daily query digests and respond to journalists actively seeking sources.</item>
      <item>Media databases (Muck Rack, Cision): paid tools for systematic journalist research at scale.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Journalist Profile">
    <p>Before writing any pitch, complete a profile for each journalist: Name, Publication, Beat (specific topics covered), 3-5 recent articles with links, writing tone (data-driven/narrative/opinion), pitch preference (email/DM/form), and one specific angle that connects your news to their beat.</p>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Pitching a journalist based only on their publication without reading their recent work.</description>
      <reason>Beat reporters specialize. A tech journalist at Forbes may cover enterprise software, not consumer apps. Sending an irrelevant pitch signals you did no research, permanently damaging the relationship.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-pitch-and-leverage.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/press-pitch.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
