<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-pitch-and-leverage" title="Story Angles, Pitch Structure, Press Kit, Follow-Up, and Leveraging Coverage">
  <summary>How to identify newsworthy story angles, craft pitches under 150 words with concrete assets offered, prepare a press kit, follow up without annoying journalists, and maximize the impact of any coverage received.</summary>

  <section title="Newsworthy Story Angles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify a specific news angle before writing any pitch; a product announcement without an angle is not news.</statement>
      <rationale>Journalists publish stories that serve their readers. "We launched a product" is not a story — it is a press release. "Bootstrapped founder reached $1M ARR by rejecting VC advice" is a story because it carries a lesson, a protagonist, and a surprising outcome. Without an angle, no pitch volume will earn coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>First: first product/company to do X in this space.</item>
      <item>Trend: your product is evidence of a larger industry shift.</item>
      <item>Data: original research, survey results, or proprietary usage data.</item>
      <item>Founder story: unique personal journey that led to the product.</item>
      <item>Funding: investment announcement with context about market.</item>
      <item>Milestone: significant user count, revenue, or growth rate.</item>
      <item>Contrarian: challenging a prevailing industry assumption with evidence.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Story formula: [Who] + [Did what] + [So what — impact] + [Why now]. Example: "Bootstrapped founder reaches $1M ARR by doing opposite of VC advice, proving small can win against well-funded competitors in the age of AI."</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Pitch Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep pitches under 150 words; subject line under 8 words; cite one specific article by the journalist; offer three concrete assets; end with one clear CTA.</statement>
      <rationale>Journalists do not read long pitches. The pitch must communicate the story value before the reader decides to scroll. Citing a specific article proves research; offering concrete assets (founder access, exclusive data, customer stories) makes the journalist's job easier.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/press-pitch.md">Cold pitch email template with all required elements</reference>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Following up more than twice after an initial pitch.</description>
      <reason>More than two follow-ups is considered spam by most journalists and damages future pitch acceptance. Accept no response as a no and move on. The relationship may still be useful for future stories.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Press Kit">
    <p>Press kit hosted at yourdomain.com/press. Required assets: founder bio (50-word and 200-word versions), company boilerplate (100 words), high-res logos (PNG and SVG), product screenshots, founder photos (headshot, candid), key stats (users, revenue, growth), pre-approved quotes, fact sheet.</p>
    <reference path="templates/founder-bio.md">Founder bio template in 50-word and 200-word formats</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Leveraging Coverage">
    <p>When coverage is published: share on social and tag the journalist (thank them publicly), add to "As Seen In" section on homepage, email the subscriber list about the coverage, track backlink and referral traffic, and note the journalist in your database as a warm contact for future stories.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Respond to all coverage — positive and negative — within 24 hours with acknowledgment; never dispute factual errors publicly without first contacting the journalist privately.</statement>
      <rationale>Journalists remember how companies respond to their coverage. Gracious acknowledgment of positive coverage builds the relationship; private fact-correction maintains credibility. Public disputes burn the relationship permanently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-journalist-targeting.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/haro-response.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
