<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="IaC PR Review Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable axis rules every IaC PR review must apply. A PR may not be approved if any axis returns a block verdict.</summary>

  <section title="The five axes">

    <rule id="r1-blast-radius-tier" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map every changed resource to a blast radius tier (S0 = global outage if misconfigured, S1 = single-region outage, S2 = single service, S3 = sandbox). Reject PR if blast radius tier is unstated for ANY changed resource, OR if S0 / S1 changes lack a documented mitigation (canary, feature flag, or maintenance window).</statement>
      <rationale source="incident postmortems">Most production IaC outages stem from a high-blast-radius change reviewed without the reviewer realizing the tier. Forcing per-resource tier surfaces the risk upfront.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-iam-changes-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every IAM-policy / role-binding / service-account change requires an explicit reviewer comment naming: principal, added_permissions, removed_permissions, scope_of_resources. Reject PR if IAM changes are present without this summary, OR if any added_permission grants wildcard ("*") action on production resources.</statement>
      <rationale source="cloud-security audit findings">Silent IAM escalation is the most common audit finding. Wildcard policies appear regularly because the original author "just needed it to work."</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-state-safety" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For Terraform / OpenTofu PRs: reviewer must verify the plan output contains no destroy-and-recreate operations on stateful resources (databases, queues, storage buckets, persistent volumes). Reject PR if such operations are detected, unless a documented state-migration ticket is linked.</statement>
      <rationale source="data-loss postmortems">Destroy-and-recreate on a stateful resource silently drops production data. Plan-output review catches this in seconds.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-secrets-handling" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Verify: (a) no plaintext secrets in diff, (b) secrets-manager references resolve via supported syntax, (c) any new secret has a documented rotation policy, (d) GHA workflows referencing `secrets.X` declare `permissions:` block. Reject PR on any failure.</statement>
      <rationale source="GHA / Terraform leak studies">Even encrypted-at-rest secrets leak through unscoped GHA permissions or untemplated secret references. The four sub-checks are non-optional.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-rollback-plan-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>PR description must include a rollback plan with: rollback_command, expected_state_after_rollback, max_time_to_rollback. Reject PR if any of these three fields is missing, vague ("revert the commit"), or unverified.</statement>
      <rationale source="MTTR studies">Outages where rollback is undefined extend MTTR by 3-10×. Pre-defined rollback turns recovery into a deterministic action.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Reviewer comment with per-axis verdict">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
## Review

[blast_radius]    S1  — RDS instance + IAM role. Mitigation: maintenance window
                       declared 2026-05-22 23:00 UTC. ✅
[iam]             added: rds:Describe* on prod-db (scoped). removed: none.
                       no wildcards. ✅
[state_safety]    plan output: 0 destroy + 0 recreate. ✅
[secrets]         no plaintext secrets. RDS password sourced from
                       aws_secretsmanager_secret_version.db_pwd. rotation = 90d. ✅
[rollback]        rollback_command: `terraform apply -target=... -auto-approve`
                       expected_state: prior tag v3.4.1. max_time: 8 min. ✅

Verdict: APPROVE.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates the five axes producing a single approval verdict.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Rubber-stamp review">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"LGTM"
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates the absence of every axis. PRs approved with "LGTM" alone fail this methodology.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
