<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="personas Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for personas. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Distinguish research-based personas (after ≥6 interviews), provisional personas (assumptions to validate), and proto-personas (team's current understanding for quick alignment). Only research-based personas should drive feature decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Provisional and proto-personas are scaffolding — useful for kickoff, but lack evidence. Building product on them propagates assumptions. Upgrade to research-based as data arrives.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every persona MUST include: name, photo/illustration, demographics, goals (3–5), frustrations (3–5), behaviors (≥2), context (when/where/devices), scenario, and at least one verbatim quote tied to a research participant. Personas without scenarios are wallpaper.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Name makes it real. Photo (illustration, not AI-generated) makes it human. Goals and frustrations are decision criteria. Behaviors show how they work. Scenario operationalizes the persona — designers test features against "would this help Sarah on Monday 9am?" not just "is this for a manager?" Quote-with-ID prevents agent fabrication.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conduct ≥6 user interviews before persona creation. Cluster interview transcripts by goals + behaviors (NOT demographics). For each cluster, surface 3+ verbatim quotes from ≥2 participants. Reject clusters supported by fewer than 2 participants. Cap at 3–5 clusters, each representing a primary persona.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">≥6 interviews surface recurring patterns; fewer interviews amplify noise. Goal/behavior clustering is more predictive than demographics. Verbatim quotes with participant ID prevent agent paraphrasing and ensure grounding in evidence. Reject noise (single-mention outliers). 3–5 clusters keep the team focused.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
