<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="personas Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for personas as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Too many personas (8+) that the team cannot remember.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each additional persona dilutes focus. Beyond 5 primary + 2 secondary, teams default to "it applies to everyone" and personas become wallpaper.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Personas without scenarios are pretty posters, ignored in real decisions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Abstract goals feel detached. Scenarios (Sarah's Monday 9am rush) make the persona operational — designers test features against the scenario, not the persona name.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM-generated personas inherit dataset biases; they look real but reproduce stereotypes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents synthesize plausible-sounding personas from averages. Require quote-with-participant-ID for every trait; reject invented demographic attributes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating personas before research — "made-up" personas reinforce assumptions and push the team in the wrong direction.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-research personas become self-fulfilling prophecies. Teams design to confirm, not discover. Wait for evidence.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Personas that are just demographics (age, gender, income) with no goals or behaviors.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Demographics don't predict behavior. A 35-year-old female manager and a 35-year-old female engineer have nothing in common. Goals and behaviors are the decision-making levers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Photos generated by AI; introduces demographic bias and accessibility issues.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>AI-generated faces encode dataset biases and can misrepresent marginalized groups. Use illustrations or initials instead.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents paraphrasing quotes silently; personas become agent interpretations, not evidence.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Paraphrasing loses nuance and lets agents inject their own biases. Every trait must have a verbatim quote with participant ID.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents inventing demographic attributes that weren't in source data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs synthesize plausible-sounding attributes. If the research says "Sarah is a manager" but doesn't mention income or family status, the agent shouldn't invent it. Stick to documented traits.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents producing 8+ personas if not capped explicitly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unconstrained agents maximize coverage. Enforce max-cluster constraint and reject low-frequency clusters.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Re-clustering on a different week produces different personas; no locking of corpus snapshot.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Different data → different clusters. Lock the interview corpus used; timestamp the clustering. If you re-cluster, note it as a refresh, not a redo.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
