<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spatial-design-tools">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Phase-gated tool selection: Figma + ShapesXR for concept, Unity/Unreal for prototype, engine for production. Standardize on USD/USDZ for visionOS, glTF for Web/Quest.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>spatial-computing</tag>
      <tag>ar-vr-mr</tag>
      <tag>tool-selection</tag>
      <tag>design-workflow</tag>
      <tag>asset-pipeline</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>spatial</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
    <updated>2026-04-26</updated>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Spatial Design Tools</title>
    <summary>A phase-gated tool selection methodology for spatial (AR/VR/MR) product workflows: concept in Figma + ShapesXR, prototype in Unity or Unreal, production in engine. Standardize on USD/USDZ for visionOS, glTF for Web/Quest handoff. Asset-budget constraints (polygon count, file size) must be set at concept stage, not after artist work is done.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Traditional 2D design tools have no first-class spatial canvas. Teams that pick tools per project rather than per phase accumulate file-format friction (USDZ, glTF, FBX, USD, Unity prefabs) that breaks asset pipelines mid-sprint. Setting polygon and texture budgets early prevents the most common rework loop — artists over-build, optimizing assets under deadline pressure.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Choosing or reviewing a tool stack for a new AR/VR/MR project.</item>
        <item>Setting up designer-to-developer handoff path (Figma 2D wireframes → ShapesXR → Unity/Unreal).</item>
        <item>Evaluating a solopreneur stack for visionOS, Quest, or WebXR delivery.</item>
        <item>Onboarding designers from 2D backgrounds onto a spatial workflow.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>2D-only projects — spatial tool overhead yields no benefit.</item>
        <item>Teams already locked into a vendor mid-project — switching costs exceed gains.</item>
        <item>Marketing-only AR effects — Spark AR / Lens Studio handle that niche; the full landscape is overkill.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Phase-Gated Tool Selection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pick tools per phase, not per project: concept in Figma + ShapesXR, prototype in Unity or Unreal, production in engine.</statement>
        <rationale>Forcing one tool across all phases introduces fidelity gaps (ShapesXR concepts look different in Unity) and breaks asset pipelines at transition points.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="Tool Matrix">
        <p>Concept phase: Figma (2D wireframes with spatial annotations) + ShapesXR or Gravity Sketch (VR-native sketching). Prototype phase: ShapesXR low-fidelity → Unity or Unreal high-fidelity, tested in target headset. Production: Unity or Unreal with XR Interaction Toolkit.</p>
        <p>Device-specific additions: visionOS → Reality Composer Pro (scene authoring); Meta Quest → Meta Quest Developer Hub (sideload + metrics); WebXR → Three.js or Babylon.js.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="Format Standards by Platform">
        <rule>
          <statement>Standardize on USD/USDZ for visionOS handoff; glTF 2.0 for Web/Quest. Pick one format per device and enforce it across the asset pipeline.</statement>
          <rationale>The file-format zoo (USDZ, glTF, FBX, USD, Unity prefabs) is the primary cause of pipeline breaks. A single missing conversion flag (axis swap, scale unit) burns hours per asset.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent-Friendly Tool Assessment">
      <p>Figma: partial agent access via REST + plugin API (concept stage, export limited). ShapesXR: limited — VR-native, manual export to Unity. Gravity Sketch: partial — export FBX/OBJ/USD. Unity: full CLI + Cloud Build (batch builds, CI). Unreal: partial (Horde, BuildGraph). Reality Composer Pro: no agent API — macOS only, manual workflow. Spark AR / Lens Studio: no API — vendor-locked.</p>
      <p>For 3D capture: Polycam and Luma AI expose REST APIs and output glTF/USDZ — useful for asset library generation.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Asset Validation CLI">
      <p>Use these tools in CI to validate spatial assets before handoff:</p>
      <list>
        <item>usdcat / usdview — inspect and validate USD/USDZ (Pixar OpenUSD)</item>
        <item>gltf-validator — validate glTF 2.0 spatial assets (Khronos)</item>
        <item>realitytool — Apple visionOS USDZ packaging (Xcode 15+)</item>
        <item>gltf-pipeline — glTF compression via Draco / Meshopt (CesiumGS)</item>
        <item>Blender --background --python — headless format conversion</item>
      </list>
      <reference path="templates/spatial-budget.sh">CI asset-budget lint script</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Integration — When to use">
      <list>
        <item>Choosing a tool stack for AR/VR/MR projects across concept → prototype → production.</item>
        <item>Setting up a designer–developer handoff path for spatial work (Figma 2D wireframes → ShapesXR → Unity/Unreal).</item>
        <item>Evaluating a one-person solopreneur stack for visionOS, Quest, or WebXR delivery.</item>
        <item>Onboarding designers from 2D backgrounds; tool selection drives the learning curve.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Where it fails / limitations">
      <list>
        <item>Tool fidelity gaps: ShapesXR concepts look different in Unity; expect re-design at the prototype stage.</item>
        <item>File-format zoo (USDZ, glTF, FBX, USD, custom Unity prefabs) breaks naive automation pipelines.</item>
        <item>Many tools have no public API (Reality Composer Pro, Spark AR Studio) — agentic automation stops at "open in app, click."</item>
        <item>Hardware lock-in: Reality Composer Pro requires macOS + Vision Pro; ShapesXR requires Quest. CI is awkward.</item>
        <item>Performance budgets only become real in target engine; concept-tool exports rarely respect them.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic workflow">
      <p>Use agents to (a) recommend the right tool per project phase given device and team constraints, (b) automate format conversions and asset-budget linting, and (c) generate handoff documentation. Tool choice itself remains human; agents help narrow but the team's existing skill stack dominates the decision.</p>
      <section name="Recommended subagents">
        <list>
          <item>faion-ux-researcher-agent — assembles tool comparison matrix from current vendor docs, refreshed quarterly.</item>
          <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — implements export/conversion scripts and CI hooks once tooling is selected.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Prompt pattern">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Recommend a spatial design tool stack for:
  team_size: <N>
  primary_device: VisionPro|Quest|HoloLens|Web
  fidelity_target: concept|hi-fi-prototype|production
  budget_usd_year: <N>
  existing_skills: [Figma, Unity, Blender, ...]

Output JSON:
  concept: {tool, reason}
  prototype: {tool, reason}
  production: {engine, reason}
  asset_pipeline: [tool→tool, format]
  handoff_format: USDZ|glTF|prefab
  estimated_learning_curve_per_role: {role: weeks}
Cite vendor docs only — no invented features.]]></code>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI tools">
      <p>Tool landscape for spatial design workflows:</p>
      <list>
        <item>usdcat / usdview — Inspect, validate, convert USD/USDZ (https://openusd.org)</item>
        <item>gltf-validator — Validate glTF spatial assets (https://github.khronos.org/glTF-Validator/)</item>
        <item>realitytool — Apple visionOS USDZ packaging (Xcode 15+)</item>
        <item>Blender --background --python — Headless asset processing, format conversion (https://www.blender.org)</item>
        <item>Unity -batchmode -nographics — Headless build, asset import pipeline (Unity docs)</item>
        <item>unreal-cli (UnrealBuildTool) — Headless Unreal builds (UE docs)</item>
        <item>gltf-pipeline — glTF compression, Draco, Meshopt (https://github.com/CesiumGS/gltf-pipeline)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Services &amp; apps">
      <p>Common spatial design platforms and their agent-friendliness:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Figma + 3D plugins (SaaS) — Partial (REST + plugin API). Concept stage; export limited.</item>
        <item>ShapesXR (SaaS) — Limited. VR-native concept; manual export to Unity.</item>
        <item>Gravity Sketch (SaaS) — Partial. VR design; export FBX/OBJ/USD.</item>
        <item>Bezel (SaaS) — Yes (REST). Browser-first spatial tool.</item>
        <item>Unity (Commercial) — Yes (CLI + Cloud Build). Production VR/AR engine.</item>
        <item>Unreal Engine (Source-available) — Yes (Horde, BuildGraph). Higher fidelity, MetaHumans.</item>
        <item>Reality Composer Pro (macOS app) — No. visionOS-only; manual workflow.</item>
        <item>Spark AR / Lens Studio (SaaS) — No. Vendor-locked AR effect tools.</item>
        <item>Adobe Aero (SaaS) — No. Sunset-track; avoid for new projects.</item>
        <item>Polycam / Luma AI (SaaS) — Yes (REST). 3D capture → glTF/USDZ for asset library.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Best practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pick tools per phase, not per project. Concept in Figma + ShapesXR, prototype in Unity, production in Unity or Unreal.</item>
        <item>Standardize on USD/USDZ for visionOS handoff; glTF for Web/Quest. Pick one per device and stick to it.</item>
        <item>Set polygon and texture budgets at concept time, not after the artist has spent two weeks on assets.</item>
        <item>Keep a "single source of truth" repo for shared assets; tool-specific copies drift within a sprint.</item>
        <item>Test in target headset by week 2 of any project; concept-tool fidelity hides 80% of the comfort issues.</item>
        <item>Document the export chain step-by-step; a single missing flag (axis swap, scale unit) burns hours per asset.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-agent gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Vendor feature lists shift fast; LLMs trained months ago miss recent additions and removals. Cite live URLs.</item>
        <item>"Reality Composer" vs. "Reality Composer Pro" are different tools; agents conflate them constantly.</item>
        <item>WebXR vs. native engine confusion: agents will recommend Three.js for a Vision Pro project (wrong runtime).</item>
        <item>Asset pipeline scripts must declare unit (meters), axis (Y-up vs. Z-up), and handedness; LLMs omit these and produce subtly broken assets.</item>
        <item>Performance estimates from agents are folklore. Always benchmark on target hardware.</item>
        <item>Subscription tiers and per-seat pricing change quietly; agent budget recommendations need a manual-confirm gate.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/visionos/">Apple, Designing for visionOS — Tools</link>
      <link href="https://developer.oculus.com/design/">Meta, Designing for Quest</link>
      <link href="https://www.khronos.org/gltf/">Khronos, glTF 2.0 Specification</link>
      <link href="https://openusd.org">Pixar / Apple, Universal Scene Description (USD)</link>
    </see-also>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/spatial-budget.sh" purpose="CI script: fail build if glTF asset exceeds polygon or size budget"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
