<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Trade-off Stakeholder Communication Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every stakeholder-tailored trade-off briefing must obey. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="risk-preservation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The same one-sentence "key risk" paragraph MUST appear verbatim in all four artefacts (exec, PM, engineer, ops). If any artefact softens or omits the risk, the bundle is invalid.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — post-mortem audit of 14 architecture decisions">Stakeholder surprise is the most expensive failure mode; identical risk wording across audiences makes the surprise impossible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="exec-word-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exec-summary MUST be ≤120 words AND state both the gain and the survivable downside in the first 60 words. Decoration before substance is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Heath &amp; Heath — Made to Stick">Executives skim; if the trade-off is not in the lede, the trade-off is not communicated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="role-fit-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each artefact MUST address its role's primary concern: exec → cost/risk-to-business, PM → roadmap/dependency impact, engineer → option mechanics + what was sacrificed, ops → runbook/oncall delta. A briefing that uses identical body text for all four roles is invalid.</statement>
      <rationale source="ATAM stakeholder analysis">Different stakeholders make different decisions with the same data; the artefact must surface the decision-relevant fields.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-hidden-sacrifice" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The engineer-note MUST list what we sacrificed by choosing this option (≥1 explicit "we gave up X" line). ADRs that document only the chosen option without the sacrifice are invalid.</statement>
      <rationale source="Michael Nygard — Documenting Architecture Decisions">Future architects assume the current implementation is optimal; without the documented sacrifice they add complexity on top instead of understanding the trade.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="convergence-review-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A separate reviewer (subagent or human) MUST verify the four artefacts agree on the risk paragraph BEFORE the bundle is approved. Single-author no-review bundles are forbidden for Type-1 decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — close-rate audit on ADR briefings 2025">The author of the technical analysis is not a reliable editor of their own summary; a separate review pass catches the laundered risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
