<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-value-and-competitors" title="Value Analysis and Competitor Pricing">
  <summary>Value metric types, capture-rate formula, competitor pricing matrix structure, and sourcing rules for competitor data.</summary>

  <section title="Value metrics">
    <p>Five types of value to quantify before setting price:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Time saved: hours/week freed up, monetized at user's hourly rate</item>
      <item>Money saved: direct cost reduction</item>
      <item>Money earned: new revenue the tool enables</item>
      <item>Risk reduced: problems prevented, cost of incidents avoided</item>
      <item>Quality improved: better outcomes that translate to user revenue or retention</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Compute the value-based price ceiling as (Value Delivered per Month x Capture Rate) minus Switching Cost. Use capture rate 10-20% for productivity SaaS; 1-3% for devtools; 15-25% for vertical SaaS.</statement>
      <rationale>The folk number of 10-20% is frequently applied outside its valid range. Devtools users are price-sensitive and have many free alternatives; vertical SaaS buyers pay a premium for domain-specific value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Value-based price ceiling calculation.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Tool saves: 5 hours/week
User's time value: $50/hour
Monthly value: 5 x $50 x 4 = $1,000/month
Capture rate (productivity SaaS): 10%
Price ceiling: $1,000 x 0.10 = $100/month
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Competitor pricing matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build a pricing matrix with at least 5-8 competitors before drawing any conclusions. Mark "sales-led" explicitly for contact-form-only pricing; never estimate hidden prices.</statement>
      <rationale>Fewer than 5 data points produces misleading range estimates. Estimating "contact us" prices introduces fabrication into the analysis and corrupts the median calculation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Randomize competitor processing order to prevent anchoring. Agents given the same list consistently over-weight the first competitor's price when synthesizing the range.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs anchor on first-processed values. Randomizing the order averages out this bias across the synthesis step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Analyze annual discount structure, included limits per tier, and free tier availability. Pricing pages are A/B tested — public list prices may not match effective prices for converted customers.</p>
    <reference path="templates/pricing-report.md">Full pricing research report template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-competitor-scrape.txt">Competitor pricing extraction agent prompt</reference>
  </section>
</text>
