<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-van-westendorp" title="Van Westendorp Price Sensitivity">
  <summary>The four-question Van Westendorp method, optimal price interpretation, minimum respondent requirement, and simplified interview alternative.</summary>

  <section title="The four questions">
    <list>
      <item>Too expensive: "At what price would this be too expensive to consider?" (upper bound)</item>
      <item>Expensive but worth it: "At what price would this be expensive but worth considering?"</item>
      <item>Good deal: "At what price would this be a good deal?"</item>
      <item>Too cheap: "At what price would this be too cheap to trust?" (lower bound)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run Van Westendorp only on engaged trial users who have hit the upgrade modal, not on cold leads or survey respondents who have never used the product.</statement>
      <rationale>Cold leads systematically low-ball because they are optimizing for a hypothetical purchase. Engaged users who have experienced the value anchor to their actual willingness to pay.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Minimum respondent rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require N&gt;=30 real respondents before running Van Westendorp synthesis. Below 30, return raw quotes only; refuse to compute a recommended price range.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents fabricate Van Westendorp distributions when given fewer than 30 responses, producing price points centered on training-data anchors ($29, $49, $99, $299) regardless of actual input.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Optimal price interpretation">
    <p>The acceptable price range runs from the point where "Too Cheap" and "Too Expensive" curves cross. The optimal price is the intersection of "Cheap" and "Expensive" curves (Point of Marginal Cheapness and Point of Marginal Expensiveness). In practice: aim for the upper end of the acceptable range to maximize revenue without significant conversion loss.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Simplified interview alternative">
    <p>When N&lt;30, use three direct interview questions instead of full Van Westendorp:</p>
    <list>
      <item>"What would you expect to pay for this?" (reference point)</item>
      <item>"Would you pay $X?" (test specific price point)</item>
      <item>"What would make $X feel like a bargain?" (value anchoring)</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-value-model.txt">Value modeling agent prompt from interview transcripts</reference>
  </section>
</text>
