<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-models-and-tiers" title="Billing Models and Tier Design">
  <summary>Billing model selection table, 3-tier design rules, feature distribution pattern, and annual pricing psychology.</summary>

  <section title="Billing model selection">
    <list>
      <item>Subscription: ongoing value, sticky usage, requires retention focus (SaaS tools)</item>
      <item>One-time: discrete deliverable, no ongoing obligation (courses, templates, guides)</item>
      <item>Usage-based: variable consumption, scales with value delivered (API calls, storage, seats)</item>
      <item>Freemium: growth-first, network effects, PLG products — requires free tier that creates upgrade pressure</item>
      <item>Tiered: different customer sizes, different budgets — most B2B products</item>
      <item>Hybrid: subscription base + usage overage — complex value delivery with floor and upside</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Tier design rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design tiers backwards from desired ARPU. The middle tier should have 70-80% of Pro features at 40-50% of Pro price; this is where most users land (decoy effect).</statement>
      <rationale>The decoy effect makes the middle tier appear as the rational choice. Designing backwards from ARPU ensures the middle tier conversion actually achieves revenue targets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a 2-3x price jump between adjacent tiers. Smaller jumps do not create sufficient upgrade motivation; larger jumps create a dead zone where no tier fits mid-market customers.</statement>
      <rationale>Price jump magnitude sets the perceived value gap between tiers. A 2-3x jump is psychologically separable; a 1.2x jump is not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not give everything in the middle tier. Reserve at least one compelling feature for Pro that addresses a real pain of mid-tier users.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a genuine Pro upgrade trigger, the middle tier becomes the permanent stopping point and upgrade conversion collapses.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Annual pricing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Frame annual pricing as "2 months free" rather than "17% off" or "20% discount". Identical math; "2 months free" has significantly higher take-up in A/B tests.</statement>
      <rationale>Concrete gift framing (months free) is more actionable than percentage savings. The equivalent math does not change retention or cash flow but does change conversion rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement explicit grandfather policy for price increases: "we honor your price for 12 months". Silent grandfathering forever erodes margin; silent removal destroys trust.</statement>
      <rationale>Documented, time-limited grandfathering is predictable and builds trust with early adopters without permanently subsidizing them at new-customer CAC.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/pricing-report.md">Tier structure section of the pricing report template</reference>
  </section>
</text>
