<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-gotchas" title="Pricing Research Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Capture-rate priors by category, annual-discount math trap, currency localization, three-agent separation rule, and human-in-loop checkpoints.</summary>

  <section title="Capture-rate over-estimation">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent suggests 10-15% capture rate regardless of product category or market context.</description>
      <reason>The 10-20% folk number appears frequently in startup content. LLMs apply it uniformly without category adjustment.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Override capture rate with category-specific priors: devtools 1-3%, productivity 5-10%, vertical SaaS 15-25%. Apply these as hard overrides when the agent suggests a generic range.</statement>
      <rationale>Category-specific priors are derived from actual SaaS benchmarks (OpenView, ProfitWell). Generic 10-20% systematically overestimates devtools pricing potential and underestimates vertical SaaS.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Annual discount math">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent computes annual price as "12 x monthly x 0.83" (17% off) instead of "10 x monthly" (2 months free).</description>
      <reason>Percentage-discount framing triggers percentage math. The "2 months free" framing should produce 10 x monthly but agents revert to percentage calculation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Force the formula in the prompt: annual_price = monthly_price x 10. Do not describe it as a percentage discount.</statement>
      <rationale>Explicit formula prevents the recalculation error. The math is identical to "2 months free" and "16.7% off" but the agent will compute it correctly only when given the multiplier form.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Three-agent separation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use three separate agents for competitor scraping, value modeling, and tier design. Never let a single agent do all three — pricing logic compounds errors across stages.</statement>
      <rationale>Each stage has a different fabrication risk. A single agent accumulates errors from competitor confabulation into value modeling, then into tier recommendations. Separation provides natural checkpoints.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Currency and localization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Serve EUR/INR/BRL prices adjusted for PPP, not 1:1 USD conversion. Agents routinely miss regional pricing adjustments and produce USD-only recommendations.</statement>
      <rationale>Flat USD pricing in markets with significantly lower purchasing power dramatically reduces conversion. PPP-adjusted bands are standard for SaaS products targeting global markets.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-loop checkpoints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Actual price commits (creating Stripe price objects, publishing pricing page) are human decisions. Agent output is "recommended bands"; the button-press is not delegated.</statement>
      <rationale>Pricing errors are hard to reverse — raising prices costs customer trust; refunding grandfathered customers costs margin. The final decision requires human judgment that accounts for current business context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Reject any Van Westendorp synthesis computed from fewer than 30 real respondents.</item>
      <item>Reject any competitor feature row without a source_quote from the actual pricing page.</item>
      <item>Mark all "contact us" tiers as negotiated and exclude from median calculations.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
