<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="LB Technology Selection Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for LB technology selection. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="managed-default-on-cloud" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>On AWS / GCP / Azure, the managed LB (ALB / NLB / Global LB / Cloud LB / App Gateway / Front Door) MUST be the default choice. Self-hosted HAProxy / Nginx on cloud VMs is allowed only with a documented reason (compliance, plugin requirement, cost).</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected + GCP reliability docs">Managed LBs deliver HA, cert rotation, anycast, and DDoS protection out of the box. Self-hosting reinvents the wheel and adds 1+ FTE of ops burden.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="kubernetes-uses-ingress" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For Kubernetes workloads, the LB MUST be a Kubernetes Ingress controller (or Gateway API), not a raw HAProxy / Nginx outside the cluster targeting node IPs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kubernetes Ingress production checklist">An Ingress controller registers backend pods automatically via Endpoints; an external LB hard-coded to node IPs breaks every time the cluster scales.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="bare-metal-uses-haproxy-or-nginx" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For bare-metal deployments (no managed cloud LB and no Kubernetes), the LB MUST be HAProxy (TCP-heavy + rate limiting) or Nginx (HTTP-only + static caching). MetalLB + ingress-nginx is allowed for bare-metal K8s.</statement>
      <rationale source="HAProxy + Nginx + MetalLB reference">These two cover 95 % of bare-metal use cases; using bespoke C/Go LBs on bare-metal adds maintenance debt with no upside.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="layer-matches-tech" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The chosen technology MUST be capable of the layer chosen in lb-layer-selection. Pure L4: NLB / HAProxy mode tcp. L7: ALB / Nginx / HAProxy mode http / Envoy. Hybrid: L4 in front of L7.</statement>
      <rationale source="A10 L4-vs-L7 reference">Layer + tech inconsistency (e.g., "ALB for raw TCP") is a top architecture-review failure; tie the decision back to lb-layer-selection explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="operational-capacity-gates-self-hosted" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Self-hosted HAProxy / Nginx LBs require ≥ 2 engineers with on-call coverage trained on the tool. Teams below that capacity MUST default to managed LBs even at higher cost.</statement>
      <rationale source="SRE workbook + LB ops anecdotes">A single owner = SPOF on the operations side; 2 a.m. cert rotation failures need backup. Managed LBs let small teams ship without staffing for LB ops.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
