<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="competitive-positioning">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Use Dunford's six-step framework to position products against alternatives, translating unique attributes into measurable customer value with defensible competitive statements.</summary>
    <category>positioning</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>positioning</tag>
      <tag>competitive-analysis</tag>
      <tag>dunford</tag>
      <tag>differentiation</tag>
      <tag>product-strategy</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="competitor-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="user-personas"/>
      <ref slug="landing-page-design"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Competitive Positioning</title>

    <summary>Competitive positioning defines how a product is uniquely valuable compared to alternatives — answering "why should customers choose us?" using April Dunford's six-step framework: competitive alternatives → unique attributes → value translation → best-fit customer → market category → positioning statement. The output is a positioning-canvas.md and a one-page positioning-statement.md. Cap unique attributes at 3; every attribute must have a time-to-copy estimate; every value benefit must terminate in a measurable outcome.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Products that position as "like X but better" compete on features and lose to incumbents with larger teams. Dunford's framework finds what is genuinely different — not superior — and binds it to the customer who cares most. Without this, PMs default to comparative language ("faster", "easier") that is both unprovable and easily matched. Positioning done once and versioned in git prevents the drift that happens when landing page, pricing page, and sales deck each drift independently.</p>
      <p>The parallel Python multiprocessing engine is meaningfully faster than Super-Linter's sequential bash and produces SARIF that drops directly into GitHub Code Scanning's UI. The "one umbrella in CI, one native tool per language at the hook" split prevents the well-known anti-pattern of running MegaLinter locally (multi-gigabyte Docker pull on every commit) while still giving the agent a unified CI feed to fix from.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch positioning sprint: product exists, 3–7 named alternatives exist, landing page is next</item>
        <item>Repositioning after a pivot or pricing change where existing copy no longer matches</item>
        <item>New segment entry: same product, new ICP, parallel positioning canvas needed</item>
        <item>Pitch deck "why us, why now" slide</item>
        <item>Category-creation decision: joining existing category vs. naming a new one</item>
        <item>Quarterly positioning audit to verify unique attributes are still defensible</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before competitor analysis exists — the canvas consumes competitor-analysis.md; without it the canvas is fiction</item>
        <item>Before 5–10 user interviews — best-fit customer cannot be filled honestly without discovery</item>
        <item>Pure copywriting / headline polish — that is landing-page-design, not positioning</item>
        <item>Internal tools, side projects, or anything with a single user</item>
        <item>B2B-enterprise positioning requiring analyst relations (Gartner, Forrester) — agents lack the relationships and the data</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="six-step-framework">
      <p>April Dunford's six-step competitive positioning process with rules, strategy options, and the constraint that unique attributes must be capped at 3 with measurable outcomes.</p>

      <p>Step 1: list competitive alternatives (direct, indirect, status quo). Step 2: identify unique attributes — features only you have, approach only you take, expertise only you possess. Step 3: translate attributes to customer value via "so what" laddering. Step 4: identify best-fit customers — who values this most and why. Step 5: define market category (existing, subcategory, new). Step 6: craft positioning statement using the For/Who/Is/That/Unlike/We template.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Cap unique attributes at 3. More than 3 means no positioning — just a feature list. Agents over-list; trim hard.</statement>
        <rationale>A positioning statement with more than 3 unique attributes fails to differentiate because customers cannot hold more than 3 comparative distinctions in working memory simultaneously.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Add a time-to-copy column to the unique-attributes table. Anything copyable in fewer than 2 quarters is not a positioning anchor — it is a feature.</statement>
        <rationale>Positioning must be durable. An attribute a competitor can ship in 6 weeks is a temporary advantage, not a positioning moat. Time-to-copy forces the team to find genuinely defensible attributes.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The "so what" ladder must terminate in a measurable outcome (hours, dollars, percent, retention). Reject "save time" without a number.</statement>
        <rationale>Vague value claims cannot be tested or proven. Measurable outcomes give the sales team concrete proof points and give the agent a clear standard for rejection.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="positioning-strategies">
      <p>Head-to-Head: you are better on established criteria — risk is feature wars. Differentiation: you serve a specific need others ignore — risk is niche too small. Niche Dominance: you own a specific segment — risk is growth ceiling. Category Creation: you are truly new — risk is market education cost (18-24 months, analyst briefings, sales enablement budget required).</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For category-creation decisions, require a budget estimate for market education before proceeding. If the education cost exceeds GTM runway, fall back to subcategory positioning.</statement>
        <rationale>Category creation is not a positioning choice — it is a multi-year investment. Agents will declare new categories confidently without estimating the education cost.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="positioning-statement-requirements">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The positioning statement must contain all six clauses: For, Who, Is, That, Unlike, We. Fail the build if any clause is missing.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents drop the "Unlike" clause because it feels confrontational. Without it, the statement has no competitive anchor and reduces to a tagline.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Test the statement against three "would this exclude?" questions: (a) a persona you don't want, (b) a use case you don't serve, (c) a price point above or below yours. If none are excluded, the positioning is too broad.</statement>
        <rationale>Good positioning is as much about who you are not for as who you are for. A statement that excludes nobody is marketing copy, not positioning.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Better" positioning: competitive claims of faster, easier, simpler without a stated dimension and number.</description>
        <reason>Comparative-without-dimension claims cannot be proven, are easily matched by competitors, and signal that the team has not found real differentiation. "5x faster at data export than Salesforce" is allowed; "faster" alone is not.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Static positioning: canvas written once and never revisited as market changes.</description>
        <reason>Version the canvas in git with a date stamp. Quarterly diff reveals positioning drift before customers notice. Markets shift; positioning must track.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Best-fit-customer defined as "ambitious teams who want to ship faster."</description>
        <reason>Enforce a persona schema: role, company size, trigger event, current alternative, willingness-to-pay. Without schema enforcement, agents produce meaningless audience descriptions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="worked-examples">
      <example type="good" title="Project Management Tool Positioning">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Solo project manager positioned against complex tools.

Alternatives: Asana/Monday (feature-rich, complex), Trello (simple but limited), Spreadsheets (free but painful).
Unique attributes: designed for solo creators, no team features (simpler), built-in time tracking.
Time-to-copy: 6-12 quarters (teams at Asana have no product incentive to simplify — that would cannibalize team plans).
Value: get organized in 5 minutes, not 5 hours.
Best-fit: solo freelancers overwhelmed by big tools (trigger: just bounced from Asana free trial; WTP: $12/mo).
Market category: personal project manager (existing subcategory, not new category).

Positioning statement:
For solo freelancers
Who need to track projects without complexity
SoloBoard is a personal project manager
That gets you organized in 5 minutes
Unlike Asana and Monday
We deliberately have no team features.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Failed Positioning Attempt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"SoloBoard is the easiest and most powerful project manager for modern teams."

FAILS: "easiest" and "most powerful" are unsupported superlatives.
FAILS: "modern teams" is not a best-fit customer — it excludes nobody.
FAILS: missing Unlike clause.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Email Marketing Platform Positioning">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Indie writer platform positioned against subscriber-based pricing.

Alternatives: Mailchimp (all-in-one, expensive at scale), ConvertKit (creator-focused), Substack (newsletter-native).
Unique attributes: flat pricing (no per-subscriber fees), focused on &lt;10k subscribers, native Ghost/WordPress integration.
Time-to-copy: 2-4 quarters (Mailchimp changing pricing model requires board-level decision; ConvertKit has subscriber-based revenue dependency).
Value: grow without pricing anxiety (measurable: no bill increase when subscriber count doubles).
Best-fit: indie writers and bloggers building an audience (trigger: hit 1k subscribers on Mailchimp, saw next month's bill; WTP: $29/mo flat).

Positioning statement:
For indie writers growing their newsletter
Who worry about costs as they scale
WriterMail is email marketing
That stays affordable forever
Unlike Mailchimp and ConvertKit
We charge flat fees, not per-subscriber.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Positioning Map Usage">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
2x2 map to visualize gaps. Use mermaid-cli to render as SVG for stakeholder review.

Dimensions:
  X-axis: Price (low -> high)
  Y-axis: Simplicity (complex -> simple)

Position us in the "low price + simple" quadrant.
Competitors Asana/Monday: high price + complex.
Trello: low price + complex (more features than it looks).
Gap: low price + simple -- that is our position.

Mermaid render:
mmdc -i positioning-map.mmd -o positioning-map.svg
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive this with the faion-research-agent (or a dedicated faion-positioning-agent if available; otherwise reuse faion-research-agent in mode: niche) as the orchestrator on top of an existing competitive-analysis.md. The orchestrator runs Dunford's six steps serially because each step constrains the next: alternatives → unique attributes → value translation → best-fit customer → market category → statement. Fan out only the value-translation step (one parallel "so-what laddering" Task per attribute) since attributes are independent. Final synthesis writes .aidocs/product_docs/positioning-canvas.md and a one-page positioning-statement.md. Always run a devil's-advocate pass with a different model (sonnet → opus) that critiques the statement from each named competitor's CMO perspective.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run Dunford's six steps serially because each step constrains the next. Fan out only the value-translation step (one parallel task per attribute) since attributes are independent.</statement>
        <rationale>Steps 1-4 have hard dependencies: alternatives must exist before attributes, attributes before value, value before best-fit customer. Parallelizing constrained steps produces incoherent outputs.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run positioning AFTER competitor-analysis AND user-personas exist. Both are inputs; canvas without them is fiction.</statement>
        <rationale>Hallucinated competitor positioning (agent invents taglines from training data rather than current homepages) is the dominant quality failure. Real competitor pages must be fetched and passed as input.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always run a devil's-advocate pass with a different model (sonnet → opus) that role-plays each top-3 competitor's CMO trying to dismiss your positioning. Iterate once based on the critique.</statement>
        <rationale>Self-serving positioning is invisible to the agent that produced it. An adversarial pass from the competitor's perspective surfaces weaknesses that peer review misses.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="orchestrator-prompt-pattern">
      <example type="good" title="Orchestrator Entry Prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Build positioning canvas for {product}. Inputs:
- .aidocs/product_docs/competitive-analysis.md (alternatives + matrix)
- .aidocs/product_docs/user-personas.md (best-fit-customer source)
Use Dunford's 6-step framework.
Hard rules:
- No comparatives ("better/faster/easier") without dimension + number.
- Every unique attribute must have a time-to-copy estimate in quarters.
- Reject any best-fit segment that includes >30% of alternatives' user bases.
Output: positioning-canvas.md + positioning-statement.md (one page).
Then spawn devil's-advocate Task from each top-3 competitor's CMO POV; iterate once.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Per-Attribute Value-Laddering Fan-Out">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
So-what ladder for attribute: '{attribute}'.
Three levels: feature benefit -> business benefit -> emotional/strategic outcome.
Bind the outcome to a measurable: hours saved, revenue, retention, risk reduction.
No vague verbs ("improve", "enhance"). Each level must use a different noun class.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Comparative language by default: LLMs produce "better/faster/easier" even when prompted for differentiation.</description>
        <reason>Explicit prompt rule plus positioning-lint.sh pre-commit hook catches it. Comparative without dimension+number is the single most common positioning quality failure from LLM agents.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated competitor positioning from training data instead of current homepages.</description>
        <reason>Pass live homepage HTML/text into the prompt. Never let the agent rely on memory for competitor claims — they are updated constantly and the agent's training is stale.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Ladder collapse: so-what laddering produces three levels that paraphrase the same idea.</description>
        <reason>Force each level to use a different noun class (feature benefit → business outcome → emotional/strategic outcome) and a measurable at the terminal level.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Category-creation inflation: every product becomes "the first AI-native X."</description>
        <reason>Require a citation that the proposed category does not yet exist — G2 search returning zero results, or no Wikipedia entry for the category name. Fiction categories harm credibility.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Proof points filled with "trusted by leaders" marketing copy.</description>
        <reason>Every proof point must be a citable URL, customer quote, or measurable outcome. Marketing copy is not evidence and fails the agent's own lint rules.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="human-in-the-loop-checkpoints">
      <list>
        <item>Approve the unique-attributes shortlist (no more than 3) before value-laddering begins</item>
        <item>Sign off on best-fit-customer narrowing before the statement is drafted</item>
        <item>Approve the final positioning statement before it enters marketing, landing-page, or pricing copy — this is a strategic decision agents must not own</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Run positioning AFTER competitor-analysis AND user-personas — never in parallel. Both are inputs; canvas without them is fiction.</item>
        <item>Force the agent to fill the "Competitive Alternatives" cell with the literal verbatim from won/lost CRM notes ("we considered X but went with Y because…"), not from Google searches.</item>
        <item>Cap "unique attributes" at 3. More than 3 = no positioning, just a feature list. Agents over-list; trim hard.</item>
        <item>Add a "time-to-copy" column to the unique-attributes table. Anything copyable in less than 2 quarters is not a positioning anchor; it's a feature.</item>
        <item>The "so-what" ladder must terminate in a measurable outcome (hours, dollars, percent, retention) — not a vague verb. Reject "save time" without a number.</item>
        <item>Best-fit customer narrows over iterations, never widens. If round 2 of the canvas has a broader ICP than round 1, the agent regressed.</item>
        <item>Run a separate devil's-advocate pass with a different model (sonnet/opus combo) that role-plays each top-3 competitor's CMO and tries to dismiss your positioning. Iterate once.</item>
        <item>Version the canvas in git with a date stamp; quarter-over-quarter diff reveals positioning drift before customers notice.</item>
        <item>Test the statement against three "would this exclude…?" questions: (a) a persona you don't want, (b) a use case you don't serve, (c) a price point above/below yours. If none get excluded, the positioning is too broad.</item>
        <item>For category-creation decisions, require the agent to budget the education cost (analyst briefings, content marketing months, sales enablement). If the budget exceeds GTM runway, fall back to subcategory positioning.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="references-and-related">
      <list>
        <item>April Dunford, Obviously Awesome (2019) — canonical 10-step positioning framework; chapters 5-9 are the source for the canvas.</item>
        <item>April Dunford, Sales Pitch (2023) — extends positioning into the deck; useful for the proof-points section.</item>
        <item>Geoffrey Moore, Crossing the Chasm (1991/2014) — segment-and-niche-dominance reasoning; foundation for steps 4-5.</item>
        <item>Al Ries &amp; Jack Trout, Positioning: The Battle for Your Mind (1981) — the original "you are positioned in the customer's mind, not in your spec sheet".</item>
        <item>Michael Porter, Competitive Strategy (1980) — Five Forces underlying competitive-alternatives analysis.</item>
        <item>A. Osterwalder, Value Proposition Design (2014) — pain-gain-job mapping for the value-translation step.</item>
        <item>pro/research/researcher/competitor-analysis/agent-integration.md — upstream dependency; how to produce the alternatives input this canvas consumes.</item>
        <item>pro/research/researcher/agent-invocation/README.md — faion-research-agent invocation reference.</item>
        <item>solo/product/product-planning/ — sibling solo-tier positioning material when full PM stack isn't needed.</item>
        <item>Anthropic, Building effective agents (2024) — orchestrator-workers pattern (used here for value-laddering fan-out).</item>
        <item>Pmarca / a16z, The only thing that matters — product-market-fit lens for pressure-testing best-fit customer.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/positioning-canvas.md" purpose="Positioning canvas: alternatives, attributes, value translation, customer, category, statement"/>
      <template path="templates/positioning-lint.sh" purpose="Linter: flags comparative language without dimension and checks six-clause structure"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="competitor-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="user-personas"/>
      <ref slug="landing-page-design"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
