<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="match-real-world Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for match-real-world. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use user-friendly language in place of technical jargon: "Log out" instead of "Terminate session", "Search" instead of "Execute query", "Please enter a valid email" instead of "Invalid input", "Folder / Collection" instead of "Repository", "Sign in" instead of "Authenticate", "Update / Refresh" instead of "Synchronize".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Users search and think in everyday language. Technical terminology creates a barrier to entry and forces users to learn internal system concepts before accomplishing their actual goal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Error messages must explain what happened in plain language (no error codes or HTTP status), tell the user what to do next, and match the intended tone (friendly/professional/minimal).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Error messages occur at moments of user frustration. A technical error code adds confusion; plain language + next steps restores user agency and reduces support load.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Logical information order must follow how the user thinks, not how the system stores data. Address forms: Street → City → State → Zip → Country (user mental model), not Country → State → City → Street → Zip (database schema).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Users have a cognitive map of how things are organized in the real world. Forcing them to learn the system's organization creates confusion and errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Icons must be paired with text labels (or tooltips if space-constrained). Icon-only controls force users to recall meaning; recognition is easier than recall.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Even if a metaphor is outdated (e.g., floppy disk for save), users recognize it. But unfamiliar icons are pure memorization burden.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plain-language alternatives must be sourced from support tickets and user interview transcripts, not from the team's internal vocabulary. Do not guess.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Plausible-sounding terminology chosen by designers often differs from what users actually search for and use. Research is the only reliable input.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For multi-locale products, have a native speaker validate terminology in each locale independently — direct translation of English user-friendly terms can produce awkward or misleading text.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">What is plain language in one culture may be confusing or offended in another. Localization requires cultural expertise, not just language skill.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
