<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Multi-Product Portfolio Management Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Solo Multi-Product Portfolio Management application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-time-block-per-product" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign explicit weekly hours per product. Sum &lt; 40h. Without explicit blocks, attention defaults to newest product.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Attention is the scarce input; without budget, newest product cannibalizes maintenance of older ones.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-kill-criteria-quarterly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each product has explicit kill criteria reviewed quarterly: MRR &lt; $X for 6 months OR user count declining 3 consecutive quarters. Below = kill or transfer.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Sunk-cost is the silent killer of solo portfolios; explicit criteria prevent indefinite zombies.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-shared-audience-leverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Products share an audience channel (newsletter, X account, community). Cross-promote sparingly (≤1 mention / 4 weeks per channel).</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Audience leverage is the moat of solo portfolios; over-promotion = unsubscribe spike.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-tech-stack-consolidation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Products share stack components where possible (auth, billing, design system). Different stacks per product multiplies maintenance load.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">5 stacks across 5 products = 5× security updates; consolidation cuts maintenance 50-70%.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-90-day-revenue-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly review: MRR / hour-spent per product. Lowest-ratio product gets reduced time OR killed. Highest-ratio gets more time.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Time-allocation should follow evidence, not enthusiasm; quarterly review is the rebalance.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>