<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="lessons-learned">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Continuous capture and structured retrieval of project knowledge to prevent repeated mistakes, with mandatory kickoff consultation and artifact-driven feedback loops.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>lessons-learned</tag>
      <tag>retrospectives</tag>
      <tag>knowledge-management</tag>
      <tag>organizational-learning</tag>
      <tag>continuous-improvement</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>closure</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Lessons Learned</title>
    <summary>Continuous capture, structured categorisation, and mandatory retrieval of project knowledge so that the same mistakes are not repeated. A lesson is only valid if it has a specific situation, measurable impact, root cause, and an actionable recommendation with a verb. "Communication was bad" is not a lesson — it is noise.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Most lessons-learned databases are write-only: entries are logged at project close and never read again. The failure mode is not lack of capture — it is lack of retrieval at future project kickoff and lack of a feedback loop into checklists and templates. Without a mandatory retrieval step at kickoff, the database is decorative.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Capturing decision rationale and outcomes throughout a project, not only at close-out</item>
        <item>Running structured retrospectives (per milestone, per sprint, project-end)</item>
        <item>Building an org-level knowledge base queried by future PMs before starting similar projects</item>
        <item>Feeding faion-improver and faion-sdd-execution mistake/pattern memories with structured lessons</item>
        <item>Generating project close-out reports where the top 5 lessons are the executive summary</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Trivial routine work where lessons are predictable — capturing them adds noise</item>
        <item>Active blame/political environments — fix the culture first or run anonymous-only retros</item>
        <item>Live-incident postmortems — use a blameless postmortem template, not project lessons</item>
        <item>Confidential/regulated programs where each lesson requires individual legal review before sharing</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="when-to-capture">
      <title>When to Capture</title>
      <rule>
        <statement>Capture lessons within 24 hours of the trigger event. Weekly retros lose specifics; project-close retros lose everything from earlier phases.</statement>
        <rationale>Memory decays exponentially. Within 24 hours, the context, numbers, and causal chain are still accessible; a month later only the emotion remains.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Capture triggers: after each milestone, when problems occur, when successes happen, during retrospectives, at project close.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="lesson-schema">
      <title>Lesson Schema</title>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every lesson must have all five fields: situation (facts), impact (effect on project), root_cause (why), lesson (insight), recommendation (actionable change with a verb, an owner type, and a measurable outcome).</statement>
        <rationale>Missing any field makes the lesson unusable: no situation = no context, no recommendation = no change.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/lesson-validator.py">Validator that rejects incomplete or vague lessons</reference>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Lesson: "Communication was bad." No situation, no root cause, no actionable recommendation. This is the median entry in most lessons databases.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Situation: new framework introduced with no training time budgeted. Impact: development 40% longer. Root cause: excitement about new tech, no training estimate. Lesson: new technology requires explicit ramp time. Recommendation: add 25% buffer when introducing a framework new to the team and schedule a dedicated 2-day training sprint before development begins.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="specificity-rules">
      <title>Specificity Rules</title>
      <rule>
        <statement>Reject any recommendation that lacks an action verb, an owner type, and either a metric or a process change. "Improve estimation" fails; "Add 25% buffer to estimates when introducing a framework new to the team" passes.</statement>
        <rationale>Vague recommendations are re-logged identically on the next project. Specificity is what makes the lesson transferable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag lessons by context, not just category: technology stack, team size, vendor involvement, regulated domain. Retrieval needs context match, not just topic match.</statement>
        <rationale>A lesson about API integration on a regulated healthcare project is not the same as one on an unregulated internal tool, even if both are tagged "technical".</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="capture-antipatterns">
      <title>Capture Antipatterns</title>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Lessons captured only at project end.</description>
        <reason>Recency bias and survivorship bias dominate: only the last few weeks are memorable, and only people still on the project participate.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Blame sessions framed as lessons-learned meetings.</description>
        <reason>Teams stop sharing honestly when the session becomes a post-mortem of individual failures. Facilitator must enforce "process not people" ground rule actively.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM summarisation of retro notes producing generic platitudes.</description>
        <reason>Summarisation compresses two distinct lessons into one homogeneous statement. Preserve verbatim quotes alongside derived summaries.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="mandatory-kickoff-retrieval">
      <title>Mandatory Kickoff Retrieval</title>
      <rule>
        <statement>At every project kickoff, retrieve the top 3–5 lessons matching the project context (tech, team size, vendor count, regulated flag) and read them aloud with the team. An unread database is dead weight.</statement>
        <rationale>The only way to break the write-only pattern is to make retrieval a mandatory step in the kickoff agenda, not an optional pre-read.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Sunset lessons older than 24 months or re-validate them against current context. Stale lessons reflect a different technology and team environment and can mislead.</statement>
        <rationale>Industry tooling, team norms, and project contexts drift; a 3-year-old lesson about a deprecated framework is actively harmful.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="retro-session-structure">
      <title>Retro Session Structure</title>
      <p>Six-phase structure: (1) open with ground rules (process not people, equal participation, honest), (2) what worked — 15 min, (3) what did not work — 15 min, (4) root causes — 15 min, (5) recommendations with owners — 15 min, (6) action items with due dates — 10 min.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Prompt explicitly for negative lessons: "what slowed us down?" must be asked with equal weight to "what worked?". Positive-framed prompts produce 3:1 positive-to-negative ratio by default.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs and human facilitators both have politeness bias; negative lessons require explicit prompting to surface.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="storage-and-tagging">
      <title>Storage and Tagging</title>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use a closed tag enum for category: planning | execution | technical | team | vendor | stakeholder | other. Reject free-text categories — they drift into ungroupable noise within three projects.</statement>
        <rationale>Consistent tagging is the prerequisite for semantic search; ad-hoc categories produce a lookup table that no query matches reliably.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track which lessons led to checklist or template updates — these are the high-value ones. Archive the rest after 24 months if they produced no process change.</statement>
        <rationale>A lesson that has been re-logged three times without producing a process change is not a lesson — it is a complaint. Archive it and fix the underlying process.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="feedback-loop">
      <title>Feedback Loop</title>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every lesson recommendation must trace to a concrete artifact update (checklist item added, template modified, onboarding doc updated) or be flagged as "recommendation not implemented" in the next quarterly review.</statement>
        <rationale>Recommendations with no artifact update are decorative. The close-the-loop step is what differentiates a learning organisation from a complaint archive.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <title>Agentic Workflow</title>
      <p>The agent runs three loops. (1) Capture loop: a daily Slack/Discord bot prompts "any lesson today?" and parses unstructured replies into the standard schema. (2) Retro loop: a facilitator agent runs structured sessions (6-phase agenda), captures sticky-note input, clusters via embeddings, surfaces root causes. (3) Apply loop: at every new project's kickoff, a kickoff-briefer agent queries the lessons DB for matching context (similar tech, similar team size, similar vendor) and pre-loads the relevant top-5. Humans verify, edit, and commit lessons; humans also own the action items.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>lesson-capturer — converts free-text retro notes into the canonical schema (situation/impact/root-cause/lesson/recommendation)</item>
        <item>retro-facilitator — runs the 6-phase agenda; enforces equal speaking time; clusters themes via embedding similarity</item>
        <item>kickoff-briefer — given a new project profile, retrieves top-N matching lessons from history</item>
        <item>recommendation-tracker — tracks whether lessons' recommendations got integrated into checklists/templates; flags decay</item>
        <item>faion-improver — already runs an audit/improve loop; lessons feed the mistakes.md memory</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-execution — patterns and mistakes from lessons feed reflexion memory in the next sprint</item>
      </list>
      <p>Capture mode prompt:</p>
      <p>Input: free text (Slack message, retro note). Output JSON: { "title": "&lt;short&gt;", "category": "planning|execution|technical|team|vendor|stakeholder|other", "impact_level": "high|medium|low", "situation": "&lt;facts&gt;", "impact": "&lt;effect on project&gt;", "root_cause": "&lt;why&gt;", "lesson": "&lt;insight&gt;", "recommendation": "&lt;actionable change&gt;", "evidence_links": ["&lt;URL&gt;"] }. Reject if recommendation is not actionable (no verb, no owner, no metric).</p>
      <p>Retrieval mode prompt (kickoff):</p>
      <p>Input: {project_type, tech_stack, team_size, vendor_count, regulated}. Output: top 5 lessons by semantic + tag similarity, with confidence.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <title>Best Practices</title>
      <list>
        <item>Capture lessons within 24 hours of the trigger event; weekly retros lose specifics</item>
        <item>Make the recommendation testable: "Add 25% buffer when introducing new framework" beats "improve estimation"</item>
        <item>Tag lessons by context (tech, team size, vendor type, regulation), not just by category. Retrieval needs context match, not topic match</item>
        <item>Review the top 3 matching lessons at every kickoff out loud; an unread database is dead weight</item>
        <item>Sunset lessons older than 24 months (or re-validate); industry context drifts and stale lessons mislead</item>
        <item>Track which lessons led to checklist/template updates — these are the high-value ones. Archive the rest</item>
        <item>Run lessons-learned blame-free: facilitator opens with "we discuss processes, not people", and enforces it</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <title>AI-Agent Gotchas</title>
      <list>
        <item>LLMs flatten distinct lessons into homogeneous platitudes during summarisation. Preserve verbatim quotes plus a derived summary</item>
        <item>Categorisation drift: ten retros run by ten agents create twenty category names. Pin a closed enum (planning/execution/technical/team/vendor/stakeholder/other) and reject others</item>
        <item>Sentiment bias: positive-framed prompts harvest "what went well" &gt; "what went wrong" by 3:1; balance the prompt explicitly</item>
        <item>Hallucinated impact metrics: agents fabricate "delayed 3 weeks" when the source said "some delay". Demand evidence_links or refuse</item>
        <item>Privacy: lesson capture often contains PII / vendor names / financials; run a PII redactor before storing in shared DB</item>
        <item>Embedding drift: model upgrades silently change retrieval; re-index with version pinned</item>
        <item>"Action item theatre": agents emit recommendations with no owner/due-date and the database fills with orphans. Require owner + by-date or reject the lesson</item>
        <item>Survivorship bias in retro: only project survivors speak; quitters' lessons are missing. Run mid-project pulse surveys for early signal</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations">
      <title>Where It Fails / Limitations</title>
      <list>
        <item>Most lessons-learned databases are write-only: people log entries no one ever reads. Without a query path at project-start, the methodology fails</item>
        <item>Lessons captured at project end suffer recency bias and survivorship bias; only people still on the project participate</item>
        <item>"Communication was bad" is the median lesson — vague, unactionable, repeated forever. Without specificity rules, the database becomes wallpaper</item>
        <item>LLM summarisation flattens nuance: two distinct lessons collapse into a generic platitude</item>
        <item>Cross-project search depends on consistent tagging; ad-hoc category fields drift over years and become ungroupable</item>
        <item>Anonymisation tension: removing names hides the source context that gives a lesson credibility; keeping names suppresses honesty</item>
        <item>Recommendations rarely close the loop into checklists/process; without a feedback mechanism, the lesson is decorative</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <title>Tools and Services</title>
      <p>CLI tools:</p>
      <list>
        <item>obsidian-cli — Manage lessons in an Obsidian vault with bidirectional links (https://github.com/Yakitrak/obsidian-cli)</item>
        <item>git — Version-control lessons; review via PRs (https://git-scm.com/)</item>
        <item>chromadb / qdrant / weaviate — Embedding store for semantic retrieval (https://www.trychroma.com/)</item>
        <item>pandoc — Convert lessons MD → close-out PDF / DOCX (https://pandoc.org/)</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli — Render fishbone / 5-whys diagrams in lessons (https://github.com/mermaid-js/mermaid-cli)</item>
        <item>jq — Query JSONL lesson archives (https://stedolan.github.io/jq/)</item>
        <item>gh issue — Track recommendation actions as GitHub issues (https://cli.github.com/)</item>
      </list>
      <p>Services &amp; apps:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Confluence + AI — SaaS, REST API. Standard PMO knowledge home; weak tagging</item>
        <item>Notion — SaaS, REST API. Database + relations; good for tagging</item>
        <item>Obsidian — OSS, file-based. Markdown vault; agent-friendly</item>
        <item>GitBook — SaaS, REST API. Public-facing playbooks</item>
        <item>Glean / Mem — SaaS, REST API. Org-wide enterprise search over lessons</item>
        <item>Coda — SaaS, REST API. Database-driven retros</item>
        <item>Miro / Mural — SaaS, REST API. Live retro boards; export to MD</item>
        <item>FunRetro / Parabol / EasyRetro — SaaS, REST API. Dedicated retro tools</item>
        <item>Linear / Jira — SaaS, REST API. Track recommendation actions</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/lesson-validator.py" purpose="Validates a lesson dict against the required schema and rejects vague recommendations" />
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://pmi.org/learning/pmbok-guide">PMI PMBOK Guide 6th Ed., Chapter 4 — Project Integration Management (Lessons Learned Register)</link>
      <link href="https://www.amazon.com/Project-Retrospectives-Handbook-Improving-Organization/dp/0932633447">Norman Kerth — Project Retrospectives (originator of the Prime Directive, blame-free retros)</link>
      <link href="https://www.amazon.com/Agile-Retrospectives-Making-Teams-Retrospectives/dp/0977616649">Esther Derby &amp; Diana Larsen — Agile Retrospectives</link>
      <link href="https://www.atlassian.com/incident-management/postmortem/blameless">Atlassian's Blameless Postmortem playbook</link>
      <link href="https://www.amyedmondson.com/">Edmondson — The Fearless Organization (psychological safety preconditions for honest lessons)</link>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/68683.html">ISO 30401:2018 — Knowledge Management Systems</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
