<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="azure-private-link Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for azure-private-link as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Private Endpoints break public DNS by default in the same VNet. Without the `privatelink.*` zone linked to every consumer VNet, resolution lands on the public IP and connects fine — to the public endpoint, defeating the entire purpose.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Azure DNS resolver checks for Private DNS zone overrides. If no zone is linked, the standard CNAME chain resolves to the public IP. There is no error — the connection succeeds, but it goes over the internet instead of the Azure backbone.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Service Endpoints and Private Endpoints look interchangeable but are not: Service Endpoints leak via subnet identity; Private Endpoints inject an IP into your VNet.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Service Endpoints allow subnet-based access to PaaS services but the service still has a public IP. Private Endpoints make the service genuinely private — no public IP exposure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Private Endpoints in module or Bicep loops without unique `name` collide silently — last-write-wins.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>When creating multiple Private Endpoints via `for_each` or `count`, each must have a unique name. Duplicate names cause silent overwrites in Terraform state or ARM deployment failures.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
