<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Mobile UX Patterns Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Mobile UX Patterns. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-touch-target-44" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Touch targets are at least 44 by 44 CSS pixels (Apple) or 48 by 48 dp (Material); spacing between targets is at least 8 pixels.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG and Material Design guidelines">Smaller targets produce mis-taps and rage-tap events.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-thumb-zone" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Primary actions live within the thumb-reach zone on one-handed grip; secondary actions may sit at the top.</statement>
      <rationale source="Steven Hoober — thumb-zone studies">Primary actions outside the thumb zone slow flows and cause grip-shift errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-platform-conventions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>iOS and Android native conventions are honoured for back navigation, modal presentation, and system shares; cross-platform divergence requires a written rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG and Material Design guidelines">Breaking conventions confuses users on their primary platform.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-offline-state" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every screen handles offline and slow-network states with explicit copy and retry affordances; spinners alone are not acceptable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mobile-network performance studies">Spinner-only states produce abandonment within seven seconds on slow networks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-orientation-safe" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rotation preserves state and scroll position unless the screen is intentionally portrait-locked.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — rotation bug reports">State loss on rotation is a recurring high-severity bug pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-mobile-ux-patterns.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
