<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Match Real World Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every match-real-world application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-user-vocabulary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every UI string flagged MUST cite evidence from the user-vocabulary corpus (ticket id, transcript line, search-log entry) before a substitution is proposed. Substitutions without citation are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen — 10 usability heuristics">Substitutions without citation are team preference, not user vocabulary; documented citations make the audit reviewable and reversible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-consistent-substitution" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a substitution is applied, it MUST be applied consistently across all surfaces (web + mobile + email + docs). Same concept, same term — inconsistency is itself a heuristic violation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen — Heuristic #4 (Consistency)">Inconsistent terms ("Sign in" / "Login" / "Log in") force users to question whether the actions are the same, breaking the mental model.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-domain-convention" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Follow established domain conventions (cart, inbox, trash) even when the underlying metaphor is dated. Replace only when user research shows the convention itself confuses the target users.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen — Heuristic #2">Conventions are pre-trained patterns; breaking them costs comprehension. The exception is research-driven, not preference-driven.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-locale-format" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dates, numbers, and addresses MUST follow the user's locale conventions. Ambiguous formats (03/04/2025) MUST be replaced with unambiguous forms (4 Mar 2025 or 2025-03-04).</statement>
      <rationale source="ICU Locale Data Markup Language">Locale-blind formats cause real errors (medical, financial, travel). The unambiguous form is mandatory.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-icon-with-label" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Primary navigation icons MUST be paired with text labels. Icon-only is allowed only for universally-recognised exceptions (magnifying-glass search, X close) with confirmed recognition evidence for the target user population.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — icon usability research">"Universal" icons are not universal; research-confirmed exceptions only.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-domain-expert-override" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For domain-expert products, "plain language" means the domain's language. Over-simplifying expert vocabulary (rewriting "invoice" → "bill" in an accounting tool) is a heuristic violation, not an improvement.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen — Heuristic #2 nuance">Expert users have precise vocabulary expectations; simplifying removes signal and loses trust.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
