<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Match Real World: Language, Conventions, and Icons">
  <summary>Rules for using familiar user vocabulary, following domain conventions, and ordering information the way users expect.</summary>

  <section title="Language Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the words users actually say when describing their tasks. Audit all UI strings by asking: would a non-technical user understand this without explanation?</statement>
      <rationale>Users have zero obligation to learn system terminology. When the interface speaks their language, the learning curve disappears and cognitive load drops. Nielsen's heuristic #2 is empirically tied to task completion rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Replace jargon and system-centric terms with plain equivalents. Apply substitutions consistently across the entire product — inconsistency between screens is itself a heuristic violation.</statement>
      <rationale>Inconsistent terminology ("sign in" on one page, "log in" on another) forces users to question whether the actions are the same, adding cognitive friction where none should exist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Jargon substitution table — prefer the right column</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Terminate session  →  Log out
Execute query      →  Search
Invalid input      →  Please enter a valid email
Repository         →  Folder / Collection
Authenticate       →  Sign in
Synchronize        →  Update / Refresh
DOB                →  Date of birth
Configure SMTP     →  Set up email sending
Record created     →  Your booking is confirmed
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Domain Conventions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow established domain conventions for navigation labels, interaction patterns, and terminology even if the underlying metaphor is technically outdated (e.g., floppy disk = save).</statement>
      <rationale>Users have built strong mental models from prior product experience. Deviating from domain conventions for novelty forces unlearning and increases errors. The save icon is universally understood regardless of whether floppy disks exist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>E-commerce: shopping cart, checkout, wishlist, order history</item>
      <item>Documents: files, folders, save, open, trash (recoverable)</item>
      <item>Email: inbox, sent, draft, archive, snooze</item>
      <item>Social: friends, followers, like, share, feed</item>
      <item>Navigation: home, back, menu, search</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Information Order">
    <rule>
      <statement>Order information the way users think about it, not the way the system processes it. Match locale conventions for date, number, and address formats.</statement>
      <rationale>Address forms ordered Country first (system-centric) require users to mentally reverse their natural address recall order. Locale-mismatched date formats cause data entry errors and may have legal implications in financial or medical contexts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Address form — user-natural order</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Good: Street → City → State → ZIP → Country
Bad:  Country → State → City → Street → ZIP
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Icon Metaphors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always pair icons with text labels in primary navigation. Never rely on icon-only navigation except for universally recognized symbols with confirmed user recognition.</statement>
      <rationale>Icon comprehension varies significantly by culture and age group. Labels eliminate ambiguity at no usability cost. Icon-only navigation consistently scores lower on task success in usability studies.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
