<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Real-World Match Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Product examples demonstrating correct language use, and antipatterns showing system-centric violations with rewrites.</summary>

  <section title="Good Product Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Airbnb — domain language matching hotel mental models</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Check in" / "Check out"  (not "Start date" / "End date")
"Guests"                  (not "Users")
"Listing"                 (not "Property record")
"Your trips"              (not "Booking history")
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Gmail — physical mailbox metaphors users recognize</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Inbox"    — physical mailbox concept
"Archive"  — storing for later, not deleting
"Snooze"   — sleep metaphor for timed reminders
"Labels"   — physical label stickers on folders
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Technical jargon as primary UI copy: "Configure SMTP parameters for outbound mail relay"</description>
      <reason>Requires technical knowledge the user does not have. Rewrite: "Set up email sending". The action is the same; the user does not need to know what SMTP is.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>System-centric confirmation messages: "Record created successfully"</description>
      <reason>Confirms the system's action, not the user's goal. Rewrite: "Your booking is confirmed" — confirms what the user was trying to achieve.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Inconsistent terminology across pages: "Sign in" on homepage, "Login" on mobile, "Log in" in email</description>
      <reason>Forces users to question whether these are the same action. Pick one term and apply it everywhere. Inconsistency is a heuristic #2 violation regardless of individual clarity.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Locale-blind date format: displaying "03/04/2025" without locale detection</description>
      <reason>March 4 in US format is April 3 in European format. For financial, travel, and medical products, this is not just confusing — it can cause errors with real consequences. Use unambiguous formats or locale detection.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Forced simplification of technical terms that users expect: changing "invoice" to "bill" in an accounting tool</description>
      <reason>Domain-expert users have precise vocabulary expectations. Over-simplifying removes signal. For expert-user products, "plain language" means the domain's language, not generic consumer language.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Research Methods for User Vocabulary">
    <rule>
      <statement>Extract actual user vocabulary from support tickets, user interview recordings, and search query logs before writing UI copy. Use the words users use, not words the team prefers.</statement>
      <rationale>The most common source of heuristic #2 violations is team vocabulary leaking into UI copy. Users reveal their language in support requests and search queries — those are the ground truth.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
