<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>
  <section name="env-file-patterns">
    <summary>.env file format rules, systemd EnvironmentFile integration constraints, and file permission requirements.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Set chmod 600 on every .env file immediately after creating it; world-readable secrets are a breach waiting to happen.</statement>
      <rationale>Default umask creates files with mode 644. A world-readable .env containing API keys or database credentials can be read by any process on the server, including compromised services.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Never use the export prefix in .env files intended for systemd EnvironmentFile; systemd does not parse shell syntax, only bare KEY=VALUE pairs.</statement>
      <rationale>export DATABASE_URL=... is valid shell syntax but systemd EnvironmentFile treats the word "export" as part of the variable name, creating a variable literally named "export DATABASE_URL".</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Never expand variables in .env values ($OTHER_VAR); systemd EnvironmentFile does not perform variable substitution.</statement>
      <rationale>REDIS_URL=redis://$HOST:6379 will be passed literally with "$HOST" as a string, not expanded. Write full literal values in .env files for systemd consumption.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section name="format-rules">
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# .env — valid format for systemd EnvironmentFile
# Comments with # are allowed
# No spaces around =
# No export prefix
# Quote values containing spaces or special characters
# Literal values only (no $VAR expansion)

DATABASE_URL=postgresql://nero:secretpass@localhost:5432/nero_db
REDIS_URL=redis://localhost:6379/0
ANTHROPIC_API_KEY=sk-ant-api03-xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx
JWT_SECRET=a-long-random-string-here
RABBITMQ_URL=amqp://nero:rabbitpass@localhost:5672/nero
LOG_LEVEL=INFO
DEBUG=false
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Wrong: export prefix breaks systemd EnvironmentFile
export DATABASE_URL=postgresql://localhost/nero_db

# Wrong: variable expansion silently fails in systemd
HOST=localhost
DB_PORT=5432
DATABASE_URL=postgresql://$HOST:$DB_PORT/nero_db

# Wrong: spaces around = break the parse
DATABASE_URL = postgresql://localhost/nero_db
        ]]></code>
        <note>All three patterns above work in a shell (source .env) but silently fail or produce wrong values when loaded by systemd EnvironmentFile.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="systemd-environmentfile">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use the - prefix (EnvironmentFile=-/path) for optional override files; required files without - will fail the service start if missing.</statement>
        <rationale>A missing required EnvironmentFile causes the systemd unit to fail with "No such file or directory" before the process even starts. The - prefix makes the file optional, useful for per-instance overrides.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="ini"><![CDATA[
[Service]
# Required: service fails to start if this is missing
EnvironmentFile=/srv/nero/nero-core/.env

# Optional: loaded if present, ignored if absent
EnvironmentFile=-/srv/nero/nero-core/.env.local

ExecStart=/srv/nero/nero-core/.venv/bin/python -m src.main
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="file-layout">
      <list>
        <item>~/workspace/.env — master secrets file, source of truth for all credentials</item>
        <item>/srv/project/.env — per-service copy or symlink; chmod 600</item>
        <item>.env.example — committed to git, shows variable names with placeholder values</item>
        <item>.env.tpl — 1Password inject template with op:// references; safe to commit</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>
</text>
