<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>
  <section name="secret-rotation">
    <summary>Rotation schedule by secret type, safe rotation procedure, and 1Password op inject workflow for zero-secret-on-disk deployments.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Always generate the new secret before revoking the old one; never create a gap where neither works.</statement>
      <rationale>Revoking first leaves services broken until the new secret is deployed. Generating first allows a brief overlap window where both are valid, enabling zero-downtime rotation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Restart all affected services immediately after updating .env; stale processes still hold the old secret in memory.</statement>
      <rationale>A running service loaded its environment variables at startup. Updating .env on disk has no effect on running processes until they are restarted and reload the file via systemd EnvironmentFile.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section name="rotation-schedule">
      <list>
        <item>API keys (Anthropic, OpenAI): rotate every 90 days or immediately on suspected compromise</item>
        <item>Database passwords: rotate every 180 days or on team member departure</item>
        <item>JWT signing keys: rotate every 90 days (invalidates all active sessions)</item>
        <item>SSH keys: rotate annually or on machine compromise</item>
        <item>RabbitMQ passwords: rotate every 180 days</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="rotation-procedure">
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Safe rotation procedure (zero-downtime)
# 1. Generate new secret in provider dashboard (keep old active)
# 2. Update in 1Password vault
op item edit "Anthropic" "api-key=sk-ant-api03-NEW_VALUE"

# 3. Regenerate .env from 1Password template
op inject -i ~/workspace/.env.tpl -o ~/workspace/.env
chmod 600 ~/workspace/.env

# 4. Restart affected services
systemctl --user restart nero-core nero-channel-web nero-channel-tg

# 5. Verify services healthy
systemctl --user status nero-core
curl -sf http://127.0.0.1:8100/health

# 6. Revoke old secret in provider dashboard
# 7. Done — old secret is now invalid but services run on new one
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="op-inject-workflow">
      <summary>1Password op inject pattern: .env.tpl references vault items; op inject generates .env at deploy time with no secrets on disk between rotations.</summary>

      <rule>
        <statement>Store the OP_SERVICE_ACCOUNT_TOKEN in ~/.bashrc or a secure environment (not in .env.tpl itself); it is the master key that unlocks all other secrets.</statement>
        <rationale>The service account token is a bootstrap credential that cannot be stored in the vault it unlocks. It belongs in a separate secret storage path (system environment or secure config).</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# .env.tpl — committed to git, no actual secrets
DATABASE_URL={{ op://ServerVault/Database/url }}
ANTHROPIC_API_KEY={{ op://ServerVault/Anthropic/api-key }}
JWT_SECRET={{ op://ServerVault/JWT/secret }}
TELEGRAM_BOT_TOKEN={{ op://ServerVault/TelegramBot/token }}
LOG_LEVEL=INFO
DEBUG=false

# Generate .env from template (run at deploy time or after rotation)
export OP_SERVICE_ACCOUNT_TOKEN="ops_xxxxxxxxxxxx"
op inject -i ~/workspace/.env.tpl -o ~/workspace/.env
chmod 600 ~/workspace/.env
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <reference path="templates/validate_env.py">Python startup validator: required vars list, fail-fast with clear error message</reference>
      <reference path="templates/env.tpl">.env.tpl with 1Password op:// references for common service credentials</reference>
    </section>
  </section>
</text>
