<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Scope-Creep Firewall Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every solo-operator scope-creep firewall must enforce so the engagement leaks margin only when the operator consciously chooses to, never by default.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-single-intake" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per engagement, exactly one named inbound channel is the firewall (one ticket tag, one email alias, one Slack channel). Requests arriving outside the channel are not refused, but the operator's first move is to ask the requester to re-post in the firewall channel — or the operator re-posts on their behalf with the original message quoted. Multi-channel intake is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Triage-surface concentration">A solo operator cannot defend N parallel inboxes. Concentrating intake into one channel makes the firewall actually functional and makes "is there a queue?" answerable at a glance. The re-post-on-their-behalf escape valve keeps the rule from looking rigid to the client.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-three-question-classifier" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every firewall item is classified by answering exactly three yes/no questions: (1) Is this in the signed SOW as written? (2) Is this a clarification of existing deliverable, not a new deliverable? (3) Would delivering this consume ≤30 minutes of work? The 2³ truth-table maps deterministically to one of the four routing outcomes — operator judgment is not in the path.</statement>
      <rationale source="Deterministic triage">Per-ask debate is what eats the 60-minute push-back budget. A three-question gate removes deliberation: same input → same routing. The 30-minute threshold for question 3 is calibrated to the goodwill cap and prevents "tiny" tasks from death-by-a-thousand-cuts when summed.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-5min-triage-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Triage of any single firewall item must complete in ≤5 minutes including answering the three questions and dispatching the routing email or change-order draft. Items that cannot triage in 5 minutes are tagged `needs-call` and a 15-minute slot is offered — extended async deliberation is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operator economics">Long triage is what makes solo operators give up on the firewall. The 5-minute cap forces decisive action and protects the operator from the failure mode where triage itself becomes the time leak.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-change-order-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any of the three classifier questions is "no" (not-in-SOW OR new-deliverable OR &gt;30min), the default routing is `change-order-required`. Override to "absorb" requires an explicit, logged decision tagged `goodwill-spend` against the engagement's 5% goodwill budget. "Just doing it" without the goodwill tag is rejected on the weekly creep-trend report.</statement>
      <rationale source="Default-changes-incentives">Whatever the default routing is becomes the operating mode. Defaulting to absorb is what builds creep into the engagement. Defaulting to change-order, with an explicit logged escape valve, flips the incentive while preserving relationship flexibility.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-weekly-summary-to-client" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Once per week the operator sends a 5-line summary to the client: items intake'd, items routed (per outcome), change-orders open / accepted / declined, goodwill consumed (running % of 5% cap). Surprise change-orders at end of engagement are rejected — every change-order must have appeared on a weekly summary first.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-surprise principle">The relationship damage from scope-creep usually comes from end-of-engagement bills the client did not expect. Weekly summaries make change-orders visible while they are still small and renegotiable, and convert the goodwill budget into a shared piece of context rather than a hidden meter.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-creep-trend-tracked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The firewall records per-engagement creep-trend metrics: weekly count of change-orders, total $ value of change-orders vs original SOW value, goodwill consumption rate, time-to-triage average. Trends crossing thresholds (CO value &gt;20% of SOW, goodwill rate &gt;0.5%/week, triage time creeping above 5min) trigger an engagement-health review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practice over event">Without tracked trends, a healthy engagement and a terminally creeping one look identical week-by-week. The thresholds catch the slope, not the absolute number, which is what actually determines whether the engagement is profitable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example>
    <description>Single firewall record + weekly trend snapshot.</description>
    <code language="yaml">
firewall_record: fw-2026-05-20-acme-007
engagement: acme-website-rebuild
intake_at: 2026-05-20T11:03:00Z
requester: @client-pm
ask: "can you also wire up the newsletter signup popup on every page?"
classifier:
  q1_in_sow: no
  q2_clarification_of_existing: no
  q3_under_30min: no
routing: change-order-required
dispatch_at: 2026-05-20T11:06:00Z   (3 minutes, within budget)
phrasing_used: tiny-tweak-v1
weekly_trend (acme-website-rebuild, week 4 of 8):
  intake_count: 6
  change_orders_open: 2
  change_orders_accepted: 3 ($1,840)
  goodwill_consumed: 0.4% of SOW (under 0.5%/wk threshold)
  triage_time_avg: 3m12s
  health_review_triggered: no
    </code>
  </example>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../scope-creep-email-language-pack/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../change-request-impact-rubric/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
