<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="user-research-at-scale">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>AI-augmented research ops for N >= 500 sessions/week; 9-stage pipeline with frozen codebook. Haiku for throughput, Sonnet for synthesis, Opus for mining with human gates before publication.</summary>
    <category>research</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>research-ops</tag>
      <tag>qualitative-analysis</tag>
      <tag>research-at-scale</tag>
      <tag>ai-augmented-research</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>User Research at Scale</title>
    <summary>AI-augmented research operations for N >= 500 sessions/week or >= 50 unmoderated tests, running a 9-stage pipeline: intake → sampling → instrumentation → collection → transcription → coding → synthesis → review → publish. Uses a frozen codebook with a separate proposed_codes overflow channel to prevent theme drift, and human-in-the-loop checkpoints before synthesis is published.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Traditional manual research does not scale with product velocity. AI handles throughput (transcription, pattern detection, codebook tagging); humans handle strategy, interpretation, and empathy. The separation is enforced by model assignment: Haiku for mechanical tasks, Sonnet for structured synthesis, Opus for cross-segment pattern mining. Mixing them collapses the quality/cost trade-off.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>N >= 500 sessions/week or >= 50 unmoderated tests where manual coding is the bottleneck.</item>
        <item>Continuous discovery teams needing a weekly pulse (Teresa Torres cadence).</item>
        <item>Product orgs with multiple teams running parallel studies (research-as-platform).</item>
        <item>Localization at scale — same study across 5+ languages, AI handles transcription + translation.</item>
        <item>Survey + behavior + interview triangulation when a single researcher cannot read everything.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Small N (less than 10 deep interviews) — AI noise overwhelms signal; human coding is faster and richer.</item>
        <item>Strategic generative discovery where pattern-recognition beats throughput.</item>
        <item>Sensitive/regulated topics (health, finance, minors) requiring manual consent chains.</item>
        <item>Early-stage startups with less than 100 users — you do not have scale problems yet.</item>
        <item>Studies where rapport, body language, or longitudinal trust is the data.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="nine-stage-pipeline">
      <list>
        <item>1. intake: convert PM brief to study spec, screener, hypotheses</item>
        <item>2. sampling: build quotas, randomize, dedupe panel respondents</item>
        <item>3. instrumentation: configure unmoderated test scripts in Maze/Userlytics</item>
        <item>4. collection: execute tests and gather session recordings</item>
        <item>5. transcription: forced-aligned transcription with diarization, PII redaction</item>
        <item>6. coding: apply frozen codebook, tag quotes with codes and valence</item>
        <item>7. synthesis: cross-segment pattern mining, confidence-tiered findings</item>
        <item>8. review: human-in-the-loop checkpoint before publication</item>
        <item>9. publish: push themes/sentiment to Looker/Notion/Dovetail</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run theme-coder and bias-auditor in parallel; gate report-writer on a researcher human-in-loop checkpoint at step 8.</statement>
        <rationale>AI synthesis can proceed while bias audit runs — they are independent. But publishing without a human checkpoint after synthesis lets AI-invented "insights" reach stakeholders without review.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="subagent-model-assignments">
      <rule>
        <statement>Assign Haiku to mechanical tasks (panel-sampler, protocol-runner, transcript-cleaner, dashboard-publisher); Sonnet to structured synthesis (theme-coder, quote-curator, bias-auditor); Opus to cross-segment pattern mining and executive synthesis.</statement>
        <rationale>This assignment minimizes cost while matching model capability to task complexity. Inverting it — Opus on transcript cleaning, Haiku on pattern mining — either burns tokens or degrades quality.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>research-intake (Sonnet): PM brief → study-spec.md + screener JSON</item>
        <item>panel-sampler (Haiku): quotas, randomize, dedupe → participant CSV</item>
        <item>protocol-runner (Haiku): execute unmoderated tests in Maze/Userlytics → session IDs</item>
        <item>transcript-cleaner (Haiku): strip filler, redact PII, normalize timestamps → clean VTT/JSON</item>
        <item>theme-coder (Sonnet): apply codebook, tag quotes with codes + valence → coded JSONL</item>
        <item>pattern-analyst (Opus): cross-segment clustering, confidence-tiered findings → findings draft</item>
        <item>quote-curator (Sonnet): representative + outlier quotes per finding → quote bank</item>
        <item>report-writer (Opus): executive synthesis, recommendations, confidence tiers → final report MD</item>
        <item>bias-auditor (Sonnet): leading phrasing, sample bias detection → audit notes</item>
        <item>dashboard-publisher (Haiku): push themes/sentiment to Looker/Notion/Dovetail → URLs</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="frozen-codebook-pattern">
      <rule>
        <statement>Lock the codebook before collection; version it (v1.0.0) and bump only with documented diffs; use a separate proposed_codes overflow channel instead of modifying the codebook mid-study.</statement>
        <rationale>Theme drift across batches is the #1 AI coding failure mode. A frozen codebook with a version + proposed_codes channel surfaces emergent themes for human review without corrupting the existing taxonomy.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Theme-coder prompt with frozen codebook and proposed_codes channel:</note>
        <code lang="xml"><![CDATA[
<task>code-transcript</task>
<codebook src=".aidocs/research/codebook.yaml"/>
<rules>
  <rule>One quote may receive multiple codes; record span offsets.</rule>
  <rule>Reject codes not in codebook. Emit proposed_codes list instead.</rule>
  <rule>Tag valence in {-2,-1,0,1,2} with one-line evidence.</rule>
  <rule>If transcript is less than 80% English confidence, halt and request translation.</rule>
</rules>
<output schema="coded_quote_v1">JSONL</output>
<gotcha>Do not summarize. Preserve verbatim spans.</gotcha>
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <rule>
        <statement>Sample 10% of AI-coded segments for human re-coding every batch; track inter-rater agreement (Cohen's kappa >= 0.7) and recalibrate when it drops below threshold.</statement>
        <rationale>AI coding accuracy drifts as transcripts vary in quality and subject matter. Kappa tracking catches drift before it contaminates an entire study's findings.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>whisperx: forced-aligned transcription with diarization, faster than vanilla Whisper</item>
        <item>pyannote-audio: speaker diarization when WhisperX is insufficient</item>
        <item>ffmpeg: slice session recordings into per-task clips for AI scoring</item>
        <item>yt-dlp: pull session videos from CDN URLs given by panel platforms</item>
        <item>jq / duckdb: query coded JSONL transcripts and platform exports</item>
        <item>pandas + sentence-transformers: embed and cluster open-ended survey responses</item>
        <item>bertopic: topic modeling on large response corpora</item>
        <item>dvc / lakefs: version control for transcripts + codebooks (audit trail)</item>
        <item>presidio: PII redaction before sending to external LLMs</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Gate on Whisper confidence score >= 0.6 per transcript before coding — low-quality audio produces confident-but-wrong text that the coder cannot distinguish from accurate transcription.</statement>
        <rationale>Downstream coding errors from bad transcription are undetectable at the finding layer. The confidence gate catches the problem at the source.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="platform-services">
      <list>
        <item>UserTesting (enterprise): REST API + webhook; largest panel, AI Insights add-on</item>
        <item>Userlytics (mid+): REST API; 2M+ panel, AI analytics, EU-friendly</item>
        <item>Maze (self-serve+): API + Zapier; bias detection, dynamic follow-ups</item>
        <item>dscout (enterprise): API; mobile ethnography and longitudinal diaries</item>
        <item>Dovetail (all tiers): REST + GraphQL; repository + AI tagging, codebook host</item>
        <item>Sprig (mid): API + JS SDK; in-product micro-surveys at session scale</item>
        <item>Hotjar / FullStory (mid): API; session replay + heatmaps for behavior layer</item>
        <item>Rally / User Interviews (mid): API; recruitment and scheduling automation</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cache full transcripts in the LLM context using prompt caching when coding hundreds of quotes against the same codebook — the savings are substantial at scale.</statement>
        <rationale>Repeated codebook context is identical across all transcript coding calls. Prompt caching eliminates the redundant token cost of loading the codebook on every call.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Publish disconfirming quotes alongside confirming ones — outliers are signal, not noise.</statement>
        <rationale>LLM summarization compresses outliers. The most valuable insights often come from the user who had the unexpected reaction. Requiring outlier inclusion in the quote bank prevents systematic suppression.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Stratify panels by behavior (active/lapsed/new), not just demographics — demographic-only sampling hides usage truth.</statement>
        <rationale>Demographic similarity does not predict usage similarity. Active and churned users of the same age have opposite perspectives on the product's value.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Triangulate every finding with AI sentiment + behavioral analytics + verbatim quote — never report from one source alone.</statement>
        <rationale>Single-source findings have low reliability at scale. Three-source triangulation with confidence tiers (high >= 3 types, medium = 2, low = 1) enables stakeholders to calibrate trust.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Add a "draft/published" gate on every finding — dashboards auto-update faster than humans can vet.</statement>
        <rationale>Unvetted AI findings reaching a product meeting without a human review can redirect roadmap decisions based on hallucinated patterns.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="sentiment-coding-limitations">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running sentiment analysis on non-English transcripts without routing by language.</description>
        <reason>Sentiment models miss sarcasm, code-switching, and culture-specific affect in non-English text. Polarity flips on negation in low-resource languages without language-aware routing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Letting the theme-coder invent codes when the codebook is unclear rather than using the proposed_codes overflow channel.</description>
        <reason>Invented codes contaminate the taxonomy and produce theme drift across batches. Strict allow-list enforcement with a separate proposed_codes channel keeps the codebook clean.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinating participant IDs in the report when citing quotes.</description>
        <reason>Agents invent participant IDs that do not exist in the corpus. Require verbatim span offsets (start_char, end_char) tied to a specific session file, not paraphrases.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="cost-context-traps">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Re-running coding on the same transcript without caching, burning 10x tokens.</description>
        <reason>Hash the transcript content and cache the coded output. Skip transcripts that already have a cached result. Uncached re-runs are pure waste.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Feeding full transcript bundles > 200k tokens into a long-context model without chunking.</description>
        <reason>Long-context models silently truncate at token boundaries. Chunk at session boundaries with overlap and verify completeness before synthesis.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Pattern-analyst over-indexing on the first segment in the prompt.</description>
        <reason>LLMs weight earlier context more heavily. Randomize segment order across runs and compare findings to detect position bias.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="privacy-consent">
      <rule>
        <statement>Redact PII with Presidio before any external LLM call; confirm that platform recordings have consented to AI processing before feeding into the pipeline.</statement>
        <rationale>Sending raw PII to a non-zero-retention LLM endpoint violates GDPR and platform ToS. Presidio redaction runs locally before any external call. Consent flags must be read by the transcript-cleaner before quoting.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never present synthetic users or AI-generated personas as real research findings.</statement>
        <rationale>Synthetic personas leak training-data clichés and introduce systematic bias toward the modal user in the training set. They are planning tools, not research evidence.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cross-platform-normalization">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Mixing timestamp formats from different platforms (Maze milliseconds, UserTesting ISO, Otter seconds) without normalization.</description>
        <reason>Mixed timestamps break quote offset matching and prevent cross-platform de-duplication. Normalize in the transcript-cleaner stage before any downstream use.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents quietly dropping non-English sessions when the prompt does not explicitly handle them.</description>
        <reason>Silently dropping sessions produces a biased corpus. Assert language coverage in tests and route non-English sessions to a translation step before coding.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="where-it-fails">
      <p>Sentiment models miss sarcasm, code-switching, and culture-specific affect (especially non-English). AI auto-coding produces theme drift across batches if no fixed taxonomy is locked.</p>
      <p>Synthetic users / AI panels still bias toward training distribution; do not substitute for real users for novel UX. Bias detection (e.g., Maze) flags syntax not intent — leading questions slip through if phrased neutrally.</p>
      <p>Recordings without screen-region annotation lead AI to hallucinate user actions. LLM summarization compresses outliers — the most valuable quotes are the ones that get smoothed away.</p>
      <p>Cross-demographic clustering tends to reproduce platform demographics, not target market. No causal inference — patterns at scale still need experimental validation.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/codebook.yaml" purpose="Frozen taxonomy: codes with id/label/valence_default/examples, segment axes"/>
      <template path="templates/code-batch.sh" purpose="Batch-codes transcript directory via claude CLI, deduplicates, outputs parquet"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
