<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="audience-segmentation">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>5-step methodology for dividing potential market into distinct, scored groups using 2-3 dimensions from observed data. Produces segment matrix and target strategy decision..</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>segmentation</tag>
      <tag>marketing</tag>
      <tag>positioning</tag>
      <tag>icp</tag>
      <tag>research</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Audience Segmentation</title>

    <summary>A 5-step methodology for dividing a potential market into distinct, scored groups using 2-3 dimensions drawn from observed data (demographic, behavioral, psychographic, needs-based). Produces a scored segment matrix and a target-strategy decision. Outputs audience-segmentation.md in .aidocs/product_docs/.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>"Everyone is my customer" leads to messaging that resonates with nobody and marketing spend diffused across channels. Behavioral and needs-based segmentation — as opposed to pure demographic slicing — consistently outperforms for messaging work because it captures what users do and what they need, not just who they are. A weighted scoring model forces the team to commit to one primary segment until there is enough revenue to address more.</p>
      <p>Static segmentation rots within 6–12 months as the market shifts; without a refresh cadence the deck becomes lore. LLM-driven segmentation hallucinates plausible-sounding personas that don't exist in the data — always anchor on real interview transcripts or analytics rows.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch: deciding which single segment gets the MVP.</item>
        <item>Post-launch with mixed signals (high churn in 30% of cohort, high NPS in 50%) — segment to find actual ICP.</item>
        <item>Repositioning a stalled product where "everyone" messaging tests failed.</item>
        <item>Pricing tier design when usage data shows two or more behavioral clusters.</item>
        <item>Channel allocation when paid spend is diffuse without a clear winner.</item>
        <item>B2B GTM when sales calls reveal distinct buyer types with different objections.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>TAM under ~5k addressable accounts — further segmentation starves each segment of evidence.</item>
        <item>First 10 paying customers — too few data points; run pain-points and problem-validation first.</item>
        <item>Pure infra/dev tools where the buyer is "any engineer with this stack" — use niche-evaluation.</item>
        <item>Dimensions chosen from gut alone with no interview/CRM/analytics data backing them.</item>
        <item>One-off campaigns where the segment is already given by the brief.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="segmentation-criteria-types">
      <p>Four segmentation criteria types — demographic, behavioral, psychographic, needs-based — with use-case guidance for each.</p>

      <p>Demographic segmentation uses variables: age, income, education, occupation, company size, industry. Best for B2B targeting and pricing tier design where company size or role title directly correlates with budget authority and purchasing process.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using demographic segments alone for messaging work.</description>
        <reason>Demographics consistently underperform behavior-and-needs segments for messaging because they capture who someone is, not what they need or do. Age 25-34 tells you nothing about their workflow or pain intensity.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <p>Behavioral segmentation uses variables: usage frequency (daily/weekly/monthly), purchase history (free/paid/churned), feature usage (core only vs power user), engagement (active/passive/dormant), buying stage (aware/considering/ready). Best for product development and retention strategies.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Prefer behavioral dimensions from observed CRM or analytics data over self-reported survey data. Observable behavior is more reliable than stated intention.</statement>
        <rationale>Users over-report their engagement and under-report their churn risk in surveys. Behavioral data from product analytics captures actual usage regardless of stated preference.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Psychographic segmentation uses variables: values (quality over price, innovation), attitudes (risk-tolerant vs skeptical), lifestyle (work-life balance vs hustle), motivations (status, security, creativity), pain tolerance ("just make it work" vs perfectionist). Best for messaging and brand positioning.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Only include a psychographic dimension if it maps to a measurable data source you actually have. Dimensions like "growth mindset" cannot be measured and produce hallucinated segments.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs generate plausible psychographic segments from training data priors. Without an observable data source, the segment is fiction.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Needs-based segmentation uses variables: problem severity (critical/moderate/nice-to-have), current solution (DIY/competitor/nothing), budget (limited/flexible/unlimited), speed priority (urgent vs can wait), support needs (self-serve/guided/white-glove). Best for product tier design and pricing strategy.</p>

      <p>Needs-based segments often align most directly with pricing tier boundaries and feature gating decisions, making them the most actionable type for a solopreneur product with limited engineering capacity.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="five-step-segmentation-process">
      <p>Five-step segmentation process: gather data, pick 2-3 dimensions from observed variance, create MECE segments, score on 6 criteria, select target strategy.</p>

      <p>Step 1: Gather Data. Pick segmentation dimensions only from observed variance in actual data sources (CRM exports, interview transcripts, analytics rollups). Do not invent dimensions from a textbook. If every customer is the same on a dimension, that dimension adds no segmentation power. Dimensions that vary widely in the data are the ones that predict meaningful behavioral differences.</p>

      <p>Data sources by signal strength: customer interviews (qualitative patterns), CRM data (demographics and lifecycle), analytics (usage patterns and engagement), survey responses (preferences and attitudes), sales conversations (objections and budget).</p>

      <p>Step 2: Select Dimensions. Choose 2-3 dimensions maximum. A 2x2 matrix is the simplest useful shape. Three dimensions produce an 8-cell cube that is manageable. Four or more produce over-segmentation. More than 3 dimensions with finite data starves each cell of evidence. Real markets have 5-7 meaningful clusters, but 2x2 is enough to make the primary-vs-secondary decision at seed stage.</p>

      <p>Step 3: Create MECE Segments. Segments must be mutually exclusive and collectively exhaustive (MECE). Every customer falls into exactly one segment. Overlapping segments produce inconsistent routing: a customer who fits two segments gets conflicting messaging, pricing, and product priorities. MECE is the minimum requirement for segments to drive decisions.</p>

      <p>Name segments after their job-to-be-done rather than demographics ("The Overwhelmed Solo PM", not "Millennials in SaaS"). JTBD-based names drive messaging decisions; demographic names do not.</p>

      <p>Step 4: Score Segments. Score each segment on 6 criteria, each 1-5. Weighted total: Size 20%, Growth 15%, Reachability 20%, Profitability 20%, Fit 15%, Competition 10%.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Rank segments by attractiveness order before assigning 1-5 scores. This defeats the regression-to-the-middle problem where agents score everything 3-4.</statement>
        <rationale>Rank-ordering forces the agent to commit to a preference; numerical scoring then calibrates the magnitude. Without rank-ordering first, scores cluster at 3 and provide no differentiation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>For any scoring criterion lacking evidence, return "unknown" rather than estimating. Quantify each segment with two independent estimates and flag segments where they disagree by 3x or more.</statement>
        <rationale>Score inflation on unknown criteria produces a false ranking that misdirects product and marketing investment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Step 5: Select Target Strategy. Three strategies: Concentrated (one segment, limited resources), Differentiated (2-3 segments with different approaches), Niche (deep focus on sub-segment in crowded market).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>For solopreneurs: commit to ONE segment until reaching $10K+ MRR. Encode the chosen target as a constitution-level decision in .aidocs/ so all downstream specs, marketing copy, and pricing inherit it.</statement>
        <rationale>Splitting attention between 2+ segments at seed stage is the fastest path to muddled positioning and slow product-market fit. The constitution entry makes the segment choice explicit and prevents drift.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="segmentation-examples">
      <p>Two worked segmentation examples (CRM tool and online course) with dimension choices, segment descriptions, and target decisions.</p>

      <example type="good" title="CRM Tool Segmentation">
        <note>Dimensions: team size (Solo / 2-5 / 6-20 / 20+) and sales complexity (Transactional / Consultative).</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Segment | Size x Complexity | Needs | Price Point | Priority |
|---------|-------------------|-------|-------------|----------|
| Freelancer | Solo x Transactional | Simple pipeline | $9/mo | 3 |
| Agency | 2-5 x Consultative | Deal tracking, proposals | $29/mo | 1 |
| Startup Sales | 6-20 x Transactional | Automation, reporting | $49/mo | 2 |
| Enterprise | 20+ x Consultative | Custom, integrations | Custom | 4 |

Decision: Focus on "Agency" segment — high WTP, underserved, reachable via LinkedIn and agency communities.
        ]]></code>
        <note>Two MECE dimensions produce four clean segments. Scoring revealed Agency as the priority by combining WTP, reachability, and competition criteria.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Online Course Segmentation">
        <note>Dimensions: learning goal (Career change / Skill upgrade / Hobby) and time available (&lt;5 hrs/wk / 5-10 hrs / 10+ hrs).</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Segment | Goal x Time | Characteristics | WTP |
|---------|-------------|-----------------|-----|
| Career Changers | Career x 10+ hrs | Committed, outcome-focused | High |
| Upskilling Pros | Upgrade x 5-10 hrs | Employed, busy, ROI-minded | High |
| Hobbyists | Hobby x <5 hrs | Fun-focused, casual | Low |

Decision: Focus on "Upskilling Pros" — pay for time savings, clear ROI framing, higher budgets.
        ]]></code>
        <note>Hobbyist segment has low WTP and low urgency — good negative segment to explicitly exclude from paid acquisition.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="segmentation-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Critical failure modes in agent-driven segmentation: hallucinated segments, score inflation, dimension drift, confusing personas with segments, human-in-the-loop gates.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent produces segment profiles with no CRM ID, transcript filename, or analytics row as citation.</description>
        <reason>Agents invent plausible personas that do not exist in the data. Mitigation: require row-citations (CRM ID or transcript filename) for every claim; reject segments with zero citations.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent picks "innovative" unmeasurable dimensions like "growth mindset" or "digital native".</description>
        <reason>Unmeasurable dimensions cannot be used to classify real customers or build targeted campaigns. Constrain dimensions to a whitelist tied to data sources you actually have.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent assigns 3-4 scores on every criterion for every segment, producing a flat ranking table.</description>
        <reason>Regression to the mean is the default LLM behaviour when criteria are open-ended. Mitigation: force rank-ordering before scoring, and require evidence-or-"unknown" per criterion.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Accepting segment size estimates from a single source (e.g. LinkedIn filter count) without a second independent estimate.</description>
        <reason>Top-down market sizing sources compound error. Validate with at least one bottom-up count (CRM rows, analytics cohort, interview N) and flag 3x+ disagreements.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent produces one fictional person (Newsletter Nate) instead of a sized cluster (N=2,400, 18% of base).</description>
        <reason>A persona is a representative individual; a segment is a sized group. Do not use persona docs for ad targeting. Require "n=" and "% of base" on every segment output.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>All input transcripts are from one quarter, producing segments that over-fit to a seasonal or recency-biased cohort.</description>
        <reason>Static segmentation from a single time window misses churn patterns and market shifts. Stratify input data over at least 2 quarters before clustering.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <p>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Approve dimensions: human confirms the 2-3 dimensions are derived from observed variance before any segment generation runs.</item>
        <item>Approve candidate segments: human reviews the 4-8 candidates before scoring. This is where hallucinated segments are caught.</item>
        <item>Approve scoring inputs: human confirms the evidence pack before agents assign scores. Without this, agents score on priors.</item>
        <item>Explicitly prompt for the anti-segment (who NOT to serve); agents skip it unless asked.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive segmentation as a multi-step pipeline: (1) data-collection agents hit CRM/analytics/transcripts, (2) clustering agent proposes 5–8 candidate segments, (3) faion-research-agent (mode personas) and faion-persona-builder-agent build profiles, (4) human ranks/eliminates before agents score the survivors. Never let one agent run end-to-end without a human checkpoint between candidate generation and scoring — that is where hallucinated segments slip through.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-research-agent — orchestrator with mode personas / pains / validate; outputs user-personas.md, pain-points.md to .aidocs/product_docs/.</item>
        <item>faion-persona-builder-agent — takes raw interview/CRM rows and produces segment profile cards using the template in templates.md.</item>
        <item>faion-domain-checker-agent — for naming the segments once shortlisted (verifies name candidates aren't already taken as brand handles).</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — to encode the chosen target segment as a constitution decision and propagate it into product specs.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Prompt pattern for candidate generation:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are running mode=segmentation on the product described in <product>.
Inputs: <CRM_export.csv>, <interview_transcripts/>, <analytics_rollup.json>.
Step 1: extract dimensions only from observed variation in inputs. No inferred dimensions.
Step 2: propose 4–8 candidate segments with cited row counts.
Step 3: STOP. Return JSON {dimensions, candidates[]} for human review.
      ]]></code>

      <p>Prompt pattern for scoring approved segments:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Given approved segments <segments.json>, score each on Size/Growth/Reach/Profit/Fit/Competition (1–5) using ONLY evidence from <evidence_pack/>. For any criterion lacking evidence, return "unknown" — do not guess. Output the table from templates.md verbatim.
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools for segmentation work:</p>
      <list>
        <item>dbt — Materialize segment definitions as warehouse models so segments are queryable, not deck-trapped | https://docs.getdbt.com</item>
        <item>duckdb CLI — Local clustering / segment counts over CSV exports without a warehouse | https://duckdb.org</item>
        <item>posthog-cli — Pull cohort definitions, behavioral events, feature-flag rollouts per segment | https://posthog.com/docs/cli</item>
        <item>mixpanel Query API + httpie — Behavioral-segment counts and funnels via JQL | https://developer.mixpanel.com</item>
        <item>gh + Discussions — Pull public user discussions/tags as qualitative segment signal | https://cli.github.com</item>
        <item>jq — Slice JSON exports from Stripe/HubSpot/Pipedrive into per-segment files | https://jqlang.github.io</item>
        <item>pandas + scikit-learn (KMeans, silhouette_score) — Automated cluster discovery on numeric/behavioral matrices | https://scikit-learn.org</item>
      </list>

      <p>Services and apps for segmentation agents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>PostHog (OSS + SaaS) — Yes, agent-friendly. REST + cohort API. Cohorts map 1:1 to behavioral segments; can be created/read by agents.</item>
        <item>Mixpanel (SaaS) — Yes, agent-friendly. JQL + Cohorts API. Best for behavioral segmentation on event streams.</item>
        <item>Amplitude (SaaS) — Partial, agent-friendly. Paid tier for API. Behavioral cohorts; UI-heavy.</item>
        <item>HubSpot (SaaS) — Yes, agent-friendly. Lists API. Demographic + lifecycle segmentation; B2B CRM.</item>
        <item>Segment (Twilio) (SaaS) — Yes, agent-friendly. Personas/Computed Traits API. Identity resolution across sources before segmentation.</item>
        <item>Census / Hightouch (SaaS, reverse ETL) — Yes, agent-friendly. API + dbt models. Sync warehouse segments to ad/email platforms.</item>
        <item>Dovetail (SaaS) — Partial, agent-friendly. REST API. Tag interview transcripts; export themes for psychographic segmentation.</item>
        <item>Notably / Marvin (SaaS) — Yes, agent-friendly. Auto-tagging. AI tagging of qualitative data into segment dimensions.</item>
        <item>Statista / SimilarWeb / IBISWorld (SaaS) — Limited (paid API). Top-down market sizing per segment; require human verification.</item>
        <item>LinkedIn Sales Navigator (SaaS) — No public API for segment counts. Use the filter UI to estimate B2B TAM by firmographic segment.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices-for-segmentation">
      <list>
        <item>Pick dimensions from observed variance, not from a textbook list — if every customer is the same on a dimension, drop it.</item>
        <item>Force mutually-exclusive, collectively-exhaustive (MECE) segments; agents tend to write overlapping ones unless prompted.</item>
        <item>Quantify each segment with two independent estimates (top-down market-sizing + bottom-up CRM count); flag any segment where they disagree by 3x+.</item>
        <item>Name segments after their job-to-be-done (e.g. "The Overwhelmed Solo PM"), not their demographics — names drive messaging.</item>
        <item>Score on rank-order first (1st, 2nd, 3rd most attractive), then assign 1–5 weights, to defeat the regression-to-the-middle problem.</item>
        <item>Refresh quarterly; archive prior versions so segment-drift is visible.</item>
        <item>For solopreneurs: commit to ONE segment until $10K MRR; resist agent suggestions to "differentiate" early.</item>
        <item>Encode the chosen target as a constitution-level decision in .aidocs/ so downstream specs/marketing/pricing inherit it.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/segmentation-analysis.md" purpose="Full segmentation analysis skeleton: dimensions, segment profiles with scoring table, comparison matrix, implications."/>
      <template path="templates/segment-profile-card.md" purpose="Single segment profile card: demographics, behaviors, needs, messaging, reach, size."/>
      <template path="templates/segment-candidates.py" purpose="KMeans clustering harness: turns a user CSV into candidate behavioral segments with silhouette scoring."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://posthog.com/docs/data/cohorts"/>
      <link href="https://docs.mixpanel.com/docs/users/cohorts"/>
      <link href="https://segment.com/docs/personas/"/>
      <link href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/clustering.html"/>
      <link href="https://www.kotler.com/books/marketing-management"/>
      <link href="https://hbr.org/2005/04/marketing-malpractice-the-cause-and-the-cure"/>
      <link href="https://www.april-dunford.com/obviously-awesome"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
