<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-writing-process" title="Implementation Plan Writing Process">
  <summary>The 11-phase process for writing an implementation plan, inputs and outputs per phase, document hierarchy, and wave analysis rules.</summary>

  <section title="Document Hierarchy">
    <p>The implementation plan sits between design and execution:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Spec (FR-X): WHAT and WHY — requirements and acceptance criteria.</item>
      <item>Design (AD-X): HOW — architecture decisions, file structure, API contracts.</item>
      <item>Implementation Plan (TASK-XXX outline): IN WHAT ORDER — task breakdown, waves, token budgets.</item>
      <item>TASK_*.md files (executor input): WHAT EXACTLY — atomic work units with AC and file lists.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Write the implementation plan only after design.md has Accepted status. Writing the plan on a Draft design wastes tokens when requirements shift.</statement>
      <rationale>Implementation plans derived from Draft designs must be rewritten when the design changes. The cost of rewriting a plan is higher than the cost of waiting for design approval.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="11-Phase Writing Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Execute all 11 phases in order. Do not skip prerequisites check (Phase 2) or risk assessment (Phase 9) — these are the phases most commonly omitted under time pressure.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipped prerequisites cause execution blockers. Skipped risk assessment means the executor encounters surprises that require mid-execution plan changes, which are expensive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Phase 1: Load SDD context — read constitution.md, spec.md (extract FR-X), design.md (extract AD-X), features/done/ for patterns.</item>
      <item>Phase 2: Prerequisites check — external services, database schema, no circular dependencies, all ADs documented.</item>
      <item>Phase 3: WBS — list all CREATE/MODIFY/DELETE files, group into logical work units, apply 8-80 rule (not too big, not too small).</item>
      <item>Phase 4: Dependency graph — map each task to its dependencies, verify no circular deps, identify critical path.</item>
      <item>Phase 5: Wave analysis — group independent tasks (Wave 1), tasks depending on Wave 1 (Wave 2), continue; define checkpoint criteria per wave.</item>
      <item>Phase 6: Phase definition — logical groupings above waves (e.g., Phase 1: Infrastructure, Phase 2: Core Logic).</item>
      <item>Phase 7: Task format — fill TASK v2.0 format for Wave 1 only; later waves created after execution.</item>
      <item>Phase 8: Critical path analysis — mark longest dependency chain explicitly.</item>
      <item>Phase 9: Risk assessment — identify at least 3 risks with mitigation and contingency per risk.</item>
      <item>Phase 10: Testing strategy — unit, integration, E2E test requirements; quality gates per wave.</item>
      <item>Phase 11: Rollout strategy — deployment approach, data migrations, rollback trigger conditions.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Wave Analysis Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Wave 1 must contain only tasks with zero dependencies. Agents can run them in parallel. If Wave 1 has no parallel-safe tasks, the dependency graph has a problem — review it.</statement>
      <rationale>A Wave 1 with serial dependencies means the plan is not exploiting available parallelism. Review the dependency graph to identify incorrectly declared FS dependencies that should be concurrent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define explicit checkpoint criteria between waves. The executor must verify all Wave N tasks pass before creating Wave N+1 task files.</statement>
      <rationale>Without checkpoint criteria, a Wave 1 failure is not detected until Wave 2 executes and produces wrong results. Checkpoints enforce the gate before the cost of Wave 2 is incurred.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
