<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-quality-gates" title="Implementation Plan Quality Gates">
  <summary>Quality gate checklist for a complete implementation plan, common mistakes table, and rollout strategy requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Quality Gate Checklist">
    <rule>
      <statement>An implementation plan passes the quality gate only when all of these hold: every AD-X decision is mapped to at least one task, every FR-X requirement is mapped to at least one task, no task exceeds 100k token budget, dependency graph is acyclic, every task has testable success criteria, testing strategy covers happy path and error cases, at least 3 risks are identified with mitigation, critical path is marked explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale>Each unchecked item represents a gap that will surface during execution at higher cost. The quality gate makes gaps explicit before tokens are spent on task execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Writing the implementation plan before design.md reaches Accepted status.</description>
      <reason>Draft designs change. Plans written on Draft designs must be rewritten when requirements shift during design review.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Omitting test-writing tasks and CHANGELOG updates from the WBS.</description>
      <reason>These tasks consume 20-40k tokens each but are consistently omitted. They must appear as explicit tasks with token estimates.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Implementation plan contradicting design.md on task scope or file targets.</description>
      <reason>Agents silently follow the impl-plan when it contradicts design.md. Reconcile both documents before execution begins — the discrepancy may indicate a design error.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Token estimates are order-of-magnitude only with no breakdown.</description>
      <reason>Unitemized estimates run 2-3x over in practice. Itemized estimates by file class are diagnosable when they overrun.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Rollout Strategy Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every implementation plan must include a rollout strategy with: deployment approach (all-at-once vs phased), data migration plan (if any), rollback trigger condition (specific metric or error rate that triggers rollback), and stakeholder communication plan.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic rollout strategies ("deploy to production") provide no guidance when something goes wrong. A specific rollback trigger condition makes the decision mechanical rather than judgment-based under pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include "rollback trigger" as a specific, measurable condition: "error rate exceeds 1% for 5 minutes" or "p95 latency exceeds 2000ms". Not "if something breaks".</statement>
      <rationale>Vague rollback conditions mean the rollback decision is made under pressure by whoever is on-call. A measurable trigger removes judgment from the decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
