<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-template-rules" title="Specification Template: Rules and Fill Order">
  <summary>Rules for correctly filling the spec.md template: fill order, required sections, what belongs in spec vs design, MoSCoW on FRs and NFRs, status gate, and anti-patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Required Sections">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every spec.md must contain all required sections: Reference Documents, Overview, Problem Statement, User Personas (minimum 2), User Stories, Functional Requirements table (FR-X), Non-Functional Requirements table (NFR-X), Acceptance Criteria, Out of Scope, Assumptions and Constraints, and Dependencies.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing sections cause design agents to make ungrounded decisions. Out of Scope is the most commonly omitted section and the most important for preventing scope creep.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Reference Documents — links to constitution.md and related done/ specs</item>
      <item>Overview — 2-3 sentences describing the feature and its purpose</item>
      <item>Problem Statement — Who, Problem, Impact, Solution (high-level only), Success Metric</item>
      <item>User Personas — minimum 2, each with Role, Goal, Pain Points, Context</item>
      <item>User Stories — "As a / I want / So that" with US-X IDs and MoSCoW priority</item>
      <item>Functional Requirements — FR-X table with Requirement, Traces To (US-X), Priority (MoSCoW)</item>
      <item>Non-Functional Requirements — NFR-X table with Category, Requirement, Target (numeric), Priority</item>
      <item>Acceptance Criteria — AC-X in Given-When-Then format, linked to FR-X</item>
      <item>Out of Scope — explicit table of named excluded features with reason and timeline</item>
      <item>Assumptions and Constraints — technical and business constraints</item>
      <item>Dependencies — internal (other features) and external (APIs, services)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Spec vs Design Boundary">
    <rule>
      <statement>Spec contains WHAT and WHY only. Any sentence describing HOW something works belongs in design.md, not spec.md.</statement>
      <rationale>Implementation details in spec.md become stale when design decisions change, causing version drift between spec and design.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Implementation detail leaking into spec</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[FR-003: System SHALL use bcrypt with cost factor 12 for password hashing.]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Correct spec requirement — what, not how</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[FR-003: System SHALL store passwords using a cryptographically secure one-way hash that is resistant to brute-force attacks. [Must]]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="MoSCoW Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign MoSCoW priority (Must/Should/Could/Won't) to every FR and NFR. Unclassified requirements default to "Must" during implementation, causing scope creep.</statement>
      <rationale>Without explicit priority, executor agents treat all requirements as equally urgent and implement Could requirements before Should requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="NFR Numeric Targets">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every non-functional requirement must include a specific numeric target and measurement unit. "Fast" and "responsive" are not valid NFR values.</statement>
      <rationale>NFRs without numbers are unenforceable in testing and cannot be validated by automated checks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Vague NFR</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[NFR-001: System should have fast response times.]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Measurable NFR</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[NFR-001: API response time SHALL be &lt; 500ms at p95 under 100 concurrent users. [Must]]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Status Gate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Spec must reach Approved status before design begins. Never hand a Draft or Review spec to an executor agent.</statement>
      <rationale>Design decisions made against unapproved requirements cause rework when requirements change during the review cycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Out of Scope section lists only generic exclusions ("mobile app", "internationalization").</description>
      <reason>Out of Scope must name specific features that were discussed in requirements gathering and explicitly rejected with reasons. Generic exclusions do not prevent scope creep.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>User stories without "so that" benefit clause.</description>
      <reason>The benefit clause is where business value lives. Stories without it cannot be prioritized against each other.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Single persona for a multi-user feature.</description>
      <reason>Different personas have different goals and pain points. A single persona produces requirements that serve one audience and silently exclude others.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/spec.md">Complete spec.md template with all required sections</reference>
  <reference path="templates/spec-trace-check.sh">Bash script to verify every FR-X references a US and has an AC</reference>
</text>
