<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="persona-building">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>Create research-backed buyer personas from 10+ interviews with transcript citations, avoiding demographic theatre and hallucinated traits.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>personas</tag>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>segmentation</tag>
      <tag>buyer-archetypes</tag>
      <tag>interviews</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Persona Building</title>
    <summary>A 5-step process for creating semi-fictional buyer archetypes grounded in real interview data: gather data (minimum 10 interviews), cluster patterns, define 1-3 segments (primary / secondary / negative), build the persona with cited traits, then validate by showing the doc to actual customers. Outputs user-personas.md in .aidocs/product_docs/.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Personas built from imagination produce "demographic theatre" — stock-photo characters that never change a real product or marketing decision. Research-backed personas with transcript citations force the team to confront actual user language, purchasing triggers, and frustrations, making positioning and onboarding decisions testable rather than aesthetic.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Raw transcripts from 8+ customer interviews exist and need clustering into buyer archetypes before writing positioning or landing copy.</item>
        <item>Landing page has poor conversion and the team disagrees on "who this is for".</item>
        <item>Sales closes one segment 3x faster than others — codify that segment as primary persona.</item>
        <item>Pivoting into an adjacent market and needing a new primary persona before rewriting home page and pricing tiers.</item>
        <item>A multi-agent pipeline needs a shared persona artifact as input (faion-research-agent → faion-marketing-manager → faion-content-marketer).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF / pre-interview: zero customer conversations — run user-interviews and pain-point-research first.</item>
        <item>B2B enterprise with named-account selling and fewer than 20 logos — use account profiles and buying-committee maps.</item>
        <item>Highly heterogeneous marketplaces where the segmentation axis is transactional behavior — use audience-segmentation instead.</item>
        <item>Single-feature internal tools where the user is unambiguous — a 1-line role description beats a 2-page persona doc.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="data-sources">
      <rule>
        <statement>Conduct a minimum of 10 customer interviews before creating any persona. Do not build personas from imagination or market assumptions.</statement>
        <rationale>Personas without interview data produce "demographic theatre" — plausible-looking characters that never change a real decision. Ten interviews is the minimum for identifying patterns that recur across multiple people.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Data sources ranked by signal strength: interviews (goals, frustrations, workflow), surveys (demographics, tool usage), analytics (behavior, engagement), support tickets (problems, exact language used), social media (interests, how they talk), sales calls (objections, motivations).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="pattern-clustering">
      <p>Cluster interview findings on five dimensions: role/title, goals, frustrations, behaviors, buying triggers. Record both frequency (how many people said this) and intensity (how strongly they expressed it).</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every trait in the final persona must have a transcript citation in the format [transcript-id:line]. Traits with fewer than 3 supporting citations across transcripts are marked [WEAK] and excluded from the primary persona.</statement>
        <rationale>Uncited traits are hypotheses, not findings. Marking weak traits prevents them from driving product decisions while keeping them visible for future validation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="segment-types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Start with ONE primary persona. Add secondary personas only after the product has traction. Define a negative persona (who NOT to target) from the start.</statement>
        <rationale>Multiple personas at seed stage split focus and produce muddled positioning. The negative persona is more decision-shaping than the primary — "who do we say no to?" is the harder and more valuable question.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Segment types: Primary (main buyer, most revenue — focus all design here), Secondary (important but smaller — support their needs), Negative (explicitly not for them — do not market to, politely decline in sales).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="persona-elements">
      <p>Essential elements (required): name (memorable, role-based), role (job title/situation), demographics (only if 5+ transcripts agree), goals (what success looks like), frustrations (what blocks them), behaviors (how they work and buy), quote (verbatim from interview).</p>
      <p>Advanced elements (add only when handing off to marketing or design): day in the life, tools used, information sources, objections, buying trigger.</p>
      <templates>
        <template path="templates/persona-full.md" purpose="Full persona template with all fields"/>
        <template path="templates/persona-lean.md" purpose="Lean 6-field template for working use"/>
        <template path="templates/persona-negative.md" purpose="Negative persona template"/>
      </templates>
    </section>

    <section name="validation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Show the persona to 3 real customers and ask "does this sound like you?" before committing the document to the repository. If 2 of 3 say "no", rebuild.</statement>
        <rationale>Personas validated only internally often reflect team assumptions rather than customer reality. External validation catches the most common failure mode: the team's mental model of the customer diverges from the actual customer.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Update frequency: major update quarterly, minor tweaks as you learn, full rebuild after pivot or entry into a new market.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="example-newsletter-nate">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Primary persona for a SaaS tool targeting freelance writers. All traits sourced from interviews.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[## Newsletter Nate

**Who:** 34-year-old freelance writer, runs paid newsletter with 2,000 subscribers, makes $4K/month from writing.

**Goal:** Grow subscriber base to 10,000 and reduce time on operations.

**Frustration:** Email platform is expensive at scale; no easy way to sell digital products; analytics are confusing.

**Quote:** "I'm a writer, not a tech person. I just want it to work." [T03:L87]

**Buys when:** Current tool fails or becomes too expensive on price jump.

**Based on:** 12 interviews (all freelance writers with paid newsletters)]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="example-agency-amy">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Primary persona for a project management tool targeting 5-person design agencies.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[## Agency Amy

**Who:** 38-year-old agency owner, 5-person design agency, $500K annual revenue.

**Goals:** Stop projects going over budget; improve client communication; scale without overhead.

**Frustrations:** Team uses 6 different tools; clients don't understand project status; time tracking is inconsistent.

**Quote:** "I need my team aligned without micromanaging." [T07:L42]

**Buys when:** A project goes over budget for the third time in a quarter.

**Based on:** 15 interviews (agency owners, 3-15 employees)]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Creating personas with no interview data, using demographics or market reports as the source.</description>
        <reason>Fabricated personas produce wrong product decisions. A persona without transcript citations is a hypothesis dressed as a finding.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Creating 4+ personas at seed stage and trying to design for all of them simultaneously.</description>
        <reason>Multiple personas split focus and produce muddled messaging. One primary persona until the product has traction and ARR to justify more.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Including stock-photo demographics (age, city, salary) that no one on the team ever references in a product decision.</description>
        <reason>Demographic fields that never change a decision are dead weight. Include a demographic field only if it drives a specific product or messaging choice.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Publishing a persona document and never updating it.</description>
        <reason>By month 6 the actual ICP has often shifted. A stale persona still drives copy. Quarterly review or kill the artifact.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping the negative persona definition.</description>
        <reason>"Who do we say no to?" shapes sales qualification and product scope more concretely than the primary persona. Define it early and link it to the sales-disqualification SOP.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="hallucination-risks">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Asking an LLM to "write a persona for indie SaaS founders" without supplying transcript data.</description>
        <reason>LLMs will produce plausible-sounding frustrations, quotes, and demographics from training data priors rather than your actual customers. Every persona trait must be grounded in a transcript citation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running synthesis at temperature above 0.3 for clustering and trait extraction.</description>
        <reason>Higher temperature fabricates variation that looks like diverse customer segments. Use temperature 0 for clustering; reserve creative phrasing only for the optional characteristic quote field.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Feeding 30+ interview transcripts into one synthesis call.</description>
        <reason>Long-context dumps cause the model to collapse to averages and lose outliers. Use map-reduce: cluster per transcript, merge cluster summaries, synthesise the merged summaries.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="demographic-stereotypes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Including demographic fields (age, city, income) without 5+ transcript agreements.</description>
        <reason>LLMs encode demographic stereotypes from training data. "32-year-old freelance designer in Brooklyn" will appear plausibly even when none of your interviews confirm it. Strip demographics from the synthesis prompt unless the data supports them.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <rule>
        <statement>Instruct the synthesis agent: "Include no demographic field unless 5 or more transcripts contain explicit agreement on that dimension."</statement>
        <rationale>Enforces an evidence bar that prevents demographic stereotypes from leaking through model priors.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="pii-and-privacy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run password-scrubber-agent or equivalent before committing any interview transcript to the repository. Reference participants by ID (P07), never name.</statement>
        <rationale>Interview notes contain names, emails, Slack handles, and employer names. PII crossing repo boundaries is a compliance and trust violation, especially for EU-based interviewees under GDPR.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="transcript-ordering-bias">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Always feeding transcripts in the same order to the synthesis agent.</description>
        <reason>LLMs exhibit recency and primacy bias; the first and last transcripts in a batch disproportionately shape the output. Shuffle transcript order between runs; if the persona changes drastically, the data is too thin for a stable finding.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="human-in-the-loop-checkpoints">
      <checklist>
        <check>Before committing persona to repo: human reviews all citations; any uncited trait is flagged HALLUCINATION and removed.</check>
        <check>Before using persona to drive ad spend: human re-interviews 2 current customers to confirm the persona still holds.</check>
        <check>Do not let an agent autonomously update the persona doc on a schedule. Drift detection can be automated; rewrites must not be.</check>
      </checklist>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive persona building as a 4-step pipeline. (1) faion-research-agent (mode: personas) ingests interview transcripts from .aidocs/research/interviews/*.md and produces a clustered patterns file. (2) A synthesis pass writes a draft user-personas.md using the lean template. (3) faion-domain-checker-agent is irrelevant here; instead route the draft through faion-marketing-manager for messaging-fit review. (4) Validate by replaying the persona to 3 real customers (human-in-the-loop, do not automate this step).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-failure-modes">
      <p>"Demographic theatre": age/income/photo-stock fields filled in to look complete but never used in any real product/marketing decision. If the persona doesn't change a decision, it's dead weight.</p>
      <p>LLM hallucination of quotes: a model asked to "write a persona for indie SaaS founders" will invent plausible-sounding frustrations. Always ground in transcript citations.</p>
      <p>Persona drift: shipped once, never updated. By month 6 the actual ICP has shifted but the doc still drives copy. Quarterly review or kill the artifact.</p>
      <p>Over-segmentation: 5+ personas across a 3-person team means nobody is the focus. Cap at 1 primary + 1 negative until ARR justifies more.</p>
      <p>Confusing personas with segments: a persona is a representative individual; a segment is a group. Don't use persona docs to set ad targeting — use audience-segmentation for that.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Cite every trait. A persona without [transcript:line] citations is fiction. Treat uncited traits as hypotheses, not facts.</item>
        <item>Co-locate persona doc with messaging tests. Each persona's "Headline" field gets an open A/B ticket — if the headline never wins a test, the persona is wrong.</item>
        <item>Keep one primary persona until $X ARR threshold (team-defined). Splitting attention between 3 personas at seed-stage is the fastest path to muddled positioning.</item>
        <item>Define the negative persona early and link it to your sales-disqualification SOP. "Who do we say no to?" is more decision-shaping than the primary persona.</item>
        <item>Use lean template for working personas; only expand to full template when handing off to a marketing or design team that needs context you internalized.</item>
        <item>Re-validate every quarter by showing the doc to 3 real customers and asking "does this sound like you?" If two say "no", rebuild.</item>
        <item>Pair with jobs-to-be-done. Persona = who, JTBD = why-they-hire-the-product. Both required for a non-trivial product.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/persona-full.md" purpose="Full persona template (demographics, goals, frustrations, day-in-life, tools, buying behavior, messaging)"/>
      <template path="templates/persona-lean.md" purpose="Lean 6-field persona for working use and quick handoffs"/>
      <template path="templates/persona-negative.md" purpose="Negative persona template: who NOT to target and why"/>
      <template path="templates/cluster-personas.py" purpose="Python script: regex-based first-draft trait clustering from transcript directory"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
