<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-indiehackers-strategy Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-indiehackers-strategy. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set up a complete profile before your first post: real photo, bio that states what you're building and your background, product page with revenue (even $0), and linked Twitter/X. Incomplete profiles are ignored.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">IH community skims profiles before engaging. An incomplete profile signals low commitment. Transparent revenue — even zero — builds credibility because it shows honesty about current stage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spend 2–4 weeks answering questions, commenting on others' updates, and upvoting good content before making any post that mentions your product.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">IH community detects newcomers who appear only to promote. Early-stage promotion without participation gets ignored or flagged. Reputation is a prerequisite for reach on the platform.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When asking for feedback, specify exactly what you want feedback on, share context (what you've tried, what stage you're at), and include a screenshot or link. Reply to every comment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generic "feedback please" posts are skimmed over. Specific questions get specific answers. Replying to every comment signals engagement and generates ongoing discussion that boosts post visibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post a monthly update covering: MRR and user count, what worked this month, what failed, key learnings, and one question for the community. Share both wins and losses — losses generate more engagement than wins.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Transparent vulnerability (sharing failures) builds stronger community bonds than success posts alone. IH readers are founders who face the same failures; they engage deeply with honest loss analysis. Wins without losses look like marketing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post milestone updates at: first sale, $100 MRR, $1K MRR, $10K MRR, first 100 users, first profitable month, and job quit day. Format: journey → what worked → what to do differently → open AMA.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These specific milestones are culturally significant to the IH community. They generate high engagement because readers are either approaching these milestones (aspirational) or have passed them (they can contribute experience). The AMA format creates ongoing discussion that keeps the post visible for days.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post minimum weekly (even brief updates) to maintain visibility in the feed. Disappearing for 3+ weeks resets community familiarity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">IH shows recent activity in maker profiles. Gaps signal stalled projects. Community builds relationships with consistent voices; irregular posters are forgotten between posts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
