<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-give-first-setup" title="Profile Setup and Give-First Participation">
  <summary>Profile configuration for credibility; daily contribution activities before any self-promotion; types of helpful content that build reputation; feedback request rules.</summary>

  <section title="Profile Setup">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set up a complete profile before your first post: real photo, bio that states what you're building and your background, product page with revenue (even $0), and linked Twitter/X. Incomplete profiles are ignored.</statement>
      <rationale>IH community skims profiles before engaging. An incomplete profile signals low commitment. Transparent revenue — even zero — builds credibility because it shows honesty about current stage.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Give-First Period (2–4 Weeks Before Promotion)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Spend 2–4 weeks answering questions, commenting on others' updates, and upvoting good content before making any post that mentions your product.</statement>
      <rationale>IH community detects newcomers who appear only to promote. Early-stage promotion without participation gets ignored or flagged. Reputation is a prerequisite for reach on the platform.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Answer "how do I..." questions in your domain — daily, 2–3 per day.</item>
      <item>Comment thoughtfully on other makers' updates — not just "congrats", but specific engagement with their challenge.</item>
      <item>Share relevant tools or resources that are not your own.</item>
      <item>Connect people in the community who should know each other.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Effective Feedback Requests">
    <rule>
      <statement>When asking for feedback, specify exactly what you want feedback on, share context (what you've tried, what stage you're at), and include a screenshot or link. Reply to every comment.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic "feedback please" posts are skimmed over. Specific questions get specific answers. Replying to every comment signals engagement and generates ongoing discussion that boosts post visibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Asking "What do you think of my idea?" without context, stage information, or what kind of feedback you need.</description>
      <reason>Non-specific asks produce non-specific answers ("looks good!") that are useless. They also signal that the maker hasn't thought deeply about the problem.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
