<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-build-in-public" title="Build-in-Public Content Strategy">
  <summary>Monthly update structure; milestone post formula; what to share (wins, losses, metrics); posting frequency and engagement rules.</summary>

  <section title="Monthly Update Content">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post a monthly update covering: MRR and user count, what worked this month, what failed, key learnings, and one question for the community. Share both wins and losses — losses generate more engagement than wins.</statement>
      <rationale>Transparent vulnerability (sharing failures) builds stronger community bonds than success posts alone. IH readers are founders who face the same failures; they engage deeply with honest loss analysis. Wins without losses look like marketing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/monthly-update.txt">Monthly update template with all required sections.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Milestone Posts">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post milestone updates at: first sale, $100 MRR, $1K MRR, $10K MRR, first 100 users, first profitable month, and job quit day. Format: journey → what worked → what to do differently → open AMA.</statement>
      <rationale>These specific milestones are culturally significant to the IH community. They generate high engagement because readers are either approaching these milestones (aspirational) or have passed them (they can contribute experience). The AMA format creates ongoing discussion that keeps the post visible for days.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/milestone-post.txt">Milestone post template with journey, learnings, and AMA format.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Posting Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post minimum weekly (even brief updates) to maintain visibility in the feed. Disappearing for 3+ weeks resets community familiarity.</statement>
      <rationale>IH shows recent activity in maker profiles. Gaps signal stalled projects. Community builds relationships with consistent voices; irregular posters are forgotten between posts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Build-in-Public Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Only posting wins and growth numbers, hiding failures and pivots.</description>
      <reason>Reads as a marketing account, not a real maker. Community disengages. The most-shared IH posts are about failure, pivots, and hard lessons — not clean success stories.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Posting an update and not replying to comments for 2+ days.</description>
      <reason>Comment threads that the author ignores die immediately. Replies create ongoing discussion that keeps the post visible in the feed and signals you value the community's input.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
