<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-reddit-marketing Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-reddit-marketing. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Target subreddits with 10K–500K members, daily post activity, and rules that allow at least indirect self-promotion. Avoid subreddits over 1M members — too competitive for organic visibility.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Large subreddits bury new posts within minutes. Sub-10K subreddits have insufficient traffic to matter. The 10K–500K range offers enough audience with enough organic reach per good post.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before any product mention: account must be 30+ days old, have 100+ comment karma, and have participated in the target subreddit specifically for 2+ weeks. These are minimum thresholds — more is better.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Reddit's spam filter algorithms specifically check account age and karma. New accounts are automatically filtered in most subreddits regardless of content quality. Subreddit-specific participation builds mod familiarity, which prevents post removal on technical grounds.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For every self-promotional post or comment, make 10 value-add contributions (answers, guides, resources, comments) in the same community. Track your ratio.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Reddit communities actively monitor and discuss members who post only about their own product. A public thread calling out a spammer can permanently associate your product with spam in search results, which are permanent and indexed by Google.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>End posts with "happy to answer questions in comments" or "ask me anything about X" — never with a link to your product unless directly asked. Include a TL;DR for posts over 500 words.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ending with a product link reads as the real purpose of the post. "Happy to answer questions" creates engagement without the promotional close. Redditors who want to know your product will ask in comments — that's the conversion event you want.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When receiving harsh public criticism: acknowledge the valid point, provide a factual correction if incorrect, then stop. Do not continue arguing. One response is enough.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Extended arguments on Reddit attract pile-ons. The third reply to criticism is never the last — the community will keep the thread alive. A single gracious response and silence is how respected community members handle it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
