<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-subreddit-research" title="Subreddit Research and Karma Building">
  <summary>Subreddit evaluation criteria (size sweet spot, activity, rules, tone); karma and account age requirements; the 10:1 value-to-promo ratio rule.</summary>

  <section title="Subreddit Evaluation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Target subreddits with 10K–500K members, daily post activity, and rules that allow at least indirect self-promotion. Avoid subreddits over 1M members — too competitive for organic visibility.</statement>
      <rationale>Large subreddits bury new posts within minutes. Sub-10K subreddits have insufficient traffic to matter. The 10K–500K range offers enough audience with enough organic reach per good post.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Check: size (10K–500K ideal), post frequency (daily), rule clarity (self-promotion allowed in what form?), mod activity (do mods respond to rule questions?), community tone (helpful or aggressive?).</item>
      <item>Read the sidebar rules and the 5 most recent mod posts before any participation.</item>
      <item>Check if the subreddit has weekly self-promo threads — these are the safest channel for product mentions.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Account and Karma Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before any product mention: account must be 30+ days old, have 100+ comment karma, and have participated in the target subreddit specifically for 2+ weeks. These are minimum thresholds — more is better.</statement>
      <rationale>Reddit's spam filter algorithms specifically check account age and karma. New accounts are automatically filtered in most subreddits regardless of content quality. Subreddit-specific participation builds mod familiarity, which prevents post removal on technical grounds.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="The 10:1 Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>For every self-promotional post or comment, make 10 value-add contributions (answers, guides, resources, comments) in the same community. Track your ratio.</statement>
      <rationale>Reddit communities actively monitor and discuss members who post only about their own product. A public thread calling out a spammer can permanently associate your product with spam in search results, which are permanent and indexed by Google.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Creating multiple accounts to upvote your own posts or simulate enthusiasm ("astroturfing").</description>
      <reason>Reddit's anti-vote-manipulation detection is sophisticated. Account bans are permanent. More damaging: if caught, the community will publicly document it and the story becomes a top Google result for your product name.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
