<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-content-that-works" title="Reddit Content Formats and Self-Promotion Timing">
  <summary>Five content types that perform on Reddit; post format rules; when and how to introduce your product; handle criticism strategy.</summary>

  <section title="High-Performing Content Types">
    <list>
      <item>Guides — long-form, actionable, comprehensive. "Complete guide to X" with table of contents. No pitch at the end.</item>
      <item>Breakdowns — analytical deconstruction of how a company, product, or strategy works. Numbers and specifics required.</item>
      <item>Tools/Resources lists — curated, with brief description of each. Include competitors and alternatives (not just your product).</item>
      <item>Case studies with numbers — "How I did X in Y time" with specific metrics. The less polished it looks, the more authentic it reads.</item>
      <item>AMAs — "I'm a [role/credential], ask me anything about [specific topic]". Requires real credentials verifiable from profile.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Post Format Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>End posts with "happy to answer questions in comments" or "ask me anything about X" — never with a link to your product unless directly asked. Include a TL;DR for posts over 500 words.</statement>
      <rationale>Ending with a product link reads as the real purpose of the post. "Happy to answer questions" creates engagement without the promotional close. Redditors who want to know your product will ask in comments — that's the conversion event you want.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Strategic Self-Promotion Formats">
    <list>
      <item>Comment mention — only when someone asks "does anyone know of a tool that does X?" and your product directly answers. Natural context, not volunteered.</item>
      <item>Weekly self-promo thread — many subreddits have these. Follow the exact format specified. Do not use these threads to post guides (wrong thread).</item>
      <item>Milestone post — "Just hit $10K MRR with [product type]. Here's what worked." Product mentioned by category; link only if asked in comments.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Handling Criticism">
    <rule>
      <statement>When receiving harsh public criticism: acknowledge the valid point, provide a factual correction if incorrect, then stop. Do not continue arguing. One response is enough.</statement>
      <rationale>Extended arguments on Reddit attract pile-ons. The third reply to criticism is never the last — the community will keep the thread alive. A single gracious response and silence is how respected community members handle it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
