<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="agile-ceremonies-setup">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Defines and configures five Scrum events for team size, timezone spread, and PM tool. Ceremony overhead stays below 10% of sprint capacity with action-item closure tracking.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>scrum</tag>
      <tag>ceremonies</tag>
      <tag>sprint-planning</tag>
      <tag>retrospectives</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <category>ceremonies</category>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Agile Ceremonies Setup</title>
    <summary>Defines, configures, and continuously improves the five Scrum events — Sprint Planning, Daily Standup, Sprint Review, Retrospective, and Backlog Refinement — for a team's specific size, timezone spread, and PM tool. Total ceremony overhead must stay at or below 10% of sprint capacity. Each event has a mandatory time-box, a single sprint goal, and tracked action-item closure.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Ceremonies decay without explicit structure: standups become status reports, retrospectives surface the same complaints sprint after sprint, reviews turn into internal demos without real stakeholder feedback. Time-boxing plus outcome tracking turns ceremonies from ritual into an actual feedback loop. Untracked retro actions means the team never improves.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Bootstrapping Scrum for a new team: defining cadence, agendas, time-boxes, PM tool wiring.</item>
        <item>Migrating a waterfall or ad-hoc team to a structured ceremony rhythm.</item>
        <item>Tuning ceremonies that have decayed (silent retros, status-report standups, drifting reviews).</item>
        <item>Setting up async / hybrid ceremonies for distributed teams with wide timezone spread.</item>
        <item>Configuring Jira, Linear, or Azure DevOps to mirror the ceremony cadence.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo or 2-person teams — overhead exceeds value; lightweight async check-ins suffice.</item>
        <item>Continuous-delivery Kanban teams with WIP limits and SLA dashboards — ceremonies become anti-patterns.</item>
        <item>Teams with zero psychological safety — retros become blame sessions and worsen things before they help; fix safety first.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Time-Box Reference and Core Rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Never run a ceremony past its time-box; end on time even if the agenda is incomplete — incomplete items become backlog.</statement>
        <rationale>Ceremonies that overrun erode trust in the process; the team learns that the schedule is fictional and stops preparing.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Time-boxes by sprint length: Planning: 2h/4h/8h for 1wk/2wk/4wk. Daily: 15min always. Review: 1h/2h/4h. Retro: 45min/90min/3h. Refinement: 1-2h/2-4h/4-8h.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Sprint Goal">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write one sprint goal per sprint, before selecting backlog items. Reject a goal that does not answer "what changes for users?"</statement>
        <rationale>Without a sprint goal, the daily standup becomes a status report and the team has no shared criterion for success. LLM-generated goals tend to be vacuous ("complete sprint backlog") — reject them by the same test.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Definition of Ready and Done">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply Definition of Ready at refinement (acceptance criteria, dependencies, estimate, fits in sprint, testable). Apply Definition of Done at planning. Both must be agreed before the first sprint begins.</statement>
        <rationale>Without DoR, sprint scope is undecided at planning start. Without DoD, done means different things to developer, tester, and stakeholder.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Retro Action-Item Closure">
      <rule>
        <statement>Track retro actions as backlog items tagged with their originating sprint. If closure rate falls below 70% over three consecutive sprints, declare the retro format broken and change it.</statement>
        <rationale>Retros where actions are never implemented produce cynicism faster than no retro at all. The 70% threshold is a measurable signal that the format is working.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Ceremony Overhead Ceiling">
      <rule>
        <statement>Total ceremony time per person must not exceed 10% of sprint capacity. Audit the calendar every quarter; kill any recurring meeting where more than 20% of attendees would not voluntarily opt in.</statement>
        <rationale>Beyond 10%, the team trades delivery time for coordination overhead without proportional benefit.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Sprint Planning">
      <rule>
        <statement>Split planning into two parts: Part 1 (what) — review goal, top items, acceptance criteria. Part 2 (how) — break stories into tasks, estimate, identify dependencies, commit. Each part gets equal time.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing what and how in a single session causes scope confusion; the team commits before understanding the work.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Jira setup: backlog view + sprint-planning mode, filter "status = Ready AND sprint IS EMPTY", show story points + AC + priority. Linear setup: new cycle with dates, backlog filter "state:backlog", priority sort.</p>
      <reference path="templates/sprint-planning.md">Sprint planning artifact template</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="Daily Standup">
      <rule>
        <statement>Prefer walk-the-board format over three-questions format: start from the rightmost column, discuss each in-flight item, identify blocks. Focus on flow, not individuals.</statement>
        <rationale>Walk-the-board surfaces WIP age and blocking dependencies visually; the classic three-questions format produces individual status reports the team reads serially.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Update the board in real time during standup; never let a standup pass without moving cards. The tool is the record of the event.</statement>
        <rationale>A standup that doesn't touch the board is theater; the board and the conversation must stay synchronized.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Sprint Review">
      <rule>
        <statement>Sprint Review must include real users or external stakeholders, not only the dev team. An internal-only review is waste.</statement>
        <rationale>The purpose of the review is stakeholder feedback that adjusts the backlog; internal audiences cannot provide it. Stakeholder participation is mandatory per Scrum Guide 2020.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Agenda: welcome 5min, sprint goal recap 5min, demos 45min, feedback 15min, backlog discussion 15min, next preview 5min. Metrics to display: sprint goal met, story points completed, velocity trend.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Retrospective">
      <rule>
        <statement>Rotate retro format every 4-6 sprints (Start-Stop-Continue, 4Ls, Sailboat, Mad-Sad-Glad). Rotate the facilitator each sprint.</statement>
        <rationale>Fixed format produces diminishing returns; rotation keeps the exercise fresh and distributes facilitation skill across the team.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/retrospective.md">Retrospective artifact template</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="Backlog Refinement">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use Planning Poker for estimation: everyone votes secretly, reveal simultaneously, discuss only the outliers, re-vote if needed. Consensus must be recorded in the tool before the session ends.</statement>
        <rationale>Simultaneous reveal prevents anchoring on a first estimate; discussing outliers surfaces missing context without silencing quieter team members.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>T-shirt sizing map: XS=1pt, S=2-3pt, M=5pt, L=8pt, XL=13+ (must be split before committing). Any item over L at refinement is rejected from the next sprint until split.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Async Standup Rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Async standup prompts must focus on goal-progress and blockers, not "what did you do yesterday". Reject prompts that produce individual status reports.</statement>
        <rationale>Status questions produce status answers; goal-progress questions keep the team aligned on the sprint goal rather than individual task lists.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use tz-aware scheduling for async standups; recalculate after daylight-saving transitions. Naive UTC offsets break twice a year.</statement>
        <rationale>A standup that works in March may exclude APAC or Eastern Europe after the DST shift. Encode acceptable hours per participant in the bot config.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/standup-bot.yaml">Geekbot-compatible async standup configuration</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="Distributed Team Rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Maximum one sync ceremony per day for distributed teams; Sprint Planning and Retrospective may share a day, but no more than two sync events back-to-back.</statement>
        <rationale>Zoom fatigue compounds across sessions; more than one long sync per day collapses participation quality by the second event.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Any global recurring meeting must either rotate its time across quarters or run two sessions. Document the rotation schedule in the team calendar.</statement>
        <rationale>A fixed "Tue 10:00 UTC" permanently excludes APAC time zones from meaningful participation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Ceremony Health Measurement">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a ceremony health survey (1-5 scale) every quarter. Track: time-box compliance, sprint-goal-met rate, retro action closure rate, velocity stability. Trigger a retro on ceremonies if any metric scores below 3.</statement>
        <rationale>Without measurement, ceremony decay is invisible until the team openly refuses to attend. Quantified health scores make the problem surfaceable before that point.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ceremony rituals re-imported when a team has moved to flow-based delivery.</description>
        <reason>Sprint cadence imposed on a Kanban team adds overhead without benefit; the team "does Scrum ceremonies for Kanban" and cargo-cults both methods badly.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>Three useful agent surfaces: (1) one-time setup — generate ceremony cadence, agendas, tool config (Jira board, Linear cycle, ADO sprint) from team profile (size, timezone spread, sprint length). (2) Ongoing facilitation — async standup bot prompts (Geekbot / Standuply / Slack workflow), retro board templates per sprint, agenda generation tied to sprint metrics. (3) Continuous improvement — post-sprint analysis: did the team meet sprint goal? velocity trend? action-item closure rate? Then propose ceremony tweaks. Keep agents away from authoring sprint goals or assigning work — those are PO / team decisions.</p>
      <p>Time-box discipline collapses without an active facilitator; ceremonies bloat 2-3x and the team blames "agile" rather than facilitation. Async standups become status reports nobody reads; lose the point of the event. Sprint reviews drift into "demo theatre" instead of real stakeholder feedback. Retros that don't track action-item completion produce same complaints every sprint, then team gives up. Tool-driven ceremonies (Jira-only) miss the conversational value; tool is record, not the event.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Prompt Pattern for Agent Setup">
      <p>Inputs: team_size=7, sprint_length=2w, timezone_spread="UTC-5 to UTC+3", delivery_model="scrum", tool="jira", remote_pct=80. Output Markdown bundle: ceremony_cadence (table: event, time-box, day, mode sync/async), per_event_agenda (sprint-planning, daily, review, retro, refinement), jira_config (sprint dates, board columns, quick filters, dashboard widgets), standup_bot_config (Geekbot YAML), definition_of_ready, definition_of_done starter. Hard constraints: total ceremony overhead per person ≤ 8% of sprint capacity. Do NOT propose more than 2 sync ceremonies for high timezone spread.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Cap total ceremony time at ≤ 10% of sprint capacity. If the team complains about meetings, audit the time-boxes first.</item>
        <item>One *single* sprint goal per sprint, written before backlog selection. No goal = standup is status reporting.</item>
        <item>Definition of Ready (DoR) at refinement, Definition of Done (DoD) at planning. Without both, sprint scope is mush.</item>
        <item>Track completed retro actions as backlog items with the sprint they came from. &lt; 70% closure rate = retros aren't working.</item>
        <item>Rotate facilitators (standup, retro) — distributes facilitation skill, prevents Scrum-Master single point of failure.</item>
        <item>For distributed teams: maximum one sync ceremony per day (planning + retro can be the same day); use async for standups.</item>
        <item>Sprint Review must include real users / stakeholders, not just the dev team. Internal demo = waste.</item>
        <item>Retro format rotation (Start-Stop-Continue → 4Ls → Sailboat → Mad-Sad-Glad) every 4-6 sprints to keep it fresh.</item>
        <item>Ceremony health survey (1-5 score) every quarter — measure the ceremony, not just the work.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-Agent Gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLM defaults to Scrum vocabulary even when team is on Kanban / flow; it will invent sprints that don't exist. Anchor on `delivery_model` input.</item>
        <item>Generated agendas often exceed time-box (60+45+45 = 150 min for a 2-week sprint review is overkill); enforce sum ≤ time-box.</item>
        <item>Async standup prompts written by LLMs default to status questions ("what did you do yesterday"); push toward goal-progress + blocker focus.</item>
        <item>Retro action items often lack owner / due date / measurable outcome — agent emits "improve communication" not "implement standup template by sprint N+1, owner @x". Force structured output.</item>
        <item>Tool-config generation: Jira / Linear / ADO have rate-limited APIs and irreversible side effects (deleted boards). Always dry-run first; never let agent delete boards.</item>
        <item>Timezone math: agent forgets daylight-saving transitions; standup that worked in March breaks in November. Use tz-aware library, not naive UTC offsets.</item>
        <item>LLMs invent "Scrum guide" rules ("daily must be standing") that aren't in the actual Scrum Guide (2020). Cite version.</item>
        <item>Sprint goal generation by LLM tends to be vacuous ("complete sprint backlog"); reject if it doesn't pass the "what changes for users?" test.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/sprint-planning.md" purpose="Sprint planning artifact: goal, capacity table, backlog, risks."/>
      <template path="templates/retrospective.md" purpose="Retro artifact: metrics, went-well, improve, action items with owners."/>
      <template path="templates/standup-bot.yaml" purpose="Geekbot-compatible async standup configuration."/>
    </templates>
    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/create_sprint.sh" purpose="Create and start a Jira sprint with goal, dates, and top ready issues via jira-cli."/>
    </scripts>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://scrumguides.org/scrum-guide.html"/>
      <link href="https://pragprog.com/titles/dlret/agile-retrospectives/"/>
      <link href="https://retromat.org/"/>
      <link href="https://developer.atlassian.com/cloud/jira/platform/rest/v3/"/>
      <link href="https://developers.linear.app/"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/rest/api/azure/devops/"/>
      <link href="https://www.liberatingstructures.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
