<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="funnel-basics-framework">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>conversion-optimizer</domain>
    <summary>7-phase systematic process for funnel improvement: map, measure, prioritize drops, diagnose, hypothesize, test, repeat. Rule: always fix the largest absolute user loss first.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>funnel</tag>
      <tag>conversion</tag>
      <tag>framework</tag>
      <tag>optimization</tag>
      <tag>process</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Funnel Optimization Framework</title>
    <summary>A 7-phase process for systematically improving conversion at each step of a user journey: map steps, measure rates, find the biggest drop, diagnose the cause, generate testable hypotheses, run A/B tests, and repeat on the next biggest drop. The rule: always fix the biggest absolute loss first, not the easiest step.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Every product funnel leaks. Without a structured process, teams guess which step to fix and waste effort on small gains. The framework ensures effort is directed at the highest-leverage drop-off and that changes are validated with data before being declared wins.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>A product has measurable steps from entry to goal (signup, purchase, activation)</item>
        <item>Overall conversion is below industry benchmarks or declining</item>
        <item>You need to prioritize which step to optimize next</item>
        <item>You have at least 7 days of tracking data per step</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Fewer than 100 users per funnel step — sample size too small for meaningful diagnosis</item>
        <item>No analytics instrumentation in place — map and measure steps first before optimizing</item>
        <item>Product has not yet reached product-market fit — optimize retention before acquisition funnel</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="overview">
      <p>The 7-phase process for systematically improving conversion: map, measure, find drop, diagnose, hypothesize, test, repeat.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always fix the step with the largest absolute user loss first, not the step with the lowest percentage conversion.</statement>
        <rationale>A step losing 6,500 users at 35% conversion outweighs a step losing 300 users at 9% conversion, even though the percentage looks worse on the smaller step.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="phase-1-map-the-funnel">
      <p>Define every step from first touch to goal. This foundation step is critical because ambiguous definitions lead to tracking errors that poison later diagnosis. Get explicit stakeholder agreement on what "conversion" means in your context before instrumenting a single event.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Define every step from first touch to goal, name each step with an event name, and get stakeholder agreement before measuring.</statement>
        <rationale>Ambiguous step definitions cause tracking inconsistencies that make drop-off analysis unreliable. Rework a funnel definition mid-analysis is expensive.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>SaaS signup funnel with concrete event names at each step: page_view_home, cta_clicked, signup_form_viewed, email_submitted, email_verified, profile_completed, first_action_completed. Each event is named, ordered, and tied to a real user action or system event.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="phase-2-measure-each-step">
      <p>Collect data across all steps for the minimum time window needed for valid analysis.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Collect minimum 30 days of data and segment by traffic source, device, and new vs. returning before drawing conclusions.</statement>
        <rationale>Short windows miss weekly patterns; unsegmented data hides that mobile users drop at different steps than desktop users.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="phase-3-find-the-biggest-drop">
      <p>Identify which transition causes the largest absolute user loss.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Rank transitions by absolute users lost, not by drop percentage. Prioritize the transition with the highest user count lost.</statement>
        <rationale>A 65% drop at step 1→2 losing 6,500 users is higher priority than a 30% drop at step 6→7 losing 461 users.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="phase-4-diagnose-the-cause">
      <p>Use multiple diagnostic methods to understand why users drop off: session recordings reveal user behavior and frustration points; heatmaps show which areas users click and scroll; exit surveys capture stated reasons (user-perceived); user interviews provide depth and uncover hidden friction. Diagnostics are inputs to hypothesis generation, not conclusions. Document all findings before moving to hypotheses.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Landing to CTA: unclear value prop, poor design, slow load, confusing positioning</item>
        <item>CTA to form: too many fields, scary commitment language, unclear privacy terms</item>
        <item>Form to submit: technical errors, confusing UX, field validation unclear, error messages unhelpful</item>
        <item>Submit to verify: email in spam folder, long confirmation delay, unclear next step</item>
        <item>Onboarding to activation: too complex, no guidance, value not shown, aha-moment missing</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="phase-5-generate-hypotheses">
      <p>Create testable, data-grounded hypotheses for each diagnosed problem.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Write every hypothesis in IF/THEN/BECAUSE format: "If we [change X], then [metric] will improve by [Y%], because [diagnosis-based reason]."</statement>
        <rationale>Vague hypotheses cannot be falsified; format enforces that each hypothesis is grounded in diagnosis, not guesswork.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="phase-6-test-and-iterate">
      <p>Run A/B tests prioritized by impact and confidence.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Prioritize hypotheses with ICE (Impact x Confidence x Ease). Test the highest ICE score first. Score 20-30 means test immediately.</statement>
        <rationale>Without scoring, teams test what is easiest to build, not what will move the metric most.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="phase-7-repeat">
      <p>Iterate continuously on the next biggest drop-off.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>After implementing a winner, move to the next biggest drop-off transition. Track cumulative conversion improvement over time.</statement>
        <rationale>Funnel optimization is a continuous loop, not a one-time project.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="common-funnel-types">
      <p>Standard funnel shapes across product categories.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Marketing: Impression → Click → Landing Page → Signup → Activation → Purchase</item>
        <item>SaaS: Visit → Signup → Onboarding → Activation → Engagement → Conversion → Retention</item>
        <item>E-commerce: Visit → View Product → Add to Cart → Checkout Start → Payment → Confirmation</item>
        <item>Mobile App: App Store → Download → Open → Onboarding → Core Action → Retention → Monetization</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="per-phase-checklist">
      <p>Per-phase verification steps ensuring measurement quality, diagnosis depth, and test rigor before moving to the next phase.</p>
      <section name="phase-1-map-checklist">
        <list>
          <item>Define all steps from entry to goal</item>
          <item>Identify main funnel type (marketing, SaaS, e-commerce, mobile)</item>
          <item>Name each step with an analytics event name</item>
          <item>Identify entry point and conversion goal</item>
          <item>Document alternate paths or user segments</item>
          <item>Get stakeholder agreement on funnel definition</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-2-measure-checklist">
        <list>
          <item>Set up event tracking for all steps</item>
          <item>Collect minimum 30 days of historical data</item>
          <item>Calculate conversion rate: (users at step N / users at step 1) x 100</item>
          <item>Calculate drop rate: ((users at N - users at N+1) / users at N) x 100</item>
          <item>Segment by: traffic source, device, new vs. returning</item>
          <item>Verify data quality — no tracking errors, complete events</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-3-find-biggest-drop-checklist">
        <list>
          <item>Rank each step transition by absolute users lost</item>
          <item>Calculate percentage of total users lost per transition</item>
          <item>Identify top 3 transitions by absolute loss</item>
          <item>Confirm which drop has the largest financial impact</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-4-diagnose-checklist">
        <list>
          <item>Review session recordings for the priority drop-off step</item>
          <item>Check heatmaps (click and scroll behavior)</item>
          <item>Run exit-intent survey at drop-off point</item>
          <item>Conduct 5-10 user interviews for major product issues</item>
          <item>Check technical error logs at that step</item>
          <item>Compare mobile vs. desktop behavior</item>
          <item>Measure page load speed at that step</item>
          <item>Document all findings before generating hypotheses</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-5-hypothesize-checklist">
        <list>
          <item>Create 5-10 IF/THEN/BECAUSE statements</item>
          <item>Each hypothesis grounded in Phase 4 diagnosis</item>
          <item>Each hypothesis is testable (has a measurable metric)</item>
          <item>Cover design, copy, and flow changes</item>
          <item>Score each hypothesis with ICE (Impact, Confidence, Ease)</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-6-test-checklist">
        <list>
          <item>Rank hypotheses by ICE score; test highest first</item>
          <item>Define control and variant clearly — change only one variable</item>
          <item>Set test duration until statistical significance (p &lt; 0.05)</item>
          <item>Track primary metric plus secondary metrics</item>
          <item>Monitor test daily for anomalies</item>
          <item>Document winner and loser with statistical confidence</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-7-repeat-checklist">
        <list>
          <item>Implement winning test if lift exceeds threshold</item>
          <item>Document learnings and surprising findings</item>
          <item>Move to next hypothesis or next biggest drop</item>
          <item>Set up weekly/monthly funnel review cadence</item>
          <item>Track cumulative improvement over time</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/funnel-analysis.md" purpose="Funnel analysis document template for recording step metrics and hypotheses"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-funnel-analysis.txt" purpose="LLM prompt for analyzing funnel drop-off and prioritizing fixes"/>
    </templates>
    <section name="limitations-and-gotchas">
      <p>The framework assumes you can attribute users across steps (consistent IDs, deterministic events). Fragmented identity (cookieless, anon → identified) breaks the math; agents must validate ID stitching first.</p>
      <p>"Biggest drop" prioritization underweights downstream value; a 50% drop at "viewed pricing" can be less critical than a 10% drop at "added card" if customer LTV concentrates at the bottom. Agents should also report "users-lost-weighted-by-LTV".</p>
      <p>The ICE 1–10 scoring is subjective; without anchoring rubrics, two agents will produce different scores for the same hypothesis. Pin the rubric first.</p>
      <p>The common-cause diagnostic table is a heuristic — real causes need session recordings plus interviews; agents must not finalize a diagnosis from analytics alone.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A funnel-framework agent runs as a 7-step pipeline aligned with the process: funnel-mapper writes the step + event spec, funnel-instrumenter adds events + verifies in dev, funnel-analyzer pulls 30-day data and produces the conversion table, leak-prioritizer ranks drops by absolute and LTV-weighted loss, diagnosis-runner orchestrates session-recording / heatmap / survey reads to compose root-cause notes, hypothesis-generator emits ICE-scored hypotheses using the IF/THEN/BECAUSE template, test-planner queues experiments.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: funnel-mapper (input: product surface; output: ordered steps + event names matching the framework table format), funnel-analyzer (pulls cohort data from analytics emitting the conversion + drop-off table), leak-prioritizer (scores leaks by absolute users lost AND LTV-weighted lost revenue), diagnosis-runner (composes session-recording summaries + heatmap top-clicks + survey responses into a root-cause note), hypothesis-generator (emits 3–5 IF/THEN/BECAUSE hypotheses scored with ICE), test-planner (turns hypotheses into experiment specs with sample size + duration).</p>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="funnel-basics-examples"/>
      <ref slug="funnel-tactics-basics"/>
      <ref slug="funnel-tactics-advanced"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
