<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-trends" title="Product Development Trend Axes">
  <summary>Four primary trend axes for modern product development practice with evidence requirements and key research output types.</summary>

  <section title="Trend Axes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor every trend claim to a primary source with a publication date no older than 90 days. Reject any claim without a URL.</statement>
      <rationale>Trend reports decay fast. LLM training data is structurally behind real markets. Consumer behavior trends degrade in months; process trends degrade in one to two years.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>AI-augmented ideation — AI scans market data and surfaces weak signals; humans decide which signals are actionable. Enables pattern recognition at scale that would take weeks manually.</item>
      <item>Continuous customer feedback — real-time iteration loops replacing fixed quarterly research cycles. Reduces the time between hypothesis and evidence.</item>
      <item>Rapid pivots — quarterly adjustment cadence vs annual planning cycles. Lower cost of being wrong; faster response to competitive and market signals.</item>
      <item>Cross-functional teams — PM, Design, and Engineering co-owning discovery and delivery. Reduces handoff latency and aligns accountability with outcomes.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Research Output Types">
    <p>Trend research produces four types of artifacts for downstream consumption:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Market Analysis Reports — size, trends, competitive landscape with sourced figures</item>
      <item>User Need Assessments — pain points and unmet needs with source citations and frequency counts</item>
      <item>Concept Validation Studies — evidence that an idea has a real market before engineering begins</item>
      <item>Feature Priority Reports — ranked list of what to build first, based on evidence strength and segment fit</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Separation Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep process trends (how teams work) and consumer trends (what users want) in separate sections. Never mix them in a single bullet list.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixed trend lists prevent teams from routing insights to the right function. Process trends drive team-shape and tooling decisions; consumer trends drive feature and positioning decisions. Mixing produces unfocused roadmap inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-methodology.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/score-signals.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
