<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-methodology" title="Trend Research Pipeline">
  <summary>Three-stage pipeline for trend research: signal collection, scored triage, human checkpoint before writing deliverables.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Stage Pipeline">
    <p>Stage 1 (sonnet-class, broad): WebSearch + WebFetch across trend axes, collect raw signals. Stage 2 (opus-class, synthesis): score each signal on recency, evidence, and applicability; emit ranked table. Stage 3 (human checkpoint): accept or reject claims before they land in .aidocs/product_docs/trend-report.md.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>The human checkpoint before writing to .aidocs/ is mandatory. Hallucinated tool names or vendor capabilities must not reach deliverables.</statement>
      <rationale>Trend deliverables shape roadmap conversations. A hallucinated vendor capability or unsourced claim landing in a product brief costs more to correct downstream than the checkpoint costs upfront.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Signal Scoring">
    <p>Three scoring dimensions, each 0-3, threshold for inclusion: total &gt;= 5.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Recency: 3 = within 30 days, 2 = 31-90 days, 1 = 91-180 days, 0 = older than 180 days</item>
      <item>Evidence: 3 = primary source, 2 = 3+ independent citations, 1 = secondary aggregator</item>
      <item>Applicability: 0-3 set by human reviewer based on fit to this specific product</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/score-signals.py">Signal scoring script with threshold filtering and markdown table output</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Audit Trail">
    <rule>
      <statement>Persist raw signals to .aidocs/research/raw/signals.jsonl. The diff between this quarter and the previous file is more useful than the polished narrative.</statement>
      <rationale>The trend delta — what is new, what faded, what reversed — is the real finding. Without a persistent artifact, each quarterly run starts from scratch and misses the directional signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include a "kill list": for every trend adopted, name one prior practice stopped. Trend reports without subtractions are theatre.</statement>
      <rationale>Additive-only trend reports imply infinite capacity. A kill list forces a real trade-off and signals to the team that the methodology acknowledges opportunity cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
