<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="stakeholder-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Identifies parties, maps them on a 2x2 influence-vs-impact matrix, documents needs and concerns, plans engagement per quadrant. Register stored as YAML in git; diffs become the relationship history.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>stakeholder-management</tag>
      <tag>engagement</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>change-management</tag>
      <tag>risk-mitigation</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Stakeholder Analysis</title>

    <summary>A six-step methodology that identifies all parties affected by or influencing a change initiative, maps them on a 2x2 influence-vs-impact matrix (Manage Closely / Keep Satisfied / Keep Informed / Monitor), documents individual needs, concerns, and communication preferences, plans engagement cadence per quadrant, and stores the register as a YAML file in git so diffs become the relationship history. The register is a living artifact refreshed at minimum quarterly.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Requirements gathered from the wrong people are incomplete or conflict-laden; missing a regulator, works council, or downstream API consumer invalidates downstream artifacts. IIBA BABOK v3 ch. 3 treats stakeholder engagement as a Knowledge Area because the cost of a missing stakeholder compounds across every subsequent BA activity. Requiring an `evidence:` field on every attitude assertion prevents the politeness-bias failure where everyone is classified as "supportive."</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Kickoff of any cross-functional initiative with more than five named parties (sponsor, SMEs, end users, regulator, vendor)</item>
        <item>Migration/replacement projects where end-user resistance is the dominant risk</item>
        <item>Regulated programs (HIPAA, GDPR, SOX, MDR) — the regulator is a mandatory stakeholder</item>
        <item>M&amp;A and reorg work where the political map is unstable; rerun the matrix every 2-4 weeks</item>
        <item>Pre-RFP/vendor-selection work where the buying committee has hidden influencers (security, procurement, legal)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo founder pre-PMF with fewer than three people involved — go directly to customer interviews</item>
        <item>Strictly internal engineering refactors with no business stakeholder change — RACI alone is sufficient</item>
        <item>Public open-source projects with anonymous community contributors — influence/impact axis is meaningless; use governance patterns</item>
        <item>One-off bug fixes or hotfixes — the stakeholder map will be stale before the deploy completes</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="identification">
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include a hidden-stakeholders review step covering: legal, infosec, procurement, works council/union, accessibility, and downstream API consumers. Missing a stakeholder is the dominant real-world failure mode.</statement>
        <rationale>Hidden stakeholders discovered after elicitation begins trigger scope changes, re-validation, and delayed sign-offs; finding them at step 1 costs a single conversation. BABOK v3 ch. 3 lists stakeholder identification as a Knowledge Area, not a preliminary task.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Eight stakeholder categories:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Customer — external beneficiary (end users, buyers, partners).</item>
        <item>End User — direct solution users (employees, customers).</item>
        <item>Sponsor — provides resources and authority (executive, budget owner).</item>
        <item>Domain SME — subject matter expert (process owner, specialist, regulator).</item>
        <item>Implementation SME — technical expert (developer, architect, integrator).</item>
        <item>Tester — validates the solution (QA team, UAT participants).</item>
        <item>Regulator — compliance authority (legal, audit, government body).</item>
        <item>Supplier — external provider (vendor, partner, outsourcer).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="influence-impact-matrix">
      <rule>
        <statement>Map every stakeholder to one of four quadrants and set default engagement cadence by quadrant: Manage Closely (HH) = weekly 1:1, Keep Satisfied (HL) = biweekly summary, Keep Informed (LH) = monthly digest, Monitor (LL) = release-only. Override only with explicit rationale.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholders managed at the wrong cadence either receive information overload (damaging the relationship) or feel ignored (creating resistance); quadrant-driven defaults calibrate engagement without requiring per-stakeholder judgment for every decision.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply the Mitchell-Agle-Wood salience overlay (power × legitimacy × urgency) on top of the matrix for politically sensitive initiatives; flag "definitive" stakeholders (all three) for daily attention.</statement>
        <rationale>The 2x2 matrix collapses multi-dimensional politics into one axis; salience theory adds urgency and legitimacy that explain why some low-title stakeholders have outsized influence.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="needs-concerns-engagement">
      <rule>
        <statement>Require an evidence: field on every attitude assertion (quote, transcript line, ticket link); without evidence, attitude defaults to "unknown," not "0" (neutral).</statement>
        <rationale>Self-reported attitude is unreliable; people say "supportive" in workshops and undermine in private. Evidence-backed attitude claims are actionable; ungrounded attitude claims are noise that produces wrong engagement strategies.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Triangulate self-reported attitude with at least one behavioral signal (meeting attendance, Slack response time, sponsor escalations, ticket comments) before assigning attitude to any high-influence stakeholder.</statement>
        <rationale>High-influence stakeholders whose actual attitude diverges from stated attitude are the most dangerous source of late-stage resistance; early triangulation enables proactive management.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="conflict-resolution">
      <rule>
        <statement>When two stakeholders have conflicting needs, follow this sequence: understand each position (why, not what) → find common ground → identify trade-offs → escalate to sponsor with options → document decision with rationale.</statement>
        <rationale>Conflicts resolved by position-trading ("you get requirement A, I get requirement B") without understanding underlying interests re-emerge during design and testing. Interest-based resolution produces durable agreements.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Conflict resolution techniques:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Facilitated workshop — for groups with multiple conflicting positions.</item>
        <item>One-on-one discussions — for sensitive interpersonal conflicts or political situations.</item>
        <item>Prototype/demo — to clarify misunderstandings caused by abstract requirements.</item>
        <item>Prioritization exercise — to force trade-off choices when all options cannot be delivered.</item>
        <item>Sponsor decision — for conflicts that exceed the BA's authority to resolve.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="git-native-register">
      <rule>
        <statement>Store the stakeholder register as YAML in git (stakeholders/register.yaml); subagents emit patches, never overwrite the register directly. Each transition (added, attitude shift, escalated) is committed with a one-line rationale.</statement>
        <rationale>git log -- stakeholders/ becomes the relationship history; git blame shows who reclassified whom; CODEOWNERS gates sponsor sign-off on attitude changes. A wiki or spreadsheet cannot provide any of these audit capabilities.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Refresh the register quarterly at minimum; set a calendar trigger that opens an issue assigned to the BA. In M&amp;A and reorg contexts, refresh every 2-4 weeks.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholder registers drift in 2-6 weeks in fast-moving organizations; a static register goes stale and becomes wrong, not just old. Automated refresh triggers prevent the register from becoming a liability.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never publish names + attitudes outside the BA and sponsor; treat the register as confidential. PII regulations (GDPR Art. 9) may apply if attitude implies political opinion or health status.</statement>
        <rationale>Attitude records about named individuals are sensitive personal data; public exposure damages relationships and may create legal liability in GDPR-jurisdiction projects.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <example type="good" title="Discovery prompt">
        <note>Constrains to real org chart entries, flags unknown attitudes, and surfaces hidden stakeholders as suggestions rather than entries.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are the stakeholder-discovery agent. Inputs:
1. Org chart snippet (names, titles, reporting lines).
2. Kickoff transcript / charter.
3. Existing register (may be empty).

For each named or implied party, emit STRICT JSON:
{ "id": "S-NN", "name": "...", "role": "...",
  "category": "Customer|EndUser|Sponsor|DomainSME|ImplementationSME|Tester|Regulator|Supplier",
  "influence": "H|M|L", "impact": "H|M|L", "attitude": "+|0|-|unknown",
  "evidence": ["quote or org-chart line"],
  "engagement": "Manage Closely|Keep Satisfied|Keep Informed|Monitor",
  "rationale": "<= 2 sentences" }

Rules: do not invent people. If attitude is not directly evidenced, return "unknown".
Flag potential hidden stakeholders (legal, infosec, works council, procurement,
downstream API consumers) in a separate suggested_to_verify list.]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Engagement-plan prompt">
        <note>Uses quadrant mapping as default override policy.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Given the register below, produce the engagement table.
Quadrant mapping: HH=Manage Closely (weekly 1:1),
HL=Keep Satisfied (biweekly summary), LH=Keep Informed (monthly digest),
LL=Monitor (release notes only). Override only with explicit rationale.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent invents plausible-sounding stakeholders ("VP of Product Excellence") not present in the org chart.</description>
        <reason>Hallucinated stakeholders produce engagement plans with no real recipients; always seed with a real org chart export and reject any name not in the source list unless flagged suggested_to_verify.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent over-classifies all stakeholders as "supportive" (politeness bias).</description>
        <reason>LLMs are trained on polite discourse and default to positive sentiment; use a 4-way enum (+/0/-/unknown) with unknown as the default and require evidence for + or -.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent conflates stakeholder with persona ("As a Busy Manager persona...").</description>
        <reason>A stakeholder is a real named human or role with decision power; a persona is a synthesized archetype for design. Conflating them produces engagement plans targeting archetypes, not real people with authority.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent equates influence with seniority — ranks CFO highest influence by default.</description>
        <reason>Influence flows through indirect networks; the CFO's EA may have more influence on calendar decisions than the CFO. Force the agent to consider gatekeepers, information brokers, and informal leaders, not just org chart level.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent bulk-reclassifies 50 stakeholders in a single run.</description>
        <reason>Bulk reclassification of attitude fields is reputationally toxic if wrong; cap agent actions to 5 stakeholders per run and require human review on the diff.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="human-in-the-loop">
      <rule>
        <statement>Require human approval at three points: adding a new stakeholder, changing attitude from unknown to positive or negative, and escalating a conflict to sponsor. Agent prepares the patch; BA or sponsor approves the merge.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholder relationship decisions have political consequences; automated execution without human sign-off can damage trust, violate confidentiality expectations, and create legal liability.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <list>
        <item>The 2x2 influence/impact matrix flattens multi-dimensional politics — power, urgency, and legitimacy (Mitchell-Agle-Wood salience) are collapsed into one axis and important nuance is lost.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder lists drift fast (2–6 weeks in fast-moving orgs); a static register goes stale and becomes wrong, not just old. README mistake #5 is the dominant real-world failure.</item>
        <item>Hidden stakeholders (works councils, legal, infosec, procurement, downstream consumers of an API) are systematically missed — agents will not invent them unless given org-chart context.</item>
        <item>Self-reported attitude is unreliable — people say "supportive" in workshops and undermine in private. The matrix only works if attitude is triangulated against behaviour.</item>
        <item>LLM hallucinates plausible-sounding personas ("VP of Product Excellence") that do not exist in the target org; outputs must be validated against an actual directory / org chart.</item>
        <item>Cultures vary: in high-context cultures (JP, KR) influence flows through indirect networks the matrix does not represent.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/stakeholder-register.md" purpose="Stakeholder register table with ID, role, category, influence, impact, attitude, engagement columns."/>
      <template path="templates/stakeholder-profile.md" purpose="Individual stakeholder profile with characteristics, needs, concerns, communication preferences, engagement history."/>
      <template path="templates/stakeholder-matrix.py" purpose="Script: validate YAML register and emit Mermaid quadrant chart for influence-vs-impact visualization."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
