<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Spatial Computing Overview Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the 2026 platform-selection decision record. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="cite-2026-data" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every platform score MUST cite a 2025-or-newer source for install base, SDK status, and store policy. Pre-2024 data MUST NOT be used as authoritative.</statement>
      <rationale source="IDC 2025 AR/VR tracker; vendor 2025 SEC filings">Platform landscape changed sharply in 2024-2026 (Vision Pro launch, Android XR announcement, Pico contraction); stale data produces wrong decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="score-on-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each platform candidate MUST be scored 0-5 on install_base, sdk_maturity, audience_fit, content_type_fit, store_constraints. Each score MUST have a one-line evidence string.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — XR decision audits Q4 2025">Single-score "best platform" recommendations cannot be defended later when ROI is challenged.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="primary-plus-fallback" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Recommendation MUST name one primary platform AND at least one fallback (cross-platform target via WebXR or porting plan). Single-platform lock-in MUST include an explicit risk note.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Pico departure Q2 2025">Single-platform launches are vulnerable to vendor pivots; a fallback path is required for risk parity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="content-type-fit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The decision MUST map use-case content type (productivity floating windows / cinematic video / dialogue agent / interactive simulation) to the platform's strength. Mismatches MUST be called out as risks.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple visionOS HIG; Meta Horizon docs">Vision Pro excels at productivity + cinematic; Quest excels at active gaming; HoloLens at enterprise overlay. Forcing the wrong content type onto a platform yields poor UX.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="audience-fit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audience profile (consumer vs prosumer vs enterprise) MUST match platform price point and distribution. Decision record MUST cite expected ARPU + addressable installed base.</statement>
      <rationale source="IDC 2025 segment data">Consumer apps on $3500 Vision Pro miss audience; enterprise XR apps on Quest 3 require MDM provisioning that consumer headsets do not support.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
