<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Success Metrics Definition Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Success Metrics Definition application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-one-north-star" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The spec MUST name exactly one North Star Metric. Two or more North Stars are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Two North Stars = no North Star; the team cannot trade off between them under pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-aarrr-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The 3-5 Primary KPIs MUST collectively cover at least 3 of the AARRR stages. Single-stage KPI sets are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Single-stage coverage hides the funnel; a Retention-only KPI set ignores the leak in Activation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-exact-definition" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every metric MUST carry an exact measurement definition: event name, filter rules, time window, exclusions. "Active users" without definition is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Without exact definitions, teams argue about numbers; with definitions, they argue about strategy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-baseline-and-target" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every metric MUST carry a current baseline value AND a target value with a deadline. Targetless metrics are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">A metric without a target is a thermometer, not a decision tool.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-vanity-vs-actionable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every metric MUST be tagged vanity (look-good, not decision-driving) | actionable (decision-driving). Vanity metrics MUST be flagged on dashboards.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Vanity metrics quietly drive feature choices; explicit tagging exposes the influence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
