<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Feature Discovery Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every Feature Discovery application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-four-source-collection" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Collect feature ideas from ALL four source types before scoring: Customer Research (interviews, tickets, churn, NPS detractors), Usage Analytics (adoption, drop-off, errors), Competitive Analysis (rival features, negative reviews), Market Trends (industry reports, regulatory shifts). Single-source candidate lists are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Single-source discovery creates blind spots; analytics show what, interviews show why, competitors show expectations.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-cap-twenty" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The candidate list MUST be capped at 20 items per discovery cycle. Lists with &gt;20 items are rejected and routed back to collection refinement.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">A list longer than 20 means the collection phase wasn't selective; scoring becomes a distraction not a decision tool.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-kano-typed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every candidate MUST carry a Kano type: Must-have | Performance | Delight | Indifferent. Must-haves block Delighters in the build queue.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Delighters built on shaky Must-haves fail to retain customers; users who cannot log in are not impressed by AI features.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-effort-from-engineering" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Effort estimates MUST come from a named engineering lead (XS/S/M/L/XL). Agent-generated effort estimates are rejected as RICE inputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">RICE divides by Effort; an LLM-guessed denominator silently mis-prioritises the entire backlog.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-rice-with-explicit-confidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every RICE score MUST record Reach (users/quarter), Impact (0.25/0.5/1/2/3), Confidence (50%/80%/100%) and Effort (person-weeks) explicitly. "Confidence inferred from vibe" is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Confidence is the honesty multiplier; opaque confidence inflates scores for features without evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-validate-top-three" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The top 3 RICE-ranked candidates MUST pass a pre-build validation step (fake-door, prototype, Wizard-of-Oz, limited beta, or pre-sales) before engineering commitment.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">RICE scores are estimates; pre-build validation replaces estimates with behavioural evidence before sunk-cost.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
