<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="generative-ui-design Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for generative-ui-design. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Generate 3–5 variants per screen, not 1 — comparison is faster than iteration from a single bad start.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI-generated layouts are often visually generic. Comparing multiple variants simultaneously exposes the design space faster than iterating on one output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always start with a written spec before prompting; vague prompts produce generic output.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">"Generate a dashboard" produces unusable output. "Generate a SaaS analytics dashboard with date-range filter, KPI cards, and a line chart" produces useful starting points.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run axe-cli on any generated prototype before stakeholder review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">No generative UI tool produces accessible keyboard navigation, skip-to-content, or screen-reader-friendly markup by default. Presenting inaccessible UIs as viable designs creates false expectations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat generated code as a sketch, not a PR — always refactor before merging into a real codebase.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generated component names often conflict with existing project components. Generated code references props or methods that may not exist in the actual library version the project uses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Claude Artifacts for agent-loop iteration — it is the only tool where the agent can see and modify output without a human browser session.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Galileo has no public API and exports require a human in a Figma plugin. v0 API is not GA as of 2026. Claude Artifacts is generated inline in the agent response and immediately visible to both agent and human.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document why a variant was rejected — this becomes the signal for better next prompts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Non-deterministic output means the same prompt may yield structurally different results across runs. Rejection reasons make prompt improvements systematic rather than trial-and-error.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
