<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-workflow" title="Generative UI Design Workflow">
  <summary>Tool comparison, five-stage AI design workflow, and quality rules for generative UI output.</summary>

  <section title="Tool Comparison">
    <list>
      <item>Galileo — UI generation, production-ready visual quality, no public API (UI-only)</item>
      <item>Uizard — wireframe-to-design rapid prototypes, project API in beta</item>
      <item>v0 (Vercel) — React + Tailwind + shadcn/ui code output, CLI available</item>
      <item>Claude Artifacts — interactive prototypes, most agent-native path</item>
      <item>Relume — wireframe generation from sitemap, Figma-compatible export</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Workflow Stages">
    <list>
      <item>Ideation — AI generates 3–5 layout variants from a written spec</item>
      <item>Selection — human curates best variant based on design goals</item>
      <item>Refinement — agent + human iterate on the selected variant</item>
      <item>Brand alignment — human verifies against brand guidelines</item>
      <item>Implementation — AI-assisted coding with accessibility audit before handoff</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate 3–5 variants per screen, not 1 — comparison is faster than iteration from a single bad start.</statement>
      <rationale>AI-generated layouts are often visually generic. Comparing multiple variants simultaneously exposes the design space faster than iterating on one output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always start with a written spec before prompting; vague prompts produce generic output.</statement>
      <rationale>"Generate a dashboard" produces unusable output. "Generate a SaaS analytics dashboard with date-range filter, KPI cards, and a line chart" produces useful starting points.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run axe-cli on any generated prototype before stakeholder review.</statement>
      <rationale>No generative UI tool produces accessible keyboard navigation, skip-to-content, or screen-reader-friendly markup by default. Presenting inaccessible UIs as viable designs creates false expectations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat generated code as a sketch, not a PR — always refactor before merging into a real codebase.</statement>
      <rationale>Generated component names often conflict with existing project components. Generated code references props or methods that may not exist in the actual library version the project uses.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using v0 output when the project does not use Tailwind + shadcn/ui.</description>
      <reason>v0 generates Tailwind + shadcn/ui exclusively. If the project uses a different stack, the generated code requires full rewrite of component imports and styling.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-deploying generated UI code to production without designer and developer review.</description>
      <reason>Generated code is prototype-grade. It consistently misses accessibility requirements, may conflict with existing component naming, and uses non-deterministic output that cannot be relied upon for production.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
