<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="generative-ui-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for generative-ui-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Generated layouts are often visually safe/generic.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>AI tools optimize for "looks like a UI" rather than solving the specific design problem. Color and typography decisions are shallow; no understanding of visual hierarchy principles beyond surface patterns.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Generated React/HTML code rarely matches the project's actual component library.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Galileo and Uizard outputs are not directly Figma-compatible; import requires manual layer cleanup. v0 generates Tailwind + shadcn/ui exclusively — breaks if the project uses a different stack.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Claude Artifacts previews are sandboxed and cannot test real APIs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Claude Artifacts previews have no persistent state and cannot connect to real APIs in the preview. No fetch(), no localStorage, no external assets. Generated code using these will appear broken in preview.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Relying on reproducibility of generative tools.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The same prompt across two runs may yield structurally different components. Do not treat any single generative output as a canonical reference.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Using v0 output when the project does not use Tailwind + shadcn/ui.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>v0 generates Tailwind + shadcn/ui exclusively. If the project uses a different stack, the generated code requires full rewrite of component imports and styling.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-deploying generated UI code to production without designer and developer review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generated code is prototype-grade. It consistently misses accessibility requirements, may conflict with existing component naming, and uses non-deterministic output that cannot be relied upon for production.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
