<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Freelancer Contract Clauses — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every freelancer contract using this pack must enforce. These are HARD rules — sales urgency cannot override them.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>IP-ON-PAYMENT: Intellectual property assignment to the client MUST be conditioned on full payment of invoices related to the work product; until paid, the freelancer retains all rights and may revoke usage license on default.</statement>
      <rationale source="Default copyright doctrine (Berne Convention + 17 USC §201) + Freelancers Union collection-rate analyses">IP-on-signature gives the client every reason to delay payment; IP-on-payment converts the deliverable into payable collateral.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>LATE-FEE + STOP-WORK: Invoices unpaid past net-N (default 14) accrue an explicit late fee (default 1.5%/month, jurisdiction-capped) AND trigger automatic stop-work after N+7 days; resumption requires payment of all outstanding balances.</statement>
      <rationale source="UCC §1-309 + general commercial-payment doctrine + freelancer collection data">Soft "we'll continue while we figure out the invoice" is the #1 path to unpaid work; the automatic-stop clause is the single most-collected term in practice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>KILL FEE: Client-initiated termination before completion triggers a kill fee equal to the lesser of (remaining-deliverable-value × 30%) and (capped one month of engagement value); the kill fee is invoiced within 7 days of termination.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry kill-fee norm (Editorial Freelancers Association rate card; AIGA contract template)">Without an explicit kill fee, freelancers absorb the full opportunity cost of a cancellation; the cap keeps the clause palatable to enterprise reviewers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>MUTUAL NDA: Confidentiality runs BOTH ways and is scoped to the engagement (not "all information ever discussed"); duration is bounded (default 2 years post-termination); residual-knowledge carve-out is included.</statement>
      <rationale source="Trade-secret doctrine (DTSA 2016 + EU Directive 2016/943) + portfolio-rights ethics">One-way NDAs are routine in client templates and routinely catastrophic for the freelancer's right to portfolio + reference work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>JURISDICTION: Default governing law = freelancer's country/state; disputes resolved by arbitration administered in freelancer's jurisdiction (e.g., LCIA, AAA, local equivalent), with a small-claims carve-out for sub-$5k disputes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Hague Choice-of-Court Convention + freelancer-collection cost analyses">Litigating in a foreign jurisdiction costs more than most engagements are worth; the home-jurisdiction default reverses the burden of inertia.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Anchored clause excerpts">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
2. Intellectual Property
2.1 All deliverables remain the sole property of [Freelancer] until all related invoices are paid in full.
2.2 Upon full payment, [Freelancer] assigns to Client all right, title, and interest in the deliverables.
3. Payment & Late Fees
3.1 Invoices are due net-14 from receipt.
3.2 Past-due balances accrue 1.5% per month (or maximum allowed by law).
3.3 If any invoice remains unpaid 7 days past due, [Freelancer] shall pause all work until cured.
4. Termination
4.1 Either party may terminate for convenience on 7 days' notice.
4.2 If Client terminates, a kill fee of 30% of the unbilled engagement value (capped at one month) is due within 7 days.
5. Confidentiality (Mutual)
5.1 Each party agrees to hold Confidential Information of the other in confidence for 2 years post-termination, excluding residual knowledge and information that becomes public through no breach.
6. Governing Law & Disputes
6.1 This Agreement is governed by the laws of [Freelancer's State/Country].
6.2 Disputes shall be resolved by arbitration in [Freelancer's City] under [chosen rules], except small-claims matters under $5k may proceed in [Freelancer's local court].
]]></code>
      <note>Each clause is the lean form of the corresponding rule; together they cover the five most common ways a freelancer engagement goes sideways.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Un-anchored trust-me agreement">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"I will deliver the website. You will pay $12,000. Net-30 from acceptance."
]]></code>
      <note>No IP gate, no late-fee teeth, no kill fee, no NDA, no jurisdiction. Every concession is yours to make under pressure.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="../../pm/solo-change-order-mini-contract/" />
    <link path="../late-invoice-dunning-sequence/" />
  </see-also>
</text>
