<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-phases" title="SDD Phase Sequence">
  <summary>Complete SDD phase sequence CONSTITUTION → SPEC → DESIGN → TEST-PLAN → IMPL-PLAN → TASKS → EXECUTE → REVIEW → DONE, with artifacts, confidence thresholds, and transition gates for each phase.</summary>

  <section title="Phase Sequence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow the phase order: CONSTITUTION → SPEC → DESIGN → TEST-PLAN → IMPL-PLAN → TASKS → EXECUTE → REVIEW → DONE. Never skip TEST-PLAN before IMPL-PLAN — the test plan shapes the task breakdown. Never begin EXECUTE before IMPL-PLAN reaches 95%+ confidence.</statement>
      <rationale>Each phase is the input to the next. Skipping TEST-PLAN means tasks cannot be written as testable by design; the implementation plan is then disconnected from verification. The 95%+ confidence gate before EXECUTE prevents starting code that will require rework because the plan is incomplete.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>CONSTITUTION: tech stack, coding standards, architecture principles, quality thresholds. Artifact: constitution.md</item>
      <item>SPEC: WHAT to build — functional requirements (FR-X), acceptance criteria, non-functional requirements, MVP scope. Artifact: spec.md</item>
      <item>DESIGN: HOW to build — architecture decisions (AD-X), file structure, API contracts, data models. Artifact: design.md</item>
      <item>TEST-PLAN: HOW to verify — test case per AC, test type, edge cases, test infrastructure. Artifact: test-plan.md</item>
      <item>IMPL-PLAN: task breakdown with dependencies, execution waves, quality gates, token estimates. Artifact: implementation-plan.md</item>
      <item>TASKS: TASK-XXX-*.md files in todo/ → in-progress/ → done/ lifecycle</item>
      <item>EXECUTE: implement code against spec and design; run quality gates after each task</item>
      <item>REVIEW: independent reviewers in parallel; merge findings; fix; re-test; max 2 review cycles</item>
      <item>DONE: all tests green, all review findings resolved, feature delivered</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Confidence Thresholds">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before transitioning between phases, validate readiness using confidence thresholds. If confidence is below threshold, identify what is missing and resolve it before proceeding. Never proceed on optimism — a missing AC discovered during implementation costs far more than spending 30 minutes on spec clarification.</statement>
      <rationale>Confidence thresholds are circuit breakers that prevent cascading rework. Low-confidence transitions create technical debt at the spec and design level that compounds through every downstream phase. The thresholds are asymmetric by design: earlier phases (idea → spec) can proceed at 70% because the cost of rework is low; later phases (impl-plan → execute) require 95%+ because implementation rework is expensive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Idea → Spec: 70%+ (problem validation evidence exists)</item>
      <item>Spec → Design: 90%+ (all FR-X defined with AC, MVP scope clear)</item>
      <item>Design → Test Plan: 90%+ (architecture clear, API contracts specified)</item>
      <item>Test Plan → Impl Plan: 90%+ (every AC has at least one test case)</item>
      <item>Impl Plan → Execute: 95%+ (task dependencies resolved, no blocking open questions)</item>
      <item>Execute → Review: 100% (all tasks complete, code committed)</item>
      <item>Review → Done: 100% (all findings fixed, all tests green)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Spec Phase Gates">
    <rule>
      <statement>A spec is complete when: all FR-X are defined with Given/When/Then acceptance criteria, the MVP scope is explicit (in-scope list and out-of-scope list), non-functional requirements are documented, and a responsible human or team has approved. An LLM cannot self-approve a spec — approval requires a human confirming the requirements match the intent.</statement>
      <rationale>Specs approved without human sign-off drift from real intent. LLMs fill ambiguity with plausible assumptions; only the human who knows the business context can confirm the spec captures the right requirements. The FR/AC structure ensures "done" is objective — tests can verify ACs mechanically.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Design Phase Gates">
    <rule>
      <statement>A design is complete when: every architecture decision (AD-X) is documented with rationale and alternatives, the file structure is defined, all API contracts are specified (not just described), dependencies are identified, and the design doc status is APPROVED. A design doc in DRAFT or IN-REVIEW state cannot proceed to TEST-PLAN.</statement>
      <rationale>Proceeding to test-plan with an unapproved design means writing tests against an implementation approach that reviewers may reject. The test plan then needs to be rewritten when the design changes. Waiting for design approval is a small delay that prevents a large rework cycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Test Plan Phase Gates">
    <rule>
      <statement>A test plan is complete when: every AC has at least one test case, each test case is classified (unit / integration / e2e), edge cases and error scenarios are listed, and test infrastructure requirements (fixtures, mocks, test DB) are documented. Write the test plan before the implementation plan — test requirements shape the task breakdown.</statement>
      <rationale>Tests written before implementation-plan force each task to be "testable by design." Without this ordering, tasks are written without considering what test infrastructure they need, leading to test retrofitting after implementation — the most expensive form of testing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Review Phase">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run at least one independent reviewer (fresh context, reads spec+design+test-plan+code) before marking DONE. If multiple review tools are available (Claude subagent, Codex CLI, Kiro), run them in parallel and merge findings. A reviewer that was involved in implementation is not independent — use a fresh context or a different model.</statement>
      <rationale>The executor has implementation bias: they see what they intended to write, not what they actually wrote. An independent reviewer with fresh context catches assumptions that became invisible during implementation. Multiple models catch different issues — diversity of perspective is the primary value of running reviewers in parallel.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
