<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-sdd-levels" title="SDD Levels and 15-Minute Waterfall">
  <summary>Three SDD implementation levels (Spec-First, Spec-Anchored, Spec-as-Source), the 15-minute waterfall variant for medium tasks, and the decision rule for selecting which level to apply.</summary>

  <section title="Three SDD Levels">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose the SDD level based on the scope and lifecycle of the work. Level 1 (Spec-First) is the minimum viable SDD practice — write spec, then code. Level 2 (Spec-Anchored) keeps the spec alive after implementation. Level 3 (Spec-as-Source) makes the spec the only human-edited artifact and generates code from it.</statement>
      <rationale>Not every project justifies the full Spec-as-Source investment. Level 1 captures 80% of the anti-hallucination benefit with minimal overhead. Level 2 adds maintenance value for long-lived features. Level 3 is viable only when the spec format is machine-readable and tooling can reliably generate valid code from it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Level 1 — Spec-First: human writes spec, AI generates code, human reviews. Spec is not maintained after delivery.</item>
      <item>Level 2 — Spec-Anchored: spec evolves with the codebase across iterations. Code changes require spec updates first.</item>
      <item>Level 3 — Spec-as-Source: spec is the only human-edited artifact. Humans edit spec; tooling generates and validates code.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Level Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Level 1 for one-off features where the spec is written to guide a single implementation session. Use Level 2 for production features that will evolve over multiple iterations. Use Level 3 only when: the spec format is machine-readable (OpenAPI, GraphQL SDL, Protobuf), generation tooling is in place, and contract tests enforce alignment.</statement>
      <rationale>Level 3 requires significant tooling investment. Applying it to a markdown-format spec with no generation tooling creates a spec that quickly drifts from the implementation, making the spec worse than useless — it actively misleads. The level selection rule prevents this by gating Level 3 on concrete tooling prerequisites.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="When to Use Full SDD vs Ad-Hoc">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use full SDD for: multi-day features, cross-module coordination, AI-assisted development where reducing hallucinations is critical, production systems requiring audit trail, team collaboration requiring shared understanding. Skip full SDD and implement directly for: tasks under 2 hours with a clear path, bug fixes with known root cause, exploratory prototypes.</statement>
      <rationale>SDD overhead (spec + design + test-plan) is justified when the cost of building the wrong thing or building it poorly exceeds the planning cost. For a 2-hour bug fix, the planning overhead would dwarf the implementation. For a 2-week feature, the same planning prevents weeks of rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="15-Minute Waterfall">
    <rule>
      <statement>For medium tasks (too complex for direct implementation, too small for full SDD), use the 15-minute waterfall: 5 minutes writing a quick spec (problem, requirements, acceptance criteria), 5 minutes sketching the design (key decisions, files to change), 5 minutes listing tasks (max 5-7). Then execute with AI assistance.</statement>
      <rationale>The 15-minute waterfall captures the core anti-hallucination benefit of SDD at minimal cost. Even a rough spec with 3 requirements and 2 ACs grounds LLM code generation far more than an ad-hoc prompt. The time cap prevents over-planning for tasks that do not warrant it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/quick-spec.md">15-minute waterfall quick spec template</reference>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Quick Spec: Add email validation to signup form

## Problem (2 min)
Signup form accepts malformed emails. Users receive no error until after server-side validation fails.

## Requirements (5 min)
- R1: Validate email format on blur (not on submit)
- R2: Show inline error below field when invalid
- R3: Submit button disabled until email is valid

## Design Sketch (5 min)
- Files: SignupForm.tsx (modify), useEmailValidation.ts (create)
- Approach: custom hook with RFC 5322 regex, debounced validation

## Tasks (3 min)
1. [ ] Create useEmailValidation hook with regex + debounce
2. [ ] Wire hook into SignupForm email field
3. [ ] Add inline error component below email field

## Done When
- Entering "not-an-email" shows inline error
- Entering "user@example.com" clears error
- Submit button disabled while error is visible
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Spec as Anti-Hallucination Anchor">
    <rule>
      <statement>When using LLMs for code generation, always prepend the spec (or relevant sections) as context before the implementation prompt. Explicit requirements, structured AC format, and constraint documentation each reduce the surface area for hallucination. If the LLM generates something that contradicts the spec, the spec wins — update the code, not the spec.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs hallucinate when context is insufficient or ambiguous. A spec provides the structured constraints that narrow the generation space. The "spec wins" rule is critical: if code is auto-updated to match LLM output that contradicts the spec, the spec becomes a lie and loses all value as a contract.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
