<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="stakeholder-communication">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>communicator</domain>
    <summary>Five dialogue modes for structured stakeholder engagement with Power/Interest grid for communication strategy and difficult stakeholder type handling.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>stakeholder-management</tag>
      <tag>requirements-gathering</tag>
      <tag>dialogue-modes</tag>
      <tag>facilitation</tag>
      <tag>validation</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Stakeholder Communication</title>
    <summary>Stakeholder communication selects a dialogue mode before any conversation: Interview (requirements gathering), Brainstorm (option generation), Clarification (resolving ambiguity), Validation (confirming understanding), or Socratic (probing assumptions). Selecting the wrong mode — e.g., using Socratic questions during a validation session — produces incoherent conversations and erodes trust. Stakeholder mapping by power/interest determines communication frequency and channel per quadrant.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Different stakeholders have different communication needs: a high-power/low-interest executive needs a 2-minute summary; a high-interest subject-matter expert needs detailed clarification sessions. Using the wrong approach leads to missed requirements, resistance, and wasted meetings. Validation summaries sent within 24 hours of a meeting prevent silent requirement drift — the most expensive failure mode in any project.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Preparing interview guides for discovery sessions (requirements gathering, user research, product feedback)</item>
        <item>Mapping stakeholders by power/interest before a project kickoff</item>
        <item>Drafting post-meeting validation summaries that stakeholders must confirm before work proceeds</item>
        <item>Generating Socratic question sequences to probe vague requirements like "make it faster" or "improve UX"</item>
        <item>Handling difficult stakeholder types (silent, dominant, negative, absent, changing)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Replacing live dialogue — agent-generated questions are preparation aids, not substitutes for real conversations</item>
        <item>Situations with high political sensitivity where each word carries organizational weight beyond the stated content</item>
        <item>Legal or contractual negotiations requiring specific protocol</item>
        <item>Power/Interest grid placement without a human who knows the organizational context — job titles alone misplace politically influential stakeholders</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="dialogue-modes-overview">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Choose the dialogue mode before generating any questions. State the mode to the stakeholder at the start so they know what kind of input you need.</statement>
        <rationale>Each mode has a distinct question structure and stakeholder role. Surprise mode-switching mid-session breaks rapport and produces unfocused answers.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="mode-1-interview">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use the interview protocol sequence: Context → Problem → Impact → Goal → Constraints → Priority. Ask one question at a time. Open questions first, probing to dig deeper.</statement>
        <rationale>The sequence builds from shared context to the critical priority. Jumping to priority first produces rankings without understanding.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Open: "Tell me about your current workflow" — explore</item>
        <item>Probing: "Why is that important?" — dig deeper</item>
        <item>Clarifying: "What do you mean by X?" — remove ambiguity</item>
        <item>Hypothetical: "What if you could do Y?" — envision</item>
        <item>Summary: "So you're saying...?" — confirm</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="mode-2-brainstorm">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run three phases in order: Diverge (generate, no judgment) → Cluster (group similar ideas) → Converge (vote, prioritize). Never evaluate during the diverge phase.</statement>
        <rationale>Premature evaluation kills ideation. Mixing generation and evaluation in one pass produces fewer and less creative ideas.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Diverge prompts: "What else could we try?", "What would the opposite approach be?", "What would a competitor do?"</item>
        <item>Cluster: group semantically similar ideas, name each cluster</item>
        <item>Converge: dot voting (3-5 dots per person), impact/effort scoring</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="mode-3-clarification">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>When a stakeholder uses vague terms (fast, easy, better, all, always, never), ask a multiple-choice clarification: "When you say X, do you mean A, B, or something else?" — not an open-ended restatement.</statement>
        <rationale>Open restatements ("what do you mean?") produce more vague answers. Multiple-choice options force the stakeholder to commit to an interpretation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Definition: "What do you mean by 'user-friendly'?"</item>
        <item>Boundary: "What's included? What's excluded?"</item>
        <item>Example: "Can you give me a specific example?"</item>
        <item>Metric: "How would we measure success?"</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="mode-4-validation">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Send a written validation summary within 24 hours of a meeting. Do not silently resolve ambiguities with a default interpretation — flag them explicitly and request confirmation.</statement>
        <rationale>Memory fades within 24 hours. Silently resolving ambiguities produces a divergence between what was said and what was built, discovered only at delivery.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="mode-5-socratic">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use Socratic questioning to surface hidden assumptions and help stakeholders think through requirements they have not fully formed. Do not use this mode in sequence without human adaptation — verbatim Socratic chains in live conversation feel interrogative.</statement>
        <rationale>Socratic questioning uncovers the real need behind a surface request. Without it, "we need real-time sync" becomes a hard technical requirement when 5-minute polling would suffice.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Socratic dialogue collapsing a hard requirement to a simpler solution">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Stakeholder: "We need real-time sync."
You: "What do you mean by 'real-time'?" (Clarifying)
S: "Instant updates when data changes."
You: "What's driving that requirement?" (Assumption)
S: "Users complain about stale data."
You: "How stale? Minutes? Hours?" (Evidence)
S: "Actually... a few minutes would be fine."
You: "What would happen if we sync every 5 minutes?" (Implication)
S: "That could work, and it's much simpler."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="power-interest-grid">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Map each stakeholder to a quadrant: High Power + High Interest = Manage Closely (weekly 1-on-1s, involve in decisions); High Power + Low Interest = Keep Satisfied (bi-weekly summary, escalate issues); Low Power + High Interest = Keep Informed (monthly status); Low Power + Low Interest = Monitor (available on request).</statement>
        <rationale>Under-communicating with high-power stakeholders creates surprises and vetoes. Over-communicating with low-interest stakeholders wastes their time and reduces your credibility.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not assign quadrant positions from job titles alone. Political influence often does not track seniority — seek organizational context from a human before placing anyone.</statement>
        <rationale>An informal influencer with a mid-level title placed in "Monitor" who then vetoes the project is the most expensive stakeholder management failure.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="difficult-stakeholder-types">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Identify the stakeholder type before the session and select the facilitation response that matches. Do not use the same approach for all stakeholder types.</statement>
        <rationale>Each type represents a different underlying dynamic. A "Silent" stakeholder needs direct questions and written async input; using the same open-group format produces the same silence.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Silent (won't share): direct questions addressed by name, written async input before the meeting</item>
        <item>Dominant (talks over others): use brainwriting or round robin to enforce equal turn-taking</item>
        <item>Negative (shoots down ideas): "Yes, and..." facilitation rule; Reverse Brainstorm to channel criticism productively</item>
        <item>Absent (misses meetings): async input requests, written summary with confirmation required</item>
        <item>Changing (shifts requirements): require written confirmation per requirement; maintain a dated change log</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Accepting verbal agreement from a "Changing" stakeholder without a written confirmation.</description>
        <reason>Verbal agreements are repudiated under project pressure. A written confirmation email creates a dated record that prevents requirement drift from becoming a dispute.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Always select the dialogue mode before generating questions — Interview questions and Socratic questions have fundamentally different structures and mixing them produces incoherent sessions</item>
        <item>Validation summaries must be sent within 24 hours of a meeting while the stakeholder's memory is fresh; an agent can draft immediately post-session but a human should review before sending</item>
        <item>Clarification questions for vague terms ("real-time", "user-friendly", "scalable") must offer interpretations A/B/C rather than open-ended restatement — agents should generate multiple-choice clarifications, not just "what do you mean?"</item>
        <item>For "Changing" stakeholder type, log every requirement change with a timestamp and the stakeholder's name in the requirement capture card — agent-generated logs are admissible as a paper trail</item>
        <item>Post-session, flag ambiguities explicitly in the validation summary — do not silently resolve them with a default interpretation</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-integration-guidelines">
      <p>An agent supports stakeholder communication in the preparation and documentation phases. Pre-session: the agent receives stakeholder profile (role, known interests, concerns, dialogue mode needed) and generates a structured interview guide or brainstorm facilitation plan. Post-session: the agent receives a transcript or notes and produces a structured validation summary (requirements captured, ambiguities flagged, next steps) for stakeholder sign-off. The agent can also generate Socratic question chains from a vague requirement to help the human probe deeper in a live conversation.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Agents generating interview guides default to generic questions ("What are your goals?") unless the stakeholder role and project context are provided in specific detail.</statement>
        <rationale>The five dialogue modes require selection based on relationship context and stakeholder personality — agents recommend modes based on situation parameters alone, which may be incomplete.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Transcription-based requirement extraction fails when multiple stakeholders talk over each other or use domain jargon; human annotation of key exchanges improves accuracy significantly.</statement>
        <rationale>Validation summaries drafted by agents may paraphrase requirements inaccurately if the source transcript is ambiguous; stakeholder confirmation of the summary is mandatory before proceeding.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Socratic question chains must not be used in sequence without human adaptation — using them verbatim in a live conversation feels interrogative and damages rapport.</statement>
        <rationale>Brainstorm facilitation prompts work well as preparation but live facilitation requires real-time adaptation that agents cannot provide.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Human checkpoint required before sending any validation summary — the agent may misparaphrase a nuanced requirement, and stakeholder sign-off on a wrong summary creates downstream rework.</statement>
        <rationale>Power/Interest grid assignments must be reviewed by a human with organizational context; an agent using only job titles will misplace politically influential stakeholders who have informal power.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/meeting-prep.md" purpose="Stakeholder meeting prep card with mode selection and key questions"/>
      <template path="templates/requirement-capture.md" purpose="Requirement capture card with validation status"/>
      <template path="templates/validation-email.md" purpose="Post-meeting validation email template"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-interview-guide.txt" purpose="Prompt for generating a stakeholder interview guide"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-socratic-chain.txt" purpose="Prompt for generating a Socratic question chain from a vague requirement"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/learning/library/stakeholder-engagement-plan-6090"/>
      <link href="https://hbr.org/topic/subject/stakeholder-management"/>
      <link href="https://www.mindtools.com/pages/article/newPPM_07.htm"/>
      <ref slug="negotiation"/>
      <ref slug="selling-ideas"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
