<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Risk Assessment Framework">
  <summary>Five risk categories, probability x impact scoring, response strategies, and review cadence rules.</summary>

  <section title="Risk Categories">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enumerate at least 3 risks per category across all 5 categories: market, product, team, financial, operational.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents over-produce market and product risks (well-represented in training data) and under-produce financial, legal, and vendor risks. A minimum quota per category enforces coverage breadth.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Market Risks">
      <list>
        <item>Demand — no one wants it (market too small, poor timing)</item>
        <item>Competition — others win (incumbent copies, well-funded rival)</item>
        <item>Pricing — can't make money (commoditization, price war)</item>
        <item>Trend — market shifts (technology obsolescence)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Product Risks">
      <list>
        <item>Technical — can't build it (complexity, dependencies)</item>
        <item>Usability — users can't use it (poor UX, learning curve)</item>
        <item>Value — doesn't solve problem (feature gaps, wrong solution)</item>
        <item>Quality — doesn't work well (bugs, performance issues)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Team Risks">
      <list>
        <item>Skills — lack capabilities (missing expertise)</item>
        <item>Capacity — not enough bandwidth (founder burnout, solo limits)</item>
        <item>Alignment — different goals (co-founder conflict)</item>
        <item>Dependency — key person risk (single point of failure)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Financial Risks">
      <list>
        <item>Runway — running out of money (cash burn too high)</item>
        <item>Revenue — can't generate income (monetization fails)</item>
        <item>Costs — expenses too high (infrastructure, CAC)</item>
        <item>External — economic downturn (recession, funding winter)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Operational Risks">
      <list>
        <item>Vendor — dependency fails (API discontinued, pricing change)</item>
        <item>Legal — compliance issues (GDPR, copyright, licensing)</item>
        <item>Security — data breach (hack, data loss)</item>
        <item>Scale — can't handle growth (infrastructure breaks)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring and Response">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each risk as Probability x Impact where H=3, M=2, L=1. Use scores for relative ranking only — not absolute probability. Cap the active risk register at 10 risks; move everything below score 4 to an Accepted archive section.</statement>
      <rationale>H/M/L scoring is useful for forcing triage, not for computing expected loss. Absolute probabilities require FAIR methodology (quantitative). Capping at 10 prevents the register from becoming a comprehensive but unactionable list.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>For each high-priority risk (score 6+), define: one concrete response strategy (Avoid/Mitigate/Transfer/Accept), one specific trigger metric, one named owner, and one measurable action. Reject "monitor + diversify" or "stay agile" as mitigation.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic mitigations are never executed. A trigger metric forces the team to observe a leading indicator; a named owner prevents shared-responsibility diffusion.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Response Strategies">
      <list>
        <item>Avoid — eliminate the risk entirely (high prob, high impact)</item>
        <item>Mitigate — reduce probability or impact (medium risks)</item>
        <item>Transfer — shift to someone else (insurance, contracts)</item>
        <item>Accept — live with it (low risks; move to archive)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <rule>
      <statement>Review cadence: top 3 risks weekly, full risk register monthly, deep review with external perspective quarterly.</statement>
      <rationale>A 6-month-old risk register reflects a company that no longer exists. Monthly reviews prevent static drift; quarterly outside-view reviews counteract optimism bias that founders apply to their own assessments.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pre-Mortem">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a pre-mortem before every major launch: assume the project failed 12 months from today, write a 500-word post-mortem, then convert each failure mode into a risk row.</statement>
      <rationale>Pre-mortems are the highest-leverage risk identification artifact. They surface omissions that a forward-looking risk review misses because they require assuming failure is already a fact, bypassing optimism bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
