<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="risk-assessment Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for risk-assessment as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Too many risks in the register — 30+ active items.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Focus on the top 5-10. Everything below score 4 goes to an Accepted archive; it is still tracked but not in the active review table.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>No contingency plans for high-priority risks.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every risk with score 6+ needs a contingency plan with trigger, response, resources, and owner. A risk without a plan is just documentation of a known failure mode.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Optimism bias without outside-view reviewer.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Founders rate their own product and team risks too low. An outside reviewer quarterly is the minimum check on this bias.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Probability theater: H/M/L scoring is anchored on gut feel; absolute probabilities are wrong by an order of magnitude.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use it for relative ranking only. Absolute probabilities require FAIR methodology (quantitative loss modeling).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Black-swan blindness: the framework over-weights known categories (market/product/team/financial/operational). Tail risks (founder health, geopolitics, model regulation) get dropped.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Explicitly add a "tail risks" section or use the pre-mortem pass to surface these omissions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Mitigation inflation: every risk gets a generic "monitor + diversify" plan that nobody executes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require an action verb + owner + measurable trigger. Ban "monitor", "diversify", and "stay agile" as sole mitigations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Static drift: risk registers age fast — a 6-month-old register reflects a company that no longer exists.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Monthly reviews are mandatory. Keep monthly snapshots in git; the delta is the actual signal.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>No ROI on mitigation: cost of mitigation rarely tracked vs. expected loss; teams over-spend on low-EV risks (compliance) and under-spend on high-EV ones (concentration in one channel).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If a mitigation costs more than prob x impact in dollars, accept the risk instead.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs assign H/M/L confidently with no basis. Ungrounded probability scores inflate register quality perception.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force the agent to cite a source or comparable case for any score. Reject rows where the probability is not grounded in evidence or a base rate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Category bias: agents over-produce market and product risks and under-produce financial, legal, and vendor risks.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Enforce a quota: at least 2 risks per category. Reject submissions missing financial or operational rows.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Recency bias from web search: researcher agents will pull last week's headlines and over-weight them.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cross-check against historical base rates. A single recent event does not change the underlying probability distribution.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Optimism leak from system prompts: if the brief is enthusiastic ("groundbreaking platform"), the agent inherits the tone and scores risks lower.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use a neutral, redacted brief for the risk pass, or flip the agent into adversarial role explicitly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Mitigation handwaving: agents default to "improve monitoring" / "diversify" / "stay agile" — banned phrases.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require an action verb + owner + measurable trigger. Reject any mitigation that does not name a specific action and a specific person.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Risk register drift on re-runs: re-running the enumeration agent yields a different ID set every time.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use stable hashes (slug of risk statement) instead of sequential IDs, or have the agent diff-merge instead of regenerate, to preserve register continuity across runs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>No human checkpoint on "Avoid" decisions. "Avoid" means killing a feature or market.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Never let an agent autonomously execute an Avoid response. Hard human-in-the-loop gate required. Log the decision and the reasoning.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Confidentiality leak: risk statements often contain customer names, vendor terms, or unlaunched plans.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run the scrubber agent before any external sharing or before piping into a 3rd-party SaaS.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent can't run the pre-mortem alone. Pre-mortems need divergent perspectives — solo agent runs collapse to one viewpoint.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use 3+ agents with different system prompts (skeptic, customer, competitor) and consolidate. A single-agent pre-mortem produces a list skewed by the single prompt's optimism level.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
