<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-campaign-setup" title="LinkedIn Ads Campaign Setup and Targeting">
  <summary>Objective selection, targeting strategies (ICP, ABM, retargeting), ad formats, and audience sizing requirements for LinkedIn campaigns.</summary>

  <section title="Campaign Objectives">
    <list>
      <item>Brand Awareness — top of funnel, impressions</item>
      <item>Website Visits — traffic, clicks</item>
      <item>Engagement — reactions and comments on content</item>
      <item>Video Views — video content views</item>
      <item>Lead Generation — native lead gen forms</item>
      <item>Website Conversions — signups, demo requests, purchases</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to Lead Generation or Website Conversions for B2B campaigns; use Brand Awareness only when ICP audience size exceeds 50,000.</statement>
      <rationale>B2B budget is too expensive for pure awareness goals below $1k LTV. Conversion-optimized objectives produce measurable pipeline outcomes from day one.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Targeting Strategies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build audiences in three layers — ABM list (named accounts) + ICP (title + size + industry) + similar audience expansion — run as separate campaigns, not one targeting blob.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing audiences in a single campaign prevents performance diagnosis. A separate campaign per layer reveals which audience converts at what CPL and lets you scale or cut independently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Job Title: exact titles or title functions — primary B2B signal</item>
      <item>Job Seniority: entry to C-level</item>
      <item>Company Size: 1-10 to 10,000+</item>
      <item>Company Name: specific accounts for ABM (upload CSV)</item>
      <item>Industry: 140+ categories</item>
      <item>Skills: professional skills</item>
      <item>Groups: LinkedIn groups membership</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Minimum audience size for conversion campaigns: 20,000. Minimum for awareness: 50,000. Below 20,000, learning never converges and CPL spikes.</statement>
      <rationale>LinkedIn's optimizer needs a large enough pool to find efficient buyers. Narrow audiences cause excessive frequency, high CPMs, and no statistical learning signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Ad Formats">
    <list>
      <item>Single Image: 1200x627 — standard promotion, most common</item>
      <item>Carousel: 3-10 cards — multiple products or features</item>
      <item>Video: 3-30 seconds — storytelling, demos</item>
      <item>Text Ads: text only — low-budget awareness</item>
      <item>Message Ads: Sponsored InMail — direct outreach</item>
      <item>Lead Gen Forms: native forms pre-filled with LinkedIn data</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Lead Gen Forms in parallel with Website Conversions; LGF has higher volume but lower intent — track both to revenue, not just CPL.</statement>
      <rationale>Lead Gen Forms convert at higher rates due to pre-filled fields, but leads show lower purchase intent than those who visited the landing page. Both signals are needed to understand pipeline quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
