<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-creative-bidding" title="LinkedIn Ad Creative, Bidding, and Optimization">
  <summary>B2B ad copy formula, budget expectations, bidding strategy progression, optimization metrics, and creative refresh cadence.</summary>

  <section title="B2B Ad Copy Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure LinkedIn ad copy as: intro (problem or question for the role), headline (solution or value prop), CTA (clear action); never use generic copy that could target any professional.</statement>
      <rationale>LinkedIn CPCs of $5-15 only justify budget when the copy speaks precisely to the ICP's role-specific problem. Generic copy produces low CTR (under 0.3%) and wastes the targeting advantage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Intro text: 150 chars shown — hook with role-specific problem or question</item>
      <item>Headline: 70 chars — clear value proposition</item>
      <item>Description: 100 chars — supporting detail or proof point</item>
      <item>CTA options: Learn More, Download, Sign Up, Request Demo</item>
      <item>Image: 1200x627, professional quality</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Budget and Cost Expectations">
    <list>
      <item>CPM: $30-80 typical range</item>
      <item>CPC: $5-15 typical range</item>
      <item>Cost per lead (LGF): $30-100+</item>
      <item>Minimum daily budget: $50</item>
      <item>Minimum test budget: $2,000-5,000 (enough data for optimization)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not run LinkedIn campaigns with a daily budget under $50; the optimizer cannot exit the learning phase and burns budget on noise.</statement>
      <rationale>LinkedIn's algorithm requires a minimum number of daily actions (clicks or leads) to optimize. Below $50/day, the optimizer never achieves statistical significance within a reasonable window.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Bidding Progression">
    <rule>
      <statement>Bid manually (CPC) for the first 14 days of any new campaign until 50+ form fills accumulate; then switch to Maximum Delivery for the optimizer to use the data.</statement>
      <rationale>Maximum Delivery needs conversion history to optimize efficiently. Without data, it makes random bidding decisions that waste the first weeks of spend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Weeks 1-2: Manual CPC — full bid control, data collection</item>
      <item>After 50+ form fills: Maximum Delivery (automatic)</item>
      <item>Cost cap: set target CPA after sufficient data — constrains optimizer</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Optimization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Refresh creative every 14-21 days on LinkedIn; CTR decay is faster than Meta because the feed is sparser and users see the same ads more quickly.</statement>
      <rationale>LinkedIn's professional audience is smaller and more targeted than Meta's. High frequency against a small ICP list leads to ad fatigue within 2-3 weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>CTR benchmark: 0.4% good, 0.8%+ great</item>
      <item>Lead form rate: 10% good, 15%+ great</item>
      <item>CPL target: &lt;$75 good, &lt;$50 great</item>
      <item>Lead quality: track MQL rate and cost per opportunity, not just CPL</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Exclude existing customers and converted leads via uploaded customer-list audiences; LinkedIn has no native exclude-converters toggle.</statement>
      <rationale>Without exclusions, budget is wasted showing acquisition ads to existing customers, inflating lead counts with people who cannot convert again.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
