<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<methodology slug="data-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Five-step data analysis for discovery and quality assessment via existing-data profiling.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>data</tag>
      <tag>data-analysis</tag>
      <tag>data-dictionary</tag>
      <tag>data-quality</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>analysis</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-24</created>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Data Analysis — Requirements Discovery and Quality Assessment</title>

    <summary>Data Analysis in the BA context identifies what data the business needs, how it is structured, where it comes from and goes, its quality characteristics, and the rules governing it. The process runs five steps: identify data needs, define data elements, create a data model (conceptual → logical → physical), analyze data quality across six dimensions (accuracy, completeness, consistency, timeliness, validity, uniqueness), and define data rules (validation, derivation, default, constraint, uniqueness). Output is a data dictionary and data requirements document linked to the specification.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without data analysis, systems are built on conflicting definitions — Sales and Finance report different churn numbers because nobody aligned on the definition. Data quality issues that surface late cause integration failures and rework. Missing data requirements lead to post-launch migrations.</p>
      <p>The six-dimension quality scorecard provides a measurable, testable basis for data acceptance criteria. Converting a vague stakeholder assertion ("users abandon at checkout") into a quantified requirement requires profiling existing data to surface the actual pattern and measure baseline values before development.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-spec discovery: profiling existing tables to convert a vague stakeholder assertion into a quantified requirement.</item>
        <item>Sizing a candidate feature: running counts to confirm population, frequency, and business value before backlog entry.</item>
        <item>Reconciling conflicting stakeholder data reports by reading both definitions and running a third query.</item>
        <item>Generating evidence packs for steering committees with sourced numbers and definition footnotes.</item>
        <item>Hand-off contract with the data team: drafting a data-request.md instead of an open-ended Slack ask.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Statistical inference or A/B testing analysis — that is analytics-engineer territory; BA stops at descriptive statistics and basic segmentation.</item>
        <item>Production data pipeline authoring — BA writes throwaway exploratory SQL; promotion to dbt models requires engineering review.</item>
        <item>Direct write access to source systems — BA queries are read-only.</item>
        <item>Heavily regulated PII data without a DPIA — BA exploration on raw data is a compliance breach; require synthetic/redacted environments.</item>
        <item>Replacing a certified source-of-truth metric with an ad-hoc calculation — reference it, never recompute.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="five-step-data-analysis-process">
      <p>Data Analysis follows a repeatable five-step process, starting with business needs and ending with quality-assessed entities.</p>

      <p>Step 1: Identify Data Needs</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For each data category, document the question it answers and its role in the system before defining attributes.</statement>
        <rationale>Starting with attributes before understanding the data's purpose produces dictionaries that capture fields nobody uses and miss fields everyone needs.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>What information do users need? — Reports and screens (consumed data).</item>
        <item>What data is captured? — Input data (created by users or external systems).</item>
        <item>What data is calculated? — Derived data (computed from other fields).</item>
        <item>What data is stored persistently? — Domain entities.</item>
        <item>What data is shared with other systems? — Integration data with defined contracts.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Step 2: Define Data Elements</p>
      <p>For each attribute, document all seven characteristics:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Name — clear, unique, business-facing name (not column name).</item>
        <item>Definition — business meaning in plain language.</item>
        <item>Type — text, number, date, boolean, enumeration.</item>
        <item>Format — specific format rules (e.g., ISO 8601 dates, E.164 phone numbers).</item>
        <item>Values — valid values or ranges; enumeration members.</item>
        <item>Source — where the data originates.</item>
        <item>Owner — who is responsible for data quality.</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every number cited in a requirements document must carry a definition footnote: metric name, definition, source system, snapshot date.</statement>
        <rationale>Numbers travel without their definitions; within weeks a cited metric becomes folklore that different teams interpret differently, producing conflicting implementations.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Step 3: Data Modeling Levels</p>
      <list>
        <item>Conceptual — high-level entities and relationships. Audience: business stakeholders. No attributes.</item>
        <item>Logical — detailed attributes, data types, relationships, and business rules. Audience: BA and developers.</item>
        <item>Physical — tables, columns, indexes, constraints. Audience: database developers. Out of BA scope to author; BA reviews for alignment with logical model.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Step 4: Six Data Quality Dimensions</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Assess all six quality dimensions before defining data requirements. Missing dimensions produce requirements that assume data quality the system does not have.</statement>
        <rationale>Systems built on inaccurate or inconsistent data inherit the data's defects; post-launch data quality remediation is significantly more expensive than pre-spec assessment.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Accuracy — correct values. Measure: error rate. Target threshold: less than 2%.</item>
        <item>Completeness — all required data present. Measure: missing value percentage.</item>
        <item>Consistency — same values across systems. Measure: conflict count between sources.</item>
        <item>Timeliness — current and available. Measure: age of data against business SLA.</item>
        <item>Validity — conforms to business rules. Measure: invalid value percentage.</item>
        <item>Uniqueness — no duplicates. Measure: duplicate rate.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Step 5: Data Rules</p>
      <list>
        <item>Validation — Email must contain @; phone must match format.</item>
        <item>Derivation — Total = Quantity x Price; Age = today - birth date.</item>
        <item>Default — Status defaults to "New" on creation.</item>
        <item>Constraint — Start date must be before end date.</item>
        <item>Uniqueness — CustomerID is unique; Email is unique per account.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="discovery-loop-agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive BA Data Analysis as a discovery-loop subagent that takes a stakeholder question and produces a data-brief.md artifact, never a live dashboard.</p>

      <p>The loop: (1) Frame — agent rewrites the question into a measurable form with a target audience, time window, and decision it informs; rejects unmeasurable framings; (2) Locate — agent maps the question to source systems by reading data-dictionary.md; flags coverage gaps as blockers, not assumptions; (3) Query — agent writes read-only SQL against a warehouse role with SET statement_timeout, samples conservatively, redacts PII via Presidio before any output; (4) Interpret — agent annotates every number with definition, time window, sample size, and caveats (selection bias, data quality scores from the six-dimension scorecard); (5) Hand off — agent emits two artifacts: data-brief.md for the spec, and data-request.md for any unanswered slice routed to the data team.</p>

      <p>Persist both in git inside the SDD feature folder; treat the brief as a versioned input to spec.md, not a Slack thread.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents and responsibilities:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — picks up the data-brief.md's recommendation, opens an SDD task in .product/features/feature/todo/, and links the brief as evidence in spec.md.</item>
        <item>password-scrubber-agent — mandatory pre-LLM-context filter for any sample row, query result, or stack trace before it enters a prompt; BA exploration constantly surfaces emails, IDs, free text.</item>
        <item>ba-data-discovery agent (worth creating) — system prompt holds the canonical data-dictionary.md excerpt + the question framing rules; tools are read-only warehouse role + Presidio + a data-brief.md generator; output schema is {question, framing, sources, sql, results_redacted, caveats, recommendation, decision_owner, snapshot_at}.</item>
        <item>definition-resolver agent — when stakeholders disagree, reads the data dictionary, related dbt model docs, and the spec, then emits a single canonical definition + a SQL implementation; routes to the data team for sign-off before merge.</item>
        <item>data-request-router agent — takes a data-request.md, classifies (self-serve vs analytics-engineer vs data-engineer vs governance), and posts to the right queue with the SLA.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Prompt pattern for framing an unmeasurable question:</p>
      <code lang="text">
You are a BA data-discovery agent. The stakeholder says: &lt;quote&gt;.
Rewrite this as a measurable question with: (a) target population (SQL filter),
(b) metric (counted entity + aggregation), (c) time window (anchored to fiscal
calendar in &lt;fiscal.yaml&gt;), (d) the decision it informs (next action if metric
is X vs Y), (e) acceptable margin of error. If any element is unknowable from
the data dictionary in &lt;data-dictionary.md&gt;, output a data-request.md draft
instead of guessing. No SQL yet.
      </code>

      <p>Prompt pattern for producing a data-brief from a query result:</p>
      <code lang="text">
You profiled &lt;table&gt; answering &lt;framed-question&gt;. Sample size &lt;n&gt;,
snapshot &lt;iso-timestamp&gt;. Output a data-brief.md with: question, framing,
sources (with dictionary entries cited), the SQL (read-only, parameterised),
results redacted via Presidio, definition footnote per metric, three caveats
(selection bias / data quality / temporal confounders), recommendation with a
decision owner. No claim without a count + percentage. Reject the brief if
sample size is below the floor in &lt;power-config.yaml&gt;.
      </code>
    </section>

    <section name="example-customer-entity">
      <example type="good" title="Customer data entity with attributes and business rules">
        <note>Entity: Customer. Owner: CRM team. Source: web registration and import.</note>
        <note>Attributes: CustomerID (Integer, required, auto-generated unique — immutable, system-assigned); FirstName (Text 50, required, not empty); LastName (Text 50, required, not empty); Email (Text 100, required, valid email format — unique across all customers); Phone (Text 20, optional, valid phone format); Status (Text 10, required, enumeration: Active/Inactive/Prospect — defaults to Prospect on creation); CreatedDate (DateTime, required, auto-set on creation).</note>
        <note>Business rules: DR-01: CustomerID is system-generated and immutable. DR-02: Email must be unique across all customers. DR-03: Status defaults to Prospect for new customers.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="example-data-quality-assessment">
      <example type="good" title="Data quality assessment findings">
        <note>Assessment of Product Data. Sample size: 15,000 records. Snapshot: 2026-04-19.</note>
        <note>Accuracy: 3/5 — 8% of prices incorrect vs. catalog; root cause: manual price override without catalog sync.</note>
        <note>Completeness: 4/5 — 2% missing descriptions; root cause: bulk import without description field.</note>
        <note>Consistency: 2/5 — product names differ across CRM, ERP, and web catalog; root cause: no naming convention enforced at import.</note>
        <note>Timeliness: 5/5 — updated daily, within SLA.</note>
        <note>Validity: 4/5 — 1% with invalid category codes; root cause: legacy category codes not migrated.</note>
        <note>Uniqueness: 3/5 — 5% duplicate SKUs; root cause: multiple import channels with no deduplication.</note>
        <note>Priority issue: Consistency (score 2/5). Recommendation: establish and enforce product naming convention at all import channels before building the new product search feature.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>No data dictionary — everyone defines data differently.</description>
        <reason>Without a shared data dictionary, different teams build against different definitions of the same entity; the inconsistency surfaces as data quality failures after go-live, not before.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping data quality assessment — assuming current data is correct.</description>
        <reason>Systems built on inaccurate or inconsistent data inherit the data's defects; pre-spec assessment is orders of magnitude cheaper than post-launch remediation.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Technical-only data modeling without business definitions.</description>
        <reason>Column names and data types without business meanings produce a dictionary that developers can implement but stakeholders cannot validate; discrepancies appear only during UAT.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No data ownership assigned.</description>
        <reason>Without a named owner per entity, data quality degrades because nobody has authority or accountability to enforce rules or resolve conflicts between source systems.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Ignoring historical data — not considering how data will change over time.</description>
        <reason>Systems designed without archival, versioning, or audit-trail requirements discover these needs at scale after launch, requiring costly schema migrations.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-scope-boundaries">
      <list>
        <item>Scope drift into data engineering. A BA who can write SQL is tempting to push into building dashboards; the role is requirements, not delivery. Agents amplify this by happily producing dashboards no one owns.</item>
        <item>Definition theatre. Two stakeholders call the same thing "active user" with different windows; BA produces a query and "the number" gets cited as canonical without the definition. Numbers travel; definitions don't.</item>
        <item>Sample-of-one trap. A BA pulls 50 rows, eyeballs a pattern, and writes a requirement. Without a power check ("is 50 enough to detect the effect that matters?") the requirement is built on noise.</item>
        <item>No counterfactual. "Users who saw banner X converted 4x more" — selection bias; agents will rarely ask "what would these users have done without the banner?"</item>
        <item>Data deserts. The most important questions ("why did they leave?") have the worst data; BA forced to fall back to qualitative methods (interviews, ethnography) which this methodology does not cover.</item>
        <item>Dictionary disconnect. BA's exploratory SQL uses column names from the warehouse view; product spec uses business names; over time the spec and the data drift apart.</item>
        <item>Org-chart-bound queries. BA only knows the systems they were granted access to; they invent answers from incomplete tables instead of escalating "I cannot answer this without the billing DB".</item>
        <item>PII leakage in screenshots. A BA pastes a query result into a Confluence page or LLM prompt; row 3 is a real customer email. The methodology's data security row is not enforced at exploration time.</item>
        <item>Static numbers. A BA cites "34% churn" in a PRD; six months later the spec ships, churn is now 21%, no one updates the PRD. Snapshot timestamps are routinely omitted.</item>
        <item>Confounding business calendar. Numbers without fiscal-week alignment, holidays, or release dates produce false trends; agents will rarely overlay these annotations.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-BI-platforms">
      <p>Recommended tools for data discovery and analysis:</p>
      <list>
        <item>duckdb — In-process SQL on Parquet/CSV/Postgres without a warehouse round-trip; ideal for BA discovery loops in CI.</item>
        <item>pandas / polars — Tabular profiling, joins, frequency tables; polars for &gt;10M rows.</item>
        <item>ydata-profiling — One-command profile report (counts, missing, distributions) per table.</item>
        <item>sweetviz — Two-cohort comparison reports (e.g. churned vs retained).</item>
        <item>great_expectations — Codify the six dimensions as expectation suites; BA reuses them in briefs.</item>
        <item>presidio (Microsoft) — PII detection + redaction before any sample row enters a prompt or Confluence page.</item>
        <item>sqlglot — Parse SQL, swap dialects, extract columns/tables programmatically; agents use it to validate a query against the dictionary.</item>
        <item>dbt — Read certified models + docs; BA never authors production dbt, only references.</item>
        <item>metabase / superset CLI — Run saved questions / charts via API for canonical metrics.</item>
        <item>evidence / observable framework — Markdown-first BI; agent emits .md reports that compile to charts; perfect for data-brief.md.</item>
        <item>quarto — Reproducible analytical reports (md → HTML/PDF); pairs with Python or R.</item>
        <item>papermill — Parameterise + execute notebooks headlessly in CI for repeatable briefs.</item>
        <item>chdb / clickhouse-local — Fast OLAP scans against logs / events without a server.</item>
      </list>

      <p>SaaS platforms supporting BA data discovery:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Metabase — OSS/SaaS, Question + Card REST API; canonical certified-metrics layer.</item>
        <item>Superset — OSS, REST API; same role as Metabase; better for SQL Lab-style ad-hoc.</item>
        <item>Lightdash / Cube — OSS/SaaS, semantic layer + API; lets BA query metrics by name instead of raw SQL.</item>
        <item>Hex / Deepnote / Mode — SaaS notebooks, API + scheduled runs; useful for reproducible brief; PII risk requires careful workspace isolation.</item>
        <item>Atlan / DataHub / OpenMetadata — SaaS/OSS catalogs, REST/GraphQL; BA reads ownership + classification before querying.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Always pair quantitative with qualitative. A BA's SQL can reveal what (8% drop-off at payment) but not why; conduct follow-up interviews to understand causation.</item>
        <item>Use the six-dimension scorecard before every spec. Do not assume data quality — measure accuracy, completeness, consistency, timeliness, validity, uniqueness.</item>
        <item>Make data definitions the contract. Data dictionaries are not reference books; they are implementation contracts. Require that every column in a system matches a row in the dictionary.</item>
        <item>Assign data ownership. Every entity in the dictionary must have a named owner who is accountable for quality and authorized to resolve conflicts.</item>
        <item>Timestamp every metric. "34% churn" is meaningless without "as of 2026-04-15". Require ISO dates in all briefs and PRD metrics.</item>
        <item>Baseline before estimating. Never estimate the impact of a feature without measuring the current baseline. Baselines are your only evidence.</item>
        <item>Use structured templates. The data dictionary, data requirements, and quality assessment templates lock the shape so agents produce comparable artifacts.</item>
        <item>Redact before you share. Run Presidio on any sample row before pasting into Confluence, Slack, or an LLM prompt. PII in discovery artifacts is a compliance breach.</item>
        <item>Cite every number. In a requirement document, every number must have a footnote with source, query, and snapshot date. "Data not available" is better than a guess.</item>
        <item>Keep discovery artifacts in version control. Data briefs and quality assessments are evidence; they live in git alongside spec.md, not in Confluence.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="scope-boundaries-and-gotchas"><p>Common failure modes and scope boundaries for data analysis work:</p><list><item>Scope drift into data engineering. A BA who can write SQL is tempting to push into building dashboards; the role is requirements, not delivery. Agents amplify this by happily producing dashboards no one owns.</item><item>Definition theatre. Two stakeholders call the same thing "active user" with different windows; BA produces a query and "the number" gets cited as canonical without the definition. Numbers travel; definitions don't.</item><item>Sample-of-one trap. A BA pulls 50 rows, eyeballs a pattern, and writes a requirement. Without a power check ("is 50 enough?") the requirement is built on noise.</item><item>No counterfactual. "Users who saw banner X converted 4x more" - selection bias; agents will rarely ask "what would these users have done without the banner?"</item><item>Data deserts. The most important questions ("why did they leave?") have the worst data; BAs fall back to qualitative methods (interviews, ethnography) which methodology does not cover.</item><item>Dictionary disconnect. BA's exploratory SQL uses column names from the warehouse view; product spec uses business names; over time the spec and data drift apart.</item><item>Org-chart-bound queries. BA only knows the systems they were granted access to; they invent answers from incomplete tables instead of escalating "I cannot answer this without the billing DB".</item><item>PII leakage in screenshots. A BA pastes a query result into Confluence; row 3 is a real customer email. Discovery artifacts are compliance risks.</item><item>Static numbers. A BA cites "34% churn" in a PRD; six months later churn is 21%, no one updates the PRD. Snapshot timestamps are routinely omitted.</item><item>Confounding business calendar. Numbers without fiscal-week alignment, holidays, or release dates produce false trends; agents will rarely overlay these annotations.</item></list></section><section name="sibling-methodologies-and-handoffs"><p>Data Analysis sits upstream of solution design and implementation:</p><p>The sibling methodology pro/ba/ba-modeling/data-analysis covers the design-time view (data dictionary authoring, ERD modeling, dbt and great-expectations governance). This methodology covers the BA-led discovery view: using existing data to surface, validate, and quantify requirements. Both methodologies use the same templates (data-dictionary.md, data-requirements.md); the difference is when they are produced and by whom. Discovery BA produces briefs from existing data; architect BA produces schemas from requirements. A data-driven requirement from discovery becomes a spec artifact; a spec hand-off to design triggers data modeling work in ba-modeling/data-analysis.</p><p>Hand-offs: after a data-brief.md is approved, faion-sdd-executor-agent opens an SDD feature task and links the brief as evidence in spec.md. Data questions that cannot be answered from existing data become a data-request.md routed to the data team for investigation or new instrumentation. Data quality findings that are blocking become tickets in the data governance backlog.</p></section><templates>
      <template path="templates/data-dictionary.md" purpose="Data dictionary template: entity description, attribute table (name/definition/type/format/required/values/rules), relationships, business rules." />
      <template path="templates/data-requirements.md" purpose="Data requirements template: entities, attributes, derived data, quality requirements, volumes, integration, security." />
      <template path="templates/data-quality-assessment.md" purpose="Data quality assessment template: per-dimension findings with score, status, and recommendations." />
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://docs.getdbt.com" />
      <link href="https://www.metabase.com" />
      <link href="https://superset.apache.org" />
      <link href="https://github.com/ydataai/ydata-profiling" />
      <link href="https://microsoft.github.io/presidio" />
      <ref slug="data-driven-requirements" />
      <ref slug="acceptance-criteria" />
      <ref slug="requirements-validation" />
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>