<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-tiktok-basics Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-tiktok-basics. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use a Creator account at launch; switch to Business only after establishing consistent posting.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Creator accounts receive better algorithmic distribution. Business accounts add analytics but reduce organic reach in early phases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Bio must contain: what you do + who it is for + one CTA word, under 80 characters.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Viewers decide in 2 seconds whether to follow; a vague bio converts at 1/3 the rate of a specific one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Display name must include a searchable keyword (e.g., "SaaS Tips | Mike", not just "Mike").</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">TikTok search indexes display names; keyword inclusion drives discoverability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define 3-4 content pillars before posting. Each pillar must map to an ICP pain point.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Random content confuses the algorithm's audience-matching; consistent pillars signal which For You Pages to distribute on.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write the hook (0-3 seconds) before the rest of the script; if the hook is weak, discard the script.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hook quality is the single highest-leverage variable; a great body with a weak hook produces zero views.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always script on-screen text alongside spoken text — they may differ for emphasis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Approximately 70% of TikTok is watched without sound; captions are not optional.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Constrain hook to 8-12 spoken words; constrain each body point to 15-25 words.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generated and improvised scripts run too long; explicit word-count constraints prevent watch-time collapse.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post 1 video every day for the first 4 weeks before increasing frequency.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Daily posting builds algorithm familiarity. Skipping days in the first 30 days resets distribution testing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide the agent with 3-5 real high-performing videos in your niche as format references before requesting scripts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without format references, agents produce structurally correct but tonally generic scripts that underperform platform-native content.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
