<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="TikTok Basics for B2B/SaaS Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every TikTok Basics for B2B/SaaS application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-three-to-five-pillars" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Account MUST commit to 3-5 named content pillars before posting. Ad-hoc topical posts are rejected for the first 90 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Algorithm anchors on pillar consistency; broad accounts under-perform niche accounts of equal effort.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-profile-bio-conversion-line" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Profile bio MUST carry one conversion line (link + value prop). Generic biographies are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Bio is the only consistent CTA surface; without a conversion line the funnel leaks at the strongest moment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-three-formats-shipped-per-month" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output MUST cover ≥3 of the named formats (tutorial / story / demo / day-in-life / hot-take) per month. Single-format accounts are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Format variety lifts watch-time across viewer cohorts and stabilises reach.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-ramp-plan-with-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plan MUST define cadence by month (month 1: warm-up, month 2: scale, month 3+: optimisation). Indefinite ramp is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Without a ramp the operator under-posts in month 1 and over-promises in month 3.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-vertical-format-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Videos MUST ship in 9:16 vertical, ≤60s for the first 90 days. Landscape or long-form is rejected for the foundation phase.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">TikTok algorithm down-ranks non-native format; horizontal kills early reach.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
