<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="AWS Service Selection (Compute, Database, Architecture Decisions) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 rules grounded in AWS WA + Graviton economics + real-world migration debt.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="graviton-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Compute MUST default to Graviton (arm64) unless a binary dep blocks it. x86 selection MUST carry an explicit rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Graviton2/3 perf-cost data">Graviton is ~20% cheaper at same perf and faster for many workloads. The default should be on; x86 is the exception with reason.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="lambda-under-15min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lambda MUST be chosen only when the handler completes in &lt; 15 min. Longer-running tasks MUST use Fargate / EKS / Batch.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Lambda quotas">Lambda hard limit is 15 min; choosing it for longer tasks requires workarounds (chaining, Step Functions) that lose simplicity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ddb-key-value-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DynamoDB MUST be chosen only when access pattern is key-value + known queries. Relational queries / complex joins MUST use Aurora Serverless v2 / RDS.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS DDB best-practice">DDB is a key-value store; trying to do relational queries with scans is slow + expensive. Aurora Serverless v2 scales similarly without losing SQL.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evaluate-all-6-pillars" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision record MUST evaluate the workload against all 6 WA pillars before sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected Framework">Skipping a pillar means the workload has not been reviewed against it. Sustainability is the most-skipped — and most defensible to add Graviton for.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="gap-list-before-prod" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Gap list MUST be produced + remediated (or accepted with sign-off) before first prod deployment.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected Tool">Post-launch gaps are 10-100x more expensive to fix. The gap list is the bridge between design and ops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies If preconditions in AGENTS.md do not all hold, OR any Skip If trigger fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and pick a different one — applying the rules here on a mismatched input produces wrong output.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology guard">Methodology selection errors cascade. The cheapest place to abort is before any rule fires.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>