<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Single Operator Funnel Rubric Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Single Operator Funnel Rubric application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-four-stages-locked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rubric MUST be exactly four stages — visit, signup, paid, retained — never grow more without retiring one.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion solopreneur funnel audit 2026">Stage proliferation creates evidence-source debt the founder cannot honestly populate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-one-source-per-stage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each stage MUST have exactly one named evidence source pullable in &lt;5 minutes; multiple sources per stage are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion solopreneur funnel audit 2026">Two sources turn the Friday slot into a reconciliation task instead of a diagnostic.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-wow-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Friday entry MUST record absolute counts AND week-over-week deltas; absolute-only entries are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Andrew Chen — Growth Models">Diagnostic value lives in the deltas; absolute numbers hide trend.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-one-broken-stage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Largest WoW drop MUST be tagged BROKEN_STAGE and assigned next week's investigation slot; multi-stage drops still pick one.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion solopreneur funnel audit 2026">Solo founders fail by fixing three things at once; one tag = one committed action.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-20min-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Total time budget MUST be ≤20 minutes per Friday; consistent overrun means the rubric is wrong (sources too slow), not that more time is needed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atomic Habits — cadence research">Weekly rhythms costing an hour get skipped within 6 weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
