<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Single Operator Funnel Rubric Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that keep a solo founder's weekly funnel diagnostic honest, fast, and actionable without an analytics team.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The rubric MUST be exactly four stages — visit, signup, paid, retained — and never grow more without retiring one; "lead", "MQL", "demo", "trial" are not added.</statement>
      <rationale>Diagnosing the funnel with one-person evidence sources fails the moment the rubric has more stages than the founder can honestly populate. Capping at four forces consolidation onto stages with real evidence and matches the actual decisions a solo founder makes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Each stage MUST have exactly one named evidence source the founder owns and can pull in &lt;5 minutes (e.g. visits = Plausible total, paid = Stripe successful charges). Multiple sources per stage are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>One-person evidence sources only work if there is no debate about which number is "the" number. Two sources per stage guarantee that the Friday slot becomes a reconciliation task instead of a diagnostic.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[stages:
  visit:    {source: "Plausible — last 7d uniques"}
  signup:   {source: "Postgres — users created last 7d"}
  paid:     {source: "Stripe — subscriptions started last 7d"}
  retained: {source: "Postgres — active accounts at day 28"}]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every Friday entry MUST record absolute counts AND week-over-week deltas for all four stages; absolute-only entries are rejected because they hide trend.</statement>
      <rationale>The diagnostic value lives in the deltas — a 12% drop in signup conversion is invisible if only the absolute number is logged. WoW comparison is the minimum unit of insight cross-cutting marketing and product.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The largest WoW drop MUST be tagged "BROKEN_STAGE" and assigned the next week's investigation slot; multi-stage drops still pick a single broken stage.</statement>
      <rationale>Solo founders fail by trying to fix three things at once and fixing none. Forcing a single broken-stage tag converts the rubric output into one committed action for the next week.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The total time budget for the rubric MUST be ≤20 minutes per Friday; if the founder consistently overruns, the rubric is wrong (sources too slow) and is fixed, not extended.</statement>
      <rationale>A weekly rhythm that costs an hour gets skipped within 6 weeks. The 20-minute budget is the load-bearing constraint that keeps the rubric alive past the honeymoon period; breaching it is a signal to fix the evidence sources, not to grant more time.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
