<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SaaS Stack Audit (Micro-Agency) Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every quarterly SaaS-stack audit must enforce so the kill-list is real and the savings are measurable next quarter.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-full-stack-inventory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The inventory must reconcile against the corporate card statement: every recurring SaaS charge in the last 3 months must appear in the inventory. A claimed-inventory that contains fewer line items than the card statement is rejected as incomplete.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bottom-up reality">Top-down inventories invariably miss the forgotten subscriptions — those are the exact tools the audit needs to catch. Reconciling against the card statement forces the audit to find every paid line, including the Loom seat from 2024 and the Calendly Pro nobody uses.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-classification-bucket" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each tool is placed in exactly one of five typed buckets: `keep` | `consolidate-into-&lt;target&gt;` | `downgrade-seats` | `suspend-90d` | `cancel`. Free-form classifications ("maybe keep") are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Forcing-function classification">Soft classifications produce no action. The 5-bucket constraint forces an explicit decision per tool; the `suspend-90d` bucket exists specifically for the "I think we might need it again" case so the audit doesn't stall on it.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-evidence-required-to-keep" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A `keep` classification requires either: (a) a named client engagement that depends on the tool, OR (b) ≥3 distinct users with logins in the last 30 days, OR (c) an explicit override `keep-without-evidence: &lt;one-line-reason&gt;`. Evidence-less keeps are allowed but counted on a "feels-important-but-no-evidence" register reviewed next quarter.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-status-quo bias">Default-to-keep is what produced the sprawl. Forcing one of three concrete evidence types flips the default. The override register catches the case where the founder's instinct is correct but undocumented — and surfaces the pattern over multiple quarters if the instinct never converts to evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-kill-list-signed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The audit closes with a signed kill-list naming every tool in `suspend-90d` or `cancel`, with: vendor, monthly cost, cancellation step (link or instruction), responsible-handle, due-at (≤14 days from audit close). Unsigned audits do not count; the kill-list must be executed, not just produced.</statement>
      <rationale source="Closed-loop ops">An audit that produces only a list is theatre. Forcing handle + due-date converts the list into a tracked queue; the 14-day window is short enough that momentum from the audit session carries the executions through.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-savings-tracked-next-quarter" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The audit record carries pre-audit monthly SaaS spend and projected savings. The next quarter's audit must include a `measured_savings` field comparing actual post-audit spend to projection, with variance &gt;20% triggering a root-cause note. Audits that do not feed forward are rejected as one-offs, not a practice.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practice over event">A single audit recovers $X once; a tracked practice recovers $X every quarter and gets better at projecting. The 20% variance threshold catches both the case where cancellations didn't actually take effect (vendor kept billing) and the case where new sprawl filled the saved budget in real time.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example>
    <description>Audit record for a 6-person agency, Q2 2026.</description>
    <code language="yaml">
record_id: saas-audit-2026-q2
agency_size_at_audit: 6
pre_audit_monthly_spend: $1820
inventory_count: 31
classifications:
  keep: 19
  consolidate: 4   (4 tools → 2 targets)
  downgrade-seats: 3 (8 seats → 5 seats)
  suspend-90d: 2
  cancel: 3
projected_monthly_savings: $440
kill_list:
  - vendor: Loom (Business), monthly: $90, action: cancel, owner: @founder, due: 2026-05-27
  - vendor: Trello, monthly: $50, action: cancel (consolidated → Linear), owner: @ops, due: 2026-05-27
  - ...
override_register:
  - vendor: Mailchimp, reason: "next campaign in 6 weeks", review_next_quarter: true
next_audit_due: 2026-Q3
    </code>
  </example>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../vendor-management-pm/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../project-manager/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
