<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gha-matrix-builds Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gha-matrix-builds. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test matrix jobs MUST set fail-fast: false so that a failure on one combination does not cancel the remaining combinations.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The default fail-fast: true hides failures on secondary platforms. You need the full cross-product result to triage regressions accurately.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use exclude to remove invalid combinations and include to add special configurations with extra variables (e.g., coverage: true for one canonical combination).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Phantom combinations waste CI minutes and can fail for unrelated reasons. Include allows attaching extra variables to a specific combination without duplicating the matrix.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When uploading artifacts from a matrix job, embed the matrix variables in the artifact name: name: build-${{ matrix.os }}-${{ matrix.node }}.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Artifacts with the same name overwrite each other. Matrix-keyed names allow the downstream combine job to download-artifact with pattern: build-* and merge-multiple: true.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set max-parallel only when runner quota is constrained; otherwise omit to let GHA schedule all combinations as fast as possible.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Artificially serialising a matrix defeats its purpose. Throttle only when you know the concurrency limit of your runner pool.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
