<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="seo-basics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>seo-manager</domain>
    <summary>Technical SEO foundations: robots.txt, sitemap, multilingual hreflang, semantic HTML, WCAG 2.2 accessibility, Core Web Vitals (LCP, INP, CLS).</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>seo</tag>
      <tag>technical-seo</tag>
      <tag>crawlability</tag>
      <tag>web-vitals</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>SEO Basics</title>
    <summary>Core technical SEO foundations: robots.txt configuration, XML sitemap structure, multilingual hreflang implementation, semantic HTML with accessibility (WCAG 2.2), and Core Web Vitals optimization (LCP, INP, CLS). These are the prerequisite building blocks before any on-page or off-page SEO work.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Search engines cannot rank pages they cannot crawl and index. Poor Core Web Vitals cause ranking demotions since 2021 (page experience update). Correct hreflang prevents duplicate content penalties for multilingual sites. Semantic HTML satisfies both accessibility requirements and Google's understanding of page structure — the same markup that helps screen readers helps crawlers.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Setting up a new site's technical SEO foundation</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing site for crawlability and indexability issues</item>
        <item>Implementing multilingual SEO (hreflang + URL structure)</item>
        <item>Diagnosing Core Web Vitals failures (LCP, INP, CLS)</item>
        <item>Ensuring WCAG 2.2 accessibility compliance alongside SEO</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When content quality and keyword strategy are the bottleneck — technical fixes alone won't improve rankings for thin content</item>
        <item>When the site has zero traffic and content — build content first</item>
        <item>For AEO/AI search optimization — use technical-seo-for-ai methodology instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="technical-foundation">
      <section name="robots-txt-rules">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Block admin paths, session ID parameters, and internal APIs; explicitly allow public API paths; add Sitemap directives; never block CSS or JS files.</statement>
          <rationale>Blocking CSS/JS prevents Google from rendering pages correctly, causing ranking loss. Unblocked session URLs create infinite crawl loops that waste crawl budget on non-indexable content.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Configure AI crawlers (GPTBot, Claude-Web, PerplexityBot) separately from search crawlers — allow public content, disallow premium/paywalled content.</statement>
          <rationale>AI crawlers serve a different purpose than search crawlers: they build training data and citation sources, not indexes. Blocking them entirely sacrifices AI search visibility; blocking only premium content is the balanced approach.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="xml-sitemap-rules">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Include only indexable pages in the sitemap; update lastmod only when content actually changes; use sitemap index for sites with more than 50,000 URLs.</statement>
          <rationale>Sitemaps with stale lastmod dates or non-indexable URLs train Google's crawler to distrust the sitemap, reducing crawl frequency for the whole site.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Include hreflang alternate links inside sitemap entries for multilingual sites.</statement>
          <rationale>Sitemap hreflang is a fallback for pages where HTML head injection is complex (SPAs, CDN-level rendering). Redundancy in hreflang signals is safe and preferred.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="https-and-redirects">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Redirect HTTP to HTTPS and non-www to www (or vice versa) with 301 permanent redirects; avoid redirect chains longer than one hop.</statement>
          <rationale>Each redirect hop loses approximately 10-15% of PageRank. Chains of three or more hops can be abandoned by crawlers entirely, causing indexing failures for the destination page.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>SSL certificate installed and covering all subdomains (wildcard preferred)</item>
          <item>No mixed content: all resources (images, scripts, fonts) load over HTTPS</item>
          <item>Security headers: HSTS, X-Frame-Options, CSP</item>
          <item>Single canonical domain enforced via server-level redirect</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="multilingual-seo-and-hreflang">
      <section name="url-structure">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Use subdirectory URL structure (/en/, /uk/) for multilingual sites — not query parameters (?lang=uk).</statement>
          <rationale>Query parameter language switching creates duplicate content that Google indexes inconsistently and cannot distinguish by language. Subdirectory structure gives each language version its own crawlable URL that accumulates PageRank independently.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Subdirectories (/en/, /uk/) — recommended: shared domain authority, simple management</item>
          <item>Subdomains (uk.faion.net) — acceptable: separate hosting possible, but splits domain authority</item>
          <item>ccTLDs (faion.ua) — strong geo-signal but expensive and complex to manage</item>
          <item>Parameters (?lang=uk) — avoid: poor SEO, indexing issues, canonical confusion</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="hreflang-implementation-rules">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Every hreflang implementation must include: self-referencing tag, bidirectional linking, ISO 639-1 language codes, x-default for the fallback page.</statement>
          <rationale>Missing self-reference causes Google to ignore the entire hreflang cluster. Missing bidirectional links (A points to B but B doesn't point to A) invalidates the signal. Missing x-default leaves users with no-match locale seeing an arbitrary language version.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Never combine hreflang with noindex on the same page.</statement>
          <rationale>A noindexed page cannot appear in search results, so its hreflang signals are worthless. Google may also ignore the hreflang signals pointing to noindexed pages, breaking the entire cluster.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="metadata-localization">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Title tags and meta descriptions must match the language of the page content — never leave English metadata on a Ukrainian-language page.</statement>
          <rationale>Mismatched language in metadata and content signals low quality to Google and creates a poor user experience when the snippet appears in localized search results.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Use ISO 639-1 codes: en, uk, de, fr (not "english", "ukrainian")</item>
          <item>Use ISO 3166-1 Alpha-2 for regional variants: en-US, en-GB</item>
          <item>Language switcher must be prominent and functional</item>
          <item>Test hreflang with Google Search Console hreflang validator</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="semantic-html-and-accessibility">
      <section name="semantic-html-rules">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Use exactly one H1 per page containing the primary keyword; maintain logical heading hierarchy (H1 → H2 → H3); never skip heading levels.</statement>
          <rationale>Search crawlers use heading structure to understand page organization and extract key topics. Screen readers rely on headings for document navigation. Skipped levels confuse both.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Use semantic elements (header, main, footer, article, section, aside, nav) instead of generic divs for all structural containers.</statement>
          <rationale>Semantic HTML conveys meaning to crawlers, screen readers, and browsers without requiring ARIA overrides. Divs with ARIA roles are a workaround; semantic elements are the baseline.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="wcag-22-checklist">
        <list>
          <item>Color contrast minimum 4.5:1 for normal text, 3:1 for large text</item>
          <item>All images have descriptive alt text; decorative images use alt=""</item>
          <item>All interactive elements reachable and operable by keyboard</item>
          <item>Form inputs have associated label elements (not placeholder-only)</item>
          <item>Links use descriptive text — not "click here" or "read more"</item>
          <item>ARIA landmarks: banner, main, navigation, contentinfo</item>
          <item>Focus indicators visible on all interactive elements</item>
          <item>Test with WAVE or axe browser extension</item>
          <item>Test navigation with keyboard only (Tab, Enter, arrow keys)</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="image-optimization">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Always include explicit width and height attributes on img elements to prevent CLS; use WebP or AVIF format; lazy-load below-fold images.</statement>
          <rationale>Missing width/height causes layout shift as images load (CLS score degradation). WebP/AVIF are 25-35% smaller than JPEG/PNG at equivalent quality, improving LCP. Lazy loading defers non-critical image loading to reduce initial page weight.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="core-web-vitals-optimization">
      <section name="metric-targets">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>All three Core Web Vitals must reach the "Good" threshold: LCP &lt;= 2.5s, INP &lt;= 200ms, CLS &lt;= 0.1.</statement>
          <rationale>Pages with all three metrics in "Good" range receive a page experience ranking boost. A single metric in "Poor" range cancels the boost. Monitor in Google Search Console, not just Lighthouse — lab data and field data diverge significantly.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>LCP (Largest Contentful Paint): Good &lt;= 2.5s | Needs work 2.5-4s | Poor &gt; 4s</item>
          <item>INP (Interaction to Next Paint): Good &lt;= 200ms | Needs work 200-500ms | Poor &gt; 500ms</item>
          <item>CLS (Cumulative Layout Shift): Good &lt;= 0.1 | Needs work 0.1-0.25 | Poor &gt; 0.25</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="lcp-optimizations">
        <list>
          <item>Preload the LCP image: &lt;link rel="preload" as="image" href="..."&gt;</item>
          <item>Use WebP/AVIF formats (25-35% smaller than JPEG)</item>
          <item>Serve responsive images via srcset</item>
          <item>Optimize server response time (TTFB &lt; 800ms)</item>
          <item>Use CDN for static assets</item>
          <item>Inline critical CSS; defer non-critical CSS</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="inp-optimizations">
        <list>
          <item>Break up JavaScript long tasks into chunks under 50ms</item>
          <item>Defer all non-critical JavaScript with defer or type="module"</item>
          <item>Move heavy computation to Web Workers off the main thread</item>
          <item>Use requestIdleCallback for low-priority background work</item>
          <item>Minimize event listener overhead — debounce high-frequency events</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="cls-optimizations">
        <list>
          <item>Always specify width and height on img and video elements</item>
          <item>Reserve explicit space for ads and third-party embeds (min-height)</item>
          <item>Never insert content above existing content after page load</item>
          <item>Use font-display: swap with font preload to prevent invisible text flash</item>
          <item>Avoid CSS animations that trigger layout (use transform/opacity instead)</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Measuring Core Web Vitals only in Lighthouse lab mode</description>
        <reason>Lighthouse runs in a controlled lab environment; Google's ranking uses field data from Chrome User Experience Report (CrUX). A passing Lighthouse score can coexist with failing field CWV if real users have slower devices or connections.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/robots-txt.txt" purpose="robots.txt with AI crawler rules and sitemap directive"/>
      <template path="templates/sitemap-xml.xml" purpose="XML sitemap template with hreflang alternates"/>
      <template path="templates/hreflang-html.txt" purpose="hreflang link tags for HTML head"/>
      <template path="templates/semantic-html.txt" purpose="Semantic HTML page structure with ARIA landmarks"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
