<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Annual ↔ Quarterly OKR Stitch Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that keep the annual bet and the quarterly OKRs coupled across all four quarters.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-bet-has-bet-id" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every annual bet MUST carry a stable `bet_id` (short slug like `bet-2026-aio-search`). The id is the join key for the cascade. Bets without ids are REJECTED from the cascade authoring step.</statement>
      <rationale source="Configuration-management practice; SDD identifier discipline">Stable identifiers survive renaming, prioritisation churn, and team rotation. Free-text bet names drift; references break silently. Bet_id is the cheapest defence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-every-kr-references-bet" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every quarterly KR MUST carry a `bet_id` field referencing one annual bet (or the special `bet-internal` for non-bet keep-the-lights-on KRs). Orphan KRs (no bet_id) are REJECTED in the coupling audit. The audit MUST pass before the quarter's OKRs are committed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Roadmap-OKR drift studies">Orphan KRs are how teams accidentally spend a quarter on something the strategy did not call for. Forcing the join makes the drift visible; the PM either updates the bet or drops the KR.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-quarterly-stitch-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>At every quarterly planning meeting, the PM MUST run the coupling-audit and review missing / weak links. Output is a written stitch-review log entry per bet — what changed in the quarter, what stays, what is retired. The review is non-negotiable; skipping it for "save time" is REJECTED.</statement>
      <rationale source="Christina Wodtke's OKR cadence; quarterly ritual discipline">The annual-to-quarterly stitch decays silently unless a meeting forces the review. Quarterly cadence catches drift while there is still time to recover that quarter.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-explicit-retire-or-extend" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If a bet is NOT carried forward into the next quarter, it MUST be either (a) explicitly retired with rationale in the cascade file OR (b) extended with new KRs. Silent dropping is REJECTED. The retire decision is a high-stakes call that goes through PM + Head of Product (or equivalent).</statement>
      <rationale source="Sunk-cost vs sunk-cost-fallacy literature; institutional decision memory">Bets dropped silently come back as zombies the next year. Explicit retirement creates institutional memory: "we tried, here's what we learned, we're done."</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-kr-count-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each bet-objective pair MUST have 1-3 KRs per quarter; more than 3 dilutes focus. Each team MUST have at most 3-5 active OKRs total per quarter. Quantity is REJECTED in favour of quality; sprawl is detected and surfaced as a planning failure.</statement>
      <rationale source="Andy Grove + Doerr OKR practice; cognitive-load research">Teams that try to advance 8+ OKRs in one quarter advance none. The cap is a focus discipline; the PM negotiates trade-offs upstream rather than letting the team fail downstream.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Bet-to-OKR cascade fragment">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
bet_id: bet-2026-aio-search
title: Capture share of AIO traffic in our top-3 topic clusters
horizon: 2026-Q1..Q4
objectives:
  - obj_id: obj-aio-citation-rate
    text: Become a cited source in AIO for our priority queries
    quarter_krs:
      Q1:
        - kr: 20% of priority queries have us cited in AIO at least once
          bet_id: bet-2026-aio-search
      Q2:
        - kr: 35% of priority queries have us cited; snippet-selected rate 10%
          bet_id: bet-2026-aio-search
      Q3:
        - kr: Sustained 35%+ citation; CTR uplift measurable in analytics
          bet_id: bet-2026-aio-search
      Q4:
        - kr: 50% citation rate; revenue attribution model for AIO clicks
          bet_id: bet-2026-aio-search
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1 satisfied (bet_id present). r2 satisfied (every KR references bet_id). r5 satisfied (1-3 KRs per quarter).</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Orphan KR — Q3 OKR with no bet_id">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
Q3:
  - kr: Refactor the legacy billing pipeline (no bet_id, no parent objective)
      ]]></code>
      <note>r2 violation. This is what Q3 OKRs become without the stitch: keep-the-lights-on dressed as strategy. Decision: tag as `bet-internal` OR drop OR negotiate a real strategic objective.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
