<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Wireframing Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every wireframing application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-no-visual-styling" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Wireframes MUST show structure, hierarchy, navigation, function, and interaction patterns. They MUST EXCLUDE colour (except greyscale), typography styles, real images, branding, and final copy.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — fidelity research">Visual styling commitments before structural validation conflate two distinct design phases and create premature attachment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-all-states" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every screen wireframe MUST cover ALL states: default, empty, loading, error, success, and any permission-gated view. Missing any state is a violation.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — state coverage research">Empty + error + permission states are always missed in design but always hit by users on first use.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-three-variants" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Key screens MUST be wireframed in ≥3 layout variants before converging on one direction. Single-option reviews produce acceptance-without-exploration.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — convergent design research">Single-option reviews produce either rubber-stamp acceptance or rejection-without-alternatives.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-mobile-notes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every wireframe MUST include mobile breakpoint notes, even for desktop-first products.</statement>
      <rationale source="mobile-first research">Mobile is the dominant context; assuming desktop produces brittle responsive behaviour.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-annotation-tables" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every wireframe MUST include an annotation table covering per-element behaviour, conditional states, and technical requirements.</statement>
      <rationale source="design-engineering handoff research">Layouts without annotations defer behaviour decisions to implementation by accident.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-open-questions-section" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every wireframe document MUST include an "Open Questions" section surfacing design assumptions needing PM/owner sign-off before engineering begins.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave grounding; design-ops research">Open-question lists are the most valuable part of a wireframe doc for early-stage design; agents skip them unless prompted.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-spec-context" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Annotation tables MUST be generated from the actual feature spec / acceptance criteria. Inventing plausible-sounding behaviour without spec context is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="agent-hallucination empirical">Without spec context, agents fabricate behaviours that look correct but mislead engineering.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
