<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="wireframing Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for wireframing. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start at low fidelity; increase fidelity only after layout direction is agreed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">High-fidelity wireframes invite aesthetic feedback before structural decisions are made, conflating two distinct design decisions and slowing both.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Wireframes must show: layout structure, content hierarchy, navigation, functionality, interaction patterns. Must exclude: colors (except grayscale), typography styles, real images, branding, final copy.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Including visual design elements in wireframes causes stakeholder feedback to focus on aesthetics instead of usability. Grayscale boxes enforce structural thinking.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every wireframe must cover all states: default, empty, loading, error, success, and any permission-gated view.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Empty states and error states are always missed in first-pass wireframes and always noticed by users. Missing states in wireframes produce missing states in implementation, which ship to production and surprise users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Explicitly wireframe empty states before launch — these are always missed and always noticed by users on first use.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Empty states are what new users see first. A blank screen with no guidance is the worst possible first impression. Wireframing empty states forces the team to design a productive first-use experience.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include mobile breakpoint notes in every wireframe, even for desktop-first products.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Retrofitting responsive behavior after desktop wireframes are approved costs significantly more than adding responsive notes during the wireframing phase.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Annotation tables must include an "Open Questions" section that surfaces design assumptions needing resolution before engineering begins.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unstated assumptions in wireframes become incorrect implementations. Forcing designers to state open questions creates explicit decision points rather than hidden ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Read user needs, business requirements, technical constraints, and content inventory before sketching anything.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Wireframes that do not reflect requirements must be redone. Reading requirements first prevents the most expensive type of wireframe rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Produce at least 3 layout variants for key screens before committing to one direction.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The first layout is rarely the best. Convergence too early eliminates valid alternatives without evaluation. Sketching three variants takes minutes; reworking a committed Figma file takes hours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every wireframe must include an annotation table documenting behavior, conditional states, and technical requirements for each element.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Undocumented behavior assumptions cause expensive rework in implementation when engineers make different assumptions. The annotation table is the contract between design and engineering.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
