<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Wireframing Process">
  <summary>Five-step wireframing process from requirements to annotated layout, with fidelity level guidelines.</summary>

  <section title="Fidelity Levels">
    <list>
      <item>Low fidelity: boxes and lines only — use for early concept exploration, cheap to discard</item>
      <item>Medium fidelity: basic content structure, placeholder text — use for design iteration and stakeholder review</item>
      <item>High fidelity: detailed layout, realistic content — use to finalize structure before visual design begins</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Start at low fidelity; increase fidelity only after layout direction is agreed.</statement>
      <rationale>High-fidelity wireframes invite aesthetic feedback before structural decisions are made, conflating two distinct design decisions and slowing both.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="What to Include and Exclude">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include: layout structure, content hierarchy, navigation, functionality, interaction patterns. Exclude: colors, typography styles, images, branding, final copy.</statement>
      <rationale>Including visual design elements in wireframes causes stakeholders to debate aesthetics instead of usability. Gray boxes force attention to structure and hierarchy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 1 — Understand Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Read user needs, business requirements, technical constraints, and content inventory before sketching anything.</statement>
      <rationale>Wireframes that do not reflect requirements must be redone. Reading requirements first prevents the most expensive type of wireframe rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2 — Sketch Multiple Concepts">
    <rule>
      <statement>Produce at least 3 layout variants for key screens before committing to one direction.</statement>
      <rationale>The first layout is rarely the best. Convergence too early eliminates valid alternatives without evaluation. Sketching three variants takes minutes; reworking a committed Figma file takes hours.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3 — Create Wireframes">
    <p>Key elements to cover: header and navigation, content areas, calls to action, form elements, footer.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4 — Review and Iterate">
    <p>Review questions: Does it meet requirements? Is hierarchy clear? Can users accomplish goals? What is confusing?</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5 — Document Annotations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every wireframe must include an annotation table documenting behavior, conditional states, and technical requirements for each element.</statement>
      <rationale>Undocumented behavior assumptions cause expensive rework in implementation when engineers make different assumptions. The annotation table is the contract between design and engineering.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/wireframe-doc.md">Full wireframe documentation template with annotation table</reference>
  </section>
</text>
