<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Wireframing Rules and State Coverage">
  <summary>Rules for what to include in wireframes, required state coverage, responsive requirements, and annotation standards.</summary>

  <section title="Content Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Wireframes must show: layout structure, content hierarchy, navigation, functionality, interaction patterns. Must exclude: colors (except grayscale), typography styles, real images, branding, final copy.</statement>
      <rationale>Including visual design elements in wireframes causes stakeholder feedback to focus on aesthetics instead of usability. Grayscale boxes enforce structural thinking.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Adding color to indicate priority or state in wireframes.</description>
      <reason>Introduces visual design decisions before structural ones are validated, conflating two separate design phases and creating premature commitment to color choices.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="State Coverage Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every wireframe must cover all states: default, empty, loading, error, success, and any permission-gated view.</statement>
      <rationale>Empty states and error states are always missed in first-pass wireframes and always noticed by users. Missing states in wireframes produce missing states in implementation, which ship to production and surprise users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Default: the populated, normal-operation view</item>
      <item>Empty: first use or no-data state ("no results found", "no orders yet")</item>
      <item>Loading: while data is being fetched</item>
      <item>Error: when an operation fails (form validation, network error, permission denied)</item>
      <item>Success: confirmation after completing an action</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Explicitly wireframe empty states before launch — these are always missed and always noticed by users on first use.</statement>
      <rationale>Empty states are what new users see first. A blank screen with no guidance is the worst possible first impression. Wireframing empty states forces the team to design a productive first-use experience.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Responsive Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include mobile breakpoint notes in every wireframe, even for desktop-first products.</statement>
      <rationale>Retrofitting responsive behavior after desktop wireframes are approved costs significantly more than adding responsive notes during the wireframing phase.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Annotation Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Annotation tables must include an "Open Questions" section that surfaces design assumptions needing resolution before engineering begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Unstated assumptions in wireframes become incorrect implementations. Forcing designers to state open questions creates explicit decision points rather than hidden ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/wireframe-doc.md">Annotation table format with Open Questions section</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Presenting one layout option to stakeholders for approval.</description>
      <reason>Single-option reviews produce either acceptance without exploration or rejection without alternatives, both of which slow design progress. Minimum three variants before converging.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping sketching and opening a Figma file directly.</description>
      <reason>Digital wireframing tools have friction that suppresses exploration. Paper sketching is 10x faster for generating and discarding layout ideas. Open Figma after you know the layout direction.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
