<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Wireframing Examples and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>Low and medium fidelity wireframe examples, common element patterns, and agentic wireframe generation workflow.</summary>

  <section title="Low-Fidelity Wireframe Example">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
+----------------------------------+
|  Logo        [Nav] [Nav] [Nav]  |
+----------------------------------+
|                                  |
|  [     Hero Headline      ]     |
|  [     Subtext            ]     |
|       [  CTA Button  ]          |
|                                  |
+----------------------------------+
|  [Card]    [Card]    [Card]     |
+----------------------------------+
|  Footer links | Social | Legal  |
+----------------------------------+
      ]]></code>
      <note>Layout direction only, no colors, no content. Can be sketched in 2 minutes. Enough for stakeholders to validate page structure.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Element Patterns">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
## Navigation bar
[Logo]    [Home]  [Products]  [About]  [Get Started]

## Hero section
[     Headline H1 — clear and concise              ]
[     Subtext — 1-2 lines max                      ]
[ Primary CTA ]    [ Secondary CTA ]

## Card (3-column grid)
+----------+  +----------+  +----------+
| [Image]  |  | [Image]  |  | [Image]  |
| Title    |  | Title    |  | Title    |
| Body     |  | Body     |  | Body     |
| [Action] |  | [Action] |  | [Action] |
+----------+  +----------+  +----------+

## Form field
Label *
[Input field                         ]
Helper text: format guidance here

## Footer
[Link group] [Link group] [Link group] [Social icons]
Copyright notice | Privacy | Terms
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Agent reads a feature spec or user story set. Produces for each screen: ASCII layout diagram (boxes and labels, no colors), annotation table (Element, Description, Behavior/Notes), states checklist (default, empty, loading, error, success), responsive notes (what changes at mobile breakpoint), open questions (ambiguous decisions needing resolution before engineering). This document is the input to a Figma session, not the output.</p>
    <reference path="templates/wireframe-doc.md">Full wireframe documentation template with annotation table</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-wireframe.txt">LLM prompt for generating a wireframe spec from a user story</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent generates happy-path wireframes only, missing all error and empty states.</description>
      <reason>Explicitly add to every wireframe prompt: "include all error, empty, loading, and permission-denied states." Agents do not include these unless explicitly instructed.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>ASCII wireframes look correct in raw text but break in rendered markdown due to character width differences.</description>
      <reason>ASCII box-drawing in monospace looks correct in editors but breaks when rendered in GitHub, Notion, or Slack which use proportional fonts. Validate rendering environment before sharing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Annotation tables generated without access to the actual spec contain invented behavior descriptions.</description>
      <reason>Always provide the feature spec or acceptance criteria as context when generating annotation tables. Without it, agents invent plausible-sounding behavior that may contradict requirements.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
