<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="wireframing Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for wireframing as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Adding color to indicate priority or state in wireframes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Introduces visual design decisions before structural ones are validated, conflating two separate design phases and creating premature commitment to color choices.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates happy-path wireframes only, missing all error and empty states.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Explicitly add to every wireframe prompt: "include all error, empty, loading, and permission-denied states." Agents do not include these unless explicitly instructed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>ASCII wireframes look correct in raw text but break in rendered markdown due to character width differences.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>ASCII box-drawing in monospace looks correct in editors but breaks when rendered in GitHub, Notion, or Slack which use proportional fonts. Validate rendering environment before sharing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Annotation tables generated without access to the actual spec contain invented behavior descriptions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always provide the feature spec or acceptance criteria as context when generating annotation tables. Without it, agents invent plausible-sounding behavior that may contradict requirements.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents omit "open questions" unless explicitly instructed to flag ambiguity.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>This is the most valuable part of a wireframe document for early-stage design. Force agents to include open questions with explicit prompt instructions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Human review of wireframes skipped because the agent produced something plausible.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents surface structure but cannot judge whether it matches user mental models or business intent. Human review is mandatory before engineering starts.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Presenting one layout option to stakeholders for approval.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Single-option reviews produce either acceptance without exploration or rejection without alternatives, both of which slow design progress. Minimum three variants before converging.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping sketching and opening a Figma file directly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Digital wireframing tools have friction that suppresses exploration. Paper sketching is 10x faster for generating and discarding layout ideas. Open Figma after you know the layout direction.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
