<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Facilitation Anti-Patterns Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules with rationale + source for facilitation-anti-patterns. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="break-sponsor-monologue-at-5min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the sponsor speaks for more than five consecutive minutes inside an elicitation block, the BA interrupts with a written-poll round (sticky notes or chat) addressed to every other participant by name.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sponsor monologue research">Sponsor monologue research — applies to Facilitation Anti-Patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="force-dissent-before-consensus" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before any 'are we agreed?' close, the BA explicitly asks 'what would have to be true for this to be wrong?' and waits at least 15 seconds of silence before accepting the agreement.</statement>
      <rationale source="False-consensus anti-pattern catalogue">False-consensus anti-pattern catalogue — applies to Facilitation Anti-Patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="silent-first-elicitation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For every new question, every participant writes their answer privately for 90 seconds before any verbal sharing; the BA only reveals contributions after collection.</statement>
      <rationale source="First-speaker anchoring research">First-speaker anchoring research — applies to Facilitation Anti-Patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="parking-lot-with-clock" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every parking-lot item is tagged with an owner and a 'review by' timestamp inside the same session; any item older than two cycles without a decision is auto-escalated to the sponsor with a 'kill or schedule' choice — never silently dropped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Parking-lot graveyard anti-pattern">Parking-lot graveyard anti-pattern — applies to Facilitation Anti-Patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="name-the-hippo-override" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When the highest-paid person in the room overrides a workshop position, the BA writes the override into the minutes as 'decision by authority' with the named decider, the rejected alternatives, and the reason given — never as 'the group decided'.</statement>
      <rationale source="HiPPO / sponsor-override anti-pattern">HiPPO / sponsor-override anti-pattern — applies to Facilitation Anti-Patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="agenda-drift-recontract" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the conversation drifts off the published agenda for more than ten minutes, the BA stops and asks the room: 're-contract to the new topic and drop X, or park this and return to X?' — the room must vote before continuing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Workshop-drift anti-pattern">Workshop-drift anti-pattern — applies to Facilitation Anti-Patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the workshop has no power asymmetry, no contractual deliverable, and no historical anti-pattern, return `skipped`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to Facilitation Anti-Patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
