<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-product-hunt-launch Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-product-hunt-launch. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build an email list of 500+ interested users before launch. Without warm contacts, launch support is insufficient for early upvote velocity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Upvote velocity in the first hours determines the final ranking. Cold launches with no pre-built audience consistently fail to rank because they have no initial signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Secure a hunter with 1,000+ followers in the same niche. Hunter audience overlap with your product category matters more than raw follower count.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A niche-relevant hunter's followers are more likely to upvote and comment because the product matches their interests. A large generic hunter provides less relevant traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not launch if the product has major UX issues or is not functional. A PH launch surfaces all problems publicly and damages credibility permanently.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">PH comments are indexed and permanent. Negative launch comments about bugs or poor UX will follow the product indefinitely and reduce trust for future prospects.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tagline must be under 60 characters, benefit-focused, and contain no jargon. Validate length programmatically after generation — agents frequently exceed the limit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The tagline is the primary hook for PH visitors scanning the feed. Over-limit taglines are truncated. Jargon excludes non-technical visitors who are valid early adopters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write the first comment before launch day. Have it ready to paste within 60 seconds of the post going live — early velocity is critical.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">First comments on PH posts receive the most visibility. A prepared maker comment with backstory, differentiators, and a special offer sets the tone for all subsequent engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tagline formula: [Action verb] [outcome] [for whom] [differentiator]. Under 60 characters. Validate length after generation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Action verbs signal what the product does immediately. Outcome communicates value. "For whom" targets the right audience. Under 60 characters prevents truncation in the feed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not mention unfinished features in the listing or comments. PH commenters will test everything mentioned; negative comments about missing features compound quickly.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">PH comments are permanent and indexed. Overpromising on launch day creates immediate negative social proof that follows the product indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Respond to EVERY comment within 1 hour. Never ask for upvotes directly — this is against PH TOS and looks desperate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Active maker engagement is a strong positive signal on PH. Accounts with high comment response rates rank better and are perceived as more trustworthy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
