<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-assets-and-mistakes" title="Product Hunt Assets, Common Mistakes, and Agent Guardrails">
  <summary>Tagline formula, gallery structure, common launch failure modes, and agent production constraints.</summary>

  <section title="Tagline Formula">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Tagline formula: [Action verb] [outcome] [for whom] [differentiator]. Under 60 characters. Validate length after generation.</statement>
      <rationale>Action verbs signal what the product does immediately. Outcome communicates value. "For whom" targets the right audience. Under 60 characters prevents truncation in the feed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Tagline: "Build beautiful landing pages in minutes" — action verb (Build), outcome (beautiful landing pages), timeframe as differentiator (in minutes). 43 characters.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Tagline: "AI-Powered Landing Page Generator for Modern Businesses" — no action verb for the user, "AI-Powered" is jargon, too long (55 chars but generic). Does not communicate user outcome.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Gallery Structure">
    <list>
      <item>Image 1: Hero shot with tagline overlay</item>
      <item>Images 2-4: Key features with one-sentence explanations</item>
      <item>Image 5: Testimonials or social proof numbers</item>
      <item>Image 6: CTA or pricing summary</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not mention unfinished features in the listing or comments. PH commenters will test everything mentioned; negative comments about missing features compound quickly.</statement>
      <rationale>PH comments are permanent and indexed. Overpromising on launch day creates immediate negative social proof that follows the product indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Launching without a pre-built email list or community.</description>
      <reason>Without warm contacts to drive early upvote velocity, the listing never reaches the first page. Building the list before launch is more important than the launch date itself.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Launching on a weekend or during a major tech event.</description>
      <reason>Weekends have fewer active PH users; major events dominate attention. Tuesdays through Thursdays have the highest active user counts and lowest competition.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>First comment drafted as corporate marketing copy.</description>
      <reason>PH community values authenticity. A polished, corporate first comment reduces maker credibility. Write in first-person casual voice and review for authenticity before posting.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Guardrails">
    <rule>
      <statement>Agent must never include "upvote us" or "share with your network" in any launch copy. Explicitly forbid these phrases in the system prompt.</statement>
      <rationale>Asking for upvotes directly is a PH TOS violation and, if flagged, can result in removal of the listing. Let the product quality drive upvotes organically.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Agent drafts comment responses; a human must review and post them. No automated comment posting on public platforms.</statement>
      <rationale>Real-time public responses require human judgment on tone, accuracy, and appropriateness. Agent responses risk misrepresenting the product or making commitments the team cannot keep.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/first-comment.md">First comment template: maker intro, differentiators, special offer, roadmap teaser</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-asset-generation.txt">Agent prompt: 5 tagline variants + first comment + launch email from product brief</reference>
  </section>
</text>
