<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Platform Engineering Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed in real deployments. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="portal-first-no-backend" severity="high">
      <symptom>Backstage portal in production but every 'create service' click ends in a Slack ticket because the orchestration backend was never wired.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Humanitec Platform Maturity Model">Team built the visible part first because it shipped fast and looked impressive in demos. Backend never funded.</root-cause>
      <fix>Pause portal expansion. Fund the orchestration backend (Crossplane / Humanitec) until at least the first golden path provisions end-to-end without manual ticket.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="three-portals-concurrently" severity="high">
      <symptom>Backstage + Port + Cortex all running 'to compare'; teams pick one based on whim; three source-of-truth catalogues drift.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Spotify Backstage adoption case">'We want to evaluate everything before committing' — but evaluation continues past the point where the cost of dual-running exceeds switching cost.</root-cause>
      <fix>Pick one within 2 sprints. Time-box the evaluation. Cancel the other two POCs and migrate users.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="golden-path-mutation" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Platform team updates the Go template; every service using it sees CI fail on next push; trust collapses.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Backstage scaffolder docs">Template versioning skipped; updates pushed via 'just sync from main'.</root-cause>
      <fix>Switch to semver tags on templates. Downstream repos pin a version. Updates require an opt-in PR with a generated changelog.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="no-metrics" severity="high">
      <symptom>Platform team running on faith; CFO asks for ROI; team produces anecdotes; budget cut next quarter.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="DORA / Humanitec metrics guide">Metrics deferred 'until we have something to measure'; never happens.</root-cause>
      <fix>Ship the metrics dashboard alongside the FIRST golden path. Even a single 'TTFD for new dev' number beats no data.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>