<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="platform-engineering Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for platform-engineering as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using all three portals (Backstage, Port, Cortex) simultaneously "to compare them."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Portal choice is foundational. Each has a different API, plugin model, and operational surface. Running all three means three separate product teams, three separate security audits, three separate source-of-truth catalogs. Pick one, master it, then evolve.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating one generic golden path that handles "all possible microservices" by exposing all parameters (database, cache, messaging, payment processor, email service, etc.).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Too many parameters confuse developers and the template becomes unmaintainable. Instead, start with "critical features only" (database, one cache option, one queue) and layer advanced customizations as separate golden paths or post-scaffold guidance.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents generate Backstage templates with broken wiring between parameters and steps (variables undefined at template-render time).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Template rendering happens at scaffold time. If the LLM references a parameter that doesn't exist or misspells a step ID, the scaffold fails silently. Always render the template locally before merging.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents reach for "create one Crossplane Composition that handles all environments" — produces unmaintainable monster specs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force one Composition per concern (db, dns, queue) and compose at the XR level. Composability beats monoliths.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Score's resources block is provider-agnostic on paper; in practice the runtime mapping (postgres → RDS vs CloudSQL vs in-cluster) leaks. Agents must declare the target runtime, not assume.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A generic "postgres" resource in Score needs Humanitec or custom composition logic to map to the right provider. Agents can't guess.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents drop RBAC scope wide (system:admin) "to make it work" during scaffold tests; no one tightens it later.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force least-privilege from the first commit and have a reviewer agent enforce.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents call "provision new environment" in retry loops on transient errors.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cloud bill explodes. Wrap every IaC apply with rate limit + idempotency token.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>No platform PM; the platform team reports to infrastructure and takes tickets from the backlog. No roadmap, no SLAs, no autonomy.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Infrastructure is cost center. Products are value centers. Platform teams need autonomy to say "no, that feature doesn't align with golden-path strategy." When platform reports to infra it becomes a support queue.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>No cost gates; agents or humans provision infrastructure without seeing the financial impact.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cloud bill surprises follow. A forgotten load balancer running in production costs $500/month. Without visibility, FinOps teams become expensive data-entry clerks instead of strategic partners.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
