<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Review PR Checklist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>A PR-time design-QA checklist (10 items across token usage, component reuse, motion compliance, accessibility, content rules, breakpoint coverage) that gates whether the implementation matches the design handoff.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="ten-item-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every UI-touching PR MUST be checked against all 10 items: tokens, components, states (default/hover/focus/active/disabled/loading/error/empty), motion (prefers-reduced-motion), a11y (focus order, ARIA, contrast), content rules, breakpoints, image handling, dark-mode parity, cross-browser smoke.</statement>
      <rationale source="Material Design QA Checklist; Polaris adoption metrics">10 items map empirically to post-release defect modes; the set fits a 15-min PR review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="designer-reviewer-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A named designer or design-engineer MUST be a required PR reviewer for UI-touching PRs. Generic dev peer review does not satisfy design adherence.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian Design QA practice; Polaris case studies">PRs without designer review show 2-3x higher post-release design-bug rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-per-item" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each item check MUST include evidence: PR diff link, screenshot/recording, or script output. Pass-without-evidence is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft empirical code-review studies">Skim-review at PR time has same defect-find rate as no-review on design items; evidence forces actual look.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-style-cleanup-creep" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The checklist STAYS in its lane: design-system adherence, accessibility, content rules. It does NOT cover generic code style, test coverage, or business-logic correctness.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google Eng Practices — review effectiveness">Reviews trying to cover everything cover nothing well.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="handoff-deltas-flagged-back" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Implementation deviation from the handoff MUST be flagged back to the designer for accept-or-rework; silent acceptance is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-system maintenance research">Silent deviations decay the design system; explicit feedback either updates the system or reverts the code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — no design system; single-person dev-and-designer team; prototype/spike PR marked experimental; project phase explicitly out-of-scope), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
