<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Gdpr For Solo Saas Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every Gdpr For Solo Saas application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="data-inventory-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Operator MUST maintain a data inventory naming every data category + processor + retention period. Without inventory the operator cannot answer a Subject Access Request in 30 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 30 (light interpretation for solo scale)">GDPR Art. 30 (light interpretation for solo scale) — anchors Gdpr For Solo Saas rule `data-inventory-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="lawful-basis-per-category" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each data category MUST declare a lawful basis (consent, contract, legitimate-interest, legal-obligation). Bare &apos;we collect emails&apos; fails the test.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 6">GDPR Art. 6 — anchors Gdpr For Solo Saas rule `lawful-basis-per-category`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="processor-dpa-tracked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every external data processor MUST have a DPA on file (Stripe / Postmark / Plausible publish standard DPAs). Untracked processors = unknowable risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 28">GDPR Art. 28 — anchors Gdpr For Solo Saas rule `processor-dpa-tracked`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="breach-response-72h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Operator MUST have a documented breach-response plan reaching notification within 72h. The plan can be a one-pager but it must exist.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 33">GDPR Art. 33 — anchors Gdpr For Solo Saas rule `breach-response-72h`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="lawyer-up-triggers-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Operator MUST name the lawyer-up triggers (EU revenue &gt;€100k, sensitive category, enterprise-DPA-request). When a trigger fires, the methodology stops and counsel takes over.</statement>
      <rationale source="Pragmatic compliance practice">Pragmatic compliance practice — anchors Gdpr For Solo Saas rule `lawyer-up-triggers-named`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If special-category data, regulated B2B vertical, or EU revenue &gt;€100k applies → STOP. Methodology is insufficient; route to enterprise GDPR or specialised methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-applicability discipline">Methodology-applicability discipline — anchors Gdpr For Solo Saas rule `skip-this-methodology`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
