<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="activation-framework">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>growth-marketer</domain>
    <summary>7-step framework to improve activation: define the event correlated with D30+ retention, measure baseline, map funnel, find drop-offs, reduce friction, iterate with A/B tests.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>activation</tag>
      <tag>onboarding</tag>
      <tag>funnel-optimization</tag>
      <tag>user-retention</tag>
      <tag>aha-moment</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>growth</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Activation Framework &amp; Path Optimization</title>

    <summary>A 7-step framework for diagnosing and improving activation rate: define the activation event (behavior correlated with D30+ retention), measure baseline, map the funnel step by step, find the biggest drop-offs, reduce friction, increase motivation, and iterate with A/B tests. Correct activation event definition is the most critical and most commonly wrong step.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Most SaaS products lose 60-80% of signups before activation. The framework provides a systematic approach rather than guessing which tactic to apply first. The hardest part is defining the right activation event — it must be a behavior that predicts long-term retention, not a milestone that merely signals engagement (e.g. "completed onboarding" is less predictive than "shared a doc within 48h").</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Signups are coming in but week-1 retention is mediocre and the bottleneck is unknown.</item>
        <item>Choosing or validating an activation event ("aha moment") that should correlate with D30 retention.</item>
        <item>Mapping a funnel, instrumenting missing events, and prioritizing which drop-off to attack first.</item>
        <item>Building a weekly activation dashboard and experiment backlog.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch: design activation into onboarding from day one; no remediation framework needed.</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF: low activation may signal wrong product or wrong audience — fix the product first, not the funnel.</item>
        <item>Sales-led B2B: activation happens in human-led implementation; CSM playbooks beat self-serve frameworks.</item>
        <item>Single-session utility tools where every visit is an activation.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="activation-framework-7-steps">
      <p>Systematic process from defining the activation event through iterative optimization, with funnel mapping example.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define activation as the specific behavior that correlates most strongly with D30+ retention — not as completing onboarding or creating an account.</statement>
        <rationale>Internal milestones ("completed setup wizard") are easy to optimize but predict nothing. Retention-correlated behaviors ("shared a doc within 48h", "ran 2 reports within 7d") are the real signal.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="bad">
        <note>Activation = "completed 5-step onboarding wizard" — optimizing this can increase completion 40% with zero retention improvement.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Activation = "added 3 contacts within 24h" — users who do this have 3x D30 retention vs those who do not. Validate by comparing retention curves for users who did vs did not perform the event within N days of signup.</note>
      </example>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Calculate baseline activation rate and time-to-activation before making any changes; segment by acquisition channel to identify if the problem is channel-specific.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a baseline, you cannot measure improvement. Channel segmentation often reveals that the problem is concentrated in one source (e.g. paid ads have 15% activation vs organic at 45%).</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Email tool funnel mapping:
  Step 1: Signup           100%
  Step 2: Verify email      70%  (-30% — highest drop)
  Step 3: Connect account   50%  (-20%)
  Step 4: Import contacts   35%  (-15%)
  Step 5: Send first email  25%  (-10%) ← ACTIVATION

Priority order: fix Step 1→2 first (biggest absolute drop).
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Watch at least 20 session recordings before forming hypotheses; agents cannot replace qualitative pattern recognition from real user behavior.</statement>
        <rationale>Funnel data shows where users drop but not why. Session recordings reveal whether the cause is confusion, missing information, performance issues, or unclear next steps.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Friction reduction and motivation tactics:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Friction: too many form fields, slow load, required integrations → reduce, pre-fill, defer</item>
        <item>Friction: no guidance after signup → add tooltips, coach marks, sample data</item>
        <item>Motivation: users can activate but do not want to yet → show value earlier, add social proof</item>
        <item>Motivation: wrong user type → segment onboarding by use case</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="diagnosing-low-activation">
      <p>Symptom-to-cause mapping, ICE scoring for prioritization, and agent-specific gotchas.</p>

      <p>Diagnosis by symptom:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Drop at signup step → friction: too many fields, no SSO, password requirements → reduce to email only, add magic link</item>
        <item>Drop at onboarding → complexity: too many steps, no guidance → simplify to 3-5 steps, add templates</item>
        <item>Drop before Aha moment → unclear next step → add tooltips, coach marks, activation checklist</item>
        <item>Drop at core action → UX problems → user test and fix specific friction</item>
        <item>Long time to activate → too many steps → remove non-essential steps, pre-fill defaults</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Score every experiment hypothesis on Impact (1-10), Confidence (1-10), and Ease (1-10); prioritize by ICE average; run highest-scoring experiment first.</statement>
        <rationale>ICE forces explicit judgment about ROI before investing engineering effort. Without scoring, teams default to easiest changes (high Ease, low Impact) rather than highest-value work.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <reference path="templates/ice.py">Python ICE scorer for ranking activation experiments</reference>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Optimizing for high-completion events rather than retention-correlated behaviors.</description>
        <reason>Agents pick "completed onboarding" as activation because it has 80% completion vs "created a report" at 25%. But only the latter predicts retention. Always force the agent to score activation event candidates against D30 retention lift.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using "time-to-activation" without a fixed window definition.</description>
        <reason>Leaving the window open inflates activation rate and breaks week-over-week comparisons. Define window explicitly: e.g. "activated within 7 days of signup".</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Attacking the biggest funnel drop-off without confirming it is causal.</description>
        <reason>Funnel drop-offs are correlated with activation failure but not always the direct cause. Confirm with session recordings and user interviews before building the fix.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Reducing signup friction before fixing downstream activation steps.</description>
        <reason>More signups with the same downstream funnel just inflates the top-of-funnel number. Fix activation rate before expanding acquisition.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration">
      <p>Agentic workflow and failure modes specific to activation optimization.</p>

      <p>On `opus`, a strategist defines/audits the activation event and reviews retention correlation. A `sonnet` analyst maps the funnel from event data, identifies top 3 drop-offs, and writes hypothesis cards (ICE-scored). A `haiku` ops agent computes weekly activation rate, segments by source/persona, and posts deltas. A `sonnet` copy agent drafts onboarding microcopy, tooltip text, and email-sequence variants for top experiments.</p>

      <p>AI-agent gotchas:</p>
      <list>
        <item>The agent will pick a high-completion event as "activation" because it looks healthy — force it to score against retention lift, not absolute frequency.</item>
        <item>Funnel events with the same name across web/app but different definitions cause silent drop-offs; agent must list event-name + platform pairs.</item>
        <item>"Time-to-activation" needs a fixed window (e.g. 7d); leaving it open inflates rate and breaks comparisons week-over-week.</item>
        <item>Onboarding-flow tools (Appcues/Pendo) cache content; the agent must invalidate or version-tag flows when shipping copy changes.</item>
        <item>Don't let the agent ship microcopy variants directly to production — route through a feature-flag and an A/B test.</item>
        <item>Cross-device users get attributed twice; require the agent to use a stable user-id, not anonymous distinct_id.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ice.py" purpose="Python ICE scorer for ranking activation experiments."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com"/>
      <link href="https://andrewchen.com/"/>
      <ref slug="cohort-basics"/>
      <ref slug="ab-testing-setup"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
