<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="retention-compliance Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for retention-compliance. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Address retention levers in this priority order: manager relationship, growth opportunity, recognition, compensation, flexibility. Fixing compensation first when manager issues exist wastes budget.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Gallup's State of the American Workplace consistently identifies the manager relationship as the primary driver of voluntary turnover, above compensation. Compensation interventions have a 3-6 month effect before the underlying issue resurfaces.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conduct stay interviews with high performers quarterly; never substitute exit interviews for stay interviews — exit interviews surface the reason after the cost is sunk.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">By the time a high performer has accepted a competing offer, the retention cost has already been paid. Stay interviews identify flight risk 3-6 months earlier, when low-cost interventions are still available.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Aggregate exit interview themes quarterly; a single exit reason is anecdote, a pattern across 5+ exits is a systemic issue requiring action.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Exit interview data is only actionable when analyzed as a trend. Individual exit reasons are often rationalized post-decision; patterns reveal the underlying organizational driver.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a 9-box talent review annually for all employees; classify by current performance and assessed potential; identify flight risk separately from performance.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The 9-box surfaces succession gaps (no one in the "high performance, high potential" quadrant for a critical role) and retention priorities (Stars with high flight risk need immediate stay interviews).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit every interview question against the protected-class list before using it in a live interview; a single non-compliant question in a recorded or documented interview creates EEOC exposure.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">In the US, protected classes under Title VII, ADEA, ADA, and equivalent state laws include race, color, religion, sex, national origin, age (40+), and disability. Questions that reasonably imply any of these — even indirectly (e.g., "When did you graduate?") — are non-compliant regardless of intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require a diverse candidate slate of at least two underrepresented candidates in every final interview round before extending an offer.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LinkedIn and McKinsey data consistently show that when only one underrepresented candidate reaches the final round, statistical chance of hire approaches zero. The diverse slate requirement creates the conditions where merit-based selection is possible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit the full recruiting process annually against six dimensions: time-to-fill delays, candidate drop-off patterns, hire quality, candidate experience, compliance, and cost; act on at least one finding per audit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Process audits without required action items become reporting exercises. Assigning each finding an owner and a follow-up date converts audit outputs into improvements.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
