<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-retention-strategies" title="Employee Retention Strategies">
  <summary>Stay interview framework, exit interview analysis process, talent review using the 9-box grid, and the five primary retention levers.</summary>

  <section title="Retention Levers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Address retention levers in this priority order: manager relationship, growth opportunity, recognition, compensation, flexibility. Fixing compensation first when manager issues exist wastes budget.</statement>
      <rationale>Gallup's State of the American Workplace consistently identifies the manager relationship as the primary driver of voluntary turnover, above compensation. Compensation interventions have a 3-6 month effect before the underlying issue resurfaces.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Lever Definitions">
      <p>Manager relationship: psychological safety, feedback quality, career investment, fairness. Growth: visible career paths, L&amp;D budget, stretch assignments, promotion criteria. Recognition: regular appreciation (specific, timely), bonuses tied to outcomes, peer recognition. Compensation: market-rate base pay with regular benchmarking; pay equity across demographics. Flexibility: remote or hybrid options, schedule flexibility, time-off policies.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Stay Interview Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Conduct stay interviews with high performers quarterly; never substitute exit interviews for stay interviews — exit interviews surface the reason after the cost is sunk.</statement>
      <rationale>By the time a high performer has accepted a competing offer, the retention cost has already been paid. Stay interviews identify flight risk 3-6 months earlier, when low-cost interventions are still available.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Stay Interview Questions">
      <p>"What do you look forward to at work each day?" — surfaces engagement drivers to protect.</p>
      <p>"What would make you consider leaving?" — surfaces risk factors before they become decisions.</p>
      <p>"What would you change about your role or the team?" — surfaces friction points.</p>
      <p>"Do you feel recognized for your contributions?" — surfaces recognition gaps.</p>
      <p>"What can I do to better support you?" — surfaces manager action items.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Exit Interview Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Aggregate exit interview themes quarterly; a single exit reason is anecdote, a pattern across 5+ exits is a systemic issue requiring action.</statement>
      <rationale>Exit interview data is only actionable when analyzed as a trend. Individual exit reasons are often rationalized post-decision; patterns reveal the underlying organizational driver.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>Conduct exit interviews with a neutral HR person, not the direct manager.</item>
      <item>Use standardized questions: why leaving, what could have retained you, would you recommend us?</item>
      <item>Code free-text responses into 5-8 categories quarterly.</item>
      <item>Report themes with volume and trend to leadership.</item>
      <item>Track whether recommended actions from prior quarters were implemented.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="9-Box Talent Review">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a 9-box talent review annually for all employees; classify by current performance and assessed potential; identify flight risk separately from performance.</statement>
      <rationale>The 9-box surfaces succession gaps (no one in the "high performance, high potential" quadrant for a critical role) and retention priorities (Stars with high flight risk need immediate stay interviews).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="9-Box Grid">
      <p>Stars (high performance, high potential): highest retention priority; development-investment candidates; flight risk if unchallenged. Rising stars (medium performance, high potential): need stretch assignments to develop. Experts (high performance, low potential): stable, high-value; do not over-promote. Risk (low performance, high potential): unclear situation; reassign or investigate engagement. Stable (medium performance, medium potential): core workforce; maintain with standard development. Exit candidates (low performance, low potential): performance management, not retention investment.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
</text>
