<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-compliance-and-dei" title="Hiring Compliance and DEI Practices">
  <summary>Legal compliance requirements at each hiring funnel stage, DEI practices per stage, and process audit framework for identifying legal and equity risk.</summary>

  <section title="Hiring Compliance by Stage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Audit every interview question against the protected-class list before using it in a live interview; a single non-compliant question in a recorded or documented interview creates EEOC exposure.</statement>
      <rationale>In the US, protected classes under Title VII, ADEA, ADA, and equivalent state laws include race, color, religion, sex, national origin, age (40+), and disability. Questions that reasonably imply any of these — even indirectly (e.g., "When did you graduate?") — are non-compliant regardless of intent.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Compliance Requirements per Stage">
      <p>Job posting: no discriminatory language (age, gender, race markers); include EEO statement; publish salary range where required by law (California, Colorado, NYC, others).</p>
      <p>Application: only job-relevant questions; no questions about prior salary history (illegal in many US jurisdictions); no protected-class questions.</p>
      <p>Screening: screen on job-related criteria only; document screening criteria before reviewing candidates; apply criteria consistently to all applicants.</p>
      <p>Interviews: no questions about age, religion, national origin, marital status, disability, pregnancy, arrest record (vs. conviction in many states), or union membership. All questions must be job-related.</p>
      <p>Assessments: use only validated, job-related assessments; document validity evidence; ensure accessibility for candidates with disabilities (ADA).</p>
      <p>Background checks: obtain written consent per FCRA (US); do not use arrest records without individualized assessment; follow "ban the box" laws in applicable jurisdictions.</p>
      <p>Offers: apply consistent compensation criteria; conduct pay equity analysis before extending offers; document offer rationale.</p>
      <p>Records: retain applications, interview notes, and scorecards per EEOC guidelines (1 year for most records; 2 years for federal contractors).</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="DEI Hiring Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require a diverse candidate slate of at least two underrepresented candidates in every final interview round before extending an offer.</statement>
      <rationale>LinkedIn and McKinsey data consistently show that when only one underrepresented candidate reaches the final round, statistical chance of hire approaches zero. The diverse slate requirement creates the conditions where merit-based selection is possible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="DEI Practices per Stage">
      <p>Sourcing: proactively source from HBCUs, women's colleges, coding bootcamps, and community organizations; employee referral programs without diversity goals amplify existing demographic homogeneity.</p>
      <p>Job postings: use inclusive language tools (Textio, Gender Decoder); remove gendered language and unnecessary requirements; add explicit statement of flexible work options.</p>
      <p>Screening: run blind resume review (remove name, graduation year, school) for first pass; use standardized criteria applied consistently.</p>
      <p>Interviews: require diverse interview panels; brief all panelists on the scoring rubric and behavioral anchors before the loop begins; debrief includes explicit anti-bias check ("Are any concerns about the candidate actually about a non-job-related characteristic?").</p>
      <p>Offers: run pay equity analysis comparing the offer to current employees in the same role/level/geography before extending; close unexplained gaps before the offer is made.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Process Audit Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Audit the full recruiting process annually against six dimensions: time-to-fill delays, candidate drop-off patterns, hire quality, candidate experience, compliance, and cost; act on at least one finding per audit.</statement>
      <rationale>Process audits without required action items become reporting exercises. Assigning each finding an owner and a follow-up date converts audit outputs into improvements.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Audit Dimensions">
      <p>Time-to-fill: where are the delays? Which roles/levels/departments consistently exceed the benchmark?</p>
      <p>Drop-off: at which stage do candidates exit? Is drop-off equal across demographic groups or concentrated?</p>
      <p>Quality: are hires meeting expectations at 90 days and 1 year? Are any sources or channels producing systematically lower quality?</p>
      <p>Candidate experience: what do post-process surveys show? What are the common friction points?</p>
      <p>Compliance: are all interview questions documented and compliant? Are records retained correctly? Are assessments validated?</p>
      <p>Cost: where is cost-per-hire above target? Can any stage be optimized without quality trade-off?</p>
    </section>
  </section>
</text>
