<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="django-serializers Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for DRF serializer design. Each is checkable by AST inspection or a code-review checklist.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-input-output-split" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every endpoint that both accepts data and returns data MUST have separate Input (`EntityCreateRequest`, `EntityUpdateRequest`) and Output (`EntityResponse`, `EntityListResponse`) serializers. Both MUST inherit from `serializers.Serializer`. Forbid `ModelSerializer` with `fields = "__all__"`. Forbid one serializer used for both directions.</statement>
      <rationale source="DRF docs https://www.django-rest-framework.org/api-guide/serializers/ + Vinta best-practices https://www.vintasoftware.com/blog/how-i-test-my-drf-serializers">A single shared serializer paired with `__all__` leaks every new model field into the response automatically. Splitting the directions makes the API surface auditable and stable against model changes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-no-business-logic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>`validate_*()` and `validate()` methods MUST do shape/format checks only — no ORM queries, no service calls, no model creation/mutation. Cross-field business rules (uniqueness, ownership, side-effects) belong in `services.py`.</statement>
      <rationale source="HackSoft Django styleguide + DRF docs">Database access in validate() runs outside the service transaction; a service rollback leaves orphan state. Business logic in validate() bypasses the unit-testable service layer and conflates the validation step with the action step.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-explicit-fields" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output serializers MUST list every exposed field explicitly. Forbid `fields = "__all__"`, forbid `exclude = [...]` as the security mechanism. Sensitive fields (password, secret, token, api_key, is_staff, internal_*) MUST be absent from the output serializer's field list.</statement>
      <rationale source="OWASP API Security Cheat Sheet">An explicit allowlist is safe-by-default when a model gains a new field; an excludelist requires every author to remember the rule. Empirically, secrets leak via missed exclude entries in every codebase audited.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-explicit-field-options" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Input serializer field MUST set `required`, `allow_blank`, `allow_null`, and (when applicable) `default` explicitly. Use `write_only=True` for password / secret fields on Input. Use `read_only=True` for derived fields on Output. Do not rely on implicit DRF defaults.</statement>
      <rationale source="DRF field options docs https://www.django-rest-framework.org/api-guide/fields/#core-arguments">DRF defaults change between major versions and depend on field type. Explicit options make the API contract visible in source and stable across upgrades.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-nested-from-selector" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Nested serializers MUST consume pre-fetched data provided by a selector (via `select_related` / `prefetch_related`). Forbid `source="...all"` or `PrimaryKeyRelatedField(queryset=...)` patterns that trigger ad-hoc queries during render. Use `is_valid(raise_exception=True)` in views and pass `serializer.validated_data` to the service.</statement>
      <rationale source="DRF + Django Selectors pattern">A nested serializer that triggers its own query reintroduces N+1 inside the response phase, invisible to selector-level N+1 tests. `raise_exception=True` standardises 400 responses across endpoints.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
