<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="user-research-at-scale">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>user-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Run research in parallel with product velocity using AI-augmented pipelines: transcription, tagging, clustering, with human verification at 10% and a repository as single source of truth.</summary>
    <category>research</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>ai-augmented</tag>
      <tag>research-operations</tag>
      <tag>transcription</tag>
      <tag>tagging</tag>
    </tags>
    <applies-to>both</applies-to>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>User Research at Scale</title>

    <summary>An operating model for running research in parallel with product velocity using AI-augmented pipelines: automated transcription, agent-driven tagging and clustering, human verification on a sampled 10%, and a repository as the single source of truth. Humans own study design, ethics, interpretation, and stakeholder framing; agents own transcription, tagging, clustering, and report drafting.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Traditional one-researcher-at-a-time cadence cannot keep up with multi-squad product velocity. AI tools (transcription, sentiment tagging, affinity clustering) compress the mechanical work by 5-10x, but only when paired with human quality gates — auto-tagging errors compound silently without them. The bottleneck shifts from "who do we talk to" to "what do we do with insights," which requires a repository strategy and a decisions-ledger to prove ROI.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Product velocity outpaces a single research team — multiple squads need findings same-week, not month-later.</item>
        <item>Continuous-discovery operating model where every PM/designer is expected to run small studies, with researchers as enablers.</item>
        <item>High-volume unmoderated testing programmes (1k+ recordings/quarter) where AI-assisted analysis is a force multiplier.</item>
        <item>Multinational rollouts that require parallel sessions across regions/locales.</item>
        <item>Mature ResearchOps practice with a repository, intake, and recruitment infrastructure already in place.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF startups with fewer than 50 paying users — qualitative depth from a researcher trumps scale.</item>
        <item>Studies requiring sensitive populations (children, healthcare, accessibility) where panel quality and ethics review must dominate over throughput.</item>
        <item>Strategic generative research (problem framing) — small samples with senior researcher synthesis still wins.</item>
        <item>Regulated environments (HIPAA, GDPR with special-category data) where AI auto-tagging is restricted.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="assembly-line-model">
      <p>Structure the research pipeline as an assembly line: recruit → moderate (human or unmoderated) → transcribe → tag → cluster → report → publish. Agents own transcription, tagging, clustering, and report drafting; humans own study design, ethics, interpretation, and stakeholder framing. Mixing agent and human responsibilities without clear ownership lets errors propagate through all downstream stages silently.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use a research repository (Dovetail, Marvin, EnjoyHQ, Notably) as the single source of truth. Have agents push artefacts there with stable IDs. Run a "human verifier" subagent that samples 10% of agent-tagged segments per study and gates publication on agreement ≥ 90%.</statement>
        <rationale>Scaling research without a repository strategy produces archived reports nobody reads. The verifier catches AI auto-tagging errors that vary by domain—sentiment models trained on product reviews mis-tag user-research segments (heavy use of past tense, hypothetical framing). Build a "decisions ledger" linking tagged insights to shipped product changes; the ratio is the actual ROI of scaling.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Treat the system as an assembly line: recruit → moderate (human or unmoderated) → transcribe → tag → cluster → report → publish. Agents own transcription, tagging, clustering, and report drafting; humans own study design, ethics, interpretation, and stakeholder framing. Use a repository (Dovetail, Marvin, EnjoyHQ, Notably) as the single source of truth, and have agents push artefacts there with stable IDs. Run a "human verifier" subagent that samples 10% of agent-tagged segments per study and gates publication on agreement ≥ 90%.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Recommended subagents: a purpose-built research-synthesiser subagent that ingests transcripts + existing tag taxonomy, proposes new tags only when frequency ≥ N, emits affinity clusters with quotes. Use faion-brainstorm to convert a synthesis into stakeholder-specific framings (PM, design, exec). A bias-watcher subagent that flags leading questions in moderator scripts before recording starts. Use faion-improver for quarterly audit of repository signal-to-noise ratio (% of tagged segments referenced in shipped decisions). A recruit-screener subagent that drafts screener questions and grades panel responses for fraud signals.</statement>
        <rationale>These patterns isolate concerns and reduce the burden on any single agent, allowing each to specialize in its domain.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Tagging prompt with taxonomy enforcement">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Given 28 unmoderated session transcripts (file IDs S1..S28) and the tag
taxonomy in taxonomy.json, tag every utterance. For each tag with >=5
segments, output a cluster with: definition, 3 verbatim quotes (with
timestamp), conflicting evidence if any. Do not invent new tags; if a
segment fits none, mark untagged for human review.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Panel fraud screening prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Score these 12 screener responses 0-1 for panel-fraud risk (copy-paste,
gibberish, suspiciously fast, contradictory answers). Provide reasoning
for any score >0.5.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="platform-capabilities">
      <p>Platform tiers by team size: small teams benefit from built-in automation and AI analysis in tools like Maze and Sprig; large teams need scalable panels (Userlytics 2M+, UserTesting), collaboration across squads, and adaptable workflows with repository integration.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Stratify panels (role, geography, tenure) and report on stratification balance per study. "n=200 random" is a misleading scale claim without stratification disclosure.</statement>
        <rationale>Large panels are not high-quality panels. Panel quality (Userlytics, UserTesting) varies; professional respondents and geographic clustering bias results.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Pair every quantitative claim from unmoderated tools with at least three verbatim quotes. Raw numbers without voice rarely change behaviour.</statement>
        <rationale>Scaling produces numbers at the cost of narrative; insights without quotation become abstract and fail to resonate with stakeholders.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Cap unmoderated panel reliance at ~60-70% of mix. Complement with moderated and longitudinal studies for depth.</statement>
        <rationale>Unmoderated testing cannot capture motivations, context, or unexpected paths that a moderator would pursue.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Standardise a repository tag taxonomy first. Let no study propose new tags without a curator review.</statement>
        <rationale>Tag drift silently fragments analysis; a single curator maintains consistency across studies and squads.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use AI for first-pass tagging only. Human verification on a sampled 10% before publication gates quality.</statement>
        <rationale>AI errors compound silently through downstream analysis; verification gates catch them before insights reach stakeholders.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Build a "decisions ledger" linking tagged insights to shipped product changes. The ratio is the actual ROI of scaling.</statement>
        <rationale>Without evidence that insights changed product, scaling research looks like overhead rather than investment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Watch for over-recruitment of "professional respondents". Rotate panels and audit completion times.</statement>
        <rationale>Professional respondents answer differently than real users; rotation and audit reduce systematic bias from repeat panelists.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="localization">
      <rule>
        <statement>Transcribe in source language, translate after tagging, never the reverse.</statement>
        <rationale>Translation loses tag-relevant nuance. Code-switching and cultural idioms that carry emotional weight in the original disappear in translation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-summarisers compress 30-minute interviews to one paragraph and lose disconfirming evidence.</description>
        <reason>Compression loses context; require quote retention with timestamps for every claim.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Sentiment models trained on product reviews mis-tag user-research segments (heavy use of past tense, hypothetical framing).</description>
        <reason>User-research speech patterns differ fundamentally from product reviews; retrain or use domain-specific sentiment models.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM "synthetic users" used to validate willingness-to-pay or behaviour.</description>
        <reason>Synthetic users are sycophantic; never use them to validate go/no-go decisions, only to seed prompts and edge cases.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Diarisation errors mis-attribute moderator speech to participants, biasing tag distributions.</description>
        <reason>Always verify speaker tags before clustering; diarisation accuracy drops on overlapping speech and accents.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Multi-agent pipelines without idempotency reprocess the same recording when re-run, double-counting tags.</description>
        <reason>Require deduplication keys (recording ID + run ID) before any tagging write.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent pipelines push transcripts to a repository without PII redaction.</description>
        <reason>GDPR/CCPA require PII redaction before storage; pair with password-scrubber-agent or equivalent before pushing transcripts to a repo.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>"AI follow-up question" features that ask leading questions.</description>
        <reason>Review generated probes before they ship to participants; leading questions bias responses and violate research ethics.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools and research platforms that support at-scale operations:</p>

      <p>Transcription and diarisation: AssemblyAI, Deepgram, Whisper, whisperx (OSS local high-accuracy). Repository platforms: Dovetail API, Marvin (User Interviews) API, EnjoyHQ, Notably, Aurelius. Unmoderated testing: Maze API, UserTesting API. Panel management: Userlytics API, dscout API. Scheduling automation: Calendly, Iteratively. Local transcription: whisperx (OSS).</p>

      <p>Services by type: UserTesting (largest panel, AI insights add-on, agent-friendly REST API). Userlytics (2M+ panel, AI analytics, REST API). Maze (survey + prototype testing, AI follow-ups, REST API). dscout (mobile ethnography at scale, partial agent integration). Dovetail (repo with built-in AI tagging, REST API). Marvin (repo + recruit, strong AI coding, REST API). Notably (AI-native repo, REST API). Sprig (in-product micro-surveys, AI summarise, REST API). Lookback (live moderated, weaker AI integration). Respondent.io (high-quality recruit, niche panels, REST API). EnjoyHQ (repo for standardised tags across organisation).</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/tag-session.py" purpose="Whisper + Anthropic pipeline for transcription and taxonomy tagging at scale"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="user-personas-archetypes"/>
      <ref slug="interview-design-mom-test"/>
      <ref slug="pain-point-mining"/>
      <link href="https://researchops.community"/>
      <link href="https://wetrustresearch.com"/>
    </see-also>

  </content>
</methodology>
