<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-webinar-planning Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-webinar-planning. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select webinar format based on marketing objective before planning any content or promotion.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Format determines conversion style: educational webinars nurture; demo webinars close; workshops create premium offers. Mismatched format and objective produce low post-webinar conversion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock topic, date, platform, and whether there is a co-host before requesting any copy from an agent.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Changing these after drafting requires full regeneration of all assets; sequential locking prevents rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Follow the 60-minute structure: 5 min welcome, 5 min hook, 25 min content, 5 min soft pitch, 15 min Q&amp;A, 5 min close/CTA.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Deviating from this structure — especially skipping the soft pitch before Q&amp;A — leaves conversion on the table.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start promotion 3 weeks before the event; multi-channel coverage is required — email-only promotion caps registrations.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-channel (email-only) promotion consistently underperforms multi-channel by 3-5x in registrations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Registration form must have a maximum of 2 fields (email + name); each additional field reduces conversion by 20-30%.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Friction on the registration page is the second most common cause of low signups after weak promotion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide topic, audience, date/time, email list size, platform, and goal before requesting any webinar assets.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Under-specified prompts produce placeholder copy that requires full rewrite; these 6 inputs produce deployable drafts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
