<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-planning-and-promotion" title="Webinar Format Selection and Promotion Timeline">
  <summary>Format types, planning decisions, multi-channel promotion timeline, and registration page elements.</summary>

  <section title="Format Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select webinar format based on marketing objective before planning any content or promotion.</statement>
      <rationale>Format determines conversion style: educational webinars nurture; demo webinars close; workshops create premium offers. Mismatched format and objective produce low post-webinar conversion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Educational: lead generation, soft CTA, nurture path</item>
      <item>Demo: product showcase, direct CTA to trial or purchase</item>
      <item>Q&amp;A/AMA: community building, relationship-first</item>
      <item>Panel/Interview: authority building through association</item>
      <item>Workshop: deep engagement, premium offer conversion</item>
      <item>Launch event: product launches, urgency-based close</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Planning Decisions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock topic, date, platform, and whether there is a co-host before requesting any copy from an agent.</statement>
      <rationale>Changing these after drafting requires full regeneration of all assets; sequential locking prevents rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Duration: 45-60 min (30 min content + 15-30 min Q&amp;A)</item>
      <item>Timing: Tuesday-Thursday, 11am or 2pm in audience's primary timezone</item>
      <item>Frequency: Monthly is sustainable for solo founders</item>
      <item>Platforms: Zoom, Demio, Livestorm (Demio/Livestorm have better registration APIs)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow the 60-minute structure: 5 min welcome, 5 min hook, 25 min content, 5 min soft pitch, 15 min Q&amp;A, 5 min close/CTA.</statement>
      <rationale>Deviating from this structure — especially skipping the soft pitch before Q&amp;A — leaves conversion on the table.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Promotion Timeline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start promotion 3 weeks before the event; multi-channel coverage is required — email-only promotion caps registrations.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-channel (email-only) promotion consistently underperforms multi-channel by 3-5x in registrations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>3 weeks before: announce, start email + social promotion</item>
      <item>2 weeks before: guest post pitch, podcast appearance pitch, partner cross-promotion</item>
      <item>1 week before: email reminder sequence starts (3 emails)</item>
      <item>Day before: reminder email</item>
      <item>Day of: final reminder 1 hour before start</item>
      <item>After: replay email to registrants who did not attend</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Registration Page Elements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Registration form must have a maximum of 2 fields (email + name); each additional field reduces conversion by 20-30%.</statement>
      <rationale>Friction on the registration page is the second most common cause of low signups after weak promotion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Headline: problem statement (not "Join our webinar")</item>
      <item>Date/time with timezone converter link</item>
      <item>Host credibility: photo + 1-2 sentence bio</item>
      <item>3-4 specific learning outcomes as bullets</item>
      <item>Replay promise for those who cannot attend live</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Registration rate: 3% of page visits (good), 10%+ (great)</item>
      <item>Promotion email open rate: 25% (good), 40%+ (great)</item>
      <item>Show-up rate: 30% of registrants live (typical), 45%+ (good)</item>
      <item>Partner referrals: 10% of registrations (good), 30%+ (great)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
