<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Steerco Meeting Playbook Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the steerco-meeting-playbook methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="preread-3-days-early" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-read pack must land in attendee inboxes minimum 3 business days (72h) before the meeting. Same-day pre-reads are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bezos 6-pager practice; executive scheduling reality">Senior stakeholders read pre-reads in transit, not live; &lt;72h leads to 'let me get back to you' defers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ask-list-binary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Steerco must include a numbered 'Asks' section. Each ask in the form 'We ask Steerco to approve/reject/defer X by date Y'. Vague asks ('guidance on Z') are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-forcing meeting design">Without explicit binary asks, the meeting ends with vague nods that no one is bound by.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cancel-if-no-decisions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the asks list at T-5 days contains zero substantive decisions, the meeting must be cancelled and a written status memo sent instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meeting-discipline practice">Reputational cost of cancelled-with-good-reason is far lower than the credibility cost of a 90-min status read-out.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="decision-memo-48h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A decision memo must be sent to all attendees within 48 hours of the meeting: each ask + decision + rationale + owner + deadline + deferrals.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decisions-log discipline">Steerco decisions are referenced months later; without a written memo, parties remember the meeting differently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="asks-not-status-time-split" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agenda time must allocate ≤30% to status snapshot and ≥50% to asks + decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meeting-time accounting">Steerco attendee time is the most expensive minute in the project's hour-economy; status is the pre-read's job.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Forum is decorative — sponsor delegates, no quorum, decisions made elsewhere</item>
      <item>Project is in active rescue → daily war room + ad-hoc exec calls instead</item>
      <item>No decisions outstanding for this cycle — cancel the meeting (rule r3)</item>
      <item>A weekly status report already covers the audience — Steerco would duplicate</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
