<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="business-model-research">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>market-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Peer-benchmark table methodology: classify 8-15 comparables into five revenue archetypes, extract P25/P50/P75 distributions, overlay founder plan against distribution.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>business-model</tag>
      <tag>benchmarking</tag>
      <tag>revenue-archetypes</tag>
      <tag>market-research</tag>
      <tag>comp-analysis</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Business Model Research (Market-Researcher Lens)</title>
    <summary>Business model research at the market-researcher level produces a peer-benchmark table — not a single canvas. The methodology classifies 8-15 comparables (including failed and acquihired peers) into five revenue archetypes (subscription, one-time, transaction, advertising, marketplace), extracts P25/P50/P75 distributions for ARPU, gross margin, gross logo retention, NDR, and CAC payback, then overlays the founder's plan against the distribution. The core rule: always include at least 2 dead or acquihired comparables — without them, medians overstate viability by 20-40%.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Survivorship bias in comp sets is the primary failure mode: public-listed comps run higher gross margin (78-82%) than venture-stage privates (60-70%) because of scale. "Tiered subscription" is the default LLM answer for any SaaS, regardless of economics. NDR greater than 110% can hide gross logo churn greater than 25%. A distribution-first approach (P25/P50/P75 per archetype) prevents single-comp dominance and false precision, and explicitly separates the market-researcher deliverable (distributions) from the researcher sibling deliverable (a single canvas).</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-spec market-side answer to "what model do peers in this category actually use?"</item>
        <item>Investor or board memo: produce an industry revenue-model distribution by archetype</item>
        <item>Pricing committee input: pull ARPU, gross margin, NDR, and rule-of-40 from a public-comp set</item>
        <item>Category entry decision: rank 5-15 candidate categories by median LTV:CAC and CAC payback</item>
        <item>M&amp;A scoping: build a comps table mapping the target's model to nearest public proxy</item>
        <item>Cross-checking a researcher-mode canvas — verify the founder's chosen archetype against industry base rates</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-product canvas and unit-economics design — that is the researcher/business-model-research sibling's scope</item>
        <item>Markets with fewer than 3 public or well-documented private comparables — table is statistically meaningless</item>
        <item>Hyper-local services where public comps do not transfer — use local-market survey instead</item>
        <item>Pre-revenue categories with no precedent — peer benchmarking is misleading; use analogous-markets or first-principles-pricing</item>
        <item>Regulated verticals where revenue model is dictated by law — research the regulation, not the comps</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="comp-universe-construction">
      <rule>
        <statement>Build the comp universe before classifying the founder's idea. Anchoring on the founder's preferred archetype biases the universe selection and produces a confirmation table, not a benchmark.</statement>
        <rationale>If you know the founder wants "subscription" before pulling comps, you unconsciously include more subscription companies. The benchmark must be built blind to the preferred conclusion.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include at least 2 dead or acquihired comparables in the comp set. Without them, medians overstate viability by 20-40%.</statement>
        <rationale>Survivorship bias: the public-listed and well-documented companies are the ones that succeeded. The failures and acquihires that define the real distribution are invisible unless explicitly sought.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="comp-set-requirements">
        <list>
          <item>Minimum 8 comparables; downgrade from "benchmark" to "case studies" if fewer than 8 are available</item>
          <item>Mix required: public (S-1/10-K), late-stage private (Crunchbase), acquired (M&amp;A press), dead (Crunchbase "Closed")</item>
          <item>At least 20% private and at least 10% dead or acquihired</item>
          <item>Cap any single comp's weight at 1/N — one dominant peer in a 5-comp set is no longer a benchmark</item>
          <item>Cohort by stage (seed/Series-B/listed) AND geography (US/EU/RoW) before computing medians</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="archetype-classification">
        <list>
          <item>subscription: more than 60% of revenue from recurring payments</item>
          <item>one-time: more than 60% from non-recurring purchases</item>
          <item>transaction: more than 60% from per-transaction fees (including marketplace commission)</item>
          <item>advertising: more than 60% from ad inventory or sponsorships</item>
          <item>marketplace: commission + payments + seller subscriptions + ad fees combined (all-in take rate)</item>
          <item>hybrid: no single stream above 60%; tag with the two dominant streams and their split</item>
        </list>
        <rule>
          <statement>Never collapse a hybrid model into a single archetype. Shopify is not "subscription" — it is subscription + payments + advertising. Tag hybrid + split, or the archetype table lies.</statement>
          <rationale>Collapsing hybrid revenue models produces incorrect ARPU and gross margin medians. A "subscription" comp that is actually 40% subscription + 40% payments will distort the subscription archetype's metrics.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="definition-glossary">
        <list>
          <item>ARR: annualized recurring revenue from subscription contracts only</item>
          <item>ARPU: ARR divided by total active paying accounts</item>
          <item>ACV: annual contract value for a single customer (can differ from ARPU if multi-year discounts apply)</item>
          <item>Gross margin: (revenue - COGS) / revenue; excludes operating expenses</item>
          <item>Gross logo retention: percentage of customer accounts retained year-over-year regardless of expansion or contraction</item>
          <item>NDR (Net Dollar Retention): revenue retained + expansion - contraction - churn from the prior-year cohort</item>
        </list>
        <rule>
          <statement>Always pair NDR with gross logo retention. NDR above 110% can coexist with gross logo churn above 25% in a land-and-expand model. Reporting NDR alone hides the real churn problem.</statement>
          <rationale>NDR is a vanity metric when reported in isolation. A small base of large expanding accounts drives NDR up while the majority of smaller accounts churn — the pattern that precedes a retention crisis.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="metric-extraction-and-normalization">
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag every metric with source_url and filing_period (YYYY-Qn). Benchmarks without provenance cannot be reviewed, challenged, or refreshed.</statement>
        <rationale>Metrics cited without filing dates become unverifiable over time. Partners and product managers need to know whether a comp's metrics are from last quarter or three years ago.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="primary-sources">
        <list>
          <item>S-1 and 10-K filings: gold standard for ARR, gross margin, gross logo retention, NDR, CAC payback — use SEC EDGAR full-text search</item>
          <item>Wayback Machine pricing snapshots at filing date: list price verified at the moment the metrics were reported</item>
          <item>G2 reviewer-disclosed spend: effective pricing from actual buyers, with contract renewal context</item>
          <item>Crunchbase + press: funding stage, headcount, and M&amp;A status for private comps</item>
          <item>ChartMogul, Baremetrics, ProfitWell public benchmark datasets: pre-computed medians by ARPU band</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="normalization-rules">
        <rule>
          <statement>Convert all non-USD currency at the filing-period FX rate, not today's rate. Record the FX rate used in the comps CSV.</statement>
          <rationale>Currency moves of 10-20% per year between major pairs (EUR/USD, GBP/USD) distort historical comparisons if today's rate is applied retroactively to prior-period filings.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Strip one-time line items (professional services, implementation fees, hardware) from ARR. Include them in a separate "services revenue" column if material (above 10% of total revenue).</statement>
          <rationale>One-time revenue mixed into ARR overstates recurring revenue by 10-25% for companies with implementation-heavy sales motions, making their subscription margins appear higher than reality.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Annualize monthly numbers. Never compare a monthly ARPU from one comp against an annual ACV from another without explicit normalization.</statement>
          <rationale>Period mismatch is the most common metric error in comp tables. $100/month ARPU is $1,200 ACV, not $100 — a 12x difference that distorts tier-mix and LTV/CAC comparisons.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="pricing-page-normalization">
        <rule>
          <statement>Use Wayback Machine to pin pricing pages to the filing date for each comp. A pricing page scrape newer than the filing period quotes a different price than what the comp's financials reflect.</statement>
          <rationale>SaaS pricing changes frequently (often annually). Using today's pricing against last year's metrics produces false unit-economics comparisons because the price that generated those metrics was different.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="distribution-build-and-overlay">
      <rule>
        <statement>Quote distribution (P25/P50/P75), never a single median. Single medians create false precision and hide the strategic range the founder needs to understand.</statement>
        <rationale>The spread between P25 and P75 is the actionable signal. A P25-P75 ARPU spread of $15-$80 in a category tells the founder the model has not standardized. A $40-$50 spread tells them it has.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="distribution-build">
        <list>
          <item>Compute P25/P50/P75 per archetype AND per stage (seed/Series-B/listed)</item>
          <item>Flag comps more than 2 standard deviations from the median with a footnote explaining the cause (e.g., compute COGS, hardware revenue, geographic discount)</item>
          <item>Annotate trends: last 4-8 quarters delta per metric (e.g., usage-based share moved from 20% to 38% of new ARR in dev-tools cohort 2022-2025)</item>
          <item>Flag any P50 metric that shifts more than 10% quarter-over-quarter as a "regime change" warrant for the trend-analysis methodology</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="founder-plan-overlay">
        <list>
          <item>Green: founder's planned metric within P25-P75 for their archetype and stage</item>
          <item>Yellow: founder's metric within P10-P25 or P75-P90 — flagged as ambitious or conservative</item>
          <item>Red: founder's metric outside P10-P90 — requires explicit justification or model revision</item>
        </list>
        <rule>
          <statement>Do not rewrite the founder's plan. Emit a delta only — which cells are out-of-band and what is the most likely source of the discrepancy (model choice, stage mismatch, geography, or pricing page vs. realized ACV).</statement>
          <rationale>Rewriting the plan conflates the market-researcher deliverable (distributions) with the product-manager deliverable (decisions). The researcher surfaces the gap; the founder owns the response.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="re-run-cadence">
        <rule>
          <statement>Re-run the benchmark every 2 quarters. Flag any P50 metric that shifts more than 10% as a "regime change" and open an SDD task for the product-manager to revise the roadmap ARR targets.</statement>
          <rationale>SaaS economics shift materially over 6-month periods in fast-moving categories. A benchmark that is 12 months old guides product and pricing decisions toward the wrong target distribution.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <section name="structural-antipatterns">
        <antipattern>
          <description>Building a comp set with only public-listed companies</description>
          <reason>Survivorship bias: public companies run higher gross margin (78-82%) than venture-stage privates (60-70%) because of scale. Transplanting the median onto a $2M ARR target produces unachievable targets.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Freemium conversion cited as "20%" without denominator disclosure</description>
          <reason>Companies cite conversion against activated or "qualified" users; system-wide conversion from signups is 1-4%. Always normalize to signups or the comparison is meaningless.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>NDR reported without gross logo retention</description>
          <reason>NDR above 110% coexists with gross logo churn above 25% in land-and-expand; the combination indicates an expansion-dependent model at high risk if new logo growth slows.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Averaging cross-stage comps (seed + listed) without cohort annotation</description>
          <reason>A seed-stage Crunchbase pricing page averaged with a listed 10-K produces metrics that apply to neither stage. Cohort by stage before computing any statistic.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>

      <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
        <antipattern>
          <description>Agent reads "annualized recurring revenue" and treats it as ARPU</description>
          <reason>ARR / ARPU / ACV are three different denominators. Require a glossary block in the output before any metric. Conflating them produces LTV calculations that are 10-500x off.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Agent forces Shopify into "subscription" archetype</description>
          <reason>Shopify revenue is approximately 40% subscription, 40% payments (Merchant Solutions), and 20% other. Collapsing it to subscription distorts the subscription archetype's gross margin median by 5+ points.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Agent reports marketplace headline commission (e.g., Etsy 6.5%) as the take rate</description>
          <reason>All-in take rate including seller subscriptions, payment fees, and ad revenue is 13-18% — 2x or more the headline commission. Headline commission misleads strategic pricing decisions.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Agent uses today's pricing page against last year's filing metrics</description>
          <reason>SaaS pricing changes frequently; Wayback Machine snapshots at filing date are required to compare pricing to the financial metrics reported in the same period.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Agent ships a verdict ("this model is viable") instead of a distribution</description>
          <reason>The market-researcher deliverable is distributions (P25/P50/P75). The verdict belongs to the researcher sibling and the product manager. Inverting this boundary mixes two distinct roles.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/business-model-canvas.md" purpose="Business Model Canvas template with nine building blocks and revenue stream table"/>
      <template path="templates/unit-economics.md" purpose="Unit economics calculator with LTV, CAC, payback, and break-even sections"/>
      <template path="templates/bm-distribution.sh" purpose="Bash script emitting P25/P50/P75 per archetype from a comps.csv with a missing-N warning"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
