<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Support SLA Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding solo-support-sla-template. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="three-tier-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>SLA policy MUST define exactly 3 tiers (Community, Paid, Enterprise) with explicit response-time bands. Tier creep (4+ tiers solo) is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — solo support audits 2025">Three tiers maps to billing reality (free / paid / enterprise); more tiers create maintenance burden the solo operator cannot sustain.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="business-hours-boundary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>SLA MUST publish an explicit business-hours boundary (timezone + days). 24/7 promises by a solo operator are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — burnout postmortems">Implicit 24/7 from a solo operator burns the operator and erodes long-term reliability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="canned-reply-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Policy MUST ship ≥4 canned replies: acknowledgment, deflection-to-docs, escalation, after-hours. Free-form replies for routine cases are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Help Scout — Solo Support Setup">Canned replies preserve calendar; tone consistency improves perceived reliability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="escalation-trigger" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Policy MUST define an escalation trigger (e.g. paying customer with 0 reply in 48h auto-escalates to operator's phone). Implicit escalation is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — SLA breach audits">Without explicit trigger, breaches go unnoticed until churn signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="churn-signal-detection" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Policy MUST flag tickets with churn signals (cancellation, downgrade, 'thinking of switching') for same-day reply regardless of tier.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — churn-postmortem audits">Churn signals often bury in routine tickets; same-day reply is the highest-leverage save.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
