<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Model Onboarding Checklist — Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `model-onboarding-checklist` MUST enforce. Each rule carries an empirical anchor under `source`.</summary>

  <section title="Rules">
    <rule id="r1-named-trigger" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Onboarding is launched only by a named, observable trigger (provider announcement URL, internal request ticket, or capability gap). Vague triggers are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anthropic — model release notes (https://docs.anthropic.com/claude/docs/models-overview)">Trigger-action discipline keeps onboarding off the «cool model dropped» treadmill; explicit triggers make cadence reviewable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-four-phases" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply the four phases in order — intake → safety/eval → integration → production-gate. Phase k+1 starts only after phase k gate passes with named approver.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anthropic — model release notes (https://docs.anthropic.com/claude/docs/models-overview)">Skipping phases produces vibes-promotions: routes flipped without evals or rollback plan, which is the #1 cause of incident-worthy regressions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-eval-before-route" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No traffic share is given to the new model before its golden set + hallucination eval diff vs incumbent is recorded and signed off. Eval-before-route is mandatory.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anthropic — model release notes (https://docs.anthropic.com/claude/docs/models-overview)">Without an eval diff, regressions surface in customer-visible failures rather than in pre-prod measurements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-cost-compare" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per-task cost ($/1k tokens × expected tokens × route share) MUST be projected and compared against incumbent before production exposure.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anthropic — model release notes (https://docs.anthropic.com/claude/docs/models-overview)">Cost surprise is the second-most-common reason model promotions get rolled back; projecting cost in the gate memo makes it explicit and signed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-named-approver" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each phase gate has a named approver who signs the go/no-go memo. Anonymous «team approved» is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anthropic — model release notes (https://docs.anthropic.com/claude/docs/models-overview)">RACI discipline: rollback decisions require an accountable owner. Anonymous approvals tend to dissolve at incident time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
