<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Segmentation Process">
  <summary>Five-step segmentation process: gather data, pick 2-3 dimensions from observed variance, create MECE segments, score on 6 criteria, select target strategy.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Gather Data">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick segmentation dimensions only from observed variance in actual data sources (CRM exports, interview transcripts, analytics rollups). Do not invent dimensions from a textbook.</statement>
      <rationale>If every customer is the same on a dimension, that dimension adds no segmentation power. Dimensions that vary widely in the data are the ones that predict meaningful behavioral differences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Data sources by signal strength: customer interviews (qualitative patterns), CRM data (demographics and lifecycle), analytics (usage patterns and engagement), survey responses (preferences and attitudes), sales conversations (objections and budget).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Select Dimensions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose 2-3 dimensions maximum. A 2x2 matrix is the simplest useful shape. Three dimensions produce an 8-cell cube that is manageable. Four or more produce over-segmentation.</statement>
      <rationale>More than 3 dimensions with finite data starves each cell of evidence. Real markets have 5-7 meaningful clusters, but 2x2 is enough to make the primary-vs-secondary decision at seed stage.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Create MECE Segments">
    <rule>
      <statement>Segments must be mutually exclusive and collectively exhaustive (MECE). Every customer falls into exactly one segment.</statement>
      <rationale>Overlapping segments produce inconsistent routing: a customer who fits two segments gets conflicting messaging, pricing, and product priorities. MECE is the minimum requirement for segments to drive decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Name segments after their job-to-be-done rather than demographics ("The Overwhelmed Solo PM", not "Millennials in SaaS"). JTBD-based names drive messaging decisions; demographic names do not.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Score Segments">
    <p>Score each segment on 6 criteria, each 1-5. Weighted total: Size 20%, Growth 15%, Reachability 20%, Profitability 20%, Fit 15%, Competition 10%.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Rank segments by attractiveness order before assigning 1-5 scores. This defeats the regression-to-the-middle problem where agents score everything 3-4.</statement>
      <rationale>Rank-ordering forces the agent to commit to a preference; numerical scoring then calibrates the magnitude. Without rank-ordering first, scores cluster at 3 and provide no differentiation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For any scoring criterion lacking evidence, return "unknown" rather than estimating. Quantify each segment with two independent estimates and flag segments where they disagree by 3x or more.</statement>
      <rationale>Score inflation on unknown criteria produces a false ranking that misdirects product and marketing investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/segmentation-analysis.md">Full scoring table template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Select Target Strategy">
    <p>Three strategies: Concentrated (one segment, limited resources), Differentiated (2-3 segments with different approaches), Niche (deep focus on sub-segment in crowded market).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>For solopreneurs: commit to ONE segment until reaching $10K+ MRR. Encode the chosen target as a constitution-level decision in .aidocs/ so all downstream specs, marketing copy, and pricing inherit it.</statement>
      <rationale>Splitting attention between 2+ segments at seed stage is the fastest path to muddled positioning and slow product-market fit. The constitution entry makes the segment choice explicit and prevents drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
