<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="audience-segmentation Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for audience-segmentation as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using demographic segments alone for messaging work.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Demographics consistently underperform behavior-and-needs segments for messaging because they capture who someone is, not what they need or do. Age 25-34 tells you nothing about their workflow or pain intensity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent produces segment profiles with no CRM ID, transcript filename, or analytics row as citation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents invent plausible personas that do not exist in the data. Mitigation: require row-citations (CRM ID or transcript filename) for every claim; reject segments with zero citations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent picks "innovative" unmeasurable dimensions like "growth mindset" or "digital native".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unmeasurable dimensions cannot be used to classify real customers or build targeted campaigns. Constrain dimensions to a whitelist tied to data sources you actually have.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent assigns 3-4 scores on every criterion for every segment, producing a flat ranking table.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Regression to the mean is the default LLM behaviour when criteria are open-ended. Mitigation: force rank-ordering before scoring, and require evidence-or-"unknown" per criterion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Accepting segment size estimates from a single source (e.g. LinkedIn filter count) without a second independent estimate.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Top-down market sizing sources compound error. Validate with at least one bottom-up count (CRM rows, analytics cohort, interview N) and flag 3x+ disagreements.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent produces one fictional person (Newsletter Nate) instead of a sized cluster (N=2,400, 18% of base).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A persona is a representative individual; a segment is a sized group. Do not use persona docs for ad targeting. Require "n=" and "% of base" on every segment output.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>All input transcripts are from one quarter, producing segments that over-fit to a seasonal or recency-biased cohort.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Static segmentation from a single time window misses churn patterns and market shifts. Stratify input data over at least 2 quarters before clustering.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
