<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-gotchas" title="Segmentation Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Critical failure modes in agent-driven segmentation: hallucinated segments, score inflation, dimension drift, confusing personas with segments, human-in-the-loop gates.</summary>

  <section title="Hallucination Risks">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent produces segment profiles with no CRM ID, transcript filename, or analytics row as citation.</description>
      <reason>Agents invent plausible personas that do not exist in the data. Mitigation: require row-citations (CRM ID or transcript filename) for every claim; reject segments with zero citations.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent picks "innovative" unmeasurable dimensions like "growth mindset" or "digital native".</description>
      <reason>Unmeasurable dimensions cannot be used to classify real customers or build targeted campaigns. Constrain dimensions to a whitelist tied to data sources you actually have.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring Failures">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent assigns 3-4 scores on every criterion for every segment, producing a flat ranking table.</description>
      <reason>Regression to the mean is the default LLM behaviour when criteria are open-ended. Mitigation: force rank-ordering before scoring, and require evidence-or-"unknown" per criterion.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Accepting segment size estimates from a single source (e.g. LinkedIn filter count) without a second independent estimate.</description>
      <reason>Top-down market sizing sources compound error. Validate with at least one bottom-up count (CRM rows, analytics cohort, interview N) and flag 3x+ disagreements.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Segment vs Persona Confusion">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent produces one fictional person (Newsletter Nate) instead of a sized cluster (N=2,400, 18% of base).</description>
      <reason>A persona is a representative individual; a segment is a sized group. Do not use persona docs for ad targeting. Require "n=" and "% of base" on every segment output.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Context and Data Freshness">
    <antipattern>
      <description>All input transcripts are from one quarter, producing segments that over-fit to a seasonal or recency-biased cohort.</description>
      <reason>Static segmentation from a single time window misses churn patterns and market shifts. Stratify input data over at least 2 quarters before clustering.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-the-Loop Checkpoints">
    <list>
      <item>Approve dimensions: human confirms the 2-3 dimensions are derived from observed variance before any segment generation runs.</item>
      <item>Approve candidate segments: human reviews the 4-8 candidates before scoring. This is where hallucinated segments are caught.</item>
      <item>Approve scoring inputs: human confirms the evidence pack before agents assign scores. Without this, agents score on priors.</item>
      <item>Explicitly prompt for the anti-segment (who NOT to serve); agents skip it unless asked.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
