<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ads-budget-optimization">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>ppc-manager</domain>
    <summary>Use efficiency ratios and 70-20-10 rule to allocate budgets. Scale winners, optimize losers, maintain test reserve. Avoid premature cuts and large single-step increases.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>budget</tag>
      <tag>optimization</tag>
      <tag>allocation</tag>
      <tag>efficiency</tag>
      <tag>ppc</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Budget Optimization</title>

    <summary>Allocate budgets using efficiency ratios and the 70-20-10 rule. Scale campaigns beating target, optimize underperformers, and maintain test reserves. Avoid premature cuts and single-step budget doubling.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without a structured budget allocation framework, teams over-invest in proven campaigns until they saturate, cut new channels prematurely based on insufficient data, and collapse testing reserves under pressure. This leaves no pipeline for future winners and causes overall ROAS to decline as the mix stagnates. A defensible allocation model tied to efficiency metrics and learning thresholds prevents this drift.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Multi-campaign or multi-channel programs needing a reallocation framework</item>
        <item>Setting up automated budget rules in platform interfaces or custom dashboards</item>
        <item>Weekly or monthly budget review meetings requiring a decision matrix</item>
        <item>Scaling campaigns from test phase to production with controlled increments</item>
        <item>Running quarterly variance and incrementality analyses across channels</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-campaign programs — reallocate within the campaign via bid adjustments, not budget cuts</item>
        <item>Pre-learning-phase campaigns with fewer than 50 conversions — data is too sparse to make decisions</item>
        <item>Tactical daily bid optimization — budget allocation is a weekly/monthly cadence, not a hourly signal</item>
        <item>Exploring new channels for the first time — test with fixed budgets, not proportional allocation</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="target-cpa-calculation">
      <p>Target CPA foundation: customer lifetime value and acceptable payback periods.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Calculate target CPA from customer LTV before setting any bids; never use a CPA target derived from platform recommendations without validating against your unit economics.</statement>
        <rationale>Platform-suggested CPAs optimize for volume, not profitability. Your target must reflect actual margin and acceptable payback period.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Target CPA from LTV">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Average customer value: $500
Target LTV:CAC ratio: 3:1
Target CPA = $500 / 3 = $167
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="efficiency-ratio">
      <p>Efficiency ratio as the primary cross-campaign comparison metric.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use efficiency ratio (Target CPA / Actual CPA) as the primary cross-campaign comparison metric — it normalizes campaigns with different absolute costs onto a single scale.</statement>
        <rationale>A campaign with $30 CPA vs a target of $50 (ratio 1.67) should be scaled over a campaign with $60 CPA vs target of $100 (ratio 1.67 identical) — absolute CPA alone does not reveal which is better value.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Efficiency Ratio Scale">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Efficiency = Target CPA / Actual CPA

> 1.0 → Beating target → Scale
= 1.0 → At target → Hold
< 1.0 → Missing target → Optimize or cut
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="budget-allocation-rule">
      <p>The 70-20-10 budget allocation framework for campaign portfolio management.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Allocate 70% to proven campaigns, 20% to promising campaigns under optimization, and 10% to new tests — never collapse the testing budget, even under pressure.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a permanent testing reserve, the campaign mix stagnates. Proven campaigns eventually saturate; the 10% test budget is the only pipeline for future winners.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>70% — Proven: campaigns with efficiency ratio over 1.0 for 3+ weeks</item>
        <item>20% — Promising: campaigns that need optimization to reach target</item>
        <item>10% — Testing: new channels, audiences, or creative concepts</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="reallocation-decision-matrix">
      <p>Decision matrix and budget adjustment rules by CPA vs target.</p>

      <list title="Reallocation Decision Matrix">
        <item>CPA below 0.7x target: increase budget 30-50%</item>
        <item>CPA 0.7-1.0x target: increase budget 10-20%</item>
        <item>CPA 1.0-1.3x target: hold budget, optimize creative</item>
        <item>CPA 1.3-2.0x target: reduce budget 50%</item>
        <item>CPA above 2.0x target: pause, rethink strategy</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Do not cut a campaign below its minimum learning threshold (typically $500-1000/month) before giving it at least 2 weeks of data at that level.</statement>
        <rationale>Premature cuts eliminate campaigns that are still in the learning phase — the algorithm needs time to find efficient delivery patterns before performance stabilizes.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="scaling-increment-rule">
      <p>Guidelines for controlled budget scaling to prevent learning phase resets.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Never increase a campaign budget by more than 30% in a single step; wait 3-5 days before the next increase.</statement>
        <rationale>Large budget jumps force automated bidding back into learning mode, causing CPA spikes of 20-80% for 3-7 days while the algorithm re-calibrates delivery.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="diminishing-returns-model">
      <p>Expected CPA increase when scaling a single campaign.</p>

      <p>Expected CPA increase when scaling a single campaign:</p>

      <list>
        <item>+20% budget: +5-10% CPA</item>
        <item>+50% budget: +10-20% CPA</item>
        <item>+100% budget: +20-40% CPA</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>When CPA increase exceeds 40% at any budget level, stop scaling that campaign and launch a new parallel campaign targeting a different audience segment instead.</statement>
        <rationale>Beyond the diminishing-returns inflection point, adding budget to an existing campaign is less efficient than expanding the addressable audience via a new campaign.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="pacing-formula">
      <p>Daily budget pacing to ensure consistent spend throughout the month.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Pacing Formula">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Expected spend on day X = Monthly budget * (Day / Days in month)
Variance = Actual spend / Expected spend

Above 1.05: spending too fast, reduce daily budget
0.95-1.05:  on track
Below 0.95: underspending, check delivery issues
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <reference path="templates/weekly-review.md">Weekly reallocation review template</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="cross-channel-comparison">
      <p>Comparing efficiency across Meta, Google, and LinkedIn channels.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Compare channels by efficiency ratio, not absolute CPA — a $100 LinkedIn CPA may outperform a $50 Meta CPA if LinkedIn leads close at 5x the rate.</statement>
        <rationale>Different channels reach different funnel stages and audience quality levels. Raw CPA ignores downstream conversion quality and LTV differences.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Cross-Channel Comparison Table">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Channel   Spend  Conv  CPA   ROAS  Efficiency (target $60)
Meta      $5K    100   $50   4:1   1.20 → Scale
Google    $3K     50   $60   3:1   1.00 → Hold
LinkedIn  $2K     20  $100  1.5:1  0.60 → Reduce or optimize
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="incrementality-testing-budget">
      <p>Testing incrementality before cutting a channel.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Before cutting a channel, test incrementality — pause it for 2 weeks and measure whether total conversions decline, not just that channel's reported conversions.</statement>
        <rationale>Platform attribution overlaps; cutting a channel with reported poor CPA may remove touches that were assisting conversions attributed to other channels.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>High incrementality: conversions drop when channel is paused → keep and optimize</item>
        <item>Low incrementality: conversions hold when channel is paused → safe to reallocate</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="reallocation-example">
      <p>Worked example of a full budget reallocation cycle.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Monthly Budget Reallocation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Current: Meta $5K, Google $3K, LinkedIn $2K — total $10K, target CPA $60
Meta: $50 CPA, 20% under target → increase to $6K (+$1K)
Google: $75 CPA, 25% over target → decrease to $2.5K (-$500)
LinkedIn: $133 CPA, 122% over target → decrease to $1K (-$1K)
Testing reserve: +$500 for new channel test
New total: $10K maintained
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <reference path="templates/monthly-allocation.md">Monthly budget allocation table template</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns-budget">
      <p>Common budget allocation mistakes and their fixes.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Equal budget distribution across all campaigns regardless of performance.</description>
        <reason>Ignores efficiency variance; funds losing campaigns at the same rate as winning ones, capping overall ROAS.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Doubling a campaign budget in one step when performance looks good.</description>
        <reason>Triggers learning phase reset; CPA spikes 20-80% for 3-7 days, erasing the efficiency gains that prompted the increase.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Eliminating the testing budget during periods of pressure to hit efficiency targets.</description>
        <reason>Destroys the innovation pipeline; proven campaigns eventually plateau, and without tests there are no future winners to scale.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Cutting a campaign after 3-4 days of poor performance.</description>
        <reason>Insufficient data; platform algorithms need 7-14 days minimum and 50+ conversions before performance stabilizes — early data is high-variance noise.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Optimizing CPA without tracking downstream quality (lead-to-close rate, LTV).</description>
        <reason>A $20 CPA from a channel that produces 2% close rates is worse than a $100 CPA from a channel with 20% close rates — cost-per-customer matters, not cost-per-lead.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/weekly-review.md" purpose="Weekly reallocation review template"/>
      <template path="templates/monthly-allocation.md" purpose="Monthly budget allocation table template"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://support.google.com/google-ads/answer/6231218"/>
      <link href="https://www.facebook.com/business/help/188647444141775"/>
      <link href="https://business.linkedin.com/marketing-solutions/ads/bid-strategies"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
