<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Roadmap Design Framework">
  <summary>Four roadmap types, a format selection matrix based on uncertainty and audience, and a 5-step design process from strategy inputs to stakeholder communication.</summary>

  <section title="Roadmap Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select roadmap format by uncertainty level: low uncertainty → timeline; medium → Now-Next-Later; high → outcome-themed; live execution → kanban.</statement>
      <rationale>Timeline format with hard dates always slips and erodes trust when uncertainty is high. Now-Next-Later communicates priority without false precision and is the default for early-stage products.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Format Decision Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Now-Next-Later as the default internal format unless you have high confidence in delivery dates AND a stakeholder audience that requires commitments.</statement>
      <rationale>PMs who default to timeline roadmaps spend more time explaining slippage than building. Now-Next-Later shifts the conversation to priority, not dates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate two artifacts from one source — internal (with confidence levels, dependencies) and external (with capability descriptions, no internals). Never maintain them in parallel.</statement>
      <rationale>Parallel maintenance diverges within one cycle. One source of truth with a formatter subagent prevents inconsistency and saves the PM from double-editing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="5-Step Design Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — Collect strategy inputs before defining themes: product vision, business goals for the period, user research insights, and technical constraints.</statement>
      <rationale>Themes without strategic inputs produce feature-grouped buckets, not outcome-driven work areas.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Define 3–5 themes per period; each theme must name the objective it drives and provide 2–3 example initiatives.</statement>
      <rationale>More than 5 themes is aspirational for solo/small teams and dilutes focus. Each theme without an objective link cannot be defended under prioritization pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Tag each initiative with a confidence level (high/medium/low) and treat "high" as a commitment only when scoped and spec'd.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholders interpret "high confidence" as a promise. Calibrate against past quarter delivery to set a realistic confidence mix.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Always include a "Not Doing" section with explicit exclusions and reasons.</statement>
      <rationale>The cheapest scope-creep prevention. A roadmap without "Not Doing" is an invitation to add more.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5 — Review monthly, rewrite quarterly. Add a "last updated" date prominently. Cap "Later" at 8 items; cull once per quarter.</statement>
      <rationale>Stale roadmaps lose trust faster than missing ones. "Later" becomes a dumping ground without a cull policy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/now-next-later.md">Internal roadmap template with confidence levels</reference>
  <reference path="templates/quarterly-outcome.md">OKR-linked quarterly roadmap template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/external-roadmap.md">Customer-facing roadmap with disclaimer</reference>
  <reference path="templates/roadmap-diff.py">Monthly review diff script for two roadmap snapshots</reference>
</text>
