<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="roadmap-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for roadmap-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Feature list with hard delivery dates shared externally.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Customers interpret dates as commitments. When dates slip — and they always do — trust erodes. Use abstracted time horizons ("H1 2026") or capability descriptions with no dates for external sharing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Every initiative tagged "high confidence."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Confidence inflation means the signal is meaningless. Calibrate against the past quarter: if you delivered 60% of "high" items, label the rest "medium." Stakeholders will notice the discrepancy if you don't.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>"Later" bucket grows without bound.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a cull policy "Later" becomes a graveyard that discredits the whole roadmap. Cap at 8 items and run one quarterly cull pass; items that survive 3 culls without moving to Now/Next should be dropped or converted into discovery work.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Same roadmap artifact shared with all audiences (engineering, customers, executives, sales).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Engineering needs dependencies and confidence; customers need capability descriptions; executives need objective linkage. One artifact leaks too much or too little to each. Generate two versions from one source.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Initiatives on the roadmap not linked to any stated objective.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unanchored initiatives cannot be prioritized or defended. If an initiative does not drive a stated OKR or goal, ask why it is on the roadmap before adding it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Roadmap never updated between quarterly rewrites.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Monthly reviews catch reality drift before it compounds. A roadmap that was accurate in January and reviewed in April has three months of silent divergence baked in — the team loses trust that the document reflects reality.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
