<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Learning Speed as Competitive Moat Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Framework treating organisational learning velocity (belief-update rate, decision throughput, evidence freshness) as the primary competitive advantage in AI-cloneable markets; outputs a quarterly belief-audit.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="belief-register-written" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every product strategy MUST maintain a written belief register: each belief has confidence (0-1), last_update date, and the evidence type that would change it.</statement>
      <rationale source="Annie Duke — Thinking in Bets">Implicit beliefs cannot be updated; the register turns strategy into a falsifiable artifact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="decision-velocity-tracked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track decisions/quarter and time-from-question-to-decision per category (P0/P1/P2). Time-from-question target is hours for P2, days for P1, &lt;=2 weeks for P0.</statement>
      <rationale source="First Round Review — Decision Velocity">Without tracking, decision latency creeps invisibly; visibility creates the pressure to compress.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-freshness-thresholds" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Beliefs older than 90 days without re-validation MUST be flagged. Strategy artefacts citing &gt;180-day evidence MUST trigger a refresh.</statement>
      <rationale source="Continuous discovery literature">Stale evidence locks in dead assumptions; freshness thresholds force re-test cadence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="loss-attribution-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a competitor wins a deal or ships first, log the loss with cause-of-loss tag (faster-learning / better-evidence / shipped-sooner / wrong-belief). Quarterly review aggregates.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — competitive postmortems">Lost deals without cause coding don't update beliefs; the next loop repeats the same loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kill-criteria-pre-registered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every active bet MUST have written kill-criteria registered at start. Hitting kill-criteria triggers automatic re-evaluation, not silent continuation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Lean Startup — pivot/persevere criteria">Without kill criteria, sunk-cost bias preserves dying bets and starves new ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — pre-PMF where customer-development is primary; agency/consulting one-shot projects; commodity competition on price; pure execution sprint), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
