<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Learning Speed Framework">
  <summary>Defines the Learning Velocity formula, the four elements to improve at the organizational level, weekly rituals, and AI-powered signal processing that compress time-to-belief-change.</summary>

  <section title="Core Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure and report Learning Velocity as: (Signals Noticed x Update Speed x Execution Quality) / Time. Treat it as an OKR-level metric, not a qualitative goal.</statement>
      <rationale>In 2026, AI lets competitors clone product experiences in weeks. The durable moat is decision latency — how fast the org notices changes, updates beliefs, and ships different answers. Feature parity is achievable; learning-speed advantage compounds over time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Four Elements to Improve">
    <list>
      <item>Signal Collection: automate market and competitor monitoring; pull thousands of signals daily rather than relying on human curation.</item>
      <item>Belief Updates: run strategy reviews weekly, not quarterly; maintain a versioned beliefs.yaml that diffs between reviews.</item>
      <item>Decision Speed: reduce approval chains; pre-commit decision rules so verdicts are mechanical, not political.</item>
      <item>Execution: ship experiments in days via feature flags, not weeks via full deploys; time-box every bet.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Weekly Learning Rituals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap synchronous learning rituals at 2 hours per week total. More than 2 hours of rituals crowds out user research and decision execution.</statement>
      <rationale>Ritual stacking (Monday discovery + Tuesday roadmap + Wednesday competitor + Thursday OKR + Friday retro) fills the PM's calendar without producing decisions. Ritual time is overhead; decision time is value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Monday: share customer interview insights from the previous week across the squad.</item>
      <item>Wednesday: review competitor updates — changelog, pricing, job postings.</item>
      <item>Friday: analyze experiment results; update bet.md files; broadcast changed beliefs.</item>
      <item>Immediately: communicate any strategy adjustment triggered by a new signal — do not batch for the next ritual.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Powered Signal Processing">
    <list>
      <item>AI scans thousands of market signals daily — competitor changelogs, pricing pages, job postings, review sites, niche newsletters.</item>
      <item>Surfaces whitespace and emerging trends before they become obvious to competitors.</item>
      <item>Flags competitor launches and pricing shifts on the day they occur.</item>
      <item>Synthesizes customer sentiment from support themes, social, and review sites automatically.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Route AI-collected signals through a classifier that tags each signal to a specific roadmap bet or belief. Untagged signals are noise; tagged signals are evidence.</statement>
      <rationale>A signal that reaches a PM without a bet or belief tag requires manual routing and is often ignored. Pre-tagging connects signals to decisions automatically.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Organizational Infrastructure">
    <list>
      <item>Insight Repository: shared across all teams, AI-indexed, searchable by topic and bet ID.</item>
      <item>Learning Loops: rapid feedback cycles between signal, belief update, and execution.</item>
      <item>Knowledge Management: AI-indexed, searchable; no signal silo per team.</item>
      <item>Decision Logs: track predictions vs. outcomes per bet; calibration requires a log.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
