<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-pm-practices" title="PM-Level Learning Velocity Practices">
  <summary>Per-bet bet.md system, kill criteria, weekly bet-reviewer agent loop, personal calibration scorecard, and failure modes specific to individual PMs rather than org-wide signal pipelines.</summary>

  <section title="Per-Bet System">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain one bet.md per active roadmap bet in .aidocs/product/bets/. Treat it as code: PR-reviewed, diff-able, version-controlled. Cap active bets at 8 per PM; more is not manageable with the review cadence.</statement>
      <rationale>If bets live in Slack threads or Notion with no version history, belief changes are invisible. A diff of bet.md between commits is the audit trail that proves a PM is learning, not documenting busywork.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every bet.md must contain, before any work starts: hypothesis, kill criterion (measurable, time-bound, single number), leading indicator, owner, check-back date, and the two strongest opposing signals seen so far.</statement>
      <rationale>A bet without a kill criterion is a project, not a bet. The kill criterion is the only thing that forces the org to reverse a bad decision before it sinks the quarter.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Weekly Bet-Reviewer Cycle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a bet-reviewer agent (Sonnet) weekly on each active bet. Output must be one of: keep | accelerate | kill | reframe — with cited evidence. Accept or reject the recommendation, document the decision, move on.</statement>
      <rationale>A weekly mechanical review prevents the two most common PM failure modes: (1) ignoring a bet that should be killed; (2) killing a bet that just needs reframing. The agent surfaces the evidence; the PM decides.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>keep: 3+ cited supporting events in last 30 days AND no kill criterion tripped.</item>
      <item>accelerate: 3+ supporting events AND a leading indicator above target.</item>
      <item>kill: any kill criterion tripped OR fewer than 2 supporting events in last 30 days.</item>
      <item>reframe: 2+ events supporting a coherent alternative hypothesis.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Personal Calibration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run personal calibration quarterly against the decision log. Compute: kill/reframe ratio (target &gt;= 30%), prediction hit rate (target 55-75%), mean time to check-back (target &lt;= 21 days). A hit rate above 75% means the PM logs only easy bets; below 55% means guessing.</statement>
      <rationale>Without calibration, fast-learning PMs are often fast-talking PMs. The scorecard proves whether the belief-update rituals produce decisions, not documents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/pm-learning-velocity.py">Python script computing kill/reframe ratio, reversal rate, and prediction hit rate from decisions.yaml.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Performance theater: PMs publish a "weekly insights" newsletter, count it as learning velocity, and never change a roadmap line.</description>
      <reason>Learning velocity is measured by decisions reversed or accelerated, not by document volume. The audit trail must show bet.md diffs, not newsletter archives.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hero PM trap: all signals route through the most-learning PM, who becomes the bottleneck.</description>
      <reason>Personal learning velocity is not org learning velocity. PMs must explicitly delegate belief ownership to squad members so the loop is distributed, not individual.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Discovery atrophy via agentification: "events ingested" rises while "user conversations had" falls below 3/week.</description>
      <reason>Agent-collected signals go stale in 6 weeks without human-touched ground truth. A floor of 3 user conversations per week per PM is non-negotiable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Bet inflation: agents propose new bets on every signal cluster, producing 30 bets per PM that nobody can maintain.</description>
      <reason>The 8-bet cap per PM must be enforced in the bet-reviewer prompt. A PM with 30 bets has no bets — she has a list.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
