<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="learning-speed-competitive-moat Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for learning-speed-competitive-moat as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Performance theater: PMs publish a "weekly insights" newsletter, count it as learning velocity, and never change a roadmap line.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Learning velocity is measured by decisions reversed or accelerated, not by document volume. The audit trail must show bet.md diffs, not newsletter archives.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Hero PM trap: all signals route through the most-learning PM, who becomes the bottleneck.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Personal learning velocity is not org learning velocity. PMs must explicitly delegate belief ownership to squad members so the loop is distributed, not individual.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Confirmation engine: PMs usually classify their own evidence. Without a peer or red-teamer, every event becomes "evidence for the belief I already had".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The methodology is silent on this; PMs must build the social loop. Pair-review belief changes: every "kill" or "reframe" requires a peer PM or EM signoff.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Ritual stacking: Monday discovery, Tuesday roadmap, Wednesday competitor, Thursday OKRs, Friday retro — soon the PM is in rituals 4 days a week and never makes a decision.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cap rituals at ≤2 hours/week of synchronous time. More than this crowds out user research and decision execution.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Calibration debt: PMs rarely grade their own past predictions, so personal confidence drifts. Without quarterly self-calibration, the "fast-learning PM" is just a fast-talking PM.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Quarterly personal calibration is non-optional. Run pm_learning_velocity.py on your own decisions. If you cannot, you have not been logging.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-PM drift: in a multi-PM product, each PM's belief registry diverges; a customer hears three different stories.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The PM-Lead must enforce a shared belief schema even if individual beliefs differ. Read the org-wide beliefs.yaml weekly even if you do not own it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Output-trained orgs: if # of features shipped is the PM's review metric, no amount of learning ritual changes incentives.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The methodology requires the manager and skip-level to also be on learning velocity as a metric, otherwise it dies.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Discovery-debt accumulation: PMs who delegate signal collection to agents stop talking to users; their "fast learning" decays into "fast theorizing on stale data" within ~6 weeks.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a human-touched discovery floor (≥3 user conversations/week). Without it, the agent loop runs on stale truth.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Bet inflation: agents propose new bets on every signal cluster, producing 30 bets per PM that nobody can maintain.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hard cap (e.g. 8 bets in flight per PM) enforced in the bet-reviewer prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Citation laundering: an LLM cites the same Slack thread three times under three event_ids.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Dedupe by (channel, message_ts) before counting "independent" supports.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Premature kill on weekend lulls: agent runs Monday, sees zero events_for from the weekend, recommends kill.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always evaluate over a rolling 30-day window, not the last sprint.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Reframe loops: a bet that gets reframed every week is not learning, it is drifting.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Lint: reframes_in_last_quarter &lt;= 1 per bet, otherwise flag for human strategy review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Decision-log fabrication for promo: an LLM asked to "summarize my year for promo" will invent decisions you never made.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use the log to verify the narrative; never let the agent author it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale collector outputs leaking into bets: a competitor scrape returns a 2024 page; the agent dates it today.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always preserve source_published_at and reject events older than the bet's check-back window.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>PM tone homogenization: agents draft all bet updates in the same voice across all PMs in the org; execs notice.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Per-PM tone fingerprint or human-author the upward broadcasts.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Single-LLM monoculture: using one model family for collector + classifier + reviewer creates correlated errors.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>At least the reviewer should be a different model class than the classifier. Consider an alternative provider for the reviewer's red-team pass.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy in user transcripts: PM bets often cite named customers; do not let the bet-reviewer ingest raw PII into a shared belief registry.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Strip PII at the classifier stage.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-18" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-broadcasting kill decisions: an agent posts "we killed feature X" before sales, support, and partnership were notified.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a 24-hour human-review delay on kill broadcasts; not on keep or accelerate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-19" severity="medium">
      <description>Calibration as ritual instead of feedback: agent emits a calibration scorecard, PM glances and ignores.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tie the scorecard to OKR review; otherwise it has no behavioral effect.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-20" severity="medium">
      <description>Rubric drift: if quarterly calibration suggests prompt-rubric updates and the PM rewrites the bet-reviewer prompt every quarter, comparability across quarters is lost.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Version the rubric; A/B-shadow new rubrics for one quarter before switching.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-21" severity="medium">
      <description>Discovery atrophy via agentification: tracking "events ingested" rises while "user conversations had" falls.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force the dashboard to display both side-by-side; alert if conversations drop.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
