<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Ads Budget Optimization Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Ads Budget Optimization MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="70-20-10-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Budget MUST partition 70% scaling / 20% optimizing / 10% test reserve. Deviations require documented reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="Performance marketing operational practice">Without test reserve, account fossilizes; without scaling, winners under-fund; without optimization, mid-performers rot.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="efficiency-ratio-based" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reallocation MUST be driven by efficiency ratio (actual_ROAS / target_ROAS). Reallocating on raw conversions is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Efficiency-ratio methodology">Raw conversion comparisons ignore profitability; efficiency-ratio normalizes across channels with different target multiples.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="step-rule-20-percent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Single-step budget change MUST NOT exceed 20% per week unless backed by incrementality test or sample-size threshold.</statement>
      <rationale source="Smart bidding documentation">Larger steps blow up learning phase; smart bidding takes 7 days to re-equilibrate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="premature-cut-block" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Underperformers MUST run &gt;= 7 days OR &gt;= sample-size threshold before cuts. Day-2 cuts based on early signal are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Smart bidding documentation">Day-2 signal is noise; premature cuts destroy winners that surface day 4-6.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="monthly-rebalance" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cross-channel rebalance MUST happen monthly. Weekly is over-fit; quarterly is too slow.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational cadence">Monthly cadence catches drift early without amplifying noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
