<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Budget Optimization Framework">
  <summary>Target CPA calculation, efficiency ratio formula, and the 70-20-10 budget allocation rule.</summary>

  <section title="Target CPA Calculation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Calculate target CPA from customer LTV before setting any bids; never use a CPA target derived from platform recommendations without validating against your unit economics.</statement>
      <rationale>Platform-suggested CPAs optimize for volume, not profitability. Your target must reflect actual margin and acceptable payback period.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Average customer value: $500
Target LTV:CAC ratio: 3:1
Target CPA = $500 / 3 = $167
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Efficiency Ratio">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use efficiency ratio (Target CPA / Actual CPA) as the primary cross-campaign comparison metric — it normalizes campaigns with different absolute costs onto a single scale.</statement>
      <rationale>A campaign with $30 CPA vs a target of $50 (ratio 1.67) should be scaled over a campaign with $60 CPA vs target of $100 (ratio 1.67 identical) — absolute CPA alone does not reveal which is better value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Efficiency = Target CPA / Actual CPA

> 1.0 → Beating target → Scale
= 1.0 → At target → Hold
< 1.0 → Missing target → Optimize or cut
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="70-20-10 Allocation Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Allocate 70% to proven campaigns, 20% to promising campaigns under optimization, and 10% to new tests — never collapse the testing budget, even under pressure.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a permanent testing reserve, the campaign mix stagnates. Proven campaigns eventually saturate; the 10% test budget is the only pipeline for future winners.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>70% — Proven: campaigns with efficiency ratio over 1.0 for 3+ weeks</item>
      <item>20% — Promising: campaigns that need optimization to reach target</item>
      <item>10% — Testing: new channels, audiences, or creative concepts</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
