<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-email-marketing">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>content-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Value-first email marketing: list building, welcome sequences, segmentation, sales sequences. Never purchase lists—spam complaints above 0.1% trigger sanctions. Build organically with lead magnets.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>email-marketing</tag>
      <tag>list-building</tag>
      <tag>welcome-sequences</tag>
      <tag>segmentation</tag>
      <tag>deliverability</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Email Marketing</title>
    <summary>A value-first email marketing framework covering list building, welcome sequences, newsletter strategy, segmentation, and sales email sequences. Never purchase or rent lists — spam complaints above 0.1% trigger Google/Yahoo bulk sender sanctions. Build organically with lead magnets; automate the welcome sequence before any broadcast.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Email is the only audience channel you fully own — social algorithms can eliminate your reach overnight. But most email marketing fails because it prioritizes promotion over value (80% value, 20% pitch is the standard), sends irregularly, or skips the welcome sequence that captures subscribers at peak engagement. A structured Build→Nurture→Segment→Convert→Retain flow consistently produces 20-30%+ open rates where ad-driven lists produce single digits.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Launching a new product and building an email list from scratch</item>
        <item>Setting up automated welcome and nurture sequences for an existing audience</item>
        <item>Converting social media followers to an owned channel</item>
        <item>Running a promotional campaign (product launch, sale, cohort open)</item>
        <item>Re-engaging an inactive or cold subscriber list</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Audience is still undefined — list-building without ICP clarity creates churn</item>
        <item>Fewer than 50 subscribers with no consistent content cadence — focus on content first</item>
        <item>Pure B2B enterprise with procurement-driven sales — email alone won't close</item>
        <item>Compliance requirements prevent automated outreach (certain financial or healthcare contexts)</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="list-building">
      <p>Email list growth is the foundation of the strategy. Without organic list building rules in place, all subsequent tactics fail.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never purchase or rent email lists; spam complaints above 0.1% trigger Google/Yahoo bulk sender sanctions that are difficult to reverse.</statement>
        <rationale>Purchased lists have high complaint rates because recipients did not opt in. ISP blacklisting from complaint spikes can render the sending domain unusable for months.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Provide a lead magnet before asking for an email address; organic list growth without a lead magnet is near-zero on most platforms.</statement>
        <rationale>The default "subscribe to my newsletter" CTA converts at 0.1-0.5%; a specific lead magnet converts at 3-10%. The lead magnet is the primary driver of list growth.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="lead-magnet-types">
        <list>
          <item>Checklist: high conversion, easy consumption (e.g., "10-Point SEO Checklist")</item>
          <item>Template: high conversion, immediate value (e.g., "Email Swipe File")</item>
          <item>Guide/eBook: medium conversion, deep knowledge (e.g., "Complete Guide to X")</item>
          <item>Mini-course: medium conversion, nurtures relationship (e.g., "5-Day Email Course")</item>
          <item>Tool/Calculator: high conversion, interactive utility (e.g., "ROI Calculator")</item>
          <item>Webinar: high-intent, live event (converts best when topic is urgent)</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="opt-in-form-best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use a single email field (no name, no phone) for maximum conversion; each additional field reduces opt-ins by 20-30%.</statement>
        <rationale>Friction on the sign-up form is the primary cause of low list growth rates; removing the name field alone typically lifts conversion 15-25%.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Above-the-fold placement converts at 2-3x sidebar placement</item>
        <item>Clear value proposition in the headline: what they get, not "subscribe"</item>
        <item>Privacy assurance below the form ("No spam. Unsubscribe anytime.")</item>
        <item>Exit-intent popup: use sparingly, only with high-value lead magnet</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="welcome-sequence">
      <rule>
        <statement>Automate a 5-email welcome sequence triggered immediately on signup; the first 7 days after opt-in is the highest engagement window.</statement>
        <rationale>New subscribers have peak curiosity on sign-up day. Brands that send nothing for the first week lose 40-60% of potential engagement before the first broadcast.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Day 0: Deliver lead magnet + brief self-introduction</item>
        <item>Day 1: Share your story and philosophy; build connection</item>
        <item>Day 3: Best content piece (top blog post, resource, case study)</item>
        <item>Day 5: Social proof or case study from a customer</item>
        <item>Day 7: Soft pitch — mention the product, no hard sell</item>
      </list>
      <reference path="templates/welcome-sequence.txt">5-email welcome sequence with subject lines and body scaffolding</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="segmentation">
      <list>
        <item>By engagement: Active (opened last 30 days), Engaged (last 90), Inactive (90+ days), VIP (high engagement + purchasers)</item>
        <item>By lead source: different messaging per acquisition channel</item>
        <item>By purchase history: upsell relevant products to buyers</item>
        <item>By interests: targeted content per declared interest</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="newsletter-strategy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Follow the 80/20 rule: 80% value content, 20% promotional; deviating toward more promotion consistently increases unsubscribe rate.</statement>
        <rationale>Subscribers who feel a list is primarily promotional unsubscribe at 3-5x the rate of subscribers who receive value-first content. Trust is the deliverable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="newsletter-formats">
        <list>
          <item>Curated: 5-7 links + commentary — suits thought leadership positioning</item>
          <item>Educational: 1 deep topic per issue — best for teaching-based brands</item>
          <item>Personal: story + lesson — highest reply rates, builds relationship</item>
          <item>Mixed: main insight + bonus items — most common for product-adjacent newsletters</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <reference path="templates/newsletter-issue.txt">Weekly newsletter format with hook, insight, quick wins, and CTA</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="sales-launch-sequence">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run the full 8-day launch sequence for product launches; compressing to 3-4 days consistently reduces conversion by 40-60%.</statement>
        <rationale>The sequence allows different audience segments to convert at different points: early birds on day 0, consideration buyers on days 1-3, deadline buyers on days 5-6.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/sales-launch-sequence.txt">8-day product launch email sequence with timing and structure</reference>
      <list>
        <item>Day -7: announcement + value preview</item>
        <item>Day -3: deep dive on the problem</item>
        <item>Day -1: early bird reminder</item>
        <item>Day 0: launch + full details</item>
        <item>Day 1: FAQ and objection handling</item>
        <item>Day 3: case study or testimonial</item>
        <item>Day 5: last chance and scarcity</item>
        <item>Day 6: final reminder (hours left)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="key-metrics">
      <list>
        <item>Open rate: 20-25% good, 30%+ great (note: iOS Mail Privacy inflates; use click rate as primary signal)</item>
        <item>Click rate: 2-3% good, 5%+ great</item>
        <item>Unsubscribe rate: below 0.5% acceptable, below 0.2% great</item>
        <item>List growth rate: 5%/month good, 10%+ great</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="deliverability-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Set up SPF, DKIM, and DMARC on the sending domain before the first broadcast; fix deliverability infrastructure before you need it.</statement>
        <rationale>Google and Yahoo 2024+ bulk sender requirements mandate DMARC; missing it causes emails to be rejected or junked from day one of any broadcast campaign.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Send from a personal name ("Alex from Acme") rather than a brand name for personal-tone sequences.</statement>
        <rationale>Personal sender names consistently produce higher open rates across platforms because they do not trigger "promotional" mental filtering.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-engage or remove subscribers inactive for 180+ days before they degrade sender reputation.</statement>
        <rationale>Inactive subscribers lower the engagement rate that ISPs use to evaluate sender quality; a suppression campaign before large broadcasts protects deliverability.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Sending to a purchased or cold list.</description>
        <reason>High complaint rates trigger ISP blacklisting that can make the sending domain unusable for months.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No welcome sequence — sending nothing in the first 7 days after opt-in.</description>
        <reason>The first week is the highest-engagement window; missing it loses 40-60% of potential activation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Inconsistent sending schedule — emailing only when there is something to promote.</description>
        <reason>Irregular emails erode trust and train subscribers to ignore them; a regular schedule builds expectation and open habit.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-integration-guidelines">
      <p>Agents can draft full email sequences (welcome, nurture, re-engagement) given a brief with ICP, product description, and tone guidelines. Claude Sonnet handles email copywriting efficiently; Opus is appropriate for designing the full segmentation strategy or a multi-touch launch sequence. Agents should not send emails autonomously — every batch should pass a human review checkpoint before delivery.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Behavioral trigger logic (e.g., "send only if user has not logged in for 7 days") must be configured inside the ESP, not hallucinated by the agent.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent-produced trigger descriptions may be logically ambiguous; ESP configuration UI forces clarity and prevents misconfiguration.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
        <list>
          <item>Merge tag validation varies by ESP (`{{first_name}}` vs `{first_name}`) — always specify the ESP format in the prompt</item>
          <item>Segmentation logic must be verified in the ESP UI before automation activation; wrong conditions silently fire to wrong segment</item>
          <item>Agents tend to write longer emails than needed — specify a word count constraint in every prompt</item>
          <item>Subject lines with excessive punctuation or spam trigger words (FREE!!!, 100% guaranteed) will tank deliverability; always run through a checker before scheduling</item>
          <item>A/B test copy variants should be staged in the ESP, not run simultaneously by multiple agent calls</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/welcome-sequence.txt" purpose="5-email welcome sequence with subject lines and body scaffolding"/>
      <template path="templates/newsletter-issue.txt" purpose="Weekly newsletter format with hook, insight, quick wins, and CTA"/>
      <template path="templates/sales-launch-sequence.txt" purpose="8-day product launch email sequence with timing and structure"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://convertkit.com/resources"/>
      <link href="https://www.mailchimp.com/resources/email-marketing-benchmarks/"/>
      <link href="https://www.litmus.com/blog/"/>
      <link href="https://postmarkapp.com/guides"/>
      <link href="https://reallygoodemails.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
