<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Seven Performance Domains (PMBoK 8) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the seven-performance-domains methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="canonical-seven" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always use exactly these seven domain names — never add an 8th, never reintroduce 'Integration Management', 'Quality', or 'Communications' as standalone domains.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK 8 standard">PMBoK 8 explicitly integrates Quality, Communications, and Procurement; LLMs trained on PMBoK 6 hallucinate these as standalone domains.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="fixed-domain-order" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Walk the seven domains in fixed order (Governance, Scope, Schedule, Finance, Stakeholders, Resources, Risk) and emit one record per domain.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-discipline practice">Fixed order makes diffs across weekly runs stable; reordered output adds noise to version control.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="audit-before-steering" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run the domain audit before every steering committee; the output IS the status pack, not a separate manual summarisation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — status-report audits">Manual summarisation introduces optimism bias and lag.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="gap-equals-risk" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map each missing domain artefact directly to a risk entry in the Risk domain register.</statement>
      <rationale source="Risk-register practice">Risk registers that do not include process gaps undercount project risk systematically.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="default-to-governance" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a process feels homeless, default to Governance; do not invent a new domain.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK 8 governance scope">Inventing domains breaks the canonical seven and bloats taxonomy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Pure-Scrum teams where Scrum events already cover domains implicitly</item>
      <item>Solopreneur projects under 1 week with a single deliverable</item>
      <item>Shops still on PMBoK 6 in mid-project — switching narrative confuses sponsors</item>
      <item>Domain-driven design conversations — overloaded term</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
