<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-domains" title="Seven PMBoK 8 Performance Domains">
  <summary>Canonical list of the seven PMBoK 8 domains with artefacts, outcomes, and integrated areas; plus the PMBoK 7 to 8 transition delta.</summary>

  <section title="Canonical Seven Domains">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always use exactly these seven domain names — never add an 8th, never reintroduce "Integration Management", "Quality", or "Communications" as standalone domains.</statement>
      <rationale>PMBoK 8 explicitly integrates Quality, Communications, and Procurement. LLMs trained on PMBoK 6 data will hallucinate these as standalone domains; the canonical seven must be pinned in system prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Governance — oversight, decision frameworks, value realisation; replaces Integration Management; includes sustainability as a core metric</item>
      <item>Scope — define and control what is included and excluded; enhanced definition and traceability</item>
      <item>Schedule — plan and manage timelines, milestones, and dependencies</item>
      <item>Finance — budgets, costs, financial performance; replaces Cost Management; pairs with EVM</item>
      <item>Stakeholders — identify, analyse, and engage all stakeholders; now includes Communications</item>
      <item>Resources — acquire and manage team members and physical resources; enhanced focus on team development</item>
      <item>Risk — identify, analyse, and respond to uncertainties including threats and opportunities</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Artefacts per Domain">
    <p>Minimal artefact set that satisfies each domain. A missing artefact is a risk in the Risk domain.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Governance: charter.md, decision-log.md</item>
      <item>Scope: scope.md, wbs.md, requirements-traceability.md</item>
      <item>Schedule: schedule.md, milestones.md</item>
      <item>Finance: budget.md, cost-baseline.md</item>
      <item>Stakeholders: stakeholder-register.md, comms-plan.md, engagement-plan.md</item>
      <item>Resources: raci.md, team-charter.md</item>
      <item>Risk: risk-register.md</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="PMBoK 7 to 8 Delta">
    <list>
      <item>Principles: 12 (PMBoK 7) → 6 streamlined (PMBoK 8): Stewardship and Ethics, Collaboration, Value Optimisation, Systems and Complexity, Adaptability, Sustainability</item>
      <item>Domains: 8 (PMBoK 7) → 7 (PMBoK 8): Team + Project Work collapsed into Resources + Governance; Planning + Delivery merged into Scope/Schedule/Finance; Measurement absorbed into respective domains; Uncertainty → Risk</item>
      <item>Sustainability: mentioned in PMBoK 7, core principle in PMBoK 8 — needs a measurable proxy (e.g. CO2 per release, accessibility pass rate)</item>
      <item>AI Coverage: none in PMBoK 7, dedicated appendix in PMBoK 8</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
