<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-domain-audit" title="Domain Audit Workflow and Agent Rules">
  <summary>How to run a seven-domain gap audit, map missing artefacts to risks, and constraints for agent output to ensure stable, auditable results.</summary>

  <section title="Audit Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Walk the seven domains in fixed order (Governance, Scope, Schedule, Finance, Stakeholders, Resources, Risk) and for each emit: artefact_path (or MISSING), owner (or UNASSIGNED), last_updated (ISO date or never), status (green/amber/red), next_action (one imperative sentence).</statement>
      <rationale>Fixed domain order makes diffs across weekly runs stable — status changes are visible as line-level changes in version control without noise from reordering.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the domain audit before every steering committee meeting. The output is the status pack, not a separate document that the PM then summarises manually.</statement>
      <rationale>Separate manual summarisation introduces optimism bias and lag. An automated audit from source artefacts is objective and current.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Map each missing domain artefact directly to a risk entry in the Risk domain register. A missing artefact is not a process gap — it is a project risk with a probability and impact.</statement>
      <rationale>Risk registers that do not include process gaps undercount project risk systematically. Governance gaps are often higher-impact than delivery risks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/domain-audit.py">Python domain gap auditor, emits JSON</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Constraints">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM output contains "Integration Management" or "Quality Management" as a domain name.</description>
      <reason>These are PMBoK 6 terms; in PMBoK 8 they are integrated. Any output containing these names is anchored to the wrong edition and must be rejected.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent output lists eight domains (adding Quality or Communications as a standalone).</description>
      <reason>Validate output length == 7 domains. An 8th domain signals PMBoK 6 training bias; reject and re-prompt with the canonical seven in the system prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Domain status colours drift to "green" over time without human sampling.</description>
      <reason>Agents self-validate by confirming artefact existence, not artefact quality. Calibrate by sampling 1 in 5 domains for human review each cycle.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
