<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-rules" title="Accessibility-First Design Rules">
  <summary>Concrete design-phase rules for WCAG 2.2 AA compliance: contrast ratios, touch targets, focus visibility, semantic structure, and motion controls — all enforced at the token and component-spec level.</summary>

  <section title="Color and Contrast">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce a minimum contrast ratio of 4.5:1 for body text and 3:1 for large text (18pt+), UI components, and focus indicators; embed these thresholds in design tokens so non-compliant primitives cannot be exported.</statement>
      <rationale>WCAG 2.2 SC 1.4.3 and 1.4.11 define these ratios. Encoding them in tokens prevents a designer from accidentally choosing a brand color that fails at the theme level before any component is built.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use color as the sole indicator of meaning; pair every color signal with a shape, label, or pattern.</statement>
      <rationale>Approximately 8% of males have color vision deficiency. Color-only signals (red = error) are invisible to this population and fail WCAG SC 1.4.1.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Error state: red border + error icon + "Error:" label prefix. Three independent signals, any one sufficient.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Error state: red border only. Color-blind users see no distinction from normal state.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Touch Targets and Spacing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set minimum interactive element size to 44x44 CSS pixels (or platform equivalent); ensure sufficient spacing between adjacent targets so misfire probability is low.</statement>
      <rationale>WCAG 2.2 SC 2.5.8 (Target Size, Minimum) formalizes this. Spacing matters independently of size — clustered 44px targets still cause misfires for users with motor impairments or tremor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Make focus indicators visible with at least 3:1 contrast against the adjacent background; never rely on browser defaults which often fail this threshold.</statement>
      <rationale>WCAG 2.2 SC 2.4.11 (Focus Appearance, Minimum) requires a visible focus ring. Browser defaults (thin dotted outline) are often invisible on colored backgrounds.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Semantic Structure and Motion">
    <rule>
      <statement>Specify heading level (H1-H6), landmark roles (nav, main, header, footer), and ARIA labels in design handoff annotations; do not leave semantic decisions to developer interpretation.</statement>
      <rationale>Developers recreate heading hierarchies inconsistently without explicit annotation. Screen reader users navigate by headings; a flat or misordered hierarchy breaks the primary navigation pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include pause/stop controls for all auto-playing animations longer than 5 seconds; respect prefers-reduced-motion at the CSS level.</statement>
      <rationale>WCAG 2.2 SC 2.2.2 (Pause, Stop, Hide) and 2.3.3 (Animation from Interactions) protect users with vestibular disorders and cognitive disabilities from motion that prevents reading or causes nausea.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/a11y_quick.ts">Contrast ratio calculator, WCAG AA/AAA level checker, and touch-target size validator</reference>
  </section>
</text>
