<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="competitive-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Examine 3-5 direct, 2-3 indirect, and 1-2 aspirational competitors against pre-defined criteria. Output: feature matrix, profiles, Must/Should/Could/Avoid recommendations.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>competitive-analysis</tag>
      <tag>competitor-research</tag>
      <tag>market-research</tag>
      <tag>ux-design</tag>
      <tag>strategy</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>research</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Competitive Analysis (UX)</title>

    <summary>Without competitive analysis, design teams reinvent solved problems, miss user expectations set by other products in the market, and cannot answer stakeholder questions like "what do competitors do?" Analyzing direct competitors surfaces the baseline users already expect; analyzing indirect competitors reveals alternative approaches; analyzing aspirational examples (best-in-class UX from adjacent industries) reveals what "best practice" looks like. The structured output converts observations into actionable prioritization: must-have (table stakes), should-have (competitive parity), could differentiate (opportunity gaps), and avoid (observed failure modes).</summary>

    <why>
      <p>User expectations are set by the products they use. If all competitors in your market offer guest checkout, users expect guest checkout from you even if you have not shipped it yet. If no competitor offers it, you have a differentiation opportunity. Competitive analysis surfaces these expectations and opportunities systematically.</p>
      <p>Analysis of aspirational examples from adjacent industries prevents pattern lock. The 5 competitors in your market may all share the same blind spot. Studying a best-in-class product from a different industry (e.g., learning from Spotify's onboarding even if you are building an e-commerce site) exposes solutions that your competitive set has not discovered.</p>
      <p>The structured framework (scope → criteria → data gathering → documentation → pattern analysis → recommendations) converts informal observations into prioritized decisions. Without structure, competitive analysis produces a list of features; with structure, it produces a decision roadmap.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Trigger: starting a new product or feature where baseline expectations are unclear — run before opening Figma.</item>
        <item>Trigger: entering a new market segment or geo where user expectations are unknown — run during discovery.</item>
        <item>Trigger: a competitor ships a significant update (changelog, press release, App Store update note) — run a focused delta-check within 1 week.</item>
        <item>Trigger: stakeholder asks "what do others do?" and the answer is blocking a design decision — run a 1-day focused pass on the specific flow.</item>
        <item>Trigger: scheduled cadence — major refresh annually, minor refresh quarterly, focused delta on competitor-update events.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Do not substitute competitive analysis for user research — competitors' choices may also be wrong; validate with your own users before adopting patterns.</item>
        <item>Do not analyze more than 8 competitors in a single pass — depth of analysis degrades; narrow scope or run multiple focused rounds.</item>
        <item>Do not treat findings as requirements — use them as input to design decisions, not as specifications.</item>
        <item>When your product targets a problem with no direct competitors — use analogous domain research instead.</item>
        <item>When the competitive landscape changes faster than you can act (e.g., fast-moving AI tools) — snapshot analysis becomes stale within weeks; update frequently or choose a slower-moving domain.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <how-to>
      <step>Define scope. Pick 3-5 direct competitors (same problem, same user), 2-3 indirect (same problem, different approach), and 1-2 aspirational (best-in-class UX from any industry). Cap total at 8. Record each one with type, URL, primary user, and price tier in the analysis plan.</step>
      <step>Define evaluation criteria before opening any competitor product. Cover at minimum: feature coverage, primary user flows (signup, core action, checkout/conversion, support), UI patterns, information architecture, content/tone, accessibility (WCAG 2.2 AA), mobile parity, performance (initial load, time-to-interactive), error handling, onboarding time-to-value.</step>
      <step>Document a scoring rubric. Use a 4-point qualitative scale (Excellent/Good/Fair/Poor) with explicit numeric or behavioural anchors per criterion. Save it in the analysis plan before scoring anyone.</step>
      <step>Gather data hands-on. For each competitor: create a real account, complete the full primary flow on desktop and mobile, hit at least one error state intentionally, contact support with one realistic question, and run an automated accessibility audit (axe DevTools or Lighthouse) on 2-3 key screens. Capture annotated screenshots immediately.</step>
      <step>Document each competitor in the same template (templates/competitor-profile.md): overview, key screens (annotated), step-by-step flows, strengths, weaknesses, opportunities. Keep observations and recommendations in separate sections.</step>
      <step>Fill the feature matrix (templates/feature-matrix.md): rows = features/criteria, columns = competitors, cells = rubric score plus a one-line note. Add a final "expectation" column noting "all do it" / "none do it" / "top performer only".</step>
      <step>Run pattern analysis across the matrix. For each row, classify as: baseline (4+ do it well), opportunity gap (0-1 do it well), best practice (top performer distinctively excels), or anti-pattern (multiple competitors do it badly with visible user pain — App Store reviews, support threads, G2 complaints).</step>
      <step>Generate prioritised recommendations. Write each finding into one of four tiers: Must Have, Should Have, Could Differentiate, Avoid. Use templates/summary-report.md. Every recommendation must cite at least one observation (competitor + screen/flow).</step>
      <step>Validate. Run the verification checklist below. Share the report with one peer reviewer for sanity check before circulating to stakeholders.</step>
    </how-to>

    <section name="scope-and-selection">
      <p>Selecting the right competitors and scope is critical. Too broad a scope dilutes analysis depth; too narrow misses important patterns.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Select 3-5 direct competitors (same problem, same user audience), 2-3 indirect competitors (same problem, different user or approach), and 1-2 aspirational examples (best-in-class UX from any industry). Cap total at 8 to maintain depth.</statement>
        <rationale>More than 8 competitors transforms the analysis from depth-focused to breadth-focused. Breadth generates feature lists; depth generates insights. Direct competitors establish the baseline; indirect competitors reveal alternative approaches; aspirational examples break pattern lock.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define competitor types before beginning: Direct (same problem, same user — e.g., Uber vs Lyft), Indirect (same problem, different approach — e.g., Uber vs public transit), Partial (overlapping features but different scope), Aspirational (best-in-class to learn from, not a direct competitor).</statement>
        <rationale>Clarity on competitor type ensures the right analysis. Analyzing only direct competitors may miss solutions. Including aspirational examples exposes UX innovations from unrelated industries.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <prompt purpose="Generate a candidate competitor list to validate scope">
<![CDATA[
You are a UX research assistant. For the product described below, propose:
- 5 direct competitors (same problem, same user)
- 3 indirect competitors (same problem, different approach)
- 2 aspirational examples (best-in-class UX from any industry, with rationale)

For each, return JSON: {"name", "url", "type", "primary_user", "price_tier", "rationale"}.
Do not include products that are out of business, dormant >12 months, or behind enterprise paywalls.

Product: <one-sentence product description>
Target user: <persona>
Geo: <market>
]]>
      </prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="criteria-definition">
      <p>Pre-defined criteria prevent bias. Criteria chosen after observing competitors reflect what was observed, not what matters.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Establish evaluation criteria before examining any competitor product. Criteria derived after observation introduce confirmation bias.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-hoc criteria selection is unconsciously biased: analysts weight criteria where their preferred design performs well. Pre-defined criteria are neutral and repeatable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use consistent scoring rubrics for all competitors. Prefer qualitative scales (Excellent/Good/Fair/Poor) over binary (Yes/No) to capture degree of implementation.</statement>
        <rationale>Binary scoring loses nuance. A feature implemented poorly is not the same as a feature implemented well. Qualitative scales surface these degrees and produce better comparative insights.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Document your scoring criteria and definitions before beginning (e.g., "Excellent onboarding = completes in under 3 minutes and shows value immediately; Good = 3-5 minutes; Fair = 5-10 minutes; Poor = over 10 minutes or unclear value proposition").</statement>
        <rationale>Without definitions, scoring drifts across competitors. Explicit definitions ensure consistency and make scores repeatable if someone else conducts the analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Rubric anchor template">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Criterion: Onboarding time-to-first-value
- Excellent: <3 min and clear value moment shown before signup completion
- Good:      3-5 min, value moment within first session
- Fair:      5-10 min, value moment requires guidance
- Poor:      >10 min OR no clear value moment OR forced upsell first

Criterion: Mobile parity (vs desktop)
- Excellent: 100% feature parity, native mobile patterns
- Good:      ≥90% feature parity, minor degradations
- Fair:      Core flows work, secondary features degraded
- Poor:      Core flows broken or desktop-only
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="data-gathering">
      <p>Hands-on use is non-negotiable. Screenshots and marketing pages miss the actual experience.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Create real accounts and complete full user flows rather than reviewing screenshots or marketing pages. Use on both desktop and mobile, test edge cases and error states, contact support, test accessibility.</statement>
        <rationale>Screenshots reveal visual design; actual use reveals friction. Error messages, loading states, support responsiveness, and onboarding flow are invisible in screenshots. These are often where competitors differentiate.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Conduct the analysis yourself (use the product, create accounts, complete full flows). Do not delegate deep qualitative pass to an agent or junior analyst.</statement>
        <rationale>Deep insights come from hands-on use and noticing details that automated tools miss. Nuanced UX observations (tone, visual hierarchy, interaction smoothness) require human judgment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Annotate screenshots and observations immediately. Memory of details degrades fast — hours later you will forget why a particular pattern was notable.</statement>
        <rationale>Rich annotations during the session preserve context. Notes taken hours later lack the immediate sense of what made the interaction notable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <commands>
        <command name="lighthouse-perf-and-a11y">npx lighthouse "https://competitor.example/key-screen" --only-categories=performance,accessibility,best-practices --output=json --output-path=./out/competitor-1-home.json</command>
        <command name="axe-cli-a11y">npx @axe-core/cli "https://competitor.example/key-screen" --save ./out/competitor-1-home-axe.json</command>
        <command name="pa11y-a11y">npx pa11y "https://competitor.example/key-screen" --reporter json &gt; ./out/competitor-1-home-pa11y.json</command>
        <command name="full-page-screenshot">npx playwright screenshot --full-page --device="iPhone 13" "https://competitor.example/key-screen" ./out/competitor-1-home-mobile.png</command>
        <command name="archive-page">npx single-file "https://competitor.example/key-screen" ./out/competitor-1-home.html</command>
      </commands>
    </section>

    <section name="documentation-consistency">
      <p>Consistent documentation enables comparison. Inconsistent notes prevent useful synthesis.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use the same documentation structure for every competitor: per-competitor profile template with sections for overview, key screens (annotated), user flows (step-by-step), strengths, weaknesses, and opportunities.</statement>
        <rationale>Structured templates ensure the same dimensions are evaluated for all competitors. Ad-hoc notes cannot be compared across products.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Separate "what they do" observations from "what we should do" recommendations. Keep them in distinct sections until synthesis. An observation ("Competitor A shows estimated delivery on the product page") is different from a recommendation ("we should show estimated delivery earlier").</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing observations and recommendations conflates data with interpretation. Separate them to enable a later review where someone else can validate observations and challenge recommendations.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Per-competitor profile skeleton">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Competitor: <Name>
- Type: direct | indirect | aspirational
- URL: <url>
- Pricing: <free | freemium | paid tier>
- Reviewed: YYYY-MM-DD by <name>
- Plan/account used: <e.g. free, $9 plan>

## Overview
2-3 sentence summary of positioning and primary flow.

## Key screens (annotated)
| Screen | Screenshot | Notes |
|--------|------------|-------|
| Landing | ![](./shots/c1-landing.png) | … |
| Signup | ![](./shots/c1-signup.png) | … |

## User flows (step-by-step)
### Onboarding
1. …
2. …
Time-to-first-value: 4 min 12 s

## Scoring (rubric)
| Criterion | Score | Evidence |
|-----------|-------|----------|
| Onboarding TTFV | Good | screen #3, ~4 min |
| Mobile parity | Fair | search broken on iOS Safari |

## Strengths (observations)
- …

## Weaknesses (observations)
- …

## Opportunities (recommendations — separate from above)
- …
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="pattern-analysis">
      <p>Pattern analysis converts individual observations into strategic insights. Individual competitor review produces feature lists; pattern analysis produces direction.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>After documenting all competitors, identify patterns: what everyone does (baseline expectation), what nobody does (opportunity), what top performers do distinctively (best practice), and what problems appear in multiple products (anti-patterns).</statement>
        <rationale>Individual competitor analysis is a data-gathering phase; pattern analysis is where data becomes insight. A feature present in all 5 competitors is table stakes; a feature present in 0 is an opportunity; a feature that top performers execute well and others botch is a best practice.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Flag patterns that differ by product type, user segment, or use case. A pattern that holds for enterprise SaaS may not hold for consumer products. Document these distinctions.</statement>
        <rationale>Pattern blindness: assuming a pattern applies universally when it only applies to a specific segment. Noting segment differences prevents over-generalizing findings.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Include one aspirational non-competitor (different industry, best-in-class UX) to break pattern lock. Analyze whether patterns unique to your competitive set could be improved using patterns from outside your industry.</statement>
        <rationale>Entire competitive sets can converge on suboptimal patterns. A pattern transfer from a different industry often yields the highest-value insights.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="recommendation-prioritization">
      <p>Four-tier recommendation structure produces clarity and pre-empts debate.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Categorize every recommendation into Must Have (table stakes), Should Have (parity), Could Differentiate (opportunity), or Avoid (failure mode).</statement>
        <rationale>Without tiers, all recommendations appear equal and trigger debate about priority. Tiers make prioritization explicit: Must Have are blockers; Avoid are negative signals; Could Differentiate are the most valuable output.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Definition of each tier:</p>
      <term name="Must Have">Table stakes. Present in 4+ competitors or user-facing expectation. Not having it is a competitive disadvantage. Implement before shipping.</term>
      <term name="Should Have">Competitive parity. Present in 2-3 competitors or expected by power users. Implement in next release or roadmap soon.</term>
      <term name="Could Differentiate">Opportunity gap. Absent from competitors or executed poorly by all. Could differentiate if executed exceptionally. Evaluate for roadmap if resources allow.</term>
      <term name="Avoid">Failure mode. Observed in one or more competitors and consistently causes problems (support load, user complaints, accessibility issues). Document why competitors made this choice and commit to not repeating it.</term>

      <example type="good" title="E-commerce Checkout Prioritization">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Finding: All 5 competitors offer guest checkout.
Insight: Guest checkout is table stakes.
Recommendation: Must Have. Not having it is a competitive disadvantage.

Finding: Only 1 competitor shows estimated delivery on the product page.
Insight: All others show it in the cart or at checkout.
Recommendation: Could Differentiate. Showing delivery estimate earlier in the flow than competitors could reduce cart abandonment.

Finding: 3 competitors have payment errors with unclear recovery steps; users call support.
Insight: Error handling during payment is a weak point.
Recommendation: Avoid copying competitor error messages. Invest in clear error states and single-step recovery.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="SaaS Onboarding">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Competitor A: 8 onboarding steps, 15 minutes to value
Competitor B: 3 steps, 2 minutes to value
Competitor C: 5 steps, 8 minutes to value
Competitor B has highest user ratings on G2.

Insight: Time-to-first-value is the primary lever. Minimal onboarding correlates with satisfaction.
Recommendation: Target 3-4 steps maximum. Measure time-to-first-value as the primary onboarding success metric.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <prompt purpose="Synthesise findings into Must/Should/Could/Avoid tiers">
<![CDATA[
You are a UX strategist. I will paste a feature matrix (markdown table: rows=criteria,
columns=competitors, cells=rubric score + 1-line note). For every row, output a single
recommendation in this JSON shape:

{
  "criterion": "...",
  "tier": "Must Have | Should Have | Could Differentiate | Avoid",
  "evidence": ["competitorA: <observation>", "competitorB: <observation>"],
  "rationale": "<why this tier>",
  "next_action": "<concrete design or product action>"
}

Rules:
- Must Have if ≥4 of 5 direct competitors do it well.
- Should Have if 2-3 do it well.
- Could Differentiate if 0-1 do it well AND there is plausible user value.
- Avoid only if multiple competitors do it AND there is observed user pain (cite source).
- Never invent observations not present in the matrix.

Matrix:
<paste markdown matrix>
]]>
      </prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Analyzing only direct competitors and ignoring aspirational examples from other industries.</description>
        <reason>Direct competitors may all share the same blind spot. Aspirational examples expose solutions that the competitive set has not discovered. Pattern transfers across industries often yield the highest-value insights.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Copying a competitor pattern without understanding why they made that choice.</description>
        <reason>The competitor may have shipped that pattern to fix a specific problem in their system that does not apply to yours. Copying without understanding context imports constraints along with the solution.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Running competitive analysis once and treating findings as permanent.</description>
        <reason>Competitor products change continuously. Analysis older than 6-12 months describes a market that no longer exists. Schedule regular check-ins: major annually, minor quarterly, triggered when a competitor ships a significant update.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating competitive analysis as a substitute for user research.</description>
        <reason>Competitors' patterns may also be wrong. Users tolerate them because there is no better alternative. Validate competitive patterns with your own users before adopting them as design requirements.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Over-interpreting surface patterns without validating causation.</description>
        <reason>Competitors may have implemented a pattern for reasons unrelated to UX (regulatory constraint, technical limitation, legacy code). Surface observation cannot determine causation. Always include human review before committing to a recommendation based on competitor behavior.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <checklist>
      <check>Scope locked: 3-5 direct + 2-3 indirect + 1-2 aspirational, total ≤ 8, every entry has type/url/primary-user/price-tier in the analysis plan.</check>
      <check>Evaluation criteria written and rubric anchored before any competitor was opened (verify by file timestamp on analysis-plan.md predating any screenshot file in out/).</check>
      <check>For each competitor: real account created, primary flow completed on desktop AND mobile, at least one error state hit, support contacted with one realistic question.</check>
      <check>Automated accessibility audit run on ≥2 key screens per competitor (axe or Lighthouse JSON saved under out/&lt;competitor&gt;/).</check>
      <check>Each competitor has a profile from templates/competitor-profile.md with annotated screenshots, step-by-step flows, and the same section order as every other profile.</check>
      <check>Feature matrix complete: no empty cells, every cell has rubric score + 1-line note, final column classifies row as baseline / opportunity / best-practice / anti-pattern.</check>
      <check>Observations and recommendations live in separate sections per profile (no recommendation appears inside an Observations block).</check>
      <check>Every recommendation in the summary report is tagged Must Have / Should Have / Could Differentiate / Avoid AND cites at least one specific competitor + screen/flow as evidence.</check>
      <check>At least one aspirational (non-competitor) finding appears in Could Differentiate or as a pattern-transfer note.</check>
      <check>Anti-pattern claims are backed by external user-pain evidence (App Store review, G2/Trustpilot quote, support thread, or observed accessibility violation), not just analyst opinion.</check>
      <check>Report is dated and scoped (date, market, analyst). A re-run cadence is recorded (annual / quarterly / on-trigger).</check>
    </checklist>

    <verify>
      <step>Structural check: ensure these files exist and are non-empty: ./analysis-plan.md, ./feature-matrix.md, ./competitors/&lt;each&gt;.md, ./summary-report.md. Run: find . -type f -name '*.md' | xargs -I{} wc -l {} | awk '$1 &lt; 10 {print "TOO SHORT:", $0}'</step>
      <step>Coverage check: confirm competitor count is in range. Run: ls competitors/ | wc -l should return 6..8. Confirm the analysis plan tags each as direct/indirect/aspirational and totals match (3-5 / 2-3 / 1-2).</step>
      <step>Rubric consistency check: for every competitor profile, ensure all rubric criteria from the analysis plan are scored. Run a script or grep to ensure no criterion is missing per competitor.</step>
      <step>Evidence check: for every recommendation in summary-report.md under Must Have / Should Have / Could Differentiate / Avoid, grep that the recommendation references at least one competitor name and one screen or flow id.</step>
      <step>Accessibility evidence check: confirm out/&lt;competitor&gt;/*-axe.json or *-lighthouse.json exists for at least 2 screens per competitor.</step>
      <step>Freshness check: confirm every screenshot file mtime is within the analysis window (e.g. last 30 days). Run: find ./out -name '*.png' -mtime +30 — output must be empty.</step>
      <step>Peer sanity-check: a reviewer (human or independent agent) reads the summary report and answers three questions: (1) Could you reproduce any single recommendation from the cited evidence? (2) Are any recommendations not supported by an observation? (3) Is any tier (Must/Should/Could/Avoid) empty? An empty Could Differentiate tier is a yellow flag — re-examine the aspirational set.</step>
      <step>Decision-fit check: each Must Have recommendation maps to a backlog item or design ticket within 1 week of the report; otherwise the analysis was performative.</step>
    </verify>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/analysis-plan.md" purpose="Plan skeleton: objective, competitor list with types, evaluation criteria, rubric anchors, flows to analyze, timeline, re-run cadence."/>
      <template path="templates/feature-matrix.md" purpose="Comparison matrix: features × competitors with rating legend and final classification column (baseline/opportunity/best-practice/anti-pattern)."/>
      <template path="templates/competitor-profile.md" purpose="Per-competitor profile: overview, account used, key screens, flows, scoring table, strengths, weaknesses, opportunities (separate sections)."/>
      <template path="templates/summary-report.md" purpose="Executive report: key findings, feature matrix snapshot, UX pattern analysis, Must Have / Should Have / Could Differentiate / Avoid recommendations with evidence cites."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/competitive-usability-evaluations/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/how-to-do-a-competitive-analysis-in-ux-design"/>
      <link href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2018/04/competitive-analysis-ux-design/"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG22/quickref/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
