<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="competitive-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Examine 3-5 direct competitors and aspirational examples across predefined criteria to identify must-have features, parity items, differentiation opportunities, and anti-patterns to avoid.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>competitive-analysis</tag>
      <tag>competitor-research</tag>
      <tag>market-research</tag>
      <tag>ux-design</tag>
      <tag>strategy</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>research</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Competitive Analysis (UX)</title>

    <summary>Without competitive analysis, design teams reinvent solved problems, miss user expectations set by other products in the market, and cannot answer stakeholder questions like "what do competitors do?" Analyzing direct competitors surfaces the baseline users already expect; analyzing indirect competitors reveals alternative approaches; analyzing aspirational examples (best-in-class UX from adjacent industries) reveals what "best practice" looks like. The structured output converts observations into actionable prioritization: must-have (table stakes), should-have (competitive parity), could differentiate (opportunity gaps), and avoid (observed failure modes).</summary>

    <why>
      <p>User expectations are set by the products they use. If all competitors in your market offer guest checkout, users expect guest checkout from you even if you have not shipped it yet. If no competitor offers it, you have a differentiation opportunity. Competitive analysis surfaces these expectations and opportunities systematically.</p>
      <p>Analysis of aspirational examples from adjacent industries prevents pattern lock. The 5 competitors in your market may all share the same blind spot. Studying a best-in-class product from a different industry (e.g., learning from Spotify's onboarding even if you are building an e-commerce site) exposes solutions that your competitive set has not discovered.</p>
      <p>The structured framework (scope → criteria → data gathering → documentation → pattern analysis → recommendations) converts informal observations into prioritized decisions. Without structure, competitive analysis produces a list of features; with structure, it produces a decision roadmap.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before starting a new product or feature—establish baseline expectations before designing.</item>
        <item>When entering a new market segment where user expectations are unknown.</item>
        <item>When a competitor ships a significant update—evaluate whether it shifts user expectations.</item>
        <item>When stakeholders ask "what do others do?" as a blocker to a design decision.</item>
        <item>During quarterly design reviews to catch competitor product updates and emerging patterns.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Do not substitute competitive analysis for user research—competitors' choices may also be wrong; validate with your own users before adopting patterns.</item>
        <item>Do not analyze more than 8 competitors in a single pass—depth of analysis degrades; narrow scope or run multiple focused rounds.</item>
        <item>Do not treat findings as requirements—use them as input to design decisions, not as specifications.</item>
        <item>When your product targets a problem with no direct competitors—use analogous domain research instead.</item>
        <item>When the competitive landscape changes faster than you can act (e.g., fast-moving AI tools)—snapshot analysis becomes stale within weeks; update frequently or choose a slower-moving domain.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <how-to>
      <step>Define scope: select 3-5 direct competitors (same problem, same user), 2-3 indirect competitors (same problem, different approach), and 1-2 aspirational examples (best-in-class UX to learn from). Cap total at 8 to maintain analysis depth.</step>
      <step>Define evaluation criteria before examining any competitor product. Criteria derived after examination are biased toward what was observed. Consider dimensions: features (what users can do), user flows (how users accomplish goals), UI patterns (design conventions), information architecture (content organization), content and tone, accessibility compliance.</step>
      <step>Gather data by actually using products: create accounts, complete full flows end-to-end, test on both desktop and mobile, document edge cases, contact support, test accessibility. Do not review screenshots or marketing pages—they reveal visual design only; actual use reveals friction, error states, loading behavior, and onboarding quality.</step>
      <step>Document findings consistently using the same structure for every competitor: annotated screenshots, flow steps, strengths, weaknesses, and opportunities. Inconsistent documentation prevents comparison.</step>
      <step>Analyze for patterns across all competitors: identify what everyone does (baseline expectation), what nobody does (opportunity gap), what top performers do distinctively (best practice), and what problems exist in multiple products (anti-patterns to avoid).</step>
      <step>Generate prioritized recommendations: categorize every finding into Must Have (table stakes—users expect it), Should Have (competitive parity—helps feature parity), Could Differentiate (opportunity—no one does this), or Avoid (observed failure mode). This prioritization pre-empts debate about what to build first.</step>
    </how-to>

    <section name="scope-and-selection">
      <p>Selecting the right competitors and scope is critical. Too broad a scope dilutes analysis depth; too narrow misses important patterns.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Select 3-5 direct competitors (same problem, same user audience), 2-3 indirect competitors (same problem, different user or approach), and 1-2 aspirational examples (best-in-class UX from any industry). Cap total at 8 to maintain depth.</statement>
        <rationale>More than 8 competitors transforms the analysis from depth-focused to breadth-focused. Breadth generates feature lists; depth generates insights. Direct competitors establish the baseline; indirect competitors reveal alternative approaches; aspirational examples break pattern lock.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define competitor types before beginning: Direct (same problem, same user—e.g., Uber vs Lyft), Indirect (same problem, different approach—e.g., Uber vs public transit), Partial (overlapping features but different scope), Aspirational (best-in-class to learn from, not a direct competitor).</statement>
        <rationale>Clarity on competitor type ensures the right analysis. Analyzing only direct competitors may miss solutions. Including aspiration examples exposes UX innovations from unrelated industries.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="criteria-definition">
      <p>Pre-defined criteria prevent bias. Criteria chosen after observing competitors reflect what was observed, not what matters.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Establish evaluation criteria before examining any competitor product. Criteria derived after observation introduce confirmation bias.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-hoc criteria selection is unconsciously biased: analysts weight criteria where their preferred design performs well. Pre-defined criteria are neutral and repeatable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use consistent scoring rubrics for all competitors. Prefer qualitative scales (Excellent/Good/Fair/Poor) over binary (Yes/No) to capture degree of implementation.</statement>
        <rationale>Binary scoring loses nuance. A feature implemented poorly is not the same as a feature implemented well. Qualitative scales surface these degrees and produce better comparative insights.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Document your scoring criteria and definitions before beginning (e.g., "Excellent onboarding = completes in under 3 minutes and shows value immediately; Good = 3-5 minutes; Fair = 5-10 minutes; Poor = over 10 minutes or unclear value proposition").</statement>
        <rationale>Without definitions, scoring drifts across competitors. Explicit definitions ensure consistency and make scores repeatable if someone else conducts the analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="data-gathering">
      <p>Hands-on use is non-negotiable. Screenshots and marketing pages miss the actual experience.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Create real accounts and complete full user flows rather than reviewing screenshots or marketing pages. Use on both desktop and mobile, test edge cases and error states, contact support, test accessibility.</statement>
        <rationale>Screenshots reveal visual design; actual use reveals friction. Error messages, loading states, support responsiveness, and onboarding flow are invisible in screenshots. These are often where competitors differentiate.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Conduct the analysis yourself (use the product, create accounts, complete full flows). Do not delegate deep qualitative pass to an agent or junior analyst.</statement>
        <rationale>Deep insights come from hands-on use and noticing details that automated tools miss. Nuanced UX observations (tone, visual hierarchy, interaction smoothness) require human judgment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Annotate screenshots and observations immediately. Memory of details degrades fast—hours later you will forget why a particular pattern was notable.</statement>
        <rationale>Rich annotations during the session preserve context. Notes taken hours later lack the immediate sense of what made the interaction notable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="documentation-consistency">
      <p>Consistent documentation enables comparison. Inconsistent notes prevent useful synthesis.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use the same documentation structure for every competitor: per-competitor profile template with sections for overview, key screens (annotated), user flows (step-by-step), strengths, weaknesses, and opportunities.</statement>
        <rationale>Structured templates ensure the same dimensions are evaluated for all competitors. Ad-hoc notes cannot be compared across products.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Separate "what they do" observations from "what we should do" recommendations. Keep them in distinct sections until synthesis. An observation ("Competitor A shows estimated delivery on the product page") is different from a recommendation ("we should show estimated delivery earlier").</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing observations and recommendations conflates data with interpretation. Separate them to enable a later review where someone else can validate observations and challenge recommendations.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="pattern-analysis">
      <p>Pattern analysis converts individual observations into strategic insights. Individual competitor review produces feature lists; pattern analysis produces direction.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>After documenting all competitors, identify patterns: what everyone does (baseline expectation), what nobody does (opportunity), what top performers do distinctively (best practice), and what problems appear in multiple products (anti-patterns).</statement>
        <rationale>Individual competitor analysis is a data-gathering phase; pattern analysis is where data becomes insight. A feature present in all 5 competitors is table stakes; a feature present in 0 is an opportunity; a feature that top performers execute well and others botch is a best practice.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Flag patterns that differ by product type, user segment, or use case. A pattern that holds for enterprise SaaS may not hold for consumer products. Document these distinctions.</statement>
        <rationale>Pattern blindness: assuming a pattern applies universally when it only applies to a specific segment. Noting segment differences prevents over-generalizing findings.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Include one aspirational non-competitor (different industry, best-in-class UX) to break pattern lock. Analyze whether patterns unique to your competitive set could be improved using patterns from outside your industry.</statement>
        <rationale>Entire competitive sets can converge on suboptimal patterns. A pattern transfer from a different industry often yields the highest-value insights.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="recommendation-prioritization">
      <p>Four-tier recommendation structure produces clarity and pre-empts debate.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Categorize every recommendation into Must Have (table stakes), Should Have (parity), Could Differentiate (opportunity), or Avoid (failure mode).</statement>
        <rationale>Without tiers, all recommendations appear equal and trigger debate about priority. Tiers make prioritization explicit: Must Have are blockers; Avoid are negative signals; Could Differentiate are the most valuable output.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Definition of each tier:</p>
      <term name="Must Have">Table stakes. Present in 4+ competitors or user-facing expectation. Not having it is a competitive disadvantage. Implement before shipping.</term>
      <term name="Should Have">Competitive parity. Present in 2-3 competitors or expected by power users. Implement in next release or roadmap soon.</term>
      <term name="Could Differentiate">Opportunity gap. Absent from competitors or executed poorly by all. Could differentiate if executed exceptionally. Evaluate for roadmap if resources allow.</term>
      <term name="Avoid">Failure mode. Observed in one or more competitors and consistently causes problems (support load, user complaints, accessibility issues). Document why competitors made this choice and commit to not repeating it.</term>

      <example type="good" title="E-commerce Checkout Prioritization">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Finding: All 5 competitors offer guest checkout.
Insight: Guest checkout is table stakes.
Recommendation: Must Have. Not having it is a competitive disadvantage.

Finding: Only 1 competitor shows estimated delivery on the product page.
Insight: All others show it in the cart or at checkout.
Recommendation: Could Differentiate. Showing delivery estimate earlier in the flow than competitors could reduce cart abandonment.

Finding: 3 competitors have payment errors with unclear recovery steps; users call support.
Insight: Error handling during payment is a weak point.
Recommendation: Avoid copying competitor error messages. Invest in clear error states and single-step recovery.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="SaaS Onboarding">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Competitor A: 8 onboarding steps, 15 minutes to value
Competitor B: 3 steps, 2 minutes to value
Competitor C: 5 steps, 8 minutes to value
Competitor B has highest user ratings on G2.

Insight: Time-to-first-value is the primary lever. Minimal onboarding correlates with satisfaction.
Recommendation: Target 3-4 steps maximum. Measure time-to-first-value as the primary onboarding success metric.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Analyzing only direct competitors and ignoring aspirational examples from other industries.</description>
        <reason>Direct competitors may all share the same blind spot. Aspirational examples expose solutions that the competitive set has not discovered. Pattern transfers across industries often yield the highest-value insights.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Copying a competitor pattern without understanding why they made that choice.</description>
        <reason>The competitor may have shipped that pattern to fix a specific problem in their system that does not apply to yours. Copying without understanding context imports constraints along with the solution.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Running competitive analysis once and treating findings as permanent.</description>
        <reason>Competitor products change continuously. Analysis older than 6-12 months describes a market that no longer exists. Schedule regular check-ins: major annually, minor quarterly, triggered when a competitor ships a significant update.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating competitive analysis as a substitute for user research.</description>
        <reason>Competitors' patterns may also be wrong. Users tolerate them because there is no better alternative. Validate competitive patterns with your own users before adopting them as design requirements.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Over-interpreting surface patterns without validating causation.</description>
        <reason>Competitors may have implemented a pattern for reasons unrelated to UX (regulatory constraint, technical limitation, legacy code). Surface observation cannot determine causation. Always include human review before committing to a recommendation based on competitor behavior.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/analysis-plan.md" purpose="Plan skeleton: objective, competitor list with types, evaluation criteria, flows to analyze, timeline."/>
      <template path="templates/feature-matrix.md" purpose="Comparison matrix: features × competitors with rating legend."/>
      <template path="templates/competitor-profile.md" purpose="Per-competitor profile: overview, key screens, flows, strengths, weaknesses, opportunities."/>
      <template path="templates/summary-report.md" purpose="Executive report: key findings, feature comparison, UX pattern analysis, Must Have/Should Have/Could Differentiate/Avoid recommendations."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/competitive-usability-evaluations/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/how-to-do-a-competitive-analysis-in-ux-design"/>
      <link href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2018/04/competitive-analysis-ux-design/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
