<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Market Research: TAM/SAM/SOM Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Market Research: TAM/SAM/SOM methodology. Every rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale, plus the universal skip-this-methodology gate.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="both-top-down-and-bottom-up" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every TAM/SAM/SOM artefact MUST include both a top-down number (industry-report-scaled) and a bottom-up number (price x reachable units).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — market-size due-diligence">Single-source sizing is unauditable; triangulation surfaces hidden assumptions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="reconcile-30pct-delta" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If top-down and bottom-up disagree by more than 30%, write an explicit reconciliation paragraph; do not just average them.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Q1 2026 market-size audit">A 30%+ delta signals a wrong assumption (geography, ICP, price band); averaging hides the bug.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cite-every-number" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every TAM/SAM/SOM number MUST cite a URL + retrieval date.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — pitch-deck rejection log">Industry reports change; without a date the number cannot be replicated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="som-confidence-tag" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>SOM MUST carry a confidence tag (high/medium/low) with a one-line reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — investor due-diligence">Unhedged SOM in a pitch deck is a credibility liability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="geo-and-icp-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>TAM/SAM/SOM MUST be computed for an explicitly pinned geography list + ICP definition; refuse 'global' as a geography.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — multi-region launch audit">Global TAM is meaningless for a product that ships in 3 countries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only if all entries in `## Applies If` hold and none of `## Skip If` triggers; otherwise abort and route to the correct methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — decision tree minimum form">A misrouted methodology produces wrong-shape output; the explicit skip rule is the universal default branch from the decision tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
