<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Async Standup Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every async-Slack standup must enforce. These are hard rules — individual contributor preferences do not override them.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-three-field-shape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every post in the standup thread has exactly three labeled fields in this order: Yesterday, Today, Blocker. No additional headers, no "personal" fields, no "mood" fields. If "Blocker" is empty, write "Blocker: none." Never omit the field.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitLab async handbook; Doist Twist async pattern; Atlassian Distributed-team playbook">Three fields scan in 8 seconds. Free-form updates take 30+ seconds and 70% of the PM's reading time turns into reading prose, not extracting signal. The empty-Blocker-with-explicit-"none" rule prevents "did they forget or do they have no blocker?" ambiguity that wastes the PM's day.</rationale>
      <example type="good" title="Shape-compliant post">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Yesterday: shipped checkout flow v2 to staging; pair-debugged the
  Klaviyo webhook 4xx with Maria.
Today: production rollout behind feature flag (10% canary), then
  monitor metrics for 4h before broader.
Blocker: need @raj to confirm DB migration window for the canary
  promotion — current proposal is 14:00 UTC tomorrow.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Free-form drift">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Hey team! Crazy day yesterday with the launch but we got through it.
Today I'm going to try to wrap up the checkout work. There's a small
thing with the database that I should mention.
        ]]></code>
        <note>No labels, no actionable blocker, requires the PM to extract intent from prose. Standup defeats itself.</note>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-post-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each contributor posts within their local working window (first 2 hours of their working day OR last 1 hour of the previous working day). Posting outside the window is allowed but flagged. If a contributor misses two consecutive working days without a heads-up, trigger the silence-detector ping.</statement>
      <rationale source="Distributed-team coordination research (GitLab All-Remote survey, 2024)">Window-anchoring lets the PM batch-read once per day at a predictable time instead of refreshing Slack hourly. The 2-day silence threshold balances "respect deep work" against "did the contractor ghost?" — the most common failure mode in P4 outsource engagements.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-blocker-routing-and-sla" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Blocker field that is non-"none" must @-mention exactly one owner (the person who can unblock or escalate). The owner must respond in the thread within 12 hours of their next working day start. If no response in window, escalate to PM with @-here.</statement>
      <rationale source="Doist communication-tier model; Slack official Async Standup playbook">Unrouted blockers stay blocked. The single-owner rule prevents the "diffusion of responsibility" anti-pattern where 3 people are @-tagged and none responds. 12 hours is short enough to keep progress moving, long enough to respect timezone gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-silence-detection" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A scheduled job (Slack Workflow Builder, GitHub Action, or PM script) checks for missed posts and DMs the missing contributor at 4h before their working-day end. If still no post after 8h, ping the PM. Two consecutive misses → PM phone-call or video check-in, not Slack-only.</statement>
      <rationale source="Distributed-team retention research (Buffer State of Remote Work, 2024); outsource project failure-mode analysis">In outsource engagements the highest-value early signal of contractor disengagement is "stopped posting standup." Detecting it within hours rather than a week is the difference between rescue and replacement. Phone-call escalation matters because "lost contractor" is often a personal-life issue, not a work issue.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-weekly-digest" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Friday (or last working day of the team's shared week) the PM (or an AI summarizer) generates a 5-line weekly digest from the 5 daily threads: (1) shipped/done, (2) in-progress carry-overs, (3) unresolved blockers, (4) any contributor with ≥2 missed posts, (5) one upcoming-week risk. Posted in the standup channel and pinned for the next week.</statement>
      <rationale source="Shape Up / Basecamp 'hill chart' weekly cadence; GitLab weekly recap practice">Daily posts are noise without weekly compression. The digest closes the loop: contributors see their work reflected, the client/PM-of-record sees aggregate progress, the next week starts with carry-over visibility. Without the digest, async standup is a write-only log.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
