<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gcp-resource-hierarchy Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gcp-resource-hierarchy. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep folder nesting depth at 3 or fewer levels. Deeply nested hierarchies increase policy complexity without adding governance value.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each additional folder level adds an inheritance layer to debug when IAM or org-policy issues occur. Flat hierarchies are easier to reason about and audit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Separate environments (dev/staging/prod) into different projects, not different folders inside one project. Each environment must have its own project.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Projects are the billing and API-enablement boundary. Mixing environments in one project makes it impossible to restrict prod APIs from dev workloads or attribute costs separately.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All projects MUST follow the naming pattern: {resource-type}-{environment}-{application}. Project IDs must be globally unique and immutable once created — include a short hex suffix if needed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Project names are mutable but project IDs are not. Using a deterministic prefix scheme (prj-prod-ecommerce) makes the hierarchy navigable without console access and avoids naming conflicts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Projects MUST carry at minimum three labels: env (prod|staging|dev), team (owning team), cost_center (cost center code). Enforce this via an org policy custom constraint.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Labels are the only mechanism for attributing costs to teams and cost centers in BigQuery billing exports. Projects without labels appear as unattributed spend in cost reports.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
