<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Kubernetes Cost Optimisation Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>≥5 testable rules grounding the finops-devops-cost-kubernetes methodology, each paired with rationale and source reference.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="workload-pool-segmentation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Split node pools by workload class — system, on-demand stateful, Spot batch, GPU — and taint Spot + GPU pools so only tolerating workloads land on them.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Mixing classes blocks autoscaler from down-scaling and forces over-provisioning for the worst-case pod.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="request-limit-ratio" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set CPU requests to observed P95 and memory requests + limits equal; do not set CPU limits unless throttling is required.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Memory limit ≠ request triggers OOMKill on bursts; CPU limits at request level cause throttling under load.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="hpa-on-business-metric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use HPA on a business-level metric (RPS, queue depth) or P95 CPU, with min replicas ≥ 2 for production workloads and stabilizationWindowSeconds set on scale-down.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">CPU-only HPA lags traffic spikes; aggressive scale-down without a stabilisation window thrashes the cluster.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="namespace-quotas" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply ResourceQuota + LimitRange in every tenant namespace and enforce required cost-allocation labels at admission.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Without quotas one team's runaway job can starve the whole cluster; labels keep chargeback honest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kubecost-coverage-target" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track utilisation per workload via kubecost or OpenCost and alert when cluster CPU utilisation falls below 35% or memory below 50% sustained over 7 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Sub-threshold utilisation is the kubernetes-specific signal that node-pool sizing has drifted from reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, do NOT run this methodology — return early with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree's negative branch must terminate cleanly without partial output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold AND scope is explicit, run the methodology end-to-end and produce the canonical artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree positive-branch terminus; aliases the apply-end-to-end verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
