<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-canvas-and-revenue-models" title="Business Model Canvas and Revenue Archetypes">
  <summary>Nine-block Business Model Canvas with Hard/Soft cell tagging and five revenue archetypes with variant tables and best-fit signals.</summary>

  <section title="Business Model Canvas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Populate all 9 Canvas blocks before naming any price; tag each cell Hard (sourced from a public filing, pricing page, or comparable company) or Soft (founder estimate).</statement>
      <rationale>Agents skip the Canvas and produce unit economics without understanding the cost structure. Hard/Soft tagging makes the assumptions ledger auditable and enables future re-runs to diff what changed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Customer Segments: who are the paying users? primary + secondary</item>
      <item>Value Propositions: what value is delivered to each segment?</item>
      <item>Channels: awareness, evaluation, purchase, delivery, after-sales</item>
      <item>Customer Relationships: self-serve / assisted / automated; retention mechanisms</item>
      <item>Revenue Streams: model type, price, estimated % of total revenue</item>
      <item>Key Resources: physical, intellectual, human, financial</item>
      <item>Key Activities: the 3 most critical activities for delivering value</item>
      <item>Key Partners: what they provide, what they get in return</item>
      <item>Cost Structure: fixed vs variable; cost-driven vs value-driven orientation</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Revenue Archetypes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Shortlist exactly 2 of the 5 revenue archetypes that fit the value chain; reject the others on record with a one-line reason before running unit economics.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs default to SaaS subscription whenever the product is digital. Forcing an explicit rejection of the other four archetypes surfaces assumptions that would otherwise remain implicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Subscription/SaaS: flat rate, tiered, per-seat, usage-based, freemium — best for ongoing value delivery, sticky products. Key metrics: MRR, churn, LTV, CAC.</item>
      <item>One-time purchase: digital product, software license, physical product — best for discrete value and impulse buys. Key metrics: units sold, revenue per product, repeat purchase rate.</item>
      <item>Transaction-based: percentage cut, flat fee per transaction, hybrid — best for marketplaces, payments, brokerage. Key metrics: GMV, take rate, transaction volume.</item>
      <item>Advertising: display, sponsored, affiliate — best for high-traffic content platforms. Key metrics: DAU, CPM, CTR, ad inventory fill rate.</item>
      <item>Marketplace/Commission: service, product, lead generation — best for matching problems with network effects. Key metrics: GMV, take rate, liquidity.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Archetype Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Assuming 20-30% take rate for a new marketplace.</description>
      <reason>Real successful marketplaces compress to 5-15% as suppliers gain leverage (Etsy 6.5%, Airbnb 14%, Upwork 10%). Agents assume high take rates because they pattern-match aspirational claims.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using revenue as if it were profit in the Canvas Cost Structure block.</description>
      <reason>Gross margin must be sourced separately; AI-heavy products run 30-50% due to inference costs, not 80% SaaS folklore. Missing the Cost Structure block makes LTV:CAC unreliable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Modeling freemium conversion at 15% without evidence.</description>
      <reason>Floor conversion is 2% (consumer) / 5% (B2B). Claims above these require an empirical citation or a Soft tag.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
