<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Business Model Research Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Business Model Research methodology. Every rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale, plus the universal skip-this-methodology gate.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="populate-canvas-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Populate all 9 Canvas blocks before naming any price; tag every cell Hard (sourced) or Soft (founder estimate).</statement>
      <rationale source="Strategyzer, Business Model Generation (2010)">Agents skip the Canvas and produce unit economics without understanding cost structure; Hard/Soft tagging makes the assumptions ledger auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="shortlist-two-archetypes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shortlist exactly 2 of the 5 revenue archetypes that fit the value chain; reject the other 3 on record with a one-line reason before unit economics.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — pricing audits Q1 2026">LLMs default to SaaS subscription for any digital product; forcing explicit rejection of the other archetypes surfaces hidden assumptions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ltv-cap-60-months" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always compute LTV with a lifetime cap of 60 months; the formula 1/churn explodes at low churn rates and produces fantasy LTVs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Baremetrics, ChartMogul SaaS benchmarks">1% monthly churn implies 8.3-year average lifetime; SaaS products rarely sustain customers that long without 10-K cohort evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="p10-p50-p90-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run unit economics in three scenarios (P10 pessimistic, P50 base, P90 optimistic) before writing any verdict; the P10 verdict is the only one that matters for runway decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — runway planning standard">Single-point LTV:CAC hides the distribution; operators need to know if the model survives a bad quarter, not just a median one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="five-stress-tests-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The model passes only if it survives all five stress tests (Scale, Competition, Churn, CAC, Time-to-profit) at P50 and does not go below 1:1 LTV:CAC at P10.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — VC due-diligence checklist">A model that passes only 4 of 5 has a known failure mode that materializes as the business scales; documenting it beats optimism.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="churn-floor-1pct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Refuse to compute LTV with monthly churn below 1% unless backed by a public 10-K; sub-1% churn is a unicorn claim requiring evidence.</statement>
      <rationale source="Baremetrics median SaaS monthly churn 2-4%">Agents accept 0.5%/month churn from blog posts; LTV explodes 5x and the model looks viable when it is not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only if all entries in `## Applies If` hold and none of `## Skip If` triggers; otherwise abort and route to the correct methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — decision tree minimum form">A misrouted methodology produces wrong-shape output; the explicit skip rule is the universal default branch from the decision tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
