<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Canonical L1 index for playbook goal categories. -->
<taxonomy version="1.0" axis="goal-character" target="playbooks">

  <description>
    Playbooks group by the character of the goal they achieve, not by who runs them.
    A retriever picks one or two categories from this taxonomy, then drills into
    that category's INDEX.xml to find a specific playbook.
  </description>

  <decision-tree>
    <description>
      Read top-to-bottom. The first matching trigger wins. Triggers are written from
      the user's perspective — "I want to / I need to" framing.
    </description>

    <step n="1">If user says "is X worth doing?" / "should we even build this?" → discover-validate</step>
    <step n="2">If user has validated X and needs to design / spec it → plan-design</step>
    <step n="3">If user has a plan and needs to actually ship / produce → build-ship</step>
    <step n="4">If user has shipped X and it's now an ongoing rhythm (daily / weekly / quarterly) → operate-ritual</step>
    <step n="5">If user needs to make a single decision (A vs B, hire vs not, kill vs continue) → govern-decide</step>
    <step n="6">If something is broken / failing right now → fix-incident</step>
    <step n="7">If X works but should be cheaper / faster / cleaner → optimize-tune</step>
    <step n="8">If user needs to move from old-tech / old-process to new → migrate-rebuild</step>
    <step n="9">If user needs more users / leads / MRR → acquire-grow</step>
    <step n="10">If user needs to add a person / vendor / contractor → hire-onboard</step>
    <step n="11">If user needs to prove conformance (SOC2 / GDPR / accessibility / SLA) → audit-comply</step>
  </decision-tree>

  <category id="discover-validate" trigger="є гіпотеза, треба перевірити чи варта роботи">
    <intent>Turn an idea or assumption into evidence. Output is a written go/no-go decision backed by data.</intent>
    <scope>Customer interviews, problem validation, MVP tests, demand probes, kill criteria, willingness-to-pay tests.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>signed problem statement, kill criteria, willingness-to-pay evidence, validated MVP scope</typical-outputs>
  </category>

  <category id="plan-design" trigger="є валідація, не знаю як саме будувати">
    <intent>Turn validated intent into a buildable spec. Output is something a developer / designer / agent can execute against.</intent>
    <scope>SDD specs, design briefs, RFCs, ADRs, system designs, capacity models, threat models, test plans.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>spec.md, design.md, ADR pack, threat model, test plan, capacity model</typical-outputs>
  </category>

  <category id="build-ship" trigger="є план, треба зробити і випустити">
    <intent>Convert spec into deployed, working artefact. Output is a thing users can use.</intent>
    <scope>Feature delivery, MVP launches, content production, deploys, releases, prod cutover.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>deployed feature, PR merged, content live, release cut, prod traffic switched</typical-outputs>
  </category>

  <category id="operate-ritual" trigger="це треба робити регулярно (день/тиждень/квартал)">
    <intent>Run a recurring rhythm reliably. Output is the same kind of artefact week after week.</intent>
    <scope>Daily standups, weekly metrics reviews, sprint planning, quarterly OKR resets, monthly retros, on-call handoffs.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>weekly metrics report, sprint plan, OKR refresh, retro notes, on-call handoff log</typical-outputs>
  </category>

  <category id="govern-decide" trigger="треба прийняти одне рішення серед варіантів">
    <intent>Gather inputs and make a single explicit decision. Output is a written decision with reasoning.</intent>
    <scope>Build vs buy, kill vs continue, A vs B technology choice, scope-in / scope-out, hire vs not, vendor evaluation gates.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>signed decision memo, ADR, vendor evaluation matrix, kill memo, scope gate sign-off</typical-outputs>
  </category>

  <category id="fix-incident" trigger="зараз щось зламано, треба полагодити">
    <intent>Restore a broken thing to working state. Output is service / build / pipeline back to green.</intent>
    <scope>Production incidents, broken builds, failed deploys, security breaches, account lockouts, escalations.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>incident resolved, postmortem written, root cause logged, follow-up tickets created</typical-outputs>
  </category>

  <category id="optimize-tune" trigger="воно працює, але можна краще">
    <intent>Improve a working thing along one axis (cost / speed / quality / reliability). Output is a measurable delta.</intent>
    <scope>Performance tuning, cost-cutting sweeps, conversion-rate experiments, latency reductions, code refactors, test-suite cleanups.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>perf delta, cost saving %, CR uplift, p95 improvement, refactor PR shipped</typical-outputs>
  </category>

  <category id="migrate-rebuild" trigger="треба перейти зі старого на нове">
    <intent>Move from one technology / process / contract to another with continuity. Output is the cutover completed cleanly.</intent>
    <scope>Framework upgrades, monolith→service splits, vendor switches, process change rollouts, schema migrations, repo moves.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>cutover plan executed, old tech retired, parallel-run period closed, rollback path tested</typical-outputs>
  </category>

  <category id="acquire-grow" trigger="треба більше користувачів / лідів / MRR">
    <intent>Increase top-of-funnel or move users along the funnel. Output is a measurable funnel improvement.</intent>
    <scope>SEO campaigns, paid ads, content cadence, launch campaigns, PR pushes, referral programs, retention drips.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>+N users, +X MRR, +Y% conversion, launch executed, audience grown</typical-outputs>
  </category>

  <category id="hire-onboard" trigger="треба додати людину чи контрактора">
    <intent>Add a person to the team and get them productive. Output is the person delivering useful work.</intent>
    <scope>First-hire, contractor onboarding, vendor selection, role definition, onboarding plans, 30-60-90 plans.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>signed contract, onboarding plan executed, first deliverable shipped, 90-day review</typical-outputs>
  </category>

  <category id="audit-comply" trigger="треба показати що ми відповідаємо вимогам">
    <intent>Demonstrate conformance to an external standard. Output is an audit-ready evidence pack.</intent>
    <scope>SOC2, GDPR, accessibility, security reviews, SLA reporting, regulatory KYC, ISO27k mapping.</scope>
    <typical-outputs>evidence pack, control map, audit response binder, conformance attestation</typical-outputs>
  </category>

</taxonomy>
