<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="pm-framework-focus-areas Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for pm-framework-focus-areas. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat focus areas as aspects of ongoing work, not sequential phases; Planning and Monitoring and Controlling occur throughout the project lifecycle, not just once.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Conflating focus areas with phases re-introduces waterfall thinking and misrepresents how agile and hybrid projects operate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not apply all 40 processes by default; document which processes are adopted and which are tailored out, with justification.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Applying the full menu creates overhead that exceeds value, especially for small or agile projects.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Closing is never optional; even purely agile projects require a final retrospective across all sprints and a lessons-learned record.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Skipping Closing leaves no institutional memory and no formal signal that the project is done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For agile projects, document the focus-area mapping in the charter (sprint planning = Planning + Executing slice; sprint review = Monitoring and Controlling) so reviewers do not get lost.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without an explicit mapping, reviewers apply predictive assumptions and flag missing artefacts that have agile equivalents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use "focus area" as the canonical term; never "process group" when working in PMBoK 8 context.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixing PMBoK 6 process group names with PMBoK 8 focus area names causes vocabulary drift and audit confusion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Abbreviate Monitoring and Controlling consistently as "MnC" within a project; pick one abbreviation and pin it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Inconsistent abbreviations (M&amp;C, MnC, MC) create diffs that are hard to read and audit tools that fail silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
