<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-focus-areas" title="PMBoK 8 Five Focus Areas">
  <summary>Five temporal focus areas replace Process Groups; same structure applies to predictive and agile with different artefacts.</summary>

  <section title="Focus Area Definitions">
    <list>
      <item>Initiating — establish vision, purpose, alignment. Predictive: project charter. Agile: vision, goals.</item>
      <item>Planning — define approach, build estimates, identify risks. Predictive: WBS, requirements. Agile: backlog, user stories.</item>
      <item>Executing — perform work to achieve objectives. Predictive: work packages. Agile: sprints, iterations.</item>
      <item>Monitoring and Controlling — track performance, manage changes. Predictive: EVM, baselines. Agile: velocity, burndown.</item>
      <item>Closing — formal completion, lessons learned. Predictive: final reports. Agile: project-end retrospective.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Focus Areas are Aspects, Not Phases">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat focus areas as aspects of ongoing work, not sequential phases; Planning and Monitoring and Controlling occur throughout the project lifecycle, not just once.</statement>
      <rationale>Conflating focus areas with phases re-introduces waterfall thinking and misrepresents how agile and hybrid projects operate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="40 Non-Prescriptive Processes">
    <p>PMBoK 8 distributes 40 processes across the 5 focus areas and 7 performance domains. They describe how work is commonly performed — not a mandatory checklist. Select the subset with measurable inputs and outputs for your context; skip the rest explicitly.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not apply all 40 processes by default; document which processes are adopted and which are tailored out, with justification.</statement>
      <rationale>Applying the full menu creates overhead that exceeds value, especially for small or agile projects.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="5 x 7 Matrix">
    <p>Use focus areas as the temporal index (when) and the seven performance domains as the topical index (what). The project plan is a 5 x 7 matrix; fill only the cells that apply. Empty cells are valid and must be explicitly null — do not invent artefacts to fill them.</p>
    <reference path="templates/lifecycle-matrix.md">5 x 7 matrix template for tailoring</reference>
    <reference path="scripts/matrix-to-checklist.py">Matrix YAML to stage-gate checklist generator</reference>
  </section>
</text>
