<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Focus Areas Rules and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete rules for applying PMBoK 8 focus areas correctly across predictive, agile, and hybrid projects.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Closing is never optional; even purely agile projects require a final retrospective across all sprints and a lessons-learned record.</statement>
    <rationale>Skipping Closing leaves no institutional memory and no formal signal that the project is done.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>For agile projects, document the focus-area mapping in the charter (sprint planning = Planning + Executing slice; sprint review = Monitoring and Controlling) so reviewers do not get lost.</statement>
    <rationale>Without an explicit mapping, reviewers apply predictive assumptions and flag missing artefacts that have agile equivalents.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Use "focus area" as the canonical term; never "process group" when working in PMBoK 8 context.</statement>
    <rationale>Mixing PMBoK 6 process group names with PMBoK 8 focus area names causes vocabulary drift and audit confusion.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Abbreviate Monitoring and Controlling consistently as "MnC" within a project; pick one abbreviation and pin it.</statement>
    <rationale>Inconsistent abbreviations (M&amp;C, MnC, MC) create diffs that are hard to read and audit tools that fail silently.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Listing all 40 non-prescriptive processes in the project plan when only 8-12 apply.</description>
    <reason>Full process lists inflate documentation cost and imply mandatory compliance; cap with explicit tailoring decisions.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Emitting "Stakeholder phase complete" or "Team phase done" — treating domains as phases.</description>
    <reason>Performance domains are ongoing concerns, not sequential phases; "complete" is never valid for a domain.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Skipping the Initiating focus area on internal projects ("we already started").</description>
    <reason>No charter or decision record means no traceable rationale for scope and constraints; gap surfaces during audits and change requests.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Including Procurement under Executing and dropping it when no contractors exist — then adding it back when contractors appear mid-project.</description>
    <reason>Procurement must be evaluated at Initiating/Planning; retroactive addition after kickoff disrupts cost and schedule baselines.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
