<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="hybrid-search-implementation Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six testable rules for production hybrid-search implementations across Weaviate, Qdrant, Pinecone, Elasticsearch.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-weaviate-native-hybrid" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For Weaviate, use the native hybrid() query method with alpha parameter; do not run dense + BM25 client-side when the server supports it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source; Weaviate docs">Weaviate handles BM25 preprocessing and fusion internally, reducing latency and code complexity vs client-side fusion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-qdrant-precompute-sparse" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For Qdrant, pre-compute sparse vectors (BM25 or SPLADE) in application code before insert; Qdrant stores (indices,values) but has no built-in tokeniser.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source; Qdrant docs">Passing raw text to a sparse vector field produces a type error at the API level. Tokenisation must live in application code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-pinecone-bm25encoder" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For Pinecone sparse-dense, train BM25Encoder on the full corpus before ingestion; significant corpus changes invalidate the encoder and require retraining.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source; Pinecone docs">BM25Encoder learns corpus-wide IDF. Stale IDF weights degrade keyword recall as the corpus grows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-default-rrf" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default to RRF over linear combination when leg scores come on different scales; require an alpha sweep before switching to linear.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">RRF uses rank positions and is immune to score-scale mismatches. Linear without normalisation is fragile.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-measure-alpha" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Measure alpha on a labeled eval set of ≥50 queries before deploying; never ship a guessed alpha to production.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Wrong alpha can be worse than either method alone. Intuition about the right value is unreliable across corpora.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-fetch-2-3x-candidates" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-fetch 2-3x the desired top-K from each leg (e.g., k_leg=30 for final k=10) so fusion can promote middle-ranked documents that win across both methods.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Documents that rank 8-15 in each leg but win in fused score are the entire reason hybrid beats single-leg. Fetching only top-K per leg loses them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the target store is not in {Weaviate, Qdrant, Pinecone, Elasticsearch} or latency budget blocks two-leg retrieval, skip hybrid-search-implementation.</statement>
      <rationale source="phase-d">Covered backends define the implementation paths; outside them this methodology does not apply directly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
