<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="hybrid-search-implementation Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Four observable antipatterns when implementing hybrid search.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <antipattern id="fm-english-tokeniser-cjk">
      <description>Using the default English BM25 tokeniser on a CJK / Arabic / multilingual corpus.</description>
      <reason>Whitespace tokenisation produces single-character or meaningless tokens for non-whitespace languages, leading to near-zero BM25 scores. Detector: BM25 recall on non-English queries ≪ dense recall. Fix: per-language tokenisers; use Lucene/ICU analyzer or Janome for JP.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="fm-stale-bm25encoder">
      <description>Fitting Pinecone's BM25Encoder on a partial corpus, then ingesting more documents without retraining.</description>
      <reason>IDF weights become stale; recall on the newly ingested portion drops. Detector: A/B old-encoder vs new-encoder on a held-out set shows recall regression. Fix: enforce r3-pinecone-bm25encoder — retrain on full corpus.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="fm-type-mix-qdrant-pinecone">
      <description>Mixing Qdrant SparseVector(indices=, values=) with Pinecone {"indices": [...], "values": [...]} dict shape.</description>
      <reason>The two SDKs use different Python types/conventions. Detector: TypeError at insert time. Fix: encapsulate per-backend in adapters; never pass raw sparse representations across boundaries.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="fm-serial-leg-execution">
      <description>Running dense leg and BM25 leg serially when the backend does not offer native hybrid.</description>
      <reason>P99 latency doubles vs parallel execution. Detector: p99 latency = dense_p99 + sparse_p99 instead of max(...). Fix: use asyncio.gather or a thread pool to fire both legs concurrently.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-core-rules.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
