<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="agile-ba-frameworks">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Maps BA competencies onto Scrum phases and SAFe levels. Defines BA roles per ceremony and per ART level. Includes techniques and certifications (AAC, SAFe SA, POPM, CPOA).</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>scrum</tag>
      <tag>safe</tag>
      <tag>business-analysis</tag>
      <tag>frameworks</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Agile BA Frameworks</title>
    <summary>A mapping of business analysis competencies onto Scrum ceremonies and scaled agile framework (SAFe) levels. Defines what a BA does in each Scrum phase (Sprint 0, refinement, planning, execution, review, retrospective) and at each SAFe level (Team, Program, Large Solution, Portfolio). Includes agile-specific techniques (user story mapping, example mapping, story splitting, impact mapping, event storming) and the relevant certifications (AAC, SAFe SA, POPM, CPOA).</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Business analysts struggle to find their role in agile frameworks: SAFe does not define a BA role; traditional BA activities do not map to sprints; BAs either disappear from teams or duplicate Product Owner work. An explicit mapping shows where BA skills (domain modeling, dependency analysis, capability definition) add value that Product Owners cannot cover alone.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Onboarding a BA into a Scrum team that has never had a dedicated BA function</item>
        <item>Scaling from one Scrum team to a SAFe program and needing to define BA responsibilities at program and portfolio levels</item>
        <item>Sprint retrospective revealed that stories arrive at planning without sufficient detail — BA process needs to be inserted upstream</item>
        <item>Team is adopting BDD (Cucumber, SpecFlow) and needs a BA to drive example mapping and acceptance criteria authoring</item>
        <item>Organization is evaluating agile BA certifications for team members</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Kanban or continuous-flow teams without sprint boundaries — the sprint-phase mapping does not apply</item>
        <item>Teams where the Product Owner already performs all BA activities and the overhead of a BA role is not justified</item>
        <item>Pure technical/infrastructure work where there are no business stakeholder requirements to elicit</item>
        <item>SAFe adoption is not yet decided — apply plain Scrum BA practices first, scale only when teams exist at multiple levels</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="scrum-phase-mapping">
      <rule>
        <statement>BA activities must be distributed across all Scrum phases, not concentrated in Sprint 0. Sprint 0 establishes vision, roadmap, and initial backlog; all subsequent ceremonies require BA participation to maintain quality.</statement>
        <rationale>BAs who disappear after Sprint 0 produce an initial backlog that degrades as development teams interpret stories without expert BA support during execution.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Sprint 0: vision and roadmap facilitation, initial backlog creation from stakeholder sessions, acceptance criteria on the first 5-10 stories</item>
        <item>Backlog Refinement: user story elaboration, acceptance criteria authoring, models and wireframe review, dependency identification with other teams</item>
        <item>Sprint Planning: story clarification, dependency flagging, documenting sprint commitments with acceptance criteria confirmed</item>
        <item>Sprint Execution: ad-hoc clarification (target response under 30 minutes), prototype review, preparing next sprint backlog items</item>
        <item>Sprint Review: validate acceptance criteria are met, capture stakeholder feedback, update backlog with feedback-driven changes</item>
        <item>Retrospective: share BA process improvement observations, identify collaboration gaps between BA and developers or QA</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ad-hoc-clarification-rule">
      <rule>
        <statement>Respond to in-sprint developer or QA clarification requests within 30 minutes during working hours. Unresolved clarifications block development and cause sprint failure or unreviewed implementation decisions.</statement>
        <rationale>Blocked developers make implementation decisions unilaterally; a 30-minute response target prevents this without requiring the BA to be on-call continuously.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="safe-level-mapping">
      <rule>
        <statement>Map BA responsibilities to SAFe levels: Team Level (BA acts as Product Owner — user stories, acceptance criteria, backlog management), Program Level (Senior BA / System Architect — domain modeling, feature analysis, cross-team dependency analysis), Large Solution Level (Solution Analyst — cross-ART coordination, capability definition), Portfolio Level (Enterprise BA — portfolio backlog grooming, strategic alignment, business case analysis).</statement>
        <rationale>SAFe does not define a BA role explicitly; without an explicit mapping, BA competencies are either lost (BA has no role) or duplicated (BA and PO both own the same artifacts).</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="core-ba-responsibilities-across-safe">
      <list>
        <item>Bridge business and IT: translate business needs to technical requirements at all levels</item>
        <item>Facilitate communication: enable collaboration among stakeholders across ARTs and teams</item>
        <item>Prioritize by value: support value-based feature prioritization using WSJF or RICE at program level</item>
        <item>Define vision and roadmap: support Product Management with strategic direction and capability definition</item>
        <item>Ensure alignment: verify agile delivery aligns with business goals across the program increment</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="certifications">
      <list>
        <item>Agile Analysis Certification (AAC) — IIBA: 71% of BAs practice agile; AAC holders report 16% salary premium over non-certified</item>
        <item>SAFe Agilist (SA) — Scaled Agile: enterprise agile scaling, PI Planning facilitation</item>
        <item>SAFe Product Owner / Product Manager (POPM) — Scaled Agile: backlog management at Team and Program levels</item>
        <item>Certified Product Ownership Analysis (CPOA) — IIBA: product ownership analysis skills for BA-to-PO transition</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="technique-selection-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Select agile BA techniques based on the problem being solved, not the ceremony. User story mapping for release planning and feature prioritization; example mapping for acceptance criteria clarification on a specific story; story splitting for epics that are too large for a sprint; impact mapping for connecting features to business goals; event storming for domain discovery and process modeling.</statement>
        <rationale>Applying a single technique to all BA problems produces mismatched outputs; the technique must fit the question being answered.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="technique-reference">
      <list>
        <item>User Story Mapping: visualize product as a user journey with stories organized by activity; use for release planning, identifying MVP scope, prioritizing by user flow rather than by feature</item>
        <item>Example Mapping: collaborative session (BA + dev + QA) using index cards — rules (yellow), examples (green), questions (red); use to clarify acceptance criteria on specific complex stories before sprint planning</item>
        <item>Story Splitting: decompose epics into implementable stories using 10 patterns (workflow steps, business rule variations, data complexity, interface complexity, performance, operations, test variations, defer system, defer capabilities, simple/complex); use any time a story cannot be completed within one sprint</item>
        <item>Impact Mapping: goal → actors → impacts → deliverables tree structure; use to connect a feature to a business goal and identify which actors must change behavior for the goal to be achieved</item>
        <item>Event Storming: sticky-note workshop discovering domain events (orange), commands (blue), aggregates (yellow), bounded contexts; use for domain discovery when building a new system or onboarding onto a complex existing domain</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/sprint-ba-activities.md" purpose="Sprint activity checklist: pre-sprint refinement, planning, execution, review, and retrospective BA tasks"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="acceptance-criteria"/>
      <ref slug="user-story-mapping"/>
      <link href="https://www.scaledagile.com"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
