<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GitLab Issue Boards Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the GitLab Issue Boards methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="scoped-labels-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Workflow state MUST be modelled as scoped labels (workflow::*), not as regular labels; mixing scoped and unscoped state labels is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitLab docs (scoped labels)">scoped labels enforce mutual exclusion; regular labels do not, so issues end up in multiple workflow columns at once.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="wip-limit-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every In-Progress-style column MUST have an explicit WIP limit displayed on the board; columns without WIP limits are flagged as untracked.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kanban canonical practice (Anderson, Kanban 2010)">WIP limits are the whole point of Kanban; without them the board is just a wish list.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="label-seed-via-script" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Labels MUST be seeded via the seed_labels.py script and tracked in version control; ad-hoc label creation in the UI is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion infra-as-code policy">ad-hoc labels drift between projects and break cross-project boards.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="priority-and-type-distinct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Priority (priority::*) and type (type::*) MUST be modelled as separate scoped-label sets; a single label encoding both is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitLab docs">mixed priority/type labels prevent filtering and break automation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="board-policy-documented" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each board MUST ship with a README documenting column entry/exit criteria; un-documented boards are flagged for cleanup.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — GitLab board audits">without documented entry/exit criteria, every team member uses the board differently and signal collapses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="issue-templates-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Bug and Feature issues MUST use the templates (issue-template-bug.md, issue-template-feature.md); free-form issues are downgraded to 'triage' until a template is applied.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion intake hygiene">free-form issues skip the required context (steps to reproduce, acceptance criteria) and waste reviewer time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
