<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SOC 2 Evidence Generator CLI Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every SOC 2 Evidence Generator CLI application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-pr-as-unit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each merged PR MUST emit exactly one evidence stub. Multiple stubs per PR (e.g. one per commit) are rejected as noise; zero stubs are rejected as gap.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">PR-as-unit aligns with the change-management boundary auditors already sample; commit-level noise overwhelms the store; missing stubs are audit findings.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-signed-stub" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every stub MUST be cryptographically signed at write time with a key in the evidence-signing keyring. Unsigned stubs are rejected at the store ingress.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Unsigned evidence can be forged after the fact; signing is the auditor-acceptable tamper-evidence layer.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-control-labels-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every stub MUST carry &gt;=1 control label from the engagement's control vocabulary. Stubs without labels are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Without labels, the stub cannot be queried by control during an audit; the unlabeled stub is functionally invisible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-approval-link-included" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stubs MUST embed the PR approval link (GitHub/GitLab review URL) + reviewer identity. Stubs without approval evidence are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">The approver is the human attestation; SOC 2 CC8.1 / CC3.2 cares about that signature specifically.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-immutable-store" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stubs land in an append-only, retention-protected store (S3 Object Lock, immutable bucket, write-once table). Mutable storage is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Auditors require evidence-store immutability to accept stubs as evidence rather than 'developer notes'.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
