<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Critique Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Design Critique application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-presenter-frames" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The presenter MUST state goals + constraints + open questions BEFORE reviewers speak. Cold critiques are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Without framing, reviewers default to taste; with framing, observations target the actual decision.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-observation-before-recommendation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reviewers MUST state observations (what they see) BEFORE recommendations (what to change). Recommendation-only feedback is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Recommendation without observation hides the underlying problem; the presenter cannot generalise the fix.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-principle-grounded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every observation MUST cite a heuristic, research finding, or prior decision. "I just don't like it" is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Principle-grounded feedback is actionable; taste feedback creates debate without resolution.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-decision-logged" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every accepted observation MUST become a tracked decision: owner + action + due-date. Verbal-only agreements are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Verbal agreements decay within a week; tracked decisions survive sprints.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-anonymous-feedback" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every observation MUST be attributable to a named reviewer. Anonymous "the team thinks" feedback is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Attribution lets the presenter follow up; anonymous feedback is also unaccountable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
