<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="design-critique Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for design-critique as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Without stated goals and design principles, critique sessions default to preference debates regardless of format.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without explicit goals, every comment is opinion. Goals are the foundation of structured critique.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Power dynamics suppress critique quality: junior designers do not give honest feedback to senior designers in hierarchical teams without explicit facilitation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Facilitation must create psychological safety. Ground rules posted in the room, explicit permission for juniors to speak, and framing feedback as "about the work" all help.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Async critique loses the clarifying question phase; written comments often assume rather than ask.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Async critique requires higher structure (format + examples + rubric) to compensate for missing real-time clarification. Build this in from the start.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>"Design by committee" failure mode: when everyone in the room redesigns rather than analyzes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Redirect solutioning back to analysis. Facilitator frames: "That's a great idea. Does the current design fail against a goal, or are you proposing an alternative?"</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
