<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-press-coverage">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>Relationship-driven press outreach: start with Tier 3 journalists, research their beat, craft newsworthy angles, send personalized pitches with specific article references, maximize coverage impact.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>press</tag>
      <tag>pr</tag>
      <tag>journalists</tag>
      <tag>pitch</tag>
      <tag>coverage</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="growth-gtm-strategy"/>
      <ref slug="growth-influencer-marketing"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Press &amp; PR Coverage</title>

    <summary>Relationship-driven press outreach: identify journalists by tier (Tier 3 niche first, Tier 1 only after coverage history), research each journalist's beat and recent articles, craft a newsworthy story angle (first/trend/data/milestone/contrarian), send a personalized pitch under 150 words with one specific article reference and three concrete assets offered, then maximize coverage impact through social sharing and relationship maintenance.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Generic press releases sent to Tier 1 outlets without prior coverage history are ignored — journalists need stories that serve their readers, not product announcements. Starting with Tier 3 builds a coverage record and improves Tier 1 pitch credibility. Each pitch must cite a specific, non-obvious insight from the journalist's recent work; flattery-only openers ("Loved your piece") are screened instantly.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Announcing a product launch, funding round, major milestone, or original research.</item>
        <item>Building a journalist database and coverage pipeline before a major launch.</item>
        <item>Daily HARO/Qwoted triage: filtering relevant queries and drafting pitches for human review.</item>
        <item>Maintaining and updating the press kit (founder bio, boilerplate, assets).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-product or pre-traction — without a real story (data, milestone, launch) no outreach volume earns coverage.</item>
        <item>Embargoed announcements or exclusives — relationship work that requires human-only contact.</item>
        <item>Crisis communications or legal-sensitive PR — agent-drafted statements carry legal risk.</item>
        <item>Tier-1 auto-pitching — TechCrunch, NYT, WSJ reporters will blacklist senders on first templated email.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="media-tier-strategy">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Start with Tier 3 niche blogs and newsletters; build a coverage record before approaching Tier 1 publications.</statement>
        <rationale>Tier 1 journalists (TechCrunch, NYT, Wired) receive hundreds of pitches daily. Without prior coverage, there is no social proof of newsworthiness. A few Tier 3 mentions establish credibility and provide links to cite when pitching upward. Pitching Tier 1 first before any coverage history means competing on equal footing with well-known companies.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Tier 1: TechCrunch, Wired, NYT, Forbes — major news, funding rounds, data-driven exclusives only.</item>
        <item>Tier 2: Industry publications, vertical blogs — product launches, features, milestones.</item>
        <item>Tier 3: Niche newsletters, podcasts, community blogs — any relevant news, relationship-building.</item>
        <item>HARO alternatives: Qwoted, Featured (formerly Terkel), SourceBottle, JustReachOut — respond to journalist queries as source.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Never auto-pitch Tier 1 journalists; research manually and pitch individually with journalist-specific personalization.</statement>
        <rationale>Tier 1 reporters will blacklist senders on the first templated email. Agent-drafted pitches that open with generic flattery ("Loved your piece on X") are immediately identified as templated and deleted. Each pitch must cite a specific non-obvious insight from a recent article by URL.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="finding-journalists">
      <list>
        <item>Twitter/X search: "[Publication] + [beat keyword]" to find reporters covering your space.</item>
        <item>Publication website: browse relevant sections and note bylines on recent articles in your category.</item>
        <item>Similar coverage: search for articles about direct competitors and identify who wrote them.</item>
        <item>HARO alternatives: subscribe to daily query digests and respond to journalists actively seeking sources.</item>
        <item>Media databases (Muck Rack, Cision): paid tools for systematic journalist research at scale.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="journalist-profile">
      <p>Before writing any pitch, complete a profile for each journalist: Name, Publication, Beat (specific topics covered), 3-5 recent articles with links, writing tone (data-driven/narrative/opinion), pitch preference (email/DM/form), and one specific angle that connects your news to their beat.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Pitching a journalist based only on their publication without reading their recent work.</description>
        <reason>Beat reporters specialize. A tech journalist at Forbes may cover enterprise software, not consumer apps. Sending an irrelevant pitch signals you did no research, permanently damaging the relationship.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="newsworthy-story-angles">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Identify a specific news angle before writing any pitch; a product announcement without an angle is not news.</statement>
        <rationale>Journalists publish stories that serve their readers. "We launched a product" is not a story — it is a press release. "Bootstrapped founder reached $1M ARR by rejecting VC advice" is a story because it carries a lesson, a protagonist, and a surprising outcome. Without an angle, no pitch volume will earn coverage.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>First: first product/company to do X in this space.</item>
        <item>Trend: your product is evidence of a larger industry shift.</item>
        <item>Data: original research, survey results, or proprietary usage data.</item>
        <item>Founder story: unique personal journey that led to the product.</item>
        <item>Funding: investment announcement with context about market.</item>
        <item>Milestone: significant user count, revenue, or growth rate.</item>
        <item>Contrarian: challenging a prevailing industry assumption with evidence.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Story formula: [Who] + [Did what] + [So what — impact] + [Why now]. Example: "Bootstrapped founder reaches $1M ARR by doing opposite of VC advice, proving small can win against well-funded competitors in the age of AI."</p>
    </section>

    <section name="pitch-structure">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep pitches under 150 words; subject line under 8 words; cite one specific article by the journalist; offer three concrete assets; end with one clear CTA.</statement>
        <rationale>Journalists do not read long pitches. The pitch must communicate the story value before the reader decides to scroll. Citing a specific article proves research; offering concrete assets (founder access, exclusive data, customer stories) makes the journalist's job easier.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <reference path="templates/press-pitch.md">Cold pitch email template with all required elements</reference>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Following up more than twice after an initial pitch.</description>
        <reason>More than two follow-ups is considered spam by most journalists and damages future pitch acceptance. Accept no response as a no and move on. The relationship may still be useful for future stories.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="press-kit">
      <p>Press kit hosted at yourdomain.com/press. Required assets: founder bio (50-word and 200-word versions), company boilerplate (100 words), high-res logos (PNG and SVG), product screenshots, founder photos (headshot, candid), key stats (users, revenue, growth), pre-approved quotes, fact sheet.</p>

      <reference path="templates/founder-bio.md">Founder bio template in 50-word and 200-word formats</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="leveraging-coverage">
      <p>When coverage is published: share on social and tag the journalist (thank them publicly), add to "As Seen In" section on homepage, email the subscriber list about the coverage, track backlink and referral traffic, and note the journalist in your database as a warm contact for future stories.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Respond to all coverage — positive and negative — within 24 hours with acknowledgment; never dispute factual errors publicly without first contacting the journalist privately.</statement>
        <rationale>Journalists remember how companies respond to their coverage. Gracious acknowledgment of positive coverage builds the relationship; private fact-correction maintains credibility. Public disputes burn the relationship permanently.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration">
      <p>Building and maintaining a journalist database scoped to your beats (search recent articles, extract authors, enrich contacts). Daily HARO / Qwoted / SourceBottle triage: filter, draft tailored pitches for matching queries, queue for human review. Drafting personalized cold pitches at scale (100+/month) where each is anchored to a specific recent piece by the journalist. Monitoring outcomes (open, reply, coverage) and feeding that signal back into the journalist database for ranking. Maintaining the press kit (founder bio versions, boilerplate, fact sheet, asset URLs) under version control.</p>

      <p>The PR agent runs as a multi-stage pipeline: (1) discovery — scrapes Muck Rack / Twitter / publication pages for journalists matching beat keywords; (2) enrichment — pulls last 5 articles per journalist, extracts beat tags + tone; (3) angle match — given a story brief, ranks journalists by fit; (4) draft — writes a pitch citing one specific article and a tailored hook; (5) human review — every pitch requires sign-off; (6) send + track — opens, replies, mentions logged back into the registry. Daily: triage HARO-alternatives, draft responses, queue for human.</p>

      <p>LLM-drafted pitches default to generic flattery ("Loved your piece"). Journalists screen these instantly. Agent must extract a specific, non-obvious insight from the linked article and reference it. Email deliverability: cold pitches from a new domain land in Gmail Promotions or spam. Need warmed sending domain, SPF/DKIM/DMARC, low daily volume per inbox. Embargo coordination is human work — agent cannot reliably hold back a press release across 10 reporters with different timezones. Hallucinated journalist beats are common. Agent must cite recent article URLs as evidence, not infer.</p>

      <p>Quality over volume: 10 well-researched pitches beat 100 templated ones. Agent should refuse to send if it cannot cite a specific article. Maintain a "do-not-pitch" list (journalists who said no, no-longer-at-publication, opted out). Update on every bounce/reply. Pitch Tuesday-Thursday 09:00-11:00 local to journalist. Agent must compute local time, not just send queue order. Always offer assets (founder access, exclusive data, customer story). Agent must match assets to article history. Track domain authority of placements (Ahrefs/Moz) — agent reports backlink + DA, not just mention count. Maintain founder bio versions (50w, 200w, 500w) and update annually. Stale bios undermine pitches.</p>

      <p>Tier-1 pitches: human writes, agent researches. Tier-2/3 pitches: agent drafts, human approves. HARO-alt responses: agent drafts, human approves first 20, then approves only flagged.</p>

      <p>LLMs hallucinate journalist names, beats, and quotes. Always ground in scraped + cached data; fail closed when no source URL. Sending domain reputation: agent batching 50 cold pitches/day from a new domain will get the domain blacklisted within a week. Stagger across multiple warmed inboxes; cap volume per inbox. GDPR: EU journalists' contact info needs lawful basis. Public masthead = legitimate interest, but unsubscribe still required. Embargo handling needs explicit state — agent must not auto-send any embargoed story without a hard date check + human ack. Reply detection is hard — out-of-office replies look like positive responses to naive parsers. Use a classifier or keyword filter before flagging "interested". Avoid agent-generated press releases on the wire. PR Newswire / BusinessWire have plagiarism + AI-detection checks; bland LLM prose triggers low pickup. Don't let the agent post on social on behalf of the company without approval — coverage celebration tweets misattribute or misquote often.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/press-pitch.md" purpose="Cold pitch email template: subject, personalized opener, news hook, assets offer, CTA."/>
      <template path="templates/haro-response.md" purpose="HARO/Qwoted query response format."/>
      <template path="templates/founder-bio.md" purpose="Founder bio in 50-word and 200-word versions."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://muckrack.com/blog/2024/01/17/how-to-pitch-journalists"/>
      <link href="https://www.qwoted.com/"/>
      <link href="https://featured.com/"/>
      <link href="https://justreachout.io/"/>
      <ref slug="growth-gtm-strategy"/>
      <ref slug="growth-influencer-marketing"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
