<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="seo-techniques Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for seo-techniques. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Validate all JSON-LD schema with Google Rich Results Test before deployment. Never deploy agent-generated schema without validation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents produce syntactically valid but semantically incorrect schema: wrong @type values, missing required fields, incorrect nesting. Invalid schema produces no rich results and may generate Search Console errors with no visible symptom.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Add schema markup in order of impact: Organization (global), Article (all blog posts), FAQPage (any Q&amp;A content), BreadcrumbList (all pages with navigation hierarchy).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Organization schema establishes brand entity globally. Article schema is required for Google Discover inclusion. FAQPage generates rich result expansion in SERPs. BreadcrumbList appears in search results and improves topic hierarchy signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Create a /llms.txt file at the domain root that provides AI crawlers with a curated, structured overview of the site — similar to how robots.txt guides traditional crawlers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI crawlers lack the context of traditional search crawlers. The llms.txt file provides the canonical summary of what the site is, what content it contains, and what should be excluded — reducing hallucination risk and improving citation accuracy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use the exact same brand name, product names, and key personnel names across all pages, social profiles, and external mentions. Entity name inconsistency fragments knowledge graph representation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI engines and Google's Knowledge Graph build entity representations from consistent co-occurrence patterns. Inconsistent naming ("Faion Network" vs "Faion" vs "faion.net") creates separate, weaker entity nodes instead of one authoritative entity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Open Graph images must be exactly 1200x630px (1.91:1 ratio) and under 8MB. Images outside these dimensions are cropped or rejected by social platforms.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Facebook, LinkedIn, and most social platforms use 1200x630 as the standard preview image size. Non-conforming images display incorrectly, reducing click-through rates on shared links.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every cluster page must link back to its pillar page using anchor text containing the pillar's primary keyword. Pillar pages must link to all cluster pages.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The pillar-cluster model distributes link equity from high-authority pillar pages to long-tail cluster pages, improving the ranking probability of both. Bidirectional links signal topical relationship to Google.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
