<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-structure" title="Outcome Roadmap Structure">
  <summary>The anatomy of an outcome-based roadmap: outcome block format, contrast with feature roadmaps, and quarterly template structure.</summary>

  <section title="Feature vs Outcome Roadmap">
    <p>A feature roadmap commits to solutions: "Build chat feature", "Add dark mode", "Launch mobile app". An outcome roadmap commits to metric movements: "Reduce support tickets by 30%", "Improve evening retention", "Enable on-the-go usage". The solution list under each outcome is marked "to-validate" and is mutable mid-quarter.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Every outcome must follow the pattern: verb + metric + delta + timeframe. Example: "Reduce churn from 8% to 5% by end of Q2." Outcomes missing any component are invalid.</statement>
      <rationale>The four-part pattern makes outcomes falsifiable. "Improve retention" cannot be scored at quarter-end; "Increase Day-30 retention from 20% to 35% by EOQ2" can.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Outcome Block Anatomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each quarterly outcome block must contain: outcome statement (verb+metric+delta+timeframe), metric with baseline, target, evidence (data source or research), candidate solutions (3–6, all marked "to-validate"), and an explicit not-doing list (2–3 items).</statement>
      <rationale>The not-doing list is as important as the candidate solutions. It stops scope creep, sets stakeholder expectations, and creates a record for future retrospectives.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Quarterly Structure">
    <p>Q1 slot holds the outcome + experiments to run + metrics to track + potential solutions (not committed) + success criteria. Q2 slot follows the same structure. Each quarter is a frozen outcome with a mutable solution list. Outcomes are set at quarter boundaries; the solution list mutates as experiments resolve.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Cap quarterly outcomes at 3 for solo/small team, 5 for a team with multiple streams. More outcomes destroy focus; agents will pad to fill any number you allow.</statement>
      <rationale>Focus is the primary mechanism. Every additional outcome dilutes the attention and resources available for the others. Three well-executed outcomes beat five half-pursued ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
