<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Outcome Roadmap Rules">
  <summary>Concrete rules for authoring, maintaining, and publishing outcome-based roadmaps, including agent-specific gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Authoring Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every outcome with a falsifying signal: "If activation drops below X by week 6, kill this bet." Without a kill signal, the outcome cannot be closed — teams keep pursuing it indefinitely.</statement>
      <rationale>Kill signals force honesty in retrospectives. An outcome without one will always find a reason to continue, burning resources that should pivot.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Tie every outcome to an existing analytics dashboard before publishing. If you cannot link a chart URL, the outcome is not yet real enough to plan around.</statement>
      <rationale>Outcomes anchored to real data prevent the common failure of setting targets without knowing the baseline. Agents will hallucinate plausible baselines — inject real data as context.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain two publishing artefacts: an internal roadmap (outcomes + bets + targets) and an external/customer roadmap (themes and benefits only, no metric targets). Sync via script, not copy-paste.</statement>
      <rationale>Sharing metric targets externally creates contractual expectations. Customers interpret "reduce churn to 5%" as a promise; "improve retention" keeps strategic flexibility while communicating direction.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Freeze and Mutation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep outcomes immutable for the entire quarter. Only the candidate solutions list mutates as experiments resolve. Rewrite outcomes only at quarter boundaries.</statement>
      <rationale>Mid-quarter outcome changes invalidate all in-flight experiments and destroy the team's ability to measure progress. Solutions can pivot freely; the goal cannot.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Update cadence: review the solution list monthly, rewrite outcomes quarterly. Do not rewrite the whole document every sprint.</statement>
      <rationale>Over-frequent rewrites destroy the historical signal that makes retrospectives useful. Diffs between quarters are the primary learning artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>When using an LLM to generate outcome roadmaps: require a metric + delta + verb in every outcome row, pull real baselines from analytics before prompting, clamp candidate solution lists to 6, and mark the not-doing field as required.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs restate features as outcomes ("ship onboarding redesign" becomes "improve onboarding"), hallucinate numeric baselines, balloon solution lists, and silently drop the not-doing column because it produces no generative content.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>Never let an agent publish the external roadmap directly. Human checkpoint mandatory — outcome targets can be commitments; competitive and NDA implications require human review.</statement>
      <rationale>An LLM cannot assess business risk, NDAs, or competitive signalling context. These are human judgment calls.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
