<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="outcome-based-roadmaps Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for outcome-based-roadmaps as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Vanity outcomes: "increase engagement", "delight users", "improve the platform".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unmeasurable outcomes cannot be scored, kill-signalled, or retrospected. Teams pursue them indefinitely with no feedback loop. Apply the verb+metric+delta+timeframe test: if the outcome fails it, rewrite before planning.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Outcome inflation: every quarter declares 5+ outcomes, none get the sustained focus needed.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each additional outcome divides attention and creates coordination overhead. Solo teams with 5 outcomes effectively have 5 equal priorities—indistinguishable from no priority. Cap at 3 for solo, 5 for small teams.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Disconnect from delivery: engineering runs a feature backlog and the outcome roadmap becomes a parallel document nobody trusts or references.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The roadmap becomes decoration unless initiatives in the backlog are tagged to outcome IDs. Without traceability, sprint planning ignores the roadmap entirely.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Confusing activities (inputs) with outcomes (metric movements): "run 5 user interviews" as an outcome.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Activities are means, not ends. A team can complete all activities and move no metrics. Outcomes must describe the metric state change, not the work done to achieve it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Outcome roadmap weak with stakeholders who pay per feature; they push back unless they also receive a feature-derivative view.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Some audiences need feature language to understand what they are getting. Maintain the outcome roadmap internally; produce a feature-derivative or theme-only view for feature-oriented stakeholders.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
