<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="risk-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Structured process for identifying, scoring, responding to, and monitoring project uncertainty — both threats and opportunities. Every risk requires trigger, owner, and response strategy.</summary>
    <category>risk</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>risk-management</tag>
      <tag>pmbok</tag>
      <tag>contingency</tag>
      <tag>emv</tag>
      <tag>uncertainty</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="schedule-development"/>
      <ref slug="cost-estimation"/>
      <ref slug="resource-management"/>
      <ref slug="risk-register"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Risk Management</title>

    <summary>Risk management is a structured process for identifying, scoring, responding to, and monitoring project uncertainty — including both threats (negative risks) and opportunities (positive risks). Every risk requires a trigger condition, an owner, and an explicit response strategy; risks without triggers are wishes, not plans.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without risk management, surprises become crises and budgets have no contingency basis. Probability x Impact scoring with EMV enables defensible contingency reserves. Tracking opportunity-side risks prevents teams from focusing solely on threats and missing upside. A weekly register review cycle converts risk management from a kickoff artifact into a real control mechanism.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Multi-month delivery where surprises cost real money (more than $10k or two weeks)</item>
        <item>Regulated, safety-critical, or contractual work where an audit trail is required</item>
        <item>Cross-team programs with technical, vendor, and resource interdependencies</item>
        <item>Initiatives where a quantitative reserve (contingency) must be defended to finance</item>
        <item>Programs that exhibited risk failures on prior runs</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure exploratory R&amp;D or spike work — fail-fast learning beats register hygiene</item>
        <item>Single-developer hobby project; an issue tracker risk label is enough</item>
        <item>Sub-two-week features where ceremony cost exceeds expected loss</item>
        <item>Pure-Scrum teams already running impediment and retro loops with adequate coverage</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="risk-types">
      <p>Risks come in four types: threat (negative risk; if it occurs, it harms scope, schedule, cost, or quality), opportunity (positive risk; if it occurs, it improves project outcome), known risk (identified and plannable, e.g., integration complexity, key-person dependency), and unknown risk (not identifiable in advance; black swans; managed via contingency reserves and resilience, not response plans).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Track opportunity risks in the same register as threats, color-coded; teams that log only threats systematically under-manage upside and miss scope to exploit favorable conditions.</statement>
        <rationale>Opportunity risks require active strategies (exploit, enhance, share) to realize; passive acceptance of positive risks leaves value on the table.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="four-step-process">
      <p>Step 1: Identify risks. Use brainstorming, lessons-learned reviews, PROMPT-list (Political, Regulatory, Organizational, Market, People, Technical), and expert interviews. Seed from project-specific artifacts: charter, ADRs, vendor SOWs — generic risks produce generic responses.</p>

      <p>Step 2: Analyze risks. Apply qualitative P×I scoring first; escalate to quantitative EMV for risks where contingency must be defended to finance. Record one-line rationale per score citing the source artifact.</p>

      <p>Step 3: Plan responses. Assign a strategy and response owner for every risk. Threats: Avoid / Transfer / Mitigate / Accept. Opportunities: Exploit / Enhance / Share / Accept.</p>

      <p>Step 4: Monitor and update. Review the register weekly; verify trigger conditions; close risks with documented outcomes; conduct risk reviews at every milestone.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="pi-scoring-and-emv">
      <p>Record a one-line rationale citing the source artifact for every P and I score; scores without rationale converge to "Medium" by default and lose discrimination. Teams anchor on the middle of the scale unless forced to justify; requiring source evidence prevents the normalization of everything to "Medium" that makes the register useless for prioritization.</p>

      <p>EMV (Expected Monetary Value) equals Probability × Impact (in currency). Roll all EMVs into a single contingency line; finance only funds aggregates, not per-risk reserves.</p>

      <example type="good" title="EMV scoring example">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Risk: Key developer leaves mid-project.
P=0.30 (source: HR attrition data for this role)
Impact=$30,000 delay cost (source: cost-estimation baseline)
EMV=$9,000
Mitigation: cross-training + knowledge documentation
Residual EMV=$3,000 added to contingency]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="response-strategies">
      <p>For threats: Avoid (change the plan to eliminate the risk entirely, e.g., avoid unproven technology), Transfer (shift the financial impact to a third party via insurance or fixed-price contracts), Mitigate (reduce probability or impact through cross-training, redundancy, testing), Accept passive (acknowledge the risk; take no proactive action), Accept active (set aside contingency reserves for the risk's expected impact).</p>

      <p>For opportunities: Exploit (take deliberate action to ensure the opportunity occurs), Enhance (increase probability or impact of the opportunity), Share (partner with another party better positioned to capture the opportunity), Accept (take the opportunity if it presents itself without active investment).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="triggers-and-ownership">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every risk must have a named owner and an observable trigger condition; risks without both are not managed — they are listed.</statement>
        <rationale>Without an owner, no one monitors the trigger. Without a trigger, no one knows when to activate the response plan. Both gaps guarantee the risk materializes without a prepared response.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Keep the top-five risks visible on the project status report; everything else goes in the appendix.</statement>
        <rationale>Sponsors and steering committees scan status reports; burying the critical risks in a detailed register means they are never discussed at the level where resources can be committed.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="calibration-and-freshness">
      <rule>
        <statement>Calibrate the team's probability buckets once per quarter using base-rate exercises; otherwise the team defaults to "Medium" and the register loses prioritization value.</statement>
        <rationale>Subjective probability estimation is anchoring-prone; base-rate calibration (what actually happened on previous similar projects) gives teams a shared reference that improves discrimination.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Update the risk register at every weekly status cycle; a register not reviewed in two sprints is stale and actively misleads the project team.</statement>
        <rationale>Risks materialize, disappear, change probability, and trigger new secondary risks continuously; a static register represents the state of the project at kickoff, not today.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="closure-discipline">
      <rule>
        <statement>Close risks explicitly with an outcome label ("materialized", "passed without triggering", "merged into RISK-NN") and a date; never delete closed risks.</statement>
        <rationale>Deleted risks vanish from the audit trail and lessons-learned pool; retained closed risks build the base-rate data that improves future project risk identification and scoring.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-risk-workflow">
      <p>A Claude subagent works well for the mechanical parts of risk hygiene: extracting candidate risks from project artifacts, normalizing entries, detecting drift between register and reality, and drafting response plans. The human PM keeps ownership of probability/impact judgment, EMV defensibility, and Change-Control-Board escalations. Run the agent on a weekly cadence against the live register (Markdown, Jira, or Notion) and surface a delta diff for human review — never let the agent silently mutate scores.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-pm-agent (declared in README front-matter) owns the methodology; drafts register entries from charter, scope, and meeting notes. sdd-execution quality-gate agent feeds it the register so AC reviews check for risk coverage. brainstorm diverge/converge runs a "what could go wrong" diverge round at kickoff and at each phase gate.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>The risk-identification agent must cite a source artifact for every candidate risk and mark every score with a one-line rationale; agents that invent risks without grounding produce generic registers with no project specificity.</statement>
        <rationale>LLM-generated registers default to "vendor delay", "scope creep", "key person leaves" — patterns present in training data, not analysis of the actual project. Source-grounded risks are specific and actionable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>The risk agent emits a diff (NEW, CHANGED_SCORE, CLOSED, STALE) against the prior register and never mutates fields directly; humans review and apply the diff.</statement>
        <rationale>Silent field mutation destroys the audit trail; a diff review ensures every change is intentional and documented, preserving the register's value as evidence for compliance and lessons-learned.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Risk identification prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a risk-identification assistant. Read the attached charter + WBS.
Output JSON: [{id, category, description, probability(VL/L/M/H/VH),
impact(VL/L/M/H/VH), trigger, suggested_strategy, rationale}].
Mark every score with a one-line rationale citing source text.
Do NOT invent owners. Flag any risk with score >=15 as "needs_review=true".]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Risk diff prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Diff the prior register vs the current one. Output: NEW, CHANGED_SCORE,
CLOSED, STALE (>14 days no update). Never mutate fields — emit the diff only.]]></code>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Leaving risk owners blank in the agent-generated register for a human to fill in "later."</description>
        <reason>"Later" rarely comes; unowned risks are reviewed by no one and their triggers go unmonitored. The agent should flag owner as "needs_assignment" in the output schema to force immediate assignment.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Probability×Impact scoring is anchoring-prone; teams converge on "Medium" defaults and lose discrimination. EMV summed without correlation overstates contingency for correlated risks. "Set-and-forget" registers stale within 2-3 sprints; without trigger reviews the doc is theatre. Black-swan / unknown-unknown events are by definition outside the register. Opportunity-side risks are systematically under-managed — most teams only log threats.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>pmbok-risk-register (Excel/CSV templates from PMI) provides canonical register layout. riskman (npm) is a Markdown-driven risk register with CLI scoring. risk-cli (Python) runs Monte Carlo on EMV inputs. jira CLI (go-jira, jira-cli) syncs risks as issues with risk issue-type. gh CLI syncs risks as labelled issues for solo/light projects. pandoc renders risks.md to PDF for steering reports.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <p>Jira (Risk Management for Jira, RMsis) is SaaS with REST API + JQL; first-class risk issue type, P×I custom fields. Monday.com risk template is SaaS with GraphQL API, easy for non-PMOs but weak EMV math. Smartsheet RAID log is SaaS with REST API, strong for regulated/PMO orgs. Notion + database is SaaS with REST API, best for solo/small; agent can fully drive it. @riskmgmt/risk-register (OSS, GitHub) fits SDD repos; diff-friendly. Palisade @RISK / ModelRisk is desktop with limited agent support; quantitative Monte Carlo when EMV alone underflows. ServiceNow GRC is enterprise SaaS with REST API, heavyweight; only for regulated programs.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Pair every risk with a trigger condition you can observe (metric, calendar event, signal) — risks without triggers are wishes. Calibrate the team once per quarter on probability buckets using base-rate exercises; otherwise everyone defaults to "Medium". Track opportunity risks in the same register, color-coded — forces parity of attention. Roll EMV into a single contingency line, not per-risk reserves; finance only funds aggregates. Keep the top-5 risks visible on the status report; everything else goes in the appendix. Close risks explicitly with outcome ("materialized", "passed", "merged into R-XX") — never delete.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Agents will happily auto-score every risk Medium-Medium; require explicit rationale per score in the output schema. LLMs hallucinate plausible-but-wrong risk owners — leave owner blank and have a human assign. Agent-generated registers tend toward generic ("vendor delay", "scope creep"); seed with project-specific artifacts (charter, ADRs, vendor SOWs) before running. Don't let the agent close risks autonomously; require human signoff because closure has audit consequences. Token budget: a 50-risk register is ~3-5k tokens; reading it on every turn wastes context. Pass only the top-N by score plus changed rows. Human-in-loop checkpoints: (1) initial calibration, (2) any score change >= 2 levels, (3) any new "High/Crit" entry, (4) any contingency-budget impact.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/risk-register.md" purpose="Risk register table template with all required columns"/>
      <template path="templates/risk-response-plan.md" purpose="Individual risk response plan template"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/emv.py" purpose="Score a Markdown risk register; exits non-zero on critical untriaged risks"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="schedule-development"/>
      <ref slug="cost-estimation"/>
      <ref slug="resource-management"/>
      <ref slug="risk-register"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
