<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-risk-framework" title="Discovery Risk Framework">
  <summary>Four risk categories for product ideas — value, usability, feasibility, business viability — each with technique options ranked by effort and confidence level.</summary>

  <section title="Four Risk Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Test risks in this order of priority: value risk first, then usability, then feasibility, then business viability. Kill ideas early on value risk before spending on later-stage tests.</statement>
      <rationale>Value risk is the most common and cheapest to test. Building a technically feasible, usable product that nobody wants is the most expensive failure mode in product development.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Allocate 20–30% of team capacity to discovery. Never skip to delivery without addressing the highest-risk assumption.</statement>
      <rationale>The cost of a failed feature is the engineering time plus the opportunity cost of what was not built instead. 20% discovery investment that prevents one failed 6-week feature pays for itself many times over.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Value Risk Techniques">
    <list>
      <item>Customer interviews — low effort, medium confidence — use for early-stage ideas</item>
      <item>Fake door test (link to feature that does not exist yet) — low effort, medium confidence — use for testing demand</item>
      <item>Landing page with signup — low effort, medium confidence — use for market interest</item>
      <item>Concierge MVP (deliver value manually) — medium effort, high confidence — use for service-based products</item>
      <item>Wizard of Oz (fake automation) — medium effort, high confidence — use for complex features</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Usability Risk Techniques">
    <list>
      <item>Paper prototypes — low effort, low confidence — use for early concept validation</item>
      <item>Clickable prototypes — medium effort, medium confidence — use for flow validation</item>
      <item>Usability testing with 5 users — medium effort, high confidence — use for design validation</item>
      <item>A/B testing — high effort, very high confidence — use for optimization, not validation</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Feasibility Risk Techniques">
    <list>
      <item>Technical spike (1–2 days) — low effort, high confidence — use for unknown tech</item>
      <item>Architecture review — low effort, medium confidence — use for system impact assessment</item>
      <item>Proof of concept — medium effort, high confidence — use for critical path features</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Business Viability Techniques">
    <list>
      <item>Financial modeling — low effort, medium confidence — use for revenue impact</item>
      <item>Competitive analysis — low effort, medium confidence — use for market fit</item>
      <item>Pilot program — high effort, very high confidence — use only for major investments</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
