<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Product Discovery Process">
  <summary>Five-step discovery process: identify assumptions, prioritize risks, design experiments, run and learn, decide — with a timebox constraint and a go/pivot/more-data decision framework.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1 — Identify Assumptions">
    <rule>
      <statement>List every assumption the idea depends on before choosing a technique. Categorize each by risk type (value/usability/feasibility/business) and risk level (high/medium/low).</statement>
      <rationale>Undiscovered assumptions are the primary source of post-launch surprises. An explicit assumption list makes the team agree on what they are betting on before committing resources.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2 — Prioritize Risks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Focus discovery on assumptions that are both high-risk AND easy to test. High-risk and hard-to-test assumptions need a spike or POC first to reduce uncertainty before running user experiments.</statement>
      <rationale>Testing low-risk assumptions wastes discovery budget. An assumption that is easy to test but low-risk should be accepted as true and built on, not tested.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3 — Design Experiments">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each experiment, write the hypothesis as: "If we do X, we expect Y in Z% of [user segment]." Define success criteria before running the experiment.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc success criteria are subject to confirmation bias. Defining them before running eliminates the temptation to reinterpret results.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4 — Timebox">
    <rule>
      <statement>Timebox discovery to 1–4 weeks. Discovery that takes longer than the build it is meant to de-risk has inverted the cost equation.</statement>
      <rationale>Endless discovery is a form of avoidance. A 4-week discovery timebox forces prioritization to the highest-risk assumptions and prevents "let's just do one more interview."</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5 — Decide">
    <rule>
      <statement>After experiments: if all critical risks are addressed, proceed to delivery. If a critical risk is invalidated, pivot or kill. If results are unclear, run one more targeted experiment — not another full discovery cycle.</statement>
      <rationale>The decision categories prevent the most common discovery failure: inconclusive results that produce neither a green light nor a kill signal, leaving the team stuck.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/discovery-kickoff.md">Discovery kickoff template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/experiment-report.md">Experiment hypothesis, results, and decision template</reference>
</text>
