<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Hybrid Delivery Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the Hybrid Delivery methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="component-method-by-risk" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Method MUST be assigned per component based on a documented risk profile (compliance, regulatory, novel-tech, vendor-skill); arbitrary assignment is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion hybrid-delivery audits">without risk-anchored method choice, the program collapses into 'this team prefers Scrum' politics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="translation-boundaries-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every method change between components MUST have a named translation boundary (artefact handoff, integration point, milestone) with explicit input/output contracts.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mixed-mode anti-pattern">un-named boundaries cause artefacts to leak across methods and quality gates get skipped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="governance-cadence-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Program-level governance cadence (stage-gate review) is fixed and overrides component-level cadence at the boundary; agile components MUST report into the stage-gate cycle.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stage-gate canonical practice (Cooper 1990)">drifting governance cadence kills the predictive layer that hybrid relies on.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="dod-per-component-and-program" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Definition of Done at the COMPONENT level AND at the PROGRAM level MUST be distinct; sharing a single DoD across both is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="DoD-conflation audits">component DoD optimises for the method; program DoD optimises for the funding gate. Conflation hides gate failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-per-component" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each component's method assignment MUST cite evidence (regulatory clause, risk register entry, vendor scorecard); un-anchored assignments are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-fabrication practice">agent-assigned methods without evidence drift toward 'whatever the loudest stakeholder prefers'.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
