<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Debt Vs Design Bet Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Design Debt Vs Design Bet application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="explicit-class-tag" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every design task MUST carry a class tag: `debt` OR `bet`. Untagged tasks are blocked from sprint commit.</statement>
      <rationale source="Backlog-classification discipline">Backlog-classification discipline — anchors Design Debt Vs Design Bet rule `explicit-class-tag`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="debt-needs-friction-source" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tasks tagged `debt` MUST cite a specific friction-map entry or UX-audit finding with metric impact. No source = the task is actually a bet in disguise.</statement>
      <rationale source="Friction-mapping research">Friction-mapping research — anchors Design Debt Vs Design Bet rule `debt-needs-friction-source`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="bet-needs-falsifiable-hypothesis" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tasks tagged `bet` MUST cite a falsifiable hypothesis (form: &apos;if we ship X, metric Y will move ≥Z within W weeks&apos;). No hypothesis = the task is actually debt in disguise or vanity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Falsifiability discipline">Falsifiability discipline — anchors Design Debt Vs Design Bet rule `bet-needs-falsifiable-hypothesis`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="budget-envelope-per-class" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sprint MUST allocate ≤30% capacity to bets, ≥20% to debt. Outside envelope = explicit roadmap-level decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="Budget-discipline research">Budget-discipline research — anchors Design Debt Vs Design Bet rule `budget-envelope-per-class`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kill-criterion-on-bet" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each bet MUST have a kill criterion (metric + threshold + observation window). Bets without kill criteria run forever and turn into debt.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kill-criterion discipline">Kill-criterion discipline — anchors Design Debt Vs Design Bet rule `kill-criterion-on-bet`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
