<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo X Analytics Review Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules for a weekly X / Twitter analytics review focused on indie audience growth.</summary>

  <section title="Review rules">

    <rule id="r1-five-metrics-fixed" testable="true">
      <statement>The review covers exactly five metrics: (1) total impressions, (2) profile visits, (3) net followers (gained − lost), (4) replies from strangers (not in your existing network), (5) link clicks to owned URL (newsletter / product). Follower count alone is forbidden as the headline number.</statement>
      <rationale>Impressions and follower counts move together for bot-attracting content. The "replies from strangers" + "link clicks" pair is what separates audience-growth from engagement theatre.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-20-min-time-box" testable="true">
      <statement>Total review time is capped at 20 minutes per week, on a fixed day (e.g., Friday afternoon). Within the slot: 8 min metric scan, 8 min identify the top + bottom post of the week, 4 min write the next-week experiment line. Running long means cutting depth, not extending.</statement>
      <rationale>Audience analytics expand to fill any time slot. A 20-minute cap forces selecting signal over thorough analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-outlier-rule-3x-baseline" testable="true">
      <statement>A post is an "outlier" only if its impressions are ≥3x the trailing-4-week median of the operator's own posts. Outliers are studied (what was different); non-outliers are NOT — comparing every individual post against another's algorithm-favoured post is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>Solo operators waste hours studying posts that performed at baseline, mistaking randomness for signal. A 3x threshold focuses learning on posts where something real happened.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-one-experiment-per-week" testable="true">
      <statement>Each review produces exactly one named experiment for the following week, with a hypothesis, the variable changed, and the success metric. Examples: "post hook with concrete number → expect impressions ≥1.5x baseline", "thread length 5 vs 12 tweets → expect link-click rate same or higher with 5". Zero or multiple experiments are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple simultaneous variable changes destroy the signal. One-at-a-time experimentation is the only way a solo operator builds a useful mental model of their audience over months.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-qualified-follow-discipline" testable="true">
      <statement>"Net followers" in the dashboard is tagged: % qualified vs unqualified. Qualified = bio mentions ICP keyword, or has a clearly-aligned profile. Unqualified = generic / sales accounts / suspected bot. Reviews report both numbers; chasing total-follower numbers without qualified-follower discipline is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Algorithm-bait posts attract unqualified followers at high rates. Without tagging, the operator optimises into a follower list that doesn't convert to product or newsletter readers.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## X review — W20 (2026-05-16, 18 min)

Metrics (vs trailing 4w median):
- Impressions:        82,400  (median 41,000)  → 2.0x
- Profile visits:        611  (median   390)   → 1.6x
- Net followers:        +94   (qualified ~52% / unqualified ~48%)
- Replies-from-strangers: 23  (median 11)      → 2.1x
- Link clicks:           184  (median 78)      → 2.4x

Top post (outlier, 3.4x baseline):
  "I shipped pricing v2 in 4h after staring at it for 6 weeks. Here's the
  one-table reason I was stuck — sunk-cost fear of breaking the discount
  grandfather." (with screenshot)
  → variable: emotional-vulnerability + concrete artifact

Bottom post: technical tip with no hook, baseline performance.

NEXT-WEEK EXPERIMENT (W21):
  Hypothesis: emotional-vulnerability opener + concrete artifact → outlier
  rate ≥1 outlier per 6 posts (vs current ~1 per 12).
  Variable: open with personal feeling-fact in 3 of 6 posts.
  Success metric: ≥1 post ≥3x baseline by end of W21.
]]></code>
    <note>Five metrics, outlier rule applied (3.4x), one experiment with named hypothesis + variable + success metric, qualified-followers tagged.</note>
  </example>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Operator reports "post X went viral with 50k impressions" without comparing to baseline, then concludes "longer threads work" and switches all posts to 12-tweet threads without controlling for the hook.</description>
    <reason>Violates r3 (no outlier comparison to baseline) and r4 (multiple variables changed in one experiment). Causes a 4-week confidence dip when the new format under-performs.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
