<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Discovery Research Handoff Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Discovery Research Handoff Template application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="one-page-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Handoff MUST fit on one page (≤500 words). Longer artefacts go unread by the receiving lead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Handoff-research">Handoff-research — anchors Discovery Research Handoff Template rule `one-page-cap`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="five-required-sections" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Handoff MUST contain all five sections: problem statement, persona snapshot, JTBD, evidence, success metric. Missing any section = the handoff is rejected by the receiving lead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Discovery-handoff practice">Discovery-handoff practice — anchors Discovery Research Handoff Template rule `five-required-sections`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-three-quotes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Evidence section MUST contain ≥3 verbatim customer quotes with source attribution (interview-id + date). Paraphrased summaries are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Verbatim-evidence research">Verbatim-evidence research — anchors Discovery Research Handoff Template rule `evidence-three-quotes`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="dual-signature" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Handoff MUST be signed by both the PM AND the receiving lead before solutioning starts. Single-signature handoffs lack the shared-understanding gate they were designed to create.</statement>
      <rationale source="Handoff-governance practice">Handoff-governance practice — anchors Discovery Research Handoff Template rule `dual-signature`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="success-metric-singular" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Success metric MUST be exactly one observable + threshold + window. Multi-metric handoffs hand off scope ambiguity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Goal-Question-Metric">Goal-Question-Metric — anchors Discovery Research Handoff Template rule `success-metric-singular`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
