<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Cost Estimation Process">
  <summary>Five-step process from WBS work packages to a fully-loaded cost baseline with risk-driven contingency.</summary>

  <section title="Cost Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Direct Costs — salaries, contractors, software licenses, hardware directly attributed to the project</item>
      <item>Indirect Costs — office overhead, utilities, management overhead loaded as a percentage of direct labor</item>
      <item>Fixed Costs — subscriptions, base salaries, regardless of project activity level</item>
      <item>Variable Costs — overtime, cloud usage, contractor hours that scale with project work</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 1: Bottom-Up Estimation">
    <p>For each WBS work package, estimate labor hours by role and multiply by fully-loaded rate. Example: Design (16h x $75) + Development (40h x $100) + Testing (8h x $60) + Documentation (4h x $50) = $5,880 per package. Sum all packages for total direct labor cost.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Resource Rate Loading">
    <list>
      <item>Full-time employee: (annual salary x fully-loaded multiplier) / working days. Multiplier: 1.3x (low-tax market) to 2.0x (high-benefit market).</item>
      <item>Contractor: hourly rate x estimated hours. Cite contract or market survey as source.</item>
      <item>Software/SaaS: license + seats + integration cost over project duration.</item>
      <item>Infrastructure: provisioned capacity x unit rate x duration; use infracost or cloud provider pricing API for accuracy.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Three-Point PERT">
    <p>For uncertain cost items: Expected Cost = (Optimistic + 4 x Most Likely + Pessimistic) / 6. Example — cloud hosting: O=$200/mo, M=$350/mo, P=$800/mo → Expected = (200 + 1400 + 800)/6 = $400/mo. Track P80 of Monte Carlo simulation as the budget target, not P50.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Risk-Driven Contingency">
    <p>Sum (probability x cost_impact) for all open risks in the risk register. This replaces flat-percentage reserves, which systematically over- or under-fund based on risk profile. Unknown Unknowns (Management Reserve) is an additional 5-10% held by sponsors, released only for major scope changes.</p>
    <reference path="scripts/risk-contingency.py">Monte Carlo risk-driven contingency calculator</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Cost Baseline">
    <list>
      <item>Cost Baseline = Direct Costs + Indirect Costs + Risk-Driven Contingency Reserve</item>
      <item>Budget at Completion (BAC) = Cost Baseline + Management Reserve</item>
      <item>Lock the baseline after approval; re-baseline only on approved change requests</item>
      <item>Track Schedule Performance Index (SPI) and Cost Performance Index (CPI) from EVM weekly</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/cost-worksheet.md">Full cost estimation worksheet</reference>
  </section>
</text>
