<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Cost Estimation Rules and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete rules for rate citation, burden loading, contingency method selection, and avoiding common agent estimation errors.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Cite source on every labor rate; reject any rate card that lacks a contract reference or market survey citation.</statement>
    <rationale>LLMs hallucinate benchmark rates from stale training data; rates can differ 30%+ from current market; sourced rates are auditable and defensible.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Use risk-driven contingency (sum of probability x cost_impact per open risk); do not use a flat percentage when an active risk register exists.</statement>
    <rationale>Flat contingency double-charges when combined with risk-driven reserve; it also ignores actual risk profile, over-funding low-risk and under-funding high-risk projects.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Track P80 of Monte Carlo simulation as the cost target, not P50 or PERT mean.</statement>
    <rationale>P50 means the budget is breached 50% of the time; P80 provides a realistic target with acceptable overrun probability.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Separate management reserve from contingency reserve; contingency releases on identified risks; management reserve releases on scope changes only.</statement>
    <rationale>Conflating the two removes sponsor control and misrepresents budget authority.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Effort hours are not elapsed days; model resource availability when computing duration-based costs (a 40-hour task for a 60%-available person costs 100% of their rate for 66 hours elapsed, not 40).</statement>
    <rationale>Effort-elapsed confusion is the most common single source of budget overrun in agent-generated cost estimates.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <antipattern>
    <description>LLM outputs suspiciously round numbers ($50k, $100k, $200k) without showing the calculation.</description>
    <reason>Round numbers are anchors from training data, not estimates; require the bottom-up calculation or reject the output.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Using a single overhead multiplier (1.3x) globally across all regions and employment types.</description>
    <reason>Overhead loading varies by region, tax regime, and benefits structure (1.3x to 2.0x); a single multiplier is wrong for cross-border projects.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Including both risk-driven contingency AND a flat 15% on top of it.</description>
    <reason>Double-charging inflates the budget and misrepresents the risk exposure; pick one method and document the choice.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Re-estimating after work has started without accounting for sunk costs, anchoring on the original number.</description>
    <reason>Re-estimates must derive from remaining scope only; anchoring to the original produces estimates that are always "a little over" the baseline.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
