<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Critical-Issue Triage Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Four testable rules that turn post-session triage from a gut call into a defensible decision in 30 minutes.</summary>

  <section title="The four rules">

    <rule id="r1-severity-scale" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each finding MUST be assigned a severity 0-4 using the rubric: 0=cosmetic, 1=minor (workaround obvious), 2=major (workaround exists but is painful), 3=catastrophic (user cannot complete the primary task), 4=catastrophic+accessibility/safety. Severity assignment is committed in the triage table with the one-line evidence ("user 3 quit after 7 attempts").</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen severity rating scale + practitioner adaptations">A consistent 0-4 scale across sessions allows trend analysis ("we have 4 sev-3 findings this quarter"). Ad-hoc severity language ("really bad", "kinda bad") makes triage incomparable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-frequency-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Frequency MUST be expressed as a band against observed N: SINGLE (1/N), FEW (2-3/N or &lt;= 30%), MANY (40-70% of N), MOST (&gt; 70%). Raw counts without a band are rejected — bands are what the action matrix consumes. "One user hit it" is not actionable; "1/N with severity 4" is.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sample-size heuristic from Jakob Nielsen, '5 users find 85% of usability problems'">With small N (5-8), a single occurrence may already represent a real population issue. Bands acknowledge sample limits without dismissing one-off severe findings.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-context-modifier" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Context modifiers MUST be applied: REVENUE-CRITICAL path (checkout, signup) bumps action by one level; REGULATED user (medical, financial, accessibility-rights) bumps by one level; INTERNAL-TOOL path may demote by one level. The modifier is recorded so the rationale is auditable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Risk-management practice; impact varies by path criticality">A confusing button in admin settings is different from the same button on the checkout page. The modifier captures the business context the raw severity ignores.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-action-matrix" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Action MUST come from the matrix lookup: severity × frequency × context-modifier → SAME-DAY-FIX / NEXT-SPRINT / BACKLOG / DISCARD. The lookup is deterministic. Overrides are allowed but require a written one-line justification ("override to same-day because customer demo tomorrow"). Verbal overrides are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-rule stability over personal preference">Deterministic lookup prevents the recurring "loud finding" bias — a finding that was vivid in observation gets escalated past its real severity.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Triage row with rationale">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Finding: User cannot find "Add to cart" button on mobile product page (button is below the fold and color contrast 2.5:1).
Severity: 3 (catastrophic — primary purchase path blocked)
Frequency: MANY (4/5 mobile users)
Context: REVENUE-CRITICAL +1 -> effective severity 4
Action: SAME-DAY-FIX
Owner: UI lead, eng to deploy by EOD
Rationale: Sev-3 + MANY + REVENUE-CRITICAL hits matrix top-left.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Rubric applied, modifier recorded, owner named, action deterministic.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Improvised triage">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"User 3 was really frustrated by the cart icon. Should we fix it ASAP?"
      ]]></code>
      <note>Single user, no severity, no frequency, no modifier, ambiguous action. Loud-user bias.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
