<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Critical-Issue Triage Protocol Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Critical-Issue Triage Protocol. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-severity-scale-0-4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each finding is assigned severity 0..4 using the calibrated rubric (0 cosmetic / 1 minor / 2 major / 3 catastrophic / 4 catastrophic+accessibility-safety); rating ad-hoc adjectives are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen severity scale + practitioner adaptations">Consistent 0..4 scale enables trend analysis across sessions; ad-hoc severity makes triage incomparable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-frequency-band-not-count" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Frequency is expressed as a band against observed N: SINGLE (1/N), FEW (2-3/N or &lt;=30%), MANY (40-70%), MOST (&gt;70%). Raw counts without a band are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Jakob Nielsen sample-size heuristic">With small N, a single occurrence may already signal a real population issue. Bands acknowledge sample limits without dismissing severe one-offs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-context-modifier-applied" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Context modifiers are applied: REVENUE-CRITICAL +1, REGULATED +1, INTERNAL-TOOL -1. The modifier is recorded so the rationale is auditable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Risk-management practice">Impact varies by path criticality; the modifier captures the business context raw severity ignores.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-action-matrix-deterministic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Action is taken from the matrix lookup (severity × frequency × context-modifier → SAME-DAY-FIX / NEXT-SPRINT / BACKLOG / DISCARD). Overrides require a written one-line justification.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-rule stability over personal preference">Deterministic lookup prevents the loud-finding bias — a vivid finding gets escalated past its real severity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-evidence-line-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each triage row carries a one-line evidence statement (e.g. &apos;user 3 quit after 7 attempts&apos;) alongside the score; rows without evidence are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Grounded-decision convention">Score-without-evidence is folklore; the evidence line lets reviewers re-litigate the decision when needed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-critical-issue-triage-protocol.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
