<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Triage Protocol Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five failure modes that erode the triage protocol. Each has a detector and a repair.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="high">
      <description>Panic-patch — a sev-3 finding triggers an immediate code change that breaks an adjacent flow.</description>
      <detector>SAME-DAY-FIX ticket closed in &lt; 1 hour AND no QA pass logged AND a follow-up bug arrives within 48h</detector>
      <repair>Even SAME-DAY-FIX gets a 10-minute QA pass on adjacent flows. Add the QA-pass requirement to the action matrix. A real same-day fix takes 2-4 hours including verification.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="high">
      <description>Loud-user bias — one expressive user's frustration drives a SAME-DAY-FIX for a SINGLE-frequency issue.</description>
      <detector>SAME-DAY-FIX action AND frequency_band = SINGLE AND no context-modifier present</detector>
      <repair>Re-evaluate per the matrix. SINGLE + no modifier = NEXT-SPRINT at most. Vivid user observations are data, not severity escalators.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Low-sev pile — every sev-1/sev-2 finding goes to BACKLOG and never returns. Quality erosion is invisible.</description>
      <detector>BACKLOG has &gt; 30 sev-1/sev-2 findings older than 6 months AND no batch-fix sprint has been scheduled</detector>
      <repair>Schedule a quarterly "low-sev fix" sprint OR add a rule: sev-1/2 with frequency MANY/MOST escalates to NEXT-SPRINT regardless. Low severity at high frequency = compounding pain.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Triage skipped because session was "just informal."</description>
      <detector>Session notes exist but no triage-table-session-NNN.md was created</detector>
      <repair>Run the 30-minute triage. Informal sessions still produce findings that affect users. Skipping triage is how "we knew about that" becomes a postmortem line.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Context modifier abused — designer marks everything REVENUE-CRITICAL to push their pet finding to the top.</description>
      <detector>&gt; 60% of findings in a session marked REVENUE-CRITICAL OR the marked path is not actually a revenue path</detector>
      <repair>Define REVENUE-CRITICAL paths explicitly per product (checkout, signup, activation). Modifier requires path membership, not just claim. Audit triage tables periodically.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>If an LLM helps draft the triage table from session transcripts, it must not auto-escalate severity based on user emotional language ("frustrated", "angry") — those are inputs to the rubric, not direct severity outputs. The designer applies the rubric.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>The designer (or product owner) is the final triage decision-maker. Matrix output is a recommendation; overrides are written and reviewed. SAME-DAY-FIX actions are also surfaced to the engineering lead before commit, since they consume engineering capacity.</p>
  </section>
</text>
