<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agency Revenue Mix Audit Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five hard rules for a quarterly agency revenue-mix research audit.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-line-classification-rigor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every invoice maps to ONE line: project / retainer / productized / misc. Edge cases (a retainer scope-up, a project that extended) are documented in a "reclassification log". An invoice cannot be split across lines.</statement>
      <rationale source="data-quality fundamentals; Profit First categorization">Inconsistent line assignment makes trend analysis noise. The reclassification log preserves audit integrity when borderline cases require judgment. Splitting an invoice across lines compounds the mess.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-margin-per-line-not-just-revenue" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every line carries gross_margin_percent = (revenue - direct_costs) / revenue. Direct costs = contractor pay + delivery tooling + third-party services attributable to that line. Revenue without margin is vanity; margin tells you which line is sustainable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Parakeeto agency benchmarks 2024; Built to Sell methodology">Many agencies discover their "biggest" line is their lowest margin (often Project, because of competitive pricing). Retainer often has higher margin once ramped. Productized has the highest margin but requires marketing investment. Margin-blind decisions optimize the wrong line.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-six-quarter-trend-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trend analysis covers exactly 6 quarters (1.5 years). Shorter windows are seasonality not trend; longer windows include strategic shifts that obscure current state. Always 6.</statement>
      <rationale source="time-series analysis fundamentals; B2B sales cycle data">4 quarters is one cycle = no trend visible. 8+ quarters dilutes recent strategic changes. 6 quarters threads the needle: 1 full year + 2 quarters of newer signal. Industry-standard for SaaS and service-business retention research.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-concentration-cross-cut" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Concentration analysis runs at two levels: (a) within each line — what % of retainer revenue is from top-3 retainer clients? (b) across all lines — what % of total revenue is from top-3 clients regardless of line? Both must be reported. Single-level concentration hides cross-line risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="risk-concentration research; Bain SMB resilience studies">A client paying for both a retainer AND a project at the same time can show 20% in each line but 30% globally. Across-lines concentration is the real exposure. Within-line concentration shows which line has built dependency on one player.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-five-decision-questions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit closes with exactly 5 decision questions for the founder, each with a recommended answer informed by the data: (1) raise rates by X% on which line? (2) drop bottom-margin clients? (3) productize which repeated deliverable? (4) hire FT vs. continue contracting which role? (5) exit which line entirely? Forced choice generates action.</statement>
      <rationale source="strategic-planning facilitation; Lencioni - "death by meeting"">Reports without decision asks become wallpaper. Forced 5-question close generates a quarterly action set the founder either commits to or explicitly defers. The 5-count is tight enough to drive action; broader sets dilute focus.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Audit revealing the productization opportunity">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Q4-2024 to Q1-2026 audit findings:

Line mix (% of total revenue):
              Q4'24  Q1'25  Q2'25  Q3'25  Q4'25  Q1'26
Project       62%    58%    51%    49%    43%    38%
Retainer      32%    36%    41%    43%    47%    51%
Productized   4%     5%     7%     7%     9%     11%
Misc          2%     1%     1%     1%     1%     0%

Margin per line (Q1'26):
  Project:      38% (declining from 42% in Q4'24 — price pressure)
  Retainer:     54% (stable, ramped)
  Productized:  71% (highest margin, scaling)

Concentration (Q1'26):
  Within-retainer top-3:  61% ⚠
  Across-all top-3:        47%

Decision questions (with recommended answer):
  Q1 Raise rates on Project line +12%?  YES — margin trend negative
  Q2 Drop bottom-margin Project clients (margin &lt; 30%)?  YES — 3 candidates
  Q3 Productize the "tech audit" deliverable shipped 14 times in 6 quarters?  YES
  Q4 Hire FT designer (currently 2 contractors at 65% util combined)?  YES
  Q5 Exit Project line entirely over next 4 quarters?  DEFER — too early; revisit Q3'26
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1-r5 in a single output.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Revenue-only audit (margin-blind)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Revenue is up 18% YoY — we're growing!"

Hides: Project margin dropped from 42% to 38%; Project revenue is up but
absolute profit is flat. Retainer margin is higher but smaller absolute. The
"growth" is unprofitable.
Repair: enforce margin-per-line + trend window. The audit must show profit
trajectory, not vanity revenue.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Revenue-only is the canonical false-positive pattern.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
