<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="focus-groups">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Moderated qualitative method with 6-10 participants per group. Run 3+ groups per segment. Use written-first exercises to capture unanchored opinions before group discussion.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>qualitative-research</tag>
      <tag>focus-groups</tag>
      <tag>concept-testing</tag>
      <tag>moderation</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Focus Groups</title>
    <summary>A moderated qualitative method with 6–10 participants per group, 60–90 minutes, run in a minimum of 3 groups per segment before themes are treated as stable. Structure: warm-up (10 min), three core topics with probe ladders (40–60 min), concept reveal late (last 25%), wrap-up. Use written-first exercises before open discussion to capture unanchored individual opinions. Recruit one extra participant per group to absorb ~20% no-show rate.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Focus groups surface group vocabulary, attitude ranges, and concept reactions faster than sequential 1:1 interviews. The key mechanism is social elicitation: participants build on and contrast each other's views, revealing disagreements that solo interviewees suppress. The minimum-3-groups rule exists because themes from 1–2 groups systematically over-represent the first articulate speaker.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Early-stage concept exploration before quantitative or 1:1 interview research.</item>
        <item>Generating reaction data on copy, naming, value propositions, or visual concepts.</item>
        <item>Mapping user vocabulary—how customers describe a problem in their own words.</item>
        <item>Recruiting stakeholder buy-in by letting PMs observe live discussion.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Usability testing—group dynamics drown individual task behavior.</item>
        <item>Sensitive or personal topics (health, finance, harassment)—social pressure distorts answers.</item>
        <item>Final decision-making—small N plus groupthink does not equal representative data.</item>
        <item>Anything shipped without a 1:1 follow-up—group consensus is unreliable signal alone.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Group Composition Rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a minimum of 3 focus groups per user segment before treating findings as stable. Themes from 1–2 groups systematically over-represent the first articulate speaker.</statement>
        <rationale>With 1–2 groups, a single dominant voice can define the "consensus". Three groups provide enough comparison to distinguish genuine themes from dominant-speaker artifacts.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Size each group at 6–10 participants: homogeneous enough for comfort and candor, diverse enough for range of opinion. Recruit one extra per group to absorb ~20% no-show rate.</statement>
        <rationale>Below 6 participants, the group lacks sufficient dynamic range. Above 10, time per participant drops below the threshold needed for meaningful contribution and moderation becomes crowd management.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Session Structure">
      <p>Standard 90-minute format (60 minutes for online): welcome and ground rules (5 min), warm-up with an easy question (10 min), three core topics with probe ladders (40–60 min), concept reveal (last 25%—no earlier), wrap-up with final thoughts (5 min).</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Reveal stimulus concepts (mockups, prototypes, copy) in the last 25% of the session only. Concept reveal early in a session biases all subsequent discussion.</statement>
        <rationale>Early concept exposure anchors the group's vocabulary and evaluation frame to the specific concept shown, suppressing the organic attitudes and language the session was designed to uncover.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use written-first exercises before group discussion for key questions. Have every participant write their response individually before speaking.</statement>
        <rationale>Captures unanchored individual opinions before the first articulate speaker anchors the group. Written-first responses reveal dissent that oral-first discussion suppresses.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Moderation Techniques">
      <section name="Managing Dominant Participants">
        <p>Redirect after first contribution: "Thanks—let's hear from others." Direct questions explicitly to quiet participants by name. Sit adjacent to dominant participants (reduces eye contact as reinforcement). Use round-robin for specific questions to equalize contribution.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="Probing Deeper">
        <p>Clarification: "What do you mean by...?" Expansion: "Tell me more about that." Reason: "Why do you feel that way?" Contrast: "How does that compare to...?" Example: "Can you give me an example?" These five probes cover 90% of facilitation needs.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="Managing Conflict">
        <p>Acknowledge both views without resolution: "It sounds like there are different experiences here—let's explore both perspectives." Never push for consensus in a focus group—disagreement is data.</p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="Recruitment">
      <rule>
        <statement>Stagger participant arrival 5 minutes before start. Avoid pre-session group bonding that lets a leader emerge before the session begins.</statement>
        <rationale>Pre-session social dynamics can establish a group hierarchy that the moderator then fights for 90 minutes. Staggered arrival prevents "lobby leadership" from transferring into the room.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Compensate all participants equally regardless of contribution. Pay-for-talk incentive structures corrupt data by rewarding quantity over quality.</statement>
        <rationale>Variable compensation creates pressure to speak, producing filler contributions from quiet participants and over-contribution from dominant participants chasing the maximum payout.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>One loud voice asserting a position early, followed by apparent group agreement without independent confirmation.</description>
        <reason>Groupthink: participants anchor on the first articulate opinion and suppress dissent. Written-first exercises and direct probing of quiet participants are the only reliable countermeasures.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating a single group's consensus as representative of the segment.</description>
        <reason>One group's "everyone agreed" is one group's dominant voice. Require at minimum 3 groups and cross-group comparison before any finding enters a decision artifact.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Moderator leading questions: "Don't you think this is confusing?" or "Most people find X helpful—do you agree?"</description>
        <reason>Leading questions suppress genuine reaction and replace it with social compliance. All discussion guide questions must be neutral; run a lint pass on the guide before sessions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Online focus groups running longer than 60 minutes or with more than 6 participants.</description>
        <reason>Online format loses body language, creates speaking-order awkwardness, and induces fatigue faster than in-person. Shorter sessions with smaller groups preserve data quality.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Analysis Framework">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cross-group comparison is mandatory before reporting. For each theme, record which groups expressed it, strength of consensus, and any between-group divergence.</statement>
        <rationale>A theme present in one group but absent in two others is a segment-specific finding, not a general one. Conflating the two produces misleading recommendations.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Reporting structure per finding: what was heard (summary of discussion), representative quote (verbatim, with participant type), implication (what this means for design or strategy).</p>
      <p>Surprise and contradiction log: document moments where findings contradict research goals or prior data. These are often the most valuable outputs of a focus group.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>Drive Claude to scaffold the discussion guide from research objectives, generate screener questions, and draft moderator probe ladders. After sessions, hand transcripts to a thematic-analysis agent that produces cross-group comparison tables and verbatim-quote bundles per theme. A separate "skeptic" agent flags: groupthink moments (anchor speaker + rapid agreement sequence), dominant-voice capture (one speaker contributing more than 30% of utterances), and facilitator-leading (questions containing "isn't it", "don't you think", leading negatives).</p>
      <p>Human-in-loop gate: a human researcher must review themes before they enter any decision artifact. LLMs hallucinate speaker quotes and collapse minority views. Explicitly prompt for "minority views" and "contradictions"—without this, LLM theme synthesis systematically suppresses dissent.</p>
      <p>PII handling: redact names, emails, and health detail before passing transcripts to any model. Recordings often contain consent-scope drift—tag and segment accordingly before analysis.</p>
      <p>Prompt Pattern:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Goal: <research objective>. Audience: <segment>.
Draft a 90-min discussion guide: warm-up, 3 core topics with probes,
concept reaction (15 min), wrap-up. Avoid leading phrasing. Include
"call on quiet participant" prompts at the 30/60-min marks.]]></code>
      <p>Prompt Pattern (Post-Session Analysis):</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Given <transcript JSON with speaker tags>, output:
- Themes (3-7) with frequency by speaker.
- Verbatim quotes per theme with timestamps.
- Suspected groupthink moments (anchor speaker + sequence of agreement).
- Surprises / contradictions vs. research goals.]]></code>
      <p>Recommended Subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-ux-researcher-agent—guide drafting, theme synthesis, cross-group comparison.</item>
        <item>faion-usability-agent—sanity-check tasks against research goals.</item>
        <item>A custom transcript-themer—chunk transcripts, embed, cluster, output theme tree with quote citations.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Tools and Services">
      <p>CLI Tools:</p>
      <list>
        <item>whisper / whisperx—local transcription with speaker diarization. pip install whisperx</item>
        <item>pyannote-audio—speaker diarization. pip install pyannote.audio</item>
        <item>otter-cli (unofficial)—pull Otter.ai transcripts via API. github.com/eml-tools/otter-api</item>
        <item>dovetail-cli (REST)—push tagged segments to Dovetail. dovetailapp.com/developers</item>
        <item>recall.ai API—auto-record Zoom/Meet/Teams sessions. docs.recall.ai</item>
      </list>
      <p>Services and Platforms:</p>
      <list>
        <item>User Interviews—SaaS, recruiting platform; CSV export of screened participants.</item>
        <item>Respondent.io—SaaS, recruiting + scheduling API.</item>
        <item>dscout—SaaS, async-first; agent can drive prompts.</item>
        <item>Dovetail—SaaS, tag transcripts, generate themes via REST API.</item>
        <item>Reduct.video—SaaS, searchable transcript with video clips.</item>
        <item>Zoom + Otter.ai—SaaS, cheap baseline; manual transcript export.</item>
        <item>FocusVision (Forsta)—SaaS, enterprise focus-group platform.</item>
        <item>Discuss.io—SaaS, built for focus groups, recording included.</item>
        <item>Lookback—SaaS, live observer rooms; agent listens via API.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Run at least 3 groups per segment—themes don't stabilize with 1–2.</item>
        <item>Stagger arrival 5 min before start to avoid pre-session "leader" bonding skewing dynamics.</item>
        <item>Use written-first exercises before discussion to capture initial individual opinions un-anchored.</item>
        <item>Compensate equally regardless of contribution; pay-for-talk corrupts data.</item>
        <item>Time-box concept reveal late (last 25%) so reactions aren't biased by early tangents.</item>
        <item>Always recruit one extra participant per group; ~20% no-show rate.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-Agent Gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLM theme synthesis collapses dissent; explicitly prompt for "minority views" and "contradictions".</item>
        <item>Auto-generated discussion guides over-rely on closed/leading questions ("Don't you think…?"); lint pass required.</item>
        <item>Speaker diarization mis-attributes overlapping speech, especially online—manual spot-check required.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoint: a human researcher must review themes before they enter any decision artifact; LLMs hallucinate speaker quotes.</item>
        <item>PII and recordings: redact names/emails/health detail BEFORE handing transcripts to the model. Recordings often contain consent-scope drift—tag and segment accordingly.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/discussion-guide.md" purpose="Full 90-min discussion guide: welcome, ground rules, warm-up, topics, concept reaction, wrap-up"/>
      <template path="templates/note-taking.md" purpose="Per-session note-taking template with participant table, group dynamics, and quote capture"/>
      <template path="templates/transcript-themer.py" purpose="TF-IDF + k-means theme extraction from transcript JSON with speaker attribution"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://nngroup.com/articles/focus-groups">Nielsen Norman Group—When to Use Focus Groups</link>
      <ref slug="surveys"/>
      <ref slug="tree-testing"/>
      <ref slug="diary-studies"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
