<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Anti-Pattern Rationale Template Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Anti-Pattern Rationale Template. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-single-instance-per-record" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each Anti-Pattern Rationale Template artefact captures exactly one instance; batched records that conflate multiple instances are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-conflation pattern — F-066 grounding">Batching turns a 1-decision artefact into a debate club; per-instance records keep rationale traceable and stale-detection accurate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-evidence-link-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every artefact carries at least one evidence link (URL or repo path) pointing at the user-behaviour data; prose-only evidence is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Falsifiability principle; Practitioner audits">Untraceable evidence makes the artefact unauditable; future readers cannot verify the claim or detect drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Owner field is a named handle, email, or role-with-rotation; pronouns (we, us, team) are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI / single-throat-to-choke">Plural ownership = no ownership; future readers need a named human to chase when the artefact goes stale.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-semver-and-last-reviewed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Artefact carries semver version and ISO last_reviewed date; stale records (&gt;90 days unreviewed) must surface a warning on read.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice; F-066 maintenance budget">Decision artefacts decay; treating them as immutable produces folklore. Versioning + dated review force a refresh cadence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-rationale-cites-input" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rationale section names at least one input (Prerequisites table row) by name; rationales without a sourced citation are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Grounded-output convention">Ungrounded rationales are post-hoc justifications that drift from the real evidence; named citations are auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-anti-pattern-rationale-template.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
