<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="writing-implementation-plans Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for writing-implementation-plans as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Task with acceptance criteria that say "works correctly" or "functions as expected".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Vague AC cannot be verified by a test or a quality gate check. Every AC must specify a concrete observable outcome: a status code, a file that exists, a database row, a rendered element.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent declares all tasks as Wave 1 (no dependencies) to maximize apparent parallelism.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Missing dependencies cause merge conflicts and broken builds when parallel agents overwrite each other's files. Require dependency evidence from design.md for every "no dependencies" claim.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent declares all tasks as depending on the previous one, producing a purely sequential plan.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs default to sequential thinking. A purely sequential plan with more than 3 tasks likely contains false dependencies. Review each FS edge: does the downstream task actually need the upstream file to exist, or is it just logically related?</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Task token estimate over 100k with no split.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Declare the task as "Split Required" and decompose into subtasks before proceeding. A 150k task is not one complex task — it is two or three tasks with a shared header.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Task references another task in "Depends on" that does not exist in the plan.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add the missing task or fix the reference. Missing dependency tasks are the second most common cause of execution failures after token overruns.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Circular dependency (TASK-A → TASK-B → TASK-A).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Restructure the dependency chain. Circular deps indicate a design problem: one of the two tasks needs to be split, or one dependency is false (logically related but not a real FS constraint).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>File structure section listing non-existent files or files that cannot be split as declared.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Verify every listed file against the actual codebase. Executor agents will either create orphaned files or fail when files they need do not exist.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
