<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-quality-gates" title="Implementation Plan Quality Gates">
  <summary>Traceability 100% rule, pre-writing checklist, and common issues with detection and fixes.</summary>

  <section title="Traceability 100% Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every AD-X from design.md must have at least one corresponding task. Every FR-X from spec.md must trace to at least one task. Every task must trace to at least one AD-X or FR-X. Zero orphan tasks permitted.</statement>
      <rationale>The 100% rule ensures no design decision is left unimplemented and no task was invented without requirement backing. It is the primary completeness check before execution begins.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Verify traceability by running: `grep -c "AD-" implementation-plan.md` and comparing to the AD-X count in design.md. Do the same for FR-X. Any gap must be resolved before the plan is approved.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual counting is error-prone. The grep check takes 10 seconds and catches the most common oversight: a design decision that was noted but never assigned to a task.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pre-Writing Checklist">
    <list>
      <item>spec.md status: Approved</item>
      <item>design.md status: Approved</item>
      <item>All AD-X decisions finalized (no "TBD" entries)</item>
      <item>constitution.md read for project naming and testing standards</item>
      <item>Completed plans in done/ reviewed for patterns</item>
    </list>

    <rule>
      <statement>Do not write an implementation plan against a design doc with TBD architectural decisions. Resolve all TBDs in design.md first.</statement>
      <rationale>Planning against unresolved decisions produces tasks that change as soon as the decision is made, wasting the planning work and creating confusion during execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Issues">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Task token estimate over 100k with no split.</description>
      <reason>Declare the task as "Split Required" and decompose into subtasks before proceeding. A 150k task is not one complex task — it is two or three tasks with a shared header.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Task references another task in "Depends on" that does not exist in the plan.</description>
      <reason>Add the missing task or fix the reference. Missing dependency tasks are the second most common cause of execution failures after token overruns.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Circular dependency (TASK-A → TASK-B → TASK-A).</description>
      <reason>Restructure the dependency chain. Circular deps indicate a design problem: one of the two tasks needs to be split, or one dependency is false (logically related but not a real FS constraint).</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
