<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-security" title="AWS S3 Bucket Security">
  <summary>Block public access rules, encryption options (SSE-S3/KMS/DSSE-KMS, April 2026 SSE-C change), and bucket policy HTTPS enforcement.</summary>

  <section title="Public Access Blocking">
    <rule>
      <statement>Block all public access at both account level (S3 Block Public Access) and individual bucket level; set Object Ownership to BucketOwnerEnforced (disables ACLs); never grant public read via bucket policy.</statement>
      <rationale>S3 misconfiguration (public access) is among the top causes of cloud data breaches. Account-level blocking provides a backstop even if per-bucket settings are misconfigured. ACLs are a legacy mechanism superseded by bucket policies.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Encryption">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable SSE-KMS with a customer-managed KMS key for buckets containing sensitive, regulated, or production data; use SSE-S3 (AES-256) for general non-sensitive buckets; enable S3 Bucket Keys to reduce KMS API call cost by up to 99%.</statement>
      <rationale>SSE-KMS provides audit trails of key usage (CloudTrail), key rotation, and access policy control. SSE-S3 is free and requires no key management. Bucket Keys batch multiple object operations into a single KMS call.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Starting April 2026: SSE-C (customer-provided keys) is disabled by default for new buckets. If SSE-C is required, explicitly enable it via PutBucketEncryption API before any SSE-C upload.</statement>
      <rationale>AWS changed the default to prevent misconfigured SSE-C usage where key management falls entirely on the customer with no AWS-side recovery. Teams migrating workloads must re-enable it explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Bucket Policy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a bucket policy denying all s3:* actions where aws:SecureTransport is false; this enforces HTTPS for all access including IAM principals with s3:GetObject permission.</statement>
      <rationale>HTTP requests to S3 transmit data and credentials in cleartext. The SecureTransport condition denies HTTP even if IAM policies grant access, enforcing encryption in transit at the bucket level.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "Version": "2012-10-17",
  "Statement": [{
    "Sid": "DenyHTTP",
    "Effect": "Deny",
    "Principal": "*",
    "Action": "s3:*",
    "Resource": [
      "arn:aws:s3:::BUCKET_NAME",
      "arn:aws:s3:::BUCKET_NAME/*"
    ],
    "Condition": {
      "Bool": { "aws:SecureTransport": "false" }
    }
  }]
}
]]></code>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use VPC Gateway endpoints for S3 access from EC2, ECS, Lambda, and EKS; configure endpoint policies to restrict access to specific bucket ARNs.</statement>
      <rationale>Gateway endpoints are free and route S3 traffic over the AWS backbone rather than the public internet. Endpoint policies prevent the endpoint from being used to access unauthorized buckets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>S3 buckets with public read access enabled via bucket policy or ACL.</description>
      <reason>Public buckets are indexed by search engines and security scanners within minutes of creation. Even accidentally exposed sensitive files become permanently cached and accessible.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
