<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Late-Fee and Pause-Clause Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules for late-fee, work-pause and re-engagement clauses in a freelance SOW or MSA.</summary>

  <section title="Clause rules">

    <rule id="r1-clause-in-sow-not-email" testable="true">
      <statement>The late-fee, pause-right and re-engagement-fee clauses MUST appear in the signed SOW (or referenced MSA), not in invoice footers or follow-up emails. A clause invoked but not signed is unenforceable.</statement>
      <rationale>Courts and arbitration reject post-hoc invoice terms as unilateral. Pre-signed paper is the lever.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-late-fee-tiered" testable="true">
      <statement>Late fee is tiered: 0% during net-payment window, 1.5% per month (or local statutory max, whichever is lower) accrued daily starting day 1 past due, capped at the relevant statutory cap. Fee starts the day after net-terms expire, not on a vague "around month-end".</statement>
      <rationale>Daily-accrual tiered fees withstand legal challenge better than flat lump-sum fees, which are sometimes recharacterised as unenforceable penalties.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-pause-after-14-days" testable="true">
      <statement>If any invoice is more than 14 calendar days past due, the freelancer has a unilateral right to suspend all work without breach. Resumption requires payment of the past-due invoice in full plus the re-engagement fee. The clause names "14 days" explicitly — not "promptly", not "in a timely manner".</statement>
      <rationale>Vague triggers ("reasonable time") are unworkable. A bright-line trigger removes negotiation from the dispute moment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-re-engagement-fee" testable="true">
      <statement>Re-engagement after a paused engagement requires a flat re-engagement fee (typically 10% of the past-due invoice or one week of billing, whichever is higher). The fee is non-refundable and paid before work resumes.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a friction fee, clients learn that "pause" costs them nothing and weaponise non-payment as a discount mechanism.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-jurisdiction-review" testable="true">
      <statement>Before first use, a licensed local lawyer reviews the clause in the operator's jurisdiction AND for any state/country where clients are typically billed. The reviewed version is the canonical template; ad-hoc edits per engagement are forbidden without re-review.</statement>
      <rationale>Late-fee rates and pause-rights are jurisdictionally capped (e.g., some US states cap at 1%, some EU contexts require notice). A template adopted without review can be unenforceable in the operator's main market.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <code lang="txt"><![CDATA[
8.3 Late Payment. If any undisputed invoice is not paid within fourteen (14)
calendar days after its due date, Consultant may, in addition to any other
remedies: (a) charge interest at one and one-half percent (1.5%) per month
(or the maximum permitted by applicable law, whichever is lower), accruing
daily from the original due date; and (b) suspend all Services until the
overdue amount and the Re-Engagement Fee in clause 8.4 are paid in full.
Suspension under this clause is not a breach.

8.4 Re-Engagement Fee. Resumption of suspended Services requires payment of
a flat Re-Engagement Fee equal to ten percent (10%) of the past-due invoice
or one (1) week of Consultant's then-current billing rate, whichever is
higher. The Re-Engagement Fee is non-refundable.
]]></code>
    <note>Tiered fee, bright-line 14-day trigger, named re-engagement fee. Plug into the SOW boilerplate after the payment-terms section.</note>
  </example>

  <antipattern>
    <description>SOW omits the clause; freelancer adds "5% late fee" to the third overdue invoice footer and expects it to stick.</description>
    <reason>Violates r1. Unilateral terms added after the fact are routinely set aside; the operator has no real leverage.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
