<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Business Analysis Planning Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed in real applications of this methodology. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>
  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern id="invented-stakeholders" severity="medium">
      <symptom>T2 lists plausible-sounding roles ('Director of UX', 'VP of Platform') that do not exist in the org chart.</symptom>
      <root-cause>LLMs hallucinate stakeholder roles based on training distributions; the gap to reality causes missed sign-offs at critical decision points.</root-cause>
      <fix>Cross-check every T2 entry against the org-chart CSV before approving; reject any name not on the list.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="merged-ka1" severity="high">
      <symptom>Single 'BA Plan' document is produced; T4 information-management and T5 performance-metrics are silently dropped.</symptom>
      <root-cause>T4 and T5 are the least visible BABOK tasks; LLMs drop them because they appear in fewer training examples.</root-cause>
      <fix>Validate against the five-artefact schema; reject when any of T1-T5 is missing.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="vague-approvers" severity="high">
      <symptom>T3 governance lists approvers as 'leadership' or 'the product team'.</symptom>
      <root-cause>Vague approvers cannot sign off; escalation paths point to a role, not a person.</root-cause>
      <fix>Require an email or @-handle per approver; reject role-only outputs.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="baselines-invented" severity="medium">
      <symptom>T5 metrics ship with invented baselines like 'rework_rate=12%' on the first cycle when no data has been collected.</symptom>
      <root-cause>Invented baselines are post-hoc rationalisations; the first cycle is for measurement establishment.</root-cause>
      <fix>Force baseline=null and target=null on the first cycle; only populate after two cycles of actual data.</fix>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
