<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="diary-studies">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Longitudinal research via self-recorded participant experiences over days/weeks. Reveals behavior change, habit formation, and churn precursors invisible to lab studies.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>longitudinal</tag>
      <tag>diary-studies</tag>
      <tag>behavior-change</tag>
      <tag>qualitative</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
      <tool>dscout</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Diary Studies</title>

    <summary>A longitudinal UX research method where participants self-record experiences in the moment over days or weeks. Three types: interval-contingent (fixed schedule), event-contingent (on trigger), signal-contingent (random prompt). Cap entry time at 5 minutes; entries exceeding that spike attrition. Recruit 30% over target to absorb 20–40% dropout. Run a 3-day pilot with 2 participants before launch. Lab studies capture a moment; diary studies capture behavior change over time — habit formation, onboarding progression, context switching, churn precursors. These patterns are invisible to any single-session method.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Lab studies capture a moment; diary studies capture behavior change over time — habit formation, onboarding progression, context switching, churn precursors. These patterns are invisible to any single-session method. The 5-minute entry cap and varied prompts are the two most important mechanical controls: drop either and data quality collapses after day 4.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Studying longitudinal behavior: onboarding, habit formation, churn precursors.</item>
        <item>Multi-device or context-switching usage scattered across days.</item>
        <item>Pre-redesign discovery for products with dispersed usage (fitness, journaling, sleep, medication).</item>
        <item>Validating retention drivers — what triggers re-engagement vs. abandonment.</item>
        <item>B2B day-in-the-life research where workflows span weeks.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Quick directional input on a feature — use intercept survey or unmoderated test instead.</item>
        <item>One-time or rare events unlikely to surface within study duration.</item>
        <item>Fully synchronous tasks where in-context observation is more valuable (use contextual inquiry).</item>
        <item>Highly regulated domains where ongoing self-reporting risks PII/PHI leak.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="study-types">
      <p>Three diary study types, selected by the nature of the behavior under study:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Interval-contingent: participants record at fixed times (daily, weekly). Best for: routine behaviors, habit formation, onboarding progression.</item>
        <item>Event-contingent: participants record when a specific event occurs (used the product, experienced a problem). Best for: specific interactions, trigger mapping.</item>
        <item>Signal-contingent: participants record when prompted at random intervals. Best for: capturing natural moments, reducing recall bias. Requires careful timezone handling per participant.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="design-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap entry completion time at 5 minutes. Any entry that takes longer causes attrition spikes after day 4.</statement>
        <rationale>Diary fatigue in interval-contingent studies begins around day 7 and accelerates if entry burden is high. The 5-minute cap is the single most important mechanical control for data quality across the study period.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Vary the prompt text daily. Repeated identical prompts degrade response quality after day 4 as participants learn to minimize effort.</statement>
        <rationale>Participants answer what they expect the prompt to ask, not what it actually asks. Prompt variation forces genuine recall each entry.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Recruit 30% over target to absorb 20–40% dropout over 4 weeks. Pay incentives in tranches (signup, mid-study, exit interview).</statement>
        <rationale>Flat one-shot incentive payment increases dropout once the payment is received. Tranche structure maintains engagement through the full study duration.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Run a 3-day pilot with 2 participants before launching the full study.</statement>
        <rationale>Every logistic bug (broken reminder links, confusing entry fields, wrong timezone, missing consent flow) surfaces in a pilot. Fixing post-launch costs 10x the pilot effort.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="entry-format">
      <p>Each entry should collect: timestamp (auto), location/context (structured options), what happened (open text), outcome rating (1–5 scale), problems or frustrations (open text), optional photo or voice note. Limit to 5 required questions maximum.</p>

      <p>Weekly micro-interviews (15 min per participant) clarify ambiguous entries while context is fresh. Do not accumulate 4 weeks of entries before starting analysis — code incrementally.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="planning-checklist">
      <p>Before launch: research questions defined, study type and duration decided, entry frequency and format designed, capture platform selected, entry template tested by 2 pilots, incentive structure finalized, ethics review completed (can stall weeks — start early), screening criteria defined, consent flow built.</p>

      <p>Recruitment: participants recruited and screened, consent obtained, onboarding session completed, reminder cadence configured, attrition escalation path defined.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running analysis only after all entries are collected (batch analysis at study end).</description>
        <reason>Losing context by waiting too long: late-study entries are analyzed without the pattern visibility that incremental coding provides. Themes from early entries often reframe late-entry meaning.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Signal-contingent prompts sent at fixed UTC times without per-participant timezone localization.</description>
        <reason>Prompts arriving at 2 AM local time get skipped or dashed off. LLMs default to UTC and disrespect local norms — pin to verified participant timezone table.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Uploading photo entries to a cloud LLM before PII redaction.</description>
        <reason>Photo entries often contain inadvertent PII: faces, addresses, documents visible in frame. Redact before any cloud upload. EXIF metadata also contains GPS coordinates.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-translating multi-language entries during analysis.</description>
        <reason>Quote in source language, translate at reporting time only. Auto-translation during analysis changes nuance and destroys the verbatim evidence needed for credibility.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="self-report-bias-controls">
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat participant self-report as directional signal, not metric. Never aggregate sentiment scores from diary entries into a single KPI without human coding validation.</statement>
        <rationale>Self-report bias suppresses negative and embarrassing moments. Participants under-report breakdowns in contexts where they feel observed. Sentiment scoring of self-report is noisy; LLM synthesis can generate patterns absent in sparse longitudinal data.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agents are strong for: scaffolding (study plan, screener, entry templates, reminder cadence), automating follow-up scheduling, clustering and theme extraction from the entry corpus, attrition tracking. Agents are weak for: generating synthetic insights before human-coded baseline (LLMs over-fit to their own clustering), speaker attribution in audio entries, PII detection in images.</p>

      <p>Schedule reminder dispatch via cron or queue, not conversational chat. Diary studies live or die on logistics consistency — an agent that misses a reminder cohort destroys that day's data window.</p>

      <p>Entry coding schema for LLM-assisted analysis: timestamp (ISO8601), location_context (home|work|commute|other), trigger (string or null), outcome (string or null), sentiment (-2 to 2 scale), feature_used (array), breakdown_reported (bool), quote (verbatim or null). Mark uncertain fields as null. Never invent quote text. Output as JSONL, one entry per line.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Self-report bias: participants under-report negative or embarrassing moments. Diary fatigue starts around day 7 in interval-contingent studies; entries collapse to "same as yesterday." Participant attrition is high (20–40% over 4 weeks); recruit 30% over target. Signal-contingent prompts at random times annoy people in meetings; entries get skipped or dashed off. Cross-cultural and translation issues compound across longitudinal entries. Ethics review can stall studies for weeks — not a fast research method.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <note>CLI tools: cron / systemd timer (scheduled prompt dispatch), n8n / temporal (workflow orchestration), pandoc (normalize entries), whisperx (transcribe audio/video entries), taguette (qualitative coding), jq / csvkit (wrangle entry corpora), python-twilio (SMS prompt + ingest).</note>
      <note>Services: dscout (SaaS, REST + export, mobile-native gold standard), Indeemo (SaaS, strong video diary), Revelation (SaaS, enterprise multi-method), Lookback (SaaS, limited for diary), Userbrain / Userlytics (SaaS, lightweight), Typeform / Google Forms + Twilio (DIY, cheapest), Telegram / WhatsApp Business API (high response in SMS-dead regions), Notion / Airtable (DIY data store).</note>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Pilot with 2 participants for 3 days before launch — every logistic bug surfaces here. Cap entry time at 5 minutes; over that, attrition spikes. Vary the prompt — repeated identical prompts degrade response quality after day 4. Use mixed media (text + photo + voice) selectively; photo-only studies miss context, voice-only studies hide breakdowns. Run a weekly micro-interview (15 min) per participant to clarify ambiguous entries while context is fresh. Pay incentives in tranches (signup, mid-study, exit-interview) — flat one-shot payment increases drop-off. Plan analysis incrementally — don't accumulate 4 weeks of entries before starting to code.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/study-plan.md" purpose="Full study plan template: objectives, participants, design, timeline, quality measures."/>
      <template path="templates/entry-daily.md" purpose="Daily diary entry template (context, rating, issues, media)."/>
      <template path="templates/entry-event.md" purpose="Event-contingent entry template (trigger, goal, outcome, sentiment)."/>
      <template path="templates/diary-reminders.py" purpose="Script: emit per-participant reminder schedule with early-study weighting."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/diary-studies/"/>
      <link href="https://dscout.com/people-nerds/diary-studies"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/how-to-conduct-diary-studies"/>
      <link href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
