<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Weekly Cadence Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules for the Sunday-review + Monday-prime weekly cadence used by a one-operator product or practice.</summary>

  <section title="Cadence rules">

    <rule id="r1-two-artifacts-only" testable="true">
      <statement>The cadence produces exactly two artifacts each week: (a) Week Note — a single file with last-week's outcomes, blockers, and learnings; (b) Next-Week Plan — at most five "must-ship" items with a single named "rock" (the one item the week is built around). No third weekly artifact (no weekly newsletter, retro, kanban audit) is added without removing one.</statement>
      <rationale>Artifact creep is the proximate cause of cadence death. Two artifacts survive long-term; five do not.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-four-mandatory-inputs" testable="true">
      <statement>The Sunday review MUST scan exactly four inputs in this order: (1) last-week's Next-Week Plan (what was checked off vs. carried), (2) the KPI dashboard (metric movements), (3) the inbox / support queue (themes, not item-by-item), (4) the open-loops list (commitments to others that aged a week). Skipping an input or adding a fifth breaks the cadence.</statement>
      <rationale>A fixed input scan prevents the review from collapsing into "whatever felt important on Sunday". The fourth input (open loops) is the one solo operators systematically drop, with reputational consequences.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-memory-hook-required" testable="true">
      <statement>Each Week Note ends with one explicit memory-hook line that ties this week to a prior week's decision or pattern (e.g., "the activation drop matches week 12's cohort"). The hook references the date or week number of the prior note. Notes without a memory hook are flagged.</statement>
      <rationale>Solo operators chronically re-discover patterns they already saw 6 months ago. The memory hook converts a sequence of weekly notes into a navigable history.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-60-min-time-box" testable="true">
      <statement>Total time spent on the cadence is capped at 60 minutes: 30 minutes Sunday (review + Next-Week Plan draft) plus 30 minutes Monday morning (prime — block calendar, confirm rock, set first deep-work session). Running long is a defect; the response is to cut review depth, not to extend the slot.</statement>
      <rationale>Variable-length rituals get skipped. A fixed time-box that fits between Sunday evening tasks and Monday morning calendar is survivable for years.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-catchup-restart" testable="true">
      <statement>If the cadence is skipped 3 weeks in a row, the operator restarts FRESH with the current week, NOT by attempting to write three retrospective Week Notes. The first restart Week Note explicitly logs the skip ("3 weeks dark; restart 2026-05-19; reasons: ...") and the cadence resumes.</statement>
      <rationale>"Catch-up" attempts collapse motivation and produce low-quality reconstructed notes that pollute the memory log. A clean restart preserves the cadence as a sustainable habit.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Week 2026-W20 (Sun review 2026-05-17, 28 min)

### Last-week shipped
- Activation email v2 [shipped]
- Stripe webhook hardening [carried — moved to W21]
- Pricing page rewrite [shipped]
- Support ticket triage [skipped]

### Inputs scanned (4/4)
- Plan: 2/4 shipped, 1 carried, 1 skipped (support)
- KPI: signups flat, activation +6pp, MRR +$240
- Inbox: 3 tickets all on the same export bug
- Open loops: contract review from Sam (aged 9 days — chase Monday)

### Next week (W21) rock + plan
ROCK: ship the export-bug fix (3 tickets pile-up + a paid-tier blocker)
- Export bug fix + post-mortem note
- Stripe webhook hardening (carried)
- Support triage block (60 min, time-boxed)
- Chase Sam re contract
- ... (max 5)

### Memory hook
Activation +6pp this week tracks the W18 cohort hypothesis ("dropping the 2nd
onboarding slide will lift d1→d7"). Confirmed.
]]></code>
    <note>Two artifacts (week note + plan), four inputs scanned, memory hook to W18, under the 30-min Sunday budget, single rock named.</note>
  </example>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Operator skips 5 weeks, then on Sunday writes "weeks 16-20 in one go", spends 3 hours doing it, never opens the file again.</description>
    <reason>Violates r4 (time-box) and r5 (catch-up). Cadence health is permanently damaged because the operator now associates the ritual with a 3-hour guilt session.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
