<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-workspace-setup" title="Linear Workspace and Team Configuration">
  <summary>Team configuration, issue properties, cycle workflow, project and roadmap setup for engineering teams.</summary>

  <section title="Team Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure each team with: key prefix (e.g., BAK), workflow states (Backlog/Todo/In Progress/In Review/Done/Canceled), Fibonacci estimate scale (0/1/2/3/5/8/13), and triage enabled.</statement>
      <rationale>Team key prefixes make issue identifiers human-readable across multi-team workspaces (BAK-123 vs FE-456); Fibonacci scale prevents false precision in estimates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set cycle duration to 2 weeks, start day Monday, auto-archive enabled — cycles provide time-boxing without requiring manual sprint management.</statement>
      <rationale>Linear cycles auto-advance and archive completed issues; manual sprint management adds overhead that Linear's opinionated workflow is designed to eliminate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Issue Properties">
    <rule>
      <statement>Required issue properties: Status, Priority (Urgent/High/Medium/Low/No Priority), Estimate (Fibonacci), Cycle, Project, Label, Assignee. Priority is an integer enum (Urgent=1, High=2, Medium=3, Low=4, NoPriority=0) in the API — not a string.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents receiving natural-language priority must map explicitly to integers before calling the API; passing strings causes silent mutation failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cycle Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cycle scope must be frozen after Day 2 of the cycle; API-driven cycle assignment must target nextCycle or futureCycle only — never the active cycle.</statement>
      <rationale>Mid-cycle additions disrupt velocity tracking and flow; agents that auto-add issues to active cycles create scope creep without human intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cycle IDs rotate every cycle; always resolve the current cycle by querying team.activeCycle — never hardcode a cycle ID in agent configuration.</statement>
      <rationale>Hardcoded cycle IDs break every 2 weeks when the cycle advances; dynamic resolution via activeCycle query is always correct.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Projects and Roadmap">
    <rule>
      <statement>Projects span multiple cycles and represent initiatives; use milestones within projects to mark key deliverables with target dates.</statement>
      <rationale>Cycles are time-boxes; projects are outcome-scopes. Mixing them confuses velocity (cycle) with delivery (project completion).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
