<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-workflow" title="Linear Workflow: Triage, GitHub Integration, Views">
  <summary>Triage process, GitHub sync configuration, custom view patterns, and keyboard shortcut usage.</summary>

  <section title="Triage Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Process triage in this order: valid? → urgent? → scoped? → ready for backlog. Invalid issues go to Closed/Duplicate immediately; unscoped issues get "Needs Refinement" label and stay in triage.</statement>
      <rationale>Triage order prevents time spent scoping issues that should be closed; "Needs Refinement" creates a visible queue for refinement sessions without cluttering the backlog.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Triage is a human-only step; agents must not auto-close or auto-route issues from the triage inbox without a human checkpoint.</statement>
      <rationale>Triage decisions require context that agents cannot infer from issue text alone (duplicate detection, organizational priority, business context).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="GitHub Integration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure GitHub integration: branch format "{username}/bak-{issue_number}-{issue_title}", PR-opened → "In Review", PR-merged → "Done", commit pattern "Fixes BAK-\\d+".</statement>
      <rationale>Consistent branch naming enables bidirectional traceability; fix commit pattern auto-links PRs to issues; auto-transitions eliminate manual status updates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store issue identifiers (e.g., BAK-123) in git branch names and PR titles to enable bidirectional traceability between Linear issues and GitHub PRs.</statement>
      <rationale>Linear's GitHub integration matches PRs to issues by identifier in branch name or PR title; without this, no automatic status transitions occur.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Views">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create four standard views: my_work (assignee:me, group by priority), team_board (team filter, group by status, show estimates), bugs_triage (label:bug, status:triage, sort by created date), release_scope (project filter, status:-canceled).</statement>
      <rationale>These four views cover the four daily PM workflows: individual task focus, team coordination, bug queue, and release tracking — without proliferating context-specific views.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use issueSearch with server-side filters rather than fetching issues and filtering client-side — server-side filtering is 10x faster on large workspaces.</statement>
      <rationale>Client-side filtering on 5000+ issues requires fetching all pages then discarding most results; server-side filters push this work to Linear's query engine.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
