<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-concepts" title="Core Statistical Concepts for A/B Testing">
  <summary>Null hypothesis, p-value, alpha, power, confidence intervals, and the Type I/II error trade-off.</summary>

  <section title="Hypothesis Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>State H0 (no difference) and H1 (difference exists) before collecting any data.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc hypothesis selection inflates false positive rates; the null hypothesis is the default claim the test must disprove.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>H0: conversion_rate_A = conversion_rate_B; H1: conversion_rate_A != conversion_rate_B (two-tailed)</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="P-value and Alpha">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set alpha = 0.05 before launch; reject H0 only when p-value is strictly less than alpha.</statement>
      <rationale>Alpha defines acceptable false positive rate. p-value is the probability of seeing this result (or more extreme) if H0 were true — not the probability that B is better.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>p &lt; 0.01: strong evidence of difference</item>
      <item>0.01 &lt;= p &lt; 0.05: moderate evidence</item>
      <item>0.05 &lt;= p &lt; 0.10: weak evidence, collect more data</item>
      <item>p &gt;= 0.10: insufficient evidence to reject H0</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Statistical Power">
    <rule>
      <statement>Target 80% power; calculate required sample size from baseline rate, MDE, alpha, and power before starting.</statement>
      <rationale>80% power means a 20% chance of missing a real effect (Type II error). Running underpowered tests wastes traffic and produces untrustworthy null results.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Running with 500 per variant when 57,600 are needed gives ~6% power — essentially useless for detecting a 0.5% absolute lift from 10% baseline.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Confidence Intervals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Report the 95% CI for the difference alongside p-value; do not ship a result where the CI lower bound is economically irrelevant.</statement>
      <rationale>A significant p-value with CI [0.01%, 4%] is statistically real but the lower bound may not justify shipping costs. CI width reflects data quantity — wider = need more data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Conversion A=5.0%, B=5.8%, difference=+0.8%, 95% CI=[0.2%, 1.4%] — zero not in interval, significant and economically meaningful.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Error Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Alpha controls Type I error (false positive); power controls Type II error (false negative) — tune both for the business cost of each mistake.</statement>
      <rationale>Shipping a bad change (Type I) is costly in high-traffic funnels. Missing a real improvement (Type II) is costly when testing is expensive. High-stakes tests warrant alpha=0.01 or power=90%.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Bayesian vs Frequentist">
    <p>Frequentist p-values say "if H0 is true, how likely is this data?" Bayesian posteriors say "given this data, how likely is B better?" For teams that want intuitive probability statements, Bayesian A/B testing is a valid alternative but requires prior assumptions.</p>
  </section>
</text>
