<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="statistics-basics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for statistics-basics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Peeking at results and stopping early when the desired direction appears.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each early look inflates the cumulative false positive rate above alpha. A test peeked 5 times at p=0.05 has a true false positive rate near 19%.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using one-tailed tests by default to get lower p-values.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>One-tailed tests assume you would never ship the variant if it regressed. This is rarely true and halves the threshold, doubling false positives in the expected direction.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Stopping the test as soon as p &lt; 0.05, regardless of pre-registered sample size.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>P-values fluctuate during data collection. The test is only valid at the pre-registered sample size or end date — not at any earlier random crossing of alpha.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Testing 10 metrics and reporting the one that reached significance.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multiple comparisons: with 10 independent tests at alpha=0.05, expected false positives = 0.5. Apply Bonferroni correction (alpha/k) or designate one primary metric before launch.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating "not significant" as proof that there is no effect.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Absence of evidence is not evidence of absence. A non-significant result in an underpowered test is uninformative. Say "insufficient evidence" not "no effect".</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring practical significance when statistical significance is achieved.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A +0.01% lift can be statistically significant at N=10M but economically irrelevant. Always check whether the CI lower bound justifies shipping cost and ongoing maintenance.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
