<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-bootstrap-pipeline" title="Project Bootstrap Pipeline">
  <summary>Seven-phase pipeline from idea to TASK_000, with mandatory Phase 4 user confirmation and the output artifact structure under .aidocs/.</summary>

  <section title="Pipeline Phases">
    <p>Phase sequence: 1. Vision Brainstorm (Five Whys to real need) → 2. Tech Stack Selection (frontend, backend, database) → 3. MVP Definition (max 3-5 features, cut 50% nice-to-haves) → 4. User Confirmation (MANDATORY — present summary, get explicit approval) → 5. Backlog Creation (feature specs with FR/AC) → 6. Constitution (write project constitution) → 7. TASK_000 (setup task with project goals).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Output Structure">
    <p>Bootstrap produces: .aidocs/constitution.md, .aidocs/roadmap.md, .aidocs/features/backlog/{NN}-{feature}/spec.md (max 5 features), .aidocs/features/00-setup/tasks/todo/TASK_000_project_setup.md.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 4 Confirmation Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Phase 4 user confirmation cannot be skipped or simulated — the bootstrap pipeline must hard-fail with NEEDS-HUMAN if no explicit approval token is received.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs eager to complete will simulate user approval; bootstrap must detect non-interactive mode and exit rather than invent answers. An unsigned constitution is not a constitution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Bootstrap must detect non-interactive mode (cron, CI) and exit with FAIL needs-human; do not invent answers.</statement>
      <rationale>The AskUserQuestion step blocks in non-interactive runs; an agent that invents user approval produces a constitution nobody agreed to, corrupting the entire project record.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Backlog Creation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every spec must have a RICE row (reach/impact/confidence/effort frontmatter) before leaving backlog; reject specs without RICE at grooming time.</statement>
      <rationale>Unscored backlog items cannot be prioritized; RICE without frontmatter is invisible to the rice-reorder script and the sprint kickoff agent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Agents must refuse to invent features not present in the idea-validation or competitive-analysis inputs.</statement>
      <rationale>MLP hallucination — inventing WOW features without competitor evidence — is the most common failure mode; the PM's job is to make evidence the precondition, not the review step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/rice-reorder.sh">RICE-sort the backlog and write a ranked INDEX.md</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Numbering Lock">
    <rule>
      <statement>When two PM agents may run concurrently, take a flock on .aidocs/.numbering.lock before assigning the next feature number or task number.</statement>
      <rationale>Concurrent agents assigning {NN} without a lock create numbering collisions that break spec filenames and all downstream references.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
