<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Product Manager Workflows Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Product Manager Workflows plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="phase-4-confirmation-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Bootstrap Phase 4 user confirmation MUST be explicit; LLMs MUST NOT simulate user approval — hard-fail with NEEDS-HUMAN if no approval token is received.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — PM workflow audit Q1 2026">An unsigned constitution is not a constitution. LLMs eager to complete will invent answers; bootstrap must detect non-interactive mode and exit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rice-required-before-leaving-backlog" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every spec MUST carry a RICE row (reach/impact/confidence/effort) in frontmatter before leaving backlog; grooming MUST reject specs without RICE.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reforge — PM Operating Model">Unscored backlog items cannot be prioritised; the rice-reorder script and sprint kickoff agent ignore items without frontmatter RICE.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-invented-features" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agents MUST refuse to invent MLP WOW features not grounded in mvp-scope-analysis.md or competitive-analysis.md; speculative features MUST land under 'Deferred — needs validation'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion-mlp-agent evals 2026-Q1">MLP hallucination — proposing WOW features without competitor evidence — is the primary observed failure mode of faion-mlp-agent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="numbering-lock-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Concurrent PM agents MUST take a flock on .aidocs/.numbering.lock before assigning the next feature {NN} or TASK_{NNN}.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — sprint kickoff incident 2026-03">Numbering collisions break spec filenames and all downstream tracker references; lockless concurrent assignment is the root cause of seen FR-NN duplicates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="aidocs-is-source-of-truth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>.aidocs/features/ MUST be the planning source of truth; Jira/Linear MUST be treated as an execution mirror — never the reverse.</statement>
      <rationale source="Marty Cagan — Inspired (SVPG 2017)">Tracker tickets get deleted or migrated; the .aidocs/ tree has git history. Making tracker authoritative loses history when tickets are deleted.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="mlp-modes-sequential" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The five faion-mlp-agent modes MUST run strictly in sequence: analyze → find-gaps → propose → update → plan; each mode persists its artefact so a failed run resumes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion-mlp-agent design notes">Running propose before analyze produces WOW features ungrounded in competitor evidence; sequencing is the gate that prevents speculation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
