<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-mlp-planning" title="MLP Planning Workflow">
  <summary>Five-mode sequential MLP pipeline that transforms a shipped MVP into a Most Lovable Product, with constraints on WOW feature grounding and a cap of 7 WOW items.</summary>

  <section title="MLP Five-Mode Sequence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the five faion-mlp-agent modes strictly in sequence: analyze → find-gaps → propose → update → plan. Each mode persists its artifact so a failed run can resume from the last completed mode.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping modes — especially running propose before analyze — produces WOW features ungrounded in competitor evidence, which is the primary MLP failure mode.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Output artifacts: product_docs/mvp-scope-analysis.md (analyze), product_docs/mlp-analysis-report.md (find-gaps), product_docs/mlp-implementation-order.md (plan). Each file is the input to the next mode.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="WOW Feature Constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every WOW feature must cite a row in mvp-scope-analysis.md; features with no competitor evidence are labeled "speculative" and placed under "Deferred — needs validation".</statement>
      <rationale>Speculative WOW features not grounded in competitor evidence or customer data are guesses; they belong in the deferred bucket, not the MLP roadmap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap WOW features at 7; more than 7 and the MLP becomes a v2.0 plan, not an MLP.</statement>
      <rationale>MLP is the minimum set of WOW features that makes users love the product — a superset of MVP but not a full feature rebuild. Empirically, 8+ WOW features require a second release cycle to ship.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run MLP propose only after the MVP ships and produces real telemetry; propose-without-data is the primary failure mode the workflow does not warn about in its README.</statement>
      <rationale>WOW feature selection without usage data is marketing speculation; the propose mode needs to know which MVP features users actually used before proposing enhancements.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="MLP Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>MLP "update" mode rewrites spec files in-place on retry, clobbering FR numbering.</description>
      <reason>Always run git status before and after update mode; agents on retry have been observed overwriting FR-NN.N numbering with duplicates. Use the artifact files as checkpoints, not as editable scratch space.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running the full MLP pipeline from cron when the product is still in MVP phase with no telemetry.</description>
      <reason>MLP propose generates fictional WOW features when there is no usage data; the cron trigger must check for the existence of a telemetry artifact before running.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
