<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules">
  <rule id="r1" testable="true">The cascade is one page per team containing exactly 5 sections: company OBJECTIVE the team supports, the company KR(s) this team moves, team OBJECTIVE, team KRs (3-5, each with baseline + target + measure source), and contribution map (role → owned KR + secondary KRs they consult on); missing any section invalidates the cascade.</rule>
  <rule id="r2" testable="true">Each team KR must have an explicit "moves company KR X by Y" line; if the contribution to a company KR cannot be quantified or estimated within a band, the team KR is rejected — vanity KRs are forbidden in the cascade.</rule>
  <rule id="r3" testable="true">Declare every cross-team dependency in a "depends-on" block listing the upstream team, the artifact required, and the latest-acceptable date; dependencies missing dates trigger an immediate sync with the upstream team owner before the OKR is locked.</rule>
  <rule id="r4" testable="true">Run alignment review with company leadership before quarter start: each team OKR is presented in ≤5 minutes, leadership confirms the link to a company KR or rejects; no team enters the quarter without alignment sign-off.</rule>
  <rule id="r5" testable="true">Cascade is reviewed bi-weekly: KR progress (% of target), risk colour (green/amber/red), dependency status; red-amber rows for >2 reviews trigger a written re-plan, not silent drift to next quarter.</rule>
  <rule id="r6" testable="true">Mid-quarter changes to KR targets are tracked in a changelog and require sign-off from the contributing teams whose dependencies are affected; un-versioned target edits are forbidden — they hide accountability.</rule>
  <rule id="r7" testable="true">At quarter end, every team KR gets a 0.0-1.0 score and a written "what we learned" line (≤1 sentence); learnings feed the next quarter's cascade — without it the cascade is theatre.</rule>
  <example>P6 team "Growth-Pod" (9 people, PM + 4 eng + 2 design + 2 data) cascades to company OKR "Increase Activation". Team OBJ: "Make first-week activation feel inevitable." Team KRs: (1) D7-activation 41%→52% (moves company KR by ~3pp), (2) Onboarding completion 71%→85%, (3) Time-to-first-value 11min→4min. Depends-on: Auth-team (passwordless flow by week 5), Data-pipe (event schema by week 2). Contribution map: PM owns KR1, EM owns KR2, design lead owns KR3, data owns measurement source. Bi-weekly review: KR1 amber at week 6 due to Auth-team slip → re-plan logged.</example>
</text>
