<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="technical-debt-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-operations</domain>
    <summary>Make debt visible, quantify interest cost, prioritize paydown against roadmap. Allocate 15-20% sprint capacity. Score on Interest/Contagion/Effort/Alignment.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>technical-debt</tag>
      <tag>refactoring</tag>
      <tag>code-quality</tag>
      <tag>sprint-planning</tag>
      <tag>engineering-velocity</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Technical Debt Management</title>

    <summary>Systematic process for making technical debt visible, quantifying its interest cost, prioritizing paydown against the roadmap, and allocating 15-20% of sprint capacity continuously. Classifies debt into 6 types (deliberate, accidental, bit-rot, design, documentation, test), scores each on Interest/Contagion/Effort/Alignment, and sequences paydown aligned with planned feature work to minimize marginal cost.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Technical debt is invisible to non-technical stakeholders and never systematically addressed until it causes a crisis. The interest metaphor makes the cost concrete: debt slows delivery by a measurable fraction of sprint velocity, compounds over time, and blocks future features. Making it visible with a register and quantifying it in dev-days-per-quarter creates the business case needed to allocate capacity consistently.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Codebase has aging dependencies, fragmented patterns, and "fear zones" engineers avoid.</item>
        <item>Onboarding: agent surveys repo for hot-spots and surfaces undocumented assumptions.</item>
        <item>Quarterly debt-paydown planning: scoring and sequencing the register against upcoming roadmap.</item>
        <item>Pre-acquisition or pre-investment due diligence: producing defensible debt inventory.</item>
        <item>Migration planning (lib upgrade, framework jump, monolith decomposition).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>One-person codebase under 6 months old — debt is rounding error, ship features.</item>
        <item>Debt that is actually a missing feature — do not classify "we never built X" as "we built X badly".</item>
        <item>Production incident response — debt management is a planning activity, not firefighting.</item>
        <item>Code-quality theater — do not run an agent to generate a debt list nobody will fund.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="debt-types">
      <list>
        <item>Deliberate — conscious shortcut: "Ship now, refactor later"</item>
        <item>Accidental — learned better way after the fact: "Didn't know about X pattern"</item>
        <item>Bit-rot — environment changed: dependencies outdated, platform APIs deprecated</item>
        <item>Design — architecture limitations: "Can't scale current approach"</item>
        <item>Documentation — missing docs: "No one knows how this works"</item>
        <item>Test — missing tests: "Can't safely change X without coverage"</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Distinguish Prudent Deliberate debt (conscious shortcut with plan to fix) from Reckless debt (no design awareness). Only prudent debt is acceptable.</statement>
        <rationale>Reckless debt — "no time for design" or "what's a design?" — compounds without a paydown trigger. Prudent deliberate debt has a known cost and a plan.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Test debt is not optional: untested code cannot be safely refactored. Prioritize test debt before structural refactoring.</statement>
        <rationale>Refactoring untested code produces regressions that are invisible until production. Tests are the safety net that makes all other paydown possible.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="scoring-formula">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Score each debt item on four factors (1-5 each): Interest (how much it slows velocity), Contagion (does it spread?), Effort (cost to fix), Alignment (proximity to planned work). Priority = (Interest x Alignment) / Effort.</statement>
        <rationale>Interest × Alignment / Effort identifies debt that is hurting us now AND can be fixed cheaply because we're already touching that code. This is the lowest marginal-cost paydown strategy.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent scoring style/lint issues as "design debt".</description>
        <reason>Style and formatting are cosmetic, not structural. Inflating the register with cosmetic items buries real debt. Apply a severity rubric and reject purely stylistic signals at the classification stage.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using LLM-generated time estimates ("2 days") without team calibration.</description>
        <reason>LLM effort estimates for debt paydown are confabulation; actual work is 5-10x more. Calibrate from past resolved-debt items in the register.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="capacity-allocation">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Allocate 15-20% of sprint capacity continuously to debt paydown rather than saving it for "debt sprints".</statement>
        <rationale>Debt sprints allow debt to re-accumulate between them. Sustained 15-20% allocation keeps the interest rate stable and builds the habit.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Dedicated % (recommended) — 15-20% of each sprint, continuous</item>
        <item>Boy Scout — clean as you touch, 30-min cap per PR to prevent scope creep</item>
        <item>Debt sprints — quarterly focused sprint, only for large architectural work</item>
        <item>Spike — specific investigation of an unknown, before adding to register</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="process-steps">
      <list>
        <item>Step 1: Make visible — tag items in tracker, keep a register, add code comments (TODO/FIXME with ticket links)</item>
        <item>Step 2: Quantify — measure time tax (dev-days slowed per quarter), risk (what could break), opportunity cost (what features are blocked)</item>
        <item>Step 3: Prioritize — score on Interest/Contagion/Effort/Alignment, rank</item>
        <item>Step 4: Allocate — 15-20% continuous + quarterly focused time for architectural work</item>
        <item>Step 5: Pay down strategically — fix during related feature work, fix highest-interest first, fix blocking debt first</item>
        <item>Step 6: Prevent new debt — Definition of Done includes "no new debt added", code review catches it</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Make debt visible with money, not adjectives: "this costs 6 dev-days per quarter" beats "this is bad code".</statement>
        <rationale>Non-technical stakeholders cannot prioritize "bad code" against features. Quantified business impact creates the case for allocation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every new reckless debt item added to the register must link to an Architectural Decision Record explaining why it was accepted.</statement>
        <rationale>Debt without a decision record has no paydown trigger. ADR creates accountability and makes the cost explicit to whoever incurred it.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-pipeline">
      <list>
        <item>repo-surveyor (sonnet) — runs static analysis tools, assembles raw signals (churn, complexity, TODOs, stale deps)</item>
        <item>debt-classifier (sonnet) — reviews signals + PR comments, classifies into 6 types, scores 4 factors</item>
        <item>debt-prioritizer (opus, quarterly) — intersects scored register with roadmap, proposes paydown sequence</item>
        <item>boy-scout-reviewer (haiku, per-PR) — inline cleanup suggestions with 30-min scope cap</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Apply debt paydown changes via PR; never auto-merge debt-paydown commits.</statement>
        <rationale>Debt fixes change production behavior. Auto-merged paydown bypasses review and can introduce regressions or break consumers of refactored APIs.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent proposing big-bang rewrites as the "fix approach" for debt items.</description>
        <reason>LLMs bias toward rewrites. Prompt constraint: minimal local change, avoid diffs over 20 lines without explicit justification.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent auto-upgrading dependencies with semver-major version bumps.</description>
        <reason>Breaking changes in major upgrades require consumer testing. Route to humans and require breaking-change detection before any major upgrade is applied.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="human-in-loop-checkpoints">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Paydown capacity allocation (the % of sprint dedicated to debt) is engineering-leadership territory. Agents propose; humans approve.</statement>
        <rationale>Changing the allocation ratio affects feature velocity visible to stakeholders. It requires trade-off authority that agents do not have.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <list>
        <item>scc / tokei — LOC + complexity counts</item>
        <item>radon (Python) — Cyclomatic, maintainability metrics</item>
        <item>lizard — Multi-language complexity analysis</item>
        <item>semgrep — Pattern + security findings</item>
        <item>dependency-cruiser (JS) — Import graph, cycle detection</item>
        <item>pydeps (Python) — Module graph analysis</item>
        <item>pip-audit / npm audit / osv-scanner — Dependency vulnerability + outdated checks</item>
        <item>git-of-theseus — Code aging analysis</item>
        <item>code-maat — Hot-spot mining via git history</item>
        <item>SonarQube / SonarCloud — Severity-graded findings; CI integration</item>
        <item>CodeScene — Hot-spot + behavioral analysis</item>
        <item>Codacy / Code Climate — Multi-language quality grades</item>
        <item>Snyk / Dependabot / Renovate — Bot-driven dependency upgrades</item>
        <item>Trunk.io — Aggregates linters; agent-friendly artifacts</item>
        <item>GitHub Code Scanning — Free for OSS; agent reads JSON output</item>
        <item>Stepsize — Debt tracking integrated with Jira/Linear/GitHub</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="common-ai-agent-failures">
      <p>Agents love rewrites; bias toward big-bang refactors which are wrong. Prompt: "minimal local change; avoid >20-line diffs without reason". Style nits flagged as "design debt" inflate the register. Filter at signal stage. Generated "fix approaches" hallucinate APIs/libraries. Verify with build. Cyclomatic complexity is not always debt — sometimes inherent. Force comparison vs team baseline. Estimates are confabulation: agent says "2 days"; actual is 2 weeks. Calibrate via past resolved items.</p>
      <p>Dependency upgrade auto-merges break consumers; route to humans and require breaking-change detection. Long-context whole-repo scans cost compute; tier the analysis (cheap signals → mid → deep dive only on top-20 hot files). Agents conflate "old code" with "bad code"; old + working + low-churn = leave alone.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Make debt visible with money, not adjectives: "this slows us 6 dev-days/quarter" beats "this is bad code".</item>
        <item>Pay down where you're already touching: lowest marginal cost. Pair debt items with feature work.</item>
        <item>Boy-scout rule with limits: 30-min cap per PR; agent flags scope creep.</item>
        <item>15-20% sustained allocation > debt sprints: sprint approach lets debt re-accumulate between them.</item>
        <item>Track trend, not absolute: total debt count is meaningless; high-interest count + interest trend matter.</item>
        <item>Reckless debt requires architectural decision record (ADR): agent should refuse to file new debt without an ADR link.</item>
        <item>Test debt isn't optional: untested code can't be refactored safely; prioritize test debt before structural.</item>
        <item>Bit-rot has a clock: dependency upgrades compound — Renovate/Dependabot weekly.</item>
        <item>Don't refactor working code without a reason: agent must tie every refactor to a feature/bug/risk.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs love rewrites; bias toward big-bang refactors which are exactly the wrong move. Prompt: "minimal local change; avoid >20-line diffs without reason".</item>
        <item>Style nits flagged as "design debt" inflate the register. Filter at signal stage, not rationalization stage.</item>
        <item>Generated "fix approaches" routinely hallucinate APIs/libraries. Verify with build before committing.</item>
        <item>Cyclomatic complexity ≠ debt — sometimes inherent. Force comparison vs. team baseline.</item>
        <item>Estimates are confabulation: agent says "2 days"; actual is 2 weeks. Calibrate via past resolved-debt items.</item>
        <item>Dependency upgrade auto-merges break consumers; pin "breaking change" detection (semver-major) and route to humans.</item>
        <item>Long-context whole-repo scans cost compute; tier the analysis (cheap signals → mid → deep dive only on top-20 hot files).</item>
        <item>Agents conflate "old code" with "bad code"; old + working + low-churn = leave alone.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/debt-register.md" purpose="Per-item register: type, location, description, impact (time tax + risk), fix effort, priority, related work."/>
      <template path="templates/debt-prioritization-matrix.md" purpose="Quarterly scoring table with Interest/Contagion/Effort/Alignment columns, sprint plan, and deferred list."/>
      <template path="templates/sprint-debt-budget.md" purpose="Sprint-level debt work log: budget, items, effort, owners, outcomes."/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/debt-survey.sh" purpose="Quarterly repo survey: git churn, radon complexity, TODO/FIXME, outdated deps, coverage gaps → feeds debt-classifier agent."/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://github.com/adamtornhill/code-maat"/>
      <link href="https://codescene.io/"/>
      <link href="https://www.sonarqube.org/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
