<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Negotiation and Persuasion Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding negotiation. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="batna-computed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prep brief MUST contain a concrete BATNA (named alternative + its value). 'I'll walk away' is not a BATNA.</statement>
      <rationale source="Fisher &amp; Ury — Getting to Yes">Without a concrete BATNA the author negotiates from fear, not options.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="zopa-checked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prep brief MUST estimate the ZOPA (zone of possible agreement) by overlapping each party's reserve point. If ZOPA is negative, the deal is impossible — change scope or walk.</statement>
      <rationale source="Fisher &amp; Ury — Getting to Yes">Negotiating without ZOPA estimation wastes both parties' time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="interests-not-positions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Brief MUST map interests (the why) for both parties separately from positions (the what). Positions-only briefs miss creative options.</statement>
      <rationale source="Fisher &amp; Ury — Getting to Yes">Positions are zero-sum by construction; interests often allow mutual-gain bundling.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="objective-criteria" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Brief MUST cite objective criteria (market rate, third-party benchmark, prior agreement) for each term. 'Because I want it' is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Fisher &amp; Ury — Getting to Yes">Objective criteria anchor the conversation in shared facts; without them it devolves into willpower contest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cialdini-honest" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Persuasion levers (reciprocity, commitment, social proof, authority, liking, scarcity) MUST be tagged honestly. Manipulative use (fake scarcity, fake authority) is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Robert Cialdini — Influence">Manipulative use destroys trust on detection; honest use surfaces real reasons to agree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
