<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="product-discovery">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Time-boxed process (1–4 weeks) for de-risking an idea before committing build resources, testing value, usability, feasibility, and business viability risks.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>product-discovery</tag>
      <tag>risk-framework</tag>
      <tag>experiments</tag>
      <tag>validation</tag>
      <tag>product-management</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Product Discovery</title>
    <summary>Product discovery is a time-boxed process (1–4 weeks) for de-risking an idea before committing build resources. It tests four risk types — value (will customers buy/use it?), usability (can they figure it out?), feasibility (can we build it?), and business viability (does it work for the business?) — using the cheapest technique that gives sufficient confidence at each stage.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Teams that skip discovery build features nobody wants. Marty Cagan's research shows that roughly half of features shipped by product teams deliver zero measurable value — not because of poor execution but because the wrong things were built. Discovery is cheap compared to the engineering cost of a feature that fails post-launch.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-build validation of any significant feature or product idea.</item>
        <item>High-risk assumptions that would kill the idea if wrong (value risk, feasibility risk).</item>
        <item>Before committing to a 4+ week development effort.</item>
        <item>When the team disagrees on whether users actually have the problem being solved.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Tiny bug fixes or incremental improvements with known user impact — just ship.</item>
        <item>Compliance or security requirements with no alternative — no discovery needed, build it.</item>
        <item>Post-PMF continuous learning — use continuous-discovery instead (recurring cadence vs one-time deep dive).</item>
        <item>Discovery that would take longer than the build itself — run a spike instead.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="risk-framework">
      <rule>
        <statement>Test risks in this order of priority: value risk first, then usability, then feasibility, then business viability. Kill ideas early on value risk before spending on later-stage tests.</statement>
        <rationale>Value risk is the most common and cheapest to test. Building a technically feasible, usable product that nobody wants is the most expensive failure mode in product development.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Allocate 20–30% of team capacity to discovery. Never skip to delivery without addressing the highest-risk assumption.</statement>
        <rationale>The cost of a failed feature is the engineering time plus the opportunity cost of what was not built instead. 20% discovery investment that prevents one failed 6-week feature pays for itself many times over.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="value-risk-techniques">
      <list>
        <item>Customer interviews — low effort, medium confidence — use for early-stage ideas</item>
        <item>Fake door test (link to feature that does not exist yet) — low effort, medium confidence — use for testing demand</item>
        <item>Landing page with signup — low effort, medium confidence — use for market interest</item>
        <item>Concierge MVP (deliver value manually) — medium effort, high confidence — use for service-based products</item>
        <item>Wizard of Oz (fake automation) — medium effort, high confidence — use for complex features</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="usability-risk-techniques">
      <list>
        <item>Paper prototypes — low effort, low confidence — use for early concept validation</item>
        <item>Clickable prototypes — medium effort, medium confidence — use for flow validation</item>
        <item>Usability testing with 5 users — medium effort, high confidence — use for design validation</item>
        <item>A/B testing — high effort, very high confidence — use for optimization, not validation</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="feasibility-risk-techniques">
      <list>
        <item>Technical spike (1–2 days) — low effort, high confidence — use for unknown tech</item>
        <item>Architecture review — low effort, medium confidence — use for system impact assessment</item>
        <item>Proof of concept — medium effort, high confidence — use for critical path features</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="business-viability-techniques">
      <list>
        <item>Financial modeling — low effort, medium confidence — use for revenue impact</item>
        <item>Competitive analysis — low effort, medium confidence — use for market fit</item>
        <item>Pilot program — high effort, very high confidence — use only for major investments</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="process-step-1-identify-assumptions">
      <rule>
        <statement>List every assumption the idea depends on before choosing a technique. Categorize each by risk type (value/usability/feasibility/business) and risk level (high/medium/low).</statement>
        <rationale>Undiscovered assumptions are the primary source of post-launch surprises. An explicit assumption list makes the team agree on what they are betting on before committing resources.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="process-step-2-prioritize-risks">
      <rule>
        <statement>Focus discovery on assumptions that are both high-risk AND easy to test. High-risk and hard-to-test assumptions need a spike or POC first to reduce uncertainty before running user experiments.</statement>
        <rationale>Testing low-risk assumptions wastes discovery budget. An assumption that is easy to test but low-risk should be accepted as true and built on, not tested.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="process-step-3-design-experiments">
      <rule>
        <statement>For each experiment, write the hypothesis as: "If we do X, we expect Y in Z% of [user segment]." Define success criteria before running the experiment.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-hoc success criteria are subject to confirmation bias. Defining them before running eliminates the temptation to reinterpret results.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="process-step-4-timebox">
      <rule>
        <statement>Timebox discovery to 1–4 weeks. Discovery that takes longer than the build it is meant to de-risk has inverted the cost equation.</statement>
        <rationale>Endless discovery is a form of avoidance. A 4-week discovery timebox forces prioritization to the highest-risk assumptions and prevents "let's just do one more interview."</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="process-step-5-decide">
      <rule>
        <statement>After experiments: if all critical risks are addressed, proceed to delivery. If a critical risk is invalidated, pivot or kill. If results are unclear, run one more targeted experiment — not another full discovery cycle.</statement>
        <rationale>The decision categories prevent the most common discovery failure: inconclusive results that produce neither a green light nor a kill signal, leaving the team stuck.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="example-ai-writing-assistant">
      <example type="good">
        <note>4 assumptions tested across value, feasibility, and business risk. Decision: proceed with MVP after full validation.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Opportunity: AI-powered writing assistant

Assumptions tested:
| Assumption | Risk Type | Test | Result |
|------------|-----------|------|--------|
| Users struggle with writing | Value | 10 customer interviews | Validated (8/10 confirmed problem) |
| Users would use AI for help | Value | Fake door test (banner link) | 15% click-through (threshold: 10%) — validated |
| We can build accurate AI | Feasibility | Technical spike, 2 days | Possible, requires 2 months integration work |
| Users will pay $10/month | Business | Pricing survey (n=50) | $10/mo acceptable to 60% of respondents — validated |

Decision: Proceed to MVP, 4-week delivery target.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="example-market-expansion">
      <example type="good">
        <note>4 assumptions tested. Decision: proceed with localization plan — assumptions validated but scope is larger than initial estimate.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Opportunity: Launch product in Germany

Assumptions tested:
| Assumption | Risk Type | Test | Result |
|------------|-----------|------|--------|
| Same product works without changes | Value | 5 DE customer interviews | Needs localization (strings, date formats, GDPR) |
| Existing payment methods work | Feasibility | Technical research | Need SEPA + Klarna — 3 weeks extra |
| Support team can handle German | Business | Team assessment | Need 1 German-speaking support hire |
| Market size justifies effort | Business | Market research | €5M SAM in target segment — viable |

Decision: Proceed with localization plan, 8-week timeline (not 4 as originally assumed).
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Designing experiments to confirm the idea rather than test it — asking leading questions, selecting friendly users, setting easy success thresholds.</description>
      <reason>Confirmation bias produces validated assumptions that are actually false. Ask "what would have to be true for this to fail?" and design the experiment to find that.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Running only customer interviews without behavioral or quantitative validation.</description>
      <reason>Interviews capture what users say; analytics and experiments capture what they do. Users often say they will use a feature and do not. Combine methods for confidence.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Discovery drags on past 4 weeks without a clear decision.</description>
      <reason>Endless discovery is avoidance in disguise. After 4 weeks you have enough signal to make a decision: proceed, pivot, or kill. "Let's do one more interview" at week 6 is not discovery — it is delay.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Team begins building features during the discovery phase.</description>
      <reason>Building during discovery means discoveries that invalidate the idea arrive after significant investment. Keep experiments cheap; if you are building, you have already decided to proceed.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Learnings from experiments are not documented or shared — they exist only in the PM's head.</description>
      <reason>Undocumented learnings evaporate. The same assumptions are re-tested in future cycles by different team members. Write an experiment report for every test, even failed ones.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/discovery-kickoff.md" purpose="Discovery kickoff document with context, team, questions, assumptions, success criteria"/>
      <template path="templates/experiment-report.md" purpose="Experiment hypothesis, setup, results, learnings, and go/no-go decision"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="continuous-discovery"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
