<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Client Firing Protocol Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Client Firing Protocol application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-criteria-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use a written checklist: (a) chronic scope abuse, (b) payment &gt;30 days late ≥3 times, (c) abusive comms to team, (d) mission-mismatch with niche, (e) margin &lt;baseline ≥6 months. ≥2 criteria = fire.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Without checklist, firing decisions get rationalized in either direction; ≥2-criteria gate prevents emotional + complacent decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-fire-in-writing-30-day-notice" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send termination in writing with ≥30-day notice (or contractual minimum, whichever is longer). Professional, not personal; reference contract clause.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Verbal firings get re-litigated; written notice is the legal anchor + closes the loop cleanly.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-handover-package-not-handoff" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deliver a handover package (artefacts, credentials in secure vault, runbook, recommended successors) BEFORE last invoice. Make the next agency's life easy.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Burning bridges is short-sighted; clean handover preserves reputation + creates referral source (yes, even from fired clients).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-final-invoice-paid-before-handover" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Final invoice + outstanding balance paid in full BEFORE handover delivery. No exceptions for 'we'll pay after we see the handover'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Last leverage moment; once handover is delivered, collection rate drops to ~50%.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-post-mortem-pattern-recognition" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Within 14 days, write a post-mortem: what signs were missed at intake, what cost was paid, what intake filter would have caught this. Pattern-recognize across past firings.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">One bad client is bad luck; two with similar profile is a pattern in your intake.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>