<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Client Firing Protocol Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `Client Firing Protocol` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="criteria-checklist-passed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The ADR MUST cite the specific criteria triggered (payment, scope abuse, burn-out, ICP) with evidence links. Vibes-only ADRs are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Client-termination postmortem corpus">Vibes-only firings reopen as regret months later; explicit criteria force a clean rationale.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="transition-plan-attached" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The ADR MUST link to a transition plan (handoff docs, asset inventory, referral alternative, comms schedule). &apos;Will figure out&apos; is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal handoff audit">Un-planned transitions cause 60+ days of follow-up; an attached plan kills the tail.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="contract-exit-clean" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The ADR MUST cite the contract clause invoked and the notice period applied. Same-day exits without a safety/harassment trigger are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-dispute audit">Same-day exits routinely escalate to legal; the cited clause keeps the exit defensible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="one-way-door-tagged" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The ADR MUST tag itself one-way-door (cannot re-engage) OR two-way-door (re-engage possible after specific repair). Default tag is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-class taxonomy audit">Untagged decisions get re-opened impulsively; explicit class enforces the post-decision discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="icp-refinement-recorded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Within 14 days of termination, founder MUST record an ICP / intake-form update that would have caught this client at intake. Skipped refinement guarantees a clone next quarter.</statement>
      <rationale source="ICP-refinement corpus">Without refinement, intake stays leaky and the same bad-fit profile re-enters; 14-day window forces extraction.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>