<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="PM Tool Selection Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding PM Tool Selection. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="five-dimension-scorecard" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Scorecard MUST cover five dimensions (ecosystem, governance, integrations, agent-API, TCO). Truncated scorecards forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion tool-selection audit">Truncated scorecards miss high-cost surprises (e.g. TCO underestimate); five dimensions are the empirically calibrated set.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="three-vendor-bake-off" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision MUST include hands-on bake-off of at least 3 vendor candidates. Paper-only evaluation forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gartner tool-selection methodology">Paper evaluations miss UX deal-breakers; bake-off surfaces real-world friction within budget.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="decision-record-with-context" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision MUST be recorded in ADR format: context, options-considered, decision, consequences, reversal-trigger.</statement>
      <rationale source="Michael Nygard, Documenting Architecture Decisions (2011)">Without ADR format, future teams can't reconstruct why; the methodology becomes 'we use X because we always have'.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="named-decision-maker" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision MUST be made by a single named decision-maker with documented authority. Committee-decisions forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bezos, Type-1 vs Type-2 decisions framework">Committee decisions either stall or muddle accountability; single decision-maker compresses cycle time and creates ownership.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="reversal-trigger-quantified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ADR MUST include a quantified reversal trigger (e.g. 'reverse if vendor lock-in exceeds 30% of annual TCO').</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion ADR discipline">Reversal triggers prevent sunk-cost lock-in; quantification makes the trigger objective.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for PM Tool Selection fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying PM Tool Selection outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
