<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="PM Certification Changes 2026 Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding PM Certification Changes 2026. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="weights-side-by-side" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Report MUST present ECO 2021 vs ECO 2026 weights side-by-side with delta column. Single-table-only reports forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI ECO release notes 2026">Single-table reports hide the change magnitude; side-by-side surfaces it for candidates and L&amp;D teams.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="effective-date-cited" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Report MUST cite the effective date 2026-07-01 and clarify that exams before that date use ECO 2021.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI ECO 2026 announcement">Candidates miscalculate exam scheduling otherwise; the effective date is the single most important fact.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="prep-time-delta-quantified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per-candidate-profile (early-career, mid-career, returning) the report MUST quantify added prep time required for the Business Environment shift.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — exam-prep delivery audit">Unquantified deltas leave candidates planning blindly; quantification ties to study plan.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="question-type-changes-listed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Report MUST list any new question types (e.g. drag-and-drop, hotspot, multi-correct) introduced in ECO 2026.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI ECO 2026 question types appendix">Question-type changes affect test-taking strategy more than content; omission misleads candidates.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="source-pmi-canonical" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All facts in the report MUST cite the PMI ECO 2026 document or PMI exam release notes. Third-party blog posts forbidden as sole source.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion research standards">Third-party sources lag and contain errors; PMI canonical sources ensure accuracy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for PM Certification Changes 2026 fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying PM Certification Changes 2026 outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
