<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="05-examples" title="Lean Stack Bootstrapper Blueprint Worked Example" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="medium">
  <summary>End-to-end worked example applying lean-stack-bootstrapper-blueprint to a representative case. Walks step-by-step through the procedure, shows the produced artefact, and highlights the rules it satisfies.</summary>

  <section title="Setup">
    <p>Context: a team that matches the Applies-If conditions for lean-stack-bootstrapper-blueprint. Inputs are populated per the Prerequisites table.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Walk-through">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: List the product&apos;s actual needs: hosting, DB, auth, payments, DNS, observability. — produced service-map.</item>
      <item>Step 2: Apply r1: pick exactly one vendor per role (≤5 total). — produced service list.</item>
      <item>Step 3: Set monthly ceiling + alert threshold per vendor admin UI. — produced ceiling configured.</item>
      <item>Step 4: Author upgrade-trigger table (r5). — produced trigger doc.</item>
      <item>Step 5: Diagram the architecture (1-page Markdown + mermaid). — produced stack-diagram.md.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Final artefact">
    <p>The team commits the final artefact (per spec shape) at the version-controlled path declared in the output contract. Owner signs and links it to downstream consumers.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Rules satisfied">
    <list>
      <item>r1-five-services-max: Stack has ≤5 services: Vercel (hosting+edge), Supabase (DB+auth+storage), Stripe (payments), Cloudflare (DNS+CDN+email f</item>
      <item>r2-cost-ceiling-explicit: Set a monthly cost ceiling ($50, $200, $500). Alert at 80%. Auto-pause non-essential at 100%.</item>
      <item>r3-no-premature-docker: Do NOT introduce Docker, Kubernetes, or self-hosted services before the lean stack hits a real bottleneck.</item>
      <item>r4-vendor-lock-acceptance: Accept vendor lock-in as a feature. Free tier&apos;s job is shipping, not portability. Optimize portability after PMF.</item>
      <item>r5-upgrade-triggers-documented: Document triggers to graduate: monthly cost &gt; 30% of MRR, p95 latency &gt; 1s, vendor outage &gt; 4h/month. Otherwise</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/01-core-rules.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
