<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-deployment" title="Grafana Deployment Rules">
  <summary>Rules for choosing a deployment model (Docker Compose vs Helm vs HA), the Grafana Agent EOL, and database backend requirements for HA.</summary>

  <section title="Deployment Model Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Docker Compose for development and single-node deployments; Kubernetes Helm for production; HA with PostgreSQL for critical systems.</statement>
      <rationale>SQLite is not supported in HA configurations — any multi-replica setup requires PostgreSQL or MySQL as the shared database.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Grafana Alloy as the data collection agent — Grafana Agent is EOL since November 1, 2025.</statement>
      <rationale>Grafana Agent (Static, Flow, and Operator modes) reached end-of-life on November 1, 2025. All three modes migrate to Grafana Alloy via the `alloy convert` command.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="High Availability Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>For HA: deploy PostgreSQL or MySQL as the shared database, expose a headless Kubernetes Service for alerting peer discovery, and set min 2 replicas behind a load balancer.</statement>
      <rationale>Sessions are stored in the database, so no session affinity is needed on the load balancer. Alerting HA uses gossip via `ha_listen_address` and `ha_peers` (or Redis) to deduplicate alert firing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure the health check endpoint `/api/health` on the load balancer, not a TCP check.</statement>
      <rationale>TCP checks pass even when Grafana is starting up. The HTTP health endpoint returns 200 only when Grafana is ready to serve traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Grafana Alloy Migration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Convert existing Grafana Agent configs with `alloy convert --source-format=static --output=config.alloy config.yaml` before EOL, then run Alloy in parallel to validate metrics continuity.</statement>
      <rationale>Parallel-run validation catches label differences or missing scrape targets before the Agent is decommissioned, preventing monitoring gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <note>Converting a static Agent config to Alloy format.</note>
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Static mode conversion
alloy convert --source-format=static --output=config.alloy config.yaml

# Flow mode conversion
alloy convert --source-format=flow --output=config.alloy config.river
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Deploying multiple Grafana replicas with SQLite.</description>
    <reason>SQLite is file-based and cannot be shared across processes. Concurrent writes from multiple replicas corrupt the database.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
