<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-provisioning" title="Grafana Provisioning Rules">
  <summary>Rules for configuration-as-code provisioning of datasources, dashboards, alerting, and secrets handling in Grafana.</summary>

  <section title="Datasource Provisioning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provision all datasources via YAML files in `/etc/grafana/provisioning/datasources/`; never create them manually in the UI in production.</statement>
      <rationale>UI-created datasources are not version-controlled and are lost on container restart unless the database is backed up. YAML provisioning is idempotent and GitOps-compatible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark all provisioned datasources as `editable: false` in production to prevent UI drift.</statement>
      <rationale>If a user modifies a provisioned datasource in the UI, the change is lost on the next restart when Grafana re-applies the provisioning files.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Inject all credentials (database passwords, API keys) via environment variables referenced in YAML as `${VAR_NAME}`, never hardcoded.</statement>
      <rationale>YAML provisioning files are committed to version control. Hardcoded credentials in Git are a security breach regardless of repository visibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Dashboard Provisioning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use `foldersFromFilesStructure: true` in the dashboard provider to derive Grafana folder names from the filesystem directory structure.</statement>
      <rationale>Manually specifying folder names for hundreds of dashboards creates maintenance overhead. Filesystem-derived folders are automatic and consistent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set `disableDeletion: true` for production dashboard providers and `allowUiUpdates: false` to prevent UI edits from diverging from Git.</statement>
      <rationale>Allows developers to view and explore dashboards without accidentally overwriting the provisioned version. Changes must go through Git to take effect.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Alerting Provisioning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provision alert rules, contact points, notification policies, and mute timings all via YAML — unified alerting must be enabled (`[unified_alerting] enabled = true`).</statement>
      <rationale>Legacy alerting (`[alerting] enabled = true`) is deprecated. Unified Alerting is the only path for provisioned alert management and HA-compatible alert deduplication.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Mixing manual UI configuration with provisioning files in the same Grafana instance.</description>
    <reason>Provisioning on restart overwrites UI changes silently. Teams discover their manual changes are gone after the next deployment, causing repeated work and confusion.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <reference path="templates/datasources.yaml">Provisioning YAML for Prometheus, Loki, Tempo, PostgreSQL</reference>
  <reference path="templates/dashboards.yaml">Dashboard provider config with folder organization</reference>
  <reference path="templates/alerting-rules.yaml">Alert rules, contact points, policies, mute timings</reference>
</text>
