<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GitOps — Progressive Delivery Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules including a `skip-this-methodology` rule. Each pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="metric-gated-promotion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Promotion between rollout steps MUST be gated by metric thresholds (success rate ≥SLO, latency ≤SLO, error rate ≤SLO) over a defined window. Time-based promotions without metrics are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Progressive delivery research">Time-based promotions miss real failures; metric gates promote only when health is verified.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="automated-rollback-on-breach" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Metric breach MUST trigger automatic rollback to the previous stable revision. Manual rollback as the only path is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Rollback discipline">Manual rollback during incidents is too slow; auto-rollback caps blast radius.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="traffic-split-step-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Canary rollouts MUST define explicit step sequence (e.g. 5%→25%→50%→100%) with per-step duration. Implicit 'gradual' rollouts are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Rollout repeatability">Implicit rollouts vary run-to-run; explicit steps are debuggable and tunable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="baseline-and-canary-shape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Canary MUST run alongside a baseline of the previous revision for direct comparison; not against historical traffic.</statement>
      <rationale source="Comparison hygiene">Historical comparison drifts (load patterns differ hour-to-hour); side-by-side baseline isolates the change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rollout-artefact-versioned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rollout configuration MUST be checked into Git alongside the deployment, versioned, owned, and reviewed.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitOps discipline">Rollout config drift is rollout failure; treat it as code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip when no traffic-split primitive OR no metric source OR static-VM infra OR sub-weekly deploys.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scope guard">Progressive delivery economics break below these thresholds; simpler patterns win.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
