<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Competitive Intelligence Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Competitive Intelligence methodology. Every rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale, plus the universal skip-this-methodology gate.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="polling-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Monitor each signal class at its natural change rate: pricing/funding weekly; feature/website daily; hiring/SEO monthly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Crayon Best Practices (2024)">Polling too slowly misses time-sensitive funding signals; too fast wastes quota on noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ttl-14d-on-battlecards" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every battlecard MUST carry a generation timestamp and a 14-day TTL; older battlecards must not be distributed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — sales-ops audit Q4 2025">Sales reps trust dated artifacts; stale-but-confident claims actively damage deals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="model-tier-split" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Haiku to mechanical collection/classification; Sonnet to synthesis/battlecards; Opus to threat assessment. Never invert.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anthropic - Building Effective Agents (2024)">Mixing reasoning-grade models into collection adds 10x cost; mixing fast models into threat analysis produces hallucinated claims.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="fact-checker-head" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every digest and battlecard MUST pass a fact-checker that HEAD-requests every cited URL before distribution.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — citation hallucination audit">LLMs invent URLs like /pricing/enterprise that never existed; publishing an invented citation destroys trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="event-id-on-every-claim" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every factual claim MUST reference an event_id from the collector NDJSON.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — provenance policy">Unsourced claims are liabilities; provenance is the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="emit-one-event-per-delta" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Collector MUST emit one event per delta; never aggregate inside the collector.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — pipeline architecture review">Aggregated events hide sequence; acceleration patterns vanish.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="source-order-api-rss-scrape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prefer competitor APIs, then RSS, then scraping, then screenshot diff - in that order, per competitor.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — ToS / legal audit">APIs are reliable and ToS-compliant; scraping is fragile and legally ambiguous.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only if all entries in `## Applies If` hold and none of `## Skip If` triggers; otherwise abort and route to the correct methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — decision tree minimum form">A misrouted methodology produces wrong-shape output; the explicit skip rule is the universal default branch from the decision tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
