<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="competitive-intelligence Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for competitive-intelligence. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Monitor each signal category at its natural change rate: pricing and funding weekly, feature launches and website changes daily, hiring and content/SEO monthly.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Polling too slowly misses time-sensitive funding and pricing signals. Polling too frequently on slow-moving signals wastes quota and generates noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick a platform tier matched to your scale: Crayon/Klue for mid-market automation and battlecard distribution; Contify Athena for agentic unstructured-content analysis; AlphaSense for filings and expert-call transcripts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Over-engineering CI infrastructure before you have 3+ named competitors and an action loop wastes budget. Under-investing means alerts are never acted on.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build toward predictive CI by feeding historical event logs into a threat-scoring model calibrated quarterly against actual lost deals.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Descriptive CI is table stakes. Predictive CI compresses the gap between a competitor signal and your strategic response from weeks to hours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stamp every battlecard with a generation date and enforce a 14-day TTL; a 2-week-old battlecard with confident tone is worse than no battlecard.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sales reps trust dated artifacts. Stale-but-confident claims actively damage deals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign Haiku to mechanical collection and classification; Sonnet to synthesis and battlecard writing; Opus to threat assessment and scenario planning—never invert this.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixing reasoning-grade models into collection tasks adds 10x cost with no marginal accuracy gain. Mixing fast models into threat analysis produces hallucinated strategic claims.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every digest and battlecard must pass a fact-checker agent that HEAD-requests every cited URL before the document is distributed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs invent URLs like /pricing/enterprise that never existed. Publishing an invented citation to a sales rep destroys trust in the entire CI function.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Emit one event per delta, never aggregate inside the collector—keeps the audit trail clean and lets the synthesizer see the raw timeline.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Aggregated events hide the sequence of competitor moves. The synthesizer needs the timeline to detect acceleration patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Force every LLM claim to carry an event_id reference; reject digests that fail the fact-checker pass.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unsourced claims are liabilities in sales conversations. Require provenance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Calibrate threat scores against actual lost deals quarterly; recalibrate the prompt if the score does not predict losses.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">An uncalibrated threat score becomes a noise source. Quarterly calibration ties CI to revenue impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Battlecard TTL ≤ 14 days. Stamp generation date prominently; sales reps trust dated artifacts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stale battlecards with confident tone damage credibility. A 14-day TTL enforces freshness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Separate "what changed" (Haiku, mechanical) from "so what" (Opus, judgment). Mixing them costs 10x and adds hallucination.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opus reasoning on raw HTML diffs is wasteful and noisy. Haiku distills the signal; Opus interprets the pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Subscribe to competitor changelog/RSS first; scraping is the fallback. APIs &gt; RSS &gt; scrape &gt; screenshot diff.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">APIs are reliable and ToS-compliant. Scraping is fragile and legally ambiguous. Use the most reliable source available per competitor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track yourself with the same pipeline. Catches what your own marketing site exposes to competitors.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">CI is bidirectional. What you publish about pricing, hiring, and product reveals your strategy to the same tools your competitors use.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep a "do-not-track" list (legal, ex-employees, personal blogs) to avoid ToS and ethical issues.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Scraping without guardrails creates legal and reputational risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run win/loss interviews monthly and feed transcripts back into battlecard prompts—review-site sentiment alone is a lagging indicator.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Win/loss data grounds CI in real deal outcomes, not sentiment signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
