<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-monitoring-framework" title="CI Monitoring Framework">
  <summary>Signal sources, monitoring frequencies, platform landscape, and CI evolution from reactive to predictive.</summary>

  <section title="Signal Sources and Frequencies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Monitor each signal category at its natural change rate: pricing and funding weekly, feature launches and website changes daily, hiring and content/SEO monthly.</statement>
      <rationale>Polling too slowly misses time-sensitive funding and pricing signals. Polling too frequently on slow-moving signals wastes quota and generates noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Pricing changes: Crayon, Klue + manual — weekly</item>
      <item>Feature launches: Product Hunt, Twitter — daily</item>
      <item>Hiring patterns: LinkedIn — monthly</item>
      <item>Funding/M&amp;A news: Crunchbase, AlphaSense — weekly</item>
      <item>Customer reviews: G2, Capterra — weekly</item>
      <item>Content/SEO changes: Ahrefs, SEMrush — monthly</item>
      <item>Website changes: Visualping, Crayon — daily</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="CI Platform Comparison">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick a platform tier matched to your scale: Crayon/Klue for mid-market automation and battlecard distribution; Contify Athena for agentic unstructured-content analysis; AlphaSense for filings and expert-call transcripts.</statement>
      <rationale>Over-engineering CI infrastructure before you have 3+ named competitors and an action loop wastes budget. Under-investing means alerts are never acted on.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Crayon: CI automation, battlecard generation, partial REST API</item>
      <item>Klue: Market intelligence distribution to Salesforce/Slack, partial REST API</item>
      <item>Contify Athena (2025): Agentic AI engine for unstructured-content reasoning</item>
      <item>AlphaSense: Multi-source intel (filings, transcripts, expert calls), API + summaries</item>
      <item>Kompyte (Semrush): Real-time site/SEO delta tracking at scale, webhook + API</item>
      <item>Valona Intelligence: Multilingual CI for EU/APAC competitors, limited API</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="CI Evolution 2025-2026">
    <p>Current (2025): Reactive and descriptive — tells you what competitors did after they did it. Emerging (2026): Predictive and prescriptive — anticipates competitor moves and recommends strategic responses via multi-agent pipelines.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Build toward predictive CI by feeding historical event logs into a threat-scoring model calibrated quarterly against actual lost deals.</statement>
      <rationale>Descriptive CI is table stakes. Predictive CI compresses the gap between a competitor signal and your strategic response from weeks to hours.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Output Cadence">
    <list>
      <item>Weekly digest: product team — Delta events per competitor, scored by signal type</item>
      <item>Monthly threat assessment: leadership — Evidence-based threat score 1-5, recommended action</item>
      <item>Quarterly feature comparison: sales, marketing — Full feature matrix vs competitors</item>
      <item>Quarterly strategic report: executive — Scenario planning, market shifts</item>
      <item>Real-time battlecards: sales reps — Auto-regenerated on high-severity events, TTL 14 days</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stamp every battlecard with a generation date and enforce a 14-day TTL; a 2-week-old battlecard with confident tone is worse than no battlecard.</statement>
      <rationale>Sales reps trust dated artifacts. Stale-but-confident claims actively damage deals.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
