<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ads-conversion-tracking Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ads-conversion-tracking. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always track both macro conversions (primary business goal) and micro conversions (funnel steps) — micro conversions provide optimization signal when macro volume is too low for smart bidding.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Smart bidding requires 30-50 conversions per week to function; new campaigns rarely achieve this on macro events alone. Micro conversions (add-to-cart, pricing page view) fill the signal gap during ramp-up.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pass dynamic purchase values whenever possible — static values prevent Target ROAS bidding from optimizing for high-value orders over low-value ones.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Static values make all conversions look equal to the algorithm; with dynamic values, bidding can allocate more spend toward user segments that produce larger orders.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Install the Meta Pixel base code on every page of the site, not just conversion pages.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The base code enables audience building from all page visitors, not just converters — required for website custom audiences and retargeting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always implement server-side tracking alongside browser pixels — never rely on browser pixels alone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ad blockers, iOS App Tracking Transparency, and browser privacy features block 20-40% of browser pixel events. Server-side events pass directly from your server, bypassing all browser restrictions, and can include richer user data for better match rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set matching event_id values in both the browser fbq() call and the CAPI server event — mismatched IDs cause double-counting, inflating reported conversions by up to 2x.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Meta deduplicates events within a 48-hour window when event_id matches; without this, the algorithm sees twice the conversions and bids accordingly, wasting budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test every conversion type manually before launch — never rely on code review alone to confirm events fire in production.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">CSP headers, async loading conflicts, and SPA routing all cause pixel silencing in production that is invisible in staging environments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set attribution windows to match your product's typical sales cycle — a B2B SaaS with a 30-day trial should use a 30-day click window, not 7 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Shorter windows than the sales cycle under-attribute conversions to ads, making campaigns appear less efficient and causing premature budget cuts on campaigns that are actually working.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always send a unique event_id (order ID, lead ID) on both pixel and CAPI for the same event — Meta dedupes within a 48-hour window. No event_id = double-count.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Event ID is the primary deduplication key. Without it, the same business event gets counted twice, inflating conversion reports and burning budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hash PII (email, phone, first/last name, city, zip) with lowercase-trim then SHA-256 before sending — and verify in Events Manager that match-quality score is &gt; 5.0.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">PII hashing enables Meta to match server events to users without transmitting PII in plaintext. Match quality score measures success; scores below 5.0 indicate data quality issues.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Fire one and only one Purchase per order. If your thank-you page can be reloaded, gate the pixel on sessionStorage or send only from server.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Multiple Purchase events per order inflate reported conversions and make optimization signal noisy. Server-side de-duplication is the most reliable approach.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep event names canonical across platforms via a single mapping table; never sprinkle platform-specific names through the codebase.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Event name standardization prevents drift where the same business action gets different names on different platforms. A mapping table makes audits and migrations easier.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set CAPI as the source of truth in the ad platform once both are stable — pixel becomes a redundant backup, not the primary signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">CAPI provides server-side data that is more accurate and less subject to browser restrictions. Once CAPI is working, make it primary so algorithms optimize on the most reliable signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test on an iOS Safari device with Private Relay on — that's where 30% of the data loss hides.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">iOS Private Relay removes IP addresses from server-side requests for some users. Testing with Private Relay reveals fingerprinting gaps and match-rate drops that staging environments miss.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
