<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ads-conversion-tracking Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ads-conversion-tracking as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>iOS 14.5+ ATT, Safari ITP, and EU consent banners cut browser-only pixel coverage by 30-60% — server-side is mandatory for accurate numbers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Browser privacy features are beyond an advertiser's control. Browser-only tracking is inherently incomplete in 2026; CAPI is the only path to ground truth.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Meta CAPI events without event_id get deduped against the pixel by event_name + timestamp window — easy to double-count if you skip event IDs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Meta's fallback deduplication is imprecise. Events with the same name fired within seconds can appear different. Event IDs prevent this false-positive dedup.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>predicted_ltv on Meta is a custom param Meta doesn't actually use for bidding (yet) — don't optimize on it.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Meta's documentation promises LTV-aware bidding but has not shipped it. Agents that instrument predicted_ltv are building for a future that may not arrive; focus on actual conversion signals instead.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>LinkedIn Insight Tag has 90-day attribution but only fires on direct site visits — single-page apps need explicit _linkedin_partner_id push on route change.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LinkedIn's tag is not universal; SPAs must hook route changes manually. Agents deploying LinkedIn without SPA-specific handling will get zero conversions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>gtag/GTM server containers don't replicate Meta's automatic advanced matching — you must hash and send PII fields explicitly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Advanced matching requires PII; GTM's server container defaults to anonymous tracking. Agents must explicitly include PII hashing to enable matching.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Apple's Private Relay strips IP from server-side requests for some users — fingerprinting fallbacks degrade silently.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>When IP is unavailable, match rates drop sharply. Agents are blind to the failure because no error is raised — the event lands but with zero match rate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
