<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="process-mining-automation">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Data-driven process discovery from event logs with objective automation scoring on volume, standardization, stability, digital input, error rate, and ROI potential.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>process-mining</tag>
      <tag>automation-assessment</tag>
      <tag>rpa</tag>
      <tag>event-logs</tag>
      <tag>data-driven</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Process Mining and Intelligent Automation Analysis</title>
    <summary>A data-driven methodology for discovering actual process execution from IT event logs and identifying automation candidates using objective scoring criteria. Combines process mining tools (Celonis, Disco, ProM) to reconstruct real process flows, conformance checking against documented processes, and an automation readiness matrix that scores candidates on volume, standardization, stability, digital input, error rate, and ROI potential. Produces an automation assessment report with full/partial/no-go recommendations.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Process documentation relies on subjective stakeholder input that diverges from actual execution; RPA initiatives fail because automation is applied to processes that are not sufficiently rule-based or stable. Process mining replaces "interview the process owner" with event-log evidence, and the scoring matrix replaces intuition-based automation selection with a reproducible, auditable decision framework.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-RPA or intelligent automation initiative where automation candidates must be ranked objectively</item>
        <item>Process variance analysis where conformance checking reveals deviations between documented and actual flows</item>
        <item>Cost reduction initiative where high-volume, rule-based processes need to be identified from system data</item>
        <item>Audit or compliance context where process evidence must come from system logs, not interviews</item>
        <item>Digital transformation assessment needing a portfolio of automation opportunities with ROI estimates</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Processes with no digital event trail (fully manual, paper-based) — mining requires event logs</item>
        <item>Highly creative or judgment-intensive processes (strategy, design) — automation readiness score will be below threshold</item>
        <item>Processes changing faster than the mining cycle — the discovered model is stale before recommendations land</item>
        <item>Organizations without access to process mining tooling or data engineering capability to extract event logs</item>
        <item>When the goal is process improvement rather than automation — use BPMN and business process analysis instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="definition-and-purpose">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Apply process mining to reconstruct actual process flows from IT system event logs before documenting process requirements or selecting automation candidates. Do not rely on stakeholder interviews alone for process discovery — actual execution diverges from documented processes in the majority of cases.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholder interviews capture the ideal process; event logs capture what actually happens. RPA initiatives built on interview-based process models fail because they automate the documented process, not the real one.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="required-ba-competencies">
      <list>
        <item>Technical: ProM, Disco, or Celonis (process mining tools), SQL for event log extraction, data visualization for conformance reports</item>
        <item>Process: BPMN 2.0 notation, process modeling, workflow variance analysis</item>
        <item>Analytical: statistics (frequency distributions, variant analysis), pattern recognition, root-cause analysis of process deviations</item>
        <item>Domain: industry-specific knowledge to interpret discovered process variants and regulatory understanding for compliance-sensitive processes</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="four-step-mining-workflow">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Process mining follows four steps in sequence: (1) Event Log Extraction — extract case ID, activity, timestamp from IT systems; (2) Process Discovery — generate actual process model from event log; (3) Conformance Checking — compare discovered model to documented design, identify deviations and their frequency; (4) Enhancement — use deviation analysis to identify bottlenecks, rework loops, and automation candidates.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping conformance checking (step 3) produces a "what is" model without identifying where and how often the process deviates from intent — the most actionable output for process improvement.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="tool-landscape">
      <list>
        <item>Celonis: process mining market leader, enterprise SaaS, strong action orientation and EMS (execution management system) integration</item>
        <item>Disco (Fluxicon): desktop tool, fast for initial exploration, imports XES and CSV event logs</item>
        <item>ProM: open-source research platform, most algorithms, requires technical expertise</item>
        <item>Microsoft Power Automate Process Advisor: M365-integrated process mining for organizations already in the Microsoft ecosystem</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="automation-readiness-scoring">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Score every automation candidate against six criteria: Volume (high = more than 100 transactions/day), Standardization (high = rule-based with few exceptions), Stability (medium = process unchanged more than 6 months), Digital Input (medium = structured data available), Error Rate (medium = high manual error frequency), ROI Potential (high = high labor cost with measurable payback). Total out of 30. Recommend: full automation above 24, partial automation 18-24, process improvement first 12-18, not suitable below 12.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a scoring matrix, automation selection is based on who has the loudest stakeholder voice. The matrix forces objective measurement across dimensions that predict automation success.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="rpa-vs-intelligent-automation">
      <list>
        <item>RPA: rule-based repetitive tasks, predefined decision logic, structured data only, no learning, human escalation for exceptions — best for high-volume stable processes</item>
        <item>Intelligent Automation: complex variable tasks, AI-driven decisions, structured and unstructured data, continuous learning, autonomous exception handling — best for variable processes with document complexity or judgment requirements</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="vendor-landscape">
      <list>
        <item>UiPath: largest pure-play RPA, enterprise leader, strong developer ecosystem and test automation integration</item>
        <item>Automation Anywhere: cloud-native architecture, strong AI integration, IQ Bot for document processing</item>
        <item>Blue Prism: enterprise governance and auditability focus, preferred in regulated industries</item>
        <item>Microsoft Power Automate: M365 integration, low barrier for Microsoft shops, desktop and cloud flows</item>
        <item>Celonis: process mining combined with automation recommendations, action engine triggers RPA from discovered bottlenecks</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="market-context">
      <p>RPA market: $35.27 billion in 2026 growing to $247.34 billion by 2035. 58% of enterprises will use RPA with AI/ML by 2026. 44% already use AI-enabled RPA for document processing. By 2026, 30% of enterprises will automate more than 50% of network activities.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="automation-assessment-example">
      <example type="good" title="Automation Assessment Example: Invoice Processing">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Process: Accounts Payable — Invoice Matching

Process Overview:
- Current Volume: 450 invoices/day
- Current FTE: 3.5
- Error Rate: 8% (manual keying errors)
- Cycle Time: 4.2 hours average

Automation Readiness Scoring:
| Criterion       | Score (1-5) | Evidence                                   |
|-----------------|-------------|---------------------------------------------|
| Volume          | 5           | 450/day >> 100/day threshold               |
| Standardization | 4           | 85% rule-based; 15% exception rate         |
| Stability       | 4           | Process unchanged 14 months               |
| Digital Input   | 3           | 60% EDI (structured), 40% PDF (unstructured)|
| Error Rate      | 4           | 8% manual error rate drives rework         |
| ROI Potential   | 5           | $210k/year labor; 8-month payback estimated|
| Total           | 25/30       |                                            |

Recommendation: Partial automation (score 25 = range 18-24 is exceeded)
  → Full automation for EDI invoices (60%)
  → Intelligent document processing for PDF invoices (40%)
  → Human review retained for exceptions (15% of volume)

ROI Estimate:
- Estimated savings: $175k/year (FTE reduction 2.5 → 0.5 exception handlers)
- Implementation cost: $85k (licensing + integration)
- Payback: 5.8 months
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="common-assessment-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Automating a high-volume process before checking for standardization — discovering mid-project that 40% of cases are exceptions.</description>
        <reason>Volume alone is not a sufficient criterion. A 1,000-transaction/day process with 50% exceptions requires human judgment more than automation; scoring all six criteria prevents this failure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Selecting automation vendor before completing the process assessment — vendor locks in architecture before requirements are known.</description>
        <reason>Complete the assessment matrix and determine whether RPA or intelligent automation applies before engaging vendors; the tool selection follows from the process characteristics, not from the vendor relationship.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="where-it-fails-limitations">
      <p>Garbage event logs. Most enterprise logs lack a stable case ID, a clean activity label, or a reliable timestamp. Mining tools amplify dirty data into confidently-wrong DFGs. Budget 60-80% of effort on log preparation.</p>
      <p>The XES tax. pm4py and most academic tooling expect XES (XML) format; real systems emit CSV. Conversion is mechanical but error-prone (timezone drift, NULL case IDs, multi-row activities).</p>
      <p>Spaghetti diagrams. A high-variability process (e.g., support ticketing with 800 unique paths) renders as an unreadable graph. Without filtering (top-K variants, frequency thresholds) the output is useless.</p>
      <p>Hallucinated automation ROI. LLMs cheerfully fabricate "saves 2 FTE = $180k/year" with no source. The README's ROI template invites this. Hard rule: every $ figure must cite log-derived volume + a documented loaded-cost rate.</p>
      <p>Vendor lock-in masquerading as analysis. Celonis/UiPath Process Mining bundle discovery + auto-recommendation; their automation suggestions skew toward their own RPA platform.</p>
      <p>Conformance theater. Conformance checking against a "designed" model that was itself wishful thinking produces inflated deviation counts. Validate the reference model first.</p>
      <p>Privacy / GDPR exposure. Event logs frequently contain PII (user IDs, customer names in activity labels, IP addresses). Mining tools store these; agents passing logs to cloud LLMs leak them.</p>
      <p>RPA-fragility. A process that scores 28/30 on the assessment matrix may still be a bad RPA candidate if upstream UIs change frequently — the matrix has no "UI volatility" criterion.</p>
      <p>Score inflation. LLMs grade their own assessment; subjective criteria (Standardization, Rule Clarity) drift to 4-5 unless rubric examples are pinned in the prompt.</p>
      <p>Mining ≠ understanding. The graph shows what happens, not why. Causality requires interviews; agents skip this and recommend automation of compensating steps that mask root cause.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Scrub before mining. Run password-scrubber-agent then presidio-analyzer on raw logs before any LLM sees them. Activity labels and free-text fields leak PII routinely.</item>
        <item>Anchor the case ID. Every dispute about mining output traces back to case-ID instability. Validate before stage 2: df.groupby("case_id").size().describe(); if median &lt; 2 events, your case ID is wrong.</item>
        <item>Filter by frequency before visualization. Always render DFG with at least an 80% frequency cutoff; full graphs are unreadable and tell you nothing.</item>
        <item>Score only with citations. Each cell in the Automation Readiness matrix must reference a stat from mining-report.md. Reject scores marked "estimated".</item>
        <item>Compare top-3 variants, not the average. Process mining averages hide variant-specific automation opportunities — the long tail is where rework lives.</item>
        <item>Quantify rework explicitly. Count loop occurrences (A → B → A) per case; loops in cases over 3 events are NVA candidates.</item>
        <item>Pin the rubric in the prompt. Subjective criteria (Standardization, Rule Clarity) drift across runs; pin examples and require comparison to examples for every score.</item>
        <item>ROI from log-derived volume only. Never accept stakeholder volume estimates when log volume is available. Hourly rate × cycle-minutes-saved × log-volume = hard floor.</item>
        <item>Pilot one variant before broadcasting recommendations. Implement the top candidate end-to-end (n8n / RPA bot), measure actual savings for 30 days, then extend the matrix to others.</item>
        <item>Re-mine after every UI/system change. Bots break when the UI changes; re-running mining on the post-change log catches drift before it cascades.</item>
        <item>Eliminate before automating. If a NVA step can be deleted (a duplicate approval, an obsolete sign-off), eliminate it; do not pave the cowpath with RPA.</item>
        <item>Keep the BPMN in source control. Export discovered BPMN XML alongside mining-report.md so changes are diffable in PRs.</item>
        <item>Separate process mining from task mining. Task mining (desktop activity capture) is a different toolset; do not conflate. Use task mining only when no system-level event log exists.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow-details">
      <p>Run a 4-stage pipeline. Stage 1 (extract) — a connector agent pulls event data from a source system (Jira REST, Salesforce Bulk API, DB SELECT) into a normalized CSV (case_id, activity, timestamp, resource, attrs). Stage 2 (mine) — a Python subagent runs pm4py to produce DFG/Petri net, variant analysis, and bottleneck stats; outputs mining-report.md + SVG. Stage 3 (assess) — an LLM subagent applies the 6-criterion automation matrix to each top-N variant, citing mining stats for every score. Stage 4 (recommend) — a synthesis agent produces a ranked candidate queue with ROI estimates (volume × loaded-cost × cycle-time saved), each row traceable to mining evidence. Use faion-ba-agent as orchestrator; delegate mining to a general-purpose Task subagent with pm4py; checkpoint between stages because re-running stage 1 is expensive.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-ba-agent (orchestrator, owns 4-stage state machine, writes outputs to .aidocs/feature-slug/), password-scrubber-agent (mandatory first pass on raw event log), general-purpose Task subagent for mining (equipped with pm4py, pandas, graphviz), faion-software-architect (consumes automation recommendations, decides whether n8n/RPA/native code), faion-sdd-executor-agent (turns approved automation candidate into spec → design → tasks), faion-research-agent (vendor selection), faion-data-agent (stage 1 connector: extract and normalize).</p>
      <p>Prompt pattern — Stage 2 (mine) dispatch: Input events.csv (case_id, activity, timestamp, resource). Run pm4py discover DFG (frequency variant), inductive miner Petri net, variant analysis (top 10 by frequency), bottleneck (mean sojourn time per activity). Write outputs to .aidocs/feature-slug/mining/: dfg.svg, petri.svg, variants.json, bottlenecks.csv, mining-report.md. Sections: Log summary, Top variants table, Bottlenecks, Rework loops, Conformance vs reference model. No prose interpretation — facts and tables only. Stage 3 (assess) dispatch: Input mining-report.md + variants.json + bottlenecks.csv. For each top 5 variants, fill Automation Readiness matrix. Rubric: Volume (cite from log), Standardization (variant frequency %), Digital Inputs (structured fields), Process Stability (6-month window), Exception Rate (inverse rework frequency), Rule Clarity (only with policy doc). Output one filled matrix per variant; refuse to score if evidence missing. End with ranked Top-3 with ROI using only log-derived volume × stated FTE cost.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools: pm4py (process discovery DFG/Petri net, conformance, variant analysis), prom-tools (ProM CLI, academic toolkit), Apromore CLI (OSS process mining), xes-standard validators (XES format), pandas + pyarrow (log normalization), graphviz (render DFG/Petri), mermaid-cli (flowcharts for review packets), bpmn-to-image (render BPMN 2.0 to SVG), csvkit (inspect/clean CSV), jq (slice JSON exports), presidio-analyzer (PII redaction), uipath-cli (deploy UiPath bots), pac (Power Platform CLI), camunda-cloud-cli (deploy BPMN to Camunda 8).</p>
      <p>Services: Celonis EMS (SaaS, REST + Studio APIs, market leader, expensive, bias toward Celonis RPA), UiPath Process Mining (SaaS, APIs, tightly coupled to UiPath RPA), SAP Signavio (SaaS, partial REST, SAP-centric), Apromore (OSS + SaaS, pairs with pm4py), Fluxicon Disco (desktop, best DFG visualization, not for automation pipelines), Microsoft Power Automate Process Mining (SaaS, Graph API, M365), QPR ProcessAnalyzer (SaaS, partial APIs), ABBYY Timeline (SaaS, document-heavy), UiPath Studio + Orchestrator (SaaS, RPA platform), Automation Anywhere A360 (SaaS, REST), Blue Prism (SaaS + on-prem, governance focus), Microsoft Power Automate (SaaS, Graph + CLI), n8n (OSS self-hosted, implement automation candidates), Camunda 8 (OSS + SaaS, executable orchestrator), Workato/Tray.io (SaaS iPaaS), Celonis Action Engine (SaaS, triggers actions on deviations).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="mining-stage-2-python-scaffold">
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
#!/usr/bin/env python3
"""
mine_and_score.py events.csv --out out/
Produces dfg.svg, variants.csv, bottlenecks.csv, top_candidates.json
columns: case_id, activity, timestamp[, resource]
"""
import argparse, json, os
from pathlib import Path
import pandas as pd
import pm4py
from pm4py.algo.discovery.dfg import algorithm as dfg_algo
from pm4py.visualization.dfg import visualizer as dfg_vis
from pm4py.statistics.variants.log import get as variants_get

p = argparse.ArgumentParser()
p.add_argument("csv"); p.add_argument("--out", default="out")
p.add_argument("--top", type=int, default=5)
a = p.parse_args(); Path(a.out).mkdir(exist_ok=True)

df = pd.read_csv(a.csv, parse_dates=["timestamp"])
log = pm4py.format_dataframe(
    df, case_id="case_id", activity_key="activity", timestamp_key="timestamp"
)
dfg = dfg_algo.apply(log)
dfg_vis.save(dfg_vis.apply(dfg, log=log, variant=dfg_vis.Variants.FREQUENCY),
             f"{a.out}/dfg.svg")

variants = variants_get.get_variants(log)
rows = sorted(
    [{"variant": " > ".join(v), "count": len(cs)} for v, cs in variants.items()],
    key=lambda r: -r["count"]
)[: a.top]
pd.DataFrame(rows).to_csv(f"{a.out}/variants.csv", index=False)

dur = (df.groupby("case_id")["timestamp"].agg(["min", "max"])
         .assign(cycle_min=lambda x: (x["max"] - x["min"]).dt.total_seconds() / 60))
total = len(df["case_id"].unique())
candidates = [
    {"variant": r["variant"], "share": r["count"] / total,
     "score_volume": 5 if r["count"] > 100 else (3 if r["count"] > 20 else 1),
     "score_standardization": 5 if r["count"] / total > 0.7 else (3 if r["count"] / total > 0.3 else 1)}
    for r in rows
]
Path(f"{a.out}/top_candidates.json").write_text(json.dumps(candidates, indent=2))
print(f"wrote {a.out}/dfg.svg, variants.csv, top_candidates.json "
      f"(cases={total}, mean_cycle_min={dur['cycle_min'].mean():.1f})")
      ]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="pipeline-state-file-template">
      <code lang="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "process": "<name>",
  "stages": ["extract", "mine", "assess", "recommend"],
  "completed": [],
  "source_system": "<jira|salesforce|servicenow|sap|...>",
  "log_window": {"from": "<iso>", "to": "<iso>"},
  "case_count": 0,
  "artifacts": {
    "raw_log": null,
    "scrubbed_log": null,
    "mining_report": null,
    "assessment_matrix": null,
    "candidates": null
  }
}
      ]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Volume hallucination. Without explicit grounding, LLMs invent transaction volumes. Hard rule: cite a count from variants.csv for every Volume score.</item>
        <item>Activity-name normalization drift. "Approve PR" / "PR_APPROVED" / "approved purchase request" should collapse to one activity. LLMs may either over-merge (lose detail) or under-merge (variant explosion). Pin a normalization map.</item>
        <item>PII in activity labels. Logs like activity = "Email sent to john.doe@acme.com" push PII into the LLM context. Pre-redact with regex + presidio before mining.</item>
        <item>Vendor pitch contamination. When agent has web access, "best RPA tool for X" returns vendor blogs that bias scoring. Restrict to neutral sources or require multi-source corroboration.</item>
        <item>Loop-mining false positives. pm4py flags loops where the real process has retries on transient errors. Filter event logs by terminal states or remove sub-second consecutive duplicates first.</item>
        <item>Token blow-up at synthesis. A 50k-event log exceeds context. Pre-aggregate to variants + per-activity stats; never feed raw log to an LLM.</item>
        <item>"Estimated" creep. Agents hide unsupported claims behind "(estimated)". Hard-block: write Data not available if no log evidence; refuse to fill the cell otherwise.</item>
        <item>Auto-bias toward "automate everything". README's RPA framing nudges agents to recommend automation. Add an explicit Eliminate | Simplify | Automate decision in stage 4 with elimination preferred when feasible.</item>
        <item>Confounding cycle time and lead time. Cycle time = time the case is being worked; lead time = total elapsed. LLMs use them interchangeably. Define both in the prompt.</item>
        <item>Fabricated FTE math. "1.5 FTE saved" with no math shown is a tell. Require the formula: cycle_min_saved × cases_per_year / (60 × hours_per_FTE_year).</item>
        <item>Deterministic re-runs. Run scoring twice at temperature 0; flag any cell that differs across runs and route for human review.</item>
        <item>No automation = no observability. RPA bots fail silently; recommendation must include monitoring (Orchestrator alerts, n8n error workflow) or it is incomplete.</item>
        <item>Cron-mode interactivity gap. Scoring is automatable; selecting which top candidate to pilot is a human decision. Freeze the workflow at stage 4, emit a ranked list, do not auto-advance to implementation.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/automation-assessment.md" purpose="Process overview, 6-criterion readiness scoring table, recommendation bands, and ROI estimate section"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.tf-pm.org/resources/manifesto"/>
      <link href="https://pm4py.fit.fraunhofer.de/documentation"/>
      <link href="https://xes-standard.org"/>
      <link href="https://www.gartner.com/en/documents"/>
      <link href="https://docs.celonis.com"/>
      <link href="https://docs.uipath.com/process-mining"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/power-automate/process-mining-overview"/>
      <link href="https://apromore.com/platform/community-edition"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
