<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="finops-devops-cost-rightsizing Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for finops-devops-cost-rightsizing. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before rightsizing any production instance, verify average CPU is below 20% AND average memory is below 30% over a 14-day window. Maintain 20% headroom above peak (not average) in the target size. Always rightsize non-production environments first.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Using averages without checking peaks causes performance incidents. A 14-day window captures weekly traffic patterns. Non-production first gives evidence of safe sizing before applying to production.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Consider ARM-based instances (AWS Graviton, Azure Ampere) for eligible workloads (web servers, containerized apps, batch jobs). ARM instances deliver 20-40% better price-performance vs x86 equivalents for these workloads.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Graviton3/Ampere benchmarks show consistent throughput-per-dollar gains for Linux workloads. The migration cost is a one-time recompile/test; the savings are permanent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a monthly waste scan identifying: unattached EBS volumes/Azure Disks/GCP Persistent Disks, unused Elastic IPs/Public IPs, idle load balancers (zero healthy targets for 14+ days), orphaned snapshots older than 90 days beyond retention policy, unused NAT Gateways. Tag intentionally-retained resources with `keep=true` before the scan. Delete the rest after 5-business-day approval window.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Untagged idle resources accumulate silently. A monthly cadence prevents the backlog from exceeding one month of waste. The 5-day window catches false positives before deletion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dev and staging RDS/Cloud SQL instances MUST NOT use Multi-AZ or read replicas. Multi-AZ doubles cost for availability that non-production environments do not require. Remove Multi-AZ from all non-production databases as a first-week action.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Multi-AZ provides synchronous standby for production HA. Dev/staging have no SLA requiring this. Typical savings: $35k/month on a $70k RDS bill where dev had Multi-AZ.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Establish a weekly rightsizing review cycle: pull Compute Optimizer/Azure Advisor/GCP Active Assist recommendations, triage by savings impact, implement top recommendations within the sprint. Track implemented vs deferred count and cumulative monthly savings.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cloud provider recommendation engines update as new utilization data arrives. Checking weekly ensures new waste is caught within days, not months.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
