<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="cost-estimation">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Bottom-up cost estimation with three-point PERT per WBS package, fully-loaded labor rates, risk-driven contingency, and P80-based cost baseline for defensible project budgets.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>cost-estimation</tag>
      <tag>budgeting</tag>
      <tag>risk-management</tag>
      <tag>project-management</tag>
      <tag>pmbok</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>planning</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Cost Estimation</title>
    <summary>A bottom-up cost estimation process: decompose the WBS into work packages, apply three-point PERT estimation per package, load labor with a fully-loaded multiplier (1.3-2.0x depending on region and benefits), add tools and infrastructure costs, calculate risk-driven contingency (sum of probability x cost-exposure per open risk), separate contingency reserve from management reserve, and produce a cost baseline (BAC = Cost Baseline + Management Reserve). The agent is a calculator and auditor, not a decision-maker; humans approve all numbers before they enter the budget.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Projects fail financially because they underestimate true costs, forget indirect costs, use flat-percentage contingencies that ignore actual risk exposure, and do not update the baseline when scope changes. Risk-driven contingency calibrates to actual exposure. Tracking P80 rather than P50 means the budget is breached only 20% of the time rather than 50%. Citing sources on every rate prevents hallucinated benchmarks from corrupting the baseline.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Producing the initial budget from an approved WBS before kickoff</item>
        <item>Bottom-up cost roll-up for an RFP response requiring a defensible cost baseline</item>
        <item>Build-vs-buy / build-vs-SaaS decisions where opportunity cost matters</item>
        <item>Updating the cost baseline after an approved change-control event</item>
        <item>Solopreneur "true cost" analysis pricing own time at market rate</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Agile teams that fund team capacity by time-box, not by feature — use team-month run-rate, not bottom-up sum</item>
        <item>Pre-discovery with requirements &lt;30% defined — output will have false precision; use ROM (±50%) instead</item>
        <item>Already-negotiated fixed-fee contracts — re-estimating internally has no contractual force</item>
        <item>Tasks under 1 week where estimate cost exceeds work cost</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="cost-categories">
      <title>Cost Categories</title>
      <list>
        <item>Direct Costs — salaries, contractors, software licenses, hardware directly attributed to the project</item>
        <item>Indirect Costs — office overhead, utilities, management overhead loaded as a percentage of direct labor</item>
        <item>Fixed Costs — subscriptions, base salaries, regardless of project activity level</item>
        <item>Variable Costs — overtime, cloud usage, contractor hours that scale with project work</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="bottom-up-estimation">
      <title>Step 1: Bottom-Up Estimation</title>
      <p>For each WBS work package, estimate labor hours by role and multiply by fully-loaded rate. Example: Design (16h x $75) + Development (40h x $100) + Testing (8h x $60) + Documentation (4h x $50) = $5,880 per package. Sum all packages for total direct labor cost.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="resource-rate-loading">
      <title>Step 2: Resource Rate Loading</title>
      <list>
        <item>Full-time employee: (annual salary x fully-loaded multiplier) / working days. Multiplier: 1.3x (low-tax market) to 2.0x (high-benefit market).</item>
        <item>Contractor: hourly rate x estimated hours. Cite contract or market survey as source.</item>
        <item>Software/SaaS: license + seats + integration cost over project duration.</item>
        <item>Infrastructure: provisioned capacity x unit rate x duration; use infracost or cloud provider pricing API for accuracy.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="three-point-pert">
      <title>Step 3: Three-Point PERT</title>
      <p>For uncertain cost items: Expected Cost = (Optimistic + 4 x Most Likely + Pessimistic) / 6. Example — cloud hosting: O=$200/mo, M=$350/mo, P=$800/mo → Expected = (200 + 1400 + 800)/6 = $400/mo. Track P80 of Monte Carlo simulation as the budget target, not P50.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="risk-driven-contingency">
      <title>Step 4: Risk-Driven Contingency</title>
      <p>Sum (probability x cost_impact) for all open risks in the risk register. This replaces flat-percentage reserves, which systematically over- or under-fund based on risk profile. Unknown Unknowns (Management Reserve) is an additional 5-10% held by sponsors, released only for major scope changes.</p>
      <reference path="scripts/risk-contingency.py">Monte Carlo risk-driven contingency calculator</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="cost-baseline">
      <title>Step 5: Cost Baseline</title>
      <list>
        <item>Cost Baseline = Direct Costs + Indirect Costs + Risk-Driven Contingency Reserve</item>
        <item>Budget at Completion (BAC) = Cost Baseline + Management Reserve</item>
        <item>Lock the baseline after approval; re-baseline only on approved change requests</item>
        <item>Track Schedule Performance Index (SPI) and Cost Performance Index (CPI) from EVM weekly</item>
      </list>
      <reference path="templates/cost-worksheet.md">Full cost estimation worksheet</reference>
    </section>
    <rules>
      <rule>
        <statement>Cite source on every labor rate; reject any rate card that lacks a contract reference or market survey citation.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs hallucinate benchmark rates from stale training data; rates can differ 30%+ from current market; sourced rates are auditable and defensible.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use risk-driven contingency (sum of probability x cost_impact per open risk); do not use a flat percentage when an active risk register exists.</statement>
        <rationale>Flat contingency double-charges when combined with risk-driven reserve; it also ignores actual risk profile, over-funding low-risk and under-funding high-risk projects.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track P80 of Monte Carlo simulation as the cost target, not P50 or PERT mean.</statement>
        <rationale>P50 means the budget is breached 50% of the time; P80 provides a realistic target with acceptable overrun probability.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Separate management reserve from contingency reserve; contingency releases on identified risks; management reserve releases on scope changes only.</statement>
        <rationale>Conflating the two removes sponsor control and misrepresents budget authority.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Effort hours are not elapsed days; model resource availability when computing duration-based costs (a 40-hour task for a 60%-available person costs 100% of their rate for 66 hours elapsed, not 40).</statement>
        <rationale>Effort-elapsed confusion is the most common single source of budget overrun in agent-generated cost estimates.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </rules>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM outputs suspiciously round numbers ($50k, $100k, $200k) without showing the calculation.</description>
      <reason>Round numbers are anchors from training data, not estimates; require the bottom-up calculation or reject the output.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using a single overhead multiplier (1.3x) globally across all regions and employment types.</description>
      <reason>Overhead loading varies by region, tax regime, and benefits structure (1.3x to 2.0x); a single multiplier is wrong for cross-border projects.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Including both risk-driven contingency AND a flat 15% on top of it.</description>
      <reason>Double-charging inflates the budget and misrepresents the risk exposure; pick one method and document the choice.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Re-estimating after work has started without accounting for sunk costs, anchoring on the original number.</description>
      <reason>Re-estimates must derive from remaining scope only; anchoring to the original produces estimates that are always "a little over" the baseline.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <section name="agent-workflow">
      <title>Agentic Workflow</title>
      <p>The agent is a calculator + auditor, not a decision-maker. Feed it the WBS (work packages with effort hours), a labor rate card with sources, an infra/tools list, and a risk register; it produces a structured cost baseline (direct, indirect, contingency, management reserve) plus a Monte Carlo sensitivity. A human approves the numbers before they enter the budget. Re-run on every approved change request to keep the baseline live.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>cost-estimator — reads wbs.yaml + rates.yaml, outputs cost-baseline JSON with PERT 3-point per work package</item>
        <item>sensitivity-analyzer — Monte Carlo over the 3-point distributions, returns P50/P80/P95 totals with cost-driver tornado</item>
        <item>risk-driven-reserve — converts risk register entries (probability × impact × cost exposure) into a risk-driven contingency, replacing flat %</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor — drives implementation through quality gates once estimates become tasks</item>
      </list>
      <p>Inputs:</p>
      <list>
        <item>wbs.yaml: [{id, name, effort_optimistic_h, most_likely_h, pessimistic_h, role}]</item>
        <item>rates.yaml: hourly rate per role, with cite source field</item>
        <item>overhead: 1.3 (fully-loaded multiplier on labor)</item>
        <item>risks.yaml: risk register with cost exposure per risk</item>
        <item>duration_months: &lt;int&gt;</item>
        <item>tools.yaml: SaaS subscriptions in scope</item>
      </list>
      <p>Output JSON should include: direct_costs_usd, indirect_costs_usd, risk_driven_contingency_usd, management_reserve_usd, cost_baseline_usd, budget_at_completion_usd, sensitivity (p50, p80, p95, tornado), and assumptions.</p>
      <p>Rules:</p>
      <list>
        <item>No invented rates; rates.yaml must include source per role</item>
        <item>Round to nearest USD; never $X.XX precision</item>
        <item>If any input missing, return {"error": "..."} not a guess</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <title>Tools and Services</title>
      <p>CLI tools:</p>
      <list>
        <item>infracost — Cloud infra cost from Terraform / Pulumi diff (https://www.infracost.io/)</item>
        <item>numpy + scipy.stats — Beta / triangular / lognormal distributions for PERT (https://scipy.org/)</item>
        <item>montecarlo-cli (mcli) — Quick CLI Monte Carlo on cost ranges (https://github.com/cetra3/mcli)</item>
        <item>gh / jira-cli — Pull effort / story-point data for bottom-up (https://cli.github.com/)</item>
        <item>awscost-cli / gcloud billing / az consumption — Live cloud cost benchmarking</item>
        <item>xlsxwriter / openpyxl — Generate cost worksheets in Excel format</item>
        <item>currency-converter (cnvrt) — FX rates for multi-region budgets (OpenExchangeRates / ECB API)</item>
      </list>
      <p>Services &amp; apps:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Float / Resource Guru — SaaS, REST API. Capacity + rate cards; CSV export</item>
        <item>Harvest / Toggl — SaaS, REST API. Actual hours by role for re-baselining</item>
        <item>Forecast (Harvest) — SaaS, REST API. Project budget vs actuals</item>
        <item>Productive.io — SaaS, REST API. Agency-grade cost + margin</item>
        <item>Mosaic / Runn — SaaS, REST API. Resource forecasting</item>
        <item>Infracost — SaaS / OSS. Infra cost baseline + PR diff</item>
        <item>Vantage / CloudZero — SaaS, REST API. Cloud unit cost (cost per customer / per request)</item>
        <item>Notion / Confluence — SaaS, REST API. Where the cost baseline doc lives</item>
        <item>Excel / Google Sheets API — SaaS, REST API. Cost worksheet generation</item>
        <item>QuickBooks / Xero API — SaaS, REST API. Actuals reconciliation</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <title>Best Practices</title>
      <list>
        <item>Cite source on every rate. "Senior engineer = $X" without a source is hallucinated; require the rate card to point to a contract / market survey.</item>
        <item>Use risk-driven contingency, not flat 15%. Sum (probability × cost) of register entries; if list is empty, fix the risk process before the budget.</item>
        <item>Separate management reserve from contingency. Contingency releases on identified risks; management reserve releases on scope changes only.</item>
        <item>Track P80, not P50, in the baseline. P50 means you blow the budget half the time.</item>
        <item>Re-baseline only on approved change requests. Constant re-baselining hides slip; lock the original.</item>
        <item>Compare estimate to actual quarterly; feed estimation error back into the rate card and effort multipliers (calibration).</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <title>AI-Agent Gotchas</title>
      <list>
        <item>Rate hallucination: agents emit "$120/hr senior engineer" with no source. Always require rates.yaml as input, never let the model invent.</item>
        <item>Burden multiplier confusion: salary × 1.3 ≠ cost. Add taxes, benefits, equipment, training, idle time; "fully-loaded" can be 1.4-2.0x.</item>
        <item>Currency: agents output USD by default and silently convert; budgets must declare currency per line.</item>
        <item>Contingency double-count: risk-driven reserve PLUS a flat 15% double-charges; pick one.</item>
        <item>Stale benchmark prices: cloud, SaaS subscription, and contractor rates from training data can be 30% off; require live API fetch for high-stakes estimates.</item>
        <item>Effort-vs-elapsed: 40 effort hours is not 5 days when developer is at 60% utilisation; force the agent to multiply by availability.</item>
        <item>LLMs prefer round numbers (5, 10, 15, 25); round numbers are anchors, not estimates. Reject suspiciously round outputs.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations">
      <title>Where It Fails / Limitations</title>
      <list>
        <item>Three-point estimation gives false precision: PERT mean assumes a beta distribution rarely true in software; pessimistic cost is consistently under-estimated by humans and LLMs.</item>
        <item>Contingency reserve sized as a flat 10-25% ignores the risk register; high-risk projects need risk-driven contingency, not a percentage.</item>
        <item>Overhead loading varies by region (1.3x in low-tax markets, 1.8x+ in high-tax / high-benefit markets); a single multiplier is wrong cross-border.</item>
        <item>LLM benchmark hourly rates come from training data 12-24 months stale; current rates can differ by 30%+.</item>
        <item>Currency / FX volatility in multi-region projects is not captured by static numbers.</item>
        <item>Sunk-cost bias: re-estimates after work has started anchor on the original number rather than re-deriving from remaining scope.</item>
        <item>Cost-loaded WBS hides resource calendar effects — a $100k labour line at 50% utilisation actually costs $200k of elapsed budget.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/cost-worksheet.md" purpose="Full cost estimation table: direct / indirect / reserves / total budget" />
    </templates>
    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/risk-contingency.py" purpose="Risk-driven contingency via Monte Carlo over Bernoulli risk events; outputs expected, P50, P80, P95" />
    </scripts>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://pmi.org/learning/pmbok-guide">PMI PMBOK Guide 6th Ed., Chapter 7 — Project Cost Management</link>
      <link href="https://www.aacei.org/">AACE International Recommended Practice 18R-97 (Cost Estimate Classification)</link>
      <link href="https://www.howtomeasureanything.com/">Hubbard, How to Measure Anything (2014) — calibrated estimation</link>
      <link href="https://www.stevemcconnell.com/">McConnell, Software Estimation: Demystifying the Black Art (2006)</link>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COCOMO">COCOMO II model for parametric software estimation</link>
      <link href="https://www.goldratt.com/">Goldratt, The Goal — buffer placement vs per-task padding</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
