<text id="01-concepts" title="WireGuard VPN: Concepts">

  <summary>
    WireGuard uses cryptokey routing: each peer's AllowedIPs list defines which source IPs its key is trusted to send from, and which destination IPs get encrypted to that peer. ~4,000 lines of kernel code vs OpenVPN's 100,000+.
  </summary>

  <section title="Cryptokey Routing">
    <p>When a packet arrives on a WireGuard interface, the source IP is checked against every peer's AllowedIPs. If it matches, the packet is accepted and decrypted with that peer's key. If it does not match any peer's AllowedIPs, the packet is silently dropped.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>AllowedIPs serves two purposes: ingress filter (which source IPs to accept) and egress routing table (which destination IPs to send to this peer).</statement>
      <rationale>This dual role is the core of WireGuard's simplicity — no separate routing table entries needed, no certificate authority, just keys and IP ranges.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
# Server sees packets from 10.0.0.2 → trusts them if signed by laptop's key
# Server sees packets for 10.0.0.2 → encrypts and sends to laptop

Peer (laptop): AllowedIPs = 10.0.0.2/32
Peer (RPi + LAN): AllowedIPs = 10.0.0.3/32, 192.168.1.0/24
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Types">
    <list>
      <item>Private key — generated with `wg genkey`. Never leave the device. chmod 600.</item>
      <item>Public key — derived from private key with `wg pubkey`. Share with all peers who need to connect to you.</item>
      <item>Preshared key — optional symmetric key shared between two specific peers. Adds a post-quantum resistance layer. Generated with `wg genpsk`.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Network Architecture">
    <p>VPS acts as the hub. All peers connect to it. Peer-to-peer traffic routes through the VPS unless direct routing is configured.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
VPS wg0: 10.0.0.1/24  (hub)
  Peer: dev laptop  10.0.0.2/32  (split tunnel)
  Peer: home RPi    10.0.0.3/32 + 192.168.1.0/24  (site-to-site)
  Peer: phone       10.0.0.4/32  (full tunnel)
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Full Tunnel vs Split Tunnel">
    <p>The only difference is AllowedIPs on the client config.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Full tunnel: `AllowedIPs = 0.0.0.0/0, ::/0` — all traffic routes through VPN</item>
      <item>Split tunnel: `AllowedIPs = 10.0.0.0/24` — only VPN subnet uses tunnel, internet goes direct</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-configuration.xml">Server and client configuration details</link>
    <link path="templates/wg0-server.conf">Server config with multiple peer types</link>
  </see-also>

</text>
