<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="onboarding-30-day Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for onboarding-30-day. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The 30-day phase has one primary objective: build foundation of knowledge and relationships. Do not assign production ownership in the first 30 days; shadow first, contribute second.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">20% of voluntary turnover happens within the first 45 days. Effective structured onboarding (82% retention improvement per BambooHR) requires deliberate sequencing, not front-loading responsibilities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every 30-day plan must define exactly one meaningful milestone: the first PR shipped, the first sales call completed, the first support ticket resolved. "Completed all training" is not a valid milestone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Activity-based milestones measure compliance, not contribution. A contribution milestone creates a shared definition of success and prevents "set and forget" plans that no one revisits.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run three structured check-ins during the 30-day phase: Day 7 (first week experience), Day 14 (buddy/navigation), Day 30 (milestone assessment). Each check-in has a written agenda prepared in advance.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Check-ins without written agendas default to "how's it going?" — which produces no actionable information and misses blocked items that are invisible to managers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never auto-schedule calendar invites without reading freebusy data first. Always check for conflicts before generating an .ics file or sending invites.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Auto-scheduled invites without freebusy checks produce double-bookings on Day 1, creating a bad first impression that is difficult to recover from.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Day 1 agenda: working laptop, accounts configured, lunch with team. No heavy training modules on Day 1.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">First impressions are sticky. A new hire who spends Day 1 watching compliance videos and waiting for IT access remembers that experience. Functional setup + human connection on Day 1 drives 30-day satisfaction scores.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Onboarding plans may contain manager-only information (project codenames, customer names, team rosters). Enforce visibility boundaries — do not include restricted information in new-hire-visible onboarding documents.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">New hires do not have the same information access as managers on Day 1. Including restricted details in their onboarding doc creates an unauthorized disclosure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>HRIS data sent to LLM prompts for onboarding plan generation must comply with GDPR and local data protection rules. Do not send personal data across jurisdictions without verified legal basis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Personal data (name, role, manager, project assignment) crossing borders into LLM API calls may require data processing agreements not yet in place for new-hire data.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
