<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="30-Day Onboarding Phase Framework">
  <summary>Day 1-30 phase structure with weekly objectives, single-milestone rule, and check-in schedule.</summary>

  <section title="Phase objectives">
    <rule>
      <statement>The 30-day phase has one primary objective: build foundation of knowledge and relationships. Do not assign production ownership in the first 30 days; shadow first, contribute second.</statement>
      <rationale>20% of voluntary turnover happens within the first 45 days. Effective structured onboarding (82% retention improvement per BambooHR) requires deliberate sequencing, not front-loading responsibilities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Days 1-7 (Orientation): HR paperwork, IT setup, meet direct team, manager 1:1 on role expectations, review company docs.</item>
      <item>Days 8-14 (Foundation): required training modules, shadow key workflows, meet cross-functional stakeholders, primary tools.</item>
      <item>Days 15-30 (Deep Dive): understand current projects, review past work, identify gaps, begin small tasks with guidance.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Single-milestone rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every 30-day plan must define exactly one meaningful milestone: the first PR shipped, the first sales call completed, the first support ticket resolved. "Completed all training" is not a valid milestone.</statement>
      <rationale>Activity-based milestones measure compliance, not contribution. A contribution milestone creates a shared definition of success and prevents "set and forget" plans that no one revisits.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Software Engineer — 30-Day Milestone
Ship first PR to production (typo fix, documentation, or small bug fix
guided by team lead). PR must pass CI and receive at least one approved review.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Bad milestone
Complete all required LMS training modules by Day 30.
      ]]></code>
      <note>This measures activity (course clicks), not contribution. A new hire can complete all training and still be lost on Day 31.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Check-in schedule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run three structured check-ins during the 30-day phase: Day 7 (first week experience), Day 14 (buddy/navigation), Day 30 (milestone assessment). Each check-in has a written agenda prepared in advance.</statement>
      <rationale>Check-ins without written agendas default to "how's it going?" — which produces no actionable information and misses blocked items that are invisible to managers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Day 7: manager 1:1 — first week experience, blockers, questions.</item>
      <item>Day 14: buddy check — navigation questions, culture, team dynamics.</item>
      <item>Day 30: manager review — milestone assessment, 60-day goals, satisfaction rating.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/30-day-plan.md">Universal 30-day plan template with week-by-week structure and success criteria.</reference>
</text>
