<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="onboarding-30-day Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for onboarding-30-day as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Including "review company values" or "explore documentation" without linking to a specific page or resource.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generic tasks are busywork that new hires complete by opening a random wiki page. Every task must point to a named resource; agents should fail loudly if the resource link is missing from the input context.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Applying US-style "celebrate Day 1" high-energy onboarding tone to DE/JP/UA new hires without localization.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Onboarding formality norms differ significantly across cultures. An overly casual, celebrations-heavy tone lands awkwardly in markets where professional distance is expected in the first weeks.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs cargo-culting generic onboarding tasks without ingesting team-specific runbooks, producing generic output.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without actual workflow tools, team structure, and runbook context, agents auto-generate placeholder tasks that don't reflect the real onboarding experience. Require team-specific runbook input before generating a 30-day plan.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Calendar invites for week 1 generated without timezone awareness and conflict checking, producing overlapping events.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents auto-scheduling without read access to calendars create double-bookings and look unprofessional. Always validate freebusy before generating .ics invites.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
