<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules-and-gotchas" title="Onboarding Agent Rules and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Calendar conflict risks, privacy constraints, localization issues, and agent-specific failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Generic-task injection">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Including "review company values" or "explore documentation" without linking to a specific page or resource.</description>
      <reason>Generic tasks are busywork that new hires complete by opening a random wiki page. Every task must point to a named resource; agents should fail loudly if the resource link is missing from the input context.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Calendar scheduling rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never auto-schedule calendar invites without reading freebusy data first. Always check for conflicts before generating an .ics file or sending invites.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-scheduled invites without freebusy checks produce double-bookings on Day 1, creating a bad first impression that is difficult to recover from.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Day 1 agenda: working laptop, accounts configured, lunch with team. No heavy training modules on Day 1.</statement>
      <rationale>First impressions are sticky. A new hire who spends Day 1 watching compliance videos and waiting for IT access remembers that experience. Functional setup + human connection on Day 1 drives 30-day satisfaction scores.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Privacy constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Onboarding plans may contain manager-only information (project codenames, customer names, team rosters). Enforce visibility boundaries — do not include restricted information in new-hire-visible onboarding documents.</statement>
      <rationale>New hires do not have the same information access as managers on Day 1. Including restricted details in their onboarding doc creates an unauthorized disclosure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>HRIS data sent to LLM prompts for onboarding plan generation must comply with GDPR and local data protection rules. Do not send personal data across jurisdictions without verified legal basis.</statement>
      <rationale>Personal data (name, role, manager, project assignment) crossing borders into LLM API calls may require data processing agreements not yet in place for new-hire data.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Localization">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying US-style "celebrate Day 1" high-energy onboarding tone to DE/JP/UA new hires without localization.</description>
      <reason>Onboarding formality norms differ significantly across cultures. An overly casual, celebrations-heavy tone lands awkwardly in markets where professional distance is expected in the first weeks.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/bootstrap-newhire.sh">Agent entry point: generate plan from inputs and create GitHub issue for manager.</reference>
</text>
