<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Niche Disqualifier Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules for filtering cold inbound to protect a freelancer's specialisation premium.</summary>

  <section title="Disqualifier rules">

    <rule id="r1-hard-no-list" testable="true">
      <statement>The freelancer maintains a written hard-no list — at least 5 named industries / company types / project shapes outside the specialisation. A lead whose brief matches any hard-no item is rejected without a call.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a pre-written list, every lead gets the benefit of the doubt and lands in the discovery-call funnel, eroding capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-5-min-budget" testable="true">
      <statement>Each cold lead gets at most 5 minutes of evaluation time before deciding "discovery call" or "not a fit". 5 minutes is enough to scan a website, check LinkedIn, and read the inbound brief. Longer evaluations migrate decision quality into politeness and waste capacity.</statement>
      <rationale>Solo operators systematically under-budget evaluation time and over-budget polite engagement. A hard cap converts a fuzzy "should I take this call" into a deterministic decision.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-below-floor-rejected" testable="true">
      <statement>If the brief states or implies a budget below the floor rate, the lead is rejected. Acceptable evidence: "we have a $2k budget", "looking for entry-level", "should be quick — about 4 hours". No counter-offer at the floor, no negotiation.</statement>
      <rationale>Counter-offers at the floor signal flexibility and invite further negotiation downward. A flat rejection preserves price discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-decision-maker-named" testable="true">
      <statement>The brief must name the decision-maker (title or person). Briefs from "the team", "we're exploring options", or "I'll need to check with my co-founder before deciding anything" are rejected as not-yet-ready.</statement>
      <rationale>Multi-stakeholder briefs without a named decision-maker convert at &lt;5% and consume 3x more discovery time. Filtering them out at intake protects pipeline health.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-counter-on-disqualifier" testable="true">
      <statement>When a lead is rejected on a disqualifier signal, the reply is a single short paragraph that does NOT propose alternative pricing, alternative scope, or a future-fit window. Forbidden phrases: "but if you bump to $X", "happy to do a smaller scope", "circle back next quarter".</statement>
      <rationale>Counter-offers in rejection emails reopen negotiation and re-introduce the leak the filter exists to close.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <code lang="txt"><![CDATA[
Hi Sam,

Thanks for the note. Crypto exchanges sit outside the work I take on, so this
isn't going to be a fit. I'd point you toward the r/freelancedev hire board for
folks who specialise there.

Best,
A
]]></code>
    <note>Names the disqualifier (industry mismatch), no counter-offer, gives a low-friction alternative, under 60 words.</note>
  </example>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Lead writes "I have a $1k budget for a 4-week project" — freelancer replies "could you stretch to $3k? I might be able to make it work" and ends up running a $3k version of a $12k project.</description>
    <reason>Violates r3 and r5. Counter-offers at the disqualifier signal anchor the freelancer to a discount, training the inbound channel to under-bid.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
