<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="personas">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Create research-backed fictional user characters (3–5 primary) representing distinct user types to unify team decisions and prevent design-by-assumption.</summary>
    <category>research</category>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>personas</tag>
      <tag>research</tag>
      <tag>user-centered</tag>
      <tag>methodology</tag>
      <tag>ux</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="user-interviews"/>
      <ref slug="jobs-to-be-done"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Personas</title>

    <summary>Personas are fictional characters representing key user types, based on research. They unify team decisions by answering "would our user want this?" without shared personas, teams design by assumption, team members disagree on who the user is, discussions become opinion battles, and features nobody wants ship. Cap personas at 3–5 primary; each must include goals, frustrations, behaviors, and at least one verbatim quote tied to a research participant. Pair every persona with a JTBD ("Sarah hires the dashboard to look prepared in meetings"). Keep persona docs short (≤1 page); long personas get skimmed and forgotten. Date-stamp personas; mark as DRAFT until validated against ≥10 users. Re-cluster after every meaningful research wave (quarterly minimum).</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Teams design for themselves instead of users. Different team members have different ideas of who the user is. Discussions about features become opinion battles. Nobody can answer "would our user want this?" Without shared understanding, products miss the mark and iterate on false assumptions.</p>
      <p>Research-based personas ground feature prioritization in evidence. They scale decision-making without requiring every designer to re-read interview transcripts. Personas make the user present in the room.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>After ≥6 user interviews, when patterns are emerging and the team needs shared shorthand.</item>
        <item>Onboarding new designers / PMs / engineers to a product's user base.</item>
        <item>Pre-feature discussions where "would the user want this?" keeps surfacing.</item>
        <item>B2B products with distinct buyer / champion / end-user roles that need separate treatment.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-research: "made-up" personas reinforce assumptions and push the team in the wrong direction.</item>
        <item>Pure technical infrastructure work where the user IS the developer.</item>
        <item>Single-customer enterprise projects — a stakeholder map is more useful than personas.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="persona-types">
      <p>Three types of personas exist, each serving a different purpose and phase of the product lifecycle.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Distinguish research-based personas (after ≥6 interviews), provisional personas (assumptions to validate), and proto-personas (team's current understanding for quick alignment). Only research-based personas should drive feature decisions.</statement>
        <rationale>Provisional and proto-personas are scaffolding — useful for kickoff, but lack evidence. Building product on them propagates assumptions. Upgrade to research-based as data arrives.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Research-based persona with quote evidence">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
# Persona: Sarah, The Busy Manager

## Demographics
- Age: 38
- Role: Marketing Manager
- Location: Urban, US
- Experience: Tech-comfortable, not expert

## Quote
> "I don't have time to dig through dashboards. Just tell me
> what I need to know."
— Sarah, Interview #4, April 2026

## About
Sarah manages a team of 8 and oversees marketing campaigns.
She's constantly in meetings and checks reports between
calls. She values efficiency and clear communication.

## Goals
1. Get quick insights on campaign performance
2. Report results to leadership with confidence
3. Make data-driven decisions without becoming a data analyst

## Frustrations
1. Reports that require too many clicks to understand
2. Data presented without context or recommendations
3. Tools that require training to use effectively

## Behaviors
- Checks dashboards on mobile between meetings
- Prefers summaries over detailed data
- Delegates deep analysis to team members
- Trusts tools that save her time

## Context
- When: Early morning, between meetings
- Where: Office, commute, home
- Devices: Laptop at desk, phone on the go

## Scenario
Monday 9am: Sarah has 10 minutes before her weekly leadership
meeting. She opens the app on her phone, sees the key metrics
summary, notes that Campaign A is underperforming, and has
talking points ready.

## Key Insights for Design
- Mobile experience is critical
- Default to summary views, allow drill-down
- Highlight anomalies and recommendations
- Export-friendly for presentations
        ]]></code>
        <note>One-page format; grounded in a real interview participant (Sarah, Interview #4).</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Proto-persona for kickoff alignment">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
# Proto-Persona: Tom, The Data Engineer

## Who are they?
- Writes SQL; skeptical of "magic" (AI summaries without source data)
- Owns 30+ downstream data pipelines
- Only uses dashboards if they export exact numbers

## What do they want?
- Reproducible, auditable data pipelines
- Export to CSV so he can validate locally

## What frustrates them?
- "Top insights" claims without justifying the algorithm
- UI-only exports (can't automate via API)

## How do we help them?
- Expose the SQL behind summaries; link to the dashboard filters used
- Provide CSV/JSON export and API endpoints for automation

## Assumptions to validate
- Do data engineers really distrust UI summaries?
- How many of our target users are engineers (not analysts)?
- Would API access unblock adoption?
        ]]></code>
        <note>Quick 5-minute format for team alignment before research. Mark as DRAFT.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Persona-as-demographic-profile">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
# Persona: The 35-year-old Female Manager

- Age: 35
- Gender: Female
- Income: $80–120k
- Married, no children
- Lives in suburban area
        ]]></code>
        <note>Demographics alone tell you nothing actionable. Missing goals, behaviors, frustrations, quote.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Too many personas (8+) that the team cannot remember.</description>
        <reason>Each additional persona dilutes focus. Beyond 5 primary + 2 secondary, teams default to "it applies to everyone" and personas become wallpaper.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Personas without scenarios are pretty posters, ignored in real decisions.</description>
        <reason>Abstract goals feel detached. Scenarios (Sarah's Monday 9am rush) make the persona operational — designers test features against the scenario, not the persona name.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM-generated personas inherit dataset biases; they look real but reproduce stereotypes.</description>
        <reason>Agents synthesize plausible-sounding personas from averages. Require quote-with-participant-ID for every trait; reject invented demographic attributes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="persona-elements">
      <p>Each persona must include these elements to be actionable:</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every persona MUST include: name, photo/illustration, demographics, goals (3–5), frustrations (3–5), behaviors (≥2), context (when/where/devices), scenario, and at least one verbatim quote tied to a research participant. Personas without scenarios are wallpaper.</statement>
        <rationale>Name makes it real. Photo (illustration, not AI-generated) makes it human. Goals and frustrations are decision criteria. Behaviors show how they work. Scenario operationalizes the persona — designers test features against "would this help Sarah on Monday 9am?" not just "is this for a manager?" Quote-with-ID prevents agent fabrication.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="research-to-persona-workflow">
      <p>Convert research data to personas via clustering and evidence-based synthesis.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Conduct ≥6 user interviews before persona creation. Cluster interview transcripts by goals + behaviors (NOT demographics). For each cluster, surface 3+ verbatim quotes from ≥2 participants. Reject clusters supported by fewer than 2 participants. Cap at 3–5 clusters, each representing a primary persona.</statement>
        <rationale>≥6 interviews surface recurring patterns; fewer interviews amplify noise. Goal/behavior clustering is more predictive than demographics. Verbatim quotes with participant ID prevent agent paraphrasing and ensure grounding in evidence. Reject noise (single-mention outliers). 3–5 clusters keep the team focused.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Clustering workflow prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Read these <N> interview transcripts. Group participants into
2–5 clusters by goals + behaviors (NOT demographics). For each
cluster output:
- 3 representative verbatim quotes
- 3 shared goals
- 3 shared frustrations
- 1 contrasting cluster

Reject clusters supported by fewer than 2 participants.
        ]]></code>
        <note>Agent-assisted clustering. Humans review output, name clusters, create persona documents.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Scenario validation prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Given persona <name> and feature <X>, write a 1-paragraph
scenario showing them succeeding with <X>, then a parallel
scenario showing them failing. Use only behaviors and contexts
already documented in the persona file.
        ]]></code>
        <note>Validate that personas are internally consistent and scenarios make sense.</note>
      </example>

      <note>Recommended subagents: `faion-ux-researcher-agent` (clusters transcripts, surfaces candidate personas with quote evidence), `faion-usability-agent` (validates personas against fresh usability findings), general Claude subagent (drafts proto-personas from sales/support tickets when interviews are unavailable).</note>
    </section>

    <section name="using-personas">
      <p>Personas drive decisions only if they are active in the conversation.</p>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Reference personas by name in design reviews, requirements, and prioritization. Track which decisions referenced which persona to measure usage. Date-stamp personas; mark as DRAFT until validated against ≥10 users. Re-cluster after every meaningful research wave (quarterly minimum).</statement>
        <rationale>Active reference embeds personas into workflow. Tracking usage surfaces which personas drive decisions (and which are ignored). Dating and refresh cycles prevent outdated personas from ossifying into false assumptions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Persona reference in design review">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Design review question:
"Would Sarah understand this dashboard view in 10 seconds?"
"How would this feature help Sarah's goal of quick insights?"

(Cite Sarah, the Busy Manager, by name and specific goal.)
        ]]></code>
        <note>Makes the persona operational; forces discussion of how the design serves the user's needs.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Persona-driven prioritization">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Feature A helps Sarah (primary persona) + Tom (secondary).
Feature B helps Tom (secondary) only.
→ Prioritize Feature A.

Track: "Feature A prioritized per Sarah persona, Feb 2026."
        ]]></code>
        <note>Document why the persona drove the decision for post-hoc validation.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Persona+JTBD mismatch">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Persona: Sarah, The Busy Manager
Goal (from persona): Quick insights on campaign performance
Feature: 47-step onboarding wizard to configure data sources

"Why are we building this? Sarah doesn't configure sources;
her data team does. This doesn't match Sarah's job."
        ]]></code>
        <note>JTBD (Sarah hires the dashboard to look informed) contradicts the feature design. Feature is actually for Tom, the Data Engineer, not Sarah.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="persona-decay-and-refresh">
      <p>Personas degrade over time. Products and audiences shift faster than personas are updated.</p>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Schedule persona refresh at least quarterly or after every major product pivot. Demographic-heavy personas (age, gender) tell you nothing actionable — replace with goal-behavior clusters. Personas without scenarios are wallpaper; pair every persona with a usage scenario and JTBD.</statement>
        <rationale>Without refresh cycles, personas become outdated mythology. Goal-behavior clusters forecast feature fit better than age cohorts. Scenarios + JTBD make personas operational decision-makers, not decoration.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="anti-patterns">
      <p>Common failures that break persona usage:</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Creating personas before research — "made-up" personas reinforce assumptions and push the team in the wrong direction.</description>
        <reason>Pre-research personas become self-fulfilling prophecies. Teams design to confirm, not discover. Wait for evidence.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Personas that are just demographics (age, gender, income) with no goals or behaviors.</description>
        <reason>Demographics don't predict behavior. A 35-year-old female manager and a 35-year-old female engineer have nothing in common. Goals and behaviors are the decision-making levers.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Photos generated by AI; introduces demographic bias and accessibility issues.</description>
        <reason>AI-generated faces encode dataset biases and can misrepresent marginalized groups. Use illustrations or initials instead.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents paraphrasing quotes silently; personas become agent interpretations, not evidence.</description>
        <reason>Paraphrasing loses nuance and lets agents inject their own biases. Every trait must have a verbatim quote with participant ID.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents inventing demographic attributes that weren't in source data.</description>
        <reason>LLMs synthesize plausible-sounding attributes. If the research says "Sarah is a manager" but doesn't mention income or family status, the agent shouldn't invent it. Stick to documented traits.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents producing 8+ personas if not capped explicitly.</description>
        <reason>Unconstrained agents maximize coverage. Enforce max-cluster constraint and reject low-frequency clusters.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Re-clustering on a different week produces different personas; no locking of corpus snapshot.</description>
        <reason>Different data → different clusters. Lock the interview corpus used; timestamp the clustering. If you re-cluster, note it as a refresh, not a redo.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="personas-and-jtbd">
      <p>Personas answer WHO; JTBD answers WHAT job they're hiring the product for. Combine both:</p>

      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Persona: WHO is using the product
JTBD: WHAT job they're hiring it for

Sarah (persona) hires the dashboard (product) to
make her look informed in leadership meetings (job).

This pairing predicts whether a feature helps:
- Feature: Mobile app that shows summaries? → YES, helps Sarah
  look informed while mobile.
- Feature: Source data configuration UI? → NO, Sarah doesn't
  configure sources; that's Tom's job (different JTBD).
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="checklist">
      <checklist>
        <check>Personas based on real research (≥6 interviews minimum)</check>
        <check>Limited to 3–5 primary personas</check>
        <check>Include goals (3–5 per persona), not just demographics</check>
        <check>Pain points clearly articulated</check>
        <check>Behaviors described (how they typically act)</check>
        <check>Context of use included (when, where, devices)</check>
        <check>Each persona includes ≥1 verbatim quote tied to participant ID</check>
        <check>Scenario included (usage story that shows the persona in action)</check>
        <check>Paired with JTBD ("Sarah hires the dashboard to...")</check>
        <check>Validated with team</check>
        <check>Shared across organization</check>
        <check>Referenced in design decisions</check>
        <check>Dated and marked DRAFT until validated against ≥10 users</check>
        <check>Updated as research continues (quarterly minimum)</check>
      </checklist>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/persona/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/personas-why-and-how-you-should-use-them"/>
      <link href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2014/08/a-closer-look-at-personas-part-1/"/>
      <link href="https://uxdesign.cc/lean-user-personas-looking-into-lean-ux-personas-and-user-types-702bb75c8e8f"/>
      <ref slug="user-interviews"/>
      <ref slug="jobs-to-be-done"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
