<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-new-criteria" title="WCAG 2.2 New and Changed Success Criteria">
  <summary>All 9 new WCAG 2.2 success criteria with levels, requirements, pass/fail examples, and implementation notes; includes the 4.1.1 Parsing removal.</summary>

  <section title="New Level A Criteria">
    <section title="3.2.6 Consistent Help">
      <rule>
        <statement>If a help mechanism (help link, contact, chat widget) appears on multiple pages, it must appear in the same relative order on each page.</statement>
        <rationale>Users with cognitive disabilities rely on consistent placement to find help; "consistent" means relative position in the page section, not pixel-exact coordinates.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Consistent: "Help" link always last item in header nav
Consistent: "Contact us" always in footer before legal links
Consistent: Chat widget always bottom-right corner
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Fail: Help link appears in header on home page, in sidebar on product page
Fail: Chat widget visible on landing but hidden on checkout
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section title="3.3.7 Redundant Entry">
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not ask users to enter the same information twice in a session unless security requires re-verification or the previous entry is no longer valid.</statement>
        <rationale>Repeated entry creates barriers for users with cognitive disabilities, motor impairments, and slow typists; also improves conversion for all users.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Checkout: "Same as billing address" checkbox pre-fills shipping
Multi-step form: email entered in step 1 is pre-filled or not asked in step 2
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Fail: Step 1 asks for email; Step 2 asks for email again with no justification
Fail: Billing and shipping forms both blank with no "copy billing" option
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="New Level AA Criteria">
    <section title="2.4.11 Focus Not Obscured (Minimum)">
      <rule>
        <statement>When a component receives keyboard focus, the focus indicator must not be completely hidden by sticky headers, cookie banners, chat widgets, or modal overlays.</statement>
        <rationale>At least a partial focus indicator must remain visible. Fix: add scroll-margin-top matching the sticky header height, or adjust z-index.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
/* Fix: scroll focused elements clear of sticky header */
:focus {
  scroll-margin-top: 80px; /* match sticky header height */
}
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section title="2.5.7 Dragging Movements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every drag-and-drop operation must have a non-drag alternative (button-driven move or keyboard shortcut); keyboard-only drag is insufficient because screen reader users cannot use it.</statement>
        <rationale>WCAG 2.5.7 (AA). Drag-and-drop completely excludes users with motor disabilities and screen reader users.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
<!-- Reorderable list: keep drag but add button alternatives -->
<li>
  Item 1
  <button aria-label="Move up">Up</button>
  <button aria-label="Move down">Down</button>
</li>

<!-- Resize: add input field alternative -->
<label>Width: <input type="number" value="200"> px</label>
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section title="2.5.8 Target Size (Minimum)">
      <rule>
        <statement>Touch and click targets must be at least 24x24 CSS pixels, or have 24px of spacing around them. WCAG 2.2 AA minimum is 24x24 — not 44x44 (that is the iOS HIG / WCAG 2.5.5 AAA recommendation).</statement>
        <rationale>Agents and older guidance confuse 24px (WCAG 2.2 AA) with 44px (Apple HIG / WCAG AAA). Always cite the correct threshold in code reviews.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
/* WCAG 2.2 AA minimum */
.btn { min-width: 24px; min-height: 24px; }

/* Recommended for primary mobile actions (good practice, not 2.2 AA) */
@media (pointer: coarse) {
  .btn-primary { min-width: 44px; min-height: 44px; }
}
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section title="3.3.8 Accessible Authentication (Minimum)">
      <rule>
        <statement>Login must not require a cognitive function test — no memorizing passwords character-by-character, no math puzzles. Password managers, biometrics, magic links, and passkeys all pass.</statement>
        <rationale>Must allow paste and autocomplete so password managers work. Never set autocomplete="off" on password fields.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
<!-- Allow password manager autofill -->
<input type="email" autocomplete="username">
<input type="password" autocomplete="current-password">
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
<!-- Fails 3.3.8: blocks paste and password managers -->
<input type="password" autocomplete="off" onpaste="return false">
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Removed Criterion">
    <rule>
      <statement>4.1.1 Parsing has been removed from WCAG 2.2; do not report it as a violation in audits or automated scan output.</statement>
      <rationale>Browsers now handle HTML parsing errors gracefully. Automated tools trained on older data still flag it; strip from outputs. HTML validation remains good practice but is no longer a WCAG criterion.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
