<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-migration-checklist" title="WCAG 2.1 to 2.2 Migration Checklist">
  <summary>Ordered checklist for migrating from WCAG 2.1 to 2.2, grouped by effort level, with axe-core version and manual-test requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Tooling Prerequisites">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use axe-core >= 4.8 for WCAG 2.2 rules; older versions lack target-size and focus-not-obscured rules, and still report the removed 4.1.1 Parsing.</statement>
      <rationale>Pinning to an old version produces false negatives for new SC and false positives for the removed criterion.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Quick Wins (low effort, high impact)">
    <list>
      <item>Enable paste and autocomplete on all auth fields — set autocomplete="username" / "current-password"; never autocomplete="off". (3.3.8)</item>
      <item>Add "Same as billing address" checkbox or pre-fill on checkout/profile forms. (3.3.7)</item>
      <item>Ensure sticky headers do not fully obscure focused elements — add scroll-margin-top. (2.4.11)</item>
      <item>Verify all click targets measure >= 24x24 CSS px in DevTools. (2.5.8)</item>
      <item>Verify help link/chat widget appears in the same location across all pages. (3.2.6)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Moderate Effort">
    <list>
      <item>Add keyboard-button alternatives (up/down buttons, move-to-column dropdowns) to all drag-and-drop interactions. (2.5.7)</item>
      <item>Pre-fill or omit any form field whose value was already provided earlier in the same session. (3.3.7)</item>
      <item>Remove cognitive function tests from login: replace image CAPTCHA with behavioral/invisible CAPTCHA or passkeys. (3.3.8 / 3.3.9)</item>
      <item>Audit multi-step forms for field repetition; consolidate or auto-populate. (3.3.7)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Higher Effort">
    <list>
      <item>Implement passkey authentication (WebAuthn) — cleanly satisfies 3.3.8 and 3.3.9. (3.3.8 / 3.3.9 AAA)</item>
      <item>Replace all image CAPTCHA with invisible reCAPTCHA, hCaptcha accessibility mode, or rate limiting. (3.3.9 AAA)</item>
      <item>Full focus-visibility audit across all sticky elements (cookie banners, headers, toast notifications, chat widgets). (2.4.11 / 2.4.12 AAA)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Manual Testing Required">
    <rule>
      <statement>The following WCAG 2.2 criteria cannot be verified by automated tools alone and require structured manual testing.</statement>
      <rationale>axe-core covers target-size and partial focus-not-obscured; drag alternatives, redundant entry, consistent help, and authentication require human walkthroughs of real interaction flows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/target-size-playwright.js">Playwright + axe automation for 2.5.8 target size and 2.5.7 drag alternative checks</reference>
    <list>
      <item>2.4.11 Focus Not Obscured: manually scroll each page with keyboard, observe whether sticky elements hide focused items.</item>
      <item>2.5.7 Dragging Movements: try every drag interaction; confirm button alternatives work independently.</item>
      <item>3.2.6 Consistent Help: navigate at least 5 pages; verify help mechanism relative position is unchanged.</item>
      <item>3.3.7 Redundant Entry: complete each multi-step form flow end to end; check no field is asked twice unnecessarily.</item>
      <item>3.3.8 Accessible Authentication: test login with a password manager (1Password, Bitwarden); confirm paste works.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
