<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Wireframing Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Wireframing. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-four-section-format" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every wireframe carries four sections: information hierarchy (H1 / H2 / body slots), layout grid (columns + breakpoints), primary actions (CTA placement + label), content slots (named regions); free-form wireframes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Wireframing-discipline practice">Free-form wireframes vary too much; the fixed shape makes wireframes comparable across screens and agent-trainable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-grayscale-and-system-font" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Wireframes are grayscale + system font + no imagery + placeholder text. Color, brand font, and real imagery are rejected at wireframe fidelity.</statement>
      <rationale source="Low-fidelity-discipline convention">Polish sends the wrong signal: stakeholders critique aesthetics instead of structure; deliberate low-fidelity keeps feedback on layout.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-time-box-30-60-min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Wireframe is delivered within 30-60 minutes per screen; sessions longer than 60 min are split into multiple wireframes.</statement>
      <rationale source="MVP-iteration principle">Over-built wireframes drift toward high-fidelity; the time-box keeps fidelity honest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-primary-action-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Primary action is a single named CTA per screen (verb + object: &apos;Place order&apos; / &apos;Add to cart&apos;); generic &apos;Submit&apos; or &apos;OK&apos; are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Action-clarity convention">Generic CTAs hide intent; named CTAs ground the conversation about the screen&apos;s purpose.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-no-imagery-no-real-text" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No real product imagery, no real marketing copy; placeholder Lorem or &apos;Image: hero (16:9)&apos; annotations only.</statement>
      <rationale source="Low-fidelity-discipline convention">Real content triggers brand-tone debate before structure is settled.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-wireframing.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
