<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-closure-process" title="Project Closure — Seven-Step Process">
  <summary>Concrete steps to formally close a project: obtain acceptance, release resources, close contracts, capture lessons, archive documents, write the final report, transition to operations, and celebrate.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Verify Deliverable Acceptance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Obtain written acceptance for every deliverable before declaring closure; verbal confirmation does not hold at invoice time.</statement>
      <rationale>Ambiguous acceptance is the most common source of post-project invoice disputes and scope creep into "maintenance" work that was never bought.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>For each deliverable, confirm: all requirements met, testing complete, documentation delivered, sign-off obtained in writing.</p>
    <reference path="templates/acceptance-form.md">Per-deliverable acceptance form with criteria table and signature block.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Administrative Closure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Process all financial, resource, and contract closure actions within the closure window; do not leave open POs or un-released team members.</statement>
      <rationale>Open contracts accumulate charges. Resources "stuck" on finished projects block new assignments and frustrate individuals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Financial: final invoices, close POs, return unused budget, reconcile costs.</item>
      <item>Resource: release team members, return equipment, revoke access/permissions, notify resource managers.</item>
      <item>Contract: final vendor payments, warranty/support handover, termination letters, archive agreements.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Lessons Learned">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the lessons-learned session before the team disperses, not after; memory and candor both degrade within days.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-dispersal sessions yield low attendance and sanitized data. Lessons captured in flight are richer and more actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Document what worked and what did not; store in the organizational knowledge base. Capture both successes and failures — teams that log only failures stop contributing honestly.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Archive Project Documents">
    <rule>
      <statement>Archive documents into named categories (planning, execution, technical, contracts, closure) with a manifest so they can be found in 12 months.</statement>
      <rationale>Unstructured "shared drive" archives are unfindable; without a manifest, future auditors and PMs have no entry point.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/closeout-archive.sh">Shell script to bundle the archive with per-category folders and SHA-256 manifest.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Write Final Project Report">
    <p>Document project completion covering: executive summary, deliverables, schedule/budget/scope/quality performance, key accomplishments, challenges and resolutions, lessons-learned summary, transition information, and acknowledgments.</p>
    <reference path="templates/final-report.md">Final report skeleton with all required sections.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Transition to Operations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Hand operations a working runbook on day -7, not day 0; shadow week lets them surface gaps before you are gone.</statement>
      <rationale>Day-0 handovers leave the ops team inheriting an unsupportable system with no one to ask questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Handover items: system access, documentation, support tickets, monitoring, L1/L2/L3 contacts, escalation matrix, scheduled maintenance.</p>
    <reference path="templates/handover-doc.md">Operations handover template covering all required sections.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 7: Celebrate and Recognize">
    <rule>
      <statement>Celebrate visibly and name individual contributions; do not cut this step under schedule pressure.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping recognition is the leading cause of post-project demoralization, increasing attrition risk on the next engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/closure-checklist.md">Signed-off checklist covering all seven closure areas.</reference>
</text>
