<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="project-closure Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for project-closure. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Obtain written acceptance for every deliverable before declaring closure; verbal confirmation does not hold at invoice time.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ambiguous acceptance is the most common source of post-project invoice disputes and scope creep into "maintenance" work that was never bought.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Process all financial, resource, and contract closure actions within the closure window; do not leave open POs or un-released team members.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Open contracts accumulate charges. Resources "stuck" on finished projects block new assignments and frustrate individuals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run the lessons-learned session before the team disperses, not after; memory and candor both degrade within days.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Post-dispersal sessions yield low attendance and sanitized data. Lessons captured in flight are richer and more actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Archive documents into named categories (planning, execution, technical, contracts, closure) with a manifest so they can be found in 12 months.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unstructured "shared drive" archives are unfindable; without a manifest, future auditors and PMs have no entry point.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hand operations a working runbook on day -7, not day 0; shadow week lets them surface gaps before you are gone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Day-0 handovers leave the ops team inheriting an unsupportable system with no one to ask questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Celebrate visibly and name individual contributions; do not cut this step under schedule pressure.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Skipping recognition is the leading cause of post-project demoralization, increasing attrition risk on the next engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
