<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples-antipatterns" title="Project Closure — Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Worked examples for normal and cancelled-project closure, and the five most common closure antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Customer Portal v2.0 (6 months, $150k): final UAT sign-off obtained from business sponsor; production confirmed stable after 2-week soak; support team trained; documentation handed over; final cost $147,500 (under budget); 5 lessons captured; team celebration lunch held; final report distributed; project marked closed in system.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Cancelled Mobile App Prototype (strategic pivot, 30% complete): documented work completed and reasons; lessons learned on prototyping approach; recovered reusable design assets; released resources to other projects; negotiated early vendor contract termination; archived all documentation; final report with cancellation rationale — value recovered even from incomplete work.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Closure Types">
    <list>
      <item>Normal — objectives met: full closure process.</item>
      <item>Early (success) — objectives met ahead of schedule: accelerated closure.</item>
      <item>Early (cancelled) — stopped before completion: document reasons, recover value.</item>
      <item>Integration — absorbed into operations: transition-focused closure.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No formal acceptance — assuming silence means approved.</description>
      <reason>Closure without written acceptance leaves deliverable status ambiguous; six months later this becomes an invoice dispute with no documentation to support the PM's position.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Resources not released — people stuck on "finished" projects.</description>
      <reason>Trapped resources block new work and signal to team members that their time is not valued, increasing turnover risk.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Contracts left open — ongoing vendor charges accumulate.</description>
      <reason>Open POs continue to accrue costs and legal liabilities long after work stopped; finance discovers this in quarterly audits, not daily operations.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No lessons captured — knowledge walks out the door with the team.</description>
      <reason>Without documented lessons, the next project repeats the same mistakes. Institutional knowledge is the only free input to future project success.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No celebration — team feels unappreciated after sustained effort.</description>
      <reason>Skipping recognition signals that delivery is expected but not valued, the leading cultural factor in team attrition after project completion.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
