<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="project-closure Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for project-closure as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>No formal acceptance — assuming silence means approved.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Closure without written acceptance leaves deliverable status ambiguous; six months later this becomes an invoice dispute with no documentation to support the PM's position.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Resources not released — people stuck on "finished" projects.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Trapped resources block new work and signal to team members that their time is not valued, increasing turnover risk.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Contracts left open — ongoing vendor charges accumulate.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Open POs continue to accrue costs and legal liabilities long after work stopped; finance discovers this in quarterly audits, not daily operations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>No lessons captured — knowledge walks out the door with the team.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without documented lessons, the next project repeats the same mistakes. Institutional knowledge is the only free input to future project success.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>No celebration — team feels unappreciated after sustained effort.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Skipping recognition signals that delivery is expected but not valued, the leading cultural factor in team attrition after project completion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
