<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Burndown Diagnosis Cheatsheet Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Burndown Diagnosis Cheatsheet. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-four-named-causes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Off-track burndown has exactly 4 named root causes: scope creep, capacity loss, blocker stack, estimate drift. Diagnosis must pick one (or rank multiple).</statement>
      <rationale source="Sprint retro literature">Naming forces evidence-based diagnosis; without naming, &apos;we&apos;re behind&apos; loops indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-evidence-per-cause" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each named cause requires ≥1 concrete evidence row: scope (added story IDs), capacity (PTO/sick days), blockers (blocker IDs with age), estimates (original vs revised).</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Evidence prevents motivated reasoning; without it, blame defaults to capacity (least scary).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-remediation-per-cause" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each diagnosed cause gets a remediation with owner + due date. &apos;Try harder&apos; is not a remediation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sprint retro literature">Diagnosis without remediation is theatre; the cheatsheet&apos;s value is the loop close.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-mid-sprint-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run diagnostic only mid-sprint (day ≥3, ≥3 days remaining). End-of-sprint = retro instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Agile practice">Mid-sprint diagnostic allows in-sprint correction; end-of-sprint is post-mortem.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-archive-to-pattern-log" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Archive each diagnostic to a pattern log; quarterly review names the dominant cause type for the team.</statement>
      <rationale source="Continuous-improvement practice">Recurring patterns are the real signal; one-off diagnostics miss it.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md &quot;Applies If&quot; do not all hold, OR any &quot;Skip If&quot; disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-burndown-diagnosis-cheatsheet.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
