<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ads-twitter-ads Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ads-twitter-ads. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use follower lookalike targeting against 3-5 specific @accounts as the primary targeting method — never rely solely on Twitter's broad interest categories for B2B or tech products.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Twitter's interest taxonomy is coarser than Meta's; follower overlap against specific accounts (competitor, media, influencer) is a far more precise intent signal for niche tech and professional audiences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use keyword targeting to reach users who recently tweeted or engaged with your topic — combine with follower lookalikes to narrow to the right segment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Keyword targeting alone casts too wide a net (anyone who mentioned the word); combining with follower lookalikes ensures the keyword match occurs within an already-relevant audience.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Structure all Twitter/X ad copy as: Hook (stop scroll) → Value (what they get) → CTA (what to do) — never lead with brand name or product name.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Twitter feed scrolls at high speed; the first line determines whether users stop. Brand-first openers are ignored; problem/benefit-first openers interrupt scrolling behavior.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use conversational, text-heavy creative that looks like an organic tweet — avoid highly designed visuals with logos and taglines in the image.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Twitter users have strong ad-blindness to polished promotional imagery. Native-looking ads blend into the timeline and receive 2-3x higher engagement rates than design-heavy formats on this platform.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start with a minimum of $20/day; use $50+/day for meaningful testing data within 7 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Below $20/day, impressions are too sparse to generate statistically valid A/B comparison data between ad variations in a reasonable timeframe.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Refresh creative every 2 weeks — Twitter audiences are more homogeneous than Meta's, causing ad fatigue faster due to high impression repetition within small niche audiences.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Niche follower-lookalike audiences on Twitter can be as small as 50-200K users; at $50/day, frequency reaches 3+ within 10-14 days, after which engagement rates drop sharply.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
