<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-targeting" title="Twitter/X Targeting Methods">
  <summary>Follower lookalike, keyword, conversation, and tailored audience targeting with effective combinations.</summary>

  <section title="Targeting Methods">
    <list>
      <item>Interests — predefined category-level targeting (lower precision)</item>
      <item>Follower Lookalikes — users similar to followers of specified @accounts (high precision)</item>
      <item>Keywords — users who tweeted or engaged with specific words in the past 7 days</item>
      <item>Conversation Topics — users engaged in specific trending conversations</item>
      <item>Events — audiences around live events and moments</item>
      <item>Tailored Audiences — your own data (website pixel, email list, app)</item>
      <item>Demographics — age, gender, location</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use follower lookalike targeting against 3-5 specific @accounts as the primary targeting method — never rely solely on Twitter's broad interest categories for B2B or tech products.</statement>
      <rationale>Twitter's interest taxonomy is coarser than Meta's; follower overlap against specific accounts (competitor, media, influencer) is a far more precise intent signal for niche tech and professional audiences.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Effective Targeting Combinations">
    <list>
      <item>Tech/SaaS: Follower lookalikes (@stripe, @linear, @productboard) + Interests: Startups, Technology + Location: US</item>
      <item>Newsletter: Keywords (relevant topic terms) + Follower lookalikes (@media accounts) + Interests: Entrepreneurship</item>
      <item>Retargeting: Tailored Audience (website pixel visitors) + Demographics</item>
      <item>B2B: Follower lookalikes (@industry leaders) + Keywords (job-related terms)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Keyword Targeting">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use keyword targeting to reach users who recently tweeted or engaged with your topic — combine with follower lookalikes to narrow to the right segment.</statement>
      <rationale>Keyword targeting alone casts too wide a net (anyone who mentioned the word); combining with follower lookalikes ensures the keyword match occurs within an already-relevant audience.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
