<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ads-twitter-ads Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ads-twitter-ads as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Targeting broad interest categories without follower lookalike refinement.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Twitter's interest taxonomy is imprecise; broad interests produce high CPMs with low conversion rates because the audience pool includes tangentially interested users.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using highly polished, design-heavy creative with prominent brand elements.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Polished ads are immediately identified as advertisements and scrolled past; native-looking conversational ads achieve 2-3x higher engagement on Twitter's feed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Launching only one ad variation per campaign.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>No variation means no optimization path; Twitter's algorithm cannot identify the best creative, and a single underperforming ad exhausts budget with no recourse.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring replies on promoted tweets.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Negative or unanswered replies appear under the ad to all subsequent viewers; unmonitored negative sentiment actively damages conversion rates for the entire campaign duration.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Running the same creative for more than 3 weeks to small niche audiences.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Frequency fatigue in small audiences (under 500K) degrades engagement rates and inflates CPCs; creative must be rotated before the audience burns out.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
