<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="design-critique">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>A structured conversation about a design where participants analyze work against defined goals and principles, providing specific, actionable feedback to improve the design. Prevents opinion battles and ensures feedback is grounded in evidence.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>design-critique</tag>
      <tag>feedback</tag>
      <tag>design-review</tag>
      <tag>team-collaboration</tag>
      <tag>design-process</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Design Critique</title>

    <summary>A structured conversation analyzing design against goals and principles. Eliminates vague feedback and opinion battles through observation-principle-impact-suggestion format. Prevents preference-based rejection and ensures every comment improves the design.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Design reviews without structure turn into opinion battles. Feedback is vague: "I don't like it." Good ideas are killed by personal preferences. Junior designers don't get useful feedback. Designs don't improve through iteration. Team alignment is difficult to achieve. Inconsistent design quality results from feedback that is not grounded in evidence.</p>
      <p>A structured critique process grounds feedback in goals and principles, eliminates preference-based comments, and ensures everyone understands why a design direction was chosen or rejected. It also creates a psychologically safe space for junior designers to participate and learn.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before handoff from design to development, as a final quality gate against defined design principles.</item>
        <item>During each design sprint iteration when you need structured feedback on a single direction.</item>
        <item>When async critique is needed for distributed teams — a written structured format prevents opinion debates in Slack threads.</item>
        <item>When onboarding junior designers who need a framework for giving and receiving feedback.</item>
        <item>When a design decision has been contested by stakeholders and you need an objective evaluation against goals.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When the problem definition is still open; critique assumes a design direction exists — use brainstorming or co-design workshops instead.</item>
        <item>For pixel-level polish feedback on a concept still in wireframe stage; match feedback stage to design fidelity.</item>
        <item>When the critique group lacks context on the user, the problem, or the constraints — missing context makes feedback opinion-based regardless of the framework.</item>
        <item>As a replacement for user testing; critique surfaces expert opinions, not actual user behavior.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="critique-vs-criticism">
      <p>A critique is based on goals and is specific and actionable. Criticism is based on preference and is vague and personal.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Critique is about the work, never about the designer. Connect every feedback point to a goal or principle, never to personal taste.</statement>
        <rationale>Goal-based feedback improves the design. Preference-based feedback hurts feelings and does not improve work.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Presenter decides what to incorporate (their design, their call). Facilitator's role is to ensure feedback is structured, not to enforce compliance with feedback.</statement>
        <rationale>Decision authority stays with the designer. Feedback is input, not direction. This preserves psychological safety and ownership.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Goal-based feedback">
        <description>The progress indicator shows 5 steps. Research shows mobile users abandon at 4+ steps. Could any steps be combined? This feedback is specific (5 steps observed), grounded in evidence (research), and actionable (combine steps).</description>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Preference-based feedback">
        <description>I don't like the colors. This feedback is vague, personal, and not actionable. It does not connect to a goal.</description>
        <note>Reframe as: The color coding uses red for both "urgent" and "error" states. This might confuse users trying to prioritize actions. What if urgent used a different color family?</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Without stated goals and design principles, critique sessions default to preference debates regardless of format.</description>
        <reason>Without explicit goals, every comment is opinion. Goals are the foundation of structured critique.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Power dynamics suppress critique quality: junior designers do not give honest feedback to senior designers in hierarchical teams without explicit facilitation.</description>
        <reason>Facilitation must create psychological safety. Ground rules posted in the room, explicit permission for juniors to speak, and framing feedback as "about the work" all help.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="five-step-process">
      <p>Design critique follows a five-step process: set context, present work, ask clarifying questions, give structured feedback, capture and prioritize.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Presenter MUST state the feedback type needed at the start: Directional (Is this the right approach?) / Refinement (How can this be better?) / Polish (Is this ready to ship?). This single step prevents the most common failure mode of giving polish feedback on an exploration design.</statement>
        <rationale>Different design stages need different feedback. Polish feedback on an early exploration demoralizes the designer and wastes time. Matching feedback type to design stage is the fastest way to improve the design.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Facilitator time-boxes per-screen discussion to prevent a single contentious screen from consuming the session.</statement>
        <rationale>Without time-boxing, critiques overrun and teams lose buy-in. Time-boxing ensures all screens are covered.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Note-taker captures verbatim feedback, not paraphrases — verbatim quotes survive the "telephone effect" when referenced later.</statement>
        <rationale>Paraphrases introduce bias. Verbatim notes are ground truth for what was said and why a design decision was made.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>For async critique, require participants to use the observation-principle-impact-suggestion format — freeform comment threads devolve into preference debates.</statement>
        <rationale>Format enforces structure even when facilitators are not present. Without format, distributed teams produce unusable feedback.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Structured feedback format">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Observation:
The submit button is below the fold.

Principle:
We know from research that users often miss it.

Impact:
This could hurt conversion.

Suggestion:
What if we added a sticky footer?]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Vague comment">
        <description>Make the button more visible. This is vague (which button? how visible?), not grounded in a goal, and not actionable.</description>
        <note>Reframe using observation-principle-impact-suggestion.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Async critique loses the clarifying question phase; written comments often assume rather than ask.</description>
        <reason>Async critique requires higher structure (format + examples + rubric) to compensate for missing real-time clarification. Build this in from the start.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>"Design by committee" failure mode: when everyone in the room redesigns rather than analyzes.</description>
        <reason>Redirect solutioning back to analysis. Facilitator frames: "That's a great idea. Does the current design fail against a goal, or are you proposing an alternative?"</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="critique-formats">
      <p>Critique adapts to time and team context: quick critique for daily check-ins, standard for feature reviews, deep dive for major decisions.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Quick Critique (15 min): Context 2 min, Present 5 min, Feedback 5 min, Wrap-up 3 min. Best for: Daily check-ins, small decisions.</statement>
        <rationale>Short feedback loops encourage more critiques; fewer surprises at handoff.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Standard Critique (30–45 min): Context 5 min, Present 10 min, Questions 5 min, Feedback 15 min, Wrap-up 5 min. Best for: Feature reviews, design iterations.</statement>
        <rationale>Most common format; allows depth without overrunning.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Deep Dive (60+ min): Context 10 min, Present 15 min, Silent review 10 min, Structured feedback 20 min, Discussion 10 min, Action items 5 min. Best for: Major features, strategic decisions.</statement>
        <rationale>Silent review step allows individual processing before group discussion; reduces groupthink.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>An agent is effective as an async critique participant: given the design goals, user context, constraints, and design screenshots, it can apply structured observation-principle-impact-suggestion feedback for each screen. It functions as an always-available, non-hierarchical reviewer that never softens feedback for social reasons.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Agents will generate preference-based feedback if the principles are not explicitly stated; always supply the design principles list in the prompt.</statement>
        <rationale>Without principles, agents fall back to common-pattern analysis. Explicit principles anchor the feedback.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Vision model feedback on color and contrast requires specifying the WCAG level target; without it, agents apply inconsistent standards.</statement>
        <rationale>Accessibility is measurable only with a stated target (AA, AAA). Without target, agent advice is inconsistent.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Agents do not know your design system unless you describe it or provide it — all "design system compliance" checks require the design system to be included in context.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent cannot infer design conventions; they must be taught explicitly.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Agent critique will be biased toward common web/app patterns; non-standard interaction models will receive conservative feedback even when the non-standard approach is the right one.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents are trained on common patterns and will flag deviation. Unusual but correct patterns require human validation of the agent's feedback.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Do not treat agent critique output as a final deliverable; use it as input to a human-facilitated session or as a starting draft for async critique documents.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent output is one perspective, not a decision. Humans synthesize agent feedback with their own judgment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>A human facilitator must still run live critique sessions and make final decisions about which feedback to incorporate. Agent feedback is input, not decision.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents can generate observations and surface principle violations, but human judgment is needed to prioritize and decide what to change.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Agent critique prompt with principles">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a UX design critic. Review the attached design for [feature name].

Context:
- Problem: [What user problem this solves]
- User: [Target user description]
- Design stage: [Exploration / Iteration / Polish]
- Constraints: [Technical, business, timeline]
- Design principles to evaluate against: [List 3-5 principles]

For each screen, provide structured feedback using:
- Observation: what you see
- Principle: which design principle is relevant
- Impact: how this affects the user
- Suggestion (optional): a specific alternative

Do not give preference-based feedback. All feedback must connect to a stated principle or goal.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="culture-and-ground-rules">
      <p>Critique culture is built through consistent practice, clear ground rules, and modeling good feedback.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Post ground rules in critique sessions: (1) Critique the work, not the person. (2) Be specific, not vague. (3) Connect feedback to goals. (4) Ask questions before judging. (5) Suggest, don't dictate. (6) Everyone participates. (7) Presenter decides what to incorporate.</statement>
        <rationale>Ground rules normalize structured feedback and create psychological safety. Visible rules also educate new team members on expectations.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Decision authority stays with the presenter; after the session, they write back to participants which feedback they incorporated and why they skipped the rest.</statement>
        <rationale>Closure and transparency build trust in the process. Without feedback on decisions, participants lose faith in critique.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Separate "critique of the problem framing" from "critique of the solution" — sometimes the right feedback is that the wrong problem is being solved.</statement>
        <rationale>Both framing and solution can be wrong; keeping them separate prevents team alignment on the wrong problem.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Critique culture building">
        <description>Team starts with small 2–3 person critiques. Facilitator models good feedback (observation-principle-impact-suggestion). Feedback is captured and shared; presenter writes back on decisions. Over time, critiques expand to larger groups, and team members start offering structured feedback unprompted.</description>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <list>
        <item>No stated goals — feedback becomes opinion without criteria.</item>
        <item>Wrong stage feedback — polish feedback on exploration work demoralizes the designer.</item>
        <item>Solutioning not critiquing — designing in the meeting instead of analyzing the design.</item>
        <item>Too many cooks — everyone redesigning instead of analyzing.</item>
        <item>Defending instead of listening — presenter argues every point instead of hearing feedback.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>Tools for critique documentation and collaboration.</p>

      <list>
        <item><term name="Figma">SaaS, partial (REST API). Design file access; API can read frames, components, styles for system compliance check.</term></item>
        <item><term name="Loom">SaaS. Video-based async critique walkthroughs; no programmatic API.</term></item>
        <item><term name="Notion">SaaS, REST API. Async critique documentation; agent can write structured critique pages.</term></item>
        <item><term name="Linear">SaaS, REST API. Convert critique action items to design tickets.</term></item>
        <item><term name="Zeplin">SaaS, partial (REST API). Design handoff with annotations; API for reading spec data.</term></item>
      </list>

      <p>CLI tools for accessibility and design token checking:</p>
      <list>
        <item><term name="axe-cli">Automated accessibility critique for shipped or prototyped interfaces. `npm i -g @axe-core/cli` / github.com/dequelabs/axe-core-npm</term></item>
        <item><term name="contrast-ratio">Check foreground/background color contrast. Various tools; e.g. `npm i -g get-contrast`</term></item>
        <item><term name="stylelint">CSS/design token lint — flags deviation from design system tokens. `npm i -g stylelint` / stylelint.io</term></item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Presenter states the type of feedback needed at the start (directional / refinement / polish) — this single step prevents the most common failure mode.</item>
        <item>Facilitator time-boxes per-screen discussion to prevent a single contentious screen from consuming the session.</item>
        <item>Note-taker captures verbatim feedback, not paraphrases — verbatim quotes survive later reference.</item>
        <item>For async critique, require participants to use the observation-principle-impact-suggestion format — freeform threads devolve into preference debates.</item>
        <item>Without stated goals and design principles, critique sessions default to preference debates regardless of format.</item>
        <item>Agents cannot see rendered UI — they audit source code, token files, or exported strings. Visual auditing still requires humans or dedicated visual regression tools.</item>
        <item>Agent feedback on design system compliance requires the design system to be included in context. Agents cannot infer conventions.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/critique-session.md" purpose="Critique session template: context, goals, notes, action items, decisions"/>
      <template path="templates/feedback-framework.md" purpose="Feedback framework template with observation-principle-impact-suggestion format"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/design-critiques/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/how-to-run-a-design-critique"/>
      <link href="https://basecamp.com/shapeup"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
