<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-technical-foundation" title="Technical SEO Foundation">
  <summary>robots.txt configuration, XML sitemap structure, HTTPS setup, and redirect rules — the crawlability prerequisites.</summary>

  <section title="robots.txt Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Block admin paths, session ID parameters, and internal APIs; explicitly allow public API paths; add Sitemap directives; never block CSS or JS files.</statement>
      <rationale>Blocking CSS/JS prevents Google from rendering pages correctly, causing ranking loss. Unblocked session URLs create infinite crawl loops that waste crawl budget on non-indexable content.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure AI crawlers (GPTBot, Claude-Web, PerplexityBot) separately from search crawlers — allow public content, disallow premium/paywalled content.</statement>
      <rationale>AI crawlers serve a different purpose than search crawlers: they build training data and citation sources, not indexes. Blocking them entirely sacrifices AI search visibility; blocking only premium content is the balanced approach.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/robots-txt.txt">robots.txt template with AI crawler rules and sitemap directive</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="XML Sitemap Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include only indexable pages in the sitemap; update lastmod only when content actually changes; use sitemap index for sites with more than 50,000 URLs.</statement>
      <rationale>Sitemaps with stale lastmod dates or non-indexable URLs train Google's crawler to distrust the sitemap, reducing crawl frequency for the whole site.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include hreflang alternate links inside sitemap entries for multilingual sites.</statement>
      <rationale>Sitemap hreflang is a fallback for pages where HTML head injection is complex (SPAs, CDN-level rendering). Redundancy in hreflang signals is safe and preferred.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/sitemap-xml.xml">XML sitemap template with hreflang alternates</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="HTTPS and Redirects">
    <rule>
      <statement>Redirect HTTP to HTTPS and non-www to www (or vice versa) with 301 permanent redirects; avoid redirect chains longer than one hop.</statement>
      <rationale>Each redirect hop loses approximately 10-15% of PageRank. Chains of three or more hops can be abandoned by crawlers entirely, causing indexing failures for the destination page.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>SSL certificate installed and covering all subdomains (wildcard preferred)</item>
      <item>No mixed content: all resources (images, scripts, fonts) load over HTTPS</item>
      <item>Security headers: HSTS, X-Frame-Options, CSP</item>
      <item>Single canonical domain enforced via server-level redirect</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
