<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-multilingual-hreflang" title="Multilingual SEO and hreflang">
  <summary>URL structure options, hreflang implementation rules, and metadata localization requirements for multilingual sites.</summary>

  <section title="URL Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use subdirectory URL structure (/en/, /uk/) for multilingual sites — not query parameters (?lang=uk).</statement>
      <rationale>Query parameter language switching creates duplicate content that Google indexes inconsistently and cannot distinguish by language. Subdirectory structure gives each language version its own crawlable URL that accumulates PageRank independently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Subdirectories (/en/, /uk/) — recommended: shared domain authority, simple management</item>
      <item>Subdomains (uk.faion.net) — acceptable: separate hosting possible, but splits domain authority</item>
      <item>ccTLDs (faion.ua) — strong geo-signal but expensive and complex to manage</item>
      <item>Parameters (?lang=uk) — avoid: poor SEO, indexing issues, canonical confusion</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="hreflang Implementation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every hreflang implementation must include: self-referencing tag, bidirectional linking, ISO 639-1 language codes, x-default for the fallback page.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing self-reference causes Google to ignore the entire hreflang cluster. Missing bidirectional links (A points to B but B doesn't point to A) invalidates the signal. Missing x-default leaves users with no-match locale seeing an arbitrary language version.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never combine hreflang with noindex on the same page.</statement>
      <rationale>A noindexed page cannot appear in search results, so its hreflang signals are worthless. Google may also ignore the hreflang signals pointing to noindexed pages, breaking the entire cluster.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/hreflang-html.txt">hreflang link tags for HTML head with self-reference and x-default</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Metadata Localization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Title tags and meta descriptions must match the language of the page content — never leave English metadata on a Ukrainian-language page.</statement>
      <rationale>Mismatched language in metadata and content signals low quality to Google and creates a poor user experience when the snippet appears in localized search results.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Use ISO 639-1 codes: en, uk, de, fr (not "english", "ukrainian")</item>
      <item>Use ISO 3166-1 Alpha-2 for regional variants: en-US, en-GB</item>
      <item>Language switcher must be prominent and functional</item>
      <item>Test hreflang with Google Search Console hreflang validator</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
