<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-semantic-html-accessibility" title="Semantic HTML and Accessibility">
  <summary>HTML structure requirements, WCAG 2.2 accessibility checklist, and ARIA landmark usage that simultaneously serves screen readers and search crawlers.</summary>

  <section title="Semantic HTML Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use exactly one H1 per page containing the primary keyword; maintain logical heading hierarchy (H1 → H2 → H3); never skip heading levels.</statement>
      <rationale>Search crawlers use heading structure to understand page organization and extract key topics. Screen readers rely on headings for document navigation. Skipped levels confuse both.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use semantic elements (header, main, footer, article, section, aside, nav) instead of generic divs for all structural containers.</statement>
      <rationale>Semantic HTML conveys meaning to crawlers, screen readers, and browsers without requiring ARIA overrides. Divs with ARIA roles are a workaround; semantic elements are the baseline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/semantic-html.txt">Semantic HTML page structure with ARIA landmarks and accessible navigation</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="WCAG 2.2 Checklist">
    <list>
      <item>Color contrast minimum 4.5:1 for normal text, 3:1 for large text</item>
      <item>All images have descriptive alt text; decorative images use alt=""</item>
      <item>All interactive elements reachable and operable by keyboard</item>
      <item>Form inputs have associated label elements (not placeholder-only)</item>
      <item>Links use descriptive text — not "click here" or "read more"</item>
      <item>ARIA landmarks: banner, main, navigation, contentinfo</item>
      <item>Focus indicators visible on all interactive elements</item>
      <item>Test with WAVE or axe browser extension</item>
      <item>Test navigation with keyboard only (Tab, Enter, arrow keys)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Image Optimization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include explicit width and height attributes on img elements to prevent CLS; use WebP or AVIF format; lazy-load below-fold images.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing width/height causes layout shift as images load (CLS score degradation). WebP/AVIF are 25-35% smaller than JPEG/PNG at equivalent quality, improving LCP. Lazy loading defers non-critical image loading to reduce initial page weight.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
