<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-core-web-vitals" title="Core Web Vitals Optimization">
  <summary>LCP, INP, and CLS targets with specific optimization actions for each metric.</summary>

  <section title="Metric Targets">
    <rule>
      <statement>All three Core Web Vitals must reach the "Good" threshold: LCP &lt;= 2.5s, INP &lt;= 200ms, CLS &lt;= 0.1.</statement>
      <rationale>Pages with all three metrics in "Good" range receive a page experience ranking boost. A single metric in "Poor" range cancels the boost. Monitor in Google Search Console, not just Lighthouse — lab data and field data diverge significantly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>LCP (Largest Contentful Paint): Good &lt;= 2.5s | Needs work 2.5-4s | Poor &gt; 4s</item>
      <item>INP (Interaction to Next Paint): Good &lt;= 200ms | Needs work 200-500ms | Poor &gt; 500ms</item>
      <item>CLS (Cumulative Layout Shift): Good &lt;= 0.1 | Needs work 0.1-0.25 | Poor &gt; 0.25</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="LCP Optimizations">
    <list>
      <item>Preload the LCP image: &lt;link rel="preload" as="image" href="..."&gt;</item>
      <item>Use WebP/AVIF formats (25-35% smaller than JPEG)</item>
      <item>Serve responsive images via srcset</item>
      <item>Optimize server response time (TTFB &lt; 800ms)</item>
      <item>Use CDN for static assets</item>
      <item>Inline critical CSS; defer non-critical CSS</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="INP Optimizations">
    <list>
      <item>Break up JavaScript long tasks into chunks under 50ms</item>
      <item>Defer all non-critical JavaScript with defer or type="module"</item>
      <item>Move heavy computation to Web Workers off the main thread</item>
      <item>Use requestIdleCallback for low-priority background work</item>
      <item>Minimize event listener overhead — debounce high-frequency events</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="CLS Optimizations">
    <list>
      <item>Always specify width and height on img and video elements</item>
      <item>Reserve explicit space for ads and third-party embeds (min-height)</item>
      <item>Never insert content above existing content after page load</item>
      <item>Use font-display: swap with font preload to prevent invisible text flash</item>
      <item>Avoid CSS animations that trigger layout (use transform/opacity instead)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Measuring Core Web Vitals only in Lighthouse lab mode</description>
    <reason>Lighthouse runs in a controlled lab environment; Google's ranking uses field data from Chrome User Experience Report (CrUX). A passing Lighthouse score can coexist with failing field CWV if real users have slower devices or connections.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
