<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Azure DevOps Boards Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six testable rules for configuring ADO Boards so the result is auditable, agent-accessible, and survives org-wide template changes.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="template-inheritance" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick exactly one process template per organisation (Basic, Agile, Scrum, or CMMI) and inherit from it. Forking the template is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft Learn — Azure DevOps inherited process docs">Custom-process forks diverge quickly; template inheritance lets org-wide field changes propagate centrally. Mass-edit migrations across forks are painful and irreversible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="area-vs-iteration" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Area Path encodes team ownership; Iteration Path encodes time. Neither dimension is allowed to carry the other's concerns.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft Learn — Area &amp; Iteration paths best practice">Area/Iteration confusion is the most common ADO setup error: teams assign work to an iteration that belongs to a different area team, creating invisible cross-team dependencies.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="wip-limit-enforced" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every board column with state `Active` or equivalent MUST have a numeric WIP limit, with card-style colouring red when over limit.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kanban Method — Anderson (2010)">Without enforced limits, the Active column becomes a backlog landfill. Visual enforcement makes violations visible in stand-up without anyone reporting them.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="pat-scope-minimal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agent-used PATs MUST scope to the minimum {Work Items: Read &amp; Write}. Full-access PATs are forbidden in automation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft Learn — Azure DevOps PAT security guidance">Full-access PATs are an attack surface. Minimum-scope tokens contain blast radius if a PAT leaks via env vars or pipeline logs.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="ab-linking-enforced" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Commits and pull requests MUST reference work items via the `AB#&lt;id&gt;` syntax. CI pipeline rejects PRs without at least one valid AB#&lt;id&gt; in the title or body.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft Learn — Boards–Repos integration docs">AB-linking is the foundation for build-traceability and audit. Without it, the audit log loses the code→requirement chain CMMI and similar regimes require.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the organisation is pure GitHub stack, ≤10-person engineering-only team, or open-source/community project, the team MUST skip ADO Boards and pick a lighter alternative (GitHub Projects v2, Linear).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — PM tool-selection scorecard">ADO Boards' setup overhead only pays off in Microsoft-stack regulated organisations. Applying it elsewhere creates governance debt with no benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
