<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-setup" title="ADO Boards Setup: Templates, Hierarchy, and Board Configuration">
  <summary>Process template selection, work-item hierarchy design, board column/swimlane configuration, and Area/Iteration path structure for Azure DevOps Boards.</summary>

  <section title="Process Template Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick one process template per organisation and inherit from it — never fork. Mass-edit migrations across forks are painful and irreversible.</statement>
      <rationale>Custom-process forks diverge quickly; template inheritance lets you propagate org-wide field changes centrally.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Basic — Issue + Task: simple projects or teams new to ADO</item>
      <item>Agile — Epic, Feature, User Story, Task, Bug: standard agile teams</item>
      <item>Scrum — Epic, Feature, PBI, Task, Bug, Impediment: Scrum teams with formal impediment tracking</item>
      <item>CMMI — Epic, Feature, Requirement, Task, Bug, Change Request, Review, Risk: regulated/audit-heavy environments</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Work Item Hierarchy">
    <p>Agile process hierarchy (top to bottom): Epic (initiative) → Feature (shippable capability) → User Story (user value) → Task (technical unit) → Bug (defect, any level).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Area Path for team ownership and Iteration Path for time. Do not overload either dimension with the other's concerns.</statement>
      <rationale>Area/Iteration confusion is the most common ADO setup error: teams assign work to an iteration that belongs to a different area team, creating invisible cross-team dependencies.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Board Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set WIP limits per board column and enforce them via card-style rules that colour blocked or over-limit columns red. Without enforced limits, the Active column becomes a backlog landfill.</statement>
      <rationale>WIP limits are the primary Kanban control mechanism; visual enforcement makes violations visible in stand-up without anyone having to report them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Board column configuration with WIP limits and Doing/Done split.</note>
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
columns:
  - name: "New"
    state_mapping: ["New"]
    wip_limit: null
  - name: "Active"
    state_mapping: ["Active"]
    wip_limit: 5
    split: true          # Doing / Done sub-columns
  - name: "Resolved"
    state_mapping: ["Resolved"]
    wip_limit: 3
  - name: "Closed"
    state_mapping: ["Closed"]
swimlanes:
  - name: "Expedite"
  - name: "Default"
  - name: "Tech Debt"
card_styles:
  - name: "Blocked"
    condition: "Tags Contains 'Blocked'"
    background_color: "#FF0000"
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Sprint Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define Iteration paths with a Release/Sprint hierarchy before the first sprint starts; agents that create missing iterations in production break sprint history.</statement>
      <rationale>Iteration path creation is additive — once a sprint exists, renaming or restructuring it invalidates all historical velocity data.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
