<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Use Case Modeling Framework">
  <summary>Actor types, use case components, five-step modeling process, and relationship types (include/extend/generalize).</summary>

  <section title="Use Case Components">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every use case must identify: actor (who), goal (what), system boundary (what is in scope), and scenarios (how).</statement>
      <rationale>Missing any component produces an incomplete spec that cannot drive test case generation or traceability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Actor types: primary actors initiate use cases to achieve their own goals; secondary actors support the system (external services, databases); system actors are automated timers or other systems.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-Step Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — Identify actors: list all human roles, external systems, and timers that interact with the system boundary.</statement>
      <rationale>Actors missed at this stage produce use cases with no owner and no test persona.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Identify use cases: for each actor ask what tasks they perform, what information they need, what they create or change, and what events trigger their actions. Name each use case Verb+Noun.</statement>
      <rationale>Verb+Noun naming enforces goal orientation and prevents feature-as-use-case mistakes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Create use case diagram: visualize actors outside the system boundary, use cases inside. Show include/extend/generalize relationships only when they de-duplicate 10 or more steps.</statement>
      <rationale>Premature relationship modeling is the #1 source of UC diagram errors; relationships should emerge, not be designed in advance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Write use case specifications: document name, ID, description, actors, preconditions, main flow (5-9 steps), alternative flows, exception flows, postconditions, and business rules for each use case.</statement>
      <rationale>Specifications without exception flows miss 40%+ of real behavior and leave testing without negative-path guidance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5 — Validate with stakeholders: confirm all actor goals are covered, main flow is correct, alternatives are complete, exceptions are handled, and postconditions are observable.</statement>
      <rationale>Validation is cheapest before development; each missed exception discovered in testing costs 10x more to fix.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Relationship Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Include only when the included use case is always executed as part of the including use case and de-duplicates 10 or more steps across multiple use cases.</statement>
      <rationale>Include is misused ~80% of the time; most apparent includes are just consecutive steps within a single flow.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Extend only when an optionally added behavior branches from a specific extension point in the base use case.</statement>
      <rationale>Extend adds complexity; if the extension is not truly optional and conditional, model it as an alternative flow instead.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Generalization when a specialized actor or use case inherits all behavior of a parent and adds or overrides specific steps.</statement>
      <rationale>Generalization is the least-used relationship; apply only when the IS-A semantic is genuinely true.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/use-case-spec.md">Full use case specification shell</reference>
  <reference path="templates/use-case-diagram.md">Actor and relationship notation template</reference>
</text>
