<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-quality-rules" title="Use Case Quality Rules">
  <summary>Testability rules, step-count heuristics, naming convention, exception-flow requirements, and agentic gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Naming and Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use case names must be Verb+Noun (e.g. Place Order, Generate Report). Reject any name that is a noun only, a screen name, or contains UI elements.</statement>
      <rationale>Noun-only names describe system state, not actor goals; UI names couple the spec to a design that will change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Main flow must have 5-9 steps. Fewer than 5 indicates a system function that belongs inside another use case; more than 9 indicates a use case that should be split.</statement>
      <rationale>Step-count uniformity enables comparison and traceability; unbounded length makes review and testing unmanageable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>One step = one actor action plus one system response. Apply this heuristic uniformly across all use cases in a project.</statement>
      <rationale>Inconsistent granularity makes cross-UC comparison and test-case generation unreliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Required Flows">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every use case must have at least one alternative flow and at least one exception flow before it is accepted as complete.</statement>
      <rationale>Exception flows are the highest-value section; humans and agents skip them by default, leaving 40%+ of real behavior unspecified.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Postconditions must be observable system states (database record created, message sent, file written) — not user perceptions.</statement>
      <rationale>Unobservable postconditions cannot be verified by automated tests or acceptance criteria.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>System Response column must contain system-behavior verbs (validates, persists, emits, calculates) — never UI-rendering verbs (renders, shows, displays button).</statement>
      <rationale>UI verbs couple the spec to a specific design; system-behavior verbs remain stable across redesigns.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Checklist">
    <list>
      <item>Each use case has a clear, named primary actor</item>
      <item>Use case name is Verb+Noun</item>
      <item>Preconditions are verifiable system states</item>
      <item>Main flow has 5-9 steps</item>
      <item>At least one alternative flow documented</item>
      <item>At least one exception flow documented</item>
      <item>Postconditions are observable</item>
      <item>Business rules are referenced, not embedded</item>
      <item>Reviewed and signed off by stakeholders</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLMs write the happy path and stop, omitting alternative and exception flows.</description>
      <reason>Force at least one alternative and one exception in the output schema; reject any output that omits them.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Drafter agents insert UI details ("displays popup") even after being told not to.</description>
      <reason>Add a post-generation regex check for UI nouns (button, modal, popup, screen, click) and bounce matching drafts.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents hallucinate actors that are UI elements (Header, Sidebar) rather than human or system roles.</description>
      <reason>Constrain actor type to {human, system, timer} in the output schema and reject anything else.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Drafting 10+ use cases in a single LLM call — accuracy collapses due to template repetition errors.</description>
      <reason>Chunk one UC per call; combine only at the index-generation step.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/uc-drafter-prompt.txt">LLM prompt enforcing quality rules at generation time</reference>
  <reference path="templates/uc-reviewer-prompt.txt">LLM prompt for scoring a UC against the quality checklist</reference>
</text>
