<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Scope-Creep Park-List Template Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every walkthrough park-list run must enforce so the meeting honors stakeholder input without committing to it and so the disposition record is verifiable.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-visible-live-capture" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every "wouldn't it be cool if" idea is captured into a park-list visible to the stakeholder in real time (screen-shared doc, Figma sticky board, projected Notion page). Off-screen note-taking is rejected — if the stakeholder cannot see the item land on the list, the silence-as-agreement risk is not mitigated.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-promise-by-omission">The damage of the "polite nod" pattern is that the stakeholder remembers being heard; the designer remembers a fleeting idea. A visible live capture shows the stakeholder their input has been recorded, which is the half of the problem that good listening alone cannot solve.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-four-bucket-disposition" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each captured item is dispositioned into exactly one of four buckets before the meeting ends: `in-scope-now` | `change-order` | `backlog-v2` | `dropped-with-reason`. "We'll figure it out later" is not a valid disposition. Each `dropped-with-reason` carries a one-line rationale; each `change-order` carries an estimated impact band; each `backlog-v2` carries a "tied to which milestone" note.</statement>
      <rationale source="Forcing-function disposition">Items without disposition default to "the designer probably will" in the stakeholder's mind. Forcing one of four buckets, with a rationale or impact tied to each non-trivial bucket, makes the disposition shareable and reviewable after the meeting.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-90s-per-item-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each park-list item is dispositioned within ≤90 seconds of capture. Items that need more discussion are tagged `disposition-deferred` with a single follow-up step (calendar slot, async note) named in the park-list row. A meeting cannot end with `disposition-deferred` items lacking a follow-up step.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meeting-pace preservation">Lingering on every "cool idea" derails the walkthrough's actual purpose. The 90s cap forces snap dispositions and protects the meeting from the failure mode where the park-list itself becomes the meeting. The named follow-up step keeps deferred items from quietly evaporating.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-end-of-meeting-signoff" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The last 5 minutes of the meeting are reserved for a stakeholder readback: the designer reads each park-list item with its disposition, the stakeholder confirms or corrects each in turn. The park-list is then saved with `signoff: &lt;stakeholder_handle&gt; @ &lt;iso_timestamp&gt;`. Walkthroughs that skip readback are rejected as not-park-listed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Explicit-confirmation principle">The readback is the moment that converts the park-list from a one-sided artefact into a two-party record. Without it, the stakeholder can later claim they did not know X was dropped. With it, the stakeholder's own confirmation is part of the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-parked-item-shelf-life" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Items in `backlog-v2` carry a shelf-life of 90 days. Within the window, the item must either be promoted (next-design-review references it, kickoff includes it) or explicitly re-parked with a refreshed reason. Items past shelf-life with no action drop to `archived-from-park-list` and the engagement file records the silent drop so it cannot become a surprise later.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice">Parked items rot. Unbounded parking creates exactly the credibility problem the methodology exists to prevent — months later the stakeholder asks "what happened to X" and nobody remembers. Shelf-life forces refresh-or-archive and makes the archive itself a logged event the engagement file can cite.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example>
    <description>Live park-list with end-of-meeting signoff.</description>
    <code language="markdown">
# Park-List — Acme dashboard walkthrough — 2026-05-20

| # | Captured | Source | Disposition | Note |
|---|----------|--------|-------------|------|
| 1 | "could the chart support multi-year compare?" | stakeholder | backlog-v2 | tied to v2 milestone (Q4); shelf 90d |
| 2 | "what if we added a dark mode toggle?" | stakeholder | dropped-with-reason | "out of brand scope; brand redesign owns dark-mode roadmap" |
| 3 | "the export should be xlsx not csv" | stakeholder | change-order | impact-band: small (~3h); change-order draft to follow within 24h |
| 4 | "tooltips on every metric" | stakeholder | in-scope-now | already in spec §4.2; will confirm in next iteration |

signoff: @sponsor-acme @ 2026-05-20T15:58:00Z (readback confirmed)
deferred_items: none
follow_ups:
  - item 3: change-order draft due 2026-05-21
    </code>
  </example>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../anti-pattern-rationale-template/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../../../pro/ba/scope-creep-firewall/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
