<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-onboarding-and-experiments" title="Product-Led Growth: Experiment Design and PQL Scoring">
  <summary>Experiment design rules (SRM check, MDE pre-registration, minimum exposure), PQL scoring pattern with PostHog, and the instrumentation-first discipline that makes PLG agent workflows reliable.</summary>

  <section title="Instrumentation-First Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Instrument the funnel before optimizing. Agents producing variants on uninstrumented funnels hill-climb noise — there is no signal to optimize against.</statement>
      <rationale>PLG optimization is fundamentally an empirical loop; without telemetry, every "improvement" is untestable and every "result" is confirmation bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep one north-star metric (activation rate, NRR, or PQL-to-paid) per quarter. Rotate hypotheses, not metrics.</statement>
      <rationale>Changing the north-star metric mid-quarter makes quarter-over-quarter comparison impossible and hides whether interventions are working or just moving a different number.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Experiment Design Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Gate every experiment behind SRM (sample-ratio mismatch) check and a pre-registered MDE (minimum detectable effect). Enforce minimum exposure of ≥1k users per variant and minimum runtime of ≥7 days before allowing a winner call.</statement>
      <rationale>Both SRM and pre-registered MDE catch the most common "lift" mirages — exposing too few users or running too short produces statistically invalid conclusions that agents will confidently report as wins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When optimizing onboarding, default to subtraction before addition. Prompt agents with "subtract first" and a step-count budget. Tour-builder agents tend to add steps; PLG wins usually come from removing friction.</statement>
      <rationale>The cognitive load of each onboarding step adds drop-off risk. The empirical pattern across PLG products is that removing a step typically outperforms adding a better version of the same step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always require a retention guardrail metric alongside activation. Winning variants on activation that cannibalise D30 retention must be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Activation and retention are not always aligned — a highly frictionless onboarding that skips important setup steps can produce activation wins that reverse by day 30.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="PQL Scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define PQL weights from in-product events that predict upgrade intent (workspace_created, second_user_invited, integration_added, limit_warning_seen), not vanity events (logged in, viewed dashboard). Score users as hot (≥12), warm (≥6), cold (below 6).</statement>
      <rationale>PQL scoring based on vanity events produces a scoring system that identifies engaged free users, not users likely to pay. Upgrade-intent events (limit warnings, team invitations) predict conversion; pageviews do not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Schedule quarterly PQL model recalibration. The event weights an agent ships today decay as the product changes; a static threshold becomes progressively wrong.</statement>
      <rationale>Product changes alter which events predict upgrade intent. A PQL model trained on v1 behavior systematically mis-scores users on v3 behavior without recalibration.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/pql-scorer.py">PostHog PQL scorer: weight in-app events, write pql_score + pql_tier back as person properties</reference>
</text>
