<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules-and-gotchas" title="Product-Led Growth: Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Hard rules for agent-safe PLG work, limitations of PLG in specific contexts, and AI-agent failure modes with mitigations.</summary>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running PLG optimization on a pre-PMF product with insufficient retention signal.</description>
      <reason>PLG amplifies a working loop; on a broken product it industrialises churn. Establish product-market fit before instrumenting the PLG funnel.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>AI onboarding personalization attempting to reference user behavior data before any events have been captured (cold start in first 60 seconds).</description>
      <reason>Enforce a "no behavioural reference before event N" rule. Cold-start personalization that references unavailable data produces error messages or hallucinated user attributes.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Privacy regimes (GDPR, India DPDP) restricting event tracking that PLG analytics depend on, with consent-mode gaps distorting funnels.</description>
      <reason>Instrument consent-mode handling before running PLG analytics. Funnels measured without accounting for consent gaps systematically under-count users in regulated markets.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Safety Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pricing and packaging changes require human approval. Revenue regression risk from autonomous pricing changes is non-recoverable — never delegate these to an agent without a human approval gate.</statement>
      <rationale>An agent that can autonomously change a pricing tier can inadvertently destroy MRR for an entire customer segment in a single run. The failure mode is irreversible within the billing cycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not let agents touch consent or cookie banner logic. One mis-step breaks all downstream PLG telemetry.</statement>
      <rationale>PLG analytics depend entirely on event capture; corrupting the consent layer silently breaks all measurement without an obvious error signal, causing strategy decisions to be made on invalid data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not let agents autonomously change a stakeholder's engagement level or send communications to external users. These are relationship decisions with political and legal consequences.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated communications to users without human review can violate communication preferences, trigger opt-outs, or send legally sensitive messages without approval.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents over-fitting on small samples: calling a winner with fewer than 1k users per variant or fewer than 7 days of runtime.</description>
      <reason>Enforce the minimum exposure and runtime gates at the agent output layer, not just in the prompt. Agents will call winners on day 2 with 200 users per variant if not blocked.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLMs inventing metrics ("engagement score 0-100") that have no source event in the analytics schema.</description>
      <reason>Constrain output to a known event vocabulary loaded from the analytics schema. Invented metrics cannot be tracked or validated.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Tour-builder agents adding steps rather than removing them, even when prompted to optimize onboarding.</description>
      <reason>Prompt explicitly with "subtract first" and a step-count budget. Monitor step-count delta as a guardrail metric alongside activation rate.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>PQL scoring drift: static model becomes wrong as the product evolves but continues to be used without recalibration.</description>
      <reason>Schedule quarterly PQL model recalibration as a standing SDD task. Flag if the model has not been recalibrated in 90+ days.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
