<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Lemon Squeezy Ops Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every Lemon Squeezy operation must satisfy. Hard rules; designed to prevent double-VAT, license bypass, dunning gaps, and affiliate churn.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-six-field-store" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every LS store carries 6 mandatory fields: store_id, store_name, currency (usd | eur), refund_policy (one of LS enums), uses_mor=true, variant_count (1-8 active variants).</statement>
      <rationale source="LS dashboard data on store-setup completeness">Stores missing any of the six fields cannot publish variants reliably; LS rejects payouts on incomplete stores.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-mor-not-self-vat" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lemon Squeezy acts as Merchant of Record. You do NOT collect VAT/GST yourself on LS-billed transactions. Your invoicing system must NOT issue a separate VAT invoice for those sales.</statement>
      <rationale source="LS MoR terms; EU VAT framework">Double-taxing the buyer is the most expensive LS mistake — leads to chargebacks and possible account suspension. LS remits VAT and provides MoR receipts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-license-api-for-software" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For software / license-keyed variants, license key delivery uses Lemon Squeezy's License API. The client validates the key at startup and on a daily cadence.</statement>
      <rationale source="LS License API docs; piracy-mitigation patterns">Hard-coded keys defeat the purpose. License API also lets you revoke keys on refund without rebuilding the binary.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-dunning-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Failed renewals trigger a 3-email dunning sequence: T+1 (soft reminder), T+4 (payment-method update CTA), T+8 (final notice + grace-period offer). After T+10, subscription is auto-cancelled with a re-subscribe link.</statement>
      <rationale source="SaaS dunning-recovery benchmarks (Profitwell + Chargebee studies)">Three-touch dunning recovers 35-45% of failed renewals; single-email recovers &lt;15%.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-affiliate-commission-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Affiliate commission is set between 30% and 50% for indie LS launches. Below 30% does not motivate; above 50% leaves the founder margin-thin on LS fees.</statement>
      <rationale source="Affiliate-marketing benchmarks; LS partner-program threads">30% is the engagement floor; 50% is the ceiling where founder still nets positive after LS fees.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-monthly-review-with-promotion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Monthly: pull LS dashboard CSV. Compute conversion_rate, refund_rate, mrr per variant. Promote top 2 to feature spots; demote bottom 2 (archive or unbundle).</statement>
      <rationale source="Indie-catalogue management practice">Without monthly pruning, the catalogue rots and dashboard noise hides the few variants that compound.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies-If hold and no Skip-If trigger applies, walk the 6-step procedure end-to-end and run the validator before publishing the store.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory run leaf">Decision-tree run leaf for canonical execution path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the Applies-If preconditions are not met OR any Skip-If disqualifier holds.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory skip leaf">Decision-tree skip leaf for non-applicable inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
