<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Content Audit — 6-Step Process">
  <summary>Structured procedure for inventorying, evaluating, and assigning actions to all content assets.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Scope and Goals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define what content is in scope and what question the audit must answer before gathering any data.</statement>
      <rationale>Auditing everything without a purpose produces data nobody acts on. Scoping first constrains tool selection, evaluation criteria, and report format.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Questions to answer: What content is in scope (all pages, blog only, help center)? What do we want to learn (what exists, what performs)? How will results be used (migration, strategy, cleanup)?</p>
    <p>Evaluation criteria to set: accuracy, relevance, quality, performance, accessibility, SEO.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Gather Content Inventory">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a site crawler for automated inventory; supplement manually for gated, dynamic, and legacy content.</statement>
      <rationale>Crawlers miss PDFs, gated content, and content served by JavaScript. A combined approach ensures completeness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Automated: site crawler (Screaming Frog, Sitebulb), CMS export, sitemap.</p>
    <p>Manual additions: PDFs and downloads, gated content, dynamic content, legacy systems.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Create Spreadsheet Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture at minimum: URL, title, type, date, author, status, metrics, quality score, and assigned action.</statement>
      <rationale>Consistent columns allow sorting by action and filtering by priority. Missing columns force a second pass.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/audit-spreadsheet.md">Column schema for the content inventory spreadsheet</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Evaluate Each Piece">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each content item against all evaluation criteria before assigning an action.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping evaluation and jumping to action produces inconsistent decisions that stakeholders cannot trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Per-item questions: Is it accurate and up-to-date? Relevant to users? Well-written? Performing well in analytics? Accessible? SEO-optimized?</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Assign Actions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign exactly one of six actions to every content item: Keep, Update, Consolidate, Rewrite, Remove, or Review.</statement>
      <rationale>Unassigned items become backlog debt. Six distinct actions prevent the common collapse into "keep or delete" which misses consolidation and rewrite opportunities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Keep — high quality, performing well, accurate.</item>
      <item>Update — good content, needs refresh or minor corrections.</item>
      <item>Consolidate — duplicate or overlapping with another piece.</item>
      <item>Rewrite — poor quality but important topic.</item>
      <item>Remove — outdated, irrelevant, or low value with no recovery path.</item>
      <item>Review — needs further evaluation before deciding.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Report and Recommend">
    <rule>
      <statement>Summarize findings by type, age, and action; include prioritized recommendations with explicit owners and timelines.</statement>
      <rationale>A report without owners and timelines produces no action. Priority tiers (immediate/short-term/long-term) make the workload plannable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/audit-report.md">Executive summary and findings report skeleton</reference>
  </section>
</text>
