<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Spike Protocol Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Spike Protocol Template application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-declared-question" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spike MUST open with a single declared question in interrogative form. Open-ended 'investigate X' framing is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Open-ended spikes balloon; the question is the time-box on intent.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-timebox-set" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spike MUST carry a declared timebox in hours or sprint-fraction. Untimed spikes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Without a timebox, spikes consume capacity opportunistically; the box is the cost ceiling.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-exit-criteria" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spike MUST declare exit criteria up front (what answer/evidence ends it). Spikes that exit on 'we are tired of it' are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Exit criteria force the spike to terminate on signal, not exhaustion; without them, the team cannot know when to stop.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-outcome-captured" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spike MUST end with a written outcome: answer, evidence summary, recommended next action (none / story / ADR / design doc). Unfinished outcomes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Spikes whose findings live in chat are functionally lost; the written outcome is the only artefact that survives the sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-stealth-implementation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spike MUST NOT ship production code. Throwaway prototypes are allowed; they MUST be flagged 'spike-throwaway' and deleted on outcome capture.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Spike code merged silently becomes the answer by default; the prohibition keeps spikes honest as investigation, not delivery.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
