<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-interview-frameworks" title="User Interview Frameworks and Structure">
  <summary>Two interview frameworks (basic user-interview and customer-interview) with typed stage structures, question categories, and golden rules.</summary>

  <section title="Interview Types">
    <p>Choose type based on validation stage:</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Match interview type to validation stage: Problem interviews in early discovery, Solution interviews after the problem is confirmed, Usability interviews when a prototype exists.</statement>
      <rationale>Running a usability interview without a validated problem wastes cycles; running a problem interview with a prototype primes the user to evaluate your solution rather than describe their reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Problem interviews: open-ended exploration, goal is to confirm problem existence. Solution interviews: prototype feedback, goal is to test solution fit. Usability interviews: task-based, goal is to identify UX friction. Discovery interviews: 30 min, context-setting before a deep problem interview.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="45-Minute Interview Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a 45-minute interview in five timed stages: Warm-up (5 min), Current State (10 min), Pain Exploration (15 min), Solution Probing (10 min), Wrap-up (5 min).</statement>
      <rationale>Timed stages force the researcher to protect the deep-dive phase; without structure, warm-up expands and pain exploration shrinks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Warm-up: build rapport, no sales. Current State: how do they do it today, what tools. Pain Exploration: what is frustrating, past behavior, workarounds. Solution Probing: show concept, get reaction, willingness to pay. Wrap-up: referrals, follow-up permission.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Golden Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Talk less than 20% of the time; never pitch; ask about past behavior not future intent; look for emotional signals (frustration, excitement).</statement>
      <rationale>Future-intent questions ("would you use this?") produce socially desirable answers, not behavioral data. Past behavior is the only reliable signal of what users actually do.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Sample past-behavior questions: "Tell me about the last time you [problem]..." / "What did you try? What happened?" / "On a scale of 1-10, how frustrating is this?" / "How much time or money does this cost you?"</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Question Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use four question types in sequence: Open (explore), Probing (go deeper), Clarifying (get example), Summary (confirm understanding).</statement>
      <rationale>Open questions surface the topic; probing questions reveal intensity; clarifying questions get specifics; summary confirms you understood correctly before moving on.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Open: "Tell me about..." Probing: "Why is that?" Clarifying: "Can you give an example?" Summary: "So you are saying..."</p>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/interview-script.md">45-min warm-up/pain/wrap-up script</reference>
  <reference path="templates/interview-guide.md">Full typed guide with hypothesis, script, and notes table</reference>
</text>
