<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples-and-antipatterns" title="Interview Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete insight examples from interview batches and four antipatterns that invalidate interview data.</summary>

  <section title="What Good Interview Output Looks Like">
    <example type="good">
      <note>After 10 problem interviews on a productivity tool: 8/10 mentioned the same frustration (manual status updates). Average time wasted: 3 hours per week. Willingness to pay: $50–100/month. Verbatim: "I would kill for a solution to this." These four signals together (convergence, time cost, WTP, emotional intensity) justify moving to solution validation.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Customer interview insight cluster: 8/10 mentioned same frustration; verbatim "I would pay $100 to not deal with this"; behavior — currently using 3 tools as workaround; insight — strong problem-solution fit indicated by active workaround behavior (workarounds are the most reliable signal that a real job exists).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Leading questions: "Don't you think X is great?" or "Isn't it frustrating when Y?"</description>
      <reason>Leading questions prime the answer; the user confirms your hypothesis rather than revealing their reality. All signal from a leading question must be discarded.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Future hypotheticals: "Would you use this if it existed?" or "Would you pay for this?"</description>
      <reason>Stated future intent does not predict behavior. People are optimistic about their future selves. Only past behavior and present commitments (pre-orders, sign-ups with a cost) are reliable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Pitching during the interview: explaining your solution before the pain has been fully explored.</description>
      <reason>Once the researcher pitches, the user evaluates the solution instead of describing their problem. The remainder of the interview produces solution feedback, not problem validation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Asking multiple questions at once: "What is the most frustrating part and how much time does it take and would you pay for a fix?"</description>
      <reason>The user answers only the last or easiest question. Each question must land and breathe independently.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Limitations">
    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>LLMs can draft guides and synthesize transcripts but cannot conduct live interviews; scrub PII before feeding transcripts to any LLM; validate synthesized insight clusters against raw source before using for decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Transcript synthesis misses sarcasm, hesitation, and emotional subtext; confirmation bias compounds when the agent was given a one-sided brief.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/prompt-draft-guide.txt">LLM prompt to draft an interview guide from a hypothesis</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-synthesize.txt">LLM prompt to extract themes and surprising findings from transcripts</reference>
  <reference path="templates/theme-extractor.py">Batch keyword counter across transcript .txt files</reference>
</text>
