<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Legal Fundamentals for Founders: ToS, Privacy, and Trademark Basics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `ops-legal-basics` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-three-document-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ship Terms of Service, Privacy Policy, and at least one IP-protection artefact (trademark filing or copyright notice) BEFORE accepting the first paying customer. Operating without these is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Online-business legal practice (Bloomberg Law, Cooley GO templates)">Operating without a ToS / Privacy Policy exposes the operator to unlimited liability and regulator action (GDPR, CCPA fines start at the first user). The floor is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-tos-required-clauses" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ToS MUST include: payment terms, billing cycles, IP ownership, disclaimers, liability cap, termination, and governing-law clause. Missing any of these renders the ToS unenforceable in most disputes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-law canon (Restatement (Second) of Contracts §§ 1-19)">Courts routinely strike incomplete ToS as unconscionable or unenforceable. The seven clauses above are the operational floor for any consumer-facing agreement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-privacy-policy-disclosure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Privacy Policy MUST disclose: data categories collected, purposes, retention period, user rights (access / deletion / portability), and security measures. Vague language ('we may collect') is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Data-protection canon (GDPR Art. 13-14; CCPA § 1798.100)">GDPR and CCPA require specific, layered disclosure with user-rights language. Vague disclosure is treated as no disclosure under enforcement actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-trademark-before-brand-spend" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>File for trademark registration on the brand name BEFORE any paid marketing campaign that uses the mark prominently. Spending on a mark before filing exposes the operator to squatting and infringement risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="USPTO and EUIPO trademark practice">Common-law trademark rights are narrow; registered marks get nationwide protection. Pre-spend filing is the cheapest insurance against losing the brand to a faster registrant.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-jurisdiction-specific-localisation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Confirm jurisdiction-specific requirements (GDPR / CCPA / COPPA / ADA) per the markets the product accepts customers from. US-only ToS for an EU-accessible site is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cross-border privacy and accessibility practice">Regulators apply law based on customer location, not operator location. EU-accessible products must comply with GDPR regardless of where the operator is.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
