<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-entity-and-policies" title="Business Entity and Essential Policies">
  <summary>Entity selection framework and required online-business policies for a new solopreneur product.</summary>

  <section title="Entity Choice">
    <rule>
      <statement>Form a business entity before taking real money. Personal liability flowing from business activities is the most common and most preventable founder mistake.</statement>
      <rationale>Sole proprietorships provide zero liability protection. An LLC costs $50–500 to form and creates a legal barrier between business debts and personal assets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Entity comparison for solopreneurs:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Sole Proprietorship — no liability protection, personal taxes, use only for idea validation</item>
      <item>LLC — liability protection, pass-through taxes, credible with customers; correct choice for most solopreneurs</item>
      <item>S-Corp — liability protection, salary + distributions tax structure; evaluate at $80–100K+ SE income</item>
      <item>C-Corp — liability protection, corporate taxes; only for investment-seeking startups</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>For US-based businesses, form in home state unless Delaware or Wyoming offers a specific advantage (e.g., anonymous ownership in Wyoming, or investor expectation in Delaware for future fundraising).</statement>
      <rationale>Foreign-state registration requires a registered agent fee plus an extra annual report in your home state, negating cost savings for most solopreneurs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>LLC formation steps: choose state, file articles of organization, obtain EIN from IRS, open business bank account, register for state taxes if required.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Required Policies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Publish a Terms of Service, Privacy Policy, Cookie Policy, and Refund Policy before accepting user data or payment from any jurisdiction.</statement>
      <rationale>GDPR requires a Privacy Policy as a legal obligation for any EU user; ToS limits liability; Cookie Policy is required for GDPR/CCPA cookie consent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Terms of Service must include: acceptance of terms, service description, user responsibilities, payment terms, IP ownership, disclaimers (no warranty, limitation of liability), termination, and governing law.</p>
    <p>Privacy Policy must include: data collected and how, purpose of use, third-party sharing, retention period, user rights (access/correction/deletion, GDPR/CCPA), security measures, and contact information.</p>
    <reference path="templates/policy-sections.txt">Required sections for ToS and Privacy Policy as plain-text scaffolds</reference>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never copy a competitor's policy. Copyright violation and factual inaccuracies from the copied policy both create enforcement risks.</statement>
      <rationale>Policies contain factual claims about your data practices. A competitor's claims about their vendors and retention do not match yours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag and date every policy at the top with "Effective Date: YYYY-MM-DD, Version: N" and maintain a version history page.</statement>
      <rationale>Regulators and users reference specific effective dates during disputes; un-dated policies have no evidentiary force.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
