<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-regulations-and-ip" title="Privacy Regulations, IP Protection, and Contract Essentials">
  <summary>Key privacy regulations matrix, IP type priorities, and minimum contract set for a new online business.</summary>

  <section title="Privacy Regulations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Determine which regulations apply based on user geography, not company location: GDPR applies if you have EU users; CCPA applies if you have California users; CAN-SPAM applies to all US email marketing.</statement>
      <rationale>Regulation follows the user, not the business address. A US LLC serving EU users must comply with GDPR.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Regulation matrix:</p>
    <list>
      <item>GDPR (EU users): consent for non-essential cookies, data processing agreement with vendors, respond to access/deletion requests within 30 days, report breaches within 72 hours</item>
      <item>CCPA/CPRA (California users): disclose data collection, provide opt-out of sale, honor access and deletion requests</item>
      <item>CAN-SPAM (US email): no deceptive subject lines, include physical address, working unsubscribe link, honor opt-outs within 10 days</item>
      <item>COPPA (children under 13): parental consent required before collecting any data; avoid targeting if product may attract minors</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Intellectual Property">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before launch, search the USPTO TESS database for your company name, product name, and tagline. Register the company name trademark as the first priority.</statement>
      <rationale>Trademark rights in the US attach to first use, but registration is required to sue for infringement. A name collision discovered post-launch requires rebranding, which costs far more than a $350 trademark filing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>IP type priority order: (1) company name trademark, (2) product name, (3) logo, (4) tagline if distinctive. Copyright on creative works is automatic — registration is optional but required to sue. Trade secrets require only consistent internal secrecy; no registration.</p>
    <reference path="templates/tsdr-status.py">USPTO trademark status lookup stub via TSDR API</reference>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a pre-launch name check: USPTO TESS search, domain availability, social media handle availability. Do all three before committing to a brand name.</statement>
      <rationale>Acquiring a domain after launch from a squatter costs 10–100x registration price. Social handle conflicts require awkward alternatives.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Contract Essentials">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every contractor agreement must include: "work for hire" IP assignment clause, moral-rights waiver where jurisdiction allows, confidentiality clause, independent-contractor status statement, and payment terms.</statement>
      <rationale>Without IP assignment, the contractor may retain copyright on work product. Without independent-contractor language, "employee-style" controls (set hours, supplied equipment) create misclassification liability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Minimum contract set: customer agreement (scope, payment, liability), contractor agreement (IP assignment, confidentiality, IC status), NDA (for sharing confidential information with partners), affiliate agreement (commission structure, disclosure requirements, approved messaging).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include severability and entire-agreement clauses in every contract.</statement>
      <rationale>Severability prevents one unenforceable clause from voiding the whole contract. Entire-agreement prevents verbal side-deals from becoming enforceable obligations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
