<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples-and-gotchas" title="Examples and AI-Agent Gotchas for Legal Basics">
  <summary>SaaS and info-product legal setup examples with concrete decisions, and AI-agent limitations for legal drafting.</summary>

  <section title="Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS legal setup (project management tool): Delaware LLC, GDPR-compliant Privacy Policy, ToS with 99.9% SLA target (not guaranteed), customer owns their data, liability capped at subscription fees, automatic renewal with 30-day notice, cookie consent banner, DPA available for enterprise customers.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Info-product legal setup (online course): Wyoming LLC, ToS with education disclaimers (no guarantee of results, educational purposes only, not professional advice), 30-day refund policy, earnings disclaimer on testimonials with typical results disclosure.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Founder launches a subscription SaaS, takes $5K in revenue, then incorporates. The revenue period before entity formation exposed the founder personally to any claims arising during that period.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="When to Get a Lawyer">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use templates and services for standard solopreneur legal needs; hire a lawyer for: raising investment, large contracts, IP disputes, regulatory issues, and acquisition.</statement>
      <rationale>Legal templates handle 80% of solopreneur needs at 1% of lawyer cost. The exceptions are situations where a mistake has multi-year financial consequences.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using LLM-generated contracts without human counsel review before signing.</description>
      <reason>LLMs hallucinate jurisdictions, statutes, and unenforceable clauses. "Legalese" bias produces florid clauses from training data. Limitation-of-liability and arbitration clauses have jurisdiction-specific enforceability nuances that agents flatten.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-generating privacy policies without grounding each claim in a vendor inventory.</description>
      <reason>Agents overclaim (disclose more processing than occurs) or underdisclose — both are enforcement risks. Every Privacy Policy statement must match actual data flows.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating an agent's trademark "available?" conclusion as final without human USPTO TESS review.</description>
      <reason>Phonetic and visual proximity beats exact-string matches. An agent doing string matching will miss "Cursor" vs. "Curser" type conflicts that TESS's proximity search catches.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Feeding privileged draft contracts to a public LLM API.</description>
      <reason>Attorney-client privilege may be waived when communications are shared with third-party AI services. Use local models or counsel's own tooling for privileged work.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent-drafted contractor agreements re-introducing employee-style controls (set hours, supplied tools).</description>
      <reason>Fixed hours and employer-supplied equipment are IRS misclassification flags. Cross-check every contractor agreement against `ops-contractor-basics`.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
