<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ops-legal-basics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ops-legal-basics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Adopting a ToS that includes "no refunds, ever" or "company is not liable for any damages, including data loss or security breaches."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Absolute liability waivers are often unenforceable; courts may deem them unconscionable. Balancing customer protection (reasonable cancellation, data export rights) with company protection (reasonable liability caps, remedies) is the goal.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Stating "We use Google Analytics" without mentioning that Google Analytics transfers EU user data to the US, which requires either Standard Contractual Clauses or a Data Processing Agreement under GDPR.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Data transfers outside the EU are heavily regulated. If you do not have appropriate legal mechanisms in place, you are violating GDPR even if the Privacy Policy mentions Google Analytics. Transparency alone is not sufficient; you must also have legal agreements with processors.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Assuming that because you registered a domain name (example.com), your brand name is legally protected.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Domain registration and trademark registration are separate. Domain registration gives you the web address; trademark registration protects your brand name in commerce. You can have a domain without a trademark and vice versa.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Hiring a law firm to write a complete legal package (ToS, Privacy Policy, DPA, NDA, employee handbook) before launch or with minimal revenue.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-launch legal spending of $10k plus is usually wasteful because the business model and feature set are still changing. Customize a template first, then get lawyer review after you have paying customers and revenue to justify the cost.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
