<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gcp-billing-cost Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gcp-billing-cost. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every production project MUST have a budget configured with alert thresholds at 50%, 90%, and 100% of the monthly spend target. Alerts MUST route to a monitored notification channel (email group or Pub/Sub).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without budget alerts, cost anomalies (runaway VMs, data egress spikes, accidental BigQuery full table scans) go undetected until the monthly bill. Multi-threshold alerts give early warning before overspend is irrecoverable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Billing exports MUST be enabled to BigQuery for all production billing accounts. The export dataset must be queried via scheduled queries or Looker Studio to produce per-team cost reports at least monthly.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The GCP console billing UI does not support custom cost allocation or chargeback. BigQuery exports are the only way to query costs by label, folder, or project combination at scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All projects MUST have env, team, and cost_center labels. All major resources (VMs, GKE node pools, Cloud SQL instances, buckets) MUST inherit or carry the same labels. Enforce via org policy custom constraint (custom.requireProjectLabels).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Labels are propagated to billing export line items. A missing label on a VM means that VM's cost appears as unattributed in chargeback reports — the team is not charged and no one investigates the spend.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
