<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="interview-methods">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>hr-recruiter</domain>
    <summary>Structured-interview methodologies: competencies, STAR behavioral questions, scorecards, technical assessments, reference checks, and debrief. Cap competencies 4-6; use observable behavioral anchors.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>structured-interview</tag>
      <tag>hiring</tag>
      <tag>behavioral-interview</tag>
      <tag>competencies</tag>
      <tag>recruitment</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <author>Schmidt, Hunter (1998)</author>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Interview Methods</title>

    <summary>Bundle of structured-interview methodologies covering competency definition, STAR behavioral questions, scorecards, technical assessments, culture-fit assessment, reference checks, and hiring-committee debrief. The testable rule: cap competencies at 4-6 with weights summing to 100% — more dilutes predictive signal; behavioral anchors must be observable verbs, never traits ("driven", "strong").</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Unstructured interviews have near-zero predictive validity. Schmidt and Hunter (1998) show structured behavioral interviews are roughly twice as predictive as unstructured ones. Forcing independent scorecard submission before the debrief channel opens prevents the loudest-voice-wins dynamic. Inter-rater reliability (Cohen's kappa) below 0.4 on any competency signals recalibration is needed before a hire decision.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Standing up an interview process from scratch for a new role family: competencies → questions → scorecards → debrief flow.</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing process whose interview-to-offer rate falls outside the 15-25% band.</item>
        <item>Calibrating interviewers across geographies where in-person calibration is impractical.</item>
        <item>Rolling out structured interviews after a hiring-manager change before legacy bias re-anchors.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-hire one-off (founder hiring a co-founder, exec search) — overhead exceeds benefit; use a 2-step trust-and-reference loop.</item>
        <item>Roles where the only valid signal is portfolio review (illustrators, cinematographers).</item>
        <item>Volume retail or hourly hiring at scale — use realistic job previews, not panel interviews.</item>
        <item>Statutorily-fixed questionnaires (clinical, legal regulated roles).</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="process-overview">
      <p>End-to-end structured interview pipeline: competency definition, question generation, scorecard, calibration, and debrief synthesis.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Define exactly 4-6 competencies with weights summing to 100%. Each competency must be described in observable verbs ("re-architected payment retry to cut failures"), never traits ("driven", "strong").</statement>
        <rationale>Schmidt and Hunter (1998): structured interviews with observable behavioral anchors are ~2x more predictive than unstructured. More than 6 competencies dilutes the signal; fewer than 4 leaves critical gaps.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Generate 2-3 STAR questions per competency, each in past-tense behavioral framing. Include 2 probing follow-ups per question. Cap at one competency per question — no double-barreled questions.</statement>
        <rationale>Double-barreled questions ("tell me about a time you led a team and resolved conflict") let candidates answer only the easier half, producing incomplete evidence on both competencies.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Behavioral anchors per competency must describe observable outcomes at scores 1, 3, and 5. Never use adjectives for anchors; use specific past-tense action descriptions.</statement>
        <rationale>Without observable anchors, scores reflect similarity to the hiring manager ("5 = reminds me of our best performer") rather than competency evidence, producing homogeneous hires.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Generate 3 mock candidate answers (strong/borderline/weak) per question for new interviewer calibration. Use these in the training session, not in real candidate assessment.</statement>
        <rationale>Interviewers who have never calibrated on the same response produce inter-rater agreement (Cohen's kappa) below 0.4 — essentially random scoring that defeats the purpose of structured interviews.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Run debrief synthesis only after all independent scorecards are submitted. Never before. Surface competencies with score variance >= 2 and evidence vs. impression-only language.</statement>
        <rationale>Debrief synthesis before independent scoring causes anchoring: interviewers adjust their scores toward whoever spoke first, eliminating the value of independent evaluation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Debrief synthesis must not produce a hire/no-hire recommendation. It surfaces data for human decision makers. The hiring decision is always human.</statement>
        <rationale>LLM-produced "hire" recommendations create legal exposure (automated employment decisions under EU AI Act, EEOC) and remove human accountability for the decision.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <reference path="templates/interview-scorecard.md">Competency scorecard with behavioral anchors and hire/no-hire field.</reference>
      <reference path="templates/irr-check.py">Cohen's kappa inter-rater check; gates debrief when kappa &lt; 0.4.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="method-catalog">
      <p>Quick-reference catalog of six interview methods with decision criteria for when to use each.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use structured behavioral interview (STAR) for any role where past behavior predicts future performance: managerial, cross-functional, customer-facing. Same questions for every candidate at the same level.</statement>
        <rationale>Inconsistent questions between candidates make comparison impossible and introduce evaluator bias toward candidates whose answers happened to match their prepared questions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Pair technical assessment with behavioral for roles at L3+. Time-box at 2-4 hours max. Provide clear evaluation criteria in writing before the candidate begins. Compensate candidate time for take-home assessments >2 hours.</statement>
        <rationale>Uncompensated multi-hour take-homes create selection bias toward candidates who can afford the unpaid time, systematically disadvantaging caregivers and those working multiple jobs.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Technical assessment formats:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Take-home project: deep evaluation, async, best for senior roles.</item>
        <item>Live coding: real-time problem-solving and thinking-aloud signal.</item>
        <item>Code review: real-world quality judgment, harder to coach.</item>
        <item>System design: senior IC and manager roles.</item>
        <item>Pair programming: collaboration signal, requires calibrated interviewer.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Never use "culture fit" as a scoring dimension without defining it in observable, values-based terms. "Culture fit" as an undefined concept is a documented path to homogeneous, legally vulnerable hires.</statement>
        <rationale>Undefined culture-fit scores correlate with protected-class characteristics (background, communication style, school pedigree) and are the leading cause of disparate impact claims in hiring.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use "Would you rehire them?" as the terminal reference question. Ask about specific behaviors from the candidate's STAR responses when possible, to verify claims.</statement>
        <rationale>"Would you rehire?" forces a binary judgment that correlates more strongly with actual performance than open-ended "what were their strengths?" questions, which produce social desirability bias.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Lock debrief discussion until all scorecards are submitted. Review high-variance competencies first. Require that every "hire" and "no hire" recommendation cite specific evidence from the interview record.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a process lock, the first speaker anchors the group. High-variance competencies need resolution before consensus, not after — otherwise strong signals get averaged away.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="rules-and-gotchas">
      <p>Competency cap rule, bias/legal review pass, auto-score block, FCRA/GDPR constraints, and calibration drift. LLM-specific limitations: over-production of competencies (8-12 are common outputs), question clustering in leadership/communication with under-coverage of technical depth, behavioral anchors written with lifestyle adjectives ("driven", "strong") instead of observable behaviors, and cross-cultural pragmatics issues where STAR storytelling style varies by region.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Hard cap at 4-6 competencies. Run a deduplication pass on generated questions to ensure no question cluster covers the same competency twice from different angles.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs over-produce competencies (8-12 are common outputs) and cluster questions in leadership/communication. Explicit caps and dedup are necessary post-processing steps, not optional.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Lock the question bank per role-level for a minimum of 6 months after calibration. Every change resets the inter-rater baseline, invalidating historical comparison data.</statement>
        <rationale>Per-hiring-manager question variation is the primary cause of "same competency, wildly different hire bar" problems within the same team.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Run a fresh-context bias review pass on every generated question bank before use. The reviewing agent must not have access to the original generation rationale.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs silently inject protected-class proxies ("willing to relocate with family?", "where are you originally from?"). The reviewing agent needs a clean context to surface these without anchoring to the generator's intent.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Run the IRR check (Cohen's kappa) monthly across the same role's scorecards. Flag any interviewer whose kappa vs. peers drops below 0.4 on any competency for calibration.</statement>
        <rationale>Calibration drift is invisible without metrics. An interviewer who scores 5 on communication for every candidate (regardless of evidence) dilutes the panel's signal without being visible to peers.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Interview process stage guidance for agents: Stage 1 (competency definition) use Opus — interrogate the JD + leveling rubric, emit 4-6 competencies with weights. Stage 2 (question generation) use Sonnet, parameterized per competency with hard count cap — avoid double-barreled questions. Stage 3 (scorecard) use Sonnet — produce behavioral anchors per competency on 1-5 scale, never adjectives. Stage 4 (calibration pack) use Sonnet — generate 3 mock candidate answers (strong/borderline/weak) per question. Stage 5 (debrief synthesis) use Opus only after independent scores submitted — surface high-variance competencies and evidence vs. impression-only language. Never produce hire/no-hire recommendations; surface data for human decision makers.</p>

      <p>ATS and tool compatibility: prefer systems with REST APIs + per-stage webhooks (Greenhouse, Lever, Ashby, Workable). Polling burns tokens. Video-interview tools like HireVue allow transcript extraction but never auto-scoring (regulatory risk). Technical assessment tools (CodeSignal, HackerRank, CoderPad) support REST + webhook on submission. Background checks (Checkr, Certn) are REST-accessible but consent flow is human-only by law. Assessments tools (Modern Hire, Plum) require explicit bias audit if used.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Sending reference-check questions via agent without logging candidate consent in the ATS.</description>
        <reason>FCRA (US), GDPR (EU), and UK GDPR require documented consent before conducting third-party reference checks. Auto-send without consent logging is a compliance violation.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Bias silent in the questions an agent picks rather than the language used.</description>
        <reason>Historical hiring data biases the bank toward what already worked; explicit bias review and cross-cultural calibration are necessary safeguards.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>STAR scoring assuming US-grad-style narrative conventions.</description>
        <reason>Cross-cultural pragmatics vary; agent scoring must account for regional communication style differences, not penalize non-Western candidates for narrative structure.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <reference path="templates/interview-scorecard.md">Behavioral anchor scorecard per competency.</reference>
      <reference path="templates/irr-check.py">Inter-rater agreement computation with debrief gate at kappa &lt; 0.4.</reference>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/interview-scorecard.md" purpose="Competency-by-competency scoring template with behavioral anchors and hire/no-hire field."/>
      <template path="templates/irr-check.py" purpose="Cohen's kappa inter-rater agreement check; gates debrief when kappa &lt; 0.4 per competency."/>
    </templates>

    <checklist>
      <check>Competencies defined (4-6) with observable behavioral verbs, no trait adjectives.</check>
      <check>Questions generated: 2-3 STAR format per competency, past-tense behavioral framing, no double-barreling.</check>
      <check>Behavioral anchors written for scores 1, 3, 5 per competency using observable actions, not adjectives.</check>
      <check>Mock candidate answers (strong/borderline/weak) created per question for calibration.</check>
      <check>Fresh-context bias review completed; protected-class proxies flagged and removed.</check>
      <check>Inter-rater reliability (Cohen's kappa) >= 0.4 across interviewers on each competency before hire decision.</check>
      <check>Question bank locked for minimum 6 months post-calibration; any changes require re-calibration.</check>
      <check>All reference-check consent logged in ATS before agent sends questions.</check>
    </checklist>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Structured_interview"/>
      <link href="https://www.shrm.org/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
