<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SLO Definition Template Per Service Class Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the SLO Definition Template Per Service Class methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-template-per-service-class" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each service-class MUST have a canonical SLI template (PromQL query + label keys + window). Authors fork the template; they don't write SLIs from scratch.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Workbook Ch.4">Hand-rolled SLIs drift in format; templates make them comparable across teams.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-customer-facing-sli" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>User-facing SLIs MUST measure the customer experience: HTTP success rate, end-to-end latency, error rate. Resource-utilisation metrics (CPU, RAM) are NOT user-facing SLIs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Workbook — defining SLOs">CPU &lt; 80% can hold while customers see 5xx; SLIs measure the customer, not the box.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-target-with-rationale" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every SLO target carries a recorded rationale referencing customer commitment, business cost of breach, or peer benchmark. '99.9% because it sounds good' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="SLO design — Liu, Beyer et al.">Magic numbers calcify; documented rationale lets future authors recalibrate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-window-matched-to-decision" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Error-budget window MUST match the decision cycle: 30 days for ship-freeze decisions, 7 days for canary-halt decisions, 24h for incident bridge decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="multi-window multi-burn-rate alerting">30-day windows hide fast-burn; 1h windows are too noisy for ship-freeze. Window must match the action it gates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-sli-as-recording-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>SLI PromQL MUST be a recording rule (level:metric:operation pattern), not an ad-hoc query in alert/dashboard. Recording rule is the canonical SLI series.</statement>
      <rationale source="Prometheus recording-rule best practices">Ad-hoc queries drift; one recording rule per SLI prevents 3 dashboards measuring 'availability' differently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-class-coverage-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every service in the catalog MUST be assigned to exactly one service class; services without a class are flagged as gaps, not silently skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="catalog hygiene">Unclassified services produce orphan SLOs or none at all.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
