<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="SLO Definition — Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six failure modes when authoring SLOs per class. Each has a detector and a repair.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="high">
      <description>Dashboard-driven SLOs: targets copied from current Grafana lines without a user-acceptable conversation.</description>
      <detector>SLO target value matches the trailing-30-day baseline value ±0.05 AND user_acceptable_error_rationale field is empty or generic</detector>
      <repair>Hold the product conversation. Capture the rationale in writing. Re-set the target based on user acceptability; document the gap (or congruence) with current performance.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="high">
      <description>Missing budget policy: SLO exists but no document defines what burn means operationally. Burn alerts are noise.</description>
      <detector>budget_policy_path empty OR document does not exist</detector>
      <repair>Write the policy. Even a 1-page minimum: who owns the SLO, what triggers a freeze, what reverts it. The SLO is not in production until the policy is published.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="high">
      <description>Class mismatch: service classified as API but is actually an async worker masked behind an API. Template SLIs miss the queue-age signal that matters.</description>
      <detector>API SLI set in use AND service has a backlog metric showing &gt;1min queue age routinely</detector>
      <repair>Re-classify the service. Apply the async-worker template. Document the class change.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>SLI sprawl: 9 SLIs per service; alerts everywhere; nobody owns the response.</description>
      <detector>sli_set length &gt; 6 per service</detector>
      <repair>Cut to template + 2. Move discarded metrics to monitoring dashboards (informational) but not SLI status. Document the rationale.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Calendar-month window leak: SLO is computed monthly; end-of-month sees panic and Jan-1 sees an artificial reset that hides drift.</description>
      <detector>window field equals "calendar-month" OR cron-driven monthly resets exist in the metric pipeline</detector>
      <repair>Switch to 30-day rolling window. Update the metric query and alerting rules. Communicate the change to stakeholders.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale review: SLO defined 18 months ago; service has 10x more traffic and 2 new dependencies; target is no longer meaningful.</description>
      <detector>last_reviewed older than 90 days OR traffic volume changed &gt; 3x since last review</detector>
      <repair>Quarterly SLO review with product. Update target or window as needed. Spawn ADR if architecture changed substantially.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>
      SLO scaffolding agents read service code and Grafana dashboards. They MUST
      NOT propose a target based on the current dashboard value alone. The
      user-acceptable rationale comes from product; the agent suggests, the
      product owner approves.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>
      Product owner co-signs SLO targets. SRE / DevOps owns the SLI definitions
      and the budget policy. The 90-day review forces fresh conversation rather
      than passive carry-over.
    </p>
  </section>
</text>
