<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Azure Compute Tier Selection Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Azure Compute Tier Selection` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="workload-identity-aks" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>AKS workloads MUST use Workload Identity (OIDC federation); deprecated Pod Identity is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Azure AKS Workload Identity docs">Pod Identity is deprecated; secrets-in-cluster patterns are higher-risk.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="managed-identity-everywhere" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All Azure resource access from compute MUST use Managed Identity. Service principal credentials in env vars / secrets are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Azure security baseline">Stored credentials can be exfiltrated; MI tokens expire with the resource.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="vmss-flex-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>VMSS MUST use Flexible orchestration for new workloads; Uniform mode is deprecated.</statement>
      <rationale source="Azure VMSS roadmap">Uniform mode is being retired by Microsoft; Flexible supports mixed instance types and zone spreading.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="zone-redundant-prod" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production VMs + VMSS MUST be deployed across Availability Zones (99.99% SLA). Availability Sets (99.95% SLA) are forbidden for new workloads.</statement>
      <rationale source="Azure SLA docs">Zone failures, while rare, are documented; AZ deployment is the only zone-failure protection.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="spot-mix-not-pure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pure Spot is forbidden for prod. Spot Priority Mix with a non-zero on-demand baseline is the only acceptable Spot pattern for prod.</statement>
      <rationale source="Azure Spot eviction analyses">Spot eviction rates &gt; 20% during peak demand make pure-Spot prod unreliable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="private-endpoint-paas" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Compute resources MUST reach PaaS services (SQL / Storage / KV / ACR) via private endpoints, not public endpoints.</statement>
      <rationale source="Azure Private Link guide">Public endpoints expose PaaS to internet routing + DDoS even when locked down by firewall.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>