<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="acceptance-criteria">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Testable conditions for requirement acceptance. BDD or checklist format covering paths, boundaries, errors, non-functional constraints. Maps to test cases in Definition of Done.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>acceptance-criteria</tag>
      <tag>bdd</tag>
      <tag>testing</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Acceptance Criteria</title>
    <summary>Explicit, testable conditions that define when a requirement is accepted as complete. Written in Given-When-Then (BDD) or rule-based checklist format, covering the happy path, alternative paths, boundaries, error handling, performance, and security. Each criterion maps to at least one test case and forms part of the Definition of Done.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>"Done" means different things to different people: developers consider a feature complete while users disagree; testing cannot run without something to test against; acceptance meetings become disputes. Acceptance criteria create a shared, pre-agreed finish line that eliminates subjective acceptance, drives testability, and prevents disputes at delivery.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Every user story or requirement before a sprint starts — criteria must exist before development begins</item>
        <item>Bug fixes where the distinction between "expected" and "actual" behavior needs to be documented</item>
        <item>Technical stories where success requires a measurable outcome (throughput, error rate, response time)</item>
        <item>Before UAT to give users a concrete verification script rather than open-ended exploration</item>
        <item>Integrating with BDD tooling (Cucumber, SpecFlow) where Given-When-Then maps directly to test steps</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Vague exploratory stories tagged "spike" or "research" — an output contract is the right artifact, not acceptance criteria</item>
        <item>When writing criteria for 30+ scenarios in one story — the story is too large; split it first</item>
        <item>System-level non-functional requirements (SLOs, capacity) — these belong in the architecture decision record or SLA, not per-story criteria</item>
        <item>Pure infrastructure/ops tasks with no user-visible behavior — a runbook or configuration checklist applies instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="format-options">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use Given-When-Then (BDD) format for scenarios with distinct preconditions and user actions — one scenario per behavior path. Use rule-based checklist format for lists of system constraints and validation rules with no actor interaction sequence.</statement>
        <rationale>BDD format is tool-executable (Cucumber, SpecFlow) and enforces context-action-outcome structure; checklist format is faster for pure validation rules but lacks scenario context.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>BDD template: "Given [precondition/context] / And [additional condition] / When [action taken] / Then [expected outcome] / And [additional outcome]". Each Given-When-Then block is one scenario and produces at least one test case.</statement>
        <rationale>One-to-one mapping between scenarios and test cases makes coverage measurement deterministic.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="five-coverage-categories">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every requirement must have acceptance criteria covering at minimum: happy path (everything works), at least one alternative path (valid variation), at least one boundary condition, at least one error handling case, and any applicable non-functional constraints (performance, security).</statement>
        <rationale>Happy-path-only criteria are the most common acceptance criteria failure; missing alternative and error scenarios are discovered during UAT when correction cost is highest.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Happy path: what happens when all inputs are valid and system is in normal state</item>
        <item>Alternatives: valid variations in actor actions or system state</item>
        <item>Boundaries: limit values (min, max, exactly-at-limit, just-over-limit)</item>
        <item>Errors: invalid input, system failure, business rule violation</item>
        <item>Non-functional: specific performance thresholds, security access controls</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="five-step-authoring-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 1 — understand the requirement: identify the actor goal, expected outcome, what could go wrong, and where the boundaries are. Step 2 — choose format (BDD vs. checklist). Step 3 — write criteria covering all five categories. Step 4 — validate with Product Owner, developers, and QA. Step 5 — use each criterion as a test case trigger in the Definition of Done.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping validation with QA produces untestable criteria; skipping validation with developers produces technically infeasible criteria — both discovered at the wrong time.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="testability-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every acceptance criterion must be independently testable: there must exist a concrete action that produces a verifiable, observable outcome. Reject any criterion that is subjective ("user-friendly"), implementation-specific ("store in MySQL"), or unmeasurable ("fast").</statement>
        <rationale>Untestable criteria cannot be included in the Definition of Done; they become subjective acceptance disputes at delivery time.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Performance criteria must specify exact numeric thresholds: "Response time under 2 seconds at 95th percentile under 500 concurrent users" — not "the system must be fast".</statement>
        <rationale>Without a numeric threshold, QA cannot write a load test and "fast" means different things to every stakeholder.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Security criteria must specify the role and the prohibited or required action: "Only users with Admin role can delete customer records." Never "the system must be secure."</statement>
        <rationale>Role-based security criteria map directly to authorization test cases; vague security statements map to nothing testable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="story-type-guidelines">
      <p>Feature stories: focus on user outcomes, cover happy path and at least 2 alternative scenarios, include error handling, add performance criteria only if the feature has a response-time requirement.</p>
      <p>Bug fixes: describe expected vs. actual behavior precisely, include reproduction steps, define the "fixed" state as an observable outcome.</p>
      <p>Technical stories: focus on technical outcomes (throughput, error rate, API contract), include a measurable verification method, define "done" as a observable system state or metric.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Too vague: "User can log in" — no context, no error handling, no boundary conditions.</description>
        <reason>Vague criteria cannot produce test cases; every meaningful word in a criterion must be independently testable.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Implementation details: "Store session token in Redis with 30-minute TTL" — the how, not the what.</description>
        <reason>Implementation criteria couple the spec to a specific technical choice; when the implementation changes the criteria become false without the behavior changing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Only happy path: no error scenarios, no boundary conditions.</description>
        <reason>Error paths are discovered during UAT; correcting them after development costs 10x more than specifying them upfront.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Too many criteria for one story: 50+ criteria indicate the story should be split.</description>
        <reason>A story with 50 criteria takes a sprint to test; split into smaller stories that can be independently accepted and deployed.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="login-feature-bdd-example">
      <example type="good" title="Login Feature with BDD Format">
        <code lang="gherkin"><![CDATA[
Scenario 1: Successful login
  Given I am on the login page
  And I have a valid registered account
  When I enter my correct email and password
  And I click "Login"
  Then I am redirected to the dashboard
  And I see a welcome message containing my first name
  And my session is active for 30 minutes

Scenario 2: Invalid credentials
  Given I am on the login page
  When I enter an incorrect email or password
  And I click "Login"
  Then I see the error message "Invalid email or password"
  And I remain on the login page
  And the password field is cleared

Scenario 3: Account locked after repeated failures
  Given I have failed login 5 consecutive times
  When I attempt to log in again
  Then I see "Account locked. Try again in 30 minutes."
  And login attempts are rejected for 30 minutes for this account

Non-functional:
  - Login request must complete within 2 seconds (p95, production load)
  - Password must not appear in application logs or network responses
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="shopping-cart-checklist-example">
      <example type="good" title="Shopping Cart with Rule-Based Checklist">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Functional criteria:
- [ ] User can add a product to the cart from the product detail page
- [ ] User can add a product to the cart from search results
- [ ] Cart icon in the header shows current item count
- [ ] Adding the same product increments quantity (no duplicate line items)
- [ ] Maximum quantity per product per cart is 99
- [ ] User sees a confirmation notification when an item is added

Persistence criteria:
- [ ] Cart persists for 30 days for logged-in users
- [ ] Cart persists for the browser session duration for guest users

Validation criteria:
- [ ] Out-of-stock products cannot be added to the cart
- [ ] Quantity field accepts only positive integers between 1 and 99
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ba-facilitation-and-cross-team-handoff">
      <p>Business analysts facilitate AC authoring as a cross-team conversation, not a solo transcription effort. The BA→QA hand-off is critical: AC is the contract between BA (who understands business intent) and QA (who writes executable test cases). AC must outlive the sprint and feed regression suites, audit evidence, or vendor sign-off in regulated domains (SOC 2, HIPAA). BA owns the requirement; separate QA teams write test cases from AC. AC is versioned with the story; changes after sprint planning = new story. Without BA facilitation, AC becomes theatre—copy-pasted from prior stories, unread, and forgotten.</p>
      <p>Three-amigos refinement session: BA facilitates conversation with dev + QA to agree on done before sprint planning. BDD scenarios written by BA but executed by QA must stay in sync; untested scenarios rot and contradict implementation within 2-3 sprints. Cross-team AC for events/async flows often miss the "what if the message never arrives?" branch — failure is silent until production. Non-functional AC ("must be performant") with no measurement gate is worse than no AC. AC inflation: PO + BA add criteria after sprint planning, devs do not re-estimate, QA finds 6 new scenarios in test design. Treat AC as versioned with the story. API/integration stories require machine-checkable AC: developer A's "done" is consumer team B's "started". Spike/research stories should use Definition of Ready exit-criteria checklists, not AC—the outcome is a recommendation, not behavior.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow-for-ac">
      <p>The BA agent drafts AC from elicited requirements in Given-When-Then format. A reviewer agent checks AC against INVEST + testability heuristics before the story is marked Ready. A QA agent converts each criterion into executable test cases (Gherkin/pytest stubs). Traceability matrix auto-updates per story. Pipeline: requirement → BA agent drafts AC → reviewer agent lints → human PO approves → QA agent generates test stubs → traceability matrix updated. Recommended subagents: faion-sdd-executor enforces "AC verified" as quality gate before marking task done; feature-executor sequences tasks in story, validates each AC scenario passes before moving on; brainstorm surfaces missing scenarios (negative paths, boundary conditions, security cases) before freezing AC; custom BA-style subagent (sonnet) drafts AC from user story, cites requirement source; custom QA-style subagent (sonnet) translates each AC to pytest/Playwright/Gherkin skeletons.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="requirement-to-test-case-hierarchy">
      <example type="good" title="Requirement-AC-Test Case Hierarchy">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
REQ-045: Password Reset
  AC-1 (BDD): Successful reset via email link
    TC-1a: Valid reset link navigates to password entry form
    TC-1b: Valid new password updates credential and logs user in
  AC-2 (BDD): Expired reset link
    TC-2a: Expired link shows "Link expired" error
    TC-2b: User can request a new reset link after expiry
  AC-3 (checklist): Password rules
    TC-3a: Password under 8 characters is rejected
    TC-3b: Password without uppercase letter is rejected
    TC-3c: Password matching previous 3 passwords is rejected
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ac-bdd.md" purpose="BDD template: scenarios with Given/And/When/Then, non-functional criteria, out-of-scope section"/>
      <template path="templates/ac-checklist.md" purpose="Rule-based template: functional, validation, error handling, performance, and security criteria as checkboxes"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="user-story-mapping"/>
      <ref slug="agile-ba-frameworks"/>
      <link href="https://cucumber.io"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
