<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Brand Positioning Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Brand Positioning` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="define-customer-narrower-than-comfortable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Target customer description MUST narrow to (a) buying authority + (b) trigger event + (c) firmographic OR demographic profile. &apos;Marketers&apos; is forbidden; &apos;B2B SaaS heads of growth at companies in series-A with churn pain&apos; is acceptable.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford — Obviously Awesome 2019">Broad customer descriptions = broad messaging = no resonance. Narrower-than-comfortable forces real choices and produces messaging that converts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="map-alternatives-not-competitors" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>MUST map the buyer&apos;s actual alternatives (including &apos;do nothing&apos;, spreadsheets, internal tools). Not just direct competitor list.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford positioning framework; Bob Moesta JTBD">Buyers compare to alternatives, not just competitors. &apos;Do nothing&apos; is the largest competitor for most products; missing it means missing the actual buying decision.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="only-we-differentiator-single" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Positioning MUST name ONE &apos;only we&apos; differentiator (one capability buyer values that ONLY this product delivers). Multi-differentiator positioning is unfocused.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford; Geoffrey Moore Crossing the Chasm">Single &apos;only we&apos; is the wedge into buyer attention. Multiple = none stands out. Forces team to pick + invest in the one wedge.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="category-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Positioning MUST explicitly name the category (existing or new). &apos;A new way to X&apos; without category label is a brand failure.</statement>
      <rationale source="Geoffrey Moore category-design literature; Play Bigger">Category is the box buyer puts you in. Without naming, buyer slots you into the wrong box (likely a worse one). Name = control of the slot.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="validate-with-customer-interviews" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Positioning statement MUST be validated through &gt;= 10 customer interviews before public launch. Pure-internal positioning is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford 10-interview rule; B2B research handbook">Internal positioning reads great in slides + flops with buyers. 10 structured interviews surface where words don&apos;t land + adjust.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
