<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-positioning-framework" title="Brand Positioning Six-Step Framework">
  <summary>Step-by-step process for defining a specific, defensible market position from customer research to validated positioning statement.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Your Target Customer">
    <rule>
      <statement>Be ruthlessly specific about the target customer: name role, company type and stage, goal, and obstacle. "Businesses" or "developers" is not a target customer.</statement>
      <rationale>Positioning that resonates with everyone resonates with no one. A specific target customer description disqualifies wrong-fit prospects by design, which is a feature not a bug — it raises conversion among fit buyers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Target customer: "Businesses who want to grow their revenue." No role, no company type, no situation, no obstacle — every B2B product could claim this.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Target customer: "Marketing manager at a Series A SaaS startup who is trying to increase trial-to-paid conversion but struggles with limited engineering resources." Role + company type + goal + obstacle.</note>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/positioning-canvas.md">Positioning canvas template including target customer section</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Map Competitive Alternatives">
    <rule>
      <statement>List at least 3 competitive alternatives including: direct competitors, indirect competitors, the status quo (doing nothing), and substitutes (DIY, hire someone). Frame positioning against this list explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale>Customers always frame their decision against alternatives. Owning the framing prevents competitors from defining it. Without alternatives, positioning cannot be differentiated — "X is the Y" has no meaning without "unlike Z".</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Find Your Only">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify the one thing only your product can claim: a unique feature, approach, focus, expertise level, experience quality, proven result metric, or ecosystem integration. Pick one; more than one dilutes the claim.</statement>
      <rationale>Multi-pillar positioning is forgettable. Single-pillar positioning compounds over 12+ months into recognition. Competitors can copy features; they cannot easily copy a proven result tied to a specific methodology or a deep ecosystem integration.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Category Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose one of four category strategies: existing category (easiest to understand), sub-category (differentiate in crowded market), new category (create a space), or versus (challenger positioning). Only create a new category if you can fund market education for 2+ years.</statement>
      <rationale>Category creation looks attractive but creates an extra job: educating the market about a problem space before selling the solution. Most early-stage products should use sub-category framing to inherit existing search demand while carving a distinct niche.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Craft the Positioning Statement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write the internal positioning statement in this form: "For [target customer] who [situation/need], [Product] is the [category] that [key benefit], unlike [alternatives] we [unique differentiator]."</statement>
      <rationale>This structure forces explicit answers to all five positioning questions simultaneously and surfaces gaps (vague differentiator, undefined category) that prose descriptions hide.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Internal statement: "For solo SaaS founders who want to ship faster without a team, Faion Network is the AI development framework that provides proven methodologies and AI agents, unlike courses or just tools, we combine education with working software." External one-liner: "Faion Network helps solo founders ship products 10x faster with AI agents and proven methodologies."</note>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/messaging-hierarchy.md">Messaging hierarchy template for external communication</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Validate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Test positioning by asking customers to describe you to a peer. If they invent their own version, the positioning is not sticking. Test with 5+ customers before treating it as stable.</statement>
      <rationale>Internal positioning that sounds sharp often dissolves in the field. Customer language is the ground truth for whether positioning actually transferred.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
