<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples-and-antipatterns" title="Brand Positioning Examples and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Before/after positioning examples for developer tools and SaaS analytics, common positioning mistakes, and AI-agent gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Before/After Examples">
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Developer tool weak positioning: "A modern code editor for developers." No target customer, no differentiator, no alternative framing — every editor in the market could claim this.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Developer tool strong positioning: "For developers who hate context switching, Cursor is the AI-first code editor that understands your entire codebase, unlike VS Code or Copilot alone, we make AI your pair programmer, not just autocomplete." Specific trigger (context switching), specific alternative (VS Code + Copilot), specific differentiator (full-codebase understanding vs. token-level autocomplete).</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>SaaS analytics weak positioning: "Analytics for your business." No audience, no competitive frame, no differentiator.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS analytics strong positioning: "For bootstrapped founders who need insights without data science, Plausible is the privacy-friendly analytics that shows what matters in under 60 seconds, unlike Google Analytics, we're simple, fast, and GDPR-compliant out of the box." Audience (bootstrapped founders), trigger (no data science), differentiator (speed + privacy + compliance).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Positioning Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Target audience too broad ("businesses", "developers" without qualifiers).</description>
      <reason>Message resonates with no one; sales conversions remain low despite high traffic because wrong-fit buyers are not disqualified.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Feature-based positioning ("we have X feature").</description>
      <reason>Features are easily copied within one product cycle. Position on value, approach, or outcome — things that take more than 6 months to replicate.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Claiming too many differentiators at once.</description>
      <reason>Multi-pillar positioning is forgettable. Customers compress to one thing in their memory; let them compress to the thing you want them to remember.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Inside-out thinking: leading with features instead of customer problems.</description>
      <reason>Customers care about their goals and obstacles, not the product's architecture. Positioning must start from customer situation language.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Changing positioning within 12 months without a significant product or market reason.</description>
      <reason>Brand recognition requires repetition. Frequent pivots prevent any single positioning from accumulating recognition in the market.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLMs default to category-defining puffery: "the leading platform", "the most powerful solution".</description>
      <reason>Superlatives are unverifiable and unconvincing. Force the agent to replace every superlative with a concrete proof point tied to a named metric or customer.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents conflate features with differentiators when generating positioning.</description>
      <reason>Run a follow-up pass: "Can a competitor ship this in 6 months? If yes, it is a feature, not positioning." Differentiators must have structural defensibility.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Positioning generated without verbatim customer-language input reads as bland and inside-out.</description>
      <reason>Block synthesis until customer interview quotes are in context. Agents hallucinate target-customer pain when research inputs are absent.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
