<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="growth-brand-positioning Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for growth-brand-positioning as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Target audience too broad ("businesses", "developers" without qualifiers).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Message resonates with no one; sales conversions remain low despite high traffic because wrong-fit buyers are not disqualified.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Feature-based positioning ("we have X feature").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Features are easily copied within one product cycle. Position on value, approach, or outcome — things that take more than 6 months to replicate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Claiming too many differentiators at once.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multi-pillar positioning is forgettable. Customers compress to one thing in their memory; let them compress to the thing you want them to remember.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Inside-out thinking: leading with features instead of customer problems.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Customers care about their goals and obstacles, not the product's architecture. Positioning must start from customer situation language.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Changing positioning within 12 months without a significant product or market reason.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Brand recognition requires repetition. Frequent pivots prevent any single positioning from accumulating recognition in the market.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs default to category-defining puffery: "the leading platform", "the most powerful solution".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Superlatives are unverifiable and unconvincing. Force the agent to replace every superlative with a concrete proof point tied to a named metric or customer.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents conflate features with differentiators when generating positioning.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run a follow-up pass: "Can a competitor ship this in 6 months? If yes, it is a feature, not positioning." Differentiators must have structural defensibility.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Positioning generated without verbatim customer-language input reads as bland and inside-out.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Block synthesis until customer interview quotes are in context. Agents hallucinate target-customer pain when research inputs are absent.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Competitive analysis from web scraping captures stated positioning, not actual market perception.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Layer in review-site sentiment. Auto-generated category names are often unsearchable nonsense ("Revenue Intelligence Cloud Platform"); validate against Google search volume and analyst categories. Messaging hierarchies will drift if regenerated each cycle — maintain the hierarchy in version control and amend, don't recreate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents over-cite Dunford / Crossing the Chasm / Ries-Trout without distinguishing when each applies.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Crossing the Chasm is for early-market enterprise tech, not consumer SaaS. Translation/localization: positioning that works in English often fails when literally translated — re-do the canvas per language market.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
