<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Release Planning Process">
  <summary>Six-step structured process for bundling, scheduling, and executing product releases with cross-functional readiness verification.</summary>

  <section title="Release Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every release as Major, Minor, Patch, or Hotfix before planning starts; the type determines ceremony level, communication scope, and rollback complexity.</statement>
      <rationale>Type-based ceremony prevents over-engineering patch releases and under-preparing major ones. Hotfixes skip the normal process entirely and use the incident-response runbook.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Major: quarterly, large features, breaking changes, high risk. Minor: monthly, new features, medium risk. Patch: weekly or as needed, bug fixes, low risk. Hotfix: immediate, critical fixes, bypass release planning.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Release Goals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every release must have a primary outcome, a success metric, and optionally a theme before contents are selected.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a goal, "what should go in this release" has no forcing function. Features get added by availability rather than coherence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/release-plan.md">Full release plan template including goals and metrics sections</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Select Release Contents">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include only completed features meeting definition-of-done, related bug fixes, documentation updates, and configuration changes. Exclude half-finished features and unrelated fixes.</statement>
      <rationale>Scope creep at release time is the leading cause of delayed deploys. Feature freeze 24-48 hours before deploy prevents last-minute additions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply a feature freeze 24-48 hours before the planned deploy; no new items after freeze without explicit PM exception logged in the release exceptions log.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-freeze additions bypass the readiness gate and introduce untested surface area into the release.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Assess Release Readiness">
    <rule>
      <statement>Gate release on a per-function readiness matrix (eng, docs, support, marketing, legal, GTM). Green requires an evidence URL. Yellow and red require a named owner and blocker.</statement>
      <rationale>A "release plan complete" status that masks yellow/red cells ships unready features. Evidence URLs make green cells falsifiable, not aspirational.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/release_readiness_lint.py">Script that validates the readiness matrix: green rows must have evidence URLs, yellow/red must have named owners.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Plan Communication">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag every manifest item as customer_visible (Y/N) and breaking_change (Y/N). Items with customer_visible=N skip the comms loop entirely.</statement>
      <rationale>Applying the full comms plan to infra-only releases inflates PM workload without customer benefit. The boolean forces deliberate opt-in per item.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/release-notes.md">Customer-facing release notes template with required sections and anti-fluff rules.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-release-notes.txt">LLM prompt for drafting release notes with anti-fluff discipline.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Steps 5-6: Execute and Post-Release">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deploy Monday through Wednesday; never deploy on Fridays or before holidays without a documented exception in the release exceptions log.</statement>
      <rationale>Friday deploys reduce the on-call response window and increase incident blast radius. Documented exceptions create an audit trail for policy decay detection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Monitor metrics for 24 hours post-deploy. Hold a post-release retrospective; outputs update the next release's risk register with named owners.</statement>
      <rationale>Retrospective outputs tied to the next release's risk register turn one-off incidents into systemic improvements rather than forgotten post-mortems.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ship "one more thing" after feature freeze because it is "already built".</description>
      <reason>Late additions bypass the readiness matrix and are the most common source of post-release regressions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
