<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-antipatterns" title="Release Planning Antipatterns">
  <summary>Common failure modes in release planning with root causes and concrete mitigations for the PM role.</summary>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Train-the-monster: monthly release trains accumulate too much scope; one feature slips and the whole train slips.</description>
    <reason>Large trains make pull-or-postpone tradeoffs painful at the last minute. Counter: smaller trains with feature flags decouple readiness from ship date.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Communication-plan inflation: PM builds a matrix of every audience × every channel × every revision for every release.</description>
    <reason>Most rows produce zero customer behavior change. Cut to channels where engagement can be measured; delete the rest.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Rollback theater: every plan documents "Rollback Plan: revert PR" without ever drilling it in staging.</description>
    <reason>First real rollback fails and discredits the PM. Drill rollback in staging at least quarterly with the on-call who would execute it.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Release notes written at release start and edited manually through the cycle rather than generated from merged-PR labels at deploy time.</description>
    <reason>Manual notes drift from reality as PRs land and cuts happen. Stale notes ship inaccurate and surface as customer trust incidents.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>PM as deploy gate: PM treats the release plan as a veto over engineering deploy mechanics.</description>
    <reason>Engineering owns deploy mechanics. The PM owns external readiness. Conflating the two makes the PM the bottleneck and erodes cross-functional trust.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Hidden dependencies: a feature depends on a back-office migration or vendor contract renewal not tracked in the engineering tracker.</description>
    <reason>Dependencies not in the manifest look green but are actually red. Mandate a cross-team dependencies section with a named owner per row.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Breaking-change detection delegated entirely to LLM agents reading PR titles.</description>
    <reason>Agents miss implicit breaking changes (default value flipped, undocumented header now required). Breaking-change rows must be human-asserted.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Cycle time tracked only as "ship-date hit-rate" rather than median feature commit-to-live time.</description>
    <reason>Ship-date hit-rate hides the truth: teams ship smaller things slower over time. Cycle time trend is the leading indicator of release health.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
