<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="release-planning Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for release-planning as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Ship "one more thing" after feature freeze because it is "already built".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Late additions bypass the readiness matrix and are the most common source of post-release regressions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Generate release notes from a manifest captured at T-3 days and ship without regenerating at T-1.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Late-landing PRs and last-minute cuts make T-3 manifests stale. Always regenerate from the source of truth (merged-PR labels) at deploy time.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Train-the-monster: monthly release trains accumulate too much scope; one feature slips and the whole train slips.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Large trains make pull-or-postpone tradeoffs painful at the last minute. Counter: smaller trains with feature flags decouple readiness from ship date.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Communication-plan inflation: PM builds a matrix of every audience × every channel × every revision for every release.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Most rows produce zero customer behavior change. Cut to channels where engagement can be measured; delete the rest.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Rollback theater: every plan documents "Rollback Plan: revert PR" without ever drilling it in staging.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>First real rollback fails and discredits the PM. Drill rollback in staging at least quarterly with the on-call who would execute it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Release notes written at release start and edited manually through the cycle rather than generated from merged-PR labels at deploy time.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Manual notes drift from reality as PRs land and cuts happen. Stale notes ship inaccurate and surface as customer trust incidents.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>PM as deploy gate: PM treats the release plan as a veto over engineering deploy mechanics.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Engineering owns deploy mechanics. The PM owns external readiness. Conflating the two makes the PM the bottleneck and erodes cross-functional trust.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Hidden dependencies: a feature depends on a back-office migration or vendor contract renewal not tracked in the engineering tracker.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Dependencies not in the manifest look green but are actually red. Mandate a cross-team dependencies section with a named owner per row.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Breaking-change detection delegated entirely to LLM agents reading PR titles.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents miss implicit breaking changes (default value flipped, undocumented header now required). Breaking-change rows must be human-asserted.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Cycle time tracked only as "ship-date hit-rate" rather than median feature commit-to-live time.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Ship-date hit-rate hides the truth: teams ship smaller things slower over time. Cycle time trend is the leading indicator of release health.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Hallucinated PR contents — the agent invents a feature in the notes that does not exist in any merged PR.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force every notes bullet to cite a merge SHA in an HTML comment; lint that the SHA exists in git log.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-publishing release notes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Never auto-publish. The agent emits a draft to a PR or doc; a human merges. One auto-publish of an inaccurate note destroys more trust than a year of well-edited drafts builds.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Sycophantic marketing voice — LLMs default to "thrilled" and "delighted".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add an explicit anti-fluff clause to the prompt and a post-generation lint that rejects drafts containing those tokens.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Breaking-change blindness — agents extracting notes from PR labels miss the implicit breaking change (a default value flipped, an undocumented header now required).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require breaking-change rows to be human-asserted, not LLM-derived from PR titles.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Migration-script hallucinations — agents generate confident ALTER TABLE examples that drift from the actual migration.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pull migration content from the migration files in the PR, not from the agent's interpretation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale manifest — an agent run at T-3 days that is not re-run at T-1 ships an obsolete manifest.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Make the manifest a CI artifact regenerated on every push to the release branch; consume the freshest only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Comms-channel blast radius — agents posting drafts to a customer-visible Slack channel by mistake (typo in channel ID).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Restrict the agent's channel allowlist; require an explicit --channel arg, not a default.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-18" severity="medium">
      <description>Long-context manifest dumps — feeding the entire 200-row manifest into every prompt wastes tokens and dilutes attention.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Filter to customer_visible=Y for notes; filter to breaking_change=Y for migration guides. One filter per artifact.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-19" severity="medium">
      <description>Prompt injection via PR descriptions — a hostile or sloppy contributor pastes content into a PR description that the agent ingests verbatim into release notes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Sanitize ingested text; never let agent-ingested PR text become customer-facing without human review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-20" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy bleed in retros — agents pulling support-ticket data into the post-release retro can inadvertently embed customer PII into a doc that goes wider than expected.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run password-scrubber-agent on every retro; redact ticket bodies, keep only counts and categories.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-21" severity="medium">
      <description>Versioning drift — agent picks v1.2.3 from a tag that was never pushed; or picks v1.2.4 while a hotfix already claimed v1.2.4.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always read tags from the upstream remote, never from local-only state; lint that the proposed version &gt; all existing remote tags.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-22" severity="medium">
      <description>Cohort-flag mismatch — a release plan item names feature flag new-checkout but the deployed flag is checkout-v2.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Have the agent diff the manifest's flag-names column against the live flag-platform API; mismatch = hard fail.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-23" severity="medium">
      <description>Calendar-bound assumptions — "ship Tuesday" baked into prompts ages poorly across timezones, holidays, and frozen weeks.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Encode the deploy window as a date range from a calendar source, not a string in the prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
