<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="accessibility-first-design">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>Embed accessibility at design stage: contrast ratios, semantic structure, touch targets, motion controls, focus management. 70-80% of defects are preventable at design time.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
      <tag>a11y</tag>
      <tag>design</tag>
      <tag>wcag</tag>
      <tag>inclusive-design</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Accessibility-First Design</title>
    <summary>Methodology for embedding accessibility requirements at the design stage — color contrast ratios, semantic structure, touch target sizing, motion controls, and focus management — before a single line of code is written. The core rule: 70-80% of accessibility defects are preventable at design time; retrofitting costs far more than getting it right first.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Accessibility defects found in development cost 10-100x more to fix than those caught in design. Designing with WCAG AA contrast ratios, semantic heading hierarchies, visible focus states, and 44×44px touch targets removes entire categories of defects. It also expands the addressable user base and satisfies legal compliance requirements in the EU, US (ADA), and UK.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Starting a new UI design (web, mobile, or desktop)</item>
        <item>Adding a new component or page to an existing design system</item>
        <item>Conducting a design review before dev handoff</item>
        <item>Evaluating a Figma/Sketch file for accessibility gaps</item>
        <item>Writing design spec annotations for developers</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Post-production audits where design files no longer exist — use code-level audit tools (axe, Lighthouse) instead</item>
        <item>Back-end or API work with no visual output</item>
        <item>Content writing (separate content accessibility concerns apply)</item>
        <item>Late-stage retrofit of an existing product — use a11y-testing to find issues, then fix systematically</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="color-and-contrast">
      <p>Color and contrast are the foundation of visual accessibility. These rules ensure text and UI components are readable for low-vision users and in various lighting conditions.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Body text must meet a 4.5:1 contrast ratio against its background (WCAG AA). Large text (18pt+ or 14pt bold) requires 3:1. UI components and focus indicators require 3:1.</statement>
        <rationale>Contrast ratios below these thresholds make text unreadable for low-vision users and in high-ambient-light environments.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never use color as the sole indicator of meaning (e.g., red = error). Always pair color with a text label, icon, or pattern.</statement>
        <rationale>Approximately 8% of males have color vision deficiency; color-only signals are invisible to them.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Test designs with a color blindness simulator (e.g., Stark plugin) for deuteranopia, protanopia, and achromatopsia before developer handoff.</statement>
        <rationale>Simulation catches color-only patterns that pass contrast ratio checks but still fail color-blind users.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="touch-targets-and-spacing">
      <p>Touch targets and spacing directly impact usability for users with motor impairments. These precise rules prevent mis-taps and interaction failures.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Touch targets must be at minimum 24×24px (WCAG 2.2 AA). Use 44×44px as the production target; 48×48dp for Material Design contexts.</statement>
        <rationale>Targets below 24px are consistently missed by users with motor impairments and elderly users with reduced dexterity.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Maintain at least 8px spacing between adjacent interactive elements to prevent mis-taps.</statement>
        <rationale>Dense interactive element layouts produce high error rates for users with tremors or limited fine motor control.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="focus-and-keyboard-navigation">
      <p>Keyboard navigation and focus management are critical for users who cannot use a mouse. These rules ensure full keyboard accessibility.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Design visible focus indicators for every interactive element with a minimum 3:1 contrast ratio against adjacent colors. Never remove the default browser focus ring without a replacement.</statement>
        <rationale>Keyboard-only users and switch control users navigate entirely via focus indicators; invisible focus makes the interface unusable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Plan and annotate the keyboard focus order in design specs. Logical tab order must follow reading order; modal dialogs must trap focus while open and return focus to the trigger on close.</statement>
        <rationale>An unspecified focus order results in developer-guessed tab sequences that are often illogical or inaccessible.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="motion-and-time-limits">
      <p>Motion and time limits have serious implications for certain user populations. These rules protect vestibular and photosensitive users.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>All animations must be pausable and must respect the prefers-reduced-motion media query. No auto-playing video with sound. No flashing content above 3 flashes per second.</statement>
        <rationale>Motion triggers vestibular disorders in some users; flashing above 3 Hz can induce photosensitive seizures.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Remove time limits from interactive flows, or make them adjustable and extendable with at least 20 seconds warning.</statement>
        <rationale>Fixed time limits exclude slow readers, users with cognitive disabilities, and screen reader users who process content sequentially.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="semantic-structure">
      <p>Semantic structure is how assistive technologies understand content hierarchy and relationships. These rules ensure screen readers and other AT can navigate effectively.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Specify heading levels (H1 → H2 → H3) in design annotations. Never skip a heading level. Every page must have exactly one H1.</statement>
        <rationale>Screen reader users navigate by heading; a broken hierarchy makes content structure incomprehensible.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>All form inputs must have visible labels connected via for/id. Placeholder text is not a label substitute — it disappears on input and has insufficient contrast.</statement>
        <rationale>Placeholder-only labels fail blind users who cannot see the placeholder and sighted users once they start typing.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Include in design handoff: heading levels, image alt text, link text (no "click here"), focus order, ARIA labels for custom components, error message copy, loading state announcements.</statement>
        <rationale>Developers cannot infer accessibility semantics from visual designs; explicit annotation is required for correct implementation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="semantic-html-vs-div-soup">
      <p>Semantic HTML provides free accessibility structure that cannot be replicated with divs and CSS alone.</p>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="html"><![CDATA[
<nav aria-label="Main navigation">
  <ul>
    <li><a href="/">Home</a></li>
    <li><a href="/about">About</a></li>
  </ul>
</nav>
<main>
  <article>
    <h1>Main Title</h1>
    <section>
      <h2>Section Title</h2>
      <p>Content here...</p>
    </section>
  </article>
</main>
<aside aria-label="Related content">
  <h2>Related Articles</h2>
</aside>
        ]]></code>
        <note>Native landmark elements (nav, main, aside, footer) give screen readers free navigation without extra ARIA.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using only div and span with CSS classes for all layout and interactive elements.</description>
        <reason>Screen readers receive no semantic information; keyboard navigation and assistive technology integrations break entirely.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="forms">
      <p>Form accessibility is critical. These patterns ensure all users can identify, understand, and complete form interactions.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every input must have a visible label connected via for/id. Use aria-describedby for helper text. Mark required fields with both an asterisk and aria-required. Group related inputs with fieldset + legend.</statement>
        <rationale>Screen readers announce labels on focus; without a programmatic label the field is announced only by type ("edit blank"), giving no context.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Error messages must use aria-invalid="true" on the input and role="alert" on the error text so screen readers announce errors without requiring the user to navigate to them.</statement>
        <rationale>Sighted users see inline errors visually; blind users only discover errors if they are programmatically announced.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="html"><![CDATA[
<label for="email">Email address <span aria-hidden="true">*</span></label>
<input id="email" type="email" aria-required="true"
       aria-describedby="email-hint email-error" aria-invalid="true">
<p id="email-hint">We'll only use this to send your receipt.</p>
<p id="email-error" role="alert">Enter a valid email address.</p>
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="modal-dialogs">
      <p>Modal dialogs require special focus and keyboard handling to remain accessible.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>When a modal opens: move focus to the first interactive element inside it, trap Tab/Shift+Tab within it, close on Escape key, and return focus to the trigger element on close.</statement>
        <rationale>Without focus trapping, keyboard users tab out of the modal into an obscured background; without Escape support they cannot exit without a mouse.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Mark background content with aria-hidden="true" when a modal is open so screen readers do not read background content.</statement>
        <rationale>Without aria-hidden, screen reader users can navigate the background page while the modal is open, causing confusion.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="buttons-vs-links">
      <p>Buttons and links are semantically different and must be used correctly for assistive technology compatibility.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use button for actions that do not change the URL (submit, toggle, open modal, delete). Use anchor (a) for navigation to a new page or section. Never style one as the other without role correction.</statement>
        <rationale>Screen readers and voice control software identify interactive elements by role; a div styled as a button is not keyboard-reachable and not announced as a button.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="skip-links">
      <p>Skip links allow keyboard users to bypass repetitive navigation content.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Place a "Skip to main content" link as the first focusable element on every page. It may be visually hidden until focused.</statement>
        <rationale>Keyboard users and screen reader users must Tab through all navigation on every page load without a skip link — a severe usability barrier on navigation-heavy pages.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="progressive-enhancement">
      <p>Progressive enhancement ensures core functionality remains accessible even when JavaScript is unavailable or fails.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Build in layers: (1) semantic HTML providing core functionality, (2) CSS for visual presentation, (3) JavaScript for enhanced interactions. Core functionality must work without JavaScript.</statement>
        <rationale>JS-only interfaces break for users on low-bandwidth connections, corporate environments that block JS, and assistive technologies that execute JS inconsistently.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="mobile-checklist">
      <p>Mobile accessibility extends desktop principles with touch-specific considerations.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Touch targets at minimum 44x44px on all interactive elements</item>
        <item>No user-scalable=no in viewport meta — pinch zoom must be enabled</item>
        <item>Text resizes to 200% without horizontal scroll (WCAG 1.4.4)</item>
        <item>Forms compatible with platform autofill (correct input type and autocomplete attributes)</item>
        <item>Both portrait and landscape orientation supported</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agents help most at handoff: convert design specs to a11y annotations (heading levels, ARIA labels, focus order, alt text drafts), check tokens (contrast, sizing) against WCAG, generate semantic HTML scaffolds from a wireframe description, audit error/empty/loading states. Agents are weak at: judging visual hierarchy, evaluating motion comfort, weighing brand-vs-a11y tradeoffs. Pipeline: design tokens → contrast/size linter → component scaffold (semantic HTML) → axe regression in Storybook.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — gate component "done" on a11y checklist conformance + Storybook axe pass.</item>
        <item>Token-audit subagent — given color tokens, output the full pairwise WCAG contrast matrix and flag failing pairs by usage.</item>
        <item>Component-scaffold subagent — given a Figma component description, produce semantic HTML + minimal ARIA skeleton.</item>
        <item>Annotation-writer subagent — convert Figma layer names + comments into A11y Annotation Kit format for dev handoff.</item>
        <item>See also: a11y-testing, wcag-22-compliance, cognitive-inclusion-design.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <p>These prompt patterns guide agents in accessibility tasks:</p>
      <example type="good" title="Contrast matrix audit">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Audit this design-system color token JSON. For each FG/BG pairing actually
used in components, compute the WCAG ratio and flag:
  - <4.5 for body text → FAIL.
  - <3.0 for non-text UI / focus → FAIL.
  - <7.0 if AAA target → WARN.
Return a markdown table sorted by ratio asc.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Semantic HTML scaffold">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Convert this wireframe description to semantic HTML scaffold:
- Choose correct landmark elements (header/nav/main/aside/footer).
- Heading hierarchy.
- Buttons vs. links per behavior.
- Form labels with for/id.
- Required ARIA only (no overuse).
Return HTML + a list of ARIA labels for the dev to localize.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Be aware of these common pitfalls when using agents for accessibility work:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents over-add ARIA roles (e.g., "role=button" on actual button elements).</description>
        <reason>Enforce "no ARIA when native exists" rule in prompts.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM-generated alt text invents content for unfamiliar imagery.</description>
        <reason>Supply caption/context or require human approval for non-decorative images.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Heading-hierarchy guesses miss visual context (an H1-styled subtitle is not an H1).</description>
        <reason>Require designer-confirmed heading structure as input.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent skip-link suggestions can collide with framework routers (anchor + SPA route).</description>
        <reason>Ensure preventDefault + focus management.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Color suggestions to "fix contrast" can break brand palette.</description>
        <reason>Agents should propose tonal scale extensions, not arbitrary hex changes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-applied prefers-reduced-motion can hide essential CSS-driven loaders.</description>
        <reason>Provide static fallback, not just "remove animation".</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents tend to satisfy axe but miss focus visibility on dark themes.</description>
        <reason>Require visual regression with Chromatic or Percy + a11y addon.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Use ARIA labels everywhere" is not the same as accessibility.</description>
        <reason>Redundant labels confuse screen readers (announces twice). Agent must check pairing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Bake contrast checks into the design-system token build pipeline; fail CI when a token pair drops below threshold for its declared use.</item>
        <item>Write a11y acceptance criteria into every component spec (focus states, keyboard, ARIA, touch target).</item>
        <item>Use semantic HTML first; reach for ARIA only when no native equivalent exists. Rule: "no ARIA is better than bad ARIA".</item>
        <item>Define focus order in design (numbered overlay) before dev handoff.</item>
        <item>Annotate every image at design time — alt text either inline or "decorative" tag.</item>
        <item>Touch targets: 24×24 px is WCAG 2.2 minimum; 44×44 px is platform recommendation. Use 44 for all primary actions.</item>
        <item>Run eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y + Storybook a11y addon as merge-blocking CI.</item>
        <item>Pair with cognitive-inclusion-design when designing forms, errors, and learning content.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>pa11y / pa11y-ci — Static page scanning during dev. Install: npm i -g pa11y</item>
        <item>@axe-core/cli — Headless axe. Install: npm i -g @axe-core/cli</item>
        <item>storybook-addon-a11y — a11y panel in Storybook. https://storybook.js.org/addons/@storybook/addon-a11y</item>
        <item>eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y — Lint JSX for a11y issues. Install: npm i -D eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y</item>
        <item>axe-playwright / cypress-axe / jest-axe — Component-level a11y assertions. Install: npm i -D</item>
        <item>Figma plugin: A11y Annotation Kit — Annotation handoff. https://www.figma.com/community/plugin/731310036968334777</item>
        <item>Stark (Figma/Sketch/XD) — Contrast, color blindness, focus. https://www.getstark.co</item>
        <item>tonik / polaris-tokens style-dictionary — Token build with contrast checks. https://amzn.github.io/style-dictionary/</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <p>Various services and apps support accessibility work at different stages:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Stark (SaaS / plugin) — Best design-stage tooling; team plans for handoff.</item>
        <item>Figma + a11y plugins (A11y Annotation Kit, Contrast, Able) — Manual plugin use during design crit.</item>
        <item>Chromatic + a11y addon (SaaS) — Visual regression + a11y per Storybook story. API/CI integration.</item>
        <item>Token Studio (Figma) (SaaS / plugin) — Manage tokens with contrast metadata.</item>
        <item>Specify / zeroheight (SaaS) — Design-system docs with a11y notes per component. API integration.</item>
        <item>Material Design / Apple HIG / Fluent — Platform-native baselines. Documentation reference.</item>
        <item>Microsoft Inclusive Design Toolkit — Persona spectrum exercises. Documentation reference.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="contrast-matrix-template">
      <p>Inline contrast-matrix generator from style-dictionary tokens. This Python script computes WCAG contrast ratios for all color pairings:</p>
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
#!/usr/bin/env python3
# contrast_matrix.py tokens.json
import json, sys
def lum(hex_):
    h = hex_.lstrip("#"); r,g,b = (int(h[i:i+2],16)/255 for i in (0,2,4))
    def f(c): return c/12.92 if c<=0.03928 else ((c+0.055)/1.055)**2.4
    return 0.2126*f(r)+0.7152*f(g)+0.0722*f(b)
def ratio(a,b):
    la,lb = sorted([lum(a),lum(b)])
    return (lb+0.05)/(la+0.05)
tokens = {k:v for k,v in json.load(open(sys.argv[1])).items() if v.startswith("#")}
print("| FG | BG | Ratio | AA-text | AA-UI |")
print("|----|----|-------|---------|-------|")
for f, fc in tokens.items():
    for b, bc in tokens.items():
        if f == b: continue
        r = ratio(fc, bc)
        if r >= 3:
            print(f"| {f} | {b} | {r:.2f} | {'OK' if r>=4.5 else 'FAIL'} | {'OK' if r>=3 else 'FAIL'} |")
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="when-to-use-additional">
      <p>Additional context for when this methodology applies specifically:</p>
      <list>
        <item>New product / new feature design — apply at wireframe + visual-design stage to avoid 70-80% of post-launch a11y debt.</item>
        <item>Design-system foundation work (colors, typography, focus states, spacing tokens).</item>
        <item>Component library being built — bake a11y into each primitive's API and stories.</item>
        <item>Brand refresh / theme rework — ensure new palette passes contrast at design time, not at QA.</item>
        <item>Onboarding new designers / dev to a project — use the checklist as standards baseline.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Design-time accessibility checks have important limitations:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Design-time checks (contrast, target size) catch only ~50-60% of issues; runtime issues (ARIA misuse, keyboard traps) need code-level audits.</item>
        <item>Designers using Figma/Sketch can't test screen-reader behavior — only previews. Real AT testing happens post-handoff.</item>
        <item>Touch-target rules conflict with information-density goals (data tables, pro tools); needs case-by-case judgment.</item>
        <item>"Inclusive design principles" are guidelines, not pass/fail; agents struggle to apply them without context.</item>
        <item>Progressive enhancement only works if the team commits to it; partial buy-in produces JS-only UIs that fail without scripts.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://webaim.org/intro/"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/fundamentals/accessibility-principles/"/>
      <link href="https://www.a11yproject.com/checklist/"/>
      <link href="https://m3.material.io/foundations/accessible-design/overview"/>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/accessibility"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG22/quickref/"/>
      <link href="https://inclusivedesignprinciples.org"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/using-aria/#rule1"/>
      <ref slug="a11y-testing"/>
      <ref slug="wcag-22-compliance"/>
      <ref slug="cognitive-inclusion-design"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
