<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="facebook-ads Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for facebook-ads. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All budget values are in cents: daily_budget of 10000 equals $100.00. Always verify the unit before setting budgets.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Setting budget in dollars instead of cents causes 100x overspend. This is the most common Meta API mistake.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always create campaigns with status PAUSED. Activate only after reviewing all ad sets and creatives are correctly configured.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A campaign set to ACTIVE immediately starts spending. PAUSED allows review without risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use LOWEST_COST_WITHOUT_CAP for initial campaigns without a known target CPA. Switch to COST_CAP or LOWEST_COST_WITH_MIN_ROAS only after establishing baseline performance.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cap-based strategies require accurate cost knowledge to set. Without baseline data, caps that are too low starve the algorithm of learning budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Match optimization_goal to billing_event: OFFSITE_CONVERSIONS uses IMPRESSIONS billing; LINK_CLICKS uses IMPRESSIONS billing. Mismatched pairs cause ad set rejection.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Meta validates goal/billing combinations server-side. Rejected ad sets fail silently unless you check the API error response.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Check video upload status before creating the creative. Creating a creative with a video in non-ready state returns a validation error.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Video processing is asynchronous and can take minutes. Polling is required; there is no webhook for upload completion in the basic API.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Name campaigns, ad sets, and ads with a consistent pattern that encodes objective, audience, and date so performance can be compared across periods without pulling metadata.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ad account naming chaos makes bulk optimization and historical comparison extremely slow.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
