<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-comms-matrix" title="Communications Matrix and Status Rules">
  <summary>Rules for building the who-what-when-how stakeholder matrix, deriving status colour from metrics, and enforcing a written decision log.</summary>

  <section title="Matrix Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each stakeholder, document: information need, delivery format, frequency, owner, and allowed channels. Store in comms/plan.yaml in the project repo — not a wiki — so diffs become the cadence-change history.</statement>
      <rationale>Wiki-stored plans are updated rarely and drift undetected; a repo file under CODEOWNERS forces a review when the plan changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Standard cadences: Sponsor — budget, risks, milestones, weekly, report, PM. Team — tasks, blockers, decisions, daily, standup, Scrum Master. Client — progress, demos, feedback, biweekly, meeting, PM. Steering Committee — strategic status, monthly, presentation, PM.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit recurring meetings to less than 10% of any role's calendar. Review every quarter; kill any meeting where more than 20% of attendees would not voluntarily opt in.</statement>
      <rationale>Meeting overload is the most common communication anti-pattern; measuring it forces the explicit audit that "it feels like too many meetings" does not.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Status Colour Thresholds">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Define quantitative thresholds for GREEN / YELLOW / RED in the comms plan before the project starts. Example: schedule slip under 5 days = GREEN, 5-14 days = YELLOW, over 14 days = RED. Status colour must derive from the threshold, never from PM judgment or narrative.</statement>
      <rationale>PM-determined status colour is subject to optimism bias; quantitative thresholds make status objective, auditable, and consistent across report cycles.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Decision Log Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Decisions never live in chat. Every decision made in a meeting or async thread must have a corresponding decisions/YYYY-MM-DD-slug.md entry committed to the project repo within 24 hours.</statement>
      <rationale>Chat history is not searchable enough to be a system of record; decisions lost in thread history get re-litigated, duplicated, or simply forgotten by the team who wasn't present.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Auto-Monitoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the weekly comms audit (comms_audit.py) on a cron schedule; failures open a PM task for overdue communications. Do not rely on manual discipline to maintain cadence.</statement>
      <rationale>A plan that is not monitored decays silently; automated detection ensures stakeholders are never silently excluded for multiple cycles.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/comms_audit.py">Weekly audit script listing overdue stakeholder communications</reference>
  </section>
</text>
