<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-channel-selection" title="Channel Selection, Timezone, and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Rules for matching communication need to channel, timezone-aware scheduling, confidentiality constraints, and common failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Channel-to-Need Mapping">
    <rule>
      <statement>Match channel to communication need: urgent issues → phone or call; complex discussions → meeting; status updates → email or report; quick questions → chat; reference information → wiki; formal decisions → email with written confirmation.</statement>
      <rationale>Using a single channel for all needs either creates noise (everything in Slack) or buries urgent items (everything in email). Explicit mapping reduces cognitive load for both sender and receiver.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Legal, HR, security, and salary topics are never on public Slack channels. Encode allowed channels per topic type in comms/plan.yaml.</statement>
      <rationale>Confidential data posted on a wrong channel creates compliance exposure that cannot be undone; explicit channel-to-topic mapping prevents accidental disclosure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Timezone Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Any global recurring meeting must either rotate its time across quarters or run two sessions. Document the rotation schedule. Encode acceptable hours per participant in the comms plan.</statement>
      <rationale>A fixed "Tue 10:00 UTC" permanently excludes APAC time zones; the plan must make the exclusion explicit or resolve it with a second session.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Auto-send to executives, regulators, or external customers is forbidden. Agents prepare drafts; a human reviews and sends. Encode auto_send: false per recipient in the plan.</statement>
      <rationale>A confabulated progress claim or tone mismatch in an auto-sent executive update creates reputational damage that is hard to recover from; the draft-and-review workflow is a non-negotiable gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Too many meetings — death by calendar.</description>
      <reason>Beyond 10% of calendar dedicated to recurring meetings, delivery capacity shrinks faster than coordination benefit grows. Audit frequency every quarter.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No agenda for a recurring meeting.</description>
      <reason>Meetings without agendas wander; participants come unprepared; decisions degrade to re-litigated debates. Require a committed agenda 24h before or auto-cancel the meeting.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Status report colour set by PM narrative rather than metrics.</description>
      <reason>Optimism bias systematically delays RED status until a crisis; quantitative thresholds set before the project starts remove the subjective layer.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Same communication format for every stakeholder.</description>
      <reason>A steering committee needs a 1-page decision brief; the dev team needs a ticket list; sending both groups the same status report wastes executive attention and under-informs engineers.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../lessons-learned/">Close-out report cadence pairs with this plan</link>
  </see-also>
</text>
