<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Product Explainability Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Product Explainability plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="kb-schema-markup-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The product KB MUST emit schema.org Product + SoftwareApplication markup with name, description, featureList, applicationCategory, and offers; missing fields fail validation.</statement>
      <rationale source="schema.org/SoftwareApplication v15">AI discovery surfaces (Perplexity, Claude, ChatGPT) parse schema markup to summarise products; missing markup makes the product invisible to the discovery layer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="capability-boundary-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every feature page MUST list explicit limits ('what this does NOT do') alongside capabilities; capability-only pages are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Perplexity hallucination audit 2026">Capability-only pages cause hallucinated answers in AI surfaces ('it does X' when X is the unsupported edge); explicit boundaries are the only structural prevention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-jargon-in-public-kb" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Public KB pages MUST score ≤ Flesch-Kincaid grade 11; jargon-heavy pages MUST be rewritten or moved behind login.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen Norman Group readability guidelines">AI summarisers degrade on jargon-heavy text; sub-grade-11 prose summarises predictably across surfaces.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="machine-readable-changelog" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every product MUST publish a machine-readable changelog (RSS + JSON Feed) listing feature changes, deprecations, and limit changes within 24h of release.</statement>
      <rationale source="JSON Feed v1.1 spec">Without machine-readable changelogs, AI surfaces serve stale capability claims; changelogs are the canonical update channel.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="owner-and-review-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every KB page MUST carry a frontmatter owner + review-cadence (quarterly default); pages past review-date with no owner MUST be unpublished.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — docs rot audit 2025">Unowned KB rots; the explicit owner + cadence pair is the only durable freshness gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
