<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-explainability Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-explainability as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>KB drift as default: marketing site, docs, pricing page, schema feed, and llms.txt diverge within weeks.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each surface is edited by a different team on a different cadence. Without a single-source pipeline, contradiction is the natural state, not the exception.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Schema theater: teams add Product JSON-LD but description, audience, and feature fields repeat the marketing tagline.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Retrieval systems get no new signal from paraphrased copy. The schema markup must carry information not already in the page text.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Capability-version skew: capability statements with no validFrom/validUntil dates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Deprecated features keep getting recommended by AI assistants because there is no signal in the KB that they no longer exist. Date-bounded capability status is the fix.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Generator agents producing adjective-heavy copy ("best-in-class", "leading", "revolutionary").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a "no adjectives, no superlatives" constraint in the system prompt and lint generated output. These tokens provide no retrieval signal and reduce trust.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Extractor agent fabricating capabilities to fill empty fields.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Refuse-on-unknown must be enforced via prompt and post-hoc validator that cross-checks capability names against the feature flag registry or source code. Invented capabilities create support and legal liability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Limit array lost across multi-step pipeline summarization passes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Preserve the limits[] array verbatim across every pipeline stage. Never re-summarize limits — they carry legal and trust-critical precision that compression loses.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Probe agents producing the same response across runs due to same prompt and cached model state.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Vary question phrasing, user role, and timing across probe runs. Stable scores are an artifact of caching, not real representation quality.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Hallucinated since_version: agents guess versions if not given a changelog.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hard requirement: extractor must read a real changelog or refuse. Version strings must be validated against actual release tags.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Schema bloat: generator agents produce maximalist JSON-LD with every optional field.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>AI retrieval prefers small, dense, accurate markup. Cap field count; lint with structured-data-testing-tool.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Confidentiality leak: capability statements reveal unlaunched features, internal infra (vendor names, region IDs, partner SKUs).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run a scrubber agent before any external publish — especially before pushing llms.txt or schema.org markup.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>No human checkpoint on deprecated flips: agent autonomously removes a capability from AI-mediated discovery.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Marking a capability deprecated removes it from AI discovery and impacts revenue. Always require a product-owner sign-off before status changes; never let the agent flip status autonomously.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-locale drift via auto-translation: translation agents helpfully translate "limit" in ways that lose legal precision.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Limits and disclaimers go through human review per locale; non-negotiable. Never auto-translate capability limits.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>llms.txt echo chamber: many sites copy each other's llms.txt; the agent will follow the herd.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a pre-publish diff against the top-3 competitors' llms.txt; if similarity &gt;0.7, regenerate. Avoid herd homogenization.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Probe-set staleness: canonical question sets calcify while the product evolves.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Refresh the question set whenever a new capability ships or a customer reports a wrong AI answer. Stale questions produce artificially flat accuracy.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
