<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="instagram-basics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>smm-manager</domain>
    <summary>Instagram strategy prioritizing Reels (80%) for discovery, Stories (15%) for engagement, Feed (5%). Organic reach declined; without Reels, accounts plateau.</summary>
    <category>social-media</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>instagram</tag>
      <tag>reels</tag>
      <tag>social-media</tag>
      <tag>content-strategy</tag>
      <tag>organic-growth</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Instagram Basics</title>

    <summary>Instagram strategy prioritizing Reels (80%) for discovery, Stories (15%) for engagement, Feed (5%). Without Reels, accounts plateau. Profile optimization, pillar discipline, and hashtag minimalism foundational.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Instagram has 2B+ monthly active users, and Reels deliver 2x the reach of photos by pushing to non-followers. Accounts that ignore Reels get roughly 1/4 the reach of Reels-led accounts. The first 1.5 seconds of a Reel determine algorithmic reach; 80% of viewers watch muted — on-screen text is mandatory. DM automation requires ManyChat approval; unofficial automation risks account suspension.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Setting up an Instagram presence (founder, brand, creator) and configuring profile, highlights, and content pillars.</item>
        <item>Reels-first content strategy where the team can shoot/edit but needs scripts, hooks, and carousel scripts.</item>
        <item>Auditing an underperforming Instagram account to identify whether decline is reach, engagement, or conversion.</item>
        <item>Drafting carousel scripts (10 slides) and Story sequences for product launches.</item>
        <item>Pairing with Meta Ads where organic posts feed retargeting audiences.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Audience is purely B2B enterprise — LinkedIn and email outperform; do not invest cycles here.</item>
        <item>Team cannot shoot or edit video; Instagram without Reels gets roughly 1/4 the reach of a Reels-led account.</item>
        <item>Brand requires text-heavy, long-form content (use blog + LinkedIn).</item>
        <item>Regulated industries where every visual claim needs compliance review incompatible with Instagram's posting velocity.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="profile-optimization">
      <rule>
        <statement>Structure the Instagram bio as: line 1 = what you do for whom; line 2 = credibility/proof; line 3 = CTA.</statement>
        <rationale>Visitors decide to follow in under 3 seconds. A three-line bio that answers "what is this account, why should I trust it, and what do I do next" converts profile visits to followers more reliably than a clever but ambiguous bio.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Username: searchable and memorable (e.g., @yourproduct or @founder.name).</item>
        <item>Display name: include a keyword (e.g., "Mike | SaaS Growth").</item>
        <item>Profile photo: face clearly visible, bright, consistent with other platforms.</item>
        <item>Highlights: About, Products/Services, Testimonials, FAQ, Free Resources.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="reels-first-format">
      <rule>
        <statement>Allocate 80% of content effort to Reels; write the hook separately and only ship Reels with hook score 4+/5.</statement>
        <rationale>Reels deliver 2x the reach of photos by pushing to non-followers. The first 1.5 seconds determine algorithmic reach — a weak hook wastes the production effort. Rating hooks explicitly forces quality discipline.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include on-screen text in Reels; never rely on voiceover-only scripts.</statement>
        <rationale>80% of Instagram viewers watch muted. Scripts that put all content in voiceover fail to communicate to the majority of viewers.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Optimal Reels length: 7-15 seconds for virality; 30-60 seconds for educational depth.</item>
        <item>Hook: first 1-2 seconds critical.</item>
        <item>Hashtags: 3-5 relevant (not 30).</item>
        <item>Caption: add context and CTA.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="stories-strategy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Post Stories daily; pair every Reel with a Story re-share within 24 hours.</statement>
        <rationale>Stories maintain relationship with existing followers while Reels reach new ones. Algorithm rewards accounts that use multiple formats consistently.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="hashtag-minimalism">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use 3-5 hashtags per post (mixed small/medium/large tiers). Never request 30 hashtags from an agent.</statement>
        <rationale>Meta now favors topic understanding over hashtag density. Over-indexing on hashtags underperforms and can look spammy. Agent prompts that request 30 hashtags produce stale, low-quality tag lists.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using TikTok-watermarked Reels on Instagram.</description>
        <reason>Instagram suppresses reach for Reels that contain the TikTok watermark. Cross-posted content must have the watermark stripped and ideally be re-edited for Instagram's format.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="caption-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Caption hook must appear in the first line (before "more"); sweet spot length 150-200 characters; always include CTA.</statement>
        <rationale>Instagram truncates captions after the first line in the feed view. A hook in the first line pulls viewers to expand. Captions over 2,200 characters are permitted but rarely read in full.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Enforce a max-words-per-slide constraint for carousel scripts; reject slide 1 with more than 10 words.</statement>
        <rationale>Carousel slides with 30+ words on slide 1 fail because viewers swipe before reading. Large, readable text on a simple visual stops the scroll.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="dm-automation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Only use approved ManyChat flows for DM automation. Never use unofficial APIs to auto-send DMs at scale.</statement>
        <rationale>Instagram restricts DM automation to approved partners (Messenger Platform). Unapproved bots get accounts flagged or suspended. Agents must never send DMs via unofficial APIs regardless of scale.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM-generated captions with heavy exclamation marks and emojis.</description>
        <reason>LLMs default to enthusiastic, emoji-heavy Instagram captions. This reads as inauthentic and degrades brand credibility. Explicitly prohibit exclamation marks and emojis (or set a strict per-post limit) in every prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent picks trending hashtags from training data.</description>
        <reason>Hashtag trends change weekly. Training-data hashtag suggestions are stale. Fetch current top hashtags via a research subagent or manual lookup before generating content.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>All Reel scripts follow listicle structure ("3 tips for X").</description>
        <reason>LLMs default to listicle format. Overuse of listicles reduces content variety and engagement. Force narrative or transformation arcs periodically to avoid audience fatigue.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent recommends "trending audio" without an external lookup.</description>
        <reason>The model cannot know current trending audio on Instagram — it has no real-time data. Require an external lookup before the agent recommends audio choices.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A Claude subagent is best at scripting Reels (hook + body + CTA in 30 seconds), drafting carousel scripts (slide-by-slide), and proposing weekly Story sequences. The agent should NOT auto-post Reels (visual QA matters) but CAN schedule via Buffer/Later if approved by the operator. Pair the agent with a research subagent that pulls trending audio and competitor recent winners daily.</p>
      <p>Best practices: Pillar discipline beats clever ideas — enforce the agent's prompt to label every draft with a pillar; reject pillar-less output. Reels' first 1.5 seconds decide reach. Force the agent to write the hook separately and rate it 1-5; only ship 4+. Always include on-screen text — 80% of viewers watch muted; agents that produce voiceover-only scripts fail. Hashtag minimalism: 3-5 mixed tiers, not 30. Agent prompts that ask for "30 hashtags" hurt performance. Save a "winners library" of past top posts and inject the top 5 into every ideation prompt as positive examples. Pair every Reel with a Story re-share within 24h; agent should produce both in the same content brief.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools for content operations: instagrapi (Python, read profile and insights — unofficial, breakage risk), instaloader (backup posts/stories/highlights for analysis), ffmpeg (trim, resize 9:16, strip watermarks), imagemagick (carousel slide generation from markdown).</p>
      <p>SaaS platforms: Instagram Graph API (official, Reels + posts publishing for Business/Creator accounts), Buffer (Reels + carousel + Stories scheduling via API), Later (visual planner; preview grid before posting), Metricool (analytics + scheduling, hashtag analyzer), Iconosquare (deeper analytics, competitor tracking), ManyChat (approved DM automation flows), Canva (programmatic carousel generation), Postiz (OSS scheduler with Instagram support), CapCut (Reels editing — manual; agents can output edit scripts).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="api-constraints">
      <p>Organic reach is structurally low (often 1-3% of followers for photos) and shrinking — without Reels, growth stalls. API limits posting flexibility: Reels can be scheduled via Graph API, but Stories with stickers (polls, quizzes) often cannot. Hashtag strategy has weakened; Meta now favors topic understanding, so over-indexing on hashtag tiers underperforms. DM automation must be approved (Messenger Platform); unapproved bots get the account flagged. Cross-posting Reels from TikTok with the watermark suppresses reach; agents must strip and remix.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/bio-template.txt" purpose="Three-line bio formula with credibility and CTA."/>
      <template path="templates/reel-script.txt" purpose="Hook + body + CTA Reels script template."/>
      <template path="templates/carousel-template.txt" purpose="10-slide carousel narrative structure."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-reels.txt" purpose="Prompt for generating 5 Reels scripts with pillar tags and hook scores."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/instagram-api"/>
      <link href="https://business.instagram.com/"/>
      <link href="https://blog.hootsuite.com/instagram-algorithm/"/>
      <link href="https://later.com/blog/instagram-tips/"/>
      <link href="https://buffer.com/resources/instagram-reels/"/>
      <link href="https://manychat.com/instagram"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
