<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-thomas-kilmann" title="Thomas-Kilmann five conflict modes">
  <summary>Five conflict modes on two axes (assertiveness and cooperativeness); mode selection matters more than message quality — using Competing when Collaborating is possible produces short-term compliance and long-term resentment.</summary>

  <section title="Mode selection rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select the conflict mode before drafting any message. The wrong mode undermines even a perfectly worded NVC script.</statement>
      <rationale>Mode sets the intent (I win / we both win / no one wins). A Collaborating script delivered in a Competing posture reads as manipulative.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Competing — use when">
      <list>
        <item>Emergency requiring immediate, decisive action</item>
        <item>Unpopular decision that is clearly correct and must be made</item>
        <item>Self-protection against someone exploiting cooperative behavior</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Competing — do not use when">
      <list>
        <item>Routine issues where relationship preservation matters</item>
        <item>You might be wrong — competing with a flawed position destroys credibility</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Collaborating — use when">
      <list>
        <item>The issue is important and both parties have valid interests</item>
        <item>Long-term relationship requires genuine buy-in, not compliance</item>
        <item>Time is available to explore solutions together</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Collaborating — do not use when">
      <list>
        <item>Trivial matters where the effort is disproportionate</item>
        <item>No trust exists between parties — collaboration requires a minimum of good faith</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Compromising — use when">
      <list>
        <item>Issue is moderately important, parties have equal power, and time is limited</item>
        <item>Temporary settlement needed while a better solution is developed</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Avoiding — use when">
      <list>
        <item>Trivial issue not worth the relationship cost</item>
        <item>Emotions are too high — a cooling-off period is needed before productive dialogue</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Avoiding — do not use when">
      <list>
        <item>Issue is important and will not resolve itself — avoidance becomes accumulation</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Accommodating — use when">
      <list>
        <item>You are factually wrong — accommodation is the honest response</item>
        <item>The issue matters more to them than to you; preserving goodwill is the priority</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Accommodating — do not use when">
      <list>
        <item>Core values or principles are at stake</item>
        <item>You have accommodated repeatedly in this relationship — the pattern itself becomes the problem</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>
</text>
