<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-nvc" title="Nonviolent Communication four-step formula">
  <summary>NVC structures a message as Observation (factual, no evaluation) + Feeling (emotion, not thought) + Need (universal, not strategy) + Request (specific, positive, doable).</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Observation vs evaluation">
    <rule>
      <statement>State observable, verifiable facts only. Remove evaluations, judgments, and interpretations. Reference a specific instance with date or measurable frequency, not a pattern ("always", "never").</statement>
      <rationale>Evaluations trigger defensiveness. An observable fact is harder to dispute and keeps the conversation on the behavior, not the person's character.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Evaluation: "You're always late" → Observation: "You arrived at 9:15 for the 9:00 meeting on Tuesday"</item>
      <item>Evaluation: "You don't care" → Observation: "I haven't received a response to my 3 emails sent Monday-Wednesday"</item>
      <item>Evaluation: "The code is messy" → Observation: "I found 5 functions over 100 lines in the PR"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Feeling vs thought">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name a genuine emotion word. Reject "I feel that..." or "I feel like..." — these are thoughts, not feelings. If the word after "feel" can be replaced with "think", it is a thought.</statement>
      <rationale>"I feel that you don't respect me" is an interpretation that invites rebuttal. "I feel frustrated" names an emotion that cannot be disputed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Thought: "I feel like you don't respect me" → Feeling: "I feel frustrated"</item>
      <item>Thought: "I feel that this is unfair" → Feeling: "I feel disappointed"</item>
      <item>Positive feeling words: glad, relieved, hopeful, excited, grateful, confident</item>
      <item>Negative feeling words: frustrated, disappointed, worried, overwhelmed, hurt, confused</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Need vs strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name a universal human need, not a specific strategy or demand. Needs are satisfied by many strategies; confusing need with strategy closes off solutions.</statement>
      <rationale>Universal needs (autonomy, predictability, respect, fairness) are understandable to anyone. Strategy demands ("I need you to answer faster") sound like orders and create resistance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Strategy: "I need you to answer faster" → Need: "I need responsiveness"</item>
      <item>Strategy: "I need a bigger team" → Need: "I need support"</item>
      <item>Strategy: "I need you to stop micromanaging" → Need: "I need autonomy"</item>
      <item>Universal needs: autonomy, competence, connection, safety, predictability, fairness, respect, recognition</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Request criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Make the request specific, positive (what you want, not what you don't want), and doable within the other person's power. Vague or negative requests cannot be acted on.</statement>
      <rationale>A request that cannot be executed produces agreement without behavioral change. Negative requests ("stop doing X") leave the behavior undefined.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Vague: "Be more careful" → Specific: "Would you review the checklist before submitting?"</item>
      <item>Negative: "Stop sending late-night messages" → Positive: "Would you batch non-urgent messages for the next morning?"</item>
      <item>Outside their power: "Fix the entire codebase" → Doable: "Would you pair with me for 30 min to debug this module?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Complete NVC examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Late delivery addressed with NVC</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
When the feature was delivered 3 days after the deadline (O),
I felt stressed (F)
because I need predictability to plan my work (N).
Would you be willing to flag delays 2 days in advance? (R)
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You never deliver on time. This is unacceptable.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/nvc-message.md">NVC message template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-nvc-rewrite.txt">Prompt: rewrite emotionally charged message in NVC format</reference>
</text>
