<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-process" title="Conflict resolution process and de-escalation">
  <summary>Five-step process (Prepare → Open → Listen → Explore → Agree) with de-escalation phrases for high-emotion moments and a mediation script for third-party facilitation.</summary>

  <section title="Five-step resolution process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow the five steps in sequence: Prepare → Open → Listen → Explore → Agree. Skipping Prepare produces reactive conversations without a clear goal. Skipping Listen after sharing your view prevents understanding the other party's perspective.</statement>
      <rationale>Each step builds the foundation for the next. Opening without preparation leads to goal drift. Exploring without listening produces solutions that ignore one party's real needs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>1. PREPARE — What is the issue? What is my goal? What is their likely perspective?</item>
      <item>2. OPEN — State purpose, establish psychological safety, share your perspective (NVC)</item>
      <item>3. LISTEN — Understand their view, acknowledge feelings, ask clarifying questions</item>
      <item>4. EXPLORE — Identify shared interests, generate options together, find common ground</item>
      <item>5. AGREE — Specific actions, clear accountability (WHO does WHAT by WHEN), follow-up date</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="De-escalation when emotions are high">
    <rule>
      <statement>When you observe signs of escalation (raised voice, tears, silence, crossed arms), pause content and restore safety before continuing. Say what you are NOT doing to clarify intent.</statement>
      <rationale>High-emotion states shut down the prefrontal cortex and make rational problem-solving impossible. Safety must be restored before content can land.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>"Let's take 5 minutes and come back" — pause</item>
      <item>"I can see this is important to you" — acknowledge</item>
      <item>"It sounds like you're feeling frustrated" — name the emotion</item>
      <item>"I'm not saying you're wrong. I'm saying this specific outcome concerns me." — contrasting</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <item>Avoid: "Calm down" → use: "I want to understand your perspective"</item>
      <item>Avoid: "You're wrong" → use: "I see it differently — help me understand"</item>
      <item>Avoid: "You always..." / "You never..." → use: specific instance with date</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Mediation script for third-party facilitation">
    <rule>
      <statement>As a mediator, establish ground rules at the start, give each party equal uninterrupted time, and keep exploration focused on shared interests rather than positions or blame.</statement>
      <rationale>Ground rules create a predictable, safe container. Equal speaking time prevents the dominant party from defining the narrative. Shared-interest focus opens options that position-based negotiation closes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
OPENING:
"We're here to find a solution that works for both of you.
I'm not here to judge who's right.
Ground rules: one person speaks at a time, no personal attacks, focus on future."

EXPLORATION:
[Person A]: "Share your perspective — what happened?"
[Person B]: "What did you hear? What is your view?"

FINDING COMMON GROUND:
"What do you both agree on?"
"What outcome do you both want?"

RESOLUTION:
"What would need to happen for this to be resolved?"
"What is each of you willing to do?"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
