<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-techniques" title="Four brainstorming techniques: Classic, Brainwriting, Round Robin, Reverse">
  <summary>Four structured techniques for generating ideas in groups; technique selection depends on group size, introvert ratio, available time, and whether the goal is to surface risks or generate solutions.</summary>

  <section title="Core rules (apply to all techniques)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce Osborn's 4 rules during the diverge phase: defer judgment, go for quantity, encourage wild ideas, build on others' ideas with "Yes, and..." instead of "No, but...".</statement>
      <rationale>Criticism during idea generation reduces output quantity by 28-40% (Osborn, 1953). The evaluation phase is separate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never mix generation and evaluation in the same pass. Two distinct phases — diverge then converge — produce better idea sets than one combined pass.</statement>
      <rationale>Premature convergence causes anchoring bias: the group stops generating after finding the first good idea instead of exploring the full space.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Classic Brainstorming (4-8 people, 45-60 min)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run in five steps: Define problem (5 min) → Warm-up exercise (5 min) → Generate ideas (15-20 min) → Cluster similar ideas (10 min) → Vote/prioritize (10 min).</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping the warm-up exercise reduces idea quantity. A 5-minute creative exercise (unrelated word associations, visual prompts) primes divergent thinking.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Brainwriting 6-3-5 (exactly 6 people, 30 min)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each of 6 people writes 3 ideas in 5 minutes, then passes their paper clockwise. Each subsequent round reads prior ideas and adds 3 more. After 6 rounds: 108 ideas from 6 people. Works in shared docs for remote teams.</statement>
      <rationale>Written format eliminates speaking order bias and interruption. Introverts and junior team members contribute at equal rate to senior or extroverted colleagues.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Round Robin (4-10 people)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Go around the group; each person shares exactly one idea per turn. "Pass" is permitted but the person must contribute on the next round. No commenting or interruption until the full round is complete.</statement>
      <rationale>Sequential turns prevent dominant voices from filling all available air time. The no-comment rule lets each idea stand on its own before group response.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Reverse Brainstorming (4-8 people)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Invert the problem: instead of "How do we improve X?", ask "How could we make X as bad as possible?". Brainstorm negative answers, then reverse each negative into a positive solution.</statement>
      <rationale>Groups are more willing to criticize than prescribe. Reverse framing accesses honest risk knowledge that polite groups suppress in forward brainstorming.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Problem: "How do we increase customer satisfaction?"
Reversed: "How do we make customers hate us?"

Negative ideas → Reversed solutions:
- Long hold times → Callback system
- Rude staff → Empathy training program
- Hidden fees → Transparent pricing page
- Complicated returns → One-click return form
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
