<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-facilitation" title="Facilitation rules, problem fixes, and convergence methods">
  <summary>Facilitator rules for before, during, and after a session; specific interventions for common failure modes (dominant talker, energy dip, off-topic drift); dot voting and impact/effort scoring for convergence.</summary>

  <section title="Before session">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define a specific, single-question objective before the session. "Discuss the product" is not an objective. "Generate 20+ ideas for reducing onboarding churn from 40% to below 25%" is.</statement>
      <rationale>A vague objective produces vague output. A specific question with a quantity target gives the group a clear success criterion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Invite 4-8 people with diverse backgrounds and roles. More than 10 makes facilitation unmanageable. Fewer than 4 lacks the cross-pollination that produces non-obvious ideas.</statement>
      <rationale>Diversity of perspective is the primary predictor of idea novelty in brainstorming research.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="During session — common problems and fixes">
    <list>
      <item>Dominant talker: switch to Brainwriting or Round Robin to enforce structured turns</item>
      <item>Criticism creeping in: "Hold that thought for the evaluation phase"</item>
      <item>Running out of ideas: apply a constraint ("what if budget were 10x?"), change perspective ("what would a user say?"), use SCAMPER</item>
      <item>Off-topic drift: "Parking lot" — capture the idea on a separate board for later</item>
      <item>Group too quiet: individual silent writing for 2 min before sharing</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Convergence — dot voting">
    <rule>
      <statement>Give each participant 3-5 dots. Participants vote on their favorite ideas from the clustered list. Top-voted ideas move forward for evaluation. No discussion during voting.</statement>
      <rationale>Dot voting externalizes preferences simultaneously, preventing the anchoring effect of verbal polling where the first opinion heard shapes all subsequent votes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Convergence — impact/effort scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each idea on Impact (weight 3x) and Feasibility (weight 2x). Avoid over-weighting cost and time (1x each) — cheap but low-impact ideas should not win over expensive but transformative ones.</statement>
      <rationale>Default human judgment over-weights effort and under-weights impact. Explicit weighting corrects this bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Quick Wins: high impact, low effort — implement first</item>
      <item>Major Projects: high impact, high effort — schedule and resource</item>
      <item>Fill-ins: low impact, low effort — optional backlog</item>
      <item>Time Sinks: low impact, high effort — reject</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Skipping the convergence step after ideation — leaving participants with a list but no prioritization or owner assignments.</description>
    <reason>Ideas without owners and priorities evaporate. The session feels productive but produces no action, which destroys trust in future brainstorming sessions.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <reference path="templates/session-plan.md">Session plan template with agenda and results capture</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-generate.txt">Prompt for bulk idea generation pass</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-cluster.txt">Prompt for clustering idea list into themes</reference>
</text>
