<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="consistency-standards">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #4: users should not wonder if different words or actions mean the same thing. Audit and enforce consistency across design systems.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>consistency</tag>
      <tag>design-systems</tag>
      <tag>usability-heuristics</tag>
      <tag>design-audit</tag>
      <tag>ui-standards</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Consistency and Standards</title>

    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #4: users should not wonder whether different words, situations, or actions mean the same thing. Follow platform and industry conventions. Apply to audit visual, functional, and verbal consistency across a product, or to enforce design system compliance in code and component specs.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Inconsistency forces users to relearn the interface for each section, raising error rates and cognitive load. A consistent product lets learned behavior transfer across screens. Design systems encode consistency as enforceable rules — without them, each page drifts independently and audits become full-product exercises.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Auditing a codebase or design for visual, functional, or verbal inconsistencies before a release</item>
        <item>Scanning UI copy across a product to surface synonym clusters and establish a canonical term glossary</item>
        <item>Reviewing a new component against an existing design system to flag deviations</item>
        <item>Enforcing design token usage in code (no hardcoded color or spacing values)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Intentional brand differentiation from convention — consistency auditing does not adjudicate that decision</item>
        <item>Brand-new products with no design system — nothing to be consistent against yet</item>
        <item>Single-screen tools where cross-screen consistency is irrelevant</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="five-consistency-types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply all five consistency types: internal, external, visual, functional, and verbal.</statement>
        <rationale>Each type addresses a different failure mode. A product can be visually consistent but verbally inconsistent (Save vs. Submit vs. Done for the same action), causing user confusion despite uniform appearance.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Internal — same behavior and appearance within your product (same button style everywhere)</item>
        <item>External — follows platform and industry conventions (standard icons, expected gestures)</item>
        <item>Visual — colors, typography, spacing are uniform (same primary action color everywhere)</item>
        <item>Functional — same gesture or interaction produces same result in every context</item>
        <item>Verbal — one term per concept across all UI copy and documentation</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>When conventions conflict, follow this priority order: industry conventions, then platform conventions, then product family conventions, then internal application conventions.</statement>
        <rationale>Industry and platform conventions represent learned behavior from millions of users across many products. Violating them forces relearning; following them gives users immediate competency via transfer.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>iOS: back button always in top-left, swipe from edge to go back, pull to refresh, tab bar at bottom. These platform conventions must be followed even if an internal convention conflicts.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="canonical-verb-set">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pick one canonical verb per UX action and use it everywhere; document the glossary and enforce it in design review.</statement>
        <rationale>Users learn terminology from repetition. Mixed terms for the same action (Create / Add / New / Insert) break that learning and force re-decision at every encounter.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Create → Create (not Add, New, Insert). Delete → Delete (not Remove, Trash, Erase). Edit → Edit (not Modify, Change, Update). Save → Save (not Store, Apply, Confirm).</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad">
        <note>Page 1: [Save]. Page 2: [Submit]. Page 3: [Done]. Same action, three labels — user must re-evaluate the button meaning each time.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="visual-consistency-standards">
      <rule>
        <statement>Define a design token system before writing component code; retrofitting tokens into existing code costs 5x more than starting with them.</statement>
        <rationale>Without tokens, every developer hardcodes colors, spacing, and typography values, producing a combinatorial explosion of inconsistencies that no audit can fully correct.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Color tokens: primary-action always #0066CC, destructive always #CC0000, success always #00CC66. Spacing: base 8px, margins are multiples (8, 16, 24, 32).</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="functional-consistency-patterns">
      <rule>
        <statement>Establish behavior standards for navigation and interaction that hold across every screen, with no exceptions without documentation.</statement>
        <rationale>One inconsistent screen breaks the learned behavior for the whole product. Users encounter the exception, fail, then begin to distrust every interaction.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Logo click: always goes to home. Back button: always goes to previous page. Search: always in top area. Single click: select. Double click: open/edit.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad">
        <note>Page 1: [Cancel] [Save]. Page 2: [Save] [Cancel]. Button order reversed — user trained by page 1 will accidentally click Save when trying to Cancel.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="design-system-requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Document every component with: visual examples, usage guidelines, do/don't rules, and accessibility notes — not just appearance specs.</statement>
        <rationale>A component spec that shows only appearance is incomplete. Without usage guidelines, developers apply components in wrong contexts, producing functional inconsistencies despite visual uniformity.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Typography: font families, sizes, weights (heading hierarchy and body)</item>
        <item>Colors: full palette with usage rules per semantic role</item>
        <item>Spacing: base unit and grid rules</item>
        <item>Buttons: all variants (primary, secondary, destructive, ghost) and all states</item>
        <item>Form elements: inputs, selects, checkboxes, radio buttons</item>
        <item>Navigation: menus, tabs, breadcrumbs</item>
        <item>Feedback: alerts, toasts, error states</item>
        <item>Icons: consistent icon set with label requirements</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Run a consistency audit at the start of each major feature cycle, not at the end; fixing mid-feature is cheaper than post-release.</statement>
        <rationale>Design drift accumulates continuously. Post-release consistency fixes require user communication, staged rollouts, and regression testing. Mid-cycle fixes are local and contained.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="good-examples">
      <example type="good">
        <note>iOS: back button always in top-left, swipe from edge to go back, pull to refresh, tab bar at bottom. Platform conventions held without exception across every iOS app from Apple.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Google products: consistent Material Design across Search, Gmail, Drive, Docs. Same account menu, same search pattern, shared iconography. Users transfer learned behavior between products at zero learning cost.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="bad-examples">
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Page 1: [Save]. Page 2: [Submit]. Page 3: [Done]. Same action, three different labels. User re-evaluates button meaning at every screen instead of acting automatically.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad">
        <note>Page 1: [Cancel] [Save]. Page 2: [Save] [Cancel]. Button order reversed. User trained by page 1 clicks Save when intending Cancel — destructive error caused by inconsistency.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflows">
      <p>Agent reads all UI copy from i18n files, component templates, or scraped live pages. Groups synonym clusters for each UX concept. Produces terminology audit report with recommended canonical term per concept. Output feeds into design system glossary and component documentation update.</p>

      <p>Agent scans codebase for hardcoded CSS color and spacing values that bypass design tokens. Generates migration list with file:line references and recommended token replacements. Can be run in CI via ripgrep or stylelint rules.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent proposes canonical terms without platform HIG validation.</description>
        <reason>LLMs pick the most common term in existing usage, which may be a legacy wrong term. Always validate canonical term selection against Apple HIG, Material Design, or Windows Fluent before adopting.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent treats locale-specific idiomatic differences as inconsistencies (Submit in en-US, Send in en-GB).</description>
        <reason>Scope terminology audits to a single locale first. Cross-locale differences may be intentional and correct.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/consistency-audit.md" purpose="Audit table: visual, functional, terminology, platform convention compliance"/>
      <template path="templates/component-spec.md" purpose="Design system component documentation: variants, sizes, states, usage rules"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/consistency-and-standards/"/>
      <link href="https://www.designbetter.co/design-systems-handbook"/>
      <link href="https://atomicdesign.bradfrost.com/"/>
      <link href="https://material.io/design/introduction"/>
      <link href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/design-systems-book/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
