<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="minimum-product-frameworks">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Decision matrix for choosing the right minimum product framework. Nine frameworks (MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC) for different markets.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>mvp</tag>
      <tag>frameworks</tag>
      <tag>product-scoping</tag>
      <tag>market-fit</tag>
      <tag>release-strategy</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Minimum Product Frameworks</title>
    <summary>A decision matrix for choosing the right "minimum X product" framework for a given market context. Nine frameworks — MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC — each suited to a different combination of market uncertainty, competitive density, and buyer type. The core rule: picking the wrong framework wastes validation budget and may guarantee failure in crowded markets where users already have "good enough" alternatives.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>"Just build an MVP" is an underspecified instruction in 2026. In a blue-ocean market with unvalidated demand, MVP is correct. In a red-ocean consumer market, shipping a barely-functional product against polished incumbents drives immediate churn. The framework choice determines whether your first release creates learning or reputation damage.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Trigger: starting a new product and deciding how much to build before first release.</item>
        <item>Trigger: switching market context (e.g. moving from B2C to B2B) and re-scoping.</item>
        <item>Trigger: team debate "is this MVP or MLP?" — use the decision matrix to resolve.</item>
        <item>Trigger: competitive analysis reveals incumbent products are already polished.</item>
        <item>Trigger: spec.md / SDD feature kickoff before writing implementation-plan.md.</item>
        <item>Trigger: pivot decision — last release missed adoption KPI; re-scope with a different framework.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Framework already chosen and validated — don't re-litigate mid-build.</item>
        <item>Pure technical feasibility spikes — use MFP by default, no matrix needed.</item>
        <item>Internal tooling with a captive user base — minimal standards differ.</item>
        <item>Bug-fix or maintenance release — framework choice does not apply.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <how-to>
      <p>Run this six-step procedure top-to-bottom. Stop when a framework is selected and recorded in spec.md.</p>
      <step>Step 1 — Classify market density. Run a search ("top 10 [product category] 2026") and count incumbents whose UX is rated 4+/5 by reviewers. 0–1 polished incumbents = blue ocean; 5+ = red ocean; 2–4 = contested.</step>
      <step>Step 2 — Classify buyer type. One of: consumer-emotional, consumer-utility, prosumer, SMB-self-serve, enterprise-procurement.</step>
      <step>Step 3 — Classify uncertainty. List the top 3 assumptions that must be true for the product to succeed. If the riskiest is "users want this at all" → uncertainty is HIGH. If it is "we can build it" → uncertainty is TECHNICAL. If "users will pay" → uncertainty is COMMERCIAL.</step>
      <step>Step 4 — Look up the recommended framework in the decision matrix below using (density, buyer, uncertainty). If two cells match, pick the one whose success criterion is closer to your current funding stage.</step>
      <step>Step 5 — Write the choice into spec.md under a "Framework" heading with three lines: chosen framework, primary success metric, kill-criterion (the metric value below which you abandon the framework).</step>
      <step>Step 6 — Translate the framework into scope. Use the framework-to-scope template below to derive must-have, should-have, must-not-have feature lists for the first release.</step>
    </how-to>
    <section name="framework-catalogue">
      <p>All nine frameworks with acronym, purpose, success metric, and when-to-use signal.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Choose the framework before scoping. The choice determines what "minimum" means for your release.</statement>
        <rationale>Each framework optimises for a different success criterion. Defaulting to MVP in a crowded consumer market produces a product users ignore.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>MVP — Minimum Viable Product: test core assumptions. Success metric: validated learning + activation rate &gt;20%. Use when entering a new market with an unvalidated idea.</item>
        <item>MLP — Minimum Lovable Product: create emotional connection. Success metric: NPS &gt;40 + organic referral &gt;15%. Use in crowded markets where differentiation is experience.</item>
        <item>MMP — Minimum Marketable Product: generate first revenue. Success metric: paid logos + retention &gt;6 months. Use in B2B and enterprise sales contexts.</item>
        <item>MAC — Minimum Awesome Component: build one killer feature. Success metric: weekly active usage of the killer feature &gt;60% of users. Use when feature-based differentiation is the strategy.</item>
        <item>RAT — Riskiest Assumption Test: validate the biggest risk. Success metric: signal yes/no on the single riskiest assumption within one sprint. Use on high-uncertainty projects before any build.</item>
        <item>MDP — Minimum Delightful Product: exceed expectations. Success metric: review rating &gt;4.5 + voluntary share rate. Use for premium positioning.</item>
        <item>MVA — Minimum Valuable Product: deliver business value to the buyer. Success metric: documented ROI per customer + renewal commitment. Use in enterprise ROI-focused contexts.</item>
        <item>MFP — Minimum Functional Product: prove technical feasibility. Success metric: end-to-end pipeline runs in production with target throughput/latency. Use for complex infrastructure or novel tech.</item>
        <item>SLC — Simple, Lovable, Complete: balance simplicity and polish. Success metric: full-loop completion rate &gt;70% on first session. Use for consumer apps needing immediate full-loop value.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="key-insight">
      <rule>
        <statement>In crowded markets, an MVP that is merely "viable" will fail. Users already have "good enough" solutions; you need "awesome" or "lovable" to earn a switch.</statement>
        <rationale>Market density changes the minimum bar. A blue-ocean product can be rough; a red-ocean product must clear an existing quality floor before users will try it.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="decision-matrix">
      <p>Market-condition to framework mapping with rationale for each selection. Read each rule as: IF condition THEN framework.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Blue ocean, unvalidated demand: use MVP or RAT. Validate existence of the problem before investing in experience.</statement>
        <rationale>No competing solutions means users will tolerate rough UX to get any solution at all. Validation cost is low, so run RAT first and MVP second.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Red ocean, many competitors: use MLP or MAC. Users must prefer your product over existing alternatives on day one.</statement>
        <rationale>Switching cost is real. A barely-functional product in a crowded market has no gravitational pull; you need either superior experience (MLP) or a single dominant feature (MAC).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Enterprise B2B: use MMP or MVA. Revenue and clear ROI story are required before procurement will sign.</statement>
        <rationale>Enterprise buyers need a business case. "Viable" and "lovable" are secondary to "provably valuable to the organisation's goals".</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Consumer, emotion-driven purchase: use MLP or MDP. The product must feel right on first use to generate word-of-mouth.</statement>
        <rationale>Consumer apps succeed on referral loops. Delight drives sharing; functional-but-bland does not.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Technical uncertainty (novel infrastructure, new integration): use MFP first, then expand. Prove it can work before proving it is loved.</statement>
        <rationale>Investing in UX and delight before technical feasibility is confirmed wastes resources if the technical approach fails.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Consumer utility, contested market, full-loop required: use SLC. Half-loops produce drop-off in tools where the value is the completed task.</statement>
        <rationale>Productivity and utility apps are judged on "did it finish my task?". A half-MVP that breaks at step 4/5 is rated worse than nothing.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Applying MVP to every product regardless of market context.</description>
        <reason>"MVP" as a default ignores market conditions. In competitive markets it produces products that users dismiss before forming a habit.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Choosing MLP or MDP for an unvalidated problem.</description>
        <reason>Investing in delight before validating demand is expensive misdirection. Polishing a product nobody wants is still a product nobody wants.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Mixing two frameworks in one release ("we'll do MLP+MMP at the same time").</description>
        <reason>Frameworks optimise for different success metrics. Pursuing both forces compromises in scope and dilutes the validation signal.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="prompt-templates">
      <p>Drop-in prompts an autonomous agent can paste into its planning step. Replace placeholders in {curly braces}.</p>
      <prompt purpose="classify-and-recommend"><![CDATA[
You are a product-planning agent. Pick exactly one framework from
{MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC}.

Inputs:
- Product idea: {one sentence}
- Target users: {who}
- Market density: {blue | contested | red}
- Buyer type: {consumer-emotional | consumer-utility | prosumer | SMB | enterprise}
- Top 3 risk assumptions: {a1; a2; a3}
- Funding stage: {pre-seed | seed | series-A+}

Output JSON only:
{
  "framework": "<acronym>",
  "rationale": "<1-2 sentences citing density + buyer + uncertainty>",
  "success_metric": "<measurable KPI with threshold>",
  "kill_criterion": "<KPI value below which we abandon>",
  "first_release_scope_hint": "<one paragraph>"
}
      ]]></prompt>
      <prompt purpose="framework-to-scope"><![CDATA[
Given framework={ACRONYM} and product brief={brief}, output three lists:

MUST-HAVE (release blockers):
- ...

SHOULD-HAVE (post-release sprint):
- ...

MUST-NOT-HAVE (out of scope; reject in PRs):
- ...

Justify each MUST-NOT-HAVE in one line — why it conflicts with the framework's success metric.
      ]]></prompt>
    </section>
    <section name="spec-template">
      <p>Paste this block under a "## Framework" heading inside spec.md. Fill all fields; leave none blank.</p>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Framework

- Chosen: <MVP|MLP|MMP|MAC|RAT|MDP|MVA|MFP|SLC>
- Why this one: <1-2 lines citing market density, buyer type, uncertainty>
- Primary success metric: <KPI + numeric threshold>
- Kill criterion: <KPI value below which we abandon or pivot>
- Review checkpoint: <after first N users / after week X>
- Out-of-scope (must-not-have): <bullet list>
      ]]></code>
    </section>
    <checklist>
      <check>Market density classified (blue / contested / red) with at least one cited source.</check>
      <check>Buyer type named explicitly from the closed list.</check>
      <check>Top 3 risk assumptions written down before framework choice.</check>
      <check>Exactly one framework selected — no hybrids.</check>
      <check>Primary success metric is numeric and time-bounded.</check>
      <check>Kill criterion is set and lower than the success metric.</check>
      <check>spec.md contains the Framework block from the template.</check>
      <check>MUST-NOT-HAVE list is non-empty and each item has a one-line justification.</check>
      <check>Decision recorded with date so future pivots can reference it.</check>
    </checklist>
    <verify>
      <step>Confirm spec.md contains a "## Framework" section: run grep -n "^## Framework" spec.md and ensure exit code 0.</step>
      <step>Confirm exactly one framework acronym appears under that heading: run grep -E "Chosen: (MVP|MLP|MMP|MAC|RAT|MDP|MVA|MFP|SLC)" spec.md.</step>
      <step>Confirm success metric contains a number and a unit/percent/timeframe: grep for a digit on the "Primary success metric" line.</step>
      <step>Confirm kill criterion is present and numerically lower than success metric.</step>
      <step>Run the framework-to-scope prompt and verify the implementation-plan.md tasks fit inside the MUST-HAVE list — no plan task implements a MUST-NOT-HAVE item.</step>
      <step>After first release, compare the realised KPI against success metric and kill criterion; record the result under "## Framework / Outcome" in spec.md.</step>
    </verify>
    <example type="good" title="SLC for a consumer utility app in a contested market">
      <description>Indie note-taking app entering a market with Notion, Obsidian, Apple Notes. Team picks SLC: ship a small but complete capture-edit-search loop. Success metric: 70% of new users complete capture+search within session 1. Kill criterion: less than 40% completion after 200 sign-ups.</description>
      <note>Choosing MVP would have shipped a half-loop (capture only) that users dismiss within minutes; choosing MLP would have over-invested in animations before proving the loop holds.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="MLP for an unvalidated B2B integration">
      <description>Team builds a polished UI for a workflow nobody confirmed they need. After launch, demos convert at less than 1%. The team had no kill criterion and burned six months. Correct choice: RAT first to test the workflow demand, then MMP for revenue.</description>
    </example>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="micro-mvps"/>
      <ref slug="mlp-planning"/>
      <ref slug="mvp-scoping"/>
      <ref slug="spec-writing"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
