<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="minimum-product-frameworks">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Decision matrix for choosing the right minimum product framework. Nine frameworks (MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC) suit different market contexts and buyer types.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>mvp</tag>
      <tag>frameworks</tag>
      <tag>product-scoping</tag>
      <tag>market-fit</tag>
      <tag>release-strategy</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Minimum Product Frameworks</title>
    <summary>A decision matrix for choosing the right "minimum X product" framework for a given market context. Nine frameworks — MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC — each suited to a different combination of market uncertainty, competitive density, and buyer type. The core rule: picking the wrong framework wastes validation budget and may guarantee failure in crowded markets where users already have "good enough" alternatives.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>"Just build an MVP" is an underspecified instruction in 2026. In a blue-ocean market with unvalidated demand, MVP is correct. In a red-ocean consumer market, shipping a barely-functional product against polished incumbents drives immediate churn. The framework choice determines whether your first release creates learning or reputation damage.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Starting a new product and deciding how much to build before first release.</item>
        <item>Switching market context (e.g. moving from B2C to B2B) and re-scoping.</item>
        <item>Team debate: "is this MVP or MLP?" — use the decision matrix to resolve.</item>
        <item>Competitive analysis reveals incumbent products are already polished.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Framework already chosen and validated — don't re-litigate mid-build.</item>
        <item>Pure technical feasibility spikes — use MFP by default, no matrix needed.</item>
        <item>Internal tooling with a captive user base — minimal standards differ.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="framework-catalogue">
      <p>All nine frameworks with acronym, purpose, and when-to-use signal.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Choose the framework before scoping. The choice determines what "minimum" means for your release.</statement>
        <rationale>Each framework optimises for a different success criterion. Defaulting to MVP in a crowded consumer market produces a product users ignore.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>MVP — Minimum Viable Product: test core assumptions. Use when entering a new market with an unvalidated idea.</item>
        <item>MLP — Minimum Lovable Product: create emotional connection. Use in crowded markets where differentiation is experience.</item>
        <item>MMP — Minimum Marketable Product: generate first revenue. Use in B2B and enterprise sales contexts.</item>
        <item>MAC — Minimum Awesome Component: build one killer feature. Use when feature-based differentiation is the strategy.</item>
        <item>RAT — Riskiest Assumption Test: validate the biggest risk. Use on high-uncertainty projects before any build.</item>
        <item>MDP — Minimum Delightful Product: exceed expectations. Use for premium positioning.</item>
        <item>MVA — Minimum Valuable Product: deliver business value to the buyer. Use in enterprise ROI-focused contexts.</item>
        <item>MFP — Minimum Functional Product: prove technical feasibility. Use for complex infrastructure or novel tech.</item>
        <item>SLC — Simple, Lovable, Complete: balance simplicity and polish. Use for consumer apps needing immediate full-loop value.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="key-insight">
      <rule>
        <statement>In crowded markets, an MVP that is merely "viable" will fail. Users already have "good enough" solutions; you need "awesome" or "lovable" to earn a switch.</statement>
        <rationale>Market density changes the minimum bar. A blue-ocean product can be rough; a red-ocean product must clear an existing quality floor before users will try it.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="decision-matrix">
      <p>Market-condition to framework mapping with rationale for each selection.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Blue ocean, unvalidated demand: use MVP or RAT. Validate existence of the problem before investing in experience.</statement>
        <rationale>No competing solutions means users will tolerate rough UX to get any solution at all. Validation cost is low, so run RAT first and MVP second.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Red ocean, many competitors: use MLP or MAC. Users must prefer your product over existing alternatives on day one.</statement>
        <rationale>Switching cost is real. A barely-functional product in a crowded market has no gravitational pull; you need either superior experience (MLP) or a single dominant feature (MAC).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Enterprise B2B: use MMP or MVA. Revenue and clear ROI story are required before procurement will sign.</statement>
        <rationale>Enterprise buyers need a business case. "Viable" and "lovable" are secondary to "provably valuable to the organisation's goals".</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Consumer, emotion-driven purchase: use MLP or MDP. The product must feel right on first use to generate word-of-mouth.</statement>
        <rationale>Consumer apps succeed on referral loops. Delight drives sharing; functional-but-bland does not.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Technical uncertainty (novel infrastructure, new integration): use MFP first, then expand. Prove it can work before proving it is loved.</statement>
        <rationale>Investing in UX and delight before technical feasibility is confirmed wastes resources if the technical approach fails.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Applying MVP to every product regardless of market context.</description>
        <reason>"MVP" as a default ignores market conditions. In competitive markets it produces products that users dismiss before forming a habit.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Choosing MLP or MDP for an unvalidated problem.</description>
        <reason>Investing in delight before validating demand is expensive misdirection. Polish a product nobody wants is still a product nobody wants.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="micro-mvps"/>
      <ref slug="mlp-planning"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
