<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ads-meta-reporting">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>ppc-manager</domain>
    <summary>Structured analyze-decide-act cycle for Meta Ads: set up custom column presets, run weekly breakdowns by age/placement/device, and diagnose performance issues by mapping symptoms to root causes.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>meta-ads</tag>
      <tag>reporting</tag>
      <tag>performance-analysis</tag>
      <tag>diagnostics</tag>
      <tag>cpa-optimization</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Meta Ads Reporting &amp; Analysis</title>
    <summary>Structured analyze-decide-act cycle for Meta Ads: set up custom column presets (CPM, CTR, CPC, CVR, CPA, ROAS), run weekly breakdowns by age/placement/device, and diagnose performance issues by mapping symptoms (high CPA, low CTR, high frequency) to root causes (creative fatigue, audience fatigue, landing page failure). Every report must produce a list of concrete actions.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Default Meta reports surface vanity metrics. Decisions made on the wrong metrics waste budget on underperforming ads. A structured diagnostic flow — CPM → CTR → CVR → CPA — pinpoints exactly where the funnel breaks and what to fix. Reporting without action is overhead; every session must produce a decision.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Weekly performance review for any active Meta campaign.</item>
        <item>Diagnosing a CPA spike or CTR decline.</item>
        <item>Presenting results to stakeholders (executive summary, creative analysis).</item>
        <item>Deciding which campaigns to scale, hold, or pause.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Daily micro-optimization — too noisy; check spend pacing and errors daily, but full analysis weekly.</item>
        <item>Campaigns in learning phase (less than 50 conversions in the optimization window) — data is not representative.</item>
        <item>Attribution decisions that require cross-platform modeling — use dedicated attribution tools, not Meta-only data.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Metric Hierarchy">
      <p>Metrics form a diagnostic chain: CPM reveals audience competitiveness, CTR reveals creative and audience fit, CVR reveals landing page effectiveness, CPA reveals overall acquisition efficiency, ROAS reveals revenue return.</p>
      <list>
        <item>CPM = (Spend / Impressions) × 1000 — cost to reach 1,000 people; high CPM signals competitive audience or low relevance score.</item>
        <item>CTR = (Clicks / Impressions) × 100 — percentage of people who clicked; below 0.5% indicates creative or audience mismatch.</item>
        <item>CPC = Spend / Clicks — cost per click; derivative of CPM and CTR.</item>
        <item>CVR = (Conversions / Clicks) × 100 — landing page conversion rate; below 1% indicates a landing page problem.</item>
        <item>CPA = Spend / Conversions — cost per acquisition; the primary optimization target.</item>
        <item>ROAS = Revenue / Spend — overall return; below 2x means the campaign is losing money at average margins.</item>
        <item>Frequency = Impressions / Reach — average times a person saw the ad; above 3 signals audience fatigue.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Benchmarks">
      <p>Industry-wide averages for Meta Ads across sectors. Use as orientation, not gospel — benchmarks vary by vertical, offer, and funnel stage.</p>
      <list>
        <item>CTR: below 0.5% = poor, 0.8-1.2% = average, above 1.5% = good.</item>
        <item>CVR: below 1% = poor, 2-3% = average, above 5% = good.</item>
        <item>Frequency: above 3 = high fatigue risk, 1.5-2.5 = healthy, below 1.5 = good.</item>
        <item>ROAS: below 2 = losing, 2-3 = average, above 4 = good.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Diagnostic Decision Tree">
      <rule>
        <statement>Diagnose high CPA by walking the metric chain: check CTR first, then CVR, then CPM, then frequency.</statement>
        <rationale>Each metric isolates one stage of the funnel. Jumping to creative changes when the problem is a landing page wastes production budget. The chain prevents misdiagnosis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>CPA rose from $10 to $18 over two weeks. Diagnosis via metric chain.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
High CPA?
├── CTR stable at 1.2%  → creative is not the issue
├── CVR dropped 4% → 2.5%  → landing page problem
├── CPM stable  → audience is not the issue
└── Frequency rose 1.8 → 3.2  → audience fatigue, secondary issue

Actions:
1. A/B test landing page (primary fix)
2. Expand audience or add new lookalike (secondary fix)
3. Refresh creative to reduce frequency impact
4. Exclude recent converters
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Changing the creative when CVR is the low metric.</description>
        <reason>CTR is a creative metric; CVR is a landing page metric. Producing new ads when the click-to-conversion rate is broken wastes creative budget and delays the actual fix.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Column Presets">
      <p>Create four saved column presets in Ads Manager: Overview (spend, impressions, reach, frequency, CTR, CPA, ROAS), Prospecting (CTR, CPC, CPA, CVR), Retargeting (ROAS, CVR, frequency), Creative Testing (CTR, 3-second video view rate, thumb-stop rate, cost per result).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Reporting Cadence">
      <rule>
        <statement>Check spend pacing and errors daily; run full performance analysis weekly; review trends and reallocate budget monthly.</statement>
        <rationale>Daily checking of full metrics is noise — algorithmic variance within a day can show apparent swings that average out over a week. Weekly analysis has enough data for decisions. Monthly reviews catch slow-moving trends that weekly snapshots miss.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Daily (5 min): spend pacing vs. budget, delivery errors, any metric changes over 30%.</item>
        <item>Weekly (30-60 min): full metric review, breakdown analysis, optimization decisions, creative refresh planning.</item>
        <item>Monthly (90 min): ROAS/CPA trend analysis, audience performance comparison, budget reallocation, strategy adjustments.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Breakdown Analysis">
      <p>Breakdowns expose which segment of your audience or placement is driving performance. Key dimensions: Age, Gender, Placement (Feed/Stories/Reels/Audience Network), Platform (Facebook/Instagram), Device (mobile/desktop), Time of day, Region.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>After identifying a breakdown winner, create a dedicated campaign or ad set for that segment rather than relying on the algorithm to favor it.</statement>
        <rationale>Meta's algorithm will spend across the full audience even when one segment converts 3x better. Isolating the winner gives it dedicated budget and prevents the budget being diluted into lower-performing segments.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Instagram Stories placement converts at 2x lower CPA than Facebook Feed. Isolate and scale.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Before: One ad set, auto-placements, CPA $18 average
After: Separate ad set for Instagram Stories only, CPA $9
Result: 50% CPA reduction by isolating winning placement
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="Budget Reallocation Decision">
      <rule>
        <statement>Scale campaigns beating target CPA; hold campaigns within 20% of target; test new creative or audience on campaigns above 20% over target; pause campaigns above 50% over target after a fair test period.</statement>
        <rationale>Budget reallocation is the primary lever for improving account efficiency without changing the product or offer. Clear numeric thresholds prevent emotional decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running weekly analysis on vanity metrics (likes, reach, impressions).</description>
        <reason>Vanity metrics do not correlate with revenue. Optimizing for reach at the expense of CPA produces popular ads that lose money.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Comparing performance across periods with different external conditions (holidays, launches, seasonality).</description>
        <reason>A 30% CPA increase week-over-week may be a Black Friday effect, not a campaign issue. Compare same-day-of-week, same-week-of-year, or use a holdout cell to isolate platform effects.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Producing a report with no action items.</description>
        <reason>A report without decisions is overhead. Every weekly analysis must produce at least one concrete action: scale, pause, test new creative, refresh audience.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Integration &amp; Automation">
      <p>Automated reporting agents can pull Insights API data on a schedule, aggregate breakdowns, compute diagnostic metrics, and post reports to Slack or email. Diagnosis agents can receive a campaign ID and date range, walk the symptom tree (CPA up → CTR/CVR/CPM/frequency → root cause), and propose 2-3 actions. Action agents apply bounded changes (pause ads with CTR below 0.5% and spend above threshold) inside guardrails without manual approval under a daily spend cap.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>When using agents for automated reporting, always state the attribution window in every report (7d_click + 1d_view); a report with no window is uninterpretable.</statement>
        <rationale>Meta's default attribution window is now 7-day click plus 1-day view; older reports use 28-day click which inflates everything 1.5-2x. Changing windows without stating it creates false alarms in trend analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Reconcile against server-side ground truth weekly; if Meta-reported revenue is greater than 25% off Stripe, fix tracking before optimizing creative. Walk the diagnostic flow in order: CTR → CVR → CPM → frequency. Skipping steps leads to fixing the wrong thing.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Known Limitations &amp; Gotchas">
      <p>Meta Insights API has rate limits per ad account (approximately 25 calls/hr for high-volume async); naive agent loops hit them on minute one. iOS 14.5+ cuts Meta-reported conversions by 15-40% vs server-side — reports comparing Meta to GA4 will look wrong even when both are correct.</p>
      <p>Breakdowns cannot be combined freely — placement + age + gender together is forbidden, agent must split into multiple calls. Async insights jobs (more than 50 rows) take minutes; agents that timeout at 30s will silently lose data. Modeled conversions in Aggregated Event Measurement look real in reports but are not deterministic — reconciliation will never be 100%.</p>
      <p>Cache Insights pulls for the same (account, date_range, fields, breakdown) key — agents that re-fetch the same data hit rate limits fast. Keep one north-star metric per campaign objective (CPA for Sales, CPL for Leads, ROAS for catalog) and grade everything against it. Vanity metrics distract.</p>
      <p>Send weekly reports on Monday morning local time, not the moment data closes — late Sunday data is often restated by Tuesday. LLMs love to say "CTR is up" without checking statistical significance — a $20 ad with 3% CTR is noise. Require minimum spend or impressions per row.</p>
      <p>Modeled conversions inflate Meta-reported numbers; agents reporting "Meta says 100, GA4 says 65" without flagging modeled-vs-deterministic produce false alarms. Do not let an agent auto-pause based on 24h data — Meta's reporting is not final for 72h. Use rolling 7-day windows for action triggers.</p>
      <p>Human-in-loop checkpoint: any auto-action that pauses spend greater than $50/day, any rule that scales budget greater than 25% in one step. Watch for Spending Limit Reached errors — they look like no spend in reports, agents misdiagnose as audience fatigue.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices for Reporting">
      <p>Always state the attribution window in every report (7d_click + 1d_view); a report with no window is uninterpretable. Reconcile against server-side ground truth weekly; if Meta-reported revenue is greater than 25% off Stripe, fix tracking before optimizing creative.</p>
      <p>Walk the diagnostic flow in order: CTR → CVR → CPM → frequency. Skipping steps leads to fixing the wrong thing. Cache Insights pulls for the same (account, date_range, fields, breakdown) key — agents that re-fetch the same data hit rate limits fast.</p>
      <p>Keep one north-star metric per campaign objective (CPA for Sales, CPL for Leads, ROAS for catalog) and grade everything against it. Vanity metrics distract. Send weekly reports on Monday morning local time, not the moment data closes — late Sunday data is often restated by Tuesday.</p>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/weekly-report.md" purpose="Weekly performance report: summary, campaign table, top ads, insights, actions."/>
      <template path="templates/creative-analysis.md" purpose="Creative performance breakdown by format and fatigue signals checklist."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="ads-meta-targeting"/>
      <ref slug="ads-retargeting"/>
      <link href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/marketing-api/insights/"/>
      <link href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/marketing-api/insights/best-practices"/>
      <link href="https://www.facebook.com/business/help/458681590974355"/>
      <link href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/marketing-api/insights/breakdowns"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
