<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Competitive Positioning Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Competitive Positioning plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="name-real-alternatives" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The positioning statement MUST name 3-7 real competitive alternatives (including 'do nothing' and 'spreadsheet'); generic phrases like 'legacy solutions' MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford — Obviously Awesome (2019)">Vague alternatives produce vague positioning; named alternatives force concrete differentiation choices.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="unique-attributes-must-be-distinct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every claimed unique attribute MUST be one a named alternative cannot truthfully claim; me-too attributes MUST be removed.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford — Obviously Awesome (2019)">Me-too attributes give buyers no reason to switch; the distinctness test is the gate against shouting into the void.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="value-must-be-quantified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each unique-attribute → customer-value translation MUST be quantified (time saved, dollars made, errors avoided) per buyer segment; qualitative-only value MUST be rewritten.</statement>
      <rationale source="Andy Raskin — Strategic Narrative">Qualitative value claims compete on adjective inflation ('faster', 'better'); quantified claims survive procurement review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="best-fit-customer-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The best-fit customer MUST be named with company size, role, trigger event, and budget signal; aspirational personas MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bob Moesta — Demand-Side Sales">Aspirational personas produce GTM messaging nobody self-identifies with; the named best-fit is the channel + targeting input.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="market-category-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The market category MUST be explicit (named or created); category-ambiguous positioning MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Play Bigger — Ramadan et al.">Without an explicit category, buyers compare against the wrong alternatives and discount accordingly; category framing is the price anchor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
