<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="competitive-positioning Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for competitive-positioning. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap unique attributes at 3. More than 3 means no positioning — just a feature list. Agents over-list; trim hard.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A positioning statement with more than 3 unique attributes fails to differentiate because customers cannot hold more than 3 comparative distinctions in working memory simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Add a time-to-copy column to the unique-attributes table. Anything copyable in fewer than 2 quarters is not a positioning anchor — it is a feature.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Positioning must be durable. An attribute a competitor can ship in 6 weeks is a temporary advantage, not a positioning moat. Time-to-copy forces the team to find genuinely defensible attributes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The "so what" ladder must terminate in a measurable outcome (hours, dollars, percent, retention). Reject "save time" without a number.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Vague value claims cannot be tested or proven. Measurable outcomes give the sales team concrete proof points and give the agent a clear standard for rejection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For category-creation decisions, require a budget estimate for market education before proceeding. If the education cost exceeds GTM runway, fall back to subcategory positioning.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Category creation is not a positioning choice — it is a multi-year investment. Agents will declare new categories confidently without estimating the education cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The positioning statement must contain all six clauses: For, Who, Is, That, Unlike, We. Fail the build if any clause is missing.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents drop the "Unlike" clause because it feels confrontational. Without it, the statement has no competitive anchor and reduces to a tagline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test the statement against three "would this exclude?" questions: (a) a persona you don't want, (b) a use case you don't serve, (c) a price point above or below yours. If none are excluded, the positioning is too broad.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Good positioning is as much about who you are not for as who you are for. A statement that excludes nobody is marketing copy, not positioning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run Dunford's six steps serially because each step constrains the next. Fan out only the value-translation step (one parallel task per attribute) since attributes are independent.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Steps 1-4 have hard dependencies: alternatives must exist before attributes, attributes before value, value before best-fit customer. Parallelizing constrained steps produces incoherent outputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run positioning AFTER competitor-analysis AND user-personas exist. Both are inputs; canvas without them is fiction.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hallucinated competitor positioning (agent invents taglines from training data rather than current homepages) is the dominant quality failure. Real competitor pages must be fetched and passed as input.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always run a devil's-advocate pass with a different model (sonnet → opus) that role-plays each top-3 competitor's CMO trying to dismiss your positioning. Iterate once based on the critique.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Self-serving positioning is invisible to the agent that produced it. An adversarial pass from the competitor's perspective surfaces weaknesses that peer review misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
