<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Dunford Six-Step Positioning Framework">
  <summary>April Dunford's six-step competitive positioning process with rules, strategy options, and the constraint that unique attributes must be capped at 3 with measurable outcomes.</summary>

  <section title="The Six Steps">
    <p>Step 1: list competitive alternatives (direct, indirect, status quo). Step 2: identify unique attributes — features only you have, approach only you take, expertise only you possess. Step 3: translate attributes to customer value via "so what" laddering. Step 4: identify best-fit customers — who values this most and why. Step 5: define market category (existing, subcategory, new). Step 6: craft positioning statement using the For/Who/Is/That/Unlike/We template.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Cap unique attributes at 3. More than 3 means no positioning — just a feature list. Agents over-list; trim hard.</statement>
      <rationale>A positioning statement with more than 3 unique attributes fails to differentiate because customers cannot hold more than 3 comparative distinctions in working memory simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Add a time-to-copy column to the unique-attributes table. Anything copyable in fewer than 2 quarters is not a positioning anchor — it is a feature.</statement>
      <rationale>Positioning must be durable. An attribute a competitor can ship in 6 weeks is a temporary advantage, not a positioning moat. Time-to-copy forces the team to find genuinely defensible attributes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>The "so what" ladder must terminate in a measurable outcome (hours, dollars, percent, retention). Reject "save time" without a number.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague value claims cannot be tested or proven. Measurable outcomes give the sales team concrete proof points and give the agent a clear standard for rejection.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Positioning Strategies">
    <p>Head-to-Head: you are better on established criteria — risk is feature wars. Differentiation: you serve a specific need others ignore — risk is niche too small. Niche Dominance: you own a specific segment — risk is growth ceiling. Category Creation: you are truly new — risk is market education cost (18-24 months, analyst briefings, sales enablement budget required).</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>For category-creation decisions, require a budget estimate for market education before proceeding. If the education cost exceeds GTM runway, fall back to subcategory positioning.</statement>
      <rationale>Category creation is not a positioning choice — it is a multi-year investment. Agents will declare new categories confidently without estimating the education cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Positioning Statement Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>The positioning statement must contain all six clauses: For, Who, Is, That, Unlike, We. Fail the build if any clause is missing.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents drop the "Unlike" clause because it feels confrontational. Without it, the statement has no competitive anchor and reduces to a tagline.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Test the statement against three "would this exclude?" questions: (a) a persona you don't want, (b) a use case you don't serve, (c) a price point above or below yours. If none are excluded, the positioning is too broad.</statement>
      <rationale>Good positioning is as much about who you are not for as who you are for. A statement that excludes nobody is marketing copy, not positioning.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>"Better" positioning: competitive claims of faster, easier, simpler without a stated dimension and number.</description>
      <reason>Comparative-without-dimension claims cannot be proven, are easily matched by competitors, and signal that the team has not found real differentiation. "5x faster at data export than Salesforce" is allowed; "faster" alone is not.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Static positioning: canvas written once and never revisited as market changes.</description>
      <reason>Version the canvas in git with a date stamp. Quarterly diff reveals positioning drift before customers notice. Markets shift; positioning must track.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Best-fit-customer defined as "ambitious teams who want to ship faster."</description>
      <reason>Enforce a persona schema: role, company size, trigger event, current alternative, willingness-to-pay. Without schema enforcement, agents produce meaningless audience descriptions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/positioning-canvas.md">Positioning canvas: alternatives, attributes, value translation, customer, category, statement</reference>
  <reference path="templates/positioning-lint.sh">Linter: flags comparative language without dimension and checks six-clause structure</reference>
</text>
