<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Competitive Positioning Worked Examples">
  <summary>Two complete positioning examples showing alternatives, unique attributes, value translation, best-fit customer, and six-clause statements.</summary>

  <section title="Example 1: Project Management Tool">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Solo project manager positioned against complex tools.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Alternatives: Asana/Monday (feature-rich, complex), Trello (simple but limited), Spreadsheets (free but painful).
Unique attributes: designed for solo creators, no team features (simpler), built-in time tracking.
Time-to-copy: 6-12 quarters (teams at Asana have no product incentive to simplify — that would cannibalize team plans).
Value: get organized in 5 minutes, not 5 hours.
Best-fit: solo freelancers overwhelmed by big tools (trigger: just bounced from Asana free trial; WTP: $12/mo).
Market category: personal project manager (existing subcategory, not new category).

Positioning statement:
For solo freelancers
Who need to track projects without complexity
SoloBoard is a personal project manager
That gets you organized in 5 minutes
Unlike Asana and Monday
We deliberately have no team features.
      ]]></code>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <note>Typical "better" positioning that fails the lint check.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"SoloBoard is the easiest and most powerful project manager for modern teams."
FAILS: "easiest" and "most powerful" are unsupported superlatives.
FAILS: "modern teams" is not a best-fit customer — it excludes nobody.
FAILS: missing Unlike clause.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example 2: Email Marketing Platform">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Indie writer platform positioned against subscriber-based pricing.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Alternatives: Mailchimp (all-in-one, expensive at scale), ConvertKit (creator-focused), Substack (newsletter-native).
Unique attributes: flat pricing (no per-subscriber fees), focused on <10k subscribers, native Ghost/WordPress integration.
Time-to-copy: 2-4 quarters (Mailchimp changing pricing model requires board-level decision; ConvertKit has subscriber-based revenue dependency).
Value: grow without pricing anxiety (measurable: no bill increase when subscriber count doubles).
Best-fit: indie writers and bloggers building an audience (trigger: hit 1k subscribers on Mailchimp, saw next month's bill; WTP: $29/mo flat).

Positioning statement:
For indie writers growing their newsletter
Who worry about costs as they scale
WriterMail is email marketing
That stays affordable forever
Unlike Mailchimp and ConvertKit
We charge flat fees, not per-subscriber.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Positioning Map Usage">
    <example type="good">
      <note>2x2 map to visualize gaps. Use mermaid-cli to render as SVG for stakeholder review.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Dimensions:
  X-axis: Price (low -> high)
  Y-axis: Simplicity (complex -> simple)

Position us in the "low price + simple" quadrant.
Competitors Asana/Monday: high price + complex.
Trello: low price + complex (more features than it looks).
Gap: low price + simple -- that is our position.

Mermaid render:
mmdc -i positioning-map.mmd -o positioning-map.svg
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
