<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="competitive-positioning Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for competitive-positioning as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>"Better" positioning: competitive claims of faster, easier, simpler without a stated dimension and number.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Comparative-without-dimension claims cannot be proven, are easily matched by competitors, and signal that the team has not found real differentiation. "5x faster at data export than Salesforce" is allowed; "faster" alone is not.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Static positioning: canvas written once and never revisited as market changes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Version the canvas in git with a date stamp. Quarterly diff reveals positioning drift before customers notice. Markets shift; positioning must track.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Best-fit-customer defined as "ambitious teams who want to ship faster."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Enforce a persona schema: role, company size, trigger event, current alternative, willingness-to-pay. Without schema enforcement, agents produce meaningless audience descriptions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Comparative language by default: LLMs produce "better/faster/easier" even when prompted for differentiation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Explicit prompt rule plus positioning-lint.sh pre-commit hook catches it. Comparative without dimension+number is the single most common positioning quality failure from LLM agents.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Hallucinated competitor positioning from training data instead of current homepages.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pass live homepage HTML/text into the prompt. Never let the agent rely on memory for competitor claims — they are updated constantly and the agent's training is stale.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Ladder collapse: so-what laddering produces three levels that paraphrase the same idea.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force each level to use a different noun class (feature benefit → business outcome → emotional/strategic outcome) and a measurable at the terminal level.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Category-creation inflation: every product becomes "the first AI-native X."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require a citation that the proposed category does not yet exist — G2 search returning zero results, or no Wikipedia entry for the category name. Fiction categories harm credibility.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Proof points filled with "trusted by leaders" marketing copy.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every proof point must be a citable URL, customer quote, or measurable outcome. Marketing copy is not evidence and fails the agent's own lint rules.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
