<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stakeholder Conflict Facilitation Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that convert a stakeholder-conflict meeting into a structured, signed decision artefact.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The meeting MUST run exactly five phases with explicit timeboxes: (1) frame the disagreement (5 min), (2) state positions (15 min), (3) apply rubric (15 min), (4) decide (10 min), (5) capture dissent + assignments (15 min). The facilitator MUST announce phase boundaries verbally and MUST NOT skip a phase even when the room "agrees early".</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping the rubric phase when "we already agree" is exactly when soft consensus papers over real disagreement — the conflict re-emerges two weeks later. Forcing every phase preserves the artefact integrity regardless of room dynamics.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Agenda AND ground rules MUST be circulated to all attendees at least 24 hours before the meeting. Ground rules MUST include at minimum: one speaker at a time, no decision before phase 4, dissent will be recorded by name.</statement>
      <rationale>"Dissent will be recorded by name" pre-announced changes behaviour: people argue more substantively when they know their name attaches to their position. Surprise-announcing the rule mid-meeting feels like a trap and damages future cooperation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Phase 3 MUST score each option using the pre-agreed rubric (criteria + weights + 1-5 scoring), live in the room, with scores read out and recorded. Narrative-only ("on balance, I prefer option B") is not a substitute for scoring.</statement>
      <rationale>The rubric forces the implicit weighing into the open: two stakeholders who "both like option B" often score it very differently, and the difference is the real conversation. Pure narrative facilitation lets the senior voice dominate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Any stakeholder who voted against the chosen option MUST have their dissent captured with name + one-sentence grounds + "I commit to the chosen option" or "I escalate" choice. Anonymising the dissent ("some attendees disagreed") or omitting it is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>Named dissent + commitment-or-escalation is the disagree-and-commit primitive — without it, dissenters re-open the decision unofficially later. Recording the commit closes the loop; recording the escalation routes the conflict cleanly upward.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Output MUST be a one-page decision log entry filed in the project's decision register (`decisions/YYYY-MM-DD-&lt;slug&gt;.md`), containing: framing, positions, rubric scores, decision, dissent, named owner for each assignment, sign-off line per attendee. The entry is published within 1 working day of the meeting.</statement>
      <rationale>An undocumented or late-documented decision is a decision in name only — within a week, attendees remember different things. Same-day publishing locks the artefact while memory is fresh and gives dissenters a chance to challenge the wording before it sets.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Decision: 2026-05-20-checkout-discount-rule

## Framing
Disagreement on whether discount codes apply to subscription products.
Sources: Maria (VP Ops) — yes; Tomás (CFO) — no.

## Positions (phase 2)
- Maria: discounts drive trial-to-paid; finance can absorb 5% lift.
- Tomás: subscription LTV math breaks if base price is discountable.

## Rubric scores (phase 3)
| Criterion          | Weight | Option A (yes) | Option B (no) |
|--------------------|--------|-----------------|----------------|
| Revenue impact     | 0.4    | 3              | 4              |
| Conversion lift    | 0.3    | 5              | 2              |
| Operational cost   | 0.2    | 3              | 4              |
| Brand consistency  | 0.1    | 4              | 4              |
| Weighted total     |        | 3.7            | 3.4            |

## Decision (phase 4)
Option A — discounts apply to subscriptions, capped at 15%.

## Dissent (phase 5)
- Tomás: "Disagree on LTV grounds. I commit to the chosen option, revisit at next QBR if churn rises."

## Sign-off
- Maria Lopes — 2026-05-20T11:40Z
- Tomás Silva  — 2026-05-20T11:41Z
- BA: Anna Mendes — 2026-05-20T11:42Z
      ]]></code>
      <note>All five phases produced an artefact. Dissent named, committed, scheduled for revisit. The decision is enforceable and reviewable.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Notes from meeting

Discussed discount codes for subscriptions.
Decided to allow them.
Some folks weren't fully convinced but agreed to move on.
      ]]></code>
      <note>No phases, no rubric, no named dissent, no sign-off. "Agreed to move on" guarantees the topic re-opens within two sprints.</note>
    </example>

  </section>
</text>
