<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-structure" title="Design Document Structure and Decision Format">
  <summary>Document hierarchy in SDD, when to write a design doc, SDD-optimized structure, AD-X decision format, and Y-statement concise form.</summary>

  <section title="Document Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write design.md after spec.md is approved and before writing implementation-plan.md; never skip this order.</statement>
      <rationale>The spec defines intent (WHAT/WHY); the design defines mechanism (HOW); the implementation plan defines sequence (WHEN/ORDER). Reversing the order produces implementations without explicit decision records and specs without feasibility validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>constitution.md: project-wide tech decisions and standards</item>
      <item>spec.md: FR-X requirements and AC-X acceptance criteria (WHAT/WHY)</item>
      <item>design.md: AD-X architectural decisions, file structure, data models, API contracts (HOW)</item>
      <item>implementation-plan.md: waves, task breakdown, token estimates (ORDER)</item>
      <item>TASK-XXX-*.md: executable tasks (EXECUTE)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="When to Write a Design Doc">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write a design doc when a feature touches 5+ files, changes a DB schema, modifies an API contract, introduces cross-service dependencies, or has security implications.</statement>
      <rationale>Design docs prevent the most expensive failure modes: incompatible implementations from parallel agents, undocumented architectural decisions re-litigated later, and security issues discovered post-implementation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Required: 5+ files touched, DB schema change, API contract modification, cross-service dependency, security-sensitive change</item>
      <item>Optional: refactoring with no interface changes (maybe if architecture changes)</item>
      <item>Skip: bug fix 1-2 files, small feature 1-2 files no arch impact, single task under ~5k tokens, greenfield spike</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="SDD-Optimized Design Structure">
    <list>
      <item>Reference Documents: links to spec, constitution, related designs</item>
      <item>Spec Coverage: FR-X to AD-X traceability matrix</item>
      <item>Architectural Decisions: AD-X blocks with rationale and alternatives</item>
      <item>File Structure: exact files to create/modify with patterns</item>
      <item>Data Models: database schemas, TypeScript types, Pydantic models</item>
      <item>API Contracts: endpoints with request/response/error examples</item>
      <item>Dependencies: packages and external services</item>
      <item>Security Considerations: auth, validation, encryption</item>
      <item>Performance Considerations: caching, optimization, scaling</item>
      <item>Testing Strategy: unit, integration, E2E approach</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="AD-X Decision Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every AD-X must have: Status, Context, Decision, Rationale, Alternatives Considered table, and Consequences; mark Status as Proposed until human-approved.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents must not implement Proposed decisions. The Alternatives Considered table prevents the decision from becoming pseudo-documentation — without it, the document records a conclusion without reasoning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### AD-001: Use Pydantic for Validation

**Status:** Accepted
**Context:** Need request/response validation with automatic error messages.
**Decision:** Use Pydantic v2 models for all request/response validation.
**Rationale:**
- Native FastAPI integration
- Automatic error message generation with field-level detail
**Alternatives Considered:**
| Alternative | Pros | Cons | Why Rejected |
|-------------|------|------|--------------|
| marshmallow | Mature, flexible | Manual integration | More boilerplate |
| Do nothing | No new dep | No validation | Blocks FR-001 |
**Consequences:**
- Positive: type safety, automatic docs generation
- Negative: Pydantic v2 migration required for existing models
**Traces to:** FR-001, FR-002
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <p>Y-statement concise form: "In the context of [use case], facing [concern], we decided for [option] to achieve [quality], accepting [downside]."</p>
  </section>
</text>
