<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Learning Speed as Competitive Moat Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Learning Speed as Competitive Moat plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="explicit-belief-tracking" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The org MUST maintain a versioned register of active product beliefs (assumption, confidence, source, last-updated); beliefs older than 90 days without update MUST be flagged.</statement>
      <rationale source="Annie Duke — Thinking in Bets (2018)">Implicit beliefs cannot be updated; without a register the org cannot tell whether it is learning or repeating yesterday's bets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="outside-view-required-per-decision" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every strategic decision MUST cite at least one outside-view input (competitor move, market data, customer signal) alongside any inside-view reasoning.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kahneman — Thinking, Fast and Slow">Inside-view-only decisions cluster on the loudest voice; outside view is the structural counter to founder narrative gravity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="decision-journal-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every reversible decision MUST be logged in a decision journal with date, alternatives considered, expected outcome, and review date; review-date no-shows are a tracked metric.</statement>
      <rationale source="Shane Parrish — Farnam Street decision journal">Without a journal, hindsight bias rewrites past decisions to look smart; the journal is the only feedback loop for calibration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kill-criteria-pre-registered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every product bet MUST have pre-registered kill criteria (signal threshold + observation window); bets without kill criteria are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Eric Ries — The Lean Startup">Without kill criteria, sunk-cost reasoning keeps bets alive past their evidence window; pre-registration is the only structural gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="weekly-belief-update-ritual" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The org MUST hold a weekly 30-minute belief-update ritual where each bet's confidence is re-scored against the week's signals; missed weeks count against the moat.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — competitive cycle audit 2026-Q1">Beliefs that update on a yearly planning cycle are slower than competitor cycles; weekly is the minimum cadence to compound a learning moat.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
