<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Learning Velocity Framework">
  <summary>The learning-speed moat model: signal collection, versioned belief tracking, weekly rituals, and the decision-log practice that compounds the advantage over time.</summary>

  <section title="Core Formula">
    <p>Learning Velocity = (Signals Noticed x Update Speed x Execution Quality) / Time. Each factor is addressable: signal collection is automated; update speed is increased by weekly reviews instead of quarterly; execution quality is maintained via the belief-update constraint (mutate only on sufficient evidence).</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Treat beliefs.yaml as code: versioned in git, PR-reviewed, diffable. PR-reviewed belief changes beat Slack-thread consensus.</statement>
      <rationale>Beliefs that live in Notion pages or Slack threads drift without audit trail. A versioned YAML file makes every belief change visible, attributable, and reversible.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Signal Collection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit the watchlist: 3–5 competitors, 1 macro trend, 1 customer segment. Broader scope equals noise, not signal.</statement>
      <rationale>AI can ingest thousands of signals per day; without a bounded watchlist the team drowns in volume and stops acting on any of it. Constraint is the design.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Ingest at least one external corpus (product analytics or competitor scrape). A system fed only internal Slack channels measures its own opinion velocity, not the market.</statement>
      <rationale>Confirmation loops where the same channel provides signals and classification are invisible and common. External corpus is the mitigation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Belief Update Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Mutate a belief only if (a) 3 or more independent event_ids agree, or (b) 1 high-severity event directly contradicts the current claim with a cited URL or transcript.</statement>
      <rationale>Single data points are noise; three independent signals from different sources constitute evidence. The threshold prevents recency over-weighting and Sonnet evidence-laundering.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every belief with a kill criterion and a check-back date. Beliefs without falsifiers rot into dogma.</statement>
      <rationale>A belief that cannot be falsified is not a belief — it is an assumption. Kill criteria and check-back dates force the team to revisit rather than defend.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Synthesizer generating insights at digest-of-digest-of-digest compression, losing original wording.</description>
      <reason>Re-grounding every synthesizer run on the raw events.ndjson is mandatory. Previous digests anchor on prior framing and lose the original signal over time.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Decision Logging">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure decisions made per week crossed with decisions reversed within 30 days. High reversal rate indicates a noisy loop; low decision count indicates an inert org.</statement>
      <rationale>Insights captured is a vanity metric. Decision count and decision stability are the actual outputs of a functioning learning system.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Run quarterly calibration: grade past predictions against outcomes. Recalibrate confidence weights and prompt scoring rubrics based on accuracy.</statement>
      <rationale>Without calibration, confidence weights become superstition. Calibration is not optional — it is the mechanism that prevents the belief system from drifting from reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Weekly Rituals">
    <p>Monday: customer interview insights shared. Wednesday: competitor updates reviewed. Friday: experiment results analyzed and strategy adjustments communicated. Time-box rituals: Monday 30 min digest, Friday 45 min strategy. Drift past those times and people skip.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Default to "kill" on the Friday review for evidence-thin roadmap items. Burden of proof is on keeping, not killing.</statement>
      <rationale>Keeping an item with thin evidence consumes H1 capacity. The asymmetric default (keep requires evidence, kill does not) prevents roadmap accumulation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
