<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="success-metrics-definition Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for success-metrics-definition as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Too many metrics (10+ KPIs tracked on the same dashboard)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Focus diffuses; teams cannot optimize for everything. 3-5 primary KPIs force prioritization.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>No North Star (multiple competing metrics treated as equally important)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Organizational misalignment; marketing optimizes for acquisition while product optimizes for retention, with no shared direction.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Vanity metrics (total signups ever, total users ever, total revenue ever)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>These only go up; they don't tell you if current cohorts are healthy. Track cohort retention and weekly active instead.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>No targets or baselines</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Metrics become decorations; teams don't know if performance is good or bad. "Retention is 60%" — is that success or failure? Without a target, no one knows.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Undefined metrics (ambiguous definitions like "active user")</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Different teams count differently; the metric becomes meaningless. Define edge cases.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>AARRR framework maps poorly to B2B enterprise products with long sales cycles</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>For B2B, adapt: Awareness (brand study), Consideration (demo requests), Decision (contracts signed), Adoption (usage depth), Expansion (upsell). The principle stays the same.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
