<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="feature-discovery Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for feature-discovery. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Collect feature ideas from all four source types before scoring: Customer Research (interviews, support tickets, churn conversations, NPS detractors), Usage Analytics (adoption rates, drop-off points, error rates), Competitive Analysis (competitor features and gaps, negative reviews), Market Trends (industry reports, technology and regulatory changes).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-source discovery creates blind spots; analytics reveal what users do but not why; interviews reveal why but not how often; competitive analysis reveals expectations but not differentiation opportunities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap the candidate list at 20 items per discovery cycle — scoring 50+ features creates decision paralysis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A list longer than 20 means the collection phase wasn't selective enough; the scoring step becomes a distraction rather than a decision tool.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Categorize each feature into one of four Kano types: Must-have (basic expectations; absence causes dissatisfaction), Performance (more = more satisfaction), Delight/Excitement (unexpected; creates delight if present), Indifferent (customers don't care). Build Must-haves before Delighters.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Delighters built on a shaky Must-have foundation fail to retain customers; users who can't log in are not impressed by AI suggestions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score each feature: Opportunity = Importance + max(Importance - Satisfaction, 0). Scale Importance and Satisfaction 1-10. High opportunity = high importance AND low satisfaction. Flag any score above 10 as high priority.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Features users find highly important but poorly served by current solutions are the highest-value targets; the formula penalizes well-served needs and rewards underserved ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Compute RICE = (Reach x Impact x Confidence) / Effort. Reach = users per quarter; Impact = 0.25/0.5/1/2/3; Confidence = 50%/80%/100%; Effort = person-weeks. Sort descending; validate top 3 before committing to build.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">RICE prevents high-effort low-reach features from crowding out low-effort high-reach features; the confidence multiplier forces honest assessment of evidence quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Validate top-RICE features before committing: Fake door test (low effort, medium confidence), Prototype (medium effort, high confidence), Wizard of Oz (medium effort, high confidence), Limited beta (high effort, very high confidence), Pre-sales (medium effort, very high confidence).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">RICE scoring is based on estimates; pre-build validation with real users replaces estimates with behavioral evidence before engineering investment begins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Separate "what customers ask for" from "what job they need done" before writing any feature spec. Request: "export to Excel" — Job: "share data with my finance team."</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Building the stated request often misses better solutions to the underlying job; understanding the job opens a wider solution space.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
