<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples-and-antipatterns" title="Feature Discovery Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Two worked examples (SaaS dashboard, mobile app DAU) and six common mistakes with concrete fixes.</summary>

  <section title="Example: SaaS Dashboard Clutter">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Problem: dashboard too cluttered, key metrics buried. Discovery: 15 interviews ("what do you look for first?"), analytics (80% of users view only 3 of 12 widgets), 23 support tickets requesting simpler view. Features identified with RICE: Customizable dashboard (1200), Focus mode (900), Saved views (600). Validation: prototype test with 10 users, 8/10 preferred simplified view. Decision: build Focus mode first — highest RICE, lowest effort.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example: Mobile App Low DAU">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Problem: low daily active users after download. Discovery: churn interviews ("I forget the app exists"), analytics (90% never enable notifications), competitor analysis (push notifications with value). Features by Opportunity Score: Smart notifications (16), Daily digest (12), Widget for home screen (10). Decision: A/B test notification types first, then build widget.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Building every feature request without prioritization.</description>
      <reason>Feature bloat reduces the product's core value proposition; every added feature increases maintenance cost and user confusion.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No validation step between RICE scoring and engineering commitment.</description>
      <reason>RICE scores are estimates; without behavioral validation, the team builds on assumptions, not evidence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Copying a competitor feature without understanding why they built it.</description>
      <reason>A competitor feature may exist for a different customer segment or job; copying it without context wastes effort and may confuse your users.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Weighting feature requests equally regardless of customer segment value.</description>
      <reason>A feature requested by 50 free-tier users may be less valuable than one requested by 5 enterprise customers; segment value must factor into prioritization.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Generating RICE confidence scores without explicit evidence assessment.</description>
      <reason>Agent-generated confidence scores are opinions, not evidence assessments; confidence must reflect the quality and quantity of actual validation data collected.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Distinctions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate "what customers ask for" from "what job they need done" before writing any feature spec. Request: "export to Excel" — Job: "share data with my finance team."</statement>
      <rationale>Building the stated request often misses better solutions to the underlying job; understanding the job opens a wider solution space.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/prompt-extract-features.txt">LLM prompt to extract feature candidates from support tickets</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-opportunity-score.txt">LLM prompt to compute Opportunity Scores</reference>
</text>
