<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="feature-discovery Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for feature-discovery as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Building every feature request without prioritization.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feature bloat reduces the product's core value proposition; every added feature increases maintenance cost and user confusion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>No validation step between RICE scoring and engineering commitment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>RICE scores are estimates; without behavioral validation, the team builds on assumptions, not evidence.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Copying a competitor feature without understanding why they built it.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A competitor feature may exist for a different customer segment or job; copying it without context wastes effort and may confuse your users.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Weighting feature requests equally regardless of customer segment value.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A feature requested by 50 free-tier users may be less valuable than one requested by 5 enterprise customers; segment value must factor into prioritization.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Generating RICE confidence scores without explicit evidence assessment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent-generated confidence scores are opinions, not evidence assessments; confidence must reflect the quality and quantity of actual validation data collected.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
