<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="stakeholder-management Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for stakeholder-management as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM hallucinating stakeholders that "should" exist for a project type ("Compliance Officer", "Data Privacy Lead") without a source.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require the model to cite an actual source — meeting notes, org chart, CODEOWNERS — before adding a row. Hallucinated stakeholders lead to wasted engagement cycles on non-existent relationships.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Models defaulting to Supporter for attitude when asked "is this exec a supporter?" because of sycophantic training.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force the model to mark Unknown unless evidence is cited; the stakeholder-lint.py script enforces this at commit time. Unknown attitudes must be resolved through 1:1 conversation, not LLM inference.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Power/interest classifications inferred from title alone in a matrix org where a "Senior Manager" has more real influence than a "VP".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feed actual org-chart text or interview snippets rather than job titles. Title-based classification is wrong in consensus-driven and matrix orgs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Cron-driven weekly stakeholder sentiment scan of Slack messages auto-escalating on mis-classified Resistor signals.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Queue sentiment findings for human review, never auto-escalate. A false Resistor classification triggering an escalation can damage a relationship the system was meant to protect.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Long-context dumps of the full register into every agent prompt, wasting tokens and leaking PII to downstream agents.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pass only the relevant slice (one quadrant, or one engagement tier) to each agent. The register as a whole is a program-management artifact, not an agent context blob.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Register rot: the doc is built once at project kick-off and never updated.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>By month 3, the named exec sponsor has left the company and the register still drives the weekly update email. Tie register review to the same cadence as roadmap review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Power/interest grids hide attitude: a high-power stakeholder coded as "Manage Closely" but secretly a Resistor.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always carry an explicit attitude column (Supporter / Neutral / Resistor) and color it. Attitude is the third dimension the grid cannot show.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Communication-plan theatre: an elaborate matrix that nobody actually executes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If the PM isn't running the weekly sync the matrix promises, the matrix is a lie. Reduce cadence to what will actually happen.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Over-engagement of Low Power, Low Interest stakeholders out of politeness.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Burns PM cycles and dilutes signal. The whole point of the grid is to deprioritize. Manage this quadrant with periodic check-ins, not active engagement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>One-way "stakeholder updates" treated as engagement: a newsletter is information, not engagement.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Engagement requires bidirectional input loops (decisions, feedback, escalation paths). Frame updates as such, not as engagement substitutes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-cultural blind spots: Power is more diffuse in matrix orgs and consensus-driven cultures.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A simple grid encodes a Western-corporate hierarchy assumption. Annotate, don't auto-trust. Feed actual org-chart data instead of inferring from titles.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
