<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules-and-gotchas" title="Stakeholder Management: Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Register-rot prevention rules, decision-log pairing requirement, agent safety constraints, and AI-agent failure modes with mitigations.</summary>

  <section title="Register Health Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tie register review to the same cadence as roadmap review (quarterly minimum). Never let the PM update the register unilaterally — refresh as a 30-minute team meeting so others can flag attitude shifts the PM misses.</statement>
      <rationale>Register rot is the most common failure: a doc built at kick-off stays unchanged while the exec sponsor leaves, attitudes shift, and new blockers emerge. Team review catches changes no single person sees.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain a "former stakeholders" archive, not just the current list. When someone moves on, record exit and reason — never delete the row. Future PMs need the context.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholder history informs future relationship-building. Knowing why a previous exec became a resistor prevents repeating the same mistake with their successor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair the register with a decision log. Each Partner-tier stakeholder must appear in the decision log monthly or be downgraded. Engagement that does not produce decisions is theater.</statement>
      <rationale>A stakeholder coded as "Partner" but absent from decision records is actually receiving "Inform"-level engagement. The decision log makes the gap visible before the relationship deteriorates.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Safety Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never let an agent autonomously change a stakeholder's engagement level from Partner to Informed. Changing someone's engagement level is a relationship downgrade with political consequences. Agent suggests, human approves.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated downgrade of a Partner-tier stakeholder to Informed can read as a snub or signal of project de-prioritization. The consequences are relationship damage that cannot be undone with a follow-up email.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run password-scrubber-agent or equivalent before committing any register or comms-plan artifact. Registers contain personal contact details, internal email addresses, sometimes phone numbers. Never let a register land in a public repo without scrubbing.</statement>
      <rationale>PII leakage via stakeholder registers is a GDPR and internal-trust risk. Agents push to git and it becomes public without a scrubbing step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For external/customer stakeholders, separate the register from any marketing CRM. Cross-link by ID, never duplicate contact data.</statement>
      <rationale>Duplicated customer lists in the register and CRM drift out of sync. When opt-out status changes in the CRM, the unlinked register continues to drive communications to opted-out users.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM hallucinating stakeholders that "should" exist for a project type ("Compliance Officer", "Data Privacy Lead") without a source.</description>
      <reason>Require the model to cite an actual source — meeting notes, org chart, CODEOWNERS — before adding a row. Hallucinated stakeholders lead to wasted engagement cycles on non-existent relationships.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Models defaulting to Supporter for attitude when asked "is this exec a supporter?" because of sycophantic training.</description>
      <reason>Force the model to mark Unknown unless evidence is cited; the stakeholder-lint.py script enforces this at commit time. Unknown attitudes must be resolved through 1:1 conversation, not LLM inference.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Power/interest classifications inferred from title alone in a matrix org where a "Senior Manager" has more real influence than a "VP".</description>
      <reason>Feed actual org-chart text or interview snippets rather than job titles. Title-based classification is wrong in consensus-driven and matrix orgs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Cron-driven weekly stakeholder sentiment scan of Slack messages auto-escalating on mis-classified Resistor signals.</description>
      <reason>Queue sentiment findings for human review, never auto-escalate. A false Resistor classification triggering an escalation can damage a relationship the system was meant to protect.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Long-context dumps of the full register into every agent prompt, wasting tokens and leaking PII to downstream agents.</description>
      <reason>Pass only the relevant slice (one quadrant, or one engagement tier) to each agent. The register as a whole is a program-management artifact, not an agent context blob.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/stakeholder-lint.py">Lint register for rot patterns: unknown attitudes, missing owners, high-power under-engagement</reference>
</text>
