<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="scrum-ceremonies Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for scrum-ceremonies as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Ceremony theatre — team runs events but DoR/DoD discipline and action follow-through are missing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Ceremonies without underlying discipline produce the appearance of Scrum without the inspect-and-adapt value. Agents that only schedule and notify reinforce theatre by making it effortless.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Standup as management reporting — standup updates go to a manager dashboard, not the team channel.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Reporting-oriented standups shift power from the self-organizing team to the manager, eroding psychological safety and turning the event into a performance rather than a coordination mechanism.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Retros without action follow-through — same actions appear sprint after sprint with no resolution.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Repeated unresolved actions signal that the team does not believe retro actions will change anything. Trust in the retro collapses; teams stop contributing honestly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>PO convergence in planning poker — PO names a number first and team votes to match it.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Authority-anchored poker produces uniform votes from the first round. No disagreement means no discussion, which means the only person whose estimate was real was the PO — poker served no purpose.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Async blocker rot — a blocker is posted in standup, no one responds, it ages past 24 hours in a thread.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unresolved async blockers compound daily. A 24-hour blocker in a 10-day sprint consumes 10% of capacity silently. Hard limit: blocker older than 1 working day must trigger a sync or escalation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
