<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>
  <section name="tool-integration">
    <summary>fzf/bat/fd cross-wiring, delta git integration, starship config, zoxide usage, and agent gotchas.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Wire all three: fzf uses fd as its file source and bat for previews; this creates a compound tool where Ctrl+T shows file previews with syntax highlighting.</statement>
      <rationale>fzf's default file source (find) is slow and noisy. fd is 5-10x faster and respects .gitignore. bat previews eliminate the need to open files just to check their content while browsing.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section name="fzf-wiring">
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# ~/.bashrc — fzf integration block (after fzf installation)
eval "$(fzf --bash)"

# Use fd as the default file source (faster, respects .gitignore)
export FZF_DEFAULT_COMMAND='fd --type f --hidden --follow \
    --exclude .git --exclude node_modules --exclude .venv --exclude __pycache__'

export FZF_CTRL_T_COMMAND="$FZF_DEFAULT_COMMAND"
export FZF_CTRL_T_OPTS="--preview 'bat --color=always --style=numbers --line-range=:300 {}'"

# Alt+C: directory jump with eza preview
export FZF_ALT_C_COMMAND='fd --type d --hidden --follow --exclude .git'
export FZF_ALT_C_OPTS="--preview 'eza --tree --level=2 --color=always {}'"
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <reference path="templates/fzf-config.sh">fzf shell integration block with bat preview, fd file source, and helper functions</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="delta-integration">
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="ini"><![CDATA[
# ~/.gitconfig — delta as git pager
[core]
    pager = delta

[interactive]
    diffFilter = delta --color-only

[delta]
    navigate = true
    side-by-side = true
    line-numbers = true
    syntax-theme = TwoDark
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="starship-zoxide">
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# ~/.bashrc — add at the end (after other exports)
# starship: replaces PS1 prompt
eval "$(starship init bash)"

# zoxide: frecency-based cd replacement
eval "$(zoxide init bash)"
# Usage: z foo     -> cd to most visited directory matching 'foo'
#        zi foo    -> interactive pick with fzf
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <reference path="templates/starship.toml">Minimal server-optimized starship config: hostname on SSH, git status, fast scan timeout</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <rule>
        <statement>In agent-generated scripts that run in CI or headless environments, never use aliases or modern tools without checking for their existence first.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents writing scripts often assume the developer environment. Scripts that call bat, eza, or fd without existence checks fail on minimal containers, CI runners, or servers where only apt defaults are installed.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Adding eval $(starship init bash) to a non-interactive shell init file like /etc/environment or a service ExecStartPre.</description>
        <reason>starship requires an interactive TTY. Running it in non-interactive contexts (systemd services, cron jobs) either fails silently or adds unusable ANSI escape codes to the environment.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Overriding cat with bat globally in scripts that parse command output.</description>
        <reason>bat adds ANSI color codes and paging that break programmatic parsing. Gate the alias with command -v and use \cat or command cat in scripts to bypass it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
  </section>
</text>
