<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Customer Testimonials and Social Proof Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Customer Testimonials and Social Proof application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-named-attribution" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every testimonial MUST carry full name + role + company + real photo. Initials-only or stock-photo testimonials halve conversion impact and are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Credibility signals are cumulative; anonymous attribution reduces believability regardless of quote quality.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-ask-at-peak-satisfaction" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Asks MUST fire immediately after a measurable customer win, not at fixed time intervals. Asks at week-N are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Peak satisfaction is time-limited; users 3 weeks post-win are no longer emotionally connected.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-cta-proximity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>≥1 testimonial MUST sit within visual proximity (above-fold or adjacent) of every primary CTA on the landing page. Bottom-only placement is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Testimonials reduce purchase anxiety at the decision moment; bottom-only placement helps only the already-decided.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-result-specific-quote" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quotes MUST contain a specific result (number, before→after, or named outcome). Generic praise ('great product') is stripped.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Result-specific quotes lift CVR measurably; generic praise has near-zero conversion impact.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-annual-refresh" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every testimonial MUST carry a refresh_date ≤ 12 months old at publication time. Older quotes are flagged stale and pulled.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Stale testimonials signal an inactive customer base; prospects notice date drift.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
