<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-collection-process" title="Testimonial Collection Process">
  <summary>Optimal timing to ask, structured question templates, follow-up sequence, and video testimonial approach.</summary>

  <section title="When to Ask">
    <rule>
      <statement>Ask for testimonials immediately after a measurable win — not at a fixed interval after purchase.</statement>
      <rationale>Peak satisfaction is time-limited. Users who achieved a milestone 3 weeks ago are no longer emotionally connected to the win. The moment after a first result is the highest-response moment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>After first win: fresh excitement, highest response rate</item>
      <item>After milestone reached: quantifiable result available</item>
      <item>After support resolution: gratitude moment</item>
      <item>After renewal: long-term satisfaction signal</item>
      <item>After referral: customer is already advocating</item>
    </list>
    <note>Follow up twice (Day 5, Day 10) after the initial ask. Response rate increases from ~15% to ~35% with two follow-ups. Three follow-ups show diminishing returns and risk relationship damage.</note>
  </section>

  <section title="Ask Questions That Produce Usable Quotes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Ask specific questions in the testimonial request, not open-ended ones. "What result did you achieve?" produces better copy than "How do you like the product?"</statement>
      <rationale>Customers default to vague praise ("It's great!") when given an open field. Specific questions unlock specific results ("saved 10 hours/week") that are actually persuasive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>"What was happening before you found us?" → relatable struggle</item>
      <item>"What specific result have you achieved?" → quantifiable proof</item>
      <item>"What would you tell someone considering [Product]?" → direct recommendation</item>
      <item>"What surprised you about using [Product]?" → unexpected benefit</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/request-email-sequence.txt">3-email ask sequence with guiding questions</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Video Testimonial Collection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Offer a specific incentive for video testimonials and provide the question list in advance. Without preparation, video testimonials are rambling and unusable.</statement>
      <rationale>Customers feel awkward on camera without preparation. Sending the 7 questions in advance lets them prepare a clear, confident response. The incentive signals the value you place on their time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>1. Tell me about your role and what you do.</item>
      <item>2. What problem were you trying to solve?</item>
      <item>3. What had you tried before?</item>
      <item>4. What made you choose [Product]?</item>
      <item>5. Walk me through how you use it.</item>
      <item>6. What results have you seen?</item>
      <item>7. What would you tell someone considering [Product]?</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
