<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-strengthening-and-display" title="Quote Strengthening and Display Antipatterns">
  <summary>Weak-to-strong transformation formula, approval workflow, and antipatterns that destroy testimonial credibility.</summary>

  <section title="Quote Transformation Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Transform weak quotes by adding specificity: [specific number] + [specific outcome] + [timeframe]. Never invent numbers — only add specificity the customer confirms.</statement>
      <rationale>Specific testimonials ("40% more signups in 30 days") convert; vague ones ("really helpful") do not. But fabricating specifics that the customer did not confirm is a credibility-destroying risk if exposed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"Great product!" — No specificity. No result. Not persuasive to any prospect.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>"We increased signups by 40% in 30 days. Our team now spends time on strategy, not spreadsheets." — Specific metric, timeframe, outcome. Persuasive to prospects with the same problem.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Get written approval on every edited or transformed quote before publishing. Track approval status per quote in a CRM field.</statement>
      <rationale>Publishing a transformed quote without approval creates legal exposure and trust damage. All testimonial approval must be a manual human checkpoint — it cannot be automated.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scaling Testimonial Collection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize testimonials from customers who match the ICP of your target buyer. A testimonial from a 5-person startup does not resonate with enterprise buyers.</statement>
      <rationale>Social proof is most effective when the testimonial source is similar to the prospect. Mismatched testimonials create negative signals ("this product is not for companies like mine").</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Set up post-purchase request automation via Customer.io or Delighted</item>
      <item>Trigger ask on NPS score 9-10 via Delighted webhook</item>
      <item>Track testimonial inventory and refresh stale quotes annually</item>
      <item>Build a case study pipeline for high-value customers (3+ months post-purchase)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using fake or heavily fabricated testimonials.</description>
      <reason>Catastrophically reputationally damaging if exposed. Only use real, approved quotes from real customers. Zero exceptions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Placing all testimonials in a single section at the bottom of the page.</description>
      <reason>Users who reach the bottom are already past the primary decision points. Testimonials below the fold assist only the most motivated readers, not the majority who abandon earlier.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Publishing stale testimonials (from customers who have churned, with old company logos, outdated roles).</description>
      <reason>Stale testimonials signal an inactive customer base. Prospects notice date signals. Refresh testimonials annually.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using only one format of social proof (only quotes, no logos, no numbers, no case studies).</description>
      <reason>Different proof types resonate with different buyers at different stages. A single format leaves trust-building opportunities on the table.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
