<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Scope Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the scope-management methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="exclusions-before-inclusions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write exclusions before inclusions in every scope statement.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field experience">Explicit 'not in scope' prevents 80% of scope disputes; ambiguity resolves toward whatever the stakeholder assumed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ac-per-must" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every must-have requirement needs a verifiable, non-tautological acceptance criterion before baselining.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK; field experience">Requirements without AC are unverifiable; tautological ACs destroy the gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="baseline-then-cr" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Baseline scope at end of planning; every subsequent change goes through Change Control with cost/schedule/risk delta.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK 7 scope domain">Without a baseline, every change becomes a negotiation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rtm-in-source-control" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store the RTM as YAML or CSV in source control, not as a Word document.</statement>
      <rationale source="Configuration management practice">Word-doc RTMs become orphaned after sprint 2; source control gives diffs and survives tool migrations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="must-cap-60" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply a quota: no more than 60% of requirements may be 'Must'.</statement>
      <rationale source="MoSCoW practice">Without a cap, stakeholders mark everything Must and scope becomes uncontrollable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="must-never-wont" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A Must requirement must never have status 'Won't'.</statement>
      <rationale source="MoSCoW practice">This combination means the project will fail by definition; force a sponsor decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="freeze-text-diff-edits" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Freeze canonical requirement text and require diff-based edits; agents must not regenerate from scratch.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — agent-RTM audits">Regeneration produces new IDs and wording — breaking all downstream traceability links.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Continuous-discovery agile product — use rolling outcomes instead of scope baselines</item>
      <item>Pure research / spike work where scope is the question</item>
      <item>Internal tools with fewer than 10 users where formal sign-off is theater</item>
      <item>Crisis incident response — scope is 'stop the bleeding'</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
