<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-scope-framework" title="Scope Management Framework">
  <summary>Five-step process for defining, baselining, validating, and controlling project scope to prevent uncontrolled expansion.</summary>

  <section title="Core Concepts">
    <list>
      <item>Product Scope — features and functions of the deliverable</item>
      <item>Project Scope — all work required to deliver the product scope</item>
      <item>Scope Baseline — approved scope statement + WBS + WBS dictionary</item>
      <item>Scope Creep — expansion without formal approval; always has cost and schedule impact</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Write exclusions before inclusions in every scope statement.</statement>
      <rationale>Explicit "not in scope" clauses prevent 80% of scope disputes because ambiguity resolves in the direction of whatever the stakeholder assumed was included.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Requirement Types">
    <p>Collect and classify requirements before writing the scope statement:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Business — why the project exists (e.g., "increase revenue 20%")</item>
      <item>Stakeholder — what each stakeholder needs ("executive dashboard")</item>
      <item>Solution/Functional — system capabilities ("calculates order totals automatically")</item>
      <item>Transition — change management, data migration, training</item>
      <item>Non-Functional — performance, security, usability constraints</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every must-have requirement needs a verifiable acceptance criterion before baselining.</statement>
      <rationale>Requirements without AC are unverifiable. Tautological ACs ("system shall display the page when the page is displayed") must be rejected; force concrete, testable conditions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scope Control">
    <rule>
      <statement>Baseline scope at end of planning; every subsequent change goes through Change Control with cost/schedule/risk delta.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a baseline there is no objective reference — every change claim becomes a negotiation. Baseline freezes the reference; changes are measured against it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture every "while you're at it" request as a formal Change Request; never absorb silently.</statement>
      <rationale>Silent absorption is the primary mechanism of gold-plating. Making every addition visible creates an audit trail and forces trade-off decisions before work starts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Verbal scope agreements without written scope statement sign-off.</description>
      <reason>Undocumented promises are interpreted differently by each party. At project end, everyone argues about what was supposed to be built based on their memory.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Vague scope language: "make it better", "improve performance".</description>
      <reason>Vague scope cannot be accepted, rejected, or measured. Every acceptance criterion must have a numeric or observable condition.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Scope Creep Prevention">
    <list>
      <item>Written scope statement with sponsor sign-off</item>
      <item>Formal Change Control process communicated at kickoff</item>
      <item>Stakeholder sign-off on scope before development starts</item>
      <item>Regular scope baseline reviews at phase gates</item>
      <item>Professional "no" process: acknowledge → explain scope constraint → offer alternative (future phase) → document decision</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/scope-statement.md">Scope statement with deliverables, boundaries, constraints, assumptions</reference>
    <reference path="templates/requirements-doc.md">Requirements document with all requirement types and MoSCoW priorities</reference>
  </section>
</text>
