<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-traceability" title="Requirements Traceability">
  <summary>RTM structure, MoSCoW invariants, and agent-specific gotchas for requirements extraction and traceability maintenance.</summary>

  <section title="Traceability Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store the RTM as YAML or CSV in source control, not as a Word document.</statement>
      <rationale>An RTM that lives in a Word doc becomes orphaned after sprint 2. Source-control storage means agents and humans can edit it, diffs are reviewable, and it survives tool migrations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Every row in the RTM must carry: requirement ID, source stakeholder, design reference, code reference, test reference, and current status. A must-have requirement missing any of these is a gap.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
- id: FR-01
  type: functional
  statement: "System calculates order totals automatically on item add/remove"
  priority: must
  source: "Sales Manager (interview 2026-04-01)"
  acceptance_criteria: "Order total updates within 200ms with no page reload"
  design_ref: "design/checkout-flow.md#totals"
  code_ref: "src/cart/calculator.py"
  test_ref: "tests/test_cart.py::test_total_update"
  status: done
]]></code>
      <note>UUIDs or content-hash IDs prevent renumbering when requirements are regenerated by agents.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="MoSCoW Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply a quota: no more than 60% of requirements may be "Must".</statement>
      <rationale>Without a cap, stakeholders mark everything Must and scope becomes uncontrollable. A 60% Must quota forces explicit prioritization trade-offs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Must — delivery-blocking; project fails if absent; requires AC and owner</item>
      <item>Should — high value but not delivery-blocking; could move to phase 2</item>
      <item>Could — nice-to-have; absorbed only if capacity permits after Must and Should</item>
      <item>Won't — explicitly deferred or excluded; prevents "assumed in scope" disputes</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>A Must requirement must never have status "Won't".</statement>
      <rationale>This combination means the project will fail by definition. Detect early and force a sponsor decision: descope the Must or cancel the project.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/moscow-lint.py">Enforce MoSCoW invariants (no MUST without AC, no MUST+Wont)</reference>
    <reference path="scripts/trace-check.py">Flag must-have requirements missing design/test coverage</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Freeze canonical requirement text and require diff-based edits; do not regenerate from scratch.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs paraphrase requirements into different wording on each pass. Regenerating produces a new document with different IDs and wording — breaking all downstream traceability links.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Force "priority" as a required JSON field in extraction prompts; agents silently drop it otherwise</item>
      <item>Tautological ACs ("system shall work correctly when it works correctly") must be rejected by the validator</item>
      <item>Agent-extracted requirements drop source stakeholder attribution — require it as a non-nullable field</item>
      <item>For regulated work, agents must not redact source quotes from RTM; auditors need original wording</item>
      <item>Gold-plating: cap NFR generation to requirements with an explicit named source — reject agent-invented NFRs</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
