<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ba-strategic-partnership Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ba-strategic-partnership. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score each requirements artifact on six axes (0-5): problem_clarity, outcome_orientation, evidence_grounding, enterprise_scope, partner_voice, kill_criterion. Auto-block if any axis scores below 2 OR if kill_criterion scores below 1.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a kill criterion a "strategic partner" who cannot say when to stop is just a louder order-taker; this is the single most important axis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Scan for these verbatim phrases before the LLM review; any hit is a guaranteed partner_voice penalty and triggers a rewrite prompt: "as requested", "as per request", "the user asked for", "please implement", "the stakeholder wants", "please add".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mechanical phrase detection via ripgrep is faster and more consistent than LLM judgment alone; it surfaces the most common order-taker signal without model overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every rewrite must: (1) quote the order-taker phrase verbatim, (2) classify the failure mode, (3) propose a strategic-partner rewrite tied to one of the org's supplied OKRs — never invent a metric not present in org_context.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Rewrites that invent metrics ("reduce churn 12%") without a source are hallucinated outcomes that erode credibility faster than order-taking language.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always require a linked_okr_id on the rewritten artifact; an outcome statement with no parent OKR is still order-taking, just dressed up.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">OKR linkage is the only way to verify that the rewrite serves a real strategic objective rather than a BA-invented priority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep the stance reviewer separate from the rewriter prompt. Two passes, one model: pass 1 judges; pass 2 rewrites. Judging-while-generating dilutes both outputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A model instructed to simultaneously evaluate and rewrite tends to rationalize the original language rather than surface the real failure mode.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
