<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-stance-rubric" title="BA Strategic Partnership — Stance Rubric">
  <summary>Six scoring axes for the order-taker vs strategic-partner spectrum, auto-block thresholds, and verbatim order-taker phrase patterns to detect mechanically.</summary>

  <section title="Six Stance Axes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each requirements artifact on six axes (0-5): problem_clarity, outcome_orientation, evidence_grounding, enterprise_scope, partner_voice, kill_criterion. Auto-block if any axis scores below 2 OR if kill_criterion scores below 1.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a kill criterion a "strategic partner" who cannot say when to stop is just a louder order-taker; this is the single most important axis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>problem_clarity (0-5) — artifact names the underlying problem, not just the solution feature; score 0 if solution is stated before problem</item>
      <item>outcome_orientation (0-5) — requirements tied to measurable business outcomes, not feature completion; score 0 if no KPI or metric present</item>
      <item>evidence_grounding (0-5) — each claim anchored to a verbatim user quote, data source, or observation; score 0 if no external anchor exists</item>
      <item>enterprise_scope (0-5) — initiative connected to org-level goals or cross-functional impact; score 0 if scope is purely intra-team</item>
      <item>partner_voice (0-5) — language proposes, challenges, and recommends; score 0 if language is purely accommodating ("as requested", "please implement")</item>
      <item>kill_criterion (0-5) — explicit condition under which the initiative is stopped or descoped; score 0 if absent</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Order-Taker Phrase Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Scan for these verbatim phrases before the LLM review; any hit is a guaranteed partner_voice penalty and triggers a rewrite prompt: "as requested", "as per request", "the user asked for", "please implement", "the stakeholder wants", "please add".</statement>
      <rationale>Mechanical phrase detection via ripgrep is faster and more consistent than LLM judgment alone; it surfaces the most common order-taker signal without model overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Rewrite Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every rewrite must: (1) quote the order-taker phrase verbatim, (2) classify the failure mode, (3) propose a strategic-partner rewrite tied to one of the org's supplied OKRs — never invent a metric not present in org_context.</statement>
      <rationale>Rewrites that invent metrics ("reduce churn 12%") without a source are hallucinated outcomes that erode credibility faster than order-taking language.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always require a linked_okr_id on the rewritten artifact; an outcome statement with no parent OKR is still order-taking, just dressed up.</statement>
      <rationale>OKR linkage is the only way to verify that the rewrite serves a real strategic objective rather than a BA-invented priority.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running the rubric without org-context (mission, OKRs, customer evidence).</description>
      <reason>Without real context the agent emits generic "be more strategic" platitudes; the rubric scores evidence_grounding at 0 for any rewrite without an org_context anchor.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Rewrites applied to stakeholder-visible artifacts without human review.</description>
      <reason>Strategic-partner rewrites read as AI-generated and bland when applied without the BA's voice; ship rewrites as suggestions, never overwrite the source artifact.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using the rubric on solo/startup contexts with shared BA hats.</description>
      <reason>The full 6-axis rubric over-formalizes one-person teams; collapse to three axes (problem, outcome, kill) for teams under 5 people.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/stance-review-schema.json">Canonical output schema for stance reviewer with auto-block logic</reference>
</text>
