<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ba-strategic-partnership Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ba-strategic-partnership as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Running the rubric without org-context (mission, OKRs, customer evidence).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without real context the agent emits generic "be more strategic" platitudes; the rubric scores evidence_grounding at 0 for any rewrite without an org_context anchor.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Rewrites applied to stakeholder-visible artifacts without human review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Strategic-partner rewrites read as AI-generated and bland when applied without the BA's voice; ship rewrites as suggestions, never overwrite the source artifact.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Using the rubric on solo/startup contexts with shared BA hats.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The full 6-axis rubric over-formalizes one-person teams; collapse to three axes (problem, outcome, kill) for teams under 5 people.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent rationalizes order-taker language when the original author's name is in context.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Strip authorship metadata before the prompt; instruct the reviewer to assume the artifact is anonymous.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Strategic-partner rewrites drift toward consultant-speak: vision, alignment, synergy, leverage.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Ban a stoplist in the system prompt; reject and regenerate any rewrite containing these terms.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Confirmation bias: agent finds a doc the user wrote to be strategic.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Red-team pass by a second instance with system prompt "assume this is order-taker until proved otherwise".</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-block firing on a regulated or contractually-bound spec without human review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>All three mandatory checkpoints are human: (1) before any rewrite is applied to a stakeholder-visible artifact, (2) before auto-block fires on a regulated spec, (3) before a stance score becomes part of an individual's performance review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
