<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-pace-framework" title="PACE Framework: Platform, Audience, Content, Engagement">
  <summary>Platform selection scorecard, content pillar definitions, and posting frequency targets for the PACE social media growth system.</summary>

  <section title="Platform Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Master ONE platform before adding a second. Choose based on where your ICP already spends time, not where it is easiest to post.</statement>
      <rationale>Follower migration across platforms is slow. Spreading across multiple platforms dilutes content quality and engagement time before momentum is built.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each platform 1-5 on four criteria: ICP audience present, content type match, competitor activity, organic reach potential. Pick the highest scorer.</statement>
      <rationale>Subjective platform preferences lead to choosing the wrong channel. The scorecard forces objective audience-first thinking.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Platform scorecard for B2B SaaS founder: Twitter/X scores 18/20 (strong ICP, text content, active competitors, high organic reach). LinkedIn scores 14/20. Decision: start Twitter/X, add LinkedIn at 6 months.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Choosing a platform because "everyone is on it" or because competitors are there without verifying ICP presence.</description>
      <reason>Competitors being on a platform does not mean your ICP converts there. Audience presence is the only criterion that matters at launch.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Pillars">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define 3-5 content pillars with percentage allocations that sum to 100%. Reserve 10% for behind-the-scenes or personal content.</statement>
      <rationale>Pillars prevent random posting and ensure audience knows what to expect. The 10% personal allocation humanizes the brand and builds trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS founder pillars: Product updates 40%, Industry insights 30%, Building in public 20%, Personal wins/fails 10%. Every content decision maps to a pillar.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Allocate at most 20% of posts to promotion. For accounts under 1K followers, use 95/5 value-to-promo ratio — trust is not yet established.</statement>
      <rationale>Promotional content before trust is built causes unfollows. Value content compounds: followers stay and refer others.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Posting Frequency">
    <rule>
      <statement>Batch content creation into 2-3 hour weekly sessions rather than creating single posts daily. Consistency improves and creative quality is higher in blocks.</statement>
      <rationale>Daily single-post creation leads to inconsistency when other priorities intervene. Batching decouples creation from posting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Twitter/X: minimum 1/day, optimal 3-5/day</item>
      <item>LinkedIn: minimum 3/week, optimal 1/day</item>
      <item>Instagram: minimum 3/week, optimal 1/day feed + daily Stories</item>
      <item>TikTok: minimum 1/day, optimal 3/day</item>
      <item>YouTube: minimum 1/week, optimal 2/week</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/content-calendar.md">Monthly content calendar with pillar distribution and daily posting slots</reference>
  </section>
</text>
