<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-engagement-and-metrics" title="Engagement Strategy and KPI Tracking">
  <summary>The 5-5-5 daily engagement method, engagement rate formula, KPI targets, and failure modes to avoid.</summary>

  <section title="Daily Engagement: 5-5-5 Method">
    <rule>
      <statement>Spend 5 minutes engaging with accounts you follow, 5 minutes replying to comments on your posts, and 5 minutes finding new accounts to engage with — daily.</statement>
      <rationale>For accounts under 10K followers, engagement time drives more growth than posting frequency. If forced to choose, engage over post.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Reply to comments within 1 hour. Ask questions at the end of posts. DM new followers with an authentic message, not a pitch.</statement>
      <rationale>Early comment engagement signals to algorithms that the post is generating conversation, boosting further distribution.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="KPI Targets">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track engagement rate, not follower count, as the primary KPI for the first 6 months. Follower growth is a lagging indicator.</statement>
      <rationale>Engagement rate reveals content quality and audience relevance. Follower count inflates via low-quality follows and does not predict conversion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Engagement rate = (Likes + Comments + Shares) / Impressions * 100. Target: above 3% is good, above 6% is excellent.</statement>
      <rationale>Rates below 1% indicate content-audience mismatch or posting to an unengaged audience. Rates above 3% signal the content resonates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/engagement-tracker.py">Parse platform analytics CSV to compute avg, median, and top post engagement rates</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Spreading across too many platforms in the first 90 days.</description>
      <reason>Dilutes content quality and engagement time before momentum builds on any single platform.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Giving up before 6 months of consistent posting.</description>
      <reason>Audience momentum is non-linear. Most accounts see exponential growth between months 4-8, not in the first 30 days.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using platform analytics only after paying for third-party tools.</description>
      <reason>Native platform analytics are free and sufficient for the first 6 months. Third-party tools add value only when cross-platform reporting becomes necessary.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Repurposing content across platforms verbatim (e.g., Twitter thread copy-pasted to LinkedIn).</description>
      <reason>Each platform has distinct tone, format preferences, and algorithmic requirements. Verbatim cross-posting underperforms platform-native content by a significant margin.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
