<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-workflow" title="BABOK Knowledge Areas — Workflow and Competencies">
  <summary>KA relationships, typical BA workflow sequence for greenfield and change-request contexts, and underlying competencies across all KAs.</summary>

  <section title="Knowledge Area Relationships">
    <p>The six KAs are not sequential — they interact throughout the project lifecycle:</p>
    <list>
      <item>KA-1 (Planning) defines the approach that governs how all other KAs operate.</item>
      <item>KA-2 (Elicitation) and KA-5 (Analysis) feed each other iteratively: elicitation produces raw material, analysis structures and validates it, gaps trigger more elicitation.</item>
      <item>KA-3 (Lifecycle) operates continuously — tracing, maintaining, and approving requirements as they evolve through all other KAs.</item>
      <item>KA-4 (Strategy) provides the current and future state context that KA-2 and KA-5 must operate within.</item>
      <item>KA-6 (Evaluation) assesses the built solution and feeds learnings back into KA-1 and KA-3 for the next cycle.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Typical BA Workflow — Greenfield">
    <rule>
      <statement>For a greenfield engagement, sequence KAs as: KA-1 → KA-4 → KA-2 → KA-5 (model) → KA-3 (prioritize and approve) → KA-5 (design) → build → KA-6.</statement>
      <rationale>Starting without KA-1 produces unplanned elicitation; starting without KA-4 produces requirements disconnected from business strategy. KA-3 between modeling and design ensures only approved requirements enter the design phase.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>KA-1: Plan BA approach, identify stakeholders.</item>
      <item>KA-4: Analyze current state, define future state.</item>
      <item>KA-2: Elicit requirements from stakeholders.</item>
      <item>KA-5: Analyze, model, and validate requirements.</item>
      <item>KA-3: Trace, prioritize, and approve requirements.</item>
      <item>KA-5: Define design options, recommend solution.</item>
      <item>Build: solution implemented.</item>
      <item>KA-6: Evaluate solution, recommend improvements.</item>
      <item>KA-3: Update requirements based on learnings.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Typical BA Workflow — Change Request">
    <rule>
      <statement>For a change request, jump directly to KA-3 (assess the change) and KA-5 (analyze impact on existing requirements). Skip KA-1 and KA-4 unless the change redefines the project scope or strategic goals.</statement>
      <rationale>Repeating full KA sequencing for a scope change wastes time; the existing BA plan and strategy analysis remain valid unless the change is transformational.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Underlying Competencies — All KAs">
    <p>Competencies required across all six knowledge areas:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Analytical — creative thinking, decision making, systems thinking, problem solving.</item>
      <item>Behavioral — ethics, accountability, trustworthiness, adaptability.</item>
      <item>Business — business acumen, industry knowledge, organization knowledge.</item>
      <item>Communication — verbal, written, listening, non-verbal.</item>
      <item>Interaction — facilitation, leadership, teamwork, negotiation.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Routing Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every BA request into one or more KAs before generating any deliverable. Use the KA routing result as shared state that all downstream agents read — never re-classify per task.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping the routing step causes agents to draft KA-5 specs when the actual gap is KA-1 stakeholder mapping; re-classifying per task produces inconsistent results across the pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLMs default to KA-5 (modelling) on any input.</description>
      <reason>Most real project failures are in KA-1 (no stakeholder map) or KA-3 (no traceability). Make the planner explicitly score all 6 KAs before dispatching.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
