<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Aesthetic and Minimalist Design Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Aesthetic and Minimalist Design. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-prioritise-by-usage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Element prioritisation is driven by usage analytics, not designer taste; the top 80 percent of usage informs primary, the bottom 20 percent informs hide/remove.</statement>
      <rationale source="Pareto analysis applied to UI">Without data, prioritisation reverts to opinion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-progressive-disclosure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rarely-needed information is hidden behind progressive disclosure (accordion, tab, expand) rather than removed outright when users still need it occasionally.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen — Progressive Disclosure">Removing rarely-used items can break niche-but-critical flows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-whitespace-tokens" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Whitespace is enforced by tokens in the design system, not ad-hoc; reducing whitespace requires a token override with rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-system practice">Ad-hoc whitespace creates inconsistent breathing room across screens.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-feature-creep-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each new feature added to an existing page passes a complexity-budget check; if the page exceeds the budget, an existing element must be moved or removed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — feature-creep audits">Without a budget pages accumulate clutter indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-test-before-removal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Removals are A/B tested or first-click tested before permanent removal; assumptions about what is rarely used can be wrong.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Removing the wrong element breaks niche-but-critical workflows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-aesthetic-minimalist.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
