<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Aesthetic and Minimalist Design Principles">
  <summary>Content hierarchy framework, visual hierarchy rules, progressive disclosure pattern, white space usage, and the remove/hide/organize/shrink decision framework.</summary>

  <section title="Core Principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the screen's single primary task before starting any audit. Every element classification (Primary/Secondary/Tertiary/Remove) is relative to that task. An element that is essential for one task may be Tertiary or Remove for a different task on the same screen.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a defined primary task, "minimalism" is arbitrary aesthetic preference. With a defined task, classification becomes testable: does this element help the user accomplish [primary task] right now? Elements that do not are candidates for removal or hiding.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every element as Primary (essential for task completion), Secondary (helpful but not critical), Tertiary (rarely needed, nice-to-have), or Remove (no value to any user). Apply the appropriate action: keep, visually subordinate, hide behind progressive disclosure, or delete.</statement>
      <rationale>Every additional element competes with Primary elements for attention. Nielsen's heuristic #8 is not about aesthetics — it is about attention economics. More elements = less visibility for each element = slower task completion and more errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Progressive Disclosure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show summaries; reveal details on demand. Hide advanced options, secondary information, and rarely-used features behind expandable sections or secondary screens. Never hide Primary-tier content behind progressive disclosure.</statement>
      <rationale>Progressive disclosure reduces visible complexity without removing functionality. Users who need advanced features can access them; users who do not are not burdened by them. Applied incorrectly (hiding Primary content), it creates friction for the majority of users.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Visual Hierarchy Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Establish visual hierarchy using size, color saturation, position, and whitespace — in that priority order. Every element should be visually subordinate to the elements above it in the content hierarchy.</statement>
      <rationale>When everything has equal visual weight, nothing reads as primary. Visual hierarchy guides the eye to what matters first. Size and saturation carry the most attention weight; position and whitespace reinforce hierarchy without adding visual complexity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Size: larger = more important. Primary action button is larger than secondary.</item>
      <item>Color saturation: high saturation draws attention. Primary action uses brand color; secondary is outlined or muted.</item>
      <item>Position: top-left is seen first (LTR). Primary content above the fold. Destructive actions at bottom or secondary positions.</item>
      <item>Whitespace: more space = emphasis. Primary elements have more breathing room.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Remove/Hide/Organize/Shrink Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before hiding an element, ask: what happens if we remove it entirely? If the answer is "nothing noticeable," remove it. If it is "some users lose access to an edge case," hide it. If it is "users lose a primary function," reorganize or shrink it — never hide Primary-tier elements.</statement>
      <rationale>Hidden elements still exist in the cognitive model of users who know about them. True minimalism removes elements that add no value; hiding is for elements needed by some users but not the majority. The distinction matters for product decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Balancing Minimalism">
    <rule>
      <statement>Too minimal is also a failure mode. When users cannot find features they need, when essential actions are hidden, or when the interface feels empty, add appropriate content and surface critical actions.</statement>
      <rationale>Minimalism is not sparseness — it is purposeful inclusion. The goal is that every element earns its place, not that the minimum number of elements exist. An overly stripped interface fails users by hiding what they need.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
