<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Aesthetic Minimalism Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete good examples of purposeful minimalism, antipatterns causing clutter or over-stripping, and balance signals for each failure mode.</summary>

  <section title="Good Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Google homepage — extreme focus on single primary task</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Primary task: Search
Elements shown: logo, search input, two buttons (Search / Feeling Lucky)
Everything else: removed from homepage entirely
Result: fastest time-to-task-completion of any major product homepage
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Apple product page — visual hierarchy with whitespace</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Primary: Large product image (dominant)
Secondary: Product name + key feature headline
Tertiary: Specs, accessories, comparison (further down page)
Remove: No competing products, no navigation clutter above hero
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Medium article view — content-focused minimal chrome</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Primary: Article content (full width, readable typography)
Secondary: Author info, clap button (floating, not competing)
Tertiary: Related articles (after end of content)
Remove: No sidebar ads, no pop-up navigation, no competing content
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Keeping all features visible at once out of fear of removing anything</description>
      <reason>Feature accumulation over time turns every screen into a toolbar of options. Each added feature dilutes the visibility of existing features. Regular content audits against the primary task prevent accumulation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Decoration that does not inform: background images, gradient overlays, animated elements that carry no information</description>
      <reason>Decorative elements consume visual attention budget without returning information value. They compete with functional elements and slow visual scanning. Every visual element should serve the primary task or remove it.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Equal visual weight for unequal elements: all buttons the same size, all text the same weight</description>
      <reason>When everything has the same visual weight, users must read everything to determine what matters. Visual hierarchy guides the eye and reduces cognitive load. A primary action button must be visually dominant over secondary actions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hiding primary functionality behind "More" menus or progressive disclosure</description>
      <reason>Progressive disclosure is for Tertiary content. Hiding Primary or Secondary content increases task completion time and error rates. If users regularly have to expand "Show more" to complete the primary task, the Primary content is wrongly classified as Tertiary.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Desktop-level information density applied to mobile layouts</description>
      <reason>Mobile screens are 4-6x smaller than desktop. Elements that read as "appropriately dense" on desktop become visually overwhelming on mobile. Mobile layouts require stricter hierarchy and more aggressive use of progressive disclosure.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Signals That Minimalism Is Wrong Direction">
    <rule>
      <statement>If users complain they cannot find features, if task completion time increases after a simplification, or if key actions have low discovery rates in heatmaps, restore visibility before shipping further removals.</statement>
      <rationale>Minimalism serving the product team's aesthetic preferences at the cost of user task success is not good UX — it is design without validation. Analytics and usability testing are the arbiters, not the designer's preference for clean screens.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
