<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="aesthetic-minimalist Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for aesthetic-minimalist as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Keeping everything - Fear of removing features</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>This leads to cluttered interfaces where important content is lost in noise.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Decoration over function - Aesthetics hurting usability</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Visual embellishments distract from content and slow task completion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Hiding too much - Minimalism becomes confusion</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Progressive disclosure taken to extremes hides critical actions from new users, increasing support load.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Equal emphasis - Everything looks the same</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without clear hierarchy users cannot distinguish primary content from secondary, prolonging task completion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring mobile - Desktop clutter on mobile</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mobile screens demand even more minimalism; failing to simplify for mobile creates unusable experiences on constrained devices.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>"Remove everything" bias: agents applying this heuristic mechanically strip features that power users rely on.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without real usage data, agents apply the heuristic too aggressively to anything that looks decorative.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Subjectivity of "noise": what looks decorative to an agent may convey brand trust to users.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Visual branding elements and trust signals are not decorative despite appearing ornamental; their removal damages perception of credibility.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Progressive disclosure can hide critical actions from new users, increasing support load.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>What is "advanced" must be validated through user testing; agents guess incorrectly and hide functionality users need immediately.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Minimalism applied to forms often removes helpful hints and validation cues, increasing error rates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Form affordances look like visual noise but serve critical guidance and error prevention functions; removing them increases support load.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Cannot substitute for actual task-completion data — a clean UI is not automatically a usable one.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Simplicity audits must be validated against real user behavior metrics; UI simplification without measurement is speculation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
