<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-retention-loop-patterns" title="Retention Loop Patterns">
  <summary>Six self-reinforcing loop patterns that drive users to return without relying solely on external notifications.</summary>

  <section title="Loop Pattern Selection Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Diagnose which loop type is operative in your product before redesigning anything; applying a content loop pattern to a workflow tool, or gamification to a B2B multi-stakeholder product, produces no retention lift and erodes product trust.</statement>
      <rationale>Each loop type requires specific product mechanics. Mismatched patterns consume engineering resources without addressing the actual return-driver for the user.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Loop">
    <p>New content creates return visits. Flow: user visits → consumes content → algorithm learns → better content next time → user returns. Examples: TikTok, Netflix, YouTube. Key mechanics: infinite scroll, personalization, creator ecosystem, new-content notifications.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Social Loop">
    <p>Friends' activity triggers returns. Flow: user posts → friends see → friends react → user notified → user returns to engage → friends notified. Examples: Facebook, Instagram, Slack. Key mechanics: activity feed, @mentions, read receipts, typing indicators.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Progress Loop">
    <p>Accumulated progress creates loss aversion that drives return. Flow: user takes action → progress recorded → streak or level increases → user invested → returns to maintain or grow. Examples: Duolingo, Fitbit, GitHub. Key mechanics: streaks, XP/levels, progress visualization, loss aversion messaging.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Stored Value Loop">
    <p>User data makes the product more valuable over time, creating pull to return. Flow: user adds data → product becomes more valuable → user depends on it → returns to access or add more. Examples: Notion, Dropbox, CRM tools. Key mechanics: easy capture, search/organization, reminders about stored items.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Workflow Loop">
    <p>Work assignments create mandatory return. Flow: work assigned → team expects completion → user must return → new work created. Examples: Jira, Asana, Linear. Key mechanics: task assignments, due dates, team notifications, blocked-work visibility.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Network Effect Loop">
    <p>Value increases with each additional user, raising switching cost. Flow: user joins → invites colleagues → more users = more value → everyone depends on product → high switching cost = retention. Examples: Slack, Zoom, Figma. Key mechanics: collaboration features, easy invites, shared workspaces.</p>
  </section>
</text>
