<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-engagement-hooks" title="Engagement Hooks: Streaks, Achievements, Variable Rewards">
  <summary>Concrete mechanics for increasing return frequency: streak implementation, achievement design, variable reward design, and commitment devices.</summary>

  <section title="Streaks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every streak implementation must include a freeze mechanic; a streak that breaks during a vacation triggers churn from frustration, not from a product quality issue.</statement>
      <rationale>Duolingo uses streak freezes to prevent involuntary churn from circumstances outside the user's control. Without a freeze, the loss-aversion mechanic becomes a source of negative emotion that accelerates departure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
def check_streak(user):
    from datetime import date, timedelta
    last_activity = user.last_activity_date
    today = date.today()

    if last_activity == today - timedelta(days=1):
        user.streak += 1
    elif last_activity < today - timedelta(days=1):
        if user.streak_freezes > 0:
            user.streak_freezes -= 1
        else:
            user.streak = 0

    return user.streak
    ]]></code>
  </section>

  <section title="Variable Rewards">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use variable rewards (randomized point values, personalized content order) instead of static rewards; static rewards saturate within 30-60 days while variable rewards keep engagement curves elevated longer.</statement>
      <rationale>Fixed-ratio reward schedules produce rapid saturation. Variable-ratio schedules maintain novelty because the user never knows exactly what the next interaction will bring.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Implementing variable rewards with a non-seeded random number generator in server code.</description>
      <reason>Non-reproducible reward sequences make bug reports impossible to reproduce and A/B test results impossible to verify. Require deterministic seeding for testability.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Commitment Devices">
    <p>Pre-commitment mechanisms increase return by creating social or financial obligations. Examples: scheduled content release ("new episode drops Monday"), calendar event creation, public commitment ("I'm doing #75hard"), prepaid subscriptions, team dependencies. Each shifts motivation from external trigger to internal obligation.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Notification Budget Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set per-user notification budgets; rate-limit to a maximum of one notification per day per channel, and permanently suppress the channel for any user who marks emails as spam or disables push.</statement>
      <rationale>Aggressive cadence drives OS-level mute and unsubscribe, which is an unrecoverable loss of trigger surface. A modest cadence that users tolerate compounds over months; a burned channel never recovers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/cohort-retention.py">D-N cohort retention calculation by signup week</reference>
</text>
