<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-reengagement-and-examples" title="Re-engagement Campaigns and Real Product Examples">
  <summary>Re-engagement email sequence design, push notification strategy by user state, and four real-product retention loop examples.</summary>

  <section title="Re-engagement Email Sequence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Trigger re-engagement at five dormancy checkpoints (3, 7, 14, 30, 60 days inactive) with escalating value framing; reserve the "is everything okay?" direct message for the 60-day contact and never use it earlier.</statement>
      <rationale>Early contacts that sound desperate accelerate unsubscribes. Graduated value reminders (missed activity, new features, social proof) convert more dormant users than direct emotional appeals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Sequence: Day 1 (3d inactive) — show missed activity; Day 4 (7d) — weekly digest + value reminder; Day 10 (14d) — new features and social proof; Day 20 (30d) — direct value proposition and help offer; Day 40 (60d) — final FOMO + win-back offer.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Push Notification Strategy">
    <p>State-based notification targeting: active users receive event-based triggers (reply notifications); slipping users receive progress-based alerts (streak at risk); inactive users receive FOMO triggers (friends posted); churned users receive win-back (new feature they requested).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Real Product Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Duolingo — Progress + Streak loop. Morning notification "Don't lose your streak!" → open app → complete one lesson → XP gained + streak maintained + leaderboard position → progress saved → tomorrow's notification. Results: 60%+ D1 retention, industry-leading D30, high DAU/MAU ratio.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Slack — Social + Workflow loop. Notification "@Sarah mentioned you in #product" → open app → read message → information received, social connection → reply sent (creates others' triggers). Results: users spend 90+ minutes/day, 65M DAU, high switching cost.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>TikTok — Content + Variable Reward loop. Boredom (internal) or notification → open app, scroll (zero friction) → entertaining personalized video (variable) → watch time trains algorithm → better content next time. Results: 90+ minutes average daily use, highest engagement of social apps.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Notion — Stored Value + Workflow loop. Need to access notes or team activity → open app, find/create content → information found, work completed → more content stored → need stored content again. Results: high enterprise retention, strong team expansion, low churn from stored value.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Studying only current cohorts when diagnosing retention problems.</description>
      <reason>Current cohorts are the surviving population — they exclude the signals that drove churned users out. Cohort-level analysis must include churned users to produce accurate loop diagnoses.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No clear external or internal trigger for return.</description>
      <reason>Users forget products that create no habit signal. Both push/email (external) and habit/time-of-day (internal) triggers must exist; relying only on external triggers creates notification dependence that collapses when users mute the channel.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/cohort-retention.py">D-N retention by signup week</reference>
</text>
