<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ADA Title II Compliance 2026 Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the ADA Title II Compliance 2026 methodology. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="wcag-21-aa-target" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conformance target is WCAG 2.1 AA across all in-scope content. Higher targets (2.2 AA, AAA) are allowed but the rule floor is 2.1 AA.</statement>
      <rationale source="ada.gov / DOJ Title II Final Rule 2024">DOJ explicitly cites WCAG 2.1 Level AA in the 2024 Title II rule.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="deadlines-by-size" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Entities with population ≥50,000 (or special purpose districts of similar scale) MUST conform by April 24, 2026; smaller entities by April 26, 2027.</statement>
      <rationale source="DOJ Title II Final Rule 2024 — §35.200">Population thresholds are codified in the rule text.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="exception-list-documented" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exceptions (archived content, third-party content meeting conditions, individualised documents, conventional electronic documents from non-entity sources, social-media posts pre-effective-date) MUST be enumerated with rationale per item.</statement>
      <rationale source="DOJ Title II Final Rule 2024 — §35.201">DOJ requires that exceptions be specific; blanket &apos;we apply all exceptions&apos; is non-compliant.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="owner-named-per-service-area" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each service area in the inventory names a single accountable owner (handle + role). &apos;Team&apos; / &apos;gov&apos; / empty are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — ADA enforcement-prep convention">OCR enforcement contacts a named owner; anonymous areas accumulate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="remediation-plan-on-fail" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any service area with conformance verdict != pass MUST link a remediation plan with milestones tied to the relevant deadline.</statement>
      <rationale source="DOJ Title II Final Rule 2024 — §35.205">DOJ expects a documented path to compliance, not just a verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent's context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-ada-title-ii-compliance-2026.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
