<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-scope-and-requirements" title="ADA Title II Scope and Technical Requirements">
  <summary>Full scope of the DOJ ADA Title II final rule, WCAG 2.1 AA technical requirements by principle, video and document requirements, and valid exemptions.</summary>

  <section title="Compliance Deadlines and Scope">
    <rule>
      <statement>Large state/local government entities (serving 50,000+ population) must comply by April 24, 2026; smaller entities by April 24, 2027. Standard: WCAG 2.1 Level AA.</statement>
      <rationale>DOJ Final Rule published April 2024. ADA Title II applies to all state and local government entities that receive federal assistance — not just websites, but all digital services used by the public.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Public-facing websites and web applications.</item>
      <item>Mobile applications (iOS and Android) — requires platform-specific AT testing, not just web axe scans.</item>
      <item>Multimedia content: all pre-recorded video requires captions; all live video requires real-time captions or equivalent alternative.</item>
      <item>PDF documents and interactive forms.</item>
      <item>Third-party content embedded on government sites (social media embeds, widgets, chat).</item>
      <item>Online services and citizen portals.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="WCAG 2.1 AA Requirements by Principle">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Principle       | Key Requirements
Perceivable     | Alt text (1.1.1), captions (1.2.x), contrast 4.5:1 normal / 3:1 large (1.4.3), responsive (1.4.4)
Operable        | Keyboard access (2.1.1), no keyboard traps (2.1.2), no time limits or adjustable (2.2.1), skip links (2.4.1), focus visible (2.4.7)
Understandable  | Language attribute (3.1.1), predictable navigation (3.2), error identification (3.3.1), error suggestion (3.3.3)
Robust          | Valid HTML with name/role/value (4.1.2), status messages (4.1.3), compatible with AT
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Video and Document Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>All pre-recorded government video must have accurate, synchronized captions and audio descriptions before publication — not retroactively after a complaint.</statement>
      <rationale>Courts define "accurate" as >= 99% accuracy; auto-generated captions from Whisper or YouTube are ~92-96% accurate and require human QA before claiming compliance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Captions: accurate, synchronized, complete; include speaker identification and non-speech sounds.</item>
      <item>Audio descriptions: visual information not available in the soundtrack must be described (extended audio descriptions if pauses are insufficient).</item>
      <item>PDFs: tagged PDF structure, defined reading order, alt text for images, labeled form fields, bookmarks for documents over 10 pages.</item>
      <item>Media player: keyboard accessible controls; screen reader compatible; caption and audio description toggle.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Exemptions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Exemptions are narrow and individually documented; each must be accompanied by an accessible alternative access method.</statement>
      <rationale>DOJ has rejected broad exemptions ("everything before the deadline"). Once an exemption applies, the organization must still provide alternative access to the information or service.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Pre-effective-date content: content published before the compliance date and NOT subsequently altered. Altering old content revokes the exemption.</item>
      <item>Archived content: clearly labeled as archived, not updated, not actively relied on by the public.</item>
      <item>Third-party content not under government control: must still provide an accessible alternative.</item>
      <item>Undue burden: requires documented cost analysis specific to the entity — not a general "too expensive" claim.</item>
      <item>Fundamental alteration: changes the essential nature of the service; very rarely applies to digital accessibility.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Deploying an accessibility overlay widget as the primary compliance strategy.</description>
      <reason>The DOJ has explicitly warned that overlays do not substitute for underlying code fixes. They remain legally exposed to Title II complaints. Fix the source, not the surface.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
