<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-ost-structure" title="OST Structure and Evidence Rules">
  <summary>OST node types (Outcome/Opportunity/Solution/Assumption Test), evidence requirements, compare-and-contrast rule, and stable ID conventions.</summary>

  <section title="OST Node Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce layer separation: Outcome (what we want to achieve, metric-based), Opportunity (unmet customer need in customer language), Solution (proposed approach — 3+ per opportunity), Assumption Test (one falsifiable experiment per solution).</statement>
      <rationale>Solutions phrased as opportunities short-circuit the discovery process. Assumptions without falsifiable tests cannot inform build/no-build decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Outcome: one per tree root — phrased as a measurable metric ("Activation rate W1: 30% to 45% by Q3")</item>
      <item>Opportunity: unmet customer need in the customer's own language — verb + need + context ("New users can't tell what to do first after signup")</item>
      <item>Solution: proposed approach — structural diversity required (one tech, one process, one content solution)</item>
      <item>Assumption Test: one pre-registered falsifiable test per solution with a failure threshold</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Evidence Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every opportunity node must cite at least 2 evidence IDs (interview transcript line, support ticket, survey row) — no evidence means no node.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs pattern-match opportunities from training data that sound plausible but trace to nothing. Evidence IDs force grounding in actual user data and enable the critic to verify the claim.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store the OST as YAML/JSON in git — Miro/Vistaly/FigJam are render targets only, not the source of truth.</statement>
      <rationale>Visual tools are write-mostly for agents. Round-tripping a hand-edited Miro board back into structured form is brittle. Git-tracked YAML enables diffing and idempotent agent passes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use stable IDs (O-1, OP-3, S-7) for all nodes — agents diff and reference by ID, not statement text which changes across passes.</statement>
      <rationale>Statement text drifts on every rewrite. Stable IDs enable the critic agent to reference prior versions and detect when a solution is being disguised as an opportunity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Compare-and-Contrast Requirement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate at least 3 solution candidates per opportunity before any selection — "compare and contrast" is the core value of the OST; single-solution branches defeat the framework.</statement>
      <rationale>A single solution under an opportunity is a waterfall roadmap with extra shapes. Three structural alternatives (e.g., interactive tour, templated starter, contextual tooltips) enable genuine trade-off analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Opportunity OP-1: "New users can't tell what to do first after signup" → S-1: Interactive 3-step product tour (desirability + usability risk), S-2: Templated starter project on first login (desirability + feasibility), S-3: Contextual tooltip overlay (usability + technical risk).</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Single solution under OP-1: "Add an onboarding checklist" — no compare-and-contrast possible; the team commits without evaluating alternatives.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Tree Depth and Width">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the tree shallow and iterable: 1 outcome, 5-7 opportunities, 3 solutions per opportunity, 1 experiment per solution. Prune monthly.</statement>
      <rationale>Brainstorming 50+ opportunities and never running experiments is width without depth — theater, not discovery. Monthly pruning archives stale branches and prevents OST collapse under its own weight.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/ost.yaml">Canonical OST schema with all four node types and stable IDs.</reference>
</text>
