<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-gotchas-and-tools" title="OST Tools, Services, and Best Practices">
  <summary>CLI tools for rendering and validating OSTs, service landscape, and best practices for maintaining a healthy tree over time.</summary>

  <section title="CLI Tools">
    <list>
      <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc): render OST JSON/YAML to SVG/PNG diagrams — npm i -g @mermaid-js/mermaid-cli</item>
      <item>markmap-cli: Markdown indented list to interactive mind-map — npm i -g markmap-cli</item>
      <item>jq: validate and transform OST JSON between passes</item>
      <item>yq: YAML variant for human-edited trees</item>
      <item>Vistaly REST API: programmatic CRUD on outcomes/opportunities/solutions/assumption-tests</item>
      <item>Miro REST API: push generated tree to a board (sticky-per-node)</item>
      <item>Linear / Jira / GitHub APIs: link Solution nodes to delivery issues</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Services">
    <list>
      <item>Vistaly: OST-native SaaS — purpose-built for Torres OST; native Jira/Linear/GitHub sync; REST + Zapier</item>
      <item>Miro: whiteboard with official OST template — REST API; sticky-note OST is brittle for diffs</item>
      <item>Mermaid Live / GitHub: diagram-as-code — best fit for git-tracked, agent-edited OSTs</item>
      <item>Productboard: can host opportunities (Insights to Features); not a true tree UI</item>
      <item>Lucidchart: generic tree shapes, no OST semantics — use only for presentation</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick one target opportunity per discovery cycle; park the rest. Width without depth is theater.</statement>
      <rationale>Spreading attention across 10 opportunities means no experiment completes within a cycle. One focused opportunity with 3 solutions and 3 experiments produces real learning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-run the critic agent after every human edit — trees decay fast as nodes are rephrased without maintaining evidence links.</statement>
      <rationale>Human edits often rephrase opportunities as solutions or break stable IDs. The critic catches drift before it propagates to experiment design.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag each solution with assumption type (desirability/viability/feasibility/usability/ethicality) so experiment design is targeted to the riskiest assumption.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic "test it" instructions produce generic smoke tests. Assumption typing directs the experiment designer to the specific risk category that would kill the solution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>"AI OST builders" that produce a tree from a one-line prompt with no evidence input.</description>
      <reason>They hallucinate opportunities with full confidence. Useful only as a starter scaffold to be torn down by evidence-grounded passes.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
