<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="helm-basics Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for helm-basics. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Helm chart MUST contain Chart.yaml (name, version, apiVersion), values.yaml (default configuration), and templates/ directory with at least one manifest. Chart.yaml MUST specify semantic version (MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH). Templates MUST follow naming conventions: resource.yaml (e.g., deployment.yaml, service.yaml), _helpers.tpl (template functions), NOTES.txt (post-install instructions). Resource metadata MUST use .Release.Name and .Chart.Name in object names to avoid conflicts when multiple releases coexist. Charts SHOULD NOT include values.lock files in Git (auto-generated per environment).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Chart.yaml specifies how Helm manages the chart: apiVersion: v2 (required for Helm 3), name and version for unique identification and dependency resolution. values.yaml provides sensible defaults so users can helm install without complex value overrides. Consistent naming (resource.yaml, not resources.yaml or app-deployment.yaml) enables other developers to locate resources quickly. Using .Release.Name and .Chart.Name ensures the same chart deployed twice with different names creates distinct, non-conflicting resources. values.lock tracks exact dependency versions across runs; ignore in Git to avoid merge conflicts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Templates MUST use .Values namespace to reference values.yaml (e.g., {{ .Values.image.repository }}). Conditionals MUST check if values exist and are non-empty before using them ({{ if .Values.ingress.enabled }}). Template functions MUST be prefixed with underscore if helper-only (_helpers.tpl defines named templates; non-output). Required values MUST be validated with {{ required "message" .Values.required_field }} to provide clear error messages when values are missing. Loops MUST use range with proper indentation control ({{ range .Values.labels | indent 2 }}) to maintain YAML structure.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">.Values namespace isolates user-provided configuration from Helm built-ins ({{ .Release.Name }}, {{ .Chart.Name }}, {{ .Namespace }}), preventing accidental variable shadowing. Conditionals without existence checks fail if user omits optional values (e.g., ingress might be disabled in dev). require() gives explicit error "database.host is required" vs vague parse error. Indentation (| indent N) preserves YAML structure; incorrect indentation breaks manifests silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>values.yaml MUST group related configuration hierarchically (image.repository, image.tag, not imageRepository, imageTag). Values MUST be documented with comments explaining purpose and valid range. Environment-specific values MUST be in separate files (values-prod.yaml, values-staging.yaml) and NOT stored in version control if they contain secrets. The values.schema.json file (optional but recommended) MUST define structure, types, and required fields for IDE validation and error messages. Sensitive data (database passwords, API keys) MUST NOT appear in values files; use external secret managers with templated references instead (e.g., externalSecrets.enabled: true).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hierarchical values (image.repository vs imageRepository) prevent naming collisions and group related config logically. Comments document intent ("enable autoscaling based on CPU"; not just "autoscaling"). Separate values files per environment prevent prod secrets from leaking into Git. values.schema.json enables VS Code validation and prevents typos (e.g., replciCount instead of replicaCount). Secrets in version control are a security liability; external managers (Sealed Secrets, Vault, AWS Secrets Manager) rotate keys independently of Helm releases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Release installation MUST use helm install (initial deploy) or helm upgrade --install (idempotent). All production upgrades MUST use --atomic flag to enable automatic rollback on failure (failure defined as one or more pods not reaching ready state within --timeout). Rollbacks MUST be tested in staging before production to ensure previous version is compatible with current data state. Release names MUST follow DNS naming (alphanumeric + dash, no underscore, &lt;253 chars). Uninstalls MUST use helm uninstall unless release protection is needed (helm.sh/resource-policy: keep annotation); uninstall does NOT delete kept resources.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">helm install fails if release exists (idempotent: use upgrade --install). --atomic ensures failed deployments don't leave the cluster in a half-upgraded state; if new version crashes, Helm automatically rolls back to previous working version within timeout. Rollbacks are instant (restore previous replica count, image, config) but only safe if the rolled-back version is compatible with current data (e.g., old schema doesn't understand new database columns). Release names in DNS format ensure they work across cloud providers and monitoring systems. --resource-policy: keep prevents Helm from deleting resources on uninstall (e.g., PersistentVolumeClaim should survive release deletion).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dependencies MUST be specified in Chart.yaml under the dependencies section with name, version, and repository. Versions MUST be semantic (X.Y.Z) and MUST NOT be flexible ranges (avoid ~, &gt;) unless testing; pin exact versions for reproducibility. Chart.lock file MUST be committed to Git for reproducible dependency resolution (prevents "it works on my machine" issues). Dependency updates (helm dependency update) MUST be done consciously before deployments, not as part of every build. Optional dependencies MUST be gated by a condition (condition: postgresql.enabled) to support environments without the dependency.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Chart.yaml + Chart.lock ensures all developers and CI/CD get the exact same dependency versions. Flexible version ranges (~1.2.x, &gt;1.0.0) can introduce breaking changes unexpectedly. Conditions allow a single chart to optionally deploy PostgreSQL in dev (enabled: true) but use managed Cloud SQL in prod (enabled: false). Explicit helm dependency update (vs auto-fetch) prevents surprise version upgrades mid-deployment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All public dependencies MUST be sourced from Artifact Hub or official vendor repositories (Bitnami, Jetstack, etc.) with version pinning in Chart.yaml. Internal charts MUST be published to a private OCI registry or Helm chart repository with RBAC restricting access. helm repo update MUST be run before helm install in CI/CD to fetch latest patch versions. Chart versions MUST use semantic versioning (MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH) and MUST be immutable once published (do not overwrite v1.0.0 with a bug fix; release v1.0.1). Repositories SHOULD be documented in CLAUDE.md or README.md with URLs, authentication, and versioning strategy.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Artifact Hub (artifacthub.io) centralizes chart discovery; official repos (Bitnami, Jetstack) are maintained by vendors. Pinning versions in Chart.yaml ensures reproducible installs; flexible ranges (~1.0.x) introduce breaking changes without notice. helm repo update fetches the latest chart list and patch releases (bug fixes). Semantic versioning signals compatibility: patch (1.0.1) = bug fix, safe to upgrade; minor (1.1.0) = new features, backwards-compatible; major (2.0.0) = breaking change, requires testing. Immutable versions prevent hidden updates: once v1.0.0 is published and consumed, do not change it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All charts MUST pass helm lint before committing (pre-commit hook recommended). Failed installs MUST be debugged with helm status and kubectl describe to identify pod failures. Helm templates MUST be dry-run tested (helm template --debug) before install to catch YAML errors early. Hook failures MUST be inspected via kubectl logs on hook pods to diagnose root cause. Release history MUST be preserved (do not delete releases) for audit trails and quick rollbacks. Rollback MUST be tested in staging before applying to production to ensure backwards compatibility.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">helm lint catches YAML syntax errors, missing required fields, deprecated API versions. helm template outputs rendered manifests without contacting cluster; useful for validation. helm status shows current release state; kubectl describe on failed pods reveals startup errors. Hook logs expose migration failures, permission issues, etc. Release history enables instant rollback (helm rollback myrelease 1) if upgrade goes wrong. Rollback testing ensures old version works with current data state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Helm charts deployed via GitOps MUST have values.yaml in Git alongside Chart.yaml. Values MUST NOT contain secrets; use external secret manager (Sealed Secrets, Vault, ExternalSecrets operator) with templated references. GitOps controllers MUST be configured with helm.upgrade --install to ensure idempotency. Release names MUST match Git folder names (apps/myapp/ → release name "myapp") for clarity. Chart repositories MUST be declared in controller config (ArgoCD/Flux helmChart source) with stable, version-pinned URLs. Secrets MUST be encrypted in Git (sealed-secrets) if stored alongside configs; plaintext secrets in Git are security vulnerabilities.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Git-driven deployments enable change review (pull request approval before deploy), audit trails (Git commit history), and disaster recovery (replay Git history to recover cluster state). idempotent upgrade (install if not present, upgrade if exists) handles both initial deploy and subsequent updates. External secret managers separate secret management from Helm; secrets are injected at deploy time via controller. Encrypted secrets in Git (sealed-secrets) are safer than plaintext but external managers (Vault) are more secure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each environment MUST have dedicated values file (values-dev.yaml, values-staging.yaml, values-prod.yaml) containing only overrides. Secrets MUST NOT appear in values files; use external secret managers. Base values.yaml MUST define sensible defaults suitable for development. Environment files MUST be structured hierarchically: if values.yaml has image.repository, values-prod.yaml should override at same path (not create new variables). Namespace isolation MUST separate environments (dev/myapp, staging/myapp, prod/myapp) to prevent accidental cross-environment access. Helm release names SHOULD include environment (myapp-dev, myapp-staging, myapp-prod) for clarity in deployment history.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single chart + multiple values files = DRY principle. No duplication: if chart changes, all environments get fix automatically. values-prod.yaml overrides: replicas (1 dev → 3 prod), resource limits, image tags, storage size, logging verbosity, etc. External secrets keep Git clean. Namespace isolation (RBAC, network policies) prevents dev pod from accessing prod database accidentally. Release names encode environment, enabling quick identification in helm history.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All Kubernetes objects MUST include labels: app.kubernetes.io/name (chart name), app.kubernetes.io/instance (release name), app.kubernetes.io/version (chart version), app.kubernetes.io/managed-by (Helm). Resource names MUST follow pattern {{ include "name.fullname" . }}-{{ resource_type }} (e.g., myapp-deployment, myapp-service, myapp-config). Resource names MUST be truncated to 63 chars (Kubernetes limit) with trimSuffix("-") to avoid trailing hyphens. Annotations SHOULD document ownership: helm.sh/chart, meta.helm.sh/release-name, meta.helm.sh/release-namespace. Namespace names SHOULD use lowercase with hyphens, not underscores or camelCase.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Standard labels enable cluster-wide resource discovery (kubectl get pods -l app.kubernetes.io/name=myapp) and metrics aggregation. Resource naming pattern makes ownership clear: {{ include "name.fullname" . }} inherits release and chart name automatically. Name truncation to 63 chars (Kubernetes object name limit) prevents silent truncation errors. Annotations preserve release metadata for operators and GitOps controllers. Lowercase namespaces follow Kubernetes conventions and DNS naming.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pods requiring Kubernetes API access MUST use dedicated ServiceAccount (not default). ServiceAccount MUST be created by chart (not pre-existing). Roles MUST grant only necessary API verbs (get, list, watch for reads; patch, update for writes; avoid wildcard permissions). RoleBindings MUST bind ServiceAccount to Role in same namespace. RBAC MUST be enabled in cluster (RBAC: true in chart values) to prevent permission escalation. Pod spec MUST reference serviceAccountName for explicit service account assignment. Automounting service account tokens MUST be disabled if not needed (automountServiceAccountToken: false).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dedicated ServiceAccount prevents pods from inheriting default cluster-admin roles. Minimal permissions prevent compromised pod from accessing other namespaces or creating admin accounts. RoleBinding in same namespace isolates blast radius. RBAC (Kubernetes default since 1.20) rejects unauthenticated API access. Explicit serviceAccountName prevents default account use. Disabling automounting tokens (if pod doesn't need Kubernetes API) reduces token exposure surface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All containers MUST specify resource requests for CPU and memory to enable Kubernetes scheduler to place pods on nodes with available capacity. Requests SHOULD be based on actual application needs (measure via metrics); defaults MUST NOT be used. Limits SHOULD be set slightly above requests (10-20%) to allow minor spikes. Memory limits MUST be set to prevent OOMKilled pods; CPU limits can be omitted if fine with throttling. Requests and limits MUST scale with replicas and environment (prod &gt; staging &gt; dev). Horizontal Pod Autoscaler (HPA) MUST reference resource requests for scaling decisions (scale when CPU &gt; 80% of request). Documentation MUST explain how to tune requests based on load testing results.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Requests guarantee minimum resources; without them, pod may be starved if node fills up. Scheduler uses requests to pack pods efficiently. Limits prevent one pod from consuming all node resources (noisy neighbor). Memory limits are hard (OOMKilled if exceeded); CPU limits are soft (throttled, not killed). HPA scales based on request percentage; without requests, HPA cannot make scaling decisions. Environment-specific tuning (dev: 64Mi, prod: 512Mi) reflects production load.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All charts MUST pass helm lint in CI/CD pre-commit. Charts MUST be tested with helm template to verify manifest output. Deployment templates MUST be validated with kubectl apply --dry-run=server (server-side validation) to catch API errors. Helm tests MUST confirm deployed release works (connectivity, health, basic operations). Test suites MUST include: connectivity test (curl service), schema validation (check ConfigMap structure), and integration test (verify feature works end-to-end). Testing MUST occur in CI/CD after every PR; only tested charts merge to main.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">helm lint catches YAML errors, missing fields, deprecated APIs early. helm template outputs manifests without contacting cluster (fast, safe). --dry-run=server validates against actual cluster API, catching version incompatibilities (e.g., policy/v1 vs policy/v1beta1). Helm tests confirm app is healthy post-deploy (pod may start but service unresponsive). Testing in CI prevents broken charts reaching production.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
