<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="helm-basics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for helm-basics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Storing environment-specific values (prod image tags, prod secrets) in values.yaml instead of separate values files.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>values.yaml should contain defaults suitable for development. Environment-specific overrides belong in separate files (values-prod.yaml, values-staging.yaml) passed at install time (helm install -f values-prod.yaml). This keeps the chart reusable and prevents accidental prod secrets in Git.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Over-templatizing values with deep conditional nesting to support "every possible configuration".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Too many conditionals (if ingress enabled, if tls enabled, if cert-manager enabled, if monitoring enabled) create exponential complexity. Helm philosophy: "One chart per application." If your chart supports two completely different architectures (monolith vs microservices), split into separate charts or use library charts. Templatize real current problems, not hypothetical future scenarios (YAGNI principle).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating overly-parameterized values.yaml to support multiple completely different applications or topologies.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If you have a single values.yaml that deploys either monolith or microservices (deeply nested conditionals), the chart is too broad in scope. Create separate charts (myapp-monolith, myapp-microservices) or use library charts to share common patterns. Helm principle: one chart per logical application.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Rolling back because upgrade introduced a bug without understanding the rollback compatibility.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Rollbacks work only if the old version is compatible with current data. If the upgrade added a new required database column, rolling back will crash because the old version doesn't know how to handle the column. Always test upgrades in staging first, and have a compatibility check before deploying to prod (e.g., migration that adds column with default value, then upgrade app).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Using chart dependencies for unrelated resources or services that should be managed separately.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If your chart depends on Redis, Kafka, and PostgreSQL (three independent services), that's acceptable for dev/demo. But if those services are managed by ops team and deployed independently, avoid bundling them in the app chart. Use separate charts per service and manage dependencies at the GitOps level (ArgoCD can orchestrate multiple releases).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Using flexible version ranges (^1.0.0, ~1.2.x, &gt;1.0.0) to automatically pick up latest chart versions in production.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Flexible ranges can introduce breaking changes without notice. Upstream PostgreSQL chart v13.0.0 might require new configuration; your charts that depend on ^12.0.0 will silently upgrade and fail. Pin exact versions, test upgrades consciously, then bump version after validation in staging.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Pinning exact chart versions and never updating, accumulating security patches and bug fixes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin versions for reproducibility, but update regularly (quarterly) to pick up patch releases (1.0.0 → 1.0.1 → 1.0.5). Security patches are in patch versions. If you pin v1.0.0 forever, you miss critical security updates. Strategy: pin version, update quarterly in staging, test, bump version after validation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Storing plaintext secrets (API keys, passwords) in values.yaml in Git.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Anyone with Git access can read secrets. Use sealed-secrets (encrypt with cluster key, decrypt on deploy) or external managers (Vault, AWS Secrets Manager). GitOps controllers integrate with external managers to inject secrets at deploy time, keeping Git clean of credentials.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating values files with conditional logic ("if dev use X else use Y") instead of simple overrides.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Conditionals in values complicate debugging (is variable used?). Helm doesn't support conditional values directly. Use separate values files with simple overrides: values-dev.yaml specifies dev value, values-prod.yaml specifies prod value. Logic stays in templates ({{ if .Values.autoscaling.enabled }}) not values.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Using hardcoded object names instead of templated names based on release and chart.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hardcoded names prevent deploying the same chart twice (second install fails with "resource already exists"). Templated names ensure uniqueness: helm install myapp1 chart → myapp1-deployment, helm install myapp2 chart → myapp2-deployment.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating Role with wildcard permissions (verbs: ["*"], apiGroups: ["*"]).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Wildcard permissions grant cluster-admin privileges to pod. If pod is compromised, attacker has full cluster access. Always specify exact API groups and verbs needed (get, list, watch for reads).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Setting resource limits equal to cluster node capacity (32Gi memory per node → limit 32Gi per pod).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pod's limit should be application max, not cluster max. If limit = node capacity, only one pod fits per node, defeating cluster multiplexing. Limit should be 2-10x request, not 100x.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Testing only with --dry-run (client-side) without server-side validation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>--dry-run=client validates syntax only, not against API server. API server might reject manifests (e.g., invalid fields, quota exceeded). Always use --dry-run=server or install in test cluster to catch real issues. Testing in actual Kubernetes environment (not just syntax validation) is critical to ensure charts work correctly with the target cluster version and configuration.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
