<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Value Proposition Design Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Value Proposition Design application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-both-sides-complete" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Both canvas sides MUST be complete: customer (jobs/pains/gains) AND offer (products/relievers/creators). One-sided canvases are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">A one-sided canvas is a feature list or a wishlist; the diagnostic value is in the pairing.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-fit-paired" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every pain MUST be paired with ≥1 pain reliever; every gain MUST be paired with ≥1 gain creator. Unpaired pains/gains are rejected (or marked as gaps).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Unpaired pains = unaddressed value; unpaired gains = wasted offer surface. Pairings are the fit check.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-evidence-grounded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Customer-side entries MUST cite the JTBD transcripts they came from. Made-up pains are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">A canvas authored from imagination misses the actual customer; JTBD grounding keeps it honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-positioning-format" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The positioning statement MUST follow Geoffrey Moore format: "For [segment] who [need], [product] is a [category] that [benefit]. Unlike [alternative], we [differentiator]." Deviations are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">A consistent format makes positioning statements comparable across products and stable across rewrites.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-one-segment" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The canvas MUST address exactly one primary segment per artefact. Multi-segment canvases are split.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Segments have different jobs/pains/gains; a multi-segment canvas conflates them and produces generic copy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
