<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="agile-ba-frameworks Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for agile-ba-frameworks. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign specific BA deliverables to each Scrum phase; do not treat BA work as a single undifferentiated "refinement" activity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">BA activities that are not assigned to a ceremony are skipped or performed ad-hoc, causing acceptance-criteria defects to surface only at Sprint Review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map the BA role to the SAFe level before the PI Planning ceremony; do not assume a single BA role covers all levels.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">SAFe does not define an explicit BA role; without explicit mapping the BA defaults to Team Level tasks even when the initiative requires Program or Portfolio BA work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select agile BA technique by purpose, not by familiarity; each technique has a distinct trigger.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Using a single technique (e.g. user stories) for all purposes leaves discovery gaps that surface as missed requirements after Sprint Review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score each of the seven IIBA Agile Extension principles with a quoted evidence line; reject any score row that lacks an evidence quote.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Principle scoring without evidence reduces to opinion; only cited artefacts survive a CCBA/CBAP audit and provide actionable gap data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose one canonical framework as the anchor and label techniques borrowed from others explicitly; do not mix IIBA AE + DA + SAFe vocabulary without declaring the anchor.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mixed vocabulary creates false precision and forces future BAs to relitigate framework choices every sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select a single DA primary lifecycle and at most one alternative; reject "all lifecycles apply" outputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">DA documents 6 lifecycles; an agent given all options will select all, making the choice useless for team planning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run the framework fit as a knowledge-retrieval and synthesis pipeline, not a periodic cron; trigger is one-shot on initiative setup or after a major team/scope change.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Framework choices are not daily tasks; automating them on a schedule produces stale recommendations that erode trust in the analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin framework versions in the constitution; refresh the framework-fit report after major team or scope changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without version pins, agent output drifts as upstream content updates; without refresh triggers, recommendations become stale after M&amp;A, new regulatory load, or team size doubling.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
