<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework-overview" title="BA Role in Scrum and Scaled Agile">
  <summary>Maps BA activities to each Scrum ceremony and to each SAFe level, and lists five canonical BA responsibilities in scaled agile delivery.</summary>

  <section title="BA in Scrum">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign specific BA deliverables to each Scrum phase; do not treat BA work as a single undifferentiated "refinement" activity.</statement>
      <rationale>BA activities that are not assigned to a ceremony are skipped or performed ad-hoc, causing acceptance-criteria defects to surface only at Sprint Review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Sprint 0: vision, roadmap, initial backlog creation. Refinement: user story elaboration, acceptance criteria, models. Planning: story clarification, dependency identification. Execution: ad-hoc clarification under 30 min response target. Review: solution validation, feedback capture. Retrospective: BA process improvement.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="BA in SAFe Levels">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map the BA role to the SAFe level before the PI Planning ceremony; do not assume a single BA role covers all levels.</statement>
      <rationale>SAFe does not define an explicit BA role; without explicit mapping the BA defaults to Team Level tasks even when the initiative requires Program or Portfolio BA work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Team Level: Product Owner duties — user stories, acceptance criteria, backlog management. Program Level: Senior BA / System Architect — domain modeling, feature analysis, dependency analysis. Large Solution: Solution Analyst — cross-ART coordination, capability definition. Portfolio Level: Enterprise BA — portfolio backlog grooming, strategic alignment.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Five Key BA Responsibilities">
    <list>
      <item>Bridge business and IT: translate business needs to technical requirements.</item>
      <item>Facilitate communication: enable collaboration among stakeholders across cadences.</item>
      <item>Prioritize by value: support value-based feature prioritization at each level.</item>
      <item>Define vision and roadmap: support Product Management in strategic direction.</item>
      <item>Ensure alignment: verify agile delivery aligns with business goals at each PI.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agile BA Techniques">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select agile BA technique by purpose, not by familiarity; each technique has a distinct trigger.</statement>
      <rationale>Using a single technique (e.g. user stories) for all purposes leaves discovery gaps that surface as missed requirements after Sprint Review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>User Story Mapping: release planning, feature prioritization. Example Mapping: acceptance criteria clarification. Story Splitting: breaking epics into implementable stories. Impact Mapping: connecting features to business goals. Event Storming: domain discovery and process modeling.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/sprint-ba-activities.md">Per-ceremony BA activity checklist for Scrum sprints.</reference>
</text>
