<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-framework-selection" title="Framework Selection and Principle Audit">
  <summary>IIBA Agile Extension seven-principle audit, Disciplined Agile lifecycle selection rules, framework comparison, and agent workflow for producing a framework-fit report.</summary>

  <section title="IIBA Agile Extension Seven Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each of the seven IIBA Agile Extension principles with a quoted evidence line; reject any score row that lacks an evidence quote.</statement>
      <rationale>Principle scoring without evidence reduces to opinion; only cited artefacts survive a CCBA/CBAP audit and provide actionable gap data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>See the Whole</item>
      <item>Think as a Customer</item>
      <item>Analyze to Determine What is Valuable</item>
      <item>Get Real Using Examples</item>
      <item>Understand What is Doable</item>
      <item>Stimulate Collaboration and Continuous Improvement</item>
      <item>Avoid Waste</item>
    </list>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Scoring "Principle 4: 4/5" with no quoted evidence. Agents routinely produce scores without source anchors, making the audit unverifiable.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Framework Comparison">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose one canonical framework as the anchor and label techniques borrowed from others explicitly; do not mix IIBA AE + DA + SAFe vocabulary without declaring the anchor.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixed vocabulary creates false precision and forces future BAs to relitigate framework choices every sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>IIBA Agile Extension: scope single team to 2-3 teams, low adoption cost, principles-based. Disciplined Agile: mid-org mixed cadences, 6 lifecycle options, explicit BA roles. SAFe: large enterprise 50+ people, highest adoption cost, strongest scaling guidance. Do not propose SAFe for teams under 50 people.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating ceremony coverage as principle adherence — "we run stand-ups therefore we Stimulate Collaboration."</description>
      <reason>Ceremonies are necessary but not sufficient; principle adherence requires evidence of behaviour change, not attendance records.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Disciplined Agile Lifecycle Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select a single DA primary lifecycle and at most one alternative; reject "all lifecycles apply" outputs.</statement>
      <rationale>DA documents 6 lifecycles; an agent given all options will select all, making the choice useless for team planning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Agile — iterative, team-scoped, low process weight.</item>
      <item>Lean — flow-optimised, WIP-limited, continuous improvement.</item>
      <item>Continuous Delivery: Agile — CD pipeline required, assumes mature DevOps.</item>
      <item>Continuous Delivery: Lean — CD + Lean, highest DevOps maturity bar.</item>
      <item>Exploratory — R&amp;D, proof-of-concept, unknown solution space.</item>
      <item>Program — multi-team coordination, large solution scope.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Framework Fit Agent Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the framework fit as a knowledge-retrieval and synthesis pipeline, not a periodic cron; trigger is one-shot on initiative setup or after a major team/scope change.</statement>
      <rationale>Framework choices are not daily tasks; automating them on a schedule produces stale recommendations that erode trust in the analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Ingest team state (constitution, roadmap, sample backlog, retro notes, regulatory profile).</item>
      <item>Step 2: Score IIBA AE seven principles (1-5, with one quoted evidence line per score).</item>
      <item>Step 3: Run DA lifecycle fit scoring against team context dimensions (size, DevOps maturity, discovery maturity).</item>
      <item>Step 4: Emit framework-fit.md: primary framework, secondary alternative, top 3 principle gaps with concrete remediation actions.</item>
      <item>Step 5: Hand off operational work (story refinement, AC generation) to the business-analyst variant agent.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin framework versions in the constitution; refresh the framework-fit report after major team or scope changes.</statement>
      <rationale>Without version pins, agent output drifts as upstream content updates; without refresh triggers, recommendations become stale after M&amp;A, new regulatory load, or team size doubling.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/framework-fit.md">Framework comparison matrix and IIBA seven-principles scorecard skeleton.</reference>
</text>
