<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Information Architecture — Templates Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Information Architecture — Templates. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-four-artefacts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every IA deliverable includes the four canonical artefacts — sitemap, taxonomy document, navigation specification, and page inventory — even if some are short.</statement>
      <rationale source="IA templates baseline">Missing artefacts cause downstream contributors to invent their own format.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-owner-per-row" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The page-inventory template requires an owner column with a real human handle on every row; 'team' or blank is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — orphan content audits">Without an owner pages drift out of date and become orphan content.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-version-and-date" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every artefact carries a version, last_reviewed date, and link back to the framework that generated it.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 methodology DoD">Artefacts without provenance cannot be updated confidently by later contributors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-machine-readable-taxonomy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The taxonomy document is exported as both human-readable Markdown and machine-readable YAML so CMS or search systems can consume it.</statement>
      <rationale source="Headless-CMS integration practice">Single-format taxonomies cannot be enforced by automation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-nav-spec-mapped-to-components" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The navigation specification names the exact component variant from the design system for each navigation type.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-system integration practice">Navigation that drifts from the design system breaks visual hierarchy guarantees.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-ia-templates.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
