<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-boundary-and-patterns" title="Hybrid Boundary Definition and Delivery Patterns">
  <summary>Five hybrid patterns, the explicit boundary rule, the tool-count constraint, and the decision framework for choosing predictive vs agile per component.</summary>

  <section title="Decision Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign each deliverable explicitly to one mode: high uncertainty + frequent change = agile; clear requirements + fixed scope = predictive; mixed characteristics = hybrid; continuous deployment needed = agile + DevOps. Document the assignment in program.yaml.</statement>
      <rationale>Mode selection by team preference or political convenience — rather than risk profile — is the primary cause of hybrid program failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Five Hybrid Patterns">
    <p>Water-Scrum-Fall: waterfall for requirements and design, Scrum for development and testing — use for hardware + software programs. Agile with Gates: agile execution inside stage-gate checkpoints — use for regulated industries (FDA, SOX). Phased Agile: multiple teams with milestone-gated phases — use for large enterprise rollouts. Selective Agile: some components agile, others predictive by risk profile. DevOps + Agile: continuous delivery with governance reviews — 2026 default for cloud-native programs.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Explicit Boundary Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name in writing which deliverables are predictive (charter, contracts, regulatory submissions, hardware BOMs) and which are agile (software increments, user research, internal services). If you cannot draw a literal line on an architecture or org diagram, the model is incoherent — do not proceed.</statement>
      <rationale>Boundary ambiguity is the dominant hybrid failure mode. Without an explicit line, every gate review becomes a negotiation about which rules apply.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain one canonical work-graph (program.yaml) with milestones, epics, and team mappings. Two competing portfolios — one for governance, one for delivery — creates divergent truth that agents and humans both get wrong.</statement>
      <rationale>Tool sprawl (backlog in Jira, gantt in MS Project, deliverables in SharePoint) means agents spend more tokens reconciling than executing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Tool Count Constraint">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Choose a tool count proportional to boundary count: ideally one tool spans both arms. Two tools maximum with an explicit sync mechanism. Three or more tools is a smell indicating an unresolved process problem.</statement>
      <rationale>Each additional tool adds a reconciliation step; three+ tools guarantee drift between arms that becomes visible only at gate reviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
