<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="hybrid-delivery Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for hybrid-delivery. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign each deliverable explicitly to one mode: high uncertainty + frequent change = agile; clear requirements + fixed scope = predictive; mixed characteristics = hybrid; continuous deployment needed = agile + DevOps. Document the assignment in program.yaml.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mode selection by team preference or political convenience — rather than risk profile — is the primary cause of hybrid program failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Name in writing which deliverables are predictive (charter, contracts, regulatory submissions, hardware BOMs) and which are agile (software increments, user research, internal services). If you cannot draw a literal line on an architecture or organizational diagram, the model is incoherent — do not proceed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Boundary ambiguity is the dominant hybrid failure mode. Without an explicit line, every gate review becomes a negotiation about which rules apply, and the program devolves into political theatre.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain one canonical work-graph (program.yaml) with milestones, epics, and team mappings. Two competing portfolios — one for governance, one for delivery — creates divergent truth that agents and humans both get wrong.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tool sprawl (backlog in Jira, gantt in MS Project, deliverables in SharePoint) means agents spend more tokens reconciling than executing. One system of record prevents drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose a tool count proportional to boundary count: ideally one tool spans both arms (Azure DevOps, GitLab Ultimate, Jira+Plans). Two tools maximum with an explicit sync mechanism. Three or more tools is a smell indicating an unresolved process problem.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each additional tool adds a reconciliation step; three+ tools guarantee drift between arms that becomes visible only at gate reviews, when correction is most expensive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define one explicit translation table before the first steering report: epic maps to deliverable, story-points map to a declared effort estimate, velocity maps to run-rate. Use the same table for every report cycle and never mix vocabularies within a single audience.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Vocabulary leakage — "milestone" used in team standups, "increment" in governance packs — causes executives to lose confidence in the program; consistent translation maintains trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set gate frequency proportional to risk: monthly for regulated programs, quarterly for steady-state, never weekly (that is just a status meeting renamed). Gate decisions — go/no-go — are sponsor calls only; agents may flag readiness but not declare it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Weekly gates produce decision fatigue and get rubber-stamped. Monthly gates align with regulatory review cadence. Quarterly gates suit established, low-risk steady-state programs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-baseline the predictive arm only when scope or contract changes, not when velocity slips. Velocity slippage is handled in retrospectives and planning; it is not a baseline trigger.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Re-baselining on velocity drift obscures the original commitment and makes trend analysis impossible; the baseline is the contract, not the forecast.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
