<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Hybrid Delivery Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Hybrid Delivery. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="workstream-mode-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every workstream MUST declare its mode (predictive OR agile) with a one-paragraph rationale. Implicit hybrid is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI Agile Practice Guide">Implicit mode causes mode drift; explicit declaration anchors governance and reporting.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="handoff-contract-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Inter-workstream handoffs MUST be defined as contracts with inputs, outputs, acceptance criteria, SLA, and escalation owner.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — hybrid delivery audit 2026">Without contracts, the agile workstream blames the waterfall workstream for late inputs and vice-versa; both miss commitments.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="single-governance-layer" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Program governance MUST run as a single layer over both modes. Parallel governance per mode is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI Agile Practice Guide; PRINCE2 Hybrid">Parallel governance creates conflicting decisions and doubles meeting load; one layer with mode-aware sub-reports prevents fragmentation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="metric-translation-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reports MUST translate workstream metrics into a common dashboard (e.g. agile velocity → cost+schedule equivalent; predictive EVM → throughput equivalent).</statement>
      <rationale source="Hybrid program reporting best practices">Without translation, stakeholders see incomparable metrics and lose program-level visibility.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="cadence-aligned-on-handoffs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Workstream cadences MAY differ internally, but MUST align at handoff dates. Mis-aligned cadences violate the program timeline.</statement>
      <rationale source="Hybrid program scheduling">Mis-aligned cadences cause handoff misses that ripple downstream; alignment forces explicit synchronisation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Hybrid Delivery fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Hybrid Delivery outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
