<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-translation-and-governance" title="Translation Layer and Gate Governance">
  <summary>Translation table rules between agile and predictive vocabulary, gate cadence calibration, EVM-on-agile warning, and anti-patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Translation Table">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define one explicit translation table before the first steering report: epic maps to deliverable, story-points map to a declared effort estimate, velocity maps to run-rate. Use the same table for every report cycle and never mix vocabularies within a single audience.</statement>
      <rationale>Vocabulary leakage — "milestone" used in team standups, "increment" in governance packs — causes executives to lose confidence in the program; consistent translation maintains trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Steering-committee pack uses: milestone, deliverable, planned-vs-actual labour, variance. Team ceremony uses: increment, story, velocity, sprint goal. The cadence-translator-agent converts between them; humans never mix the two.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agile metrics (story points, velocity) presented directly to a steering committee that thinks in deliverables and labour cost.</description>
      <reason>Executive audiences interpret story points as arbitrary numbers; without translation they discount the data or demand a switch to hours, undermining agile capacity planning.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Gate Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set gate frequency proportional to risk: monthly for regulated programs, quarterly for steady-state, never weekly (that is just a status meeting renamed). Gate decisions — go/no-go — are sponsor calls only; agents may flag readiness but not declare it.</statement>
      <rationale>Gate frequency mismatched to risk either throttles delivery (too frequent) or misses real exposure (too infrequent). Weekly gates produce decision fatigue and get rubber-stamped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-baseline the predictive arm only when scope or contract changes, not when velocity slips. Velocity slippage is handled in retrospectives and planning; it is not a baseline trigger.</statement>
      <rationale>Re-baselining on velocity drift obscures the original commitment and makes trend analysis impossible; the baseline is the contract, not the forecast.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="EVM on Agile Arm Warning">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying Earned Value Management metrics (CPI, SPI computed from story-points x hourly rate) to the agile arm without an explicitly agreed conversion.</description>
      <reason>Story points are a relative planning unit, not a labour-cost proxy; EVM computed from them produces numbers that look precise but are meaningless, and finance will hold the PM accountable for them.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Organizational Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hybrid chosen as a political compromise rather than a risk-profile decision.</description>
      <reason>PMO-wants-control + teams-want-autonomy resolved by "we do hybrid" produces neither the governance of predictive nor the adaptability of agile — it produces incoherence dressed as methodology.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agile coach distrusts gantts; PM distrusts standups.</description>
      <reason>The dominant cultural failure in hybrid programs; the solution is cross-training: PMs shadow stand-ups, coaches attend gate reviews. Neither arm is optional.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../agile-ceremonies-setup/">Agile arm rituals for the delivery teams</link>
    <link path="../cost-estimation/">Earned value baseline for the predictive arm</link>
  </see-also>
</text>
