<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="hybrid-delivery Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for hybrid-delivery as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agile metrics (story points, velocity) presented directly to a steering committee that thinks in deliverables and labour cost.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Executive audiences interpret story points as arbitrary numbers; without translation they discount the data or demand a switch to hours, undermining agile capacity planning.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Applying Earned Value Management metrics (CPI, SPI computed from story-points × hourly rate) to the agile arm without an explicitly agreed conversion.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Story points are a relative planning unit, not a labour-cost proxy; EVM computed from them produces numbers that look precise but are meaningless, and finance will hold the PM accountable for them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Hybrid chosen as a political compromise rather than a risk-profile decision.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PMO-wants-control + teams-want-autonomy resolved by "we do hybrid" produces neither the governance of predictive nor the adaptability of agile — it produces incoherence dressed as methodology.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agile coach distrusts gantts; PM distrusts standups.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The dominant cultural failure in hybrid programs. The solution is cross-training: PMs shadow stand-ups, coaches attend gate reviews. Neither arm is optional.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Governance drift: the predictive arm enforces a stage gate, the agile arm flies through it; or vice versa, agile is gated to a quarterly cadence and dies.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Gate frequency must match risk profile, not legacy habit or org politics. Misalignment between arms destroys the coherence that hybrid promises.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
