<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Decision-Options Memo Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that prevent the two recurring failures: a memo that is actually a one-option recommendation, and a memo that hides the dissent.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-three-option-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The memo MUST present at least three viable options. If only two come to mind, "do nothing" or "defer" is included as the third. More than five is rejected — the BA filters first. Single-option memos are sent back for re-framing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-analysis practice; cf. Kahneman, Thinking Fast and Slow on framing effects">Two-option memos default to false dichotomy; single-option memos default to rubber-stamp approval. Three forces real trade-off articulation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-structured-cvr" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each option MUST have a Cost-Value-Risk row populated: Cost (effort, $$$, time), Value (business outcome enabled, in measurable units where possible), Risk (top 1-3 risks with likelihood and impact). All three are populated even if a value is "negligible" or "none identified" — empty cells are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Risk-adjusted decision-making frameworks (PMI, ISO 31000)">Without parallel structure across options, the decision-maker compares apples to oranges. Forcing the same shape per option produces apples-to-apples comparison.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-recommendation-with-why-not" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The recommendation section MUST name one option and explicitly state "Why not Option B" and "Why not Option C" in 1-2 sentences each. Recommendations without why-not text are rejected — they hide the trade.</statement>
      <rationale source="Amazon 6-page memo discipline + good staff-work practice">Why-not language forces the BA to engage with the other options seriously. Without it, the memo silently treats the recommendation as obvious, which it rarely is.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-dissent-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The dissent section MUST name dissenting stakeholders (by name, not "the team") with their objection summarized in 1-2 sentences each. If no dissent surfaces in consultation, the BA writes "no dissenting view captured from [list of stakeholders consulted]." Generic "some concerns were raised" is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Good staff-work / disagree-and-commit cultures">Anonymous dissent allows the decision-maker to dismiss it; named dissent forces engagement. Empty dissent sections with disagreement under the surface produce decisions that unravel post-meeting.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-decision-required-by" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every memo MUST state: decision-required-by (ISO date), decision-maker (named individual), default-if-no-decision (one of the options auto-selected, or "project blocked"). Open-ended memos rot in queues.</statement>
      <rationale source="Project-management practice; cf. Andy Grove, High Output Management on decision timeliness">A decision without a deadline is a wish. The default-if-no-decision clause is the forcing function — it tells the decision-maker what happens if they ignore the memo.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Compliant Cost-Value-Risk row">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Option B: Use AWS RDS Aurora for the data layer
Cost:    $2,400/mo at expected load; ~3 weeks setup + DBA training.
Value:   Native multi-AZ HA without app code; backup/restore automated; SOC2-relevant audit logs out of box.
Risk:    Vendor lock-in (M/H, low likelihood near-term); cost scaling unpredictable above 10 vCPU (M/M); migration off Postgres OSS is non-trivial (H/L).
      ]]></code>
      <note>Concrete numbers, value tied to outcomes, risks have L/I and severity. Reader can compare to Option A/C in 30 seconds.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Empty structure">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Option B: AWS RDS
Cost:    A bit more
Value:   Better reliability
Risk:    Some risks
      ]]></code>
      <note>Decorative table. Doesn't enable any comparison. Violates r2.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
