<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Tiny Bets Quarterly Cadence Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Tiny Bets Quarterly Cadence application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="max-four-bets" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each quarter MUST commit to ≤4 bets total. Five or more = hedging; the cadence fails because no bet gets enough attention to be falsified.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tiny-seed / indie-portfolio practice">Tiny-seed / indie-portfolio practice — anchors Tiny Bets Quarterly Cadence rule `max-four-bets`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kill-criterion-pre-commit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each bet MUST have a written kill-criterion (metric + threshold + observation window) BEFORE committing. Bets without a kill-criterion run forever.</statement>
      <rationale source="Pre-mortem / falsifiability discipline">Pre-mortem / falsifiability discipline — anchors Tiny Bets Quarterly Cadence rule `kill-criterion-pre-commit`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="mid-quarter-cull" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>At mid-quarter (week 6), every bet MUST be graded against its kill-criterion. Bets failing the criterion MUST be killed or paused; sunk-cost continuation is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mid-quarter review practice">Mid-quarter review practice — anchors Tiny Bets Quarterly Cadence rule `mid-quarter-cull`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-owner-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every bet MUST name a single accountable owner (the operator themselves, or a named collaborator). &apos;Team&apos; / &apos;we&apos; / &apos;us&apos; fails.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-throat-to-choke practice">Single-throat-to-choke practice — anchors Tiny Bets Quarterly Cadence rule `named-owner-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="end-of-quarter-rollup" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each quarter MUST close with a rollup naming: bets shipped, bets killed, revenue delta, lessons. Without the rollup, the next quarter starts blind.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operating-rhythm research">Operating-rhythm research — anchors Tiny Bets Quarterly Cadence rule `end-of-quarter-rollup`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
