<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Competitor Analysis: Five-Step Framework">
  <summary>Five-step competitor analysis framework covering identification of all competitor types, landscape mapping, per-competitor analysis dimensions, gap identification, and differentiation statement.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Identify Competitors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify competitors across three types: direct (same product, same audience), indirect (different product, same problem), and future (emerging or could pivot). Target 5-10 direct, 3-5 indirect, 2-3 future.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing indirect competitors means missing the actual churn cause — substitutes (spreadsheets, email, "do nothing") are what users fall back to, not rival SaaS products.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Google "[problem] solution" and "alternatives to [known competitor]"</item>
      <item>Product Hunt: search by category</item>
      <item>G2/Capterra: browse category leaders</item>
      <item>Reddit: "What do you use for [problem]?" threads</item>
      <item>Ask target customers directly what they use and what they tried before</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Map the Landscape">
    <rule>
      <statement>Plot competitors on a positioning matrix (x: feature breadth, y: price) and find empty quadrants or underserved positions. The goal is to identify whitespace, not to place competitors accurately for its own sake.</statement>
      <rationale>A matrix without a whitespace conclusion is a visualization exercise — the output must be an actionable positioning recommendation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Analyze Each Competitor">
    <rule>
      <statement>Analyze each competitor across eight dimensions: product (features, gaps), pricing (model, tiers), positioning (target, message), technology (stack, integrations), traction (users, revenue estimate), team (size, funding), marketing (channels, content, ads), weaknesses (bad reviews, gaps).</statement>
      <rationale>Shallow analysis (name + pricing only) leaves differentiation opportunities invisible. All eight dimensions are required for a complete competitive profile.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Identify Gaps">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify gaps into five types: feature gap (they don't have it), quality gap (they do it poorly), audience gap (they don't serve this segment), price gap (too expensive for some), experience gap (UX/onboarding is painful). Prioritize gaps where multiple competitors share the same weakness.</statement>
      <rationale>Acting on a gap that only one competitor misses may be intentional (unprofitable to build); gaps missed by all competitors with evidence of demand are the real opportunities.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Define Differentiation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write a differentiation statement in the format: "For [target audience] who [need/problem], [Product] is a [category] that [key benefit]. Unlike [competitors], we [key differentiator]." One statement, specific and testable.</statement>
      <rationale>A vague differentiation statement ("better UX") cannot guide product or marketing decisions; specificity forces clarity about what the differentiator actually is.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>For solo freelancers who need simple project tracking, TaskLite is a project management tool that focuses on single-person workflows. Unlike Asana or Monday, we have no team features, just personal productivity.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Email marketing tool gap: all tools price by subscriber count; solopreneurs hit paywalls early; no tool focuses on under-1000 subscribers. Opportunity: generous free tier (5000 subscribers), solo-focused features, no team complexity.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
