<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-swot-and-share" title="Competitor Analysis: SWOT Grid, Share Estimation, and Portfolio Scorecard">
  <summary>Market-researcher-specific SWOT rules (one citation per cell), share-estimation conventions (5% buckets, proxy triangulation), devil's-advocate pass, and portfolio scorecard for quarterly diffing.</summary>

  <section title="SWOT Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require one citation URL per SWOT cell. Reject any cell whose evidence is the agent's prior knowledge rather than a fetched URL (review quote, metric, job posting).</statement>
      <rationale>This single rule eliminates ~80% of LLM SWOT slop. "Strong brand" as a strength with no citation is a tautology, not an observation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define Opportunities as external trends the competitor could ride. Define Threats as external trends that hurt us if the competitor rides them. Reject any cell that collapses O and T into the same bucket.</statement>
      <rationale>Most LLM-generated SWOTs list "AI disruption" as both O and T. The distinction between "trend for them" and "threat to us" is where the strategic value lives.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a devil's-advocate pass after every synthesis: from the top competitor's perspective, rebuild our SWOT. List the 3 threats they would target us with first.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-comparison bias causes agents to under-weight competitor strengths against us; a forced adversarial perspective surfaces the threats most likely to be missed.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Share Estimation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Round all share estimates to 5% buckets and always print "(est.)". Reject any number with a decimal. If share is under 5%, print "long tail".</statement>
      <rationale>Traffic + employees + reviews are correlated, not independent proxies. Agents stack them and report false precision (23.4%). Rounding to 5% buckets is the minimum honest representation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Triangulate share with at least two proxies (traffic + employees, or downloads + revenue). One proxy alone is a guess, not an estimate.</statement>
      <rationale>SimilarWeb traffic share and LinkedIn headcount both have significant noise; two uncorrelated proxies pointing in the same direction provide meaningfully more confidence than one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run market-research-tam-sam-som first to get the TAM denominator. Never quote a share percentage without naming the denominator and its source.</statement>
      <rationale>Share is a fraction — "X has 30% market share" with no denominator is meaningless marketing language, not analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For private companies pre-Series-B with no Crunchbase/SEC filing data, write TBD for numeric fields rather than inventing ARR or headcount.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents invent plausible ARR for private startups. A TBD that flags the data gap is more useful than a fabricated number that propagates into strategy decks.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Portfolio Scorecard">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the scorecard schema (competitor YAML + scorecard column headers) in git before the first run. Quarterly re-runs must use the same dimensions. Reject any run that adds new columns.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents invent new columns to "improve" the scorecard each quarter. Column drift makes quarter-over-quarter diffs meaningless — the delta is the strategy story.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag every estimate with confidence level: high = official source, med = proxy-triangulated, low = single proxy or inferred. Do not strip confidence tags in synthesis.</statement>
      <rationale>A board-ready competitive matrix with invisible confidence levels buries the distinction between a market-data-sourced number and an inference.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/market-share-proxy.sh">Assembles SimilarWeb + Crunchbase + GitHub share proxies into quarterly CSV for diffing</reference>
  <reference path="templates/competitor-report.md">Full competitor analysis report template</reference>
</text>
