<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples-and-antipatterns" title="Competitor Analysis: Examples and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Worked examples from note-taking and email marketing domains, common mistakes, and AI-agent gotchas with concrete mitigations.</summary>

  <section title="Worked Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Note-taking app analysis: Direct competitors (Notion, Obsidian, Roam Research), indirect (Apple Notes, Google Docs), future (AI writing tools). Findings: Notion strength=all-in-one, weakness=slow+complex; Obsidian strength=local-first+plugins, weakness=steep learning; Roam strength=backlinks, weakness=expensive+dated UI. Positioning: "For busy professionals who want fast, simple notes with linking. Unlike Notion, we're single-purpose and lightning fast. Unlike Obsidian, we work great out of the box."</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Email marketing gap discovery: all tools price by subscriber count; solopreneurs hit paywalls early; no tool focuses on under-1000 subscribers. Gap validated by review mining (50+ feature requests in Mailchimp community). Opportunity: generous free tier (5000 subscribers), solo-focused features, no team complexity.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Only analyzing direct competitors while ignoring indirect and future competitors.</description>
      <reason>Indirect competitors (substitutes, "do nothing") are the actual churn cause — they do not appear in "top 5 CRM alternatives" searches but account for most of the market's status quo.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Surface-level analysis (name + pricing only) without digging into reviews, pricing pages, and features.</description>
      <reason>Feature gaps and quality gaps that create differentiation opportunities are invisible at surface level; they require review mining and hands-on product evaluation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Copying competitor features rather than finding gaps to differentiate.</description>
      <reason>Feature parity is a race to the bottom; differentiation lives in the gaps the competitor chose not to fill.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>One-time analysis without setting up ongoing monitoring.</description>
      <reason>A SWOT snapshot decays in 3-6 months; without a re-run cadence, decisions made from it become stale anchors.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hallucinated funding/ARR: agent invents plausible figures like "$12.3M Series A" without Crunchbase/PitchBook access.</description>
      <reason>Hard rule: if API key absent, write TBD and audit the output for any $N not in the source CSV before publishing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>SWOT tautology: agent writes "strong brand" because the company is famous, without a cited evidence URL.</description>
      <reason>Reject any S/W cell whose evidence is the agent's prior knowledge rather than a fetched URL. One citation per cell is non-negotiable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Context overflow on 10+ competitors: agent tries to pass raw scrapes into a single synthesis prompt.</description>
      <reason>Do not pass raw scrapes into synthesis. SWOT each competitor to YAML first, then synthesize from the YAMLs only — this fits in context and produces cleaner output.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Strategic-group axis-shopping: agent picks axes post-hoc that maximise visual separation.</description>
      <reason>Pin axes in the prompt before running (e.g., price vs. feature breadth with named exemplars for each pole). If data does not separate on pre-committed axes, that is the finding.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Recency bias: SWOT skews to last-90-days news, missing structural threats from the prior 3 years.</description>
      <reason>Force a 3-year retrospective scan ("structural threats since 2023") as a separate sub-task before synthesis.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
