<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="success-metrics-definition">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>user-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Define North Star Metric, 3-5 Primary KPIs via AARRR framework, set targets, and establish measurement definitions.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>success-metrics</tag>
      <tag>kpis</tag>
      <tag>aarrr</tag>
      <tag>north-star</tag>
      <tag>product-metrics</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Success Metrics Definition</title>

    <summary>Before sprint planning or launch, define a North Star Metric and 3-5 Primary KPIs using the AARRR framework (Acquisition, Activation, Retention, Revenue, Referral). Set quantified targets based on baseline data, establish exact measurement definitions, and distinguish between vanity metrics (look good, not actionable) and actionable metrics (drive decisions). Teams that measure the wrong things or too many things waste energy on features that don't move the business; this methodology prevents that.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Teams measure the wrong things or too many things. Common issues: vanity metrics that don't drive decisions, too many KPIs with no focus, metrics that don't connect to business outcomes, and no targets or baselines. The root cause is the absence of a structured process for identifying what truly matters. Success metrics are quantifiable measures that indicate whether you're achieving your goals — they answer "How do we know if we're winning?" Without this discipline, teams optimize for the wrong outcomes and build features that move dashboard numbers without moving the business.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before sprint planning: defining what "done" looks like for a feature</item>
        <item>At product launch: establishing the AARRR baseline before any optimization</item>
        <item>When a team disagrees on whether a feature worked (no agreed metric = no resolution)</item>
        <item>OKR setup cycles: translating goals into measurable KPIs</item>
        <item>After a pivot: resetting metrics to match new product direction</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When you have no baseline data and no way to collect it (define instrumentation first)</item>
        <item>For pure infrastructure tasks where the output is binary (works / doesn't work)</item>
        <item>When the product is pre-revenue and you're still searching for problem-solution fit — metrics framework too early locks in false assumptions</item>
        <item>When stakeholders cannot agree on the North Star — skip to qualitative research first</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="metric-types">
      <p>Before building a metrics framework, distinguish between the types of metrics you'll track.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track both Input (Leading) metrics and Output (Lagging) metrics. Input metrics are activities you control (blog posts published, features shipped). Output metrics are results of activities (organic traffic, customer signups). Input metrics predict output metrics.</statement>
        <rationale>Input metrics alone show effort with no business result; output metrics alone hide the levers. Both together let you understand cause and effect.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Test each metric with this question: "If this metric changes, will we do something different?" If the answer is no, it is a vanity metric. Vanity metrics look good (e.g., "total signups ever") but do not drive decisions. Actionable metrics (e.g., "weekly active users") directly influence product roadmap decisions.</statement>
        <rationale>Metrics that don't influence action are expensive distractions; they consume engineering time to instrument and dashboard space to display, with zero business impact.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="metric-hierarchy">
      <p>Organize metrics in a hierarchy: North Star Metric at the top, then 3-5 Primary KPIs per AARRR stage, then Secondary metrics and Guardrail metrics.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Define exactly ONE North Star Metric. Characteristics: measures core value delivered, leads to revenue, measurable and understandable, actionable. Choose one of: SaaS→Weekly Active Users; Marketplace→Weekly GMV; Media→Time Spent Reading; E-commerce→Purchases per Month. All team effort flows toward moving the North Star.</statement>
        <rationale>Multiple "North Stars" produce organizational confusion; teams optimize locally without shared direction. One metric creates alignment.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="aarrr-framework">
      <p>The AARRR framework (Pirate Metrics) breaks the customer lifecycle into five stages, each with metrics.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>For each AARRR stage, define metrics: Acquisition (how do users find us? → visitors, signups, CAC), Activation (do they have a great first experience? → onboarding completion, time to value), Retention (do they come back? → DAU/MAU, churn rate), Revenue (do they pay? → MRR, ARPU, LTV), Referral (do they tell others? → NPS, referral rate, K-factor). Select 1 primary metric per stage; limit total to 3-5 KPIs.</statement>
        <rationale>AARRR maps every revenue-driving action to a single stage; this prevents omitting a critical stage and ensures balanced growth (e.g., optimizing acquisition while retention collapses).</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="metric-definition-process">
      <p>Follow this five-step process to build a metrics framework.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 1: Define Business Goals. Write goal statements: "Goal: [Objective statement], Timeframe: [When], Target: [Quantified result]". Example: "Goal: Achieve product-market fit, Timeframe: 6 months, Target: 40%+ would be 'very disappointed' without product".</statement>
        <rationale>Goals without explicit targets remain vague; "increase retention" is not a goal until you specify 95% monthly retention.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 2: Identify North Star Metric. Choose the single metric that best measures core value delivered to users. Document why it is the North Star and what outcome it predicts (e.g., "Weekly active teams predict revenue because active teams upgrade to paid plans").</statement>
        <rationale>Without a stated North Star, teams disagree on priorities and marketing optimizes different metrics than product.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 3: Break Down into Primary KPIs. For each AARRR stage, define one primary metric with exact definition (formula), data source, current baseline, and target. Limit to 3-5 total KPIs.</statement>
        <rationale>Metrics without definitions are ambiguous (what counts as "active"?); metrics without baselines make targets fiction.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 4: Set Targets. Set targets using one of four approaches: Baseline + improvement (current + X%), Benchmark (industry average if available), Goal-backward (what's needed to hit strategic goal), Experimental (test and learn). Good targets are specific numbers, time-bound, achievable but challenging, and based on data or research. NEVER set targets without baseline data — mark as [NEEDS BASELINE] until real data is provided.</statement>
        <rationale>Targets without baselines are guesses; agents will produce plausible-sounding numbers that may be wildly off. Baselines ground targets in reality.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 5: Establish Measurement. For each metric, document: exact definition (what counts / doesn't count), data source (analytics tool, database, API), calculation method (formula), reporting frequency (daily / weekly / monthly), owner (who reviews it). Include edge cases — "weekly active user" must specify what counts as active (specific event, not just login).</statement>
        <rationale>Metrics without edge cases hide the signal; without an owner they become orphaned dashboards that no one reviews.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Too many metrics (10+ KPIs tracked on the same dashboard)</description>
        <reason>Focus diffuses; teams cannot optimize for everything. 3-5 primary KPIs force prioritization.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No North Star (multiple competing metrics treated as equally important)</description>
        <reason>Organizational misalignment; marketing optimizes for acquisition while product optimizes for retention, with no shared direction.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Vanity metrics (total signups ever, total users ever, total revenue ever)</description>
        <reason>These only go up; they don't tell you if current cohorts are healthy. Track cohort retention and weekly active instead.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No targets or baselines</description>
        <reason>Metrics become decorations; teams don't know if performance is good or bad. "Retention is 60%" — is that success or failure? Without a target, no one knows.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Undefined metrics (ambiguous definitions like "active user")</description>
        <reason>Different teams count differently; the metric becomes meaningless. Define edge cases.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>AARRR framework maps poorly to B2B enterprise products with long sales cycles</description>
        <reason>For B2B, adapt: Awareness (brand study), Consideration (demo requests), Decision (contracts signed), Adoption (usage depth), Expansion (upsell). The principle stays the same.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="metrics-examples">
      <example type="good" title="B2B SaaS Metrics — North Star: Weekly Active Teams">
        <p>Primary KPIs:</p>
        <list>
          <item>Acquisition: Marketing Qualified Leads (target: 200/month)</item>
          <item>Activation: Onboarding completion in 7 days (target: 60%)</item>
          <item>Retention: Monthly logo retention (target: 95%)</item>
          <item>Revenue: Net Revenue Retention (target: 110%)</item>
          <item>Referral: NPS (target: 50+)</item>
        </list>
        <p>Guardrails: Support tickets per user &lt; 0.5/month, Page load time &lt; 2 seconds.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Consumer App Metrics — North Star: Daily Active Users">
        <p>Primary KPIs:</p>
        <list>
          <item>Acquisition: Daily app installs (target: 500/day)</item>
          <item>Activation: Day 1 retention (target: 40%)</item>
          <item>Retention: Day 7 retention (target: 20%)</item>
          <item>Revenue: ARPDAU (target: $0.05)</item>
          <item>Referral: Organic install % (target: 30%)</item>
        </list>
        <p>Guardrails: Crash rate &lt; 0.5%, App store rating &gt; 4.5.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Marketplace Metrics — North Star: Weekly GMV">
        <p>Primary KPIs:</p>
        <list>
          <item>Acquisition (Demand): New buyer signups (target: 1000/week)</item>
          <item>Acquisition (Supply): New seller signups (target: 100/week)</item>
          <item>Activation: First purchase rate (target: 25%)</item>
          <item>Retention: Repeat purchase rate in 30 days (target: 40%)</item>
          <item>Revenue: Take rate (target: 15%)</item>
        </list>
        <p>Guardrails: Search-to-purchase rate &gt; 3%, Seller satisfaction &gt; 80%.</p>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-workflow">
      <p>Claude subagents can draft a metrics framework given a product description and business goals, selecting appropriate North Star candidates from the AARRR taxonomy and generating metric specifications. However, target-setting requires real baseline data — agents must be given current metric values as input context. The framework output should be reviewed by a human before being used to set team OKRs.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Start with one North Star Metric before adding any secondary metrics; teams that start with 5 KPIs focus on none.</item>
        <item>Document metric definitions with edge cases — "weekly active user" must specify what counts as active (specific event, not just login).</item>
        <item>Set targets only after you have at least 4 weeks of baseline data; earlier targets are fiction.</item>
        <item>Include guardrail metrics alongside growth metrics — optimizing acquisition while retention collapses is a common trap.</item>
        <item>Review the entire metrics framework quarterly; retire metrics that have stopped driving decisions.</item>
        <item>Segment every metric by cohort (acquisition channel, plan type, geography) from day one — aggregates hide the signal.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Agents will confidently suggest targets without baseline data; always require the agent to mark targets as [NEEDS BASELINE] until real data is provided.</item>
        <item>AARRR stage mapping is ambiguous for non-consumer products; give the agent explicit stage definitions for the specific product type.</item>
        <item>Metric definitions generated by agents often omit edge cases (what counts as "active"?); require the agent to specify what is excluded, not just what is included.</item>
        <item>"North Star" selection by agents defaults to revenue or DAU; push for output metric that actually measures value delivered to the user, not value captured by the business.</item>
        <item>Human approval required before metrics are shared with the team — agents lack organizational context about what is politically actionable.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <p>Claude subagents can draft a metrics framework given a product description and business goals, selecting appropriate North Star candidates from the AARRR taxonomy and generating metric specifications. Use faion-market-researcher-agent to generate metrics framework for a described product and suggest North Star candidates with rationale. Use faion-research-agent in validate mode to validate that proposed metrics are actionable and not vanity metrics.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-prompt-patterns">
      <p>Example prompts for metrics definition work with Claude subagents:</p>
      <prompt purpose="metrics framework generation">
<![CDATA[
You are a metrics design agent. Given the product description and business goals below,
output a filled Metrics Framework following AARRR. For each metric include:
- exact definition (formula)
- data source
- whether it is a leading or lagging indicator
- why it is actionable (what decision changes if it moves)

Do NOT set targets — mark target fields as [NEEDS BASELINE].

Product: [description]
Goals: [goals]
]]>
      </prompt>
      <prompt purpose="vanity metric detection">
<![CDATA[
Review this proposed metric list and flag any that are vanity metrics.
For each vanity metric explain why and suggest an actionable replacement.
Apply this test: "If this metric changed by 20%, what would we do differently?"

Metrics: [list]
]]>
      </prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>For pulling baseline data and setting up metrics infrastructure, popular tools include: PostHog (OSS/SaaS, REST API with Python SDK), Mixpanel (SaaS, Events API), Amplitude (SaaS, Cohort API), Plausible (OSS/SaaS, simple stats API), Grafana (OSS, dashboards from any data source), Metabase (OSS/SaaS, SQL-based snapshots), and Stripe (SaaS, revenue metrics via API).</p>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://500hats.typepad.com/500blogs/2007/09/startup-metrics.html"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/north-star-metric"/>
      <link href="https://www.startup-marketing.com/the-startup-pyramid/"/>
      <link href="https://posthog.com/docs/product-analytics/funnels"/>
      <link href="https://amplitude.com/blog/product-metrics"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
