<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decompose one business goal into exactly 2-4 product outcomes. More than 4 outcomes from a single goal signals lack of focus and must be collapsed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Outcome trees with 6-8 branches dilute team attention and make experiment planning incoherent. Hard cap at 4 forces strategic prioritization before committing to measurement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every outcome must have a leading indicator measurable within 4 weeks. An outcome whose leading indicator requires more than 4 weeks to observe cannot support fast learning.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Slow leading indicators mean the team runs for a quarter before knowing if the outcome is moving. The 4-week constraint forces selection of leading (not lagging) metrics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every outcome must list 2-3 candidate experiments, not committed solutions. Listing solutions at the decomposition stage locks in an answer before the problem is understood.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Outcome roadmaps fail when they become feature roadmaps with outcome labels. Experiments must remain tentative until evidence promotes them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every outcome must include an "evidence we have" line and a "what we still need to learn" line. Confidence=high requires existing shipped data, not just a strong hypothesis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Confidence inflation — defaulting to "medium" or "high" without evidence — is the primary failure mode of outcome roadmaps. The evidence requirement makes confidence a checkable claim.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain one source-of-truth roadmap. Generate four audience views from it: theme-based (customers, no dates, no internal metrics), outcome-metric (board, quarterly targets, confidence column), outcome-plus-options (engineering, sprint-level when known), problem-solution (sales, only confirmed items get timing).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Four independent roadmap documents diverge immediately. Views generated from a single source remain synchronized and each line is traceable to a source row.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Customer-facing view stays at theme level for at least 2 quarters out ("better collaboration", not "real-time presence v2"). No internal metrics appear in the customer view.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Specific feature names in customer-facing roadmaps create commitment expectations the team may not be able to meet. Theme-level language preserves flexibility while communicating direction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sales view is the only view that mentions specific solutions, and only for items at high confidence. The other three views must not name solutions for items below high confidence.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sales commitment to a specific feature creates a contractual obligation in customer minds. Naming solutions only for high-confidence items limits the blast radius of delivery misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run the leading-indicator monitor weekly and propose promote/demote/replace actions to the PM. Quarterly, re-decompose the full goal tree. Re-version the roadmap only on real signal, not on every metric blip.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Rewriting the roadmap on every data point destroys stakeholder trust. The weekly/quarterly cadence separates tactical adjustments from strategic re-decomposition.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pair every roadmap presentation with a kill criterion: "if X does not move by Y, we drop this outcome." Forces honest stakes and prevents zombie outcomes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Outcomes without kill criteria become permanent features of the roadmap regardless of evidence. An explicit kill criterion makes the outcome falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use exactly three confidence levels: low, medium, high. More levels create false precision. Confidence=high requires shipped data on the surface; confidence=medium requires some data or reasonable analogues; confidence=low is hypothesis only.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A 5-level scale devolves into splitting hairs between "medium-high" and "high." The 3-level scale forces clean categorization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Board-facing roadmap leads with the metric movement, not the activity list. If a board member asks "where is the chat feature?", redirect to the outcome metric the feature is meant to move.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Boards skim metrics and ask about named features because named features feel concrete. Leading with the metric reframes the conversation to impact, not output.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
