<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-antipatterns" title="Outcome Roadmap Antipatterns: Confidence Inflation, View Drift, and Sales Pressure">
  <summary>The four recurring failure modes in outcome-based roadmaps and the rules that prevent each.</summary>

  <section title="Confidence Inflation">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Outcomes assigned confidence=medium or confidence=high without cited evidence. Agent defaults to "medium" because it sounds reasonable.</description>
      <reason>Uncalibrated confidence is opinion. Every confidence assertion must reference a query, dashboard URL, or an explicit "TO BE INSTRUMENTED" flag. Without it, the confidence column provides false precision that misleads planning.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use exactly three confidence levels: low, medium, high. More levels create false precision. Confidence=high requires shipped data on the surface; confidence=medium requires some data or reasonable analogues; confidence=low is hypothesis only.</statement>
      <rationale>A 5-level scale devolves into splitting hairs between "medium-high" and "high." The 3-level scale forces clean categorization.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="View Drift">
    <antipattern>
      <description>An audience view is edited directly rather than regenerated from the source of truth, causing the four views to diverge and contradict each other.</description>
      <reason>Direct edits to views break the single-source principle. When board and engineering views disagree, stakeholders lose confidence in all four. Run a daily diff job to flag lines in views without a source-of-truth trace.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Outcome Count Explosion">
    <antipattern>
      <description>A business goal decomposed into 6-8 outcomes because every stakeholder's priority gets included.</description>
      <reason>More outcomes = less focus = slower experiments = longer time-to-learn. The hard cap at 4 exists precisely because stakeholder pressure tends toward expansion. A PM must own the decomposition decision and defend the cap.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Sales Pressure">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Sales pressure causes specific features and dates to appear in the board view or customer view for items that are below high confidence.</description>
      <reason>Sales pressure is a political problem, not a roadmap format problem. Outcome framing reduces but does not eliminate it. Solving it requires agreement on which view each audience receives and enforcement of view boundaries by the PM.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Board-facing roadmap leads with the metric movement, not the activity list. If a board member asks "where is the chat feature?", redirect to the outcome metric the feature is meant to move.</statement>
      <rationale>Boards skim metrics and ask about named features because named features feel concrete. Leading with the metric reframes the conversation to impact, not output.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-decomposition.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/validate-outcome-tree.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
