<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Outcomes assigned confidence=medium or confidence=high without cited evidence. Agent defaults to "medium" because it sounds reasonable.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Uncalibrated confidence is opinion. Every confidence assertion must reference a query, dashboard URL, or an explicit "TO BE INSTRUMENTED" flag. Without it, the confidence column provides false precision that misleads planning.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>An audience view is edited directly rather than regenerated from the source of truth, causing the four views to diverge and contradict each other.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Direct edits to views break the single-source principle. When board and engineering views disagree, stakeholders lose confidence in all four. Run a daily diff job to flag lines in views without a source-of-truth trace.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>A business goal decomposed into 6-8 outcomes because every stakeholder's priority gets included.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>More outcomes = less focus = slower experiments = longer time-to-learn. The hard cap at 4 exists precisely because stakeholder pressure tends toward expansion. A PM must own the decomposition decision and defend the cap.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Sales pressure causes specific features and dates to appear in the board view or customer view for items that are below high confidence.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Sales pressure is a political problem, not a roadmap format problem. Outcome framing reduces but does not eliminate it. Solving it requires agreement on which view each audience receives and enforcement of view boundaries by the PM.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
