<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-assessment-types" title="Solution Assessment Types and Process">
  <summary>Four assessment types, five success criteria categories, five-step process, and assessment timing triggers.</summary>

  <section title="Four Assessment Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run four assessment types at distinct points: Design Assessment (during design — validate proposed solution meets requirements before build), Implementation Assessment (during build — verify correct implementation against spec), Deployment Assessment (at go-live — confirm readiness: QA, ops, support, training, security), Post-Implementation Assessment (after deployment at 30/60/90 days — measure actual delivered value).</statement>
      <rationale>A single end-of-project assessment misses implementation errors that could be fixed cheaply during build and cannot baseline-compare value because no pre-launch measurement was taken.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Five Success Criteria Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Business Value: ROI achieved, revenue increased, cost reduced — measured against original business case projections</item>
      <item>Functional: features work as specified in requirements — measured against requirements compliance table</item>
      <item>Performance: speed, reliability, scalability — measured against NFR thresholds defined in requirements</item>
      <item>Usability: user satisfaction score, adoption rate — measured via survey and analytics</item>
      <item>Compliance: regulatory requirements met — measured via audit findings and control effectiveness</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-Step Assessment Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — define assessment criteria and lock metric definitions with baseline queries. Step 2 — assess against requirements (compare actual to expected per requirement). Step 3 — evaluate business value (measure actuals against targets). Step 4 — identify limitations (document gaps and their business impact). Step 5 — recommend: accept, accept with remediation plan, require additional changes, or reject.</statement>
      <rationale>Steps without a defined order produce incomplete assessments; skipping step 1 (locking baselines) invalidates step 3 (value measurement).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Timing Triggers">
    <list>
      <item>Design complete → Design review assessment</item>
      <item>Sprint complete → Implementation check (sample requirements verified)</item>
      <item>Before go-live → Deployment readiness assessment</item>
      <item>30 days post go-live → Initial post-implementation assessment</item>
      <item>90 days post go-live → Full post-implementation assessment</item>
      <item>Annually → Ongoing value assessment (contract renewal, phase-gate)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/solution-assessment-report.md">Full assessment report template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/post-implementation-review.md">Post-launch review template</reference>
</text>
