<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-quality-rules" title="Solution Assessment Quality Rules">
  <summary>Evidence requirements, sample-size rules, variance thresholds, and common failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Evidence Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every metric verdict must cite at least one evidence URL with a retrieved_at timestamp. Never declare a metric "Met" based on memory, dashboard screenshots, or verbal reports — require a queryable primary source (analytics export, finance export, ticketing export).</statement>
      <rationale>Agents hallucinate KPI values when data connectors are missing; humans misremember or report the number that supports the conclusion they want. Primary source citation is the only defense.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every metric row must include sample size. A metric hit on n=12 is not a hit — it is statistically inconclusive. Require the original power calculation's minimum sample size before calling any metric "Met".</statement>
      <rationale>Small samples produce variance that cannot be distinguished from noise; declaring success on underpowered data leads to wasted follow-on investment and erodes trust in future assessments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Triangulate every business-value metric with at least two independent sources (e.g., analytics + finance, or analytics + survey). Single-source verdicts are fragile and gameable.</statement>
      <rationale>A single metric source can be manipulated by changing how the query is run; two independent sources must agree before a verdict is reliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Variance Thresholds">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use numeric variance bands for met/partial/not-met verdicts: variance ≥ 0% = Met; -15% to 0% = Partially Met; less than -15% = Not Met. Never use qualitative verdicts — "seems on track" is not a verdict.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs and humans both cluster verdicts in "partially met" when thresholds are not defined; numeric bands force a deterministic decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark requirements as "Deprecated" (not "Not Met") when the underlying business need has changed since the requirement was written. A binary Met/Not Met verdict on a stale requirement incorrectly penalizes the delivery team.</statement>
      <rationale>Requirements written 9 months before delivery may reflect a different business context; forcing a Met/Not Met verdict on stale requirements produces misleading assessment reports.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No baseline — cannot measure improvement. "Revenue went up after deployment" without a baseline is not a business value assessment.</description>
      <reason>Lock baselines before development starts using the same query and data source that will be used at assessment time.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Survey-only assessment under-samples churners — surveys reach users who still use the solution; the ones who churned never answer.</description>
      <reason>Reconcile survey n with active user count; flag if response rate is below 30% or if churned users are absent from the panel.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>One-shot assessment — a single 30-day report misses the honeymoon effect; real friction shows at 90+ days.</description>
      <reason>Run assessments at 30, 60, and 90 days; compare the three reports. A metric that was on-track at 30 and at-risk at 60 is the real story.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Assessor reports to the project sponsor whose bonus depends on the result — independence is compromised.</description>
      <reason>Route assessment through a different reporting chain or external reviewer. Independence is what gives the report weight at the steering committee.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="scripts/variance.py">Python script for variance calculation and statistical significance</reference>
</text>
