<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-pillars" title="Design System Four Pillars and Adoption Metrics">
  <summary>The four pillars of a successful design system (ownership, usable components, documentation, adoption) with an MVP launch sequence and measurable adoption metrics.</summary>

  <section title="Four Pillars">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign a single named owner or team with authority and accountability for the design system before any other work begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Systems with diffuse or absent ownership drift: no one decides breaking changes, documentation goes stale, and consumer teams lose trust and fork. Ownership is the first pillar because all others depend on it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Components must be adoptable as-is by consumer teams without local overrides; if a component requires frequent customization to use, it is not usable enough.</statement>
      <rationale>High override rates indicate the component does not fit real use cases. Components that need workarounds get bypassed — driving snowflake CSS growth rather than coverage improvement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Documentation must be discoverable and current; a page count that drifts from source code is worse than no documentation because it actively misleads consumers.</statement>
      <rationale>Stale docs erode trust faster than gaps. Consumers learn to distrust the docs and stop consulting them, creating a negative feedback loop where documentation becomes irrelevant.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the system as a product with a roadmap and SLAs, not a side project; measure adoption monthly and publish coverage metrics visibly to consumer teams.</statement>
      <rationale>Peer visibility of coverage metrics outperforms top-down mandates for driving adoption. Teams that see their coverage percentage relative to peers improve it without explicit directives.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="MVP Launch Sequence">
    <p>Start with the minimum viable system: core interactive components, design tokens (color, spacing, typography), brand colors, and a small pattern library. Launch, stress-test with one consumer product, gather feedback, then grow iteratively. Launching too large creates debt before validation.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Adoption Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure component coverage as the percentage of UI primitives (button, input, card, modal) sourced from the system versus implemented locally; count at the render site, not the import statement.</statement>
      <rationale>Import-level counting is gameable — a team may import the Button and use it once while implementing 40 custom buttons locally. Render-site AST scanning via ts-morph provides the actual usage picture.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Component coverage: % of UI primitives using system components vs local implementations</item>
      <item>Adoption rate: number of active consumer teams using the system package</item>
      <item>Contribution rate: external PRs merged to the system per quarter</item>
      <item>Bug/issue count: open issues by priority as a quality proxy</item>
      <item>Design-dev sync: % of semantic tokens matching between Figma and code</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/ds-coverage.mjs">AST-based Node script counting system vs snowflake primitive usage across consumer apps</reference>
  </section>
</text>
