<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="design-system-success-factors Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for design-system-success-factors as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent fabricating adoption percentage by counting import statements without counting render sites.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A team may import the Button once and implement 40 custom buttons locally. Import-level counting inflates coverage metrics; render-site AST scanning (ts-morph) provides the actual figure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM generating components that re-implement existing system primitives because the catalogue was not provided as context.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without the system's catalogue (Storybook index.json or package exports), the agent does not know what already exists and will write duplicate components that increase snowflake usage.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Token rename PRs from agents missing CSS-in-JS template literals and Tailwind config references.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>AST token rename tools typically handle import paths and property access, but miss string-interpolated CSS-in-JS patterns and Tailwind config keys. Require a second-pass regex sweep before merging.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent-authored PRs merging to consumer app main branches without per-app release-train coordination.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Codemods to unrelated apps must respect their release schedules. Auto-merging into main of unrelated apps can ship breaking visual changes ahead of their release cycle.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
