<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ACME TLS Renewal Automation Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the cicd-tls-renewal-automation methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced by the decision tree.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="systemd-timer-not-cron" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ACME renewal MUST run under a systemd timer with `OnFailure=` alert hook; cron is forbidden because failed renewals are silent.</statement>
      <rationale source="systemd.timer manual, ACME docs">Cron mail-only failure reporting is ignored at scale; systemd integrates with journald + alerting.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="renewal-hook-reload" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A renewal hook MUST gracefully reload the consuming service (`nginx -s reload`, `systemctl reload haproxy`); without it, a renewed cert sits unused until next deploy.</statement>
      <rationale source="certbot docs — deploy hooks">Cert file refreshed on disk doesn't reach the listener without reload; the practical effect is no renewal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="staging-then-prod" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>First-time ACME issuance MUST run against the issuer's staging environment first, then production; rate-limit lockouts from a misconfigured prod attempt take 7 days to recover.</statement>
      <rationale source="Let's Encrypt rate-limit docs">ACME rate limits are unforgiving; the staging endpoint exists specifically to avoid them.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="expiry-alert-14-days" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prometheus / blackbox_exporter MUST alert when any served cert has &lt; 14 days to expiry, independent of the renewal job's own logs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Prometheus blackbox_exporter docs">Renewal job success ≠ cert delivered; only a probe against the live listener confirms the chain.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="dns-01-for-wildcards" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Wildcard certs (`*.example.com`) MUST use DNS-01 challenge; HTTP-01 MUST NOT be attempted for wildcards.</statement>
      <rationale source="Let's Encrypt challenges docs">HTTP-01 cannot satisfy a wildcard; the issuer will reject and rate-limit budget burns.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If TLS is managed by ACM / GCP managed cert / Cloudflare proxy with auto-renewal, this methodology MUST be skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud provider docs">Self-hosted ACME duplicates the managed path and creates two rotation surfaces.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
