<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-patterns" title="Cognitive Inclusion Design Patterns by Profile">
  <summary>Concrete design patterns for four cognitive profiles: general cognitive load reduction, ADHD, autism spectrum, and dyslexia.</summary>

  <section title="General Cognitive Load Reduction">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure all content with a clear visual hierarchy, chunk information into groups of 5 or fewer items, and make navigation predictable and consistent across screens.</statement>
      <rationale>Working memory limits apply to all users; cognitive disabilities lower the threshold, so patterns that reduce load universally provide the highest inclusion return.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Clear heading hierarchy — users scan by heading, not by reading paragraph by paragraph.</item>
      <item>Non-intrusive notifications — user-controllable timing and position.</item>
      <item>Error messages — plain language, non-blaming ("The email address looks incomplete" not "Invalid input"), with a clear corrective action.</item>
      <item>Time limits — extend or eliminate where possible; always warn before expiry and offer extension without loss of progress.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="ADHD-Friendly Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide progress indicators for all multi-step tasks, auto-save on every input, and a bookmark/resume capability for long flows.</statement>
      <rationale>ADHD impairs working memory and sustained attention; losing progress on interruption causes abandonment and distrust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Progress indicators: step N of M, percentage complete, or visual stepper.</item>
      <item>Auto-save: triggered on every field blur or every 30 seconds — never on page close only.</item>
      <item>Reduced-motion option: provided as a settings toggle, not assumed system-wide via prefers-reduced-motion alone.</item>
      <item>Focus mode: hides non-essential navigation and ambient content during task completion.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Autism-Friendly Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use literal, unambiguous language throughout — no idioms, metaphors, or sarcasm — and warn users before any screen transition or state change.</statement>
      <rationale>Ambiguous language and unexpected transitions are common sources of anxiety and disorientation for autistic users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Predictable interactions: same action always produces same result across the product.</item>
      <item>Clear visual boundaries between content regions.</item>
      <item>Sensory-friendly color palettes: avoid high saturation or flashing content; offer a low-stimulation theme.</item>
      <item>Transition warnings: modal or inline notice before navigating away from a partially-completed task.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Dyslexia-Friendly Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set default line height to at least 1.5, left-align all body text (never justify), and offer a dyslexia-friendly font as an opt-in setting rather than a global default.</statement>
      <rationale>Justified text creates uneven word spacing that disrupts reading flow for dyslexic readers; left-aligned text preserves consistent spacing. Dyslexia fonts (e.g., OpenDyslexic) have weak empirical support as universal defaults but are valued by individual users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Letter spacing: offer a setting to increase spacing to at least 0.12em.</item>
      <item>High contrast modes: multiple options beyond system dark mode.</item>
      <item>Text-to-speech integration: accessible via keyboard, not hidden in menus.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
