<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Cognitive Inclusion Design Rules and Agent Limitations">
  <summary>Testable rules for implementing cognitive inclusion, with evidence caveats and known agent failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Implementation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Make all cognitive customization settings (font, spacing, motion, focus mode) discoverable, persistent across sessions, and accessible without navigating into deep settings menus.</statement>
      <rationale>A customization option that users cannot find or that resets on each visit provides zero benefit; discoverability and persistence are the minimum viability bar.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not remove motion globally based on prefers-reduced-motion alone; audit which animations are critical (focus indicators, progress feedback) before suppressing them.</statement>
      <rationale>Indiscriminate motion removal breaks critical feedback signals that sighted users rely on for orientation; targeted suppression preserves function.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Review time-limit removal with the security team; session-timeout limits may be non-negotiable security requirements that need a joint UX + security solution.</statement>
      <rationale>Time limits often exist for security reasons; unilateral removal creates vulnerabilities that require a coordinated design rather than a UX-only decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Evidence Caveats">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying a dyslexia font (e.g., OpenDyslexic) as the global default for all users.</description>
      <reason>Empirical evidence for dyslexia fonts as universal defaults is weak; offer as a user-controlled option rather than imposing on users who may find it harder to read.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using plain-language rewriting as a substitute for plain-language editing of the original content.</description>
      <reason>Cognitive design patterns assume content is already written in plain language; restructuring a screen cannot fix fundamentally complex or jargon-heavy source text.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent runs automated tools only and declares cognitive accessibility addressed.</description>
      <reason>Automated tools cannot detect cognitive issues; structured manual review plus user research with cognitively diverse participants is required.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent rewrites branded copy to plain language without coordinating with the tone-of-voice guidelines.</description>
      <reason>Plain-language rewriting can conflict with brand voice; an exception list for branded terms and voice must be agreed before bulk rewrites.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
