<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="cognitive-inclusion-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for cognitive-inclusion-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>"Dyslexia-friendly fonts" (e.g., OpenDyslexic) have weak empirical support—provide as option, not default.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Empirical evidence for dyslexia fonts as universal defaults is weak; offer as a user-controlled option rather than imposing on users who may find it harder to read.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Customization (font, color, spacing) only helps if discoverable and persistent across sessions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A hidden or session-reset setting provides zero benefit; implementation is as critical as the design pattern itself.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Plain-language and "literal language" can clash with branded voice; product needs a tone-of-voice exception list.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cognitive design patterns assume content is already written in plain language; restructuring a screen cannot fix fundamentally complex or jargon-heavy source text.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Reducing motion globally can break critical animations (focus indicators, progress feedback).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Indiscriminate motion removal breaks critical feedback signals; scope carefully and test with users relying on animation for navigation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Time-limit removal can collide with security session timeouts—needs UX + security joint review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Some time limits exist for security reasons; unilateral removal creates vulnerabilities that require coordinated design.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Most automated tools cannot detect cognitive issues; requires structured manual review + user research.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cognitive accessibility requires human evaluation. Automated tools cover only syntactic checks (headings, labels); they cannot evaluate reading level, mental model alignment, or interaction flow clarity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents add jargon to "sound professional"—enforce a banned-word list (utilize → use, leverage → use, etc.).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLM default tone is formal and jargon-heavy. Provide a banned-word list and require ≤20 words/sentence + ≤2 ideas per sentence.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs default to long sentences; require max 20 words/sentence and ≤2 ideas per sentence.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cognitive inclusion requires short, simple sentences. Explicit constraints prevent complex sentence structures.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents apply OpenDyslexic globally—keep it opt-in; default font choice is contested.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>OpenDyslexic empirical support is weak. Treat as user-optional, not default.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>"Reduce motion" agent adds * { animation: none } blanket rule, breaking focus indicators—scope carefully.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Indiscriminate motion removal breaks critical UX. Audit which animations are essential (focus, progress) before suppressing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Time-limit removal vs. security session: agent must surface this as a trade-off, not silently extend.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Some time limits are security-critical. Agent must alert humans to this conflict instead of unilaterally removing the limit.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents recommend overlay widgets—refuse; document fix at source.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Overlay widgets cannot fix structural issues and may worsen accessibility.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Cognitive needs are heterogeneous; avoid grouping users by diagnosis. Design for needs (focus, time, structure), not labels.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Two autistic users may have completely different needs. Design for underlying needs (structure, literal language) rather than diagnostic labels.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
