<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Acceptance Criteria Framework">
  <summary>BDD and rule-based formats, five coverage categories, and the five-step authoring process.</summary>

  <section title="Format Options">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Given-When-Then (BDD) format for scenarios with distinct preconditions and user actions — one scenario per behavior path. Use rule-based checklist format for lists of system constraints and validation rules with no actor interaction sequence.</statement>
      <rationale>BDD format is tool-executable (Cucumber, SpecFlow) and enforces context-action-outcome structure; checklist format is faster for pure validation rules but lacks scenario context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>BDD template: "Given [precondition/context] / And [additional condition] / When [action taken] / Then [expected outcome] / And [additional outcome]". Each Given-When-Then block is one scenario and produces at least one test case.</statement>
      <rationale>One-to-one mapping between scenarios and test cases makes coverage measurement deterministic.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Five Coverage Categories">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every requirement must have acceptance criteria covering at minimum: happy path (everything works), at least one alternative path (valid variation), at least one boundary condition, at least one error handling case, and any applicable non-functional constraints (performance, security).</statement>
      <rationale>Happy-path-only criteria are the most common acceptance criteria failure; missing alternative and error scenarios are discovered during UAT when correction cost is highest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Happy path: what happens when all inputs are valid and system is in normal state</item>
      <item>Alternatives: valid variations in actor actions or system state</item>
      <item>Boundaries: limit values (min, max, exactly-at-limit, just-over-limit)</item>
      <item>Errors: invalid input, system failure, business rule violation</item>
      <item>Non-functional: specific performance thresholds, security access controls</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-Step Authoring Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — understand the requirement: identify the actor goal, expected outcome, what could go wrong, and where the boundaries are. Step 2 — choose format (BDD vs. checklist). Step 3 — write criteria covering all five categories. Step 4 — validate with Product Owner, developers, and QA. Step 5 — use each criterion as a test case trigger in the Definition of Done.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping validation with QA produces untestable criteria; skipping validation with developers produces technically infeasible criteria — both discovered at the wrong time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/ac-bdd.md">BDD format template with scenarios</reference>
  <reference path="templates/ac-checklist.md">Rule-based checklist template</reference>
</text>
