<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-quality-rules" title="Acceptance Criteria Quality Rules">
  <summary>Testability rules, story-type guidelines, and common mistakes with their consequences.</summary>

  <section title="Testability Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every acceptance criterion must be independently testable: there must exist a concrete action that produces a verifiable, observable outcome. Reject any criterion that is subjective ("user-friendly"), implementation-specific ("store in MySQL"), or unmeasurable ("fast").</statement>
      <rationale>Untestable criteria cannot be included in the Definition of Done; they become subjective acceptance disputes at delivery time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Performance criteria must specify exact numeric thresholds: "Response time under 2 seconds at 95th percentile under 500 concurrent users" — not "the system must be fast".</statement>
      <rationale>Without a numeric threshold, QA cannot write a load test and "fast" means different things to every stakeholder.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Security criteria must specify the role and the prohibited or required action: "Only users with Admin role can delete customer records." Never "the system must be secure."</statement>
      <rationale>Role-based security criteria map directly to authorization test cases; vague security statements map to nothing testable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Story Type Guidelines">
    <p>Feature stories: focus on user outcomes, cover happy path and at least 2 alternative scenarios, include error handling, add performance criteria only if the feature has a response-time requirement.</p>
    <p>Bug fixes: describe expected vs. actual behavior precisely, include reproduction steps, define the "fixed" state as an observable outcome.</p>
    <p>Technical stories: focus on technical outcomes (throughput, error rate, API contract), include a measurable verification method, define "done" as a observable system state or metric.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Too vague: "User can log in" — no context, no error handling, no boundary conditions.</description>
      <reason>Vague criteria cannot produce test cases; every meaningful word in a criterion must be independently testable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Implementation details: "Store session token in Redis with 30-minute TTL" — the how, not the what.</description>
      <reason>Implementation criteria couple the spec to a specific technical choice; when the implementation changes the criteria become false without the behavior changing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Only happy path: no error scenarios, no boundary conditions.</description>
      <reason>Error paths are discovered during UAT; correcting them after development costs 10x more than specifying them upfront.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Too many criteria for one story: 50+ criteria indicate the story should be split.</description>
      <reason>A story with 50 criteria takes a sprint to test; split into smaller stories that can be independently accepted and deployed.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
