<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Acceptance Criteria Examples">
  <summary>Login feature with three BDD scenarios, shopping cart as rule-based checklist, and the requirement-to-test-case hierarchy.</summary>

  <section title="Login Feature: BDD Format">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="gherkin"><![CDATA[
Scenario 1: Successful login
  Given I am on the login page
  And I have a valid registered account
  When I enter my correct email and password
  And I click "Login"
  Then I am redirected to the dashboard
  And I see a welcome message containing my first name
  And my session is active for 30 minutes

Scenario 2: Invalid credentials
  Given I am on the login page
  When I enter an incorrect email or password
  And I click "Login"
  Then I see the error message "Invalid email or password"
  And I remain on the login page
  And the password field is cleared

Scenario 3: Account locked after repeated failures
  Given I have failed login 5 consecutive times
  When I attempt to log in again
  Then I see "Account locked. Try again in 30 minutes."
  And login attempts are rejected for 30 minutes for this account

Non-functional:
  - Login request must complete within 2 seconds (p95, production load)
  - Password must not appear in application logs or network responses
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Shopping Cart: Checklist Format">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Functional criteria:
- [ ] User can add a product to the cart from the product detail page
- [ ] User can add a product to the cart from search results
- [ ] Cart icon in the header shows current item count
- [ ] Adding the same product increments quantity (no duplicate line items)
- [ ] Maximum quantity per product per cart is 99
- [ ] User sees a confirmation notification when an item is added

Persistence criteria:
- [ ] Cart persists for 30 days for logged-in users
- [ ] Cart persists for the browser session duration for guest users

Validation criteria:
- [ ] Out-of-stock products cannot be added to the cart
- [ ] Quantity field accepts only positive integers between 1 and 99
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Requirement to Test Case Hierarchy">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Shows how one requirement expands to multiple AC which expand to multiple test cases.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
REQ-045: Password Reset
  AC-1 (BDD): Successful reset via email link
    TC-1a: Valid reset link navigates to password entry form
    TC-1b: Valid new password updates credential and logs user in
  AC-2 (BDD): Expired reset link
    TC-2a: Expired link shows "Link expired" error
    TC-2b: User can request a new reset link after expiry
  AC-3 (checklist): Password rules
    TC-3a: Password under 8 characters is rejected
    TC-3b: Password without uppercase letter is rejected
    TC-3c: Password matching previous 3 passwords is rejected
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
