<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="LB Session Persistence Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>3 antipatterns observed when sticky sessions are configured. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="ip-hash-corporate-nat" severity="high">
      <symptom>One backend in the pool always shows 4× the load of peers. Investigation: a single corporate customer's 5000 employees all share one NAT egress IP.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="HAProxy + Nginx sticky-session docs">`ip_hash` (or `balance source`) used for sticky sessions; collapses NAT users onto one backend.</root-cause>
      <fix>Switch to cookie-based persistence (`cookie SRVID insert indirect nocache` in HAProxy; app-managed cookie or Nginx Plus sticky cookie). Verify load evens out within a check interval.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="sticky-after-redis-migration" severity="medium">
      <symptom>App was migrated to Redis-backed sessions a year ago, but the LB config still has `cookie SRVID ... maxconn 100`. Deploys are slow because operators "must drain stickies".</symptom>
      <root-cause source="HAProxy + ASG migration patterns">Stickiness config was never removed after externalising session storage.</root-cause>
      <fix>Remove sticky directives. Pool returns to even distribution + deploys become straightforward rolling restarts. Confirm app sessions still work via end-to-end test.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="unbounded-sticky" severity="medium">
      <symptom>A backend was rolled out of the pool 3 days ago but is still receiving stray traffic from a small set of clients; rolling deploys never seem to "finish".</symptom>
      <root-cause source="HAProxy stick-table docs">Sticky cookie has no TTL; entries persist until the LB process restarts.</root-cause>
      <fix>Add `expire 1h` to stick-table or `cookie SRVID insert indirect nocache maxidle 3600 maxlife 86400`. Confirm stickiness expires on schedule by replaying logs.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
