<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Partnership Co-Marketing Playbook Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Partnership Co-Marketing Playbook MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="icp-overlap-threshold" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Partnership MUST be backed by &gt;=60% ICP overlap (named segment match). Below threshold, partnership wastes both audiences.</statement>
      <rationale source="Partnership audit 2025">Low-overlap partnerships generate 5-10x worse leads; both sides lose audience trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="audience-density-match" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audience sizes MUST be within 3x of each other (e.g., 1k vs. 3k OK, 1k vs. 10k not). Asymmetric audiences collapse the deal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal partnership debrief data">Larger-audience partner sees smaller as freeloader; expectations misalign; partnership ends bitter.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="attribution-plan-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST include shared UTM + post-event survey + lead-attribution split. Un-attributed partnerships cannot be evaluated.</statement>
      <rationale source="Attribution audit practice">Without attribution, both sides assume the other got more value; no second collaboration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="single-asset-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each partnership MUST commit to exactly one joint asset (webinar OR report OR bundle) — not bundles of bundles.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal partnership debrief data">Multi-asset partnerships over-extend both teams; success rate drops 60%.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="exit-criteria-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST list exit criteria (lead-quality threshold, audience growth, re-collaboration trigger). Indefinite partnerships are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene">Without exits, dead partnerships consume calendar slots that could fund new ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
