<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Customer Journey Mapping Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Customer Journey Mapping. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-evidence-anchored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every stage in the map cites at least one piece of qualitative or quantitative evidence — interview quote, ticket ID, or analytics event.</statement>
      <rationale source="Service-design literature">Evidence-free maps are opinion documents that drift across re-tellings.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-shared-with-stakeholders" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The map is co-created with at least one representative from product, design, engineering, and support; solo journey maps drift quickly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cross-functional service-design practice">Single-author maps reproduce that author's assumptions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-pain-points-prioritised" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pain points are scored by impact and frequency; the top three become the action backlog with named owners.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Unprioritised lists rarely turn into work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-touchpoint-grain" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Touchpoints are at the channel grain (email, in-app, support call), not feature grain; feature-grain detail belongs in user-flow diagrams.</statement>
      <rationale source="Service-design grain rules">Mixing grains makes the map both too detailed and too vague.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-emotion-lane" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An emotion lane is included and populated from real user quotes, not inferred sentiment.</statement>
      <rationale source="UX-research practice">Inferred emotion reflects team bias, not user reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-journey-mapping.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
