<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Customer Journey Mapping — 7-Step Process">
  <summary>Structured procedure for creating research-grounded journey maps that expose cross-channel friction and drive prioritized improvements.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Scope">
    <rule>
      <statement>Specify the persona, journey type, start point, end point, and channels in scope before beginning research.</statement>
      <rationale>A journey map without a defined persona and scope conflates the experiences of different user types and collapses important variation. Scope drives which data to collect.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Questions: Which persona? Which journey (purchase, onboarding, support)? Defined start and end points? Which channels are in scope?</p>
    <p>Journey types: Current state (diagnose problems), Future state (design target), Day-in-the-life (broader context), Service blueprint (includes backstage operations).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Gather Research">
    <rule>
      <statement>Base the map on actual research data — interviews, observation, analytics, support tickets, surveys. Never map from assumption.</statement>
      <rationale>A map built from internal assumptions reflects how the team thinks the product works, not how users experience it. Assumption-based maps reinforce existing blind spots rather than exposing them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Data sources: user interviews, observational studies, analytics, support data, surveys, employee interviews from customer-facing roles.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Identify Stages">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define 4-8 major stages that represent distinct phases of the user's experience. Each stage should have a clear user goal.</statement>
      <rationale>Fewer than 4 stages over-compresses the experience and hides friction. More than 8 stages produce unmaintainable maps that teams cannot use in workshops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Example e-commerce journey: Awareness → Research → Purchase → Delivery → Use → Support.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Map Actions and Touchpoints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document what users do (actions) and where they interact with the product/service (touchpoints) separately for each stage.</statement>
      <rationale>Conflating actions and touchpoints obscures whether friction is in user behavior or in a specific channel. Separate rows allow targeted intervention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/journey-map.md">Full map table with rows for actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Add Emotions and Thoughts">
    <rule>
      <statement>Record emotional state and cognitive questions at each stage — not what the user should feel, but what research shows they actually feel.</statement>
      <rationale>Emotion curves reveal where user confidence drops or anxiety spikes — these are the highest-leverage intervention points. Assuming positive emotion at product touchpoints is the most common mapping error.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Identify Pain Points and Opportunities">
    <rule>
      <statement>Distinguish pain points (current friction) from opportunities (actionable improvements). Every pain point should have at least one opportunity attached.</statement>
      <rationale>Pain points without opportunities produce a list of problems with no forward motion. Opportunities without pain points are speculation. The pairing anchors design work to diagnosed need.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 7: Visualize and Prioritize">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize opportunities by combination of user impact (frequency and severity of pain) and organizational effort to address.</statement>
      <rationale>Unprioritized opportunity lists produce no action — teams debate importance without a framework. Impact-effort prioritization produces a decision, not a discussion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/stage-detail.md">Per-stage detail template for deep-dive documentation</reference>
  </section>
</text>
