<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Customer Journey Mapping — Examples and Common Mistakes">
  <summary>E-commerce purchase journey example with stage-by-stage breakdown and key insight generation.</summary>

  <section title="E-commerce Purchase Journey Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Stages: Discover → Research → Decide → Purchase → Receive → Use. Discover: user searches, sees ad; emotion Curious; pain "hard to find what I need." Research: compares options; emotion Engaged; pain "too many choices." Decide: reads reviews; emotion Uncertain; pain "conflicting reviews." Purchase: checkout; emotion Anxious; pain "long form, hidden fees." Receive: tracks order; emotion Impatient; pain "no tracking updates." Use: unboxes; emotion varies; pain "not as expected." Key insight: Checkout produces the highest anxiety and has the most friction — simplifying checkout is the highest-leverage opportunity.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage Metrics by Journey Phase">
    <p>Awareness: reach, impressions. Consideration: engagement, time on site. Purchase: conversion rate. Onboarding: activation rate. Usage: retention, engagement. Support: resolution time, CSAT. Loyalty: NPS, repeat purchase rate.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Attach at least one measurable metric to each stage so improvements can be tracked quantitatively after implementation.</statement>
      <rationale>Journey maps without metrics remain a soft deliverable. Metrics convert the map from a qualitative description into a measurement framework that tracks change over time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Creating a journey map from team assumptions rather than user research.</description>
      <reason>Teams consistently underestimate user anxiety at handoff points and overestimate satisfaction at product touchpoints. Assumption maps reinforce these biases rather than correcting them.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Mapping actions only — no emotions or thoughts row in the map.</description>
      <reason>Actions without emotional context miss the moments where users are most at risk of abandonment or error. The emotion curve is where prioritization decisions come from.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating the journey map as a one-time workshop output never to be updated.</description>
      <reason>Journeys change when products, policies, or channels change. A stale map actively misleads teams by presenting an outdated picture as current reality. Schedule map reviews after major product changes.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Creating the map in a silo without cross-functional team participation.</description>
      <reason>Journey maps reveal problems that span organizational boundaries. Without the relevant teams present, the map does not produce cross-team ownership of the pain points it surfaces.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
