<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="journey-mapping Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for journey-mapping as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating a journey map from team assumptions rather than user research.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Teams consistently underestimate user anxiety at handoff points and overestimate satisfaction at product touchpoints. Assumption maps reinforce these biases rather than correcting them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Mapping actions only — no emotions or thoughts row in the map.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Actions without emotional context miss the moments where users are most at risk of abandonment or error. The emotion curve is where prioritization decisions come from and is often the most revealing output of the map.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating the journey map as a one-time workshop output never to be updated.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Customer behavior changes faster than maps are updated — stale maps get cited in decisions they no longer support. Schedule map reviews after major product or policy changes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating the map in a silo without cross-functional team participation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Journey maps reveal problems that span organizational boundaries. Without the relevant teams present, the map does not produce cross-team ownership of the pain points it surfaces. The workshop format is not just output production; it is alignment and commitment.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Emotion curves added as decoration rather than derived from research.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Teams draw what they expect users to feel, not what research reveals. A user might feel relief at a product touchpoint because they were terrified at an earlier stage (company's fault) — drawing the emotion curve incorrectly erases this context.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Collapsing the diversity of user experiences into a single persona path, masking segment-level differences.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Different user segments experience the product very differently. A map for the "power user" misses pain points of the "occasional user"; a map for the "early adopter" does not surface issues for the "skeptical enterprise buyer." Create separate maps per segment or note explicitly where segment paths diverge.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>In B2B contexts, conflating the "user" (person doing the task) with the "decision-maker" (person who defines success).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>B2B journey maps are especially unreliable because the person using the product and the person justifying the expense are different people with different goals. Map both, or note explicitly if the map shows only the user's perspective.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
