<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-viral-loops Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-viral-loops. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick ONE primary loop type and instrument it completely before designing a second; multi-loop products without a baseline K cannot diagnose regressions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Adding a second loop before the first is measured creates attribution confusion — you cannot tell which loop is driving new users or why K changed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Anchor K-factor expectations to category benchmarks before designing — consumer apps: K=0.1–0.3; B2B SaaS: K=0.05–0.2. Designing for K &gt; 0.5 leads to dark-pattern mechanics.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">K &gt; 1 is rare and unstable; most successful products operate at K = 0.1–0.4 and use the viral lift to reduce CAC rather than achieve exponential growth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Measure cycle time (p50 days from share to invitee activation) and treat it as a lever equal in importance to i and c — halving cycle time roughly squares compounding over a quarter.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">K = 0.4 with 3-day cycle time produces more users in 90 days than K = 0.7 with 60-day cycle time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat the invitee landing page as the highest-priority optimization surface — most loops fail at conversion, not at sharing.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Improving the landing page conversion rate multiplies every future loop turn; share-side improvements only increase volume into the current conversion rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never require signup to view shared content; a preview wall converts better than a hard gate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hard gates drop invitee conversion by 40–60%; previewing the value before requiring signup is the correct pattern for most content and social loops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Embed branding in user output only where it adds value to the recipient (source credit, attribution) — not as a tax that degrades the artifact.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Embedded branding used as a watermark without value to the recipient is perceived as spam; watermarks with source credit (Canva designs, Notion exports) are accepted because they provide context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plan to redesign embedded-branding loops every 12–18 months; users learn the pattern and conversion decays as familiarity removes novelty.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Loops are not permanent — the pattern becomes ambient within 12–18 months and the invitee motivation ("what is this?") disappears.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
