<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-loop-types" title="Viral Loop Types and Product Match Guide">
  <summary>Seven viral loop types, their mechanics, canonical examples, and a product-type match guide for selecting the right primary loop.</summary>

  <section title="Seven Loop Types">
    <list>
      <item>Inherent: product requires or fails to deliver core value without inviting others (Slack, Zoom). Test: does the product fail to work without the invitee?</item>
      <item>Word of mouth: users talk about the product unprompted (Apple, Notion). Requires a strong product story; cannot be engineered directly.</item>
      <item>Incentivized: explicit rewards for referrals — cash, credits, features (Dropbox +500MB, Uber credits). Measurable, tunable, fraud-prone.</item>
      <item>Social: user output is visible to non-users, creating FOMO (Spotify Wrapped, Wordle). Requires shareable artifacts.</item>
      <item>Collaborative: product improves or requires collaboration, pulling in teammates (Figma, Notion docs). Natural for B2B / team tools.</item>
      <item>Content: users create content that carries branding and CTAs (Canva designs, TikTok). Requires user-generated artifacts with embedded attribution.</item>
      <item>Embedded: product name appears in output ("Made with X", "Sent via X"). Low friction, low K, good for awareness at scale.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Product-Type Match Guide">
    <list>
      <item>B2C social / media: Social + Content loops</item>
      <item>B2B team tools: Collaborative + Inherent loops</item>
      <item>Productivity SaaS: Embedded + Word of mouth loops</item>
      <item>Marketplace: Inherent + Incentivized loops</item>
      <item>Consumer subscription (low viral): Incentivized loop as primary</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick ONE primary loop type and instrument it completely before designing a second; multi-loop products without a baseline K cannot diagnose regressions.</statement>
      <rationale>Adding a second loop before the first is measured creates attribution confusion — you cannot tell which loop is driving new users or why K changed.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Loop Anatomy">
    <p>Every loop has five structural elements. Define all five before engineering:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Action: what the user does that triggers the loop (completes a task, creates a document, achieves a milestone)</item>
      <item>Artifact: what is created or shared as output (badge, report, invite link, branded content)</item>
      <item>Distribution: how the artifact reaches potential new users (social share, email, in-product, search-indexable)</item>
      <item>Motivation: why a new user would want to join after seeing the artifact (FOMO, utility, social connection)</item>
      <item>Friction: steps to join from artifact exposure (target: one-click signup from invite link)</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
