<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-design-rules" title="Viral Loop Design Rules">
  <summary>Actionable design rules for viral loops: K-factor category expectations, cycle time, invitee landing page priority, friction reduction, and embedded branding.</summary>

  <section title="K-Factor Expectations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor K-factor expectations to category benchmarks before designing — consumer apps: K=0.1–0.3; B2B SaaS: K=0.05–0.2. Designing for K &gt; 0.5 leads to dark-pattern mechanics.</statement>
      <rationale>K &gt; 1 is rare and unstable; most successful products operate at K = 0.1–0.4 and use the viral lift to reduce CAC rather than achieve exponential growth.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cycle Time">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure cycle time (p50 days from share to invitee activation) and treat it as a lever equal in importance to i and c — halving cycle time roughly squares compounding over a quarter.</statement>
      <rationale>K = 0.4 with 3-day cycle time produces more users in 90 days than K = 0.7 with 60-day cycle time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>reduce cycle time: one-click signup for invitees, social login, pre-filled email from invite token</item>
      <item>monitor cycle_time_p50 weekly; sudden increase signals friction introduced by a signup or onboarding change</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Invitee Landing Page Priority">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the invitee landing page as the highest-priority optimization surface — most loops fail at conversion, not at sharing.</statement>
      <rationale>Improving the landing page conversion rate multiplies every future loop turn; share-side improvements only increase volume into the current conversion rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>show inviter name and avatar prominently</item>
      <item>display value preview before requiring signup</item>
      <item>one-click signup (Google/Apple SSO or email magic link)</item>
      <item>pre-fill email address from invite token</item>
      <item>mobile-optimize: target &lt;= 3 taps from invite link to activated account</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Friction Reduction">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never require signup to view shared content; a preview wall converts better than a hard gate.</statement>
      <rationale>Hard gates drop invitee conversion by 40–60%; previewing the value before requiring signup is the correct pattern for most content and social loops.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Embedded Branding Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Embed branding in user output only where it adds value to the recipient (source credit, attribution) — not as a tax that degrades the artifact.</statement>
      <rationale>Embedded branding used as a watermark without value to the recipient is perceived as spam; watermarks with source credit (Canva designs, Notion exports) are accepted because they provide context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Plan to redesign embedded-branding loops every 12–18 months; users learn the pattern and conversion decays as familiarity removes novelty.</statement>
      <rationale>Loops are not permanent — the pattern becomes ambient within 12–18 months and the invitee motivation ("what is this?") disappears.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
