<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Viral Loop Case Studies">
  <summary>Three canonical viral loop case studies — Dropbox (incentivized), Spotify Wrapped (social), Notion templates (content) — analyzed by loop anatomy and key success factors.</summary>

  <section title="Dropbox: Incentivized Loop">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Loop anatomy: user needs more storage → refers a friend → friend signs up → both get 500MB → friend needs more storage → loop repeats. Key factors: clear two-sided value exchange, obvious placement, instant reward delivery, shareable link. Result: 60% of signups from referrals, 35% permanent increase in signups. Note: contact-import element of this model is blocked by iOS/Android post-2021.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Spotify Wrapped: Social Loop">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Loop anatomy: user listens to music all year → Spotify creates personalized annual summary → user shares on social → friends see it and want their own → non-users download Spotify. Key factors: zero effort to create the artifact, designed for social sharing, FOMO for non-users, annual ritual creates predictable spike. Result: millions of social shares, significant December download spike.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Notion Templates: Content Loop">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Loop anatomy: power user creates a template → shares publicly in Notion gallery or community → others find template via search → need Notion to use it → some become template creators. Key factors: user-generated content, SEO-friendly (indexed by Google), real standalone utility, clear attribution. Loop is SEO-compounding: templates accumulate in search over time.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas for Loop Design">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent recommends auto-DM friends, contact upload without consent, or "share with all contacts" mechanics.</description>
      <reason>These violate platform TOS (LinkedIn, Twitter), CASL, GDPR, and CCPA. Filter at template level — do not let the agent generate these mechanics.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent labels a collaborative-tool invite flow as "inherent virality".</description>
      <reason>Inherent virality has a strict test: does the product fail to deliver core value without the invitee joining? Collaboration invites are typically incentivized or convenience-driven, not inherent.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent invents social proof claims ("join 100,000 people") without input data.</description>
      <reason>LLMs produce plausible-sounding numbers; all numeric claims in invite copy must be passed in as inputs, not generated.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
