<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-activation-and-sequence" title="Activation Metric, Email Sequence, and In-App Engagement">
  <summary>How to derive the activation metric from cohort data, structure a 9-touchpoint email sequence, and keep trial users engaged in-app.</summary>

  <section title="Activation Metric Definition">
    <rule>
      <statement>Derive the activation metric from cohort data: compare actions taken by converted vs churned trials. The activation event must have at least 2x lift over random (converted users who did it vs churned users who did it) and p &lt; 0.05 at sample size &gt;= 200 paid users.</statement>
      <rationale>Activation metrics chosen by intuition fail to predict conversion. "Invited a teammate" is meaningless if inviting users do not actually convert more. Cohort correlation with significance gate ensures the metric is real.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Activation formula: [Action] + [Quantity] + [Timeframe]. Examples: "Created 1 project in first session", "Invited 1 team member in first 3 days", "Completed 1 full workflow in first week". The formula should be achievable in under 5 minutes for 80% of users.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Project management tool: 45% activation rate, 55% trial-to-paid among activated users.</note>
      <p>Activation metric: "Created 1 project with 3+ tasks". Validated by cohort: activated users converted at 55% vs 8% for unactivated. Onboarding: pre-loaded sample project, 3-step wizard, first-task completion celebrated. Average time to activation: 3 days.</p>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Email Sequence Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every trial email campaign must subscribe to the activation event and exit immediately when it fires. A stop-on-activation rule is non-negotiable — no exceptions for engagement emails, product tips, or feature highlights.</statement>
      <rationale>Sequences that keep firing after activation produce "still need help?" messages to active users, which damages trust and increases unsubscribes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Welcome email must arrive within 60 seconds of signup with exactly one action. Later emails grow from that single action. Day 7 mid-trial check-in outperforms higher-frequency early emails — protect quiet space in days 2-6.</statement>
      <rationale>Users need exploration space before they can meaningfully respond to guidance; over-emailing in the first 3 days correlates with higher unsubscribe rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Day 0: Welcome — immediate value, one action, from a named person.</item>
      <item>Day 1: Quick start — remove blockers, show help resources.</item>
      <item>Day 3: Feature highlight — showcase key differentiating feature.</item>
      <item>Day 5: Case study — social proof from a similar company.</item>
      <item>Day 7: Mid-trial check-in — offer help, gather feedback.</item>
      <item>Day 10: Countdown begins — create trial-end awareness.</item>
      <item>Day 13: 1 day left — urgency, clear upgrade CTA.</item>
      <item>Day 14: Trial ended — invite to subscribe, offer help with export.</item>
      <item>Day 17: Win-back — single special offer if no conversion, empathetic tone.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="In-App Engagement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show trial countdown in the UI starting at Day 10, not Day 14. Display remaining days prominently but include the path to upgrade — a countdown without an upgrade CTA creates urgency without conversion.</statement>
      <rationale>Trial countdowns that create urgency but provide no path to value cause users to feel pressured and bounce rather than convert.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a progress checklist with 4-5 items linked to the activation path. Celebrate each completion with a micro-confirmation. Tie the final checklist item to the activation event.</statement>
      <rationale>Onboarding checklists increase activation rate by 15-25% by making the path explicit and each step feel achievable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Trial-to-Paid Transition">
    <rule>
      <statement>The trial-to-paid transition must be seamless: same data retained, same login credentials, no re-entry of account information. Offer monthly billing as the initial step even if annual is preferred long-term.</statement>
      <rationale>Hard paywalls at trial end that require data export or re-entry destroy win-back rate and generate negative reviews. Reducing checkout friction at the decision moment has outsized impact on conversion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/email-sequence.md">Email templates: welcome, mid-trial check-in, trial-ending</reference>
  </section>
</text>
