<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rescue-and-rules" title="Rescue Mechanics, Measurement Rules, and Antipatterns">
  <summary>At-risk signals, rescue interventions, trial extension policy, measurement window rules, and antipatterns that silently destroy conversion.</summary>

  <section title="At-Risk Signals and Rescue">
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag trials as at-risk using behavioral signals — not time elapsed. Four key flags: no login in 3+ days, onboarding not completed, only 1 feature used, no team invites in a team product.</statement>
      <rationale>Time-based rescue emails ("you haven't logged in") fire on users who are active in-app; signal-based rescue fires only when behavior confirms disengagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Offer trial extensions only to genuinely inactive trials with a credible stated reason. Do not offer extensions broadly — broad extensions train users to procrastinate conversion.</statement>
      <rationale>Inactive trials with a genuine blocker accept extensions at 30-50% rate. Offering extensions to active users who simply haven't converted yet defers conversion without adding value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>No login signal → "Did you get stuck?" email with one specific offer of help.</item>
      <item>Stuck in onboarding → Offer 1:1 setup call or video walkthrough.</item>
      <item>Low feature usage → Feature education email with a concrete use-case example.</item>
      <item>Churned without feedback → Exit survey with single question and free-text field.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/at-risk-flagger.py">Python function to classify trial at-risk flags from behavior data</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Measurement Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track trial-to-paid conversion at Day 14, Day 30, and Day 60. Deferred converters (Day 21-60) are real and typically account for 20-30% of total conversions from a cohort.</statement>
      <rationale>Measuring only at trial-end (Day 14) underestimates the true trial-to-paid rate and leads to over-investment in urgency tactics while under-investing in deferred nurture.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Expose pricing during the trial — do not hide it. Hidden pricing breaks trust and lowers conversion. Users should be able to see and compare plans from Day 1.</statement>
      <rationale>Transparency about pricing during trial is a PLG principle; surfacing it only at the end creates decision paralysis at the worst moment — the trial-end deadline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Email sequence with no stop-on-activation rule that keeps emailing active users through the entire 14-day sequence.</description>
      <reason>Active users receiving "you haven't tried feature X" emails churn from the email list, reducing the channel's future effectiveness.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Behavioral trigger logic using OR conditions where AND is required — e.g., "no login OR incomplete onboarding" fires on everyone including users who logged in but skipped one optional step.</description>
      <reason>Over-triggering rescue emails trains users to ignore them; false positives waste human CS effort and dilute the rescue signal.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Activation metric chosen by product team intuition without cohort validation.</description>
      <reason>Unvalidated metrics optimize for the wrong behavior. Optimizing "invited a teammate" when team invites do not actually predict conversion wastes all downstream effort.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hard paywall at trial end that requires data export before access is cut.</description>
      <reason>Data-loss threats trigger negative reviews and word-of-mouth damage. Offering a read-only grace period preserves goodwill and dramatically improves win-back rate.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
