<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="journey-mapping">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Visualize the complete end-to-end experience a persona has with a product across all stages, touchpoints, emotions, pain points, and opportunities to diagnose friction and prioritize improvements.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>customer-journey</tag>
      <tag>experience-mapping</tag>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>pain-points</tag>
      <tag>prioritization</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Customer Journey Mapping</title>
    <summary>A customer journey map is a visualization of the complete end-to-end experience a specific persona has with a product or service across all stages, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points, and opportunities. Current-state maps diagnose problems; future-state maps set a design target. Maps must be grounded in research (interviews, analytics, support data) — not assumption.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Optimizing individual touchpoints without seeing the full journey creates local maxima: one screen improves while handoffs between channels or departments get worse. Journey maps force cross-functional visibility into the complete experience and surface friction that no single team owns.</p>
      <p>Analytics show drop-off at a stage but cannot explain why. Support data reveals frequent complaints but without context of where in the journey users are stuck. Interviews are rich but anecdotal. Journey maps synthesize all three data types into a unified picture that stakeholders can see, understand, and act on.</p>
      <p>Journey maps give stakeholders a shared reference for prioritizing improvements by impact on the overall experience rather than by departmental ownership. A pain point that spans product and support gets visible; a problem owned by no team becomes everyone's responsibility.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before a major product redesign to document the baseline experience and identify the biggest pain points.</item>
        <item>When multiple teams own different parts of the experience and no one sees the full picture.</item>
        <item>When support data or NPS verbatims indicate friction but the location within the journey is unclear.</item>
        <item>When entering a new market segment and the team needs to understand how a different persona experiences the product.</item>
        <item>When preparing a cross-functional workshop to align stakeholders on experience priorities.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>As the first UX activity on a new product — there is no journey to map without research; build the research foundation first.</item>
        <item>When the goal is to fix a specific UI element — journey mapping is for systemic problems across stages, not individual screens.</item>
        <item>When the team cannot access real user research (interviews, analytics, support data) — a map built from assumptions is a fiction document, not a research artifact.</item>
        <item>When no stakeholder has authority to act on the findings — maps without committed owners produce posters, not change.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="scope-and-research">
      <p>A journey map without clear scope conflates the experiences of different user types and collapses important variation. Define persona, journey type, start point, end point, and channels in scope before beginning research.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Specify the persona, journey type (current state, future state, day-in-the-life, or service blueprint), start point, end point, and channels in scope before beginning research or synthesis.</statement>
        <rationale>A map without a defined persona and scope attempts to show how everyone uses the product, which obscures the specific behaviors and pain points that matter for a target user segment. Scope drives which data to collect and how to structure the map.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Base the map on actual research data — interviews, observation, analytics, support tickets, surveys. Never map from assumption.</statement>
        <rationale>A map built from internal assumptions reflects how the team thinks the product works, not how users experience it. Assumption-based maps reinforce existing blind spots rather than exposing them. Every emotion, thought, and pain point must be grounded in a research quote or event.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Collect data from multiple sources: user interviews for subjective experience, analytics for drop-off points, support tickets for common problems, and employee interviews from customer-facing roles for backstage context.</statement>
        <rationale>One data source is incomplete. Interviews reveal thought and emotion but miss frequency; analytics show what happened but not why; support data reveals common problems but lacks context; employee interviews reveal organizational barriers. All four together create a complete picture.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="journey-structure">
      <p>A journey map has six structural elements: stages, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, and pain points. Each row represents a different layer of the experience.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Define 4-8 major stages that represent distinct phases of the user's experience. Each stage should have a clear user goal and mark a transition point in the journey.</statement>
        <rationale>Fewer than 4 stages over-compresses the experience and hides friction. More than 8 stages produce unmaintainable maps that teams cannot use in workshops. Each stage should represent a moment where the user's goal or context changes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Document what users do (actions) and where they interact with the product/service (touchpoints) separately for each stage.</statement>
        <rationale>Conflating actions and touchpoints obscures whether friction is in user behavior or in a specific channel. A user might need to call support (action) because the in-app help (touchpoint) is not visible (UI problem) rather than because the action itself is wrong. Separate rows allow targeted intervention.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Record emotional state and cognitive questions at each stage — not what the user should feel, but what research shows they actually feel.</statement>
        <rationale>Emotion curves reveal where user confidence drops or anxiety spikes — these are the highest-leverage intervention points. Teams consistently assume users are happy at product touchpoints and frustrated only at competitor touchpoints. Research usually shows the opposite. Ground every emotion score in a research quote or observation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Distinguish pain points (current friction) from opportunities (actionable improvements). Every pain point should have at least one opportunity attached.</statement>
        <rationale>Pain points without opportunities produce a list of problems with no forward motion. Opportunities without pain points are speculation. The pairing anchors design work to diagnosed need and prevents bikeshedding.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="E-commerce purchase journey">
        <p>Stages: Discover → Research → Decide → Purchase → Receive → Use.</p>
        <p>Discover: User sees ad or searches; emotion Curious; pain point "hard to find what I want"; opportunity "improve search filters and category browsing."</p>
        <p>Research: User compares options within the site; emotion Engaged; pain point "too many choices, hard to compare"; opportunity "add side-by-side comparison tool."</p>
        <p>Decide: User reads reviews from external sources; emotion Uncertain; pain point "conflicting reviews undermine trust"; opportunity "synthesize reviews in your product."</p>
        <p>Purchase: User enters checkout; emotion Anxious; pain point "long form, hidden fees revealed late"; opportunity "simplify checkout, show final price upfront."</p>
        <p>Receive: User tracks order; emotion Impatient; pain point "no tracking updates, assumes lost"; opportunity "send proactive shipping updates."</p>
        <p>Use: User unboxes and uses product; emotion Varies; pain point "not as described in pictures"; opportunity "improve product photography and descriptions."</p>
        <p>Key insight: Checkout produces the highest anxiety and has the most conversion friction — simplifying checkout is the highest-leverage opportunity.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Assumption-based journey map">
        <p>A team that creates a map from internal assumptions without user research will likely show emotions increasing at product touchpoints (assumed delight) and only surface pain at competitor or legacy system touchpoints. The map will miss the real anxiety points where users actually struggle — often at handoff moments between channels or departments that the team does not see directly.</p>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="validation-and-metrics">
      <p>A completed journey map needs validation with research participants and quantified metrics to track improvement.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Share the draft map with 2–3 research participants for a member check before using it to drive decisions — they often correct assumptions that felt obvious internally.</statement>
        <rationale>Team members working inside a product are poor judges of the user experience because they have seen all the behind-the-scenes context. Research participants catch moments where the map misses a real pain point or invents a false emotion.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Attach at least one measurable metric to each stage so improvements can be tracked quantitatively after implementation.</statement>
        <rationale>Journey maps without metrics remain a soft deliverable. Metrics (conversion rate for Purchase, activation rate for Onboarding, resolution time for Support) convert the map from a qualitative description into a measurement framework that tracks change over time and shows ROI for improvements.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Date every journey map version — maps without dates get treated as current truth long after they are outdated.</statement>
        <rationale>Journeys change when products, policies, or channels change. A stale map actively misleads teams by presenting an outdated picture as current reality. Schedule map reviews after major product changes and at least annually.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Link each pain point to a specific metric (NPS score, drop-off rate, support ticket volume) so prioritization is quantified, not just directional.</statement>
        <rationale>Pain points that sound equally severe in a workshop may have very different impact. Linking to metrics surfaces that "users are confused by jargon" affects 5% of support tickets, while "checkout requires re-entering address on mobile" affects 40% of abandoned carts. Metrics prevent low-impact problems from hogging attention.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="common-failures">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Creating a journey map from team assumptions rather than user research.</description>
        <reason>Teams consistently underestimate user anxiety at handoff points and overestimate satisfaction at product touchpoints. Assumption maps reinforce these biases rather than correcting them.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Mapping actions only — no emotions or thoughts row in the map.</description>
        <reason>Actions without emotional context miss the moments where users are most at risk of abandonment or error. The emotion curve is where prioritization decisions come from and is often the most revealing output of the map.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating the journey map as a one-time workshop output never to be updated.</description>
        <reason>Customer behavior changes faster than maps are updated — stale maps get cited in decisions they no longer support. Schedule map reviews after major product or policy changes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Creating the map in a silo without cross-functional team participation.</description>
        <reason>Journey maps reveal problems that span organizational boundaries. Without the relevant teams present, the map does not produce cross-team ownership of the pain points it surfaces. The workshop format is not just output production; it is alignment and commitment.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Emotion curves added as decoration rather than derived from research.</description>
        <reason>Teams draw what they expect users to feel, not what research reveals. A user might feel relief at a product touchpoint because they were terrified at an earlier stage (company's fault) — drawing the emotion curve incorrectly erases this context.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Collapsing the diversity of user experiences into a single persona path, masking segment-level differences.</description>
        <reason>Different user segments experience the product very differently. A map for the "power user" misses pain points of the "occasional user"; a map for the "early adopter" does not surface issues for the "skeptical enterprise buyer." Create separate maps per segment or note explicitly where segment paths diverge.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>In B2B contexts, conflating the "user" (person doing the task) with the "decision-maker" (person who defines success).</description>
        <reason>B2B journey maps are especially unreliable because the person using the product and the person justifying the expense are different people with different goals. Map both, or note explicitly if the map shows only the user's perspective.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-synthesis-workflow">
      <p>Claude agents are effective at two stages: (1) synthesizing raw research inputs into a structured journey map draft, and (2) generating the opportunity prioritization section from a completed map. Visual design of the map remains a human task. Emotion data must come from research, not inferred.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Agents will invent emotion data if research inputs are thin or absent — explicitly instruct the agent to set emotions to null and flag gaps rather than infer them.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs optimize for plausible-sounding output. When research data is sparse, the agent will generate emotionally coherent curves that sound reasonable but have no grounding in actual user experience. Always require the agent to cite research evidence for emotion data.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Journey maps synthesized from only one data type (e.g., only interview transcripts) miss what other sources would reveal; agents should note which stages lack multi-source validation.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents will produce maps from available data but cannot flag the absence of missing data types. Guide the agent to note where emotion is based only on interviews (subjective) and lacks validation from support data (frequency) or analytics (drop-off).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>When agents process long interview transcripts, they tend to over-weight the most dramatic moments rather than the most frequent ones; ask for frequency counts alongside pain point descriptions.</statement>
        <rationale>Memorable moments bias output. A single user saying "I almost gave up" will surface higher than a pattern where 30% of users abandon at the same stage. Instruct the agent to score pain points by frequency and include counts in the output.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Agents cannot determine journey stage boundaries from raw data — the stage definition is a human decision that must be provided before synthesis.</statement>
        <rationale>Raw data (interview transcripts, analytics events) does not naturally partition into stages. The team must first decide: Are we mapping by user goal, time, channel, or product section? Once stages are defined, agents can map data into them; agents cannot define stages themselves.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Future-state journey maps generated entirely by an agent without grounding in research produce aspirational fiction; require the agent to cite which current-state problems each future-state improvement addresses.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents will produce optimistic future states that ignore real constraints. Every future-state improvement must have an explicit link back to a current-state pain point. If an improvement cannot be justified by current-state evidence, it is speculation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/journey-map.md" purpose="Journey map table: stages × actions/touchpoints/thoughts/emotions/pain points + opportunities."/>
      <template path="templates/stage-detail.md" purpose="Per-stage detail template: goal, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotion, pain points, metrics."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/journey-mapping-101/"/>
      <link href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/mapping-experiences/9781491923528/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/customer-journey-mapping/"/>
      <link href="https://miro.com/templates/customer-journey-map/"/>
      <link href="https://www.thisisservicedesigndoing.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
