<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="dora-metrics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>cicd-engineer</domain>
    <summary>DORA metrics measure delivery performance: Deployment Frequency, Lead Time, Change Failure Rate, MTTR. Elite teams deploy 208x faster, recover 2,604x quicker. Add Reliability metric.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>dora</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>devops</tag>
      <tag>ci-cd</tag>
      <tag>observability</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>metrics</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>DORA Metrics</title>

    <summary>DORA (DevOps Research and Assessment) metrics are four research-validated KPIs that measure software delivery performance: Deployment Frequency, Lead Time for Changes, Change Failure Rate, and Mean Time to Restore. Elite teams deploy 208x more often and recover 2,604x faster than low performers. A fifth metric — Reliability (SLO achievement) — was added in 2025. AI-generated code reduces delivery stability by approximately 7%, so batch size must be monitored when using AI tools.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>The four metrics are the only empirically-proven predictors of both technical and organizational performance (from the "Accelerate" book, 2018). They give a complete picture: throughput (Deployment Frequency + Lead Time) and stability (Change Failure Rate + Mean Time to Restore). Without them, teams optimize locally and miss systemic bottlenecks.</p>
      <p>Elite performers are 2x more likely to exceed organizational performance goals. They achieve high scores on all four metrics simultaneously, proving that speed and stability are not trade-offs but correlated.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Engineering org wants a baseline + improvement plan for software delivery performance.</item>
        <item>Quarterly/annual exec reporting: leadership needs a credible answer to "are we shipping faster?".</item>
        <item>Tracking AI-assistant adoption impact (DORA 2025 research shows AI affects stability/throughput; need data).</item>
        <item>Comparing teams' delivery health without falling into "lines of code" or "story points" anti-metrics.</item>
        <item>Justifying platform/CI investments — DORA metrics provide before/after evidence.</item>
        <item>Setting up engineering metrics for a team or service for the first time.</item>
        <item>Evaluating CI/CD pipeline health before a refactoring sprint.</item>
        <item>Connecting engineering output to business outcomes (revenue, churn, team wellbeing).</item>
        <item>Running quarterly DevOps performance reviews.</item>
        <item>Designing a metrics collection system backed by CI/CD + incident tools.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-person / very small teams — the variance dominates the signal.</item>
        <item>As a stack-rank tool ("Team X is Elite, Team Y is Low — fire the manager"). Goodhart's Law applies hard.</item>
        <item>For non-software work (data pipelines, ML training, content) — definitions don't transfer cleanly.</item>
        <item>When the org doesn't yet have basic CI/CD — measure something else first (build pass rate, deploy automation %).</item>
        <item>As the only health metric — DORA + Reliability + SPACE + developer experience surveys complement each other.</item>
        <item>Comparing individual developers — metrics are team-level, not individual.</item>
        <item>Early-stage prototype projects with no production — no deployment signal to measure.</item>
        <item>When incident tooling (PagerDuty, Opsgenie) is not yet integrated — MTTR will be inaccurate.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="four-key-metrics">
      <p>DORA metrics measure two dimensions of delivery health:</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Measure all four DORA metrics as a set — throughput (Deployment Frequency + Lead Time) and stability (Change Failure Rate + MTTR) together reveal the full delivery health picture.</statement>
        <rationale>Optimizing only throughput metrics drives risky large batches; only stability metrics drives slow but safe delivery. Elite performers achieve high scores on all four simultaneously.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Performance tiers (from DORA research):</p>
      <list>
        <item>Deployment Frequency: Elite = multiple/day; High = weekly–monthly; Medium = monthly–6mo; Low = 6mo+</item>
        <item>Lead Time for Changes: Elite = &lt;1 hour; High = 1 day–1 week; Medium = 1–6 months; Low = 6mo+</item>
        <item>Change Failure Rate: Elite = 0–15%; High = 16–30%; Medium = 31–45%; Low = 46%+</item>
        <item>Mean Time to Restore: Elite = &lt;1 hour; High = &lt;1 day; Medium = 1 day–1 week; Low = 1 week–1 month</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Track trends, not absolute values — week-over-week improvement matters more than hitting exact elite thresholds.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams in different domains (embedded, banking) have structural constraints that prevent elite Deployment Frequency; improvement trajectory predicts organizational outcomes better than absolute tier.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="metric-definitions-and-data-sources">
      <p>Precise definitions ensure consistent measurement:</p>

      <term name="Deployment Frequency">Count of successful production deployments per time period. Data: CI/CD pipeline events, deployment logs.</term>

      <term name="Lead Time for Changes">Time from first commit to successful production deployment (merge timestamp to deploy timestamp). Data: Git commit timestamps + CI/CD deployment timestamps.</term>

      <term name="Change Failure Rate">Percentage of deployments requiring rollback, hotfix, or causing an incident. Data: incident tracking system + deployment records.</term>

      <term name="Mean Time to Restore">Average time from incident detection to resolution. Data: incident management (PagerDuty, Opsgenie) resolved timestamps.</term>
    </section>

    <section name="business-impact">
      <p>Research findings from Accelerate (Forsgren, Humble, Kim, 2018):</p>
      <list>
        <item>Elite performers are 2x more likely to exceed organizational performance goals.</item>
        <item>Elite vs low: 208x higher deployment frequency.</item>
        <item>Elite vs low: 106x faster lead time.</item>
        <item>Elite vs low: 2,604x faster recovery time.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="2025-evolution">
      <p>Recent DORA research additions:</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Add Reliability (SLO achievement rate) as a fifth metric alongside the four core DORA metrics.</statement>
        <rationale>DORA 2025 research shows SLO achievement and error budget consumption predict organizational outcomes independently of the four delivery metrics.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Monitor batch size when using AI code generation tools; expect a ~7% reduction in delivery stability with heavy AI adoption.</statement>
        <rationale>AI-generated code encourages larger commits and pull requests, which violates the small-batch principle underlying elite DORA performance.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="data-collection-rules">
      <p>Accurate data collection is critical for valid metrics:</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Automate metric collection from CI/CD pipelines — never rely on manual reporting.</statement>
        <rationale>Manual reporting introduces lag and bias; teams under pressure stop updating it. Automated collection from deployment events is the only reliable baseline.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define "production deployment" precisely before collecting data: successful deploy to prod environment, not staging.</statement>
        <rationale>Ambiguous definition inflates Deployment Frequency when staging deployments are counted. The signal must reflect real user impact.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Mark deployments as rollback or hotfix at emit time, not retroactively, so Change Failure Rate is accurate.</statement>
        <rationale>Retroactive classification is inconsistent across team members; the CI/CD pipeline knows at deploy time whether the trigger was a hotfix branch or rollback workflow.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Link incident records to the deployment that caused them; Mean Time to Restore without deployment linkage cannot distinguish release-caused incidents from infrastructure failures.</statement>
        <rationale>Only release-caused incidents contribute to Change Failure Rate. Infrastructure-only incidents belong in reliability/SLO tracking, not Change Failure Rate.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="tool-integrations">
      <p>Recommended tooling by maturity:</p>
      <list>
        <item>GitLab native: enable DORA analytics (Premium/Ultimate tier) — zero additional tooling.</item>
        <item>GitHub + any incident tool: Google Four Keys (open source, GCP-native event pipeline).</item>
        <item>Multi-platform enterprise: Sleuth, LinearB, or Jellyfish for aggregation.</item>
        <item>Custom stack: Prometheus + PostgreSQL schema + Grafana dashboard (templates in this methodology).</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Export deployment events to a Prometheus-compatible endpoint or PostgreSQL from every CI/CD pipeline immediately after each successful deploy.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-hoc scraping of CI/CD logs is fragile; emit events at the point of deployment where all metadata (commit SHA, timestamp, is_rollback) is available.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="process-integration">
      <p>Using DORA metrics appropriately within organizations:</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Review DORA metrics in team retrospectives, never in performance reviews of individual engineers.</statement>
        <rationale>Using DORA metrics to evaluate individuals causes gaming (smaller commits, avoided deployments, suppressed incident reports) that destroys the signal.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Set weekly automated reports; alert on degradation (not on absolute low values) during the first 90 days of collection.</statement>
        <rationale>First 90 days establishes baseline. Early alerting on low absolute values discourages teams before the baseline is known.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="deployment-event-emission">
      <p>Example implementations for emitting deployment events:</p>

      <example type="good" title="GitHub Actions deployment event emission">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
- name: Record Deployment Event
  if: success()
  run: |
    curl -X POST "$METRICS_ENDPOINT/events/deployment" \
      -H "Content-Type: application/json" \
      -H "Authorization: Bearer ${{ secrets.DORA_API_KEY }}" \
      -d '{
        "service": "${{ github.repository }}",
        "environment": "production",
        "commit_sha": "${{ github.sha }}",
        "commit_timestamp": "${{ github.event.head_commit.timestamp }}",
        "deployed_at": "'$(date -Iseconds)'",
        "is_rollback": false,
        "is_hotfix": false
      }'
]]></code>
        <note>Emit deployment event AFTER successful deploy, not before.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Recording deployment at pipeline start — wrong placement">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
- name: Record Deployment (wrong placement)
  run: |
    curl -X POST "$METRICS_ENDPOINT/events/deployment" ...
    ./deploy.sh  # deploy happens AFTER recording — wrong
]]></code>
        <note>Will emit even if deploy fails, inflating Deployment Frequency.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="promql-queries">
      <p>Prometheus queries for DORA metrics calculation:</p>

      <example type="good" title="Deployment Frequency: deployments per day over last 7 days">
        <code lang="promql"><![CDATA[
sum(increase(deployments_total{environment="production"}[7d])) by (service) / 7
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Change Failure Rate as percentage over 30 days">
        <code lang="promql"><![CDATA[
(
  sum(increase(deployments_failed_total{environment="production"}[30d])) by (service)
  /
  sum(increase(deployments_total{environment="production"}[30d])) by (service)
) * 100
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="MTTR in minutes (average incident resolution time)">
        <code lang="promql"><![CDATA[
avg(incident_resolution_time_seconds) by (service) / 60
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="lead-time-calculation">
      <p>Python implementation for lead time statistics:</p>

      <example type="good" title="Lead time calculation from deployment records">
        <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
from datetime import datetime
from typing import List, Dict
import statistics

def calculate_lead_time(deployments: List[Dict]) -> Dict:
    lead_times = []
    for deploy in deployments:
        commit_time = datetime.fromisoformat(deploy['commit_timestamp'])
        deploy_time = datetime.fromisoformat(deploy['deployment_timestamp'])
        lead_times.append((deploy_time - commit_time).total_seconds() / 3600)

    if not lead_times:
        return {"error": "No deployments"}

    return {
        "mean_hours": statistics.mean(lead_times),
        "median_hours": statistics.median(lead_times),
        "p95_hours": statistics.quantiles(lead_times, n=20)[18] if len(lead_times) >= 20 else max(lead_times),
        "sample_size": len(lead_times),
    }
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agents should follow a structured approach to DORA implementation:</p>

      <p>DORA metrics are continuous-collection problems with periodic reporting. Have a "collector" agent ingest from Git (commits, PRs), CI/CD (pipeline runs, deploy events), and incident systems (PagerDuty/Opsgenie/Statuspage) into a normalized event store. A "computer" agent runs daily to recompute the four metrics + reliability per service per team. A "narrator" agent (Opus) produces the weekly summary: which metric moved, why (correlate with deploys, incidents, batch size), and what to investigate. Always show trends over absolute numbers; always include batch-size and AI-adoption signals as confounders. Never let one agent both compute and adjust definitions — separate.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — drives definition specs and dashboard PRs through quality gates.</item>
        <item>A custom dora-event-normalizer (Sonnet) — given heterogeneous events, maps to {deploy, change, incident, recovery} schema with a confidence score; flags low-confidence rows for human review.</item>
        <item>A custom dora-narrator (Opus, read-only) — given weekly metric snapshot + diff vs prior, produces a 200-word narrative with hypothesized drivers; cites supporting evidence.</item>
      </list>

      <prompt purpose="dora-metric-computation"><![CDATA[
Compute DORA metrics for service <X>, period <P>.
Inputs: git events (commits with merge_at), deploy events (pipeline `deploy_prod` success), incident events (severity, started_at, restored_at, deploy_correlation), feature-flag events.
Output: (1) Deployment Frequency (deploys/period), (2) Lead Time (p50, p95: merge_at → deploy_prod), (3) Change Failure Rate (incidents-tied-to-deploy / deploys), (4) MTTR (incident_started → restored), (5) Reliability proxy (SLO attainment %), (6) batch size (commits/deploy), (7) AI-assist signal (% PRs with AI co-author tag).
Forbid: counting non-prod deploys, inventing definitions, mixing services without disclosure, hiding small-N caveats (period < 10 deploys → mark as "low confidence").
]]></prompt>

      <prompt purpose="dora-weekly-narrative"><![CDATA[
Narrate week-over-week change. JSON: {metric, prev, curr, delta, hypothesized_drivers:[{driver, evidence_event_id, confidence}], suggested_investigation, confounders:[batch_size, ai_adoption, incident_severity_mix]}.
]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="common-failure-modes">
      <p>Known pitfalls in DORA metric implementation:</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>"Deployment" definition is the swamp: deploys to prod-like staging? Feature flag rollouts? Per-service or per-monorepo?</description>
        <reason>Without a written, agent-readable definition, every team measures something different.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Lead Time conflates "commit to merge" + "merge to deploy" + "deploy to release"; agents collapse them and miss the actual bottleneck.</description>
        <reason>Measure merge-to-deploy specifically, not from commit.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Change Failure Rate depends on incident classification — many "rollbacks" are routine config changes, many incidents aren't tied to a deploy.</description>
        <reason>Agents inflate or deflate CFR depending on the incident-system schema.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>MTTR includes detection time + response time + recovery time; agents compute from incident.opened_at → resolved_at and miss the silent half-hour before alert fires.</description>
        <reason>Use incident detection time, not created time.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>2025 research: AI-assistant adoption correlates with -1.5% throughput, -7.2% stability — likely because AI encourages larger batches.</description>
        <reason>Agents must track batch size or DORA improvements are illusory.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Vendor-tool dashboards (Sleuth/LinearB/Jellyfish) have opinionated definitions that may not match yours; agents take their numbers at face value.</description>
        <reason>Validate definitions match organizational intent.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Elite-vs-Low buckets feel motivating but encourage gaming (artificial micro-deploys to bump frequency).</description>
        <reason>Show trends, not absolute tiers.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>"Reliability" as the fifth metric is not yet standardized — implementations vary; agents should expose error budget burn or SLO attainment, not invent their own.</description>
        <reason>Use SLO attainment as the reliable proxy.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs invent thresholds ("Elite means daily deploys") — anchor every claim to a citation; the official thresholds change yearly in the State of DevOps report.</description>
        <reason>Always cite the research source.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Lead-time computation often pulls pr.created_at instead of pr.merged_at; this inflates lead time and hides queue-after-merge time.</description>
        <reason>Use merge timestamp, not creation timestamp.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents include hotfix deploys when computing Deployment Frequency (good) but exclude them from Change Failure Rate (wrong) because they don't open an incident — fix the schema, not the calc.</description>
        <reason>Include hotfixes in all metrics consistently.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Multi-service repos: agents attribute deploys to the wrong service when the deploy event lacks a service label.</description>
        <reason>Force the deploy event to carry {service, sha, env, success}.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>AI-coauthored PRs are detectable via co-author trailer or commit-message tags; agents skip the signal and miss the AI-impact dimension.</description>
        <reason>Expose AI adoption signal in reports.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>"Time-zone aware" matters: deploy at 23:00 UTC vs 06:00 UTC affects Deployment Frequency buckets at month boundaries; pick UTC and stay there.</description>
        <reason>Use consistent time zones.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents recompute history retroactively after a definition tweak — breaks trust.</description>
        <reason>Version the definitions and freeze old data; show "definition v2 from 2026-01-15".</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Proven practices for successful DORA implementation:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Write a definitions doc in the repo (docs/dora-definitions.md) that humans + agents both read; treat it as an Architecture Decision Record.</item>
        <item>Track per-service, not per-team — service ownership shifts; service identity is stable.</item>
        <item>Show trends with confidence intervals or low-N flags; one bad week shouldn't trigger reorgs.</item>
        <item>Pair Deployment Frequency with batch size (commits per deploy). Frequency without small batches is vanity.</item>
        <item>Include the 5th metric (Reliability) as SLO attainment, not invented uptime number.</item>
        <item>Annotate dashboards with deploys, incidents, AI-tool rollouts, team changes — narrative explains the curve.</item>
        <item>Use DORA for retrospectives, not performance reviews. People game what's used to judge them.</item>
        <item>Re-baseline after major org/process changes — comparing to old baseline misleads.</item>
        <item>Connect DORA to business outcomes (revenue, NPS, churn) once trust in definitions is established.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/deploy-event.yml" purpose="GitHub Actions workflow step emitting deployment events to a metrics endpoint."/>
      <template path="templates/prometheus-rules.yml" purpose="Prometheus recording rules and alerts for all four DORA metrics."/>
      <template path="templates/schema.sql" purpose="PostgreSQL schema for deployments + incidents tables with DORA materialized view."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://dora.dev/research/"/>
      <link href="https://itrevolution.com/product/accelerate/"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/GoogleCloudPlatform/fourkeys"/>
      <link href="https://cd.foundation/blog/2025/10/16/dora-5-metrics/"/>
      <link href="https://docs.gitlab.com/user/analytics/dora_metrics/"/>
      <link href="https://www.atlassian.com/devops/frameworks/dora-metrics"/>
      <link href="https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3454124"/>
      <link href="https://dx.com/research"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
