<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-rules" title="PWA Core: Mandatory Rules">
  <summary>Non-negotiable rules for service worker placement, manifest stability, icon format, caching strategy, and update UX.</summary>

  <section title="Service Worker Location">
    <rule>
      <statement>Serve sw.js and manifest.json from the origin root (/) with Cache-Control: no-cache. Never serve the service worker from /static/ or any subdirectory.</statement>
      <rationale>Service worker scope is tied to its path. A SW at /static/sw.js can only control resources under /static/. Origin-root placement controls the entire app.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Manifest Stability">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the manifest id field stable across deploys. Never change it after the first release.</statement>
      <rationale>Changing id forces browsers to treat the PWA as a new app, breaking existing shortcuts and triggering re-installation prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Icons">
    <rule>
      <statement>Ship all icon entries with purpose: "maskable any". Never ship icons with only purpose: "any".</statement>
      <rationale>Android crops non-maskable icons into unexpected shapes on home screen. maskable ensures the safe-zone guarantee.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Caching Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use NetworkFirst with networkTimeoutSeconds: 3 for /api/* and navigation routes. Use CacheFirst for images and fonts. Use StaleWhileRevalidate for JS/CSS static assets. Never precache personalised HTML or API responses.</statement>
      <rationale>NetworkFirst with timeout avoids spinner-of-death on flaky networks. CacheFirst for immutable assets (images, fonts) reduces redundant fetches.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Update UX">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show an update prompt on the controllerchange event. Never auto-reload mid-form. Present a user-initiated reload action.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-reload discards in-flight form data and violates user expectations. The controllerchange event fires when the new SW takes control.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="iOS Limitations">
    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>Document iOS Safari PWA limitations before promising any PWA feature to iOS users: storage evicted after ~7 days of non-use, no background sync, no periodic sync, no push on older iOS.</statement>
      <rationale>These gaps make offline-first PWAs unreliable for iOS. Agents never surface this in code review; humans must sign off on any iOS PWA claim.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
