<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="communications-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Stakeholder communication plan with per-stakeholder matrix (needs, format, frequency, owner). Status reports headline worst metric, not average. Default-to-green is the leading antipattern.</summary>
    <category>communications</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>communications</tag>
      <tag>stakeholders</tag>
      <tag>status-reporting</tag>
      <tag>meetings</tag>
    </tags>
    <related>
      <ref slug="stakeholder-engagement"/>
      <ref slug="project-integration"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Communications Management</title>

    <summary>Plan, execute, and monitor stakeholder communications so that the right people receive the right information at the right time. The core artifact is a per-stakeholder communication matrix (needs, format, frequency, owner). Every status report must show the worst metric as the headline, not the average — default-to-green status is the leading communication antipattern.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Stakeholder surprise is the most common symptom of failed communication management. Status reports that optimise for comfort over accuracy erode trust as soon as reality diverges from the narrative. A communication plan with defined cadences and channel rules prevents both information overload (too many meetings) and information gaps (missing owners, undocumented decisions).</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Bootstrapping a project's communication plan from a stakeholder register: deriving a per-stakeholder matrix of needs/format/frequency/owner.</item>
        <item>Designing meeting cadences (daily/weekly/monthly) to minimise meeting load while keeping decisions flowing.</item>
        <item>Generating standardised status report and meeting-notes templates that propagate across project portfolios.</item>
        <item>Auditing existing comms hygiene — too many meetings, missing owners, decisions undocumented, escalation path unclear.</item>
        <item>Routing comms by channel: choosing email vs Slack vs meeting vs wiki for each communication purpose.</item>
        <item>Solopreneur client-comms playbook: weekly update emails + on-demand Loom + monthly milestone review.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-stakeholder projects (just you + one customer) — informal communication suffices, the matrix is overkill.</item>
        <item>Crisis / incident response — comms move to incident-management runbook (status page, war room, hourly updates), not the PM matrix.</item>
        <item>High-trust / collocated small teams using ambient awareness; formalising channels can suppress collaboration.</item>
        <item>Sales / marketing / support communications — those are external-comms with their own playbook (CRM, email-marketing, ticketing).</item>
        <item>Already-mature org with a working comms cadence; switching to a new template imposes friction with little gain.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="communication-matrix">
      <rule>
        <statement>For each stakeholder, define: what they need to know, how often, in what format, and who sends it. Missing any field means someone will not receive what they need or will be over-informed.</statement>
        <rationale>One-size-fits-all communication produces information overload for some stakeholders and gaps for others. The matrix forces explicit decisions per stakeholder.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Refresh the communication matrix every 4-6 weeks or when stakeholders change. An unrefreshed matrix creates the same gaps it was designed to prevent.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholder roles, projects, and interest levels change; a static matrix becomes wrong within weeks in dynamic organisations.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="channel-selection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Match channel to message type: urgent issue → call; complex discussion requiring decision → meeting; status update → report; quick question → chat; reference information → wiki; formal decision record → email with confirmation.</statement>
        <rationale>Sending everything by email creates noise; using chat for formal decisions loses the record. Channel mismatch is the root cause of most "I never saw that" situations.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Default to async: written communication beats meeting unless the topic is ambiguous or decision-shaped. Meetings are expensive synchronisation; treat them as a last resort, not a default.</statement>
        <rationale>Synchronous time is the scarcest project resource. An async update that takes 5 minutes to write saves a 30-minute meeting for 8 people (240 person-minutes).</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="meeting-cadence">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every meeting requires an agenda shared 24 hours in advance, a named facilitator, documented decisions, and action items with owner and due date. Meetings without these are candidates for cancellation.</statement>
        <rationale>Agendaless meetings wander; undocumented decisions get re-litigated; action items without owners are never completed.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Audit meeting load every 4-6 weeks: if any stakeholder appears in more than 3 recurring weekly meetings, consolidate or remove one.</statement>
        <rationale>Meeting overload is self-reinforcing — people stop attending when calendars are saturated, which produces the information gaps the meetings were meant to prevent.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="escalation-path">
      <rule>
        <statement>Define escalation paths with backup contacts and out-of-office routing. A single-point escalation path fails at the worst time.</statement>
        <rationale>Escalation paths are only tested in crisis conditions when the primary contact is most likely unavailable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="rag-headline-policy">
      <rule>
        <statement>The status headline must reflect the worst single metric, not the average. If schedule is RED and cost is GREEN, overall status is RED.</statement>
        <rationale>Averaging metrics hides the failing dimension. Sponsors need to know the worst, not the mean — they will discover it themselves and the trust damage is compounded by the delay.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Status reports must cite metric values or commit/issue IDs as evidence. Reject "good progress, all on track" without quantitative support.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs and human PMs both default to optimism. Grounding on metrics or artefact IDs is the only defence against false green status.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Send status reports on a fixed day and time every week. Predictability makes the ritual; irregular cadence erodes trust.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholders who cannot predict when the next report arrives start asking for ad-hoc updates, which costs more than the regular report.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="meeting-output">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every meeting must produce a decisions log and an action-item list. Action items must have: text, owner, and due date — or they are not action items.</statement>
        <rationale>Action items without owner and due date pile up as orphans. The list becomes a backlog no one owns and nothing gets done.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Document decision rationale, not just the decision. "We chose Y because Z given trade-off with X" is a decision record. "We chose Y" is not.</statement>
        <rationale>Decisions without rationale get re-litigated when context changes. Preserved dissent and trade-off reasoning prevent re-opening settled questions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-failure-modes">
      <p>Communication matrices grow stale fast: stakeholders change, projects pivot, channels get deprecated. Without a refresh cadence, the doc lies.</p>
      <p>"Frequency × stakeholder × channel" combinatorial blowup: 20 stakeholders × 5 channels = 100 cells most of which are empty noise.</p>
      <p>LLM-generated status reports default to optimism (everything "on track") because pessimistic phrasing is rarer in training data; honesty must be enforced.</p>
      <p>Meeting templates without an enforced agenda owner devolve into status-theatre meetings.</p>
      <p>Escalation paths look clean on paper but break in practice when first-contact is unavailable or out of office; backup paths missing.</p>
      <p>"Push vs pull" framing ignores the real problem: people read 5% of pushed comms and 0% of pulled comms; the methodology lacks engagement metrics.</p>
      <p>Text-channel selection (email vs Slack) is culture-dependent; one-size-fits-all rules cause friction.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>The agent generates and maintains the communication artefacts and audits live behaviour. (1) Plan-builder: from stakeholder register → comms matrix + meeting schedule + escalation path. (2) Status-reporter: pulls metrics (sprint velocity, risk count, EVM CPI/SPI) and assembles weekly status report; routes per matrix. (3) Meeting-secretary: ingests transcript / notes, emits decisions log + action items with owners and due dates; pushes to issue tracker. (4) Comms-auditor: scans Slack/email/meeting analytics monthly to flag drift (meeting bloat, missing owners, undocumented decisions). Humans approve narrative, sensitivity calls, and escalation triggers.</p>
      <list>
        <item>comms-plan-builder — input: stakeholder register, output: matrix + meeting cadence + channel rules + escalation path.</item>
        <item>status-reporter — input: project metrics + last week's report, output: this-week's status with delta + risks.</item>
        <item>meeting-secretary — input: transcript/notes, output: decisions, actions (owner, due, status), open questions.</item>
        <item>comms-auditor — input: meeting calendar + Slack stats + email volume, output: anti-pattern flags (meeting overload, missing decision logs, single-point owners).</item>
        <item>escalation-router — input: issue + impact + first contact, output: who to notify next + by when.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Headline-first: every status starts with R/Y/G + one sentence; details below for skimmers.</p>
      <p>Default to async: writing &gt; meeting unless the topic is decision-shaped or ambiguous; meetings are expensive synchronisation.</p>
      <p>Every meeting has an agenda 24h before, an owner, decisions logged, and action items with owner + due date — or it gets cancelled.</p>
      <p>Match channel to message: urgent = call, complex = meeting, status = report, FYI = chat, reference = wiki, formal = email.</p>
      <p>Send status reports on the same day/time every week; predictability builds the ritual.</p>
      <p>Document decisions in a single decision log (ADR-style for tech, lightweight for biz). "Where was this decided?" is a smell.</p>
      <p>Escalation paths must include backup contacts and out-of-office routing; otherwise they fail at the worst time.</p>
      <p>Metric every 4-6 weeks: meeting hours per person, status report read-rate (email open / Slack reactions), action item closure rate. Cull what isn't read.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>LLM status reports default to optimism — "good progress, all on track". Force the agent to cite metrics or refuse.</p>
      <p>Action items without owner/due date pile up; require both fields or the agent rejects the meeting note.</p>
      <p>Decision summaries lose dissent: agents collapse "we considered X but chose Y because Z" into "we chose Y". Preserve dissent and rationale.</p>
      <p>Channel auto-routing: agents will email everyone for everything. Route by stakeholder preference recorded in the matrix.</p>
      <p>PII / commercial-in-confidence content leaks via meeting transcripts; run a redactor before posting summaries to broad channels.</p>
      <p>Time-zone confusion: status sent at "9 AM" varies by region; pin UTC + local in scheduled comms.</p>
      <p>Escalation hallucination: agents invent contact names not in the register. Require explicit escalation.yaml lookup.</p>
      <p>Status repetition: agents repeat last week's content if metrics didn't change; force them to surface delta or report "no change" explicitly.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Status report with no risks listed when the risk register is non-empty.</description>
        <reason>Empty risk section signals either the PM is not monitoring or is suppressing bad news. Require at least the top-3 risks by impact.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Status reports sent at "9 AM" without timezone, distributed across multiple timezones.</description>
        <reason>Recipients in different timezones receive conflicting effective send times; pin UTC plus local timezone in all scheduled communications.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Escalation contact not reachable; no backup defined.</description>
        <reason>Escalation paths fail precisely when the primary is on leave or in a different incident. Always define primary + backup + out-of-office fallback.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/comms-plan.md" purpose="Communication plan skeleton: stakeholder matrix, meeting schedule, escalation path"/>
      <template path="templates/action-extractor.py" purpose="Regex-based action-item extractor from markdown meeting notes"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="stakeholder-engagement"/>
      <ref slug="project-integration"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-and-standards/foundational-standards/pmbok-guide-7th-edition">PMI PMBOK Guide 6th Ed., Chapter 10 — Project Communications Management</link>
      <link href="https://www.calnewport.com/books/a-world-without-email/">Cal Newport, A World Without Email (2021) — async-default culture</link>
      <link href="https://www.atlassian.com/team-playbook">Atlassian Team Playbook — meeting &amp; status patterns</link>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/72303.html">ISO 21502:2020 — communication competence in project management</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
