<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="design-docs-patterns Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for design-docs-patterns. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write a design document for any feature that takes more than one engineering day, spans multiple PRs or modules, or where requirements are unclear. Skip it for bug fixes with an obvious solution, prototypes where output is discarded, and work under a few hours.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Design documents catch design flaws when changes are cheap (before code is written). The act of writing forces clarity: gaps that seem obvious in conversation become visible in prose. The overhead is justified only when the feature is complex enough that silent assumptions could cause rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use the lightweight Google-style format (1-4 pages) for team-scoped and org-scoped work. Use heavyweight formats (Amazon 6-Pager, Uber RFC) only for cross-org or executive-audience decisions requiring formal sign-off. The format should match the audience and stakes — over-engineering the format wastes time without adding value.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Lightweight docs take hours to write and review; heavyweight docs take days. Applying a 6-pager format to a team-scoped change adds bureaucratic friction without improving the outcome. Conversely, a lightweight doc for a cross-org infrastructure change may fail to reach the right decision-makers or surface all risks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A design doc moves through states: DRAFT → REVIEW → APPROVED → IMPLEMENTING → IMPLEMENTED → ARCHIVED. The APPROVED state is the gate before any implementation begins — proceeding before approval means implementation may need to be redone after review feedback.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The lifecycle state provides an explicit handshake between design and implementation. Without it, engineers start coding on a draft that is still under review, creating merge conflicts between feedback changes and in-flight code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>In the SDD lifecycle, design.md is generated after spec.md is approved (90%+ confidence). The design doc must reach APPROVED status before proceeding to test-plan.md generation. The design doc answers HOW to build; it must not answer WHAT (that belongs in spec.md).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Keeping spec and design as separate artifacts prevents conflation of requirements with implementation. If a reviewer changes the implementation approach, only design.md is updated — the spec (the contract) remains stable. This separation also allows the spec to survive a design rewrite when a better approach is discovered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every design doc must contain: overview (1-2 paragraphs), context/background, goals (specific and measurable), non-goals (explicit), proposed solution/design, alternatives considered (minimum 2 genuine alternatives), cross-cutting concerns, and open questions. Missing any of these signals an incomplete doc.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each required section serves a distinct purpose: overview provides entry-point clarity, non-goals prevent scope creep, alternatives document the reasoning behind the chosen approach, and open questions track unresolved risks. Omitting any of them means future readers must reconstruct reasoning from context, and reviewers cannot give informed sign-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include a non-goals section in every design doc. List at least two explicit non-goals. Non-goals must be real scope boundaries — not obvious statements that nobody would expect. When reviewers raise "have you considered X?", the answer is either in the design or in the non-goals.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Non-goals prevent scope creep discussions during review and implementation. When a non-goal is not written down, every reviewer asks the same question independently. Explicitly stating non-goals sets boundaries that allow the team to focus the review on the actual proposed scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include at least two genuine alternatives — not strawmen. Each alternative must have: a brief description, honest pros, honest cons, and a clear "why not chosen" rationale. Always include "do nothing" as an alternative when applicable.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Strawman alternatives (alternatives that are obviously worse) signal that the author avoided the hard thinking. Genuine alternatives show that tradeoffs were seriously considered. The "why not chosen" rationale is the most important part: it documents the reasoning that future engineers can use to revisit the decision if constraints change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set a review deadline when circulating a design doc. Cap required reviewers at 5-7. For async review, specify comment format expectations in the distribution message. For synchronous review, start with 10-20 minutes of silent reading before discussion.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Design docs without a deadline stay in "in review" indefinitely. Too many required reviewers causes diffusion of responsibility — everyone assumes someone else will catch the issue. Silent reading at the start of a review meeting eliminates the presentation overhead and ensures all reviewers have actually read the doc before discussion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After a design doc is approved, extract each significant architectural decision into a separate Architecture Decision Record (ADR) committed to the repository. Link the ADR from the design doc. ADRs are immutable once accepted; the design doc can evolve but the ADR records the decision as made.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Design docs evolve and may be archived or updated over time. ADRs are permanent records that explain why the codebase is structured the way it is. Without ADRs, engineers inherit code with no context for the decisions behind it, leading to repeated debates about settled questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When generating a design doc with an LLM, always require: (1) a human review pass before marking APPROVED; (2) at least two genuine alternatives, not placeholder text; (3) cross-cutting concerns filled with project-specific content, not generic boilerplate. Reject docs where these sections contain only template placeholders.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs pattern-match to design doc templates and generate authoritative-sounding but generic content. The most dangerous failure mode is a doc that looks complete but contains no actual domain-specific constraints. The three checks above catch the most common LLM failure patterns: missing review, strawman alternatives, and uncustomized boilerplate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
