<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-format-selection" title="Design Doc Format Selection">
  <summary>When to write a design document, how to choose between lightweight and heavyweight formats, and how the doc maps to the SDD lifecycle phases.</summary>

  <section title="When to Write a Design Doc">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write a design document for any feature that takes more than one engineering day, spans multiple PRs or modules, or where requirements are unclear. Skip it for bug fixes with an obvious solution, prototypes where output is discarded, and work under a few hours.</statement>
      <rationale>Design documents catch design flaws when changes are cheap (before code is written). The act of writing forces clarity: gaps that seem obvious in conversation become visible in prose. The overhead is justified only when the feature is complex enough that silent assumptions could cause rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Write: feature takes &gt; 1 engineering day</item>
      <item>Write: change is cross-cutting or multi-PR</item>
      <item>Write: high security or privacy implications</item>
      <item>Write: API changes affecting other teams</item>
      <item>Write: requirements are unclear or conflicting</item>
      <item>Skip: bug fix with obvious single-line solution (PR description is sufficient)</item>
      <item>Skip: prototype or spike where code will be discarded</item>
      <item>Skip: internal refactor with identical external behavior under a few hours</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Format Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the lightweight Google-style format (1-4 pages) for team-scoped and org-scoped work. Use heavyweight formats (Amazon 6-Pager, Uber RFC) only for cross-org or executive-audience decisions requiring formal sign-off. The format should match the audience and stakes — over-engineering the format wastes time without adding value.</statement>
      <rationale>Lightweight docs take hours to write and review; heavyweight docs take days. Applying a 6-pager format to a team-scoped change adds bureaucratic friction without improving the outcome. Conversely, a lightweight doc for a cross-org infrastructure change may fail to reach the right decision-makers or surface all risks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Lightweight (1-4 pages): internal team or org change, rapid iteration context</item>
      <item>Full design doc (Google-style, 5-10 pages): cross-team service or new product feature</item>
      <item>Amazon 6-Pager: strategic initiative, executive review, narrative format required</item>
      <item>Uber RFC: formal approval required, service SLAs, platform change</item>
      <item>ADR: single architectural decision to record permanently in-repo</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/design-doc-lightweight.md">Lightweight design doc template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Design Doc Lifecycle">
    <rule>
      <statement>A design doc moves through states: DRAFT → REVIEW → APPROVED → IMPLEMENTING → IMPLEMENTED → ARCHIVED. The APPROVED state is the gate before any implementation begins — proceeding before approval means implementation may need to be redone after review feedback.</statement>
      <rationale>The lifecycle state provides an explicit handshake between design and implementation. Without it, engineers start coding on a draft that is still under review, creating merge conflicts between feedback changes and in-flight code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>DRAFT: author writes initial version, may share informally</item>
      <item>REVIEW: circulate to stakeholders, collect feedback, iterate</item>
      <item>APPROVED: required approvers sign off; doc is authoritative</item>
      <item>IMPLEMENTING: referenced during development; update if design changes</item>
      <item>IMPLEMENTED: feature shipped; doc becomes historical record</item>
      <item>ARCHIVED: doc superseded or system deprecated</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="SDD Integration">
    <rule>
      <statement>In the SDD lifecycle, design.md is generated after spec.md is approved (90%+ confidence). The design doc must reach APPROVED status before proceeding to test-plan.md generation. The design doc answers HOW to build; it must not answer WHAT (that belongs in spec.md).</statement>
      <rationale>Keeping spec and design as separate artifacts prevents conflation of requirements with implementation. If a reviewer changes the implementation approach, only design.md is updated — the spec (the contract) remains stable. This separation also allows the spec to survive a design rewrite when a better approach is discovered.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM-Generated Design Docs">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating an LLM-generated design doc as authoritative without a human review pass. LLMs produce confident-sounding text that may be missing domain-specific constraints, organizational context, or real trade-offs.</description>
      <reason>LLMs pattern-match to generic design doc templates and fill in plausible-sounding content. They lack knowledge of your specific system constraints, team norms, and organizational history. A human review pass is mandatory to catch incorrect assumptions before the doc influences implementation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
