<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Legal Compliance Checklist Stage-by-Stage Implementation Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `ops-legal-compliance-checklist` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-stage-gated-progression" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Progress only when the prior stage is fully checked off: Day-1 → Month-1 → Year-1 → Ongoing. Skipping stages or marking partial completion as done is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Compliance-program practice (SOC 2 readiness playbooks)">Out-of-order completion creates compliance gaps that surface during audit. The stage gate forces sequential completion and a paper trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-presence-not-sufficiency" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The checklist verifies presence and process, NOT legal sufficiency of text. Marking a ToS row 'done' because a file exists, without attorney review, is forbidden as evidence of legal sufficiency.</statement>
      <rationale source="Legal-operations practice (LegalGeek, OnePager Legal)">Checklists confirm operational readiness; only an attorney confirms enforceability. Conflating the two creates false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-day-1-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Day-1 items (entity formation, EIN, business bank account, ToS / Privacy / Refund policies) MUST be checked off before accepting the first paying customer. Accepting customers without these is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Online-business startup practice">Operating without Day-1 items exposes the operator to personal liability and regulator action. The Day-1 floor is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-evidence-link-per-row" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every checked row carries a link to evidence (filed document, signed policy, screenshot of compliance UI). Unevidenced 'done' marks are flagged at review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-readiness practice (SOC 2 / ISO 27001)">Auditors require evidence per control. Pre-staging evidence at check-off time eliminates pre-audit panic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-ongoing-cadence-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ongoing items (policy refresh cycle, vendor contract review, data-deletion drills) have named owners and review cadences (quarterly or annual). 'Whoever has time' is forbidden as cadence.</statement>
      <rationale source="Compliance-program practice">Without named owners and cadence, ongoing items decay into stale folklore. The cadence + owner pair is the only reliable mechanism for keeping the program alive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
