<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-checklist" title="Legal Compliance Checklist — Stage-by-Stage Items">
  <summary>Compliance checklist organized by business stage: Day 1, Month 1, Year 1, and Ongoing, plus website-specific requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Day 1 — Foundation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Complete all Day 1 items before accepting any payment or collecting any user data.</statement>
      <rationale>Legal and data-protection obligations attach at the moment of business activity, not at scale. Pre-revenue compliance is cheaper than retrofitted compliance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Business entity chosen and registered (LLC, S-Corp, C-Corp, or sole proprietor)</item>
      <item>EIN obtained or applied for</item>
      <item>Business bank account opened (separate from personal)</item>
      <item>Terms of Service drafted and published</item>
      <item>Privacy Policy drafted (GDPR/CCPA-aware) and published</item>
      <item>Cookie Policy created if website uses cookies</item>
      <item>Refund/Return Policy documented</item>
      <item>Business license obtained if required by state</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Month 1 — Post-Launch">
    <list>
      <item>Terms of Service and Privacy Policy linked in website footer</item>
      <item>Contact information publicly accessible on site</item>
      <item>Consent mechanism implemented for personal data collection</item>
      <item>Marketing email opt-out mechanism working and tested</item>
      <item>GDPR compliance verified if serving EU customers (consent, DPO contact if required)</item>
      <item>CCPA compliance verified if serving California customers (Do Not Sell link if applicable)</item>
      <item>PCI-DSS compliance verified for payment processing</item>
      <item>Trademark search completed for business name and logo</item>
      <item>Licenses for any third-party content (images, fonts, code) confirmed</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Year 1 — Comprehensive">
    <list>
      <item>Tax professional (CPA/accountant) engaged</item>
      <item>Quarterly tax estimate process established</item>
      <item>Sales tax nexus determined by state</item>
      <item>Contractor agreements finalized and on file</item>
      <item>CAN-SPAM compliance verified for email marketing (physical address, unsubscribe)</item>
      <item>Industry-specific regulations identified and documented</item>
      <item>General liability insurance obtained</item>
      <item>Cyber liability insurance obtained if handling user data</item>
      <item>Trademark registration initiated for high-value brand assets</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Ongoing — Continuous">
    <rule>
      <statement>Establish a quarterly policy-review cycle. Assign a calendar reminder and treat it as a recurring sprint task, not an optional maintenance item.</statement>
      <rationale>Policies become inaccurate as the product evolves. A privacy policy written at launch that does not reflect current data flows is a compliance liability and erodes user trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Regulatory change monitoring (FTC, EDPB, ICO, state privacy laws, EU AI Act)</item>
      <item>Policies updated within 30 days of material regulatory change</item>
      <item>Data retention policy enforced and deletion procedure tested</item>
      <item>GDPR right-to-deletion process (DSAR) verified quarterly</item>
      <item>Data breach notification plan reviewed and contacts current</item>
      <item>Compliance documentation stored securely with version history</item>
      <item>Third-party vendor list reconciled against privacy policy disclosures</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Website-specific requirements">
    <list>
      <item>SSL/HTTPS installed on all pages</item>
      <item>Cookie consent banner present and compliant (no pre-ticked boxes, equal-prominence reject button)</item>
      <item>WCAG 2.1 AA accessibility verified</item>
      <item>Data access/correction/deletion request process documented and accessible</item>
      <item>Privacy policies for all analytics and tracking tools verified</item>
      <item>CDN/hosting provider data practices reviewed</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/audit-footer-legal.py"/>
    <link path="templates/policy-update-notification.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
