<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ops-legal-compliance-checklist Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ops-legal-compliance-checklist as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>No LLC or entity formation - business operates as sole proprietor with no liability protection.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Personal assets are exposed to business liability. A single lawsuit or regulatory fine reaches the founder's personal bank account, home, and savings.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Copy-pasted privacy policy from a competitor or template that does not reflect actual data practices.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A policy that does not match reality is worse than no policy: it creates a documented false statement. Regulators (FTC, EDPB) treat this as a deceptive practice independent of whether harm occurred.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Policies updated silently without user notification on material changes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Material changes to privacy terms require user notification under GDPR (Article 13/14), some state laws, and trust norms. Silent updates erode trust and may expose the business to regulatory action.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>GDPR compliance treated as a one-time checkbox at launch rather than an ongoing operational process.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>GDPR applies to every new integration, new data flow, new market, and every change in data processors. Post-launch changes (adding an analytics tool, enabling AI features) reopen compliance obligations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Cookie consent banner uses pre-ticked boxes or makes "reject all" harder to find than "accept all".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>EDPB guidelines explicitly prohibit dark patterns in consent interfaces. Non-compliant banners from major services have received multi-million euro fines. Consent must be freely given, specific, informed, and unambiguous.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>No written contracts with contractors - work is commissioned verbally or via email without a signed agreement.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a contract, IP ownership is ambiguous (contractor may own the work they created), payment terms are disputed, and confidentiality is unprotected. A contractor agreement costs less than one hour of legal time to prepare from a template.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
