<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Error Recovery — Nielsen Heuristic #9 Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Error Recovery — Nielsen Heuristic #9 application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-three-components" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every error message MUST contain all three components: what happened + why + how to fix. Messages missing any component are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Missing components leave users stuck; "An error occurred" without why or fix is the canonical bad message.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-plain-language" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Messages MUST be in plain language; jargon, error codes alone, and stack traces are rejected for end-user surfaces.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Jargon-laden messages produce support tickets; plain language resolves errors in-product.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-actionable-fix" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The "how to fix" component MUST be actionable: a specific button, link, retry path, or instruction. Vague "try again later" is rejected when a concrete path exists.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Specific actionable fixes reduce abandonment; vague suggestions push the user to support.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-blame-neutral" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Messages MUST be blame-neutral: no "you did wrong" framing. The system shares responsibility.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Blame framing degrades trust; neutral framing keeps the user engaged with the fix.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-tested-with-non-technical-users" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Drafted messages MUST be tested with non-technical users before ship. Untested messages are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Designers underestimate jargon; non-technical user testing surfaces the gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
