<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Error Recovery — Three-Component Message Structure">
  <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #9: plain-language error messages with three mandatory components and placement rules per error type.</summary>

  <section title="The Heuristic">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every error message must contain three components: what happened (problem statement), why it happened (context), and how to fix it (concrete action).</statement>
      <rationale>An error message missing any of the three components creates a dead end. Without "what happened," users do not understand the failure. Without "why," they cannot prevent recurrence. Without "how to fix," they cannot continue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Full three-component message: "You don't have permission to view this page. [What] Your account requires administrator access for this section. [Why] Contact your administrator to request access. [How]"</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"Error 403" — provides the technical code only. Users cannot act on this. Maps to none of the three components.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Five Message Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write error messages in plain language: no error codes, no technical jargon, no system-facing terminology.</statement>
      <rationale>Error codes are meaningful to engineers, not users. A user who sees ECONNREFUSED cannot diagnose or fix a network issue; "Cannot connect — check your internet connection" can.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Be specific: name the exact field or element that caused the error, not a generic summary.</statement>
      <rationale>"Invalid input" forces users to guess which field is wrong. "This email address is missing the @ symbol" points directly to the problem and its solution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never write error messages that blame the user for the error.</statement>
      <rationale>Blame language ("You entered invalid data") increases frustration and damages trust. The error message is a recovery tool, not a judgment. Passive or system-focused framing ("This email address doesn't match our records") is always preferable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always provide at least one recovery action — a button, link, or explicit instruction — never a dead-end OK button.</statement>
      <rationale>An error message without a recovery path traps users. If the only button is [OK], users return to a state with no guidance on what to do next. Every error should offer [Retry], [Go back], [Contact support], or an explicit instruction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Place error messages immediately adjacent to the element that caused them — inline for form fields, banner for page-level errors, modal only for system failures requiring full attention.</statement>
      <rationale>An error shown at the top of the page while the problem field is at the bottom forces users to scroll and cross-reference. Proximity makes the relationship between error and fix obvious.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Error Type Placement Rules">
    <p>Validation errors: inline, next to the field; show on blur or submit, not on every keystroke. Recovery: user corrects input.</p>
    <p>System errors: modal or banner when the operation has failed; recovery path: Retry, alternative action, support contact.</p>
    <p>404 Not Found: full page; message explains page not found plus navigation suggestions; recovery: links to home, search, common pages.</p>
    <p>Network errors: banner or non-blocking modal; recovery: Retry, Offline mode, Check connection instruction.</p>
    <p>Form with multiple errors: show count summary at top ("Please fix 3 errors") plus inline error at each field; both are required — summary alone forces scrolling, inline alone loses overview.</p>
    <reference path="templates/error-message.md">Per-error design doc template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/error-audit.md">Audit table for reviewing existing error messages</reference>
  </section>
</text>
