<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Error Recovery — Good and Bad Message Examples">
  <summary>Real error message examples from Stripe, GitHub, and form validation, plus anti-patterns with failure explanations.</summary>

  <section title="Good Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Stripe payment error: "Your card was declined. Your card number is incorrect. Please check the number and try again." [Try a different card] — all three components present, plain language, specific cause, recovery action provided.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>GitHub 404: "This is not the web page you are looking for. The page you requested doesn't exist. You may have typed the address incorrectly or the page may have moved." [Go to GitHub.com] [Search GitHub] — human tone, two recovery paths offered.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Form password validation: "Password must contain: checkmark At least 8 characters / X One uppercase letter (add one) / X One number (add one)" — live checklist format shows both what is satisfied and what remains; users can see progress without re-reading requirements.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Showing only a technical error code: "Error: ECONNREFUSED" or "Error 403".</description>
      <reason>Technical codes are meaningless to users. They cannot diagnose the problem or take any corrective action. Even "Connection refused" is better than the raw code.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Generic error message: "Something went wrong."</description>
      <reason>Tells users nothing about what failed, why, or what to do. Generates immediate support escalation because users have no information to self-serve.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Blame framing: "You entered invalid data" or "You did not complete the form correctly."</description>
      <reason>Accusatory language increases frustration without adding information. Replace with passive or system-focused framing: "This field requires a valid date" rather than "You entered an invalid date."</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Dead-end error with only an [OK] button and no recovery path.</description>
      <reason>Users who dismiss an [OK] dialog are returned to an unchanged state with no guidance. They will either repeat the same action (same failure) or abandon. Always offer at least one forward path.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not communicate errors by color change alone — always include an icon or text label alongside color.</statement>
      <rationale>Color-only error indication fails for users with color vision deficiency. Red borders without an error icon or text are invisible to approximately 8% of male users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use ARIA live regions or role="alert" to announce errors to screen reader users; move focus to the error message or the first invalid field on form submission.</statement>
      <rationale>Screen reader users do not perceive visual error indicators. Without ARIA announcements and focus management, they may be unaware an error occurred at all.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
