<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-program-components" title="Onboarding Program Components">
  <summary>Eight components of a repeatable new-hire onboarding program with scope and agent-workflow notes for each.</summary>

  <section title="Preboarding (Offer Accept to Day 0)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Move all paperwork, equipment shipping, and account provisioning to preboarding; Day 1 must be reserved for human connection, not e-signatures.</statement>
      <rationale>New hires who spend Day 1 on HR paperwork report lower engagement and higher anxiety. Every administrative task completed before Day 1 reduces cognitive load on the highest-anxiety workday.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Timeline: send welcome email and next-steps on offer signing; ship equipment 2 weeks before; send schedule and team-intro email 1 week before; send reminder and point-of-contact day before.</p>
    <reference path="templates/preboard-gate.py">Run 5 days before start to verify all 7 preboarding conditions are GREEN before sending the welcome email.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Day 1 Orientation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Day 1 agenda must prioritize welcome and buddy introduction in the first hour; IT setup and paperwork follow only after the human connection is established.</statement>
      <rationale>First impressions of belonging predict 90-day retention more than tool access. Reversing the order (IT first) signals that the organization values compliance over people.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Suggested flow: 9:00 welcome and buddy intro, 9:30 HR paperwork and benefits, 10:30 IT setup, 12:00 team lunch, 13:30 company overview and culture, 15:00 manager 1:1 on expectations, 16:00 self-paced onboarding.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Buddy Program">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign a buddy who is peer-level and on a different reporting line from the manager; duration 90 days minimum with weekly check-ins in month 1.</statement>
      <rationale>A manager-chosen buddy from the same chain of command replicates the manager relationship rather than providing the independent, informal channel that predicts new-hire integration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Buddy scope: culture and unwritten rules, navigating the organization, introducing cross-functional contacts. Not a second manager; the buddy does not evaluate performance.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="30-60-90 Progression">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each onboarding phase must end with an observable artifact; never accept "understands X" or "is familiar with Y" as a milestone completion criterion.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague verbs like "understand" cannot be verified at the day-30 review; observable artifacts (PR merged, doc written, customer call completed) can.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Phase structure: days 1-30 learn (context, relationships, tools); days 31-60 contribute (first owned project); days 61-90 execute (independent delivery). See separate 30-60-90-day-plan and onboarding-60-90-day methodologies for full templates.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Feedback Loops">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a 4-question pulse survey at week 1, detailed survey at day 30, check-in conversation at day 60, and full review including eNPS at day 90.</statement>
      <rationale>Rising attrition shows up in week-1 pulse data first. Waiting for the day-30 survey means losing 3 weeks of correction opportunity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Core questions: Did you feel welcomed? Was your role clear? Did you have the tools you needed? How could we improve? Keep week-1 survey to 4 questions maximum.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Manager Onboarding Guide">
    <rule>
      <statement>Train managers on the onboarding timeline and their specific actions at each milestone before the hire's first day; unprepared managers are the leading cause of poor onboarding outcomes.</statement>
      <rationale>Manager preparation (workspace set up, 1:1 schedule, expectations documented) is the variable most correlated with new-hire engagement at day 30 (Gallup).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Remote Onboarding Adaptations">
    <rule>
      <statement>For remote hires: ship laptop pre-imaged before Day 1, default Day 1 to async-plus-one-synchronous-session, and over-communicate using multiple channels.</statement>
      <rationale>Remote hires who don't receive equipment before Day 1 spend their first week without tools; the resulting frustration is disproportionate to the logistics cost of early shipping.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Remote-specific risks: isolation (mitigate with virtual coffee and buddy program), culture invisibility (explicit culture sessions and documentation), connection failure (virtual team activities in week 1).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Compliance Training">
    <rule>
      <statement>Spread compliance modules (security, harassment, GDPR, SOC 2) across days 5-30; never schedule them all on Day 1.</statement>
      <rationale>Compliance overload on Day 1 crowds out role learning and culture absorption — the two inputs that actually predict ramp speed and retention.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
