<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-checklist" title="Onboarding Checklist by Phase">
  <summary>Verifiable action items for each onboarding phase from before Day 1 through month 1, with completion criteria.</summary>

  <section title="Before Day 1">
    <rule>
      <statement>All seven preboarding items must be complete before sending the Day-1 schedule to the new hire.</statement>
      <rationale>Sending a Day-1 schedule when equipment has not shipped or accounts are not provisioned sets up a failed first day and damages trust in the organization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Equipment ordered and confirmed shipped with tracking number.</item>
      <item>Email, Slack, and primary tools accounts created and verified.</item>
      <item>Welcome email sent with first-week schedule and point-of-contact name.</item>
      <item>Team notified of start date, role, and brief intro bio.</item>
      <item>Buddy assigned and briefed on scope and first-week check-in date.</item>
      <item>Benefits enrollment instructions sent.</item>
      <item>Manager has blocked calendar for Day-1 1:1 and week-1 daily check-ins.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/preboard-gate.py">Automated gate: run 5 days before start; blocks welcome email if any item is RED.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Day 1">
    <list>
      <item>Warm welcome from team within first 30 minutes.</item>
      <item>IT setup verified complete (laptop on, tools accessible).</item>
      <item>Paperwork and benefit enrollment signed.</item>
      <item>Manager 1:1 completed: expectations discussed, first project scope shared.</item>
      <item>Introduction to buddy completed.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Week 1">
    <list>
      <item>All recurring key meetings (standups, 1:1s, team syncs) added to calendar.</item>
      <item>Access to all required systems verified by the new hire.</item>
      <item>Training modules assigned with completion dates.</item>
      <item>Week-1 pulse survey sent (4 questions, anonymous).</item>
      <item>Introduction to key stakeholders outside immediate team completed.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Month 1">
    <list>
      <item>30-day check-in completed with manager; goals for days 31-60 documented.</item>
      <item>Feedback collected and blockers addressed.</item>
      <item>Day-30 detailed onboarding survey sent.</item>
      <item>Buddy check-in: confirm buddy program is active and useful.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>30-day goals must be documented in a shared artifact before the check-in closes; verbal agreements decay within a week.</statement>
      <rationale>Undocumented goals cannot be referenced at the day-60 review; the hire enters phase 2 without a written contract of what success looks like.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Documentation-as-onboarding: assigning a new hire a reading list without synchronous context.</description>
      <reason>New hires do not read documentation as a primary learning mode; it is a reference, not an onboarding mechanism. An agent piping docs is a worse experience than a human explanation.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Buddy program with no check-in cadence or scope definition.</description>
      <reason>Buddy relationships degrade silently when buddies stop checking in; without a scheduled first meeting and defined scope, the buddy becomes a name on a form.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
