<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-error-ladder" title="VUI Error Recovery Ladder">
  <summary>Error taxonomy, three-rung re-prompt ladder rules, escalation triggers, and copy guidelines for voice interface error handling.</summary>

  <section title="Error Taxonomy">
    <p>Four error types in voice interfaces, each requiring a distinct recovery approach:</p>
    <list>
      <item>No-input: user is silent. Cause: user did not understand they should speak, distracted, or endpointing cut off early. Recovery: brief re-ask with response-timing hint.</item>
      <item>No-match: speech recognized but intent not matched. Cause: out-of-vocabulary utterance, accent mismatch, NLU gap. Recovery: re-ask with example phrases from training data.</item>
      <item>Ambiguous: multiple valid intent interpretations with similar confidence. Recovery: ask a disambiguating clarifying question — do not guess.</item>
      <item>System error: technical failure (API timeout, platform error). Recovery: apologize, state the problem briefly, suggest retry or alternative channel.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Three-Rung Ladder">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure every re-prompt sequence as exactly three rungs: rung 1 (brief re-ask), rung 2 (constructive re-ask with two example phrases), rung 3 (escalation to visual fallback, DTMF, or human agent). Cap at three rungs — escalate on the fourth attempt, never loop.</statement>
      <rationale>Users who hear the same phrase three times in a row perceive the system as broken. Three rungs balance error recovery opportunity against abandonment risk. Looping past rung 3 has near-zero recovery rate and high frustration cost.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Rung 1 (no-match):
"I didn't catch that. What's the city?"

Rung 2 (constructive):
"I'm having trouble understanding. Try saying something like 'New York' or 'Chicago'."

Rung 3 (escalation):
"Let me try a different approach. You can press 1 to continue with our menu, or say 'agent' to speak with someone."
]]></code>
      <note>Rung 2 uses exactly two example phrases from NLU training data. Rung 3 offers both DTMF and voice escalation paths.</note>
    </example>

    <rule>
      <statement>Vary the rung-2 example phrases per session. Rotate across 3–5 phrase sets so users who retry the skill do not learn to mimic one phrase, masking the true NLU coverage gap.</statement>
      <rationale>Users who successfully mimic a single example phrase suppress the signal that the NLU training data is too narrow. Rotating phrases reveals the true no-match surface area.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Copy Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use blame language: ban "you said wrong", "invalid", "didn't work", "I'm sorry" stacking (more than once per session). Voice the system's limitation, not the user's failure.</statement>
      <rationale>Blame language causes immediate abandonment. Users who feel blamed do not retry — they leave and write negative reviews. "I didn't catch that" attributes the failure to the system; "You said something I couldn't understand" attributes it to the user.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>For telephony channels, always offer DTMF fallback ("press 1 for...") on rung 3. Never escalate to human-agent-only without a self-service option.</statement>
      <rationale>Telephony channels add 8 kHz codec loss and cross-talk that no copy fix mitigates. DTMF remains reliable when ASR fails. Human-agent-only escalation has queue costs; self-service DTMF is free.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <reference path="templates/reprompt-lint.py">CI lint: flag missing rung 3 escalation, missing rung 2 examples, banned blame phrases</reference>
  </section>
</text>
