<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-antipatterns-and-workflow" title="VUI Error Handling Antipatterns and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>Known failure modes in LLM-assisted VUI error design, SSML rules, agentic workflow guidance, and human-in-loop gates.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM-driven VUI bypasses the fixed re-prompt ladder because the model improvises responses.</description>
      <reason>Realtime API and Gemini Live models improvise and do not follow rung-by-rung fallback. Use system-prompt rules to enforce escalation triggers; test that the tool call actually fires, not just that the model says "transferring you".</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Example phrases on rung 2 that do not exist in the NLU training data.</description>
      <reason>Every rung-2 example must round-trip through the recognizer. An invented example phrase trains users to say something the NLU cannot recognize, generating a guaranteed no-match on the retry.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Apologetic templates that stack "I'm sorry" across multiple rungs.</description>
      <reason>Subagents writing re-prompt copy default to apologetic patterns. A single apology on a system error is appropriate; stacking "I'm sorry" across rungs signals the system is broken rather than helping the user recover.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Re-prompts that use identical phrasing across rungs (stuck-loop pattern).</description>
      <reason>Users interpret repeated identical prompts as a system freeze. Vary phrasing across rungs to signal progression through the recovery sequence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="SSML Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add SSML pause tags when any pause in the re-prompt exceeds 300 ms. Never rely on punctuation alone for TTS timing.</statement>
      <rationale>TTS engines interpret punctuation inconsistently. A comma that sounds natural in text may render as no pause in TTS, making instructions rush together and increasing mis-recognition on retry.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Drive Claude to enumerate failure types per intent, then generate three-rung re-prompt ladders plus matching SSML/text. A second pass linting agent checks for: blame language, missing example phrases on rung 2, absent escalation on rung 3. Use a separate agent to fuzz the dialog by sampling adversarial transcripts (silence, mumble, code-switch, off-topic).</p>

    <p>Human-in-loop gate: review rung 3 escalation copy with support and legal before shipping. "Transferring to a human agent", "escalating to support", and refund-adjacent phrasing have compliance impact that agents cannot assess.</p>

    <p>Log raw ASR hypotheses (not just normalized intent) — reveals systematic mishears that copy changes alone cannot fix. When users repeat verbatim louder or slower and intent still matches, the copy is too narrow — widen the training data, not the prompt.</p>
  </section>
</text>
