<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="error-handling-in-vui Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for error-handling-in-vui as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM-driven VUI bypasses the fixed re-prompt ladder because the model improvises responses.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Realtime API and Gemini Live models improvise and do not follow rung-by-rung fallback. Use system-prompt rules to enforce escalation triggers; test that the tool call actually fires, not just that the model says "transferring you".</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Example phrases on rung 2 that do not exist in the NLU training data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every rung-2 example must round-trip through the recognizer. An invented example phrase trains users to say something the NLU cannot recognize, generating a guaranteed no-match on the retry.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Apologetic templates that stack "I'm sorry" across multiple rungs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Subagents writing re-prompt copy default to apologetic patterns. A single apology on a system error is appropriate; stacking "I'm sorry" across rungs signals the system is broken rather than helping the user recover.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Re-prompts that use identical phrasing across rungs (stuck-loop pattern).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Users interpret repeated identical prompts as a system freeze. Vary phrasing across rungs to signal progression through the recovery sequence.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
