<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-environment" title="VR Environment Anchoring and Scale Rules">
  <summary>Ground plane, horizon, scale, lighting, boundary, and grounding requirements that form the stable perceptual foundation for any VR experience.</summary>

  <section title="Grounding elements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the floor/ground plane visible at all times with consistent appearance. Never float the user in a void without a stable reference surface.</statement>
      <rationale>Loss of ground reference causes immediate disorientation; the ground plane is the primary spatial anchor for the vestibular system in VR.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain a stable, expected horizon position. The horizon provides orientation and reduces nausea independently of the ground plane.</statement>
      <rationale>An unstable horizon forces the vestibular and visual systems into conflict, the primary mechanism of VR sickness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include at least one stable reference object (cockpit in vehicle sims, dashboard in driving, wrist-mounted UI) that moves with the user and is always visible.</statement>
      <rationale>Fixed reference objects provide a visual rest point that decouples perceived self-motion from environment motion, reducing visual-vestibular mismatch.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scale">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use 1:1 real-world scale for familiar objects (doors 2 m, tables 70-75 cm, chairs 45 cm, average human height). When using intentionally different scale, make the difference unambiguous and provide a human-scale reference object.</statement>
      <rationale>Ambiguous scale breaks depth perception and comfortable interaction distance; users reach for objects at the wrong distance when scale cues are inconsistent.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Lighting">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use consistent lighting that matches real-world expectations for time of day; keep light sources visible; ensure shadows enhance depth. Avoid extremes: too dark breaks visibility, too bright causes discomfort.</statement>
      <rationale>Inconsistent lighting undermines depth perception and increases the cognitive load needed to understand the environment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Boundaries and safety">
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement a guardian/chaperone system: visual boundary at wall approach, controller haptic warning, audio alert option, experience pause on boundary crossing, easy re-centering action.</statement>
      <rationale>Physical collisions with real-world objects cause injury; guardian systems are required by all major platform certification programmes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define minimum play space requirements at first launch; warn if the space is too small and offer a seated alternative automatically.</statement>
      <rationale>Room-scale experiences designed without space constraints exclude users in smaller rooms and create safety hazards.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
