<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-locomotion-and-ui" title="Locomotion Options and UI Placement Rules">
  <summary>Locomotion method selection with comfort ratings, UI panel placement rules, gaze-confirm interaction pattern, and spatial audio requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Locomotion">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to teleportation plus snap turn. Smooth locomotion and smooth turning are opt-in only, with vignette automatically enabled when the user activates them.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents and developers default to smooth locomotion as the "modern" option; teleport must be pinned as default to protect motion-sensitive users and wheelchair users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Teleportation (high comfort): best for general movement, seated users, and wheelchair users. Should be the default.</item>
      <item>Walking/room-scale (high comfort for non-disabled): limited to the physical play area; excludes wheelchair users by design — always pair with teleport.</item>
      <item>Controller/smooth movement (medium comfort): exploration use case; requires vignette and speed cap when enabled.</item>
      <item>Vehicle/seat (high comfort): seated experiences; wheelchair-friendly.</item>
      <item>Flying (low-medium comfort): specific use cases only; highest nausea risk; offer vignette and speed limits.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always offer a seated mode that makes every interaction reachable without standing. Test with a wheelchair-user proxy before shipping.</statement>
      <rationale>Seated mode is the most commonly skipped accessibility feature in room-scale VR; agents will omit it without an explicit check.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/comfort-defaults.json">Comfort-defaults schema with locomotion, turn, vignette, UI, accessibility, and performance fields</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="UI placement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place UI panels at 1.5-3 m from the user, at eye level (sitting or standing), curved to match the viewing angle. Never head-lock any UI element.</statement>
      <rationale>Head-locked UI causes immediate nausea because it moves with every head motion; world-locked or body-locked UI stays stable relative to the environment or the user's body.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Minimum text size in VR is 14-16 pt; test readability at the actual 2 m viewing distance. Web/mobile point sizes do not transfer to VR.</statement>
      <rationale>Text that reads fine on a monitor is unreadable in a VR headset at viewing distance; agents generate text sizes from web/mobile experience and must be corrected.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer diegetic UI (holographic displays, wrist-mounted, screens on objects) where it fits the narrative. Reserve non-diegetic UI (pause menus, settings, HUDs) for meta-level interactions with clear visual distinction from the world.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixed diegetic and non-diegetic without clear distinction breaks presence and increases cognitive load.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Interaction and spatial audio">
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement gaze-plus-confirm selection (gaze highlights the object, button press or dwell confirms) as an accessible baseline interaction that works without hand precision.</statement>
      <rationale>Gaze selection works from a distance, is accessible to users with reduced hand mobility, and requires no controller precision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Confirm every button press with a spatial audio cue and synchronized haptic feedback. Add 3D-positioned audio cues for out-of-view events.</statement>
      <rationale>Multimodal feedback confirms interactions for users who may not see or feel a single modality; spatial audio for off-screen events prevents missing critical signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
