<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-accessibility" title="VR Accessibility by Disability Category">
  <summary>Disability-coverage matrix for fully-immersive VR covering vision, hearing, mobility, and cognitive needs, with testable requirements per category.</summary>

  <section title="Vision">
    <list>
      <item>High contrast mode toggle.</item>
      <item>Large text options (minimum 14-16 pt; verify at actual VR viewing distance, not on monitor).</item>
      <item>Color-blind safe palette as an option; test designs with deuteranopia, protanopia, and tritanopia simulations.</item>
      <item>Audio descriptions for all informative visual-only elements.</item>
      <item>Screen-reader integration is experimental in most VR platforms; document known gaps explicitly.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Hearing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add visual captions in 3D space for every audio-cued event. Caption size and position must be adjustable by the user.</statement>
      <rationale>Spatial audio is the primary feedback channel in VR for many critical events; deaf and hard-of-hearing users need visual equivalents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Haptic feedback synchronized with sounds.</item>
      <item>Visual flash indicators for directional audio alerts from off-screen sources.</item>
      <item>Per-source volume controls (separate sliders for music, SFX, voice, UI).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Mobility">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every interaction in the experience must be reachable from a seated position. Explicitly test the interaction reach envelope for a seated player before shipping.</statement>
      <rationale>Room-scale designs assume standing; seated-mode parity requires deliberate design of interaction distances and heights.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Teleportation available for all movement (not only as an afterthought comfort option).</item>
      <item>Voice commands mapped to all primary actions (select, menu, pause, help).</item>
      <item>Controller-free hand tracking as an optional input mode.</item>
      <item>Adjustable height offset to accommodate different sitting heights and postures.</item>
      <item>All content reachable within a standard wheelchair-accessible interaction arc.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Cognitive">
    <list>
      <item>Simplified UI mode with reduced information density and fewer simultaneous choices.</item>
      <item>Clear, step-by-step tutorials; no assumed prior VR experience from first-time users.</item>
      <item>Pauseable at any point with no time pressure during the paused state.</item>
      <item>Difficulty adjustment where content difficulty varies.</item>
      <item>Memory aids: contextual hints, progress indicators, reminders of the current objective.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Testing requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Test with at least one person prone to motion sickness, one wheelchair user (or seated-only tester), and one first-time VR user before any public release.</statement>
      <rationale>Developer familiarity with XR normalizes discomfort and novelty; the three tester profiles reveal distinct failure modes that internal teams miss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run at least one 30-minute extended-session test; short demos hide fatigue, drift, and cumulative discomfort that only appear over time.</statement>
      <rationale>Comfort problems compound over time; a 10-minute demo that feels fine can produce nausea and arm fatigue at minute 25.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
