<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-tool-landscape" title="Spatial Design Tool Landscape">
  <summary>Tool matrix organized by project phase, device target, and file-format standard for AR/VR/MR workflows.</summary>

  <section title="Phase-Gated Tool Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick tools per phase, not per project: concept in Figma + ShapesXR, prototype in Unity or Unreal, production in engine.</statement>
      <rationale>Forcing one tool across all phases introduces fidelity gaps (ShapesXR concepts look different in Unity) and breaks asset pipelines at transition points.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Tool Matrix">
      <p>Concept phase: Figma (2D wireframes with spatial annotations) + ShapesXR or Gravity Sketch (VR-native sketching). Prototype phase: ShapesXR low-fidelity → Unity or Unreal high-fidelity, tested in target headset. Production: Unity or Unreal with XR Interaction Toolkit.</p>

      <p>Device-specific additions: visionOS → Reality Composer Pro (scene authoring); Meta Quest → Meta Quest Developer Hub (sideload + metrics); WebXR → Three.js or Babylon.js.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Format Standards by Platform">
      <rule>
        <statement>Standardize on USD/USDZ for visionOS handoff; glTF 2.0 for Web/Quest. Pick one format per device and enforce it across the asset pipeline.</statement>
        <rationale>The file-format zoo (USDZ, glTF, FBX, USD, Unity prefabs) is the primary cause of pipeline breaks. A single missing conversion flag (axis swap, scale unit) burns hours per asset.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent-Friendly Tool Assessment">
    <p>Figma: partial agent access via REST + plugin API (concept stage, export limited). ShapesXR: limited — VR-native, manual export to Unity. Gravity Sketch: partial — export FBX/OBJ/USD. Unity: full CLI + Cloud Build (batch builds, CI). Unreal: partial (Horde, BuildGraph). Reality Composer Pro: no agent API — macOS only, manual workflow. Spark AR / Lens Studio: no API — vendor-locked.</p>

    <p>For 3D capture: Polycam and Luma AI expose REST APIs and output glTF/USDZ — useful for asset library generation.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Asset Validation CLI">
    <p>Use these tools in CI to validate spatial assets before handoff:</p>
    <list>
      <item>usdcat / usdview — inspect and validate USD/USDZ (Pixar OpenUSD)</item>
      <item>gltf-validator — validate glTF 2.0 spatial assets (Khronos)</item>
      <item>realitytool — Apple visionOS USDZ packaging (Xcode 15+)</item>
      <item>gltf-pipeline — glTF compression via Draco / Meshopt (CesiumGS)</item>
      <item>Blender --background --python — headless format conversion</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/spatial-budget.sh">CI asset-budget lint script</reference>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../spatial-ux-fundamentals/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
