<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-pipeline-rules" title="Spatial Asset Pipeline Rules">
  <summary>Asset-budget rules, format-choice enforcement, agentic workflow guidance, and known failure modes for spatial design pipelines.</summary>

  <section title="Asset Budget Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set polygon count and texture size budgets at concept stage, before any artist work begins. Enforce budgets in CI via a lint script.</statement>
      <rationale>Performance budgets only become real constraints inside the target engine. Concept-tool exports (ShapesXR, Gravity Sketch) do not respect engine budgets; artists who build without targets spend days optimizing under deadline pressure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Declare unit (meters), axis convention (Y-up vs. Z-up), and handedness in every export script header. Reject assets that omit these declarations.</statement>
      <rationale>A missing axis-swap flag produces subtly broken assets that look correct in one tool and appear flipped or at wrong scale in the target engine. LLMs omit these consistently — enforce at the pipeline level.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <reference path="templates/spatial-budget.sh">CI script: fail build if glTF asset exceeds polygon or size budget</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Source of Truth">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain one shared asset repository; tool-specific copies (Figma, ShapesXR, Unity, Unreal) must always derive from the shared repo, never fork from each other.</statement>
      <rationale>Tool-specific copies drift within a single sprint. A Gravity Sketch export edited in Blender and re-imported to Unity without touching the shared repo creates a fork that silently diverges.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Test in the target headset by week 2 of any project. Concept-tool fidelity hides 80% of comfort issues (interpupillary distance, locomotion sickness, focus distance).</statement>
      <rationale>Comfort issues surface only in hardware. Simulator and desktop previews mask vergence-accommodation conflict, edge distortion, and locomotion nausea.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Agents can: (a) recommend the right tool per project phase given device and team constraints, (b) automate format conversions and asset-budget linting, (c) generate handoff documentation. Tool choice itself remains human — the team's existing skill stack dominates the decision.</p>

    <p>Useful subagents: faion-ux-researcher-agent (assembles tool comparison matrix from vendor docs), faion-sdd-executor-agent (implements export/conversion scripts and CI hooks once tooling is selected).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Recommending Three.js for a Vision Pro project or Unity for a WebXR-only project.</description>
      <reason>WebXR vs. native engine confusion is the #1 agentic mistake in spatial work. Three.js does not run on visionOS; Unity WebGL output is not the Unity XR runtime.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Using "Reality Composer" and "Reality Composer Pro" interchangeably.</description>
      <reason>They are different applications with different capabilities. Reality Composer is the legacy iPad/iPhone tool; Reality Composer Pro is the macOS-only visionOS authoring environment.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Generating performance estimates from agent output without device benchmarking.</description>
      <reason>LLM performance estimates for spatial assets are folklore. Triangle count, draw calls, and frame time must be measured on target hardware — emulators understate cost.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
