<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="selling-ideas">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>communicator</domain>
    <summary>SPIN Selling, Challenger Sale, elevator pitch templates, and LAER objection handling for persuasively pitching ideas to diverse audiences.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>pitch</tag>
      <tag>spin-selling</tag>
      <tag>challenger-sale</tag>
      <tag>persuasion</tag>
      <tag>objection-handling</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Selling Ideas</title>
    <summary>A persuasion framework for pitching technical or business ideas to different audiences. Combines SPIN Selling (uncover and amplify pain before presenting a solution), the Challenger Sale (teach a new insight, tailor, take control), the elevator pitch template, and the LAER objection-handling model. The core rule: never pitch until the audience feels the problem.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Great ideas fail because of bad pitches. Technical people default to feature explanations instead of problem-then-benefit narratives. SPIN research (Rackham, 35,000 sales calls) shows that implication questions — not product descriptions — are what move decision-makers. Matching pitch structure to audience role (executive vs technical vs finance) doubles comprehension and acceptance rates.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Proposing a technical change, architecture decision, or new tooling to stakeholders</item>
        <item>Pitching a product idea to investors, clients, or executives</item>
        <item>Preparing for a presentation where you need a decision, not just understanding</item>
        <item>Writing a one-pager or executive summary that must persuade</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When the audience has already decided — objection handling mode, not pitching mode</item>
        <item>Exploratory conversations where no decision is needed yet — use active-listening instead</item>
        <item>When you lack numbers or evidence — pitching without proof reads as speculation</item>
        <item>Pure technical briefings where the audience wants depth, not persuasion structure</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="spin-selling">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Never pitch the solution until Implication questions have made the problem feel urgent to the audience.</statement>
        <rationale>Rackham's research on 35,000 sales calls showed that Implication questions — not product descriptions — are the primary driver of decision-maker movement. Features presented before pain is amplified produce "that's interesting" responses, not decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Situation (S): understand current context — "How do you currently handle X?"</item>
        <item>Problem (P): uncover pain — "What challenges do you face with X?"</item>
        <item>Implication (I): amplify consequences — "What happens if this isn't solved?"</item>
        <item>Need-Payoff (N): lead to solution — "How would it help if you could...?"</item>
      </list>
      <example type="good" title="Selling a CI/CD pipeline to an engineering manager">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
S: "How do you currently deploy to production?"
   "Manual process, takes about 2 hours"

P: "What challenges does that create?"
   "Engineers hate it, we deploy less often"

I: "What happens when you deploy less often?"
   "Bigger releases, more bugs, more rollbacks"
   "How much does a rollback cost?"
   "Usually half a day of engineering time"

N: "If deployments took 10 minutes and were automatic,
    how would that change things?"
   "We could deploy daily, catch issues early..."
   → Now present the CI/CD solution
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="challenger-sale">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use the Teach-Tailor-Take-Control sequence when the audience does not yet know they have a problem: share a surprising insight, connect it to their situation, then guide the decision.</statement>
        <rationale>Challengers win by reframing the buyer's understanding of their own problem. Mere problem-solvers compete on features; Challengers compete on perspective.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Teach: the reframe insight">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Most teams think more testing slows them down.
But data shows teams with >80% coverage deploy 3x faster.
Here's why: they catch bugs before production,
not during 2am incidents."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Tailor: connect to their context">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Connect the insight to:
- Their industry and company size
- Their specific challenges mentioned in Situation questions
- Their competitor pressures
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Take Control: guide the recommendation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Based on what you've shared, I'd recommend option A.
Here's why..."

Don't be afraid to disagree if you have better data —
that's what makes it a recommendation, not a proposal.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="elevator-pitch-template">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use the 7-line elevator pitch template to ensure every pitch covers: target customer, problem, category, key benefit, competitor contrast, and differentiator.</statement>
        <rationale>Omitting any element produces a pitch that either confuses the audience about who this is for (no target), fails to establish urgency (no problem), or cannot be remembered (no differentiator).</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="audience-specific-structures">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Match pitch structure to the audience role: executives need business impact first, technical audiences need architecture before benefits, finance needs cost savings with payback period.</statement>
        <rationale>Each role has a primary decision filter. Leading with the wrong frame (e.g., technical architecture to an executive) triggers disengagement before the key point lands.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Executives: Problem (30s) → Solution (30s) → Impact (30s) → Ask (30s)</item>
        <item>Technical: Problem (1m) → Architecture (2m) → Demo (5m) → Integration (2m) → Questions</item>
        <item>Finance: Cost savings → TCO analysis → Payback period → Risk</item>
        <item>Users: Time savings → Ease of use → Daily workflow change</item>
        <item>Security: Compliance → Data protection → Audit trail</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="laer-objection-handling">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use LAER (Listen, Acknowledge, Explore, Respond) for every objection — never skip Explore before Responding.</statement>
        <rationale>Responding before exploring treats the stated objection as the real one. The real objection is usually different: "too expensive" often means "I don't see the ROI" not "we have no budget".</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Objection: "Too expensive"
L: Let them finish.
A: "That's a valid concern."
E: "Compared to what? What's the cost of not solving this?"
R: "Let's calculate the TCO including the current manual cost..."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Objection: "We tried before"
E: "What was different then? What would need to change for it to work now?"
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="presentation-structure">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Structure presentations as: Hook → Problem → Solution → Proof → Call to Action. End with a specific ask, never an open-ended close.</statement>
        <rationale>Presentations without a clear ask produce "let me think about it" deferrals. The ask defines what decision the audience is making.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Leading with the solution before establishing the problem.</description>
        <reason>Audiences who do not yet feel the pain perceive solutions as unnecessary complexity. Pain must be established first.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Asking "Does that make sense?" after presenting.</description>
        <reason>Invites a yes/no response that shuts down dialogue. Use "What questions do you have?" instead.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using weak modal verbs: "I think we should...", "Maybe we could..."</description>
        <reason>Modality signals uncertainty, which undermines the recommendation. Use "I recommend..." and "Here's the plan..."</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-integration-guidelines">
      <p>An agent receives an idea brief (problem, solution, audience type, known objections, available metrics). It produces: (1) a SPIN question sequence to run before the pitch, (2) an audience-tailored pitch doc (problem → solution → impact → ask), (3) an objection-response map for up to 5 known objections using LAER, (4) an elevator pitch in three lengths. Each output is a separate section, clearly labeled, so the human can selectively use them.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always lead with the Problem, not the Solution — agents default to solution-first because specs are usually solution-first; explicitly reverse the order in the prompt.</statement>
        <rationale>SPIN question sequences need authentic human delivery; agent-written SPIN scripts read as interrogative rather than curious.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The Challenger Sale "Teach" step requires genuinely novel industry insight — agents will produce plausible-sounding but often generic "insights" that sophisticated buyers will recognize as boilerplate.</statement>
        <rationale>Objection handling scripts generated without real objection data tend to address imagined concerns, not actual ones.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Quantification ("40% lower TCO") requires real data; agents will hallucinate specifics if not given source numbers.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents will invent specific percentages when not given real data — always mark claims as [DATA NEEDED] in the prompt and review before use.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Build an objection library over time: after each pitch, log real objections raised and effective responses. Feed this library into future agent prompts.</statement>
        <rationale>For executive pitches: one metric per slide, no more. An agent will fill space with data; trim ruthlessly.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The Elevator Pitch 10-second version ("We help [WHO] [DO WHAT] [BETTER/FASTER/CHEAPER]") is the hardest to write well and the most important; dedicate a separate prompt pass to it.</statement>
        <rationale>SPIN sequences work best when the Implication questions quantify cost ("How much engineering time does a rollback cost?") — ensure the brief includes actual cost data, even rough estimates.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>"Ask" statements generated by agents are often weak ("Let's schedule a follow-up") — specify what type of commitment you want (time / budget / referral) in the prompt.</statement>
        <rationale>Power-phrase substitutions (Weak → Strong) can sound aggressive if applied wholesale; human review needed to calibrate tone per audience.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>SPIN question sequences generated without audience context will produce Situation questions that are too broad and Implication questions too generic to create urgency.</statement>
        <rationale>Live negotiation cannot be handled by agents that cannot adapt to in-room dynamics in real time; agents can prepare but not participate live.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/elevator-pitch.txt" purpose="Fill-in-the-blank elevator pitch template (7-line and 10-second versions)"/>
      <template path="templates/one-pager.txt" purpose="One-pager structure: Problem / Solution / Benefits / Cost / Risk / Ask"/>
      <template path="templates/executive-pitch.txt" purpose="4-block executive pitch: Problem / Solution / Impact / Ask (30 sec each)"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://hbr.org/topic/subject/persuasion"/>
      <link href="https://marp.app"/>
      <ref slug="negotiation"/>
      <ref slug="stakeholder-communication"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
