<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Build-in-Public Engine Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that keep a build-in-public motion compounding rather than burning out at week 6.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-weekly-input-ritual" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every week, the founder fills the weekly-input-log with four fields: what I shipped, what broke, what I learned, one number. Posts MUST be derived from this log. Posting without writing the log first is forbidden — it produces opinion-spam, not build-in-public content.</statement>
      <rationale source="James Clear, Atomic Habits + Pieter Levels public archive">Build-in-public dies when posts become hot takes. Tethering every post to actual product work keeps the content concrete, ICP-anchored, and inexhaustible (the work is the input).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-format-menu" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use exactly five standard formats: (1) build-log post, (2) learning post, (3) screenshot/demo, (4) number-of-the-week, (5) ask post. Free-form ranting, news commentary, or general "thought leader" takes are NOT part of the engine. The weekly cadence is roughly 3 short (formats 1-4) + 1 longer thread (format 1 or 2 expanded).</statement>
      <rationale source="Empirical analysis of high-growth indie accounts 2022-2025">Constrained format menus outperform open posting because (a) the founder spends less time deciding what to post, (b) the audience learns to recognize the patterns, (c) the engine survives low-creativity weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-hook-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every post starts with a hook line: a number, a contradiction, a question, or a screenshot. Hooks that begin "I think...", "Here's my take...", or "Random thought:" are rejected. The hook is testable: if the first line were the only thing the reader saw, would they stop scrolling?</statement>
      <rationale source="X / Twitter engagement data + Wes Kao writing courses">First-line dwell time is the dominant signal in algorithmic feeds. Generic openers train the algorithm and the audience to skip. Hook discipline is the single highest-leverage habit in the engine.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-repurposing-chain" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Long-form threads (format 1 or 2 expanded) MUST be repurposed within 7 days to: LinkedIn post, blog/Substack article, newsletter snippet. The repurpose is not a copy-paste — it's a re-edit for the platform's reading mode and a CTA that points back to the email list. Threads that never leave X waste 70% of their reach potential.</statement>
      <rationale source="Justin Welsh content operating system (5M+ revenue from one repurposing chain)">Each repurpose hits a non-overlapping audience and converts a fraction to email — the only owned channel. X account loss / algorithm shifts destroy non-repurposed engines.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-metric-loop" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track ONLY: weekly net-new followers (or list subscribers), weekly inbound DMs/replies of substance (signal not vanity), and monthly newsletter signups. Reject likes, impressions, and view counts as primary metrics — they are vanity in the build-in-public context. Monthly review uses these to decide what to keep, drop, and amplify.</statement>
      <rationale source="Lean Analytics (Croll, Yoskovitz)">Vanity metrics rise even when the engine is failing. Compound, owned-channel metrics (list, substantive DMs) correlate with actual business outcomes. Founders who measure likes optimize for a metric that doesn't pay them.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Build-log post with hook">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
shipped today: refunds now process in 12s instead of 4min.

three weeks of work. fixed by moving one query out of a Python loop.

screenshot of before/after timing in the thread.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Number-led hook, concrete what-shipped, contradiction (3 weeks for "one query"), screenshot promised. Format 1 + 3 combined.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Generic LLM-generated post">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Building in public is hard but rewarding. Here are 5 lessons every founder should know about consistency...
1/ Show up every day
2/ Be authentic
3/ ...
      ]]></code>
      <note>No work tethered, no specifics, no hook discipline. Fails r1, r3. This is the dominant LLM failure mode.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
