<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-nsm-framework" title="North Star Metric Framework">
  <summary>Definition, five characteristics of a valid NSM, four-step selection process, value equation, and disqualified metric types.</summary>

  <section title="Definition and Characteristics">
    <rule>
      <statement>The North Star Metric must measure customer value delivered, not company value extracted; it must be a leading indicator of revenue, not revenue itself.</statement>
      <rationale>Revenue as NSM causes teams to optimize for short-term extraction — discounts, forced upgrades, retention walls — at the expense of actual value delivery. When the NSM rises because customers are getting more value, revenue follows; when revenue is chased directly, product quality declines.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Five characteristics of a valid NSM: measures customer value (not company value), is a leading indicator of revenue, reflects the product vision, is actionable (specific teams can move it), is understandable by everyone in one sentence.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Disqualified Metrics">
    <p>Revenue: lags value delivery and causes extraction optimization. Sign-ups: no value exchange has occurred yet. Page views: activity without proven value. DAU/MAU alone: presence without value delivery. These are inputs or lagging outcomes, not NSM candidates.</p>
    <p>Real NSM examples by product: Airbnb — nights booked; Spotify — time spent listening; Slack — daily active users × messages sent; Uber — rides completed; Netflix — hours watched; Shopify — gross merchandise volume.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Four-Step Selection Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the four-step NSM selection: identify core value delivered, find the action that proves customers received that value, find the metric measuring that action, validate that improving the metric improves long-term revenue.</statement>
      <rationale>Without the validation step (step 4), teams adopt a plausible-sounding NSM that does not actually predict business outcomes. The validation test requires empirical correlation analysis between the candidate metric and retention or revenue growth.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Value Equation">
    <p>NSM = (action that delivers value) × frequency × number of users. This formula ensures the NSM captures breadth (users), depth (frequency), and quality (value action).</p>
  </section>
</text>
