<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-implementation-checklist" title="NSM Implementation and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Three-phase implementation checklist (define, instrument, operationalize) and common NSM mistakes.</summary>

  <section title="Phase 1: Define (Week 1)">
    <list>
      <item>List the product's core value in one sentence.</item>
      <item>Brainstorm 5-10 candidate metrics that could represent that value.</item>
      <item>Test each candidate: Does it measure customer value? Is it a leading indicator? Is it actionable? Can it be explained in one sentence?</item>
      <item>Validate empirically: run correlation analysis between each candidate and retention/revenue growth.</item>
      <item>Choose one. Get leadership buy-in before proceeding.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 2: Instrument (Week 2)">
    <list>
      <item>Write the exact calculation formula in a shared document — leave no ambiguity about what counts.</item>
      <item>Set up tracking so the metric updates at minimum weekly.</item>
      <item>Create a dashboard visible to all teams.</item>
      <item>Identify 3-5 input metrics and assign one team owner per input metric.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Phase 3: Operationalize (Ongoing)">
    <list>
      <item>Include NSM in weekly leadership reviews.</item>
      <item>Set quarterly NSM targets and align OKRs to them.</item>
      <item>Run the validation test quarterly (retention and revenue correlation).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Choosing multiple North Star metrics ("we have two NSMs").</description>
      <reason>Two NSMs produce the same misalignment problem the NSM was designed to solve. Teams trade off between them differently; there is no single shared success definition. Use input metrics for team-level targets, not additional NSMs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>NSM that requires a paragraph to explain.</description>
      <reason>If the entire company cannot understand the metric from a one-sentence description, it will not align behavior. Simplify until it passes the "explain to a new hire in 10 seconds" test.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting the NSM and not reviewing the correlation for more than a quarter.</description>
      <reason>Products evolve; metrics that were predictive at one stage become vanity metrics at the next. A stale NSM silently misaligns the company for months before anyone notices.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
