<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="vui-market-context">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>VUI market context is reference content for grounding voice-product strategy in current adoption data and platform tradeoffs. It covers voice assistant usage statistics, smart speaker penetration, platform comparison (Alexa, Google Assistant, Siri, Bixby, custom LLM-VUI), and developer access surfaces.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>voice-market</tag>
      <tag>platform-comparison</tag>
      <tag>market-research</tag>
      <tag>adoption-stats</tag>
      <tag>strategy</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>VUI Market Context</title>

    <summary>VUI market context is reference content for grounding voice-product strategy in current adoption data and platform tradeoffs. It covers voice assistant usage statistics, smart speaker penetration, platform comparison (Alexa, Google Assistant, Siri, Bixby, custom LLM-VUI), and developer access surfaces. Numbers must be stamped with source year and geographic scope — they go stale within 6-12 months.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Platform selection decisions and stakeholder primers require concrete, sourced adoption figures, not anecdote. The methodology provides a canonical stat schema and a refresh pattern so agents can pull current numbers on demand rather than relying on stale hardcoded values. LLM-native voice agents (ChatGPT Voice, Claude voice) have reshaped the landscape since 2024 and now constitute a fifth platform category bypassing skill stores.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Strategy phase of a voice-product proposal: ground the deck in current adoption stats and platform tradeoffs.</item>
        <item>Platform-selection decision: compare Alexa vs Google vs Siri vs custom LLM-VUI for target geos.</item>
        <item>Investor/stakeholder primers: a one-page market context sourced from canonical references.</item>
        <item>Quarterly brief refresh: pull current numbers on demand instead of relying on stale README values.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Implementation work — this is descriptive market context, not a how-to methodology.</item>
        <item>Platform already locked by contract — re-justification is not useful.</item>
        <item>Real-time competitive intelligence — use a market-research methodology with monitoring loops.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="stat-schema">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every market statistic must carry four fields: value, year, source URL, and geographic scope. Stats without scope or year are not citable.</statement>
        <rationale>Voice adoption varies 3-5x between US and global figures. A "62% use voice assistants" claim without geographic scope is meaningless and misleads strategy decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Distinguish these three denominator categories: smart-speaker households, voice-assistant users, voice-search query share. These are not interchangeable and come from different measurement methodologies.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing denominators produces false comparisons. Smart-speaker household penetration tracks device ownership; voice-assistant users tracks intent sessions; voice-search share tracks query-type on a specific engine. Conflating them inflates or deflates the picture arbitrarily.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="current-baseline">
      <p>Reference figures as of 2025-2026 (verify and refresh via refresh-script.py before use): 8.4B+ voice assistants in use globally; 20%+ of internet queries use voice search; 62% of US adults use a voice assistant; 55% of US households own a smart speaker; 71% of users prefer voice over typing for some tasks. All figures: US/global mixed — verify geo before reusing.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Stamp every market brief with a refreshed_at date. Refuse to publish if the brief is older than 90 days. Voice adoption statistics moved sharply post-2024 with LLM-native voice agents.</statement>
        <rationale>LLM-native voice agents (ChatGPT Voice, Claude voice mode) are reshaping the landscape faster than canonical 2024-25 sources track. Stats older than 90 days may be wrong on direction, not just magnitude.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <reference path="templates/refresh-script.py">Python script to refresh market stats via web search</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="trusted-sources">
      <list>
        <item>Statista — primary canonical source for voice adoption stats (some behind paywall)</item>
        <item>Voicebot.ai — voice industry tracking, free annual surveys</item>
        <item>Edison Research / Infinite Dial — US adoption baselines, annual PDF</item>
        <item>Nielsen Norman Group — UX-focused voice interaction analysis</item>
        <item>Pew Research — US technology adoption baselines (free)</item>
        <item>Gartner — hype cycle and enterprise predictions (paywalled)</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Restrict web-search queries to the trusted-source list. Reject SEO content-farm listicles ("10 voice assistant statistics") that cite each other without primary sources.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs default to ranking high-traffic listicles, which are recycled secondary aggregations. Requiring the agent to return primary-source URLs eliminates circular citation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="platform-landscape">
      <p>Five platforms as of 2025-2026: Alexa (Amazon devices, smart home — developer access via Alexa Skills Kit); Google Assistant (Android, Nest, web — Actions on Google; note: Conversational Actions deprecated 2023); Siri (Apple ecosystem — SiriKit, restricted intent set, requires native iOS app); Bixby (Samsung devices — Bixby Developer Studio, small reach outside Korea); Custom LLM-VUI (any platform via API — OpenAI Realtime, Claude voice, ElevenLabs Conversational — bypasses skill stores and certification entirely).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Weight platform reach by target geo, not global share. Alexa dominates US smart speakers; Google Assistant dominates Android phones globally; Siri dominates iOS. These rankings invert across geos.</statement>
        <rationale>A platform that reaches 40% of US smart-speaker households reaches a very different population than one reaching 40% of Android phones in APAC. Geo-specific reach is the decision-relevant variable, not headline global figures.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="llm-native-platform">
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat LLM-native voice agents as a fifth platform category, not a feature. They bypass skill stores and certification, support open-domain dialog, and have different design requirements (no intent/slot NLU, state managed by model or tool use).</statement>
        <rationale>LLM-native voice agents (Pipecat, Vapi, Retell, Claude voice) represent a different architectural paradigm from intent-based platforms. Conflating them with Alexa/Google design patterns produces broken systems: intent/slot design applied to open LLM dialog, or unconstrained LLM dialog applied where deterministic state is required.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="platform-selection-rule">
      <rule>
        <statement>For platform selection: (1) identify target geos and primary user device type; (2) check developer SDK health (commit activity, deprecation notices); (3) assess LLM integration openness; (4) evaluate certification requirements against timeline. Document the tradeoff, not just the winner.</statement>
        <rationale>Platform decisions are long-term bets. A platform with better current reach but a deprecated SDK or a shrinking developer community may be the wrong choice for a two-year product horizon.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/refresh-script.py" purpose="Python script: calls Claude with web_search tool to refresh stat list; stamps refreshed_at date."/>
    </templates>

    <checklist>
      <check>All market statistics carry four fields: value, year, source URL, geographic scope.</check>
      <check>Distinguish between smart-speaker households, voice-assistant users, and voice-search query share.</check>
      <check>Market brief is stamped with refreshed_at date.</check>
      <check>Brief is less than 90 days old.</check>
      <check>Platform reach is weighted by target geo, not global share.</check>
      <check>LLM-native voice agents are treated as a distinct platform category.</check>
    </checklist>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.voicebot.ai/voice-assistant-statistics/"/>
      <link href="https://www.edisonresearch.com/the-infinite-dial-2024/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/voice-interaction/"/>
      <link href="https://www.statista.com/topics/4642/voice-assistants/"/>
      <link href="https://www.pewresearch.org/internet/fact-sheet/mobile/"/>
      <link href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/guides/realtime"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
