<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Predictive Analytics for PM Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Predictive Analytics for PM. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="min-30-projects" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Training corpus MUST have ≥30 completed projects with structured outcome labels. Smaller corpora overfit.</statement>
      <rationale source="Hastie-Tibshirani-Friedman, Elements of Statistical Learning">ML models trained on &lt;30 samples produce poorly-calibrated forecasts; the minimum is empirically calibrated.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="probability-intervals-not-points" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Forecasts MUST emit probability intervals (80% PI + 95% PI), not point estimates. Point estimates forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tetlock, Superforecasting (2015)">Point estimates miscommunicate certainty; probability intervals expose model uncertainty honestly.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="calibration-checked-quarterly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Calibration (predicted PI coverage vs actual coverage) MUST be checked quarterly on held-out data. Stale calibration forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brier score / reliability diagram practice">Calibration drifts with portfolio composition; quarterly check catches degradation before it harms decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="feature-set-versioned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Feature spec MUST be versioned; rebuild on feature change. Mixing features across versions in one model run is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ML reproducibility best practices">Mixed-version features cause silent train/serve skew; version pinning prevents the bug.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="explainability-per-forecast" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each forecast MUST include top-3 contributing features with shap/lime-style attribution. Black-box outputs forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Explainable AI standards (DARPA XAI)">Black-box forecasts cannot inform action; attributed top features give PMO levers for corrective work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Predictive Analytics for PM fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Predictive Analytics for PM outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
