<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Predictive Analytics in PM — Principles and Applications">
  <summary>ML application areas for PM, data quality requirements, and the human-in-the-loop mandate that governs all predictive outputs.</summary>

  <section title="ML Application Areas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply ML only where a PMO decision changes when the model output flips — define the trigger before training.</statement>
      <rationale>A model that produces no decision change has zero value regardless of accuracy. Defining trigger first forces PMO alignment and constrains scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use reference-class forecasting (Flyvbjerg) as the required baseline; beat it before claiming ML adds value.</statement>
      <rationale>Simple comparable-project averages often outperform ML on small portfolios. The baseline prevents theater deployments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <section title="Application Table">
      <p>Target use cases by ML type and PM domain:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Schedule forecasting: analyze past schedules, predict slip in days (regression); trigger: slip &gt; 14d → escalate to steering.</item>
        <item>Budget prediction: detect cost overrun early from EVM + vendor invoice patterns; 15% reduction in overruns documented in PMI AI reports.</item>
        <item>Resource optimization: multi-variable allocation across concurrent projects; useful only when portfolio &gt; 20 projects.</item>
        <item>Risk detection: pattern recognition in issue velocity, comment cadence, owner-change count; feeds risk register.</item>
        <item>Material price forecasting: Bayesian / interval models for volatile commodities (steel, cloud spend, semiconductors).</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Data Quality Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require clean, structured historical data with consistent status labels, dated transitions, and numeric actuals before training any model.</statement>
      <rationale>Garbage-in/garbage-out dominates PM datasets. Most trackers have inconsistent labels, undated status changes, and missing actuals — no model survives that.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Predict intervals, not points: express schedule slip as "8 days ± 14 (P80)" rather than "8 days".</statement>
      <rationale>Interval forecasts guide better decisions and communicate uncertainty honestly; point predictions create false precision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use GroupKFold cross-validation grouped by project or program — never random splits.</statement>
      <rationale>Random splits leak future project data into past, producing optimistically biased evaluation metrics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Training on closed-project-only datasets.</description>
      <reason>Survivorship bias: killed projects are excluded, making the training set systematically optimistic about completion outcomes.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Shipping a model without a drift monitor.</description>
      <reason>Organisational change, new domains, and new tooling break models trained on prior projects within 6-18 months. Silent failure ensues.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-the-Loop Mandate">
    <rule>
      <statement>The model produces probability + explanation; a human retains all decision authority — no auto-action on budget or schedule.</statement>
      <rationale>Decision-rights confusion is the top governance failure: agents schedule "auto re-baseline on slip prediction" when PM decisions belong to humans.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Ship SHAP values with every prediction; a black-box risk-register entry will be ignored.</statement>
      <rationale>Explainability is non-optional in PM governance contexts. Stakeholder trust collapses on unexplained model outputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Mandatory human checkpoints: training-data contract approval, model promotion to prod, threshold changes, deprecation, any auto-action policy.</item>
      <item>LLMs orchestrate — they draft data contracts, explain SHAP outputs, and propose features. They do not do numeric prediction.</item>
      <item>Confabulated metrics: agents invent MAE/R²/AUC without running code; force metrics to come from sklearn output captured by a tool call.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../templates/slip-baseline.py"/>
    <link path="../templates/data-contract.yaml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
