<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-workflow" title="Predictive Analytics in PM — Agentic Workflow and Subagents">
  <summary>How to structure the ML analytics pipeline as an agentic system, including subagent roles, prompt patterns, and failure modes specific to LLM-driven ML orchestration.</summary>

  <section title="Pipeline Architecture">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the analytics layer as a separate ML pipeline (analytics/ repo) feeding the PM tool through alerts and dashboards — never as a Slackbot.</statement>
      <rationale>Slackbot coupling creates brittle real-time dependencies; a pipeline with explicit data contracts and scheduled runs is testable and auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>A subagent owns the data contract (issue → feature row), trains and refreshes models, monitors drift, and writes predictions to a predictions/ datastore ingested by the PM tool via webhook.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Recommended Subagents">
    <list>
      <item>data-contract-agent (sonnet): inspects PM tool exports, defines stable feature columns, flags inconsistent statuses or missing fields.</item>
      <item>feature-engineering-agent (sonnet): proposes engineered features (planned vs. actual ratios, queue ages, owner-change counts, comment cadence) with rationale.</item>
      <item>model-training-agent (sonnet): wraps scikit-learn / XGBoost / LightGBM / Prophet pipelines; outputs model + metrics + SHAP explanations.</item>
      <item>drift-monitor-agent (haiku): nightly — compares incoming feature distributions vs. training set; raises alerts when KS/PSI exceeds threshold.</item>
      <item>prediction-explainer-agent (opus): turns SHAP outputs into stakeholder-readable risk-register entries.</item>
      <item>password-scrubber-agent: scrubs PM exports before any third-party model call; Jira/Linear data leaks vendor names, prices, customer info.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/slip-baseline.py">Baseline GBR regressor — beat this before claiming ML adds value</reference>
    <reference path="templates/data-contract.yaml">Feature contract schema emitted by the data-contract agent</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Prompt Patterns">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Data-contract agent prompt — forces strict YAML output, explicit leakage exclusions:</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are the data-contract agent. Inputs:
1. Sample of 5,000 issue rows from the source PM tool (CSV).
2. Project metadata (type, sponsor, budget, dates).

Emit STRICT YAML:
features:
  - name: <snake_case>
    type: numeric|categorical|boolean|datetime
    source_field: <jira_field_id>
    nullable: true|false
    notes: "..."
target:
  name: schedule_slip_days|budget_overrun_pct|risk_materialized
  type: regression|classification
  rationale: "..."
exclusions: [ ... fields with PII/credentials ... ]
data_quality_rules:
  - "status not in {Open, In Progress, Done} → flag"
  - "actual_start > actual_end → drop row"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Explanation prompt for SHAP → risk-register entry:</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Given SHAP values for prediction id=X (top 5 features by |contribution|),
produce a 3-sentence English explanation suitable for a risk-register entry.
Cite feature name, direction, and magnitude.
Do not editorialize beyond data.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM "predicts" budget overruns from prose narrative without running a model.</description>
      <reason>LLMs are not numeric forecasters. They confabulate plausible-sounding numbers. Train a model; LLMs draft, explain, and orchestrate.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Random train/test split used for project data.</description>
      <reason>Random splits leak future project data into past training. Group splits by project_id or program are mandatory.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent declares "deployed" after model.fit() without wiring a drift monitor.</description>
      <reason>Shipping a model without monitoring is silent failure. Force a monitoring task into the SDD chain before calling any deployment complete.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Sending raw PM CSV rows to a third-party LLM API.</description>
      <reason>PM data contains salary, vendor pricing, customer names. Tokenize or run on-prem; never send raw rows externally.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
