<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-tools-and-references" title="Predictive Analytics in PM — Tools, Services, and References">
  <summary>CLI tools, SaaS/OSS services, best practices checklist, and key references for ML-driven PM analytics.</summary>

  <section title="CLI Tools">
    <list>
      <item>pandas / polars — feature engineering, ETL of PM data (pip install pandas polars)</item>
      <item>scikit-learn / xgboost / lightgbm — tabular ML for slip/overrun/risk (pip install scikit-learn xgboost lightgbm)</item>
      <item>prophet / sktime / darts — time-series for budget runs and material prices (pip install prophet sktime)</item>
      <item>shap / lime — model explanation; required for governance (pip install shap lime)</item>
      <item>evidently / nannyml / whylogs — drift and data-quality monitoring (pip install evidently nannyml)</item>
      <item>mlflow / wandb / dvc — experiment tracking and model registry (pip install mlflow dvc)</item>
      <item>dbt — SQL transformations of PM warehouse data into feature tables (https://docs.getdbt.com)</item>
      <item>duckdb — local OLAP on exported CSVs without a warehouse (pip install duckdb)</item>
      <item>great-expectations — data-quality assertions in CI (https://greatexpectations.io)</item>
      <item>prefect / dagster / airflow — orchestrate ETL → train → score → publish pipeline</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Services">
    <list>
      <item>Atlassian Intelligence / ClickUp AI / Monday AI — mostly LLM-summarization; minimal predictive ML; verify before integrating.</item>
      <item>Power BI + Project for the Web — cheapest enterprise-grade visualization on Microsoft estate; REST-accessible.</item>
      <item>Snowflake / BigQuery / Databricks — warehouse for unified PM data; required at scale.</item>
      <item>Oracle Primavera + Risk Analysis — heavy predictive scheduling for capital projects (Monte Carlo simulation).</item>
      <item>nPlan / ALICE Technologies — ML-driven schedule risk and AI scheduling for construction (REST API).</item>
      <item>AlphaSense / Bloomberg / S&amp;P Capital IQ — material price and macro forecasting feeds.</item>
      <item>Anthropic / OpenAI / Vertex AI / Azure ML — LLM hosts for orchestration; route via privacy DPA + zero-retention only.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Calibrate probabilities (Platt / isotonic) before publishing risk scores — uncalibrated outputs produce false alarms.</statement>
      <rationale>Raw sigmoid outputs from gradient boosters are not calibrated probabilities; stakeholders treating them as such will make misinformed decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Version the data, not just the model — "model says X" is meaningless without "trained on snapshot Y".</statement>
      <rationale>Without data versioning, debugging model degradation is impossible; DVC or warehouse snapshots satisfy this requirement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Document model cards (intended use, training data, metrics, limitations) per Mitchell et al. — required by AI Act for high-risk systems.</statement>
      <rationale>Model cards make assumptions and scope explicit, preventing misapplication and satisfying emerging regulatory requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="References">
    <list>
      <item>Hyndman &amp; Athanasopoulos "Forecasting: Principles and Practice" — https://otexts.com/fpp3/</item>
      <item>Flyvbjerg "Reference Class Forecasting" — https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reference_class_forecasting</item>
      <item>Mitchell et al. "Model Cards for Model Reporting" — https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.03993</item>
      <item>Lundberg &amp; Lee "A Unified Approach to Interpreting Model Predictions" (SHAP) — https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.07874</item>
      <item>Sculley et al. "Hidden Technical Debt in Machine Learning Systems" — https://research.google/pubs/pub43146/</item>
      <item>PMI "AI in Project Management" — https://www.pmi.org/learning/thought-leadership/ai-impact</item>
      <item>Sibling methodologies: earned-value-management/, risk-management/, cost-estimation/, schedule-development/, pm-tool-selection/</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
