<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-performance" title="Instagram Ads Performance and Reporting">
  <summary>Bid strategies, budget scaling rules, and placement-level reporting API for Instagram campaigns.</summary>

  <section title="Bid Strategies">
    <list>
      <item>Lowest Cost (LOWEST_COST_WITHOUT_CAP) — maximize conversions; CPA unstable at scale</item>
      <item>Cost Cap — set target CPA ceiling; delivery slows when cost exceeds cap</item>
      <item>Bid Cap — controls auction competition; use when CPM inflation is detected</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with Lowest Cost; switch to Cost Cap only after 50+ conversions per ad set to give the algorithm enough learning signal.</statement>
      <rationale>Cost Cap with insufficient conversion data causes severe under-delivery — the algorithm cannot find users at the target cost if it has no baseline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Budget Scaling">
    <rule>
      <statement>Increase budget by 20-30% maximum every 3-4 days; do not double a budget in a single step.</statement>
      <rationale>Large budget jumps force the campaign back into the learning phase, resetting optimization and causing temporary CPA spikes of 40-80%.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Placement-Level Reporting">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
curl -X GET "https://graph.facebook.com/v20.0/{adset-id}/insights?\
fields=spend,impressions,reach,clicks,cpc,cpm,ctr,\
actions,cost_per_action_type,\
video_p25_watched_actions,video_p75_watched_actions,\
video_p100_watched_actions&\
date_preset=last_7d&\
breakdowns=publisher_platform,platform_position&\
access_token={token}"
      ]]></code>
      <note>breakdowns=platform_position returns rows for instagram_stream, instagram_story, instagram_explore, instagram_reels separately.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always break down reporting by platform_position when running multi-placement ad sets; never rely on campaign-level aggregates to make placement budget decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Aggregate metrics hide placement-level CPA variance of 3-5x; scaling on aggregates can double spend on the worst-performing placement.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Frequency Control">
    <rule>
      <statement>Monitor frequency and pause or rotate creative when it exceeds 3.0 for any single placement.</statement>
      <rationale>Above frequency 3.0, engagement rates decline and CPAs rise due to audience fatigue — users have seen the ad enough to develop ad blindness.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
