<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="portfolio-strategy">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Three Horizons portfolio model: allocate 70% H1 (core), 20% H2 (adjacent), 10% H3 (transformational), with macro adjustments and quarterly re-classification on revenue evidence.</summary>
    <category>portfolio</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>portfolio-strategy</tag>
      <tag>three-horizons</tag>
      <tag>allocation</tag>
      <tag>product-strategy</tag>
      <tag>roadmap</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="competitive-positioning"/>
      <ref slug="continuous-discovery-habits"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Portfolio Strategy (70/20/10)</title>

    <summary>The Three Horizons portfolio model allocates engineering capacity across H1 (Core, 70%), H2 (Adjacent, 20%), and H3 (Transformational, 10%), with ratios adjustable to macro conditions (Growth 60/25/15, Stable 70/20/10, Recession 80/15/5). Every initiative is tagged H1/H2/H3 with a revenue-evidence string. Allocation tracks engineering cost (loaded $ or person-weeks), not ticket count. H3 bets ship with a pre-committed kill threshold. Re-classify quarterly.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Economic uncertainty requires balanced product bets. A portfolio without explicit horizon allocation drifts toward H1 under pressure (all maintenance) or H3 theater (all moonshots, zero revenue defense). The 70/20/10 model provides a numeric handle for allocation debates with finance or board. The macro-condition lever (Growth/Stable/Recession) makes ratio changes automatic and uncontroversial when conditions shift.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Annual/quarterly roadmap planning where multiple bets compete for the same engineering capacity</item>
        <item>Multi-product company or solopreneur with 3+ shipped products needing a defensible split</item>
        <item>Macro shock (recession signal, funding cut, churn spike) forcing re-allocation from H3/H2 to H1</item>
        <item>Investor/leadership update showing the portfolio is neither all moonshots nor all maintenance</item>
        <item>Backlog sizing: tag every initiative H1/H2/H3 and verify sum matches target ratios</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-product seed-stage startup with one bet — no portfolio yet; allocate 100% to PMF</item>
        <item>Pure services / agency revenue where there is no product backlog to allocate against</item>
        <item>Engineering-only resource planning (sprints, on-call, infra) — use capacity planning instead</item>
        <item>Sub-feature prioritization inside one product — RICE / WSJF / Kano are sharper at that grain</item>
        <item>Crisis quarters where survival demands 100% on one fire</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="horizon-definitions">
      <p>H1 (Core, 70%): incremental improvements to existing products, 0-12 months, known market, low risk. Metrics: revenue, retention, efficiency. H2 (Adjacent, 20%): extensions to new markets or segments, 12-24 months, partial validation, medium risk. Metrics: market validation, early revenue. H3 (Transformational, 10%): new business models or technologies, 24-36 months, option value, high risk. Metrics: learning velocity, option value.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="classification-rubric">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Classify H1 only if an item serves an existing paying segment, ships within 12 months, and operates in a known market. Default to H3 with confidence &lt;= 0.4 if revenue_evidence is empty.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs over-classify items as H2/H3 because descriptions sound novel. The revenue-evidence requirement anchors classification in commercial reality rather than novelty of language.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Track allocation by engineering cost (loaded dollars or person-weeks), not by ticket count. A 1-line H1 fix and a 3-engineer-month H3 spike both count as "1 ticket" — that destroys the allocation math.</statement>
        <rationale>Ticket-count allocation produces portfolios that look balanced but are heavily skewed in actual resource spend. Cost tracking is the only way to measure the real split.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Re-classify quarterly, not annually. SaaS bets graduate or die fast; an H3 from Q1 is often H2 by Q3 or already cancelled.</statement>
        <rationale>Annual classification locks in outdated horizons. A quarterly cadence catches graduation events (H3 → H2 after design-partner validation) and zombie prevention (H3 that never graduated but still consumes budget).</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="macro-condition-adjustments">
      <p>Growth economy: 60/25/15 (more bets). Stable economy: 70/20/10 (standard). Recession: 80/15/5 (protect core). Write the macro condition into the OKR doc. When the condition changes, the ratio change is automatic and uncontroversial.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pre-commit a kill threshold for every H3 bet at funding time (e.g. "kill if no design partner by month 4"). Without it, H3 zombies eat next year's H2 budget.</statement>
        <rationale>H3 bets without kill criteria persist indefinitely because there is no natural endpoint. The kill threshold provides a forcing function that removes zombies without political overhead.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-anti-patterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Horizon labels becoming political: every team lobbies to be H3 for more freedom and fewer KPIs.</description>
        <reason>Use the classification rubric with a neutral arbiter (portfolio-classifier agent) and require revenue_evidence for any H1 label. When classification is evidence-based, lobbying loses its lever.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>H3 budget starved first when H1 slips: teams then claim they "do innovation" while the budget shows zero.</description>
        <reason>Lock H3 budget at the start of the quarter before sprint planning. Once H1 work claims all capacity, H3 is invisible in retrospect. Pre-commitment is the protection.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating 70/20/10 as empirically optimal rather than a starting heuristic.</description>
        <reason>The numbers originated as a Google PR artifact from 2005. Treat them as a reasonable starting point, calibrate to your market and stage, and document why you deviated if you do.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Three Horizons assumes time-sequenced horizons (H3 becomes H2 becomes H1). Many SaaS bets never graduate; they die or stay niche.</description>
        <reason>Pure time framing misleads. Instruct the agent that horizons are about risk + evidence today, not a fixed escalator.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Cross-portfolio dependencies (shared platform, shared auth, shared data pipeline) are invisible in horizon math.</description>
        <reason>Surface cross-portfolio dependencies in a separate matrix; allocation math alone hides them.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="two-pass-agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive this with two passes. First, an analysis pass: a sonnet-class agent ingests the current backlog (CSV / markdown / Linear export), classifies each initiative H1/H2/H3 against an explicit rubric, and emits an allocation table. Second, a strategy pass: an opus-class agent compares actual vs. target allocation given the macro condition (Growth 60/25/15, Stable 70/20/10, Recession 80/15/5), proposes re-allocations, and flags items where horizon classification is ambiguous for human review. Both passes must produce structured JSON so a downstream review agent (or human) can audit, not prose. Use brainstorm for the rebalance step when stakeholders disagree on which bets to cut.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run two passes: (1) sonnet-class analysis agent classifies each backlog item H1/H2/H3 and emits an allocation table; (2) opus-class strategy agent compares actual vs target given macro condition and proposes re-allocations. Both produce structured JSON for audit.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing classification and strategy in one pass loses the audit trail. When a classification decision is wrong, a two-pass approach makes it visible and correctable before it affects the strategy output.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <example type="good" title="Portfolio Classifier Prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are a portfolio classifier. For each backlog item below, output JSON:
{id, horizon: "H1"|"H2"|"H3", confidence: 0-1, rationale, revenue_evidence}
Rubric:
  H1 = serves an existing paying segment, ship within 12 months, known market.
  H2 = adjacent segment OR new pricing tier, 12-24 months, partial validation.
  H3 = new business model OR new tech foundation, 24-36 months, option value.
If revenue_evidence is empty, default to H3 and set confidence &lt;= 0.4.
Backlog: &lt;paste&gt;
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Portfolio Rebalancer Prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are a portfolio rebalancer. Given current allocation {h1, h2, h3}, target
{th1, th2, th3} (set by macro condition), and a list of classified items,
output the minimal set of cuts/promotions to reach target +/- 3pp.
Output JSON with rationale per change. Do not invent items.
Pick from the existing list only. If you need new H3 bets, say so and stop.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="subagent-recommendations">
      <list>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — once allocation is approved, drive the per-horizon implementation plan (H1 features get full SDD; H3 bets get lightweight spike specs).</item>
        <item>brainstorm — diverge / converge on candidate H3 bets when you only have allocation budget but no concrete ideas.</item>
        <item>improver — quarterly review loop: read last quarter's allocation, compare to delivered outcomes, log mistakes (e.g. "we said 10% H3, shipped 0%"), feed back into next quarter's split.</item>
        <item>A custom portfolio-classifier subagent (worth creating): input = backlog item, output = {horizon, confidence, rationale, revenue_evidence}. Keep it small, cheap, and stateless.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Classifier over-tagging items as H2/H3 because the prose description sounds novel.</description>
        <reason>Force requirement: revenue_evidence field must be present and non-empty for H1 classification. Default all items without evidence to H3 with low confidence. Novelty of language is not a classification criterion.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent computing allocation percentages from ticket counts instead of engineering cost.</description>
        <reason>Validate the input schema before classifying. If eng_cost_usd or person_weeks is missing, refuse to compute allocation percentages and return an error prompting for the field.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Macro condition buried in a long prompt and silently dropped by the rebalancer.</description>
        <reason>Pass macro condition as a structured field in a dedicated XML element, not as a sentence in prose. The model must output the condition it used in the JSON response for auditability.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Rebalancer hallucinating new initiatives to fill H3 budget ("suggest H3 bets").</description>
        <reason>Constrain the rebalancer to picking from the existing list. If new H3 bets are needed, run a separate brainstorm cycle and feed the survivors back in as classified items.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent making the rebalance decision unsupervised when drift exceeds 3pp.</description>
        <reason>The allocation decision is a CPO call, not an agent call. Automate drift detection and alerting; escalate to a human when any horizon drifts beyond the threshold. Never let the agent commit a rebalance to production.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="human-in-the-loop-checkpoints">
      <list>
        <item>Approve the classification of ambiguous items (confidence &lt; 0.5) before the strategy pass</item>
        <item>Sign off on any H3 kill — it removes the bet from the option set</item>
        <item>Approve macro-condition designation (Growth/Stable/Recession) at the start of each quarter</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-integrations">
      <list>
        <item>productboard CLI / API — Pull roadmap items + tags, push horizon classification back as a custom field. https://developer.productboard.com</item>
        <item>linear API (@linear/sdk) — Read issue list with labels (H1/H2/H3), bulk-update labels via mutation. https://developers.linear.app</item>
        <item>jira REST + jira-cli — Same pattern for Jira-shop teams; JQL labels in (H1,H2,H3). https://github.com/ankitpokhrel/jira-cli</item>
        <item>gh (GitHub CLI) — If your roadmap lives in GitHub Projects v2: gh project item-list + GraphQL field updates. https://cli.github.com</item>
        <item>pandas + matplotlib — Local ETL on a CSV export → allocation pie + drift chart per quarter. pip install pandas matplotlib</item>
        <item>csvkit (csvsql, csvstat) — Quick allocation math from CSV without writing code. pip install csvkit</item>
        <item>claude CLI (Claude Code) — Drive the classifier subagent on a backlog file, emit JSON to stdout. https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/claude-code</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-platform-integrations">
      <p>Productboard (SaaS, REST API + webhooks, agent-friendly) — Native "objectives" + "drivers" map cleanly to horizons; custom field for H1/H2/H3. Aha! Roadmaps (SaaS, REST API rate-limited, partial) — Strong portfolio module; agents can read but bulk writes are slow. Linear (SaaS, GraphQL, fast, agent-friendly) — Best-in-class API; label-based horizons work well. Jira Advanced Roadmaps (Plans) (SaaS, REST, agent-friendly) — Heaviest tool; needed if PMO already standardized on it. GitHub Projects v2 (SaaS, GraphQL, agent-friendly) — Cheapest path for solo / small teams; field-based horizons. OpenStrategy / Cascade Strategy (SaaS, limited, UI-first) — Strategic-portfolio focus, exec audience; thin API. ProdPad (SaaS, REST, agent-friendly) — Idea-stage portfolio; pairs with Three Horizons natively. airfocus (SaaS, REST, agent-friendly) — Built-in portfolio scoring; agents can post scores. react-flow + custom OSS dashboard (OSS, self-built) — When SaaS is overkill: render allocation drift from a JSON file.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Anchor each H1/H2/H3 label to a revenue evidence string (URL to MRR chart, signed contract, validated landing-page conversion). Without evidence, default to H3 with low confidence — this stops the "everything is H1" drift.</item>
        <item>Re-classify quarterly, not annually. SaaS bets graduate or die fast; an H3 from Q1 is often H2 by Q3 or already cancelled.</item>
        <item>Track allocation by engineering cost (loaded $ or person-weeks), not by ticket count. A 1-line H1 fix and a 3-engineer-month H3 spike both count as "1 ticket" and that destroys the math.</item>
        <item>Use the macro-condition lever (Growth / Stable / Recession) explicitly. Write the condition into the OKR doc, not just the allocation. When the condition changes, the ratio change is automatic and uncontroversial.</item>
        <item>Pre-commit a kill threshold for every H3 bet at funding time (e.g. "kill if no design partner by month 4"). Without it, H3 zombies eat next year's H2 budget.</item>
        <item>Pair allocation review with a graduation review: any H3 bet that hit its validation gate should explicitly be re-tagged H2 (and budgeted H2-level), or it stays under-resourced.</item>
        <item>Surface cross-portfolio dependencies in a separate matrix; allocation math alone hides them.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="references-and-related">
      <list>
        <item>McKinsey, Baghai, Coley, White — "The Alchemy of Growth" (1999) — original Three Horizons model.</item>
        <item>Eric Schmidt / Google — 70/20/10 allocation rule, popularized 2005.</item>
        <item>Reforge — "Product Portfolio Strategy" essays (2022–2024).</item>
        <item>Marty Cagan, "Inspired" / "Empowered" — chapters on product strategy and bets.</item>
        <item>Roman Pichler, "Strategize" (2nd ed., 2022) — portfolio canvas and horizon mapping.</item>
        <item>Morgan Stanley 2026 macro outlook — context for the recession-bias 80/15/5 split.</item>
        <item>Productboard docs: https://developer.productboard.com</item>
        <item>Linear API: https://developers.linear.app</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/portfolio-allocate.sh" purpose="Bash+Python: compute current vs target horizon allocation from a CSV backlog"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="competitive-positioning"/>
      <ref slug="continuous-discovery-habits"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
