<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="team-development">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Structured approach to building high-performing teams using Tuckman's five-stage model with team charter, skills matrix, and retrospective cycles for continuous improvement.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>team</tag>
      <tag>tuckman</tag>
      <tag>development</tag>
      <tag>charter</tag>
      <tag>retrospectives</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Team Development</title>

    <summary>A structured approach to building high-performing teams using Tuckman's five-stage model (Forming, Storming, Norming, Performing, Adjourning), a team charter with working agreements, a skills matrix for gap planning, and retrospective cycles for continuous improvement. The PM's role shifts by stage: directive at Forming, mediating at Storming, delegating at Performing, celebrating at Adjourning.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Talented individuals do not automatically form effective teams. Unaddressed Storming causes permanent dysfunction. Skills gaps appear mid-project without a matrix to surface them. The methodology makes team health visible and gives the PM concrete actions at each stage rather than generic "improve communication" advice.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Forming a new team: producing charter, working agreements, RACI, and skills matrix in one pass</item>
        <item>Diagnosing a struggling team via Tuckman stage assessment with recommended PM actions</item>
        <item>Building a skills-gap plan (training, pairing, or hire decisions)</item>
        <item>Coaching solo-to-team transitions (first-hire integration)</item>
        <item>Generating and synthesising retrospective patterns across multiple sprints</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>HR/performance-management actions (compensation, PIPs, hiring decisions) — require a human + HR system</item>
        <item>Crisis interventions (harassment, mental health, layoffs) — agents must escalate to humans immediately</item>
        <item>Cross-cultural mediation where confidentiality and nuance dominate — automation backfires</item>
        <item>Single-person projects — no team to develop</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="tuckman-stages">
      <p>Five-stage model with characteristics, PM actions, and transition signals for each stage.</p>

      <section name="forming">
        <p>Team is polite, cautious, and dependent on the PM for direction. Roles unclear, goals abstract, conflict avoided.</p>
        <list>
          <item>PM actions: clarify roles and responsibilities, set expectations, facilitate introductions, produce team charter</item>
          <item>Transition signal: members begin asking each other questions rather than always going to the PM</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="storming">
        <p>Conflict, competition, and frustration surface as individuals push back on roles and process. This is healthy and expected; suppressing it delays Norming.</p>
        <list>
          <item>PM actions: facilitate structured discussion with ground rules, mediate with focus on shared goals, document agreed decisions</item>
          <item>Transition signal: conflict becomes task-focused rather than interpersonal; throughput stabilises</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="norming">
        <p>Trust builds, cooperation replaces competition, norms are established. Team starts self-organising.</p>
        <list>
          <item>PM actions: delegate more, reinforce positive norms, support team decisions, encourage cross-training</item>
          <item>Transition signal: team resolves minor issues independently without escalating to PM</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="performing">
        <p>High productivity, autonomy, distributed leadership. PM shifts to removing obstacles and shielding from external disruption.</p>
        <list>
          <item>PM actions: empower and trust, remove blockers, protect team from scope thrash, focus on outcomes</item>
          <item>Transition signal: velocity or throughput is stable and predictable over multiple sprints</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="adjourning">
        <p>Project ends or team dissolves. Emotional closure, knowledge preservation, and individual transition support.</p>
        <list>
          <item>PM actions: celebrate achievements, conduct final retrospective, document lessons learned, facilitate career transitions</item>
          <item>Transition signal: project closure milestone reached; team members reassigned</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <rule>
        <statement>When staging a team from indirect signals, emit a confidence score (0.0-1.0) and list the evidence; do not state the stage as fact without observable data.</statement>
        <rationale>Tuckman is a model, not a measurement instrument; overconfident staging from sparse signals leads to wrong PM actions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="rules-and-antipatterns">
      <rule>
        <statement>Co-write the team charter with the team in a 60-minute workshop; never let an agent author it solo without team input.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent-authored charters are generic and lack the buy-in that only participation creates.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every retrospective action item must have a single named owner and a sprint-deadline; reject "the team will look into this".</statement>
        <rationale>Actions without owners are not actions; they are intentions that expire at the end of the retro.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Refresh skills matrix quarterly; treat it as planning input, not performance data.</statement>
        <rationale>Skills matrices used for performance review create gaming; used for planning they create learning opportunities.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Retro outputs must not name individuals; preserve psychological safety in all summarised outputs.</statement>
        <rationale>Individual naming in retro summaries chills honest participation and can cause interpersonal harm.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Retro themes must be backed by evidence from at least two distinct sprints before being called a pattern.</statement>
        <rationale>Single-sprint observations are noise; patterns require recurrence to be actionable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Evaluate training and pairing options before proposing a hire to close a skills gap.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents default to "hire" because it is the clearest action; training and pairing are faster, cheaper, and improve retention.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Recommending "more standups" or "better communication" as the fix for most retro themes.</description>
        <reason>This is an LLM default; it rarely addresses the root cause and wastes ceremony time on the wrong intervention.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Setting skills matrix scores to 3 (median) when the agent has no information about a person.</description>
        <reason>Unknown should be "unknown", not a guess; phantom scores drive incorrect gap-planning decisions.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Flagging recurring themes as "new" each sprint because the agent has no session memory.</description>
        <reason>Pass last N synthesised theme files into context; without history the agent cannot detect patterns.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>The agent is a documentation and pattern-extraction layer. Phase 1: a team-charter-builder produces the charter from team list + project context. Phase 2: a retro-synthesiser extracts themes and action items from raw retro notes (max-N sprints) and proposes experiments. Phase 3: a tuckman-coach reads recent signals (retro themes, throughput, conflict reports) and stages the team with PM actions. All outputs require human review; never publish to the team without sign-off.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use recommended subagents: team-charter-builder (define inline) — input: team list, project context; output: charter markdown. retro-synthesiser (define inline) — input: N retro markdown files; output: themes + recurring action items + experiments. tuckman-coach (define inline) — input: signals; output: stage + recommended PM actions. skills-matrix-analyzer (define inline) — input: role expectations + matrix; output: gap plan (training / pair / hire). faion-brainstorm — to generate options for stuck retros (e.g. "we keep talking about scope").</statement>
        <rationale>Specialized subagents enforce safety constraints (no individual naming, confidence scores, minimum evidence) and prevent common LLM failure modes.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>Prompt pattern for retro synthesis — emits themes backed by evidence, not guesses</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are a retro synthesiser. Inputs: <list of retro_*.md>.
Output JSON:
{ "themes": [
    { "theme": "...",
      "evidence_count": N,
      "first_seen_sprint": "...",
      "still_present": bool,
      "proposed_experiment": "imperative, time-boxed",
      "owner_suggestion": "role" } ],
  "tuckman_signal": "Forming|Storming|Norming|Performing|Adjourning",
  "tuckman_evidence": ["..."] }
Rules:
- Do NOT name individuals; preserve psychological safety.
- Themes must be backed by ≥ 2 distinct sprints.
- Experiments must be falsifiable within 2 sprints.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Co-write the charter with the team in a 60-min workshop; do not let an agent author it solo.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent-authored charters are generic and lack buy-in.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Refresh skills matrix quarterly; treat it as planning input, not performance data.</statement>
        <rationale>Skills matrices used for performance create gaming; used for planning they create learning.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Retros: rotate facilitator, time-box, capture an action with owner + sprint deadline.</statement>
        <rationale>Action item without an owner = no action; reject.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Storming is healthy and short-lived; do not "fix" it by suppressing conflict — facilitate it.</statement>
        <rationale>Unaddressed Storming calcifies dysfunction.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Solo → team: document everything assumed-obvious; first hire onboarding fails on tribal knowledge.</statement>
        <rationale>Scaling from solo requires explicit documentation of all norms, processes, and expectations.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Track team health with one or two metrics (eNPS, throughput stability), not a dashboard with twenty.</statement>
        <rationale>More metrics increase noise; one clear signal drives better decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-safety-constraints">
      <p>LLMs name individuals in retro summaries by default — strip names; preserve psychological safety. "More standups / better communication" is a recommended-fix bias; require alternative options. Tuckman staging from sparse signals is overconfident; agents should emit a confidence score and surface evidence. Action items get reformulated into corporate-ese ("enhance synergy"); enforce imperative + measurable form. Recurring themes are flagged as "new" each sprint because the agent has no memory; pass last N synthesised theme files into context. Sensitive content (mental-health, harassment) leaks through summarisation; add a content-filter step that escalates to a human channel and aborts. Agents propose hires when the gap is process / pairing — require considering training + pairing before hire. Skills-matrix scores drift toward 3 (median) when the agent has no info; force "unknown" instead of guessing.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Tools for team collaboration and tracking: gh (pull throughput / cycle-time signals from PRs, https://cli.github.com/); jira-cli (pull velocity / WIP signals, https://github.com/ankitpokhrel/jira-cli); pandoc (render charter / matrix to DOCX / PDF, https://pandoc.org/); mermaid-cli (Tuckman state diagrams + skills heatmaps, https://github.com/mermaid-js/mermaid-cli); wordcloud-cli Python (theme visualisation across retros, https://github.com/amueller/word_cloud); ranger-mover custom (move retro notes between sprint folders).</p>

      <p>Services: Lattice SaaS (1-on-1s, growth, reviews; agent can summarise, https://lattice.com); 15Five SaaS (Pulse + 1-on-1 notes, https://www.15five.com); Culture Amp SaaS (engagement surveys for team-stage signal); Officevibe SaaS (lightweight pulse surveys); Range SaaS (async standups + check-ins); Confluence / Notion SaaS (where charter, matrix, retro outputs live); FunRetro / Parabol / Retrium SaaS (retro boards with export to JSON); Slack + Polly / Geekbot SaaS (async retros and pulse).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-gotchas">
      <p>Tuckman is a model, not a measurement instrument; agents stage teams confidently from sparse signals and can be wrong. Skills matrices are a proxy: real performance depends on context, not numbers; an agent that hires from "matrix gaps" can miss culture fit. Retro patterns repeat (communication, planning, scope) regardless of project; agents that surface only the top theme miss outliers. Confidentiality: 1-on-1 notes contain sensitive content. Agents must not auto-aggregate or store them across sessions. Bias: LLMs trained on tech-bro retros recommend "more standups" as a fix to almost everything. Conflict mediation requires presence; agents can summarise positions but cannot actually mediate. Working agreements drafted by an agent are generic unless seeded with team-specific examples.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/team-charter.md" purpose="Charter with mission, members, working agreements, meeting cadence, success metrics"/>
      <template path="templates/skills-matrix.md" purpose="Role x skill grid (1-4 scale) with gap action column"/>
      <template path="templates/retro.md" purpose="Went well / didn't go well / ideas / action items with owner and sprint deadline"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards/pmbok"/>
      <link href="https://rework.withgoogle.com/print/guides/5721312655835136/"/>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuckman%27s_stages_of_group_development"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
