<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="k8s-security-hardening">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>infrastructure-engineer</domain>
    <summary>Harden Kubernetes workloads with Pod Security Standards, container securityContext, dedicated ServiceAccounts with minimal RBAC, NetworkPolicies (default-deny), and secrets management best practices.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>kubernetes</tag>
      <tag>security</tag>
      <tag>pod-security-standards</tag>
      <tag>networkpolicy</tag>
      <tag>rbac</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>infra</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <frameworks>
      <framework>kubernetes</framework>
    </frameworks>
    <related>
      <ref slug="k8s-deployment-workloads"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Kubernetes Security Hardening</title>

    <summary>Kubernetes workload security requires five layers: Pod Security Standards (enforce restricted namespace labels), container securityContext (non-root, read-only root filesystem, drop ALL capabilities), dedicated ServiceAccounts with minimal RBAC, NetworkPolicies enforcing default-deny with explicit allow rules, and secrets never stored in ConfigMaps or environment variables — use secretKeyRef or an external vault.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Kubernetes defaults are permissive: pods run as root, can escalate privileges, read the default ServiceAccount token (which has cluster-wide permissions in many setups), and communicate with any other pod. A compromised container in a cluster without security hardening becomes an attack path to the Kubernetes API, adjacent services, and cloud metadata APIs. Pod Security Standards (replacing the deprecated PodSecurityPolicy) enforce baseline/restricted profiles at namespace admission time. NetworkPolicies enforce zero-trust pod-to-pod communication. Together they implement defence-in-depth: a compromised pod cannot pivot to the database or the API server.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Deploying any production workload to Kubernetes.</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing Deployment for security misconfigurations.</item>
        <item>Setting up a new namespace for production workloads.</item>
        <item>Implementing zero-trust pod-to-pod communication.</item>
        <item>Reviewing secrets management practices.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Development namespaces with throwaway workloads where security overhead slows iteration — use baseline PSS at minimum.</item>
        <item>Legacy applications that genuinely require root (e.g., some database init scripts) — use securityContext.runAsUser: 0 explicitly rather than omitting it, and document the exception.</item>
        <item>Namespace-level PSS enforcement on namespaces with existing workloads before validating compatibility — start with warn mode.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="pod-security-standards">
      <p>Pod Security Standards (PSS) replaced PodSecurityPolicy in Kubernetes 1.25+. Three profiles: Privileged (unrestricted), Baseline (prevents known privilege escalations), Restricted (strongly hardened). Apply via namespace labels. Three modes: enforce (reject violating pods), audit (log but allow), warn (warn but allow). Production namespaces MUST use enforce: restricted.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Label every production namespace with pod-security.kubernetes.io/enforce: restricted. Use warn and audit modes in staging to catch violations before they block production deploys.</statement>
        <rationale>The enforce label blocks admission of any pod that does not comply with the restricted profile — no root containers, no privilege escalation, no host namespaces. Without enforcement, security context fields are optional and developers omit them under deadline pressure.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Namespace with restricted PSS">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: v1
kind: Namespace
metadata:
  name: production
  labels:
    pod-security.kubernetes.io/enforce: restricted
    pod-security.kubernetes.io/enforce-version: latest
    pod-security.kubernetes.io/warn: restricted
    pod-security.kubernetes.io/warn-version: latest
    pod-security.kubernetes.io/audit: restricted
    pod-security.kubernetes.io/audit-version: latest
]]></code>
      </example>

      <section name="pss-checklist">
        <checklist>
          <check>Namespace labeled with pod-security.kubernetes.io/enforce: restricted.</check>
          <check>Namespace labeled with pod-security.kubernetes.io/warn: restricted.</check>
          <check>Namespace labeled with pod-security.kubernetes.io/audit: restricted.</check>
        </checklist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="container-security-context">
      <p>securityContext fields at container and pod level implement the mandatory controls required by the restricted PSS profile. All six fields must be set: runAsNonRoot, runAsUser, readOnlyRootFilesystem, allowPrivilegeEscalation, capabilities.drop ALL, and seccompProfile RuntimeDefault.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every production container MUST set runAsNonRoot: true, runAsUser >= 1000, readOnlyRootFilesystem: true, allowPrivilegeEscalation: false, capabilities.drop: [ALL], and seccompProfile.type: RuntimeDefault on the pod spec. Writable paths (tmp, cache) must use emptyDir volumes.</statement>
        <rationale>runAsNonRoot prevents a container compromise from immediately having UID 0 on the host. readOnlyRootFilesystem prevents malware writing to /usr/bin or /etc. Dropping ALL capabilities removes file ownership change, raw socket access, and other Linux privilege mechanisms. RuntimeDefault seccomp filters ~300 syscalls not needed by normal applications.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Container and pod security context">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
spec:
  securityContext:
    runAsNonRoot: true
    runAsUser: 1000
    runAsGroup: 1000
    fsGroup: 1000
    seccompProfile:
      type: RuntimeDefault

  containers:
    - name: api
      securityContext:
        allowPrivilegeEscalation: false
        readOnlyRootFilesystem: true
        capabilities:
          drop:
            - ALL

      volumeMounts:
        - name: tmp
          mountPath: /tmp
        - name: cache
          mountPath: /app/cache

  volumes:
    - name: tmp
      emptyDir:
        sizeLimit: 100Mi
    - name: cache
      emptyDir:
        sizeLimit: 500Mi
]]></code>
      </example>

      <section name="container-security-checklist">
        <checklist>
          <check>runAsNonRoot: true.</check>
          <check>runAsUser specified (UID 1000+).</check>
          <check>readOnlyRootFilesystem: true.</check>
          <check>allowPrivilegeEscalation: false.</check>
          <check>capabilities.drop: ["ALL"].</check>
          <check>Only necessary capabilities added back (usually none).</check>
          <check>seccompProfile.type: RuntimeDefault.</check>
          <check>Writable paths mounted as emptyDir.</check>
        </checklist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="service-account-rbac">
      <p>The default ServiceAccount in most namespaces has a mounted API token with cluster-wide read access. Applications that do not call the Kubernetes API should have automountServiceAccountToken: false. Applications that do need API access must use a dedicated ServiceAccount with a minimal Role.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Create a dedicated ServiceAccount per application. Set automountServiceAccountToken: false on the ServiceAccount (or pod spec) for applications that do not call the Kubernetes API. Use a Role and RoleBinding with minimal verbs — never ClusterRole for namespace-scoped workloads.</statement>
        <rationale>If a container is compromised, the mounted token grants the attacker whatever permissions the ServiceAccount has. The default ServiceAccount often has broad read access across the cluster. automountServiceAccountToken: false means no token to steal.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Dedicated ServiceAccount with minimal RBAC">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: v1
kind: ServiceAccount
metadata:
  name: api
  namespace: production
automountServiceAccountToken: false
---
apiVersion: rbac.authorization.k8s.io/v1
kind: Role
metadata:
  name: api
  namespace: production
rules:
  - apiGroups: [""]
    resources: ["configmaps"]
    verbs: ["get", "list", "watch"]
---
apiVersion: rbac.authorization.k8s.io/v1
kind: RoleBinding
metadata:
  name: api
  namespace: production
subjects:
  - kind: ServiceAccount
    name: api
    namespace: production
roleRef:
  kind: Role
  name: api
  apiGroup: rbac.authorization.k8s.io
]]></code>
      </example>

      <section name="service-account-checklist">
        <checklist>
          <check>Dedicated ServiceAccount (not default).</check>
          <check>automountServiceAccountToken: false if not needed.</check>
          <check>RBAC Role/RoleBinding with minimal permissions.</check>
          <check>No ClusterRole for namespace-scoped workloads.</check>
        </checklist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="secrets-management">
      <rule>
        <statement>Never store secrets in ConfigMaps or as plain environment variable values in the Deployment manifest. Always use secretKeyRef / secretRef for environment variables, or mount secrets as files. In production, use an External Secrets Operator or Vault to keep secrets out of etcd entirely.</statement>
        <rationale>ConfigMaps are not encrypted at rest by default; anyone with ConfigMap read access sees the secret. Manifest-embedded plaintext secrets leak into git history and CI logs. External secrets operators sync secrets from a vault at pod start time so only an encrypted reference is stored in Kubernetes.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Secret via secretKeyRef">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
env:
  - name: DATABASE_URL
    valueFrom:
      secretKeyRef:
        name: api-secrets
        key: database-url
  - name: SECRET_KEY
    valueFrom:
      secretKeyRef:
        name: api-secrets
        key: secret-key
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Secret in ConfigMap or plain env">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# ConfigMap - DO NOT store secrets here
apiVersion: v1
kind: ConfigMap
data:
  DATABASE_URL: "postgres://user:password@host:5432/db"
---
# Or plain env value in Deployment - DO NOT do this
env:
  - name: DATABASE_URL
    value: "postgres://user:password@host:5432/db"
]]></code>
        <note>Both patterns leak credentials to anyone with ConfigMap/Deployment read access, and into kubectl describe output visible in cluster logs.</note>
      </example>

      <section name="secrets-checklist">
        <checklist>
          <check>Secrets not hardcoded in manifests or ConfigMaps.</check>
          <check>External secrets operator or vault used in production.</check>
          <check>Secrets rotated regularly.</check>
          <check>Environment variables use secretKeyRef.</check>
        </checklist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="network-policies">
      <p>By default all pods in a Kubernetes cluster can communicate with all other pods, including pods in other namespaces. NetworkPolicy implements zero-trust at the pod level: a default-deny policy blocks all traffic, explicit rules allow only what is necessary. DNS (UDP 53 to kube-dns) must always be explicitly allowed in egress rules.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Apply a default-deny NetworkPolicy to every production namespace. Then add explicit ingress rules (from ingress controller namespace) and egress rules (to database, cache, DNS). Never use a wildcard namespaceSelector in a production NetworkPolicy.</statement>
        <rationale>A default-deny posture means a new pod that should not receive traffic from the database cannot accidentally receive it if someone misconfigures the deployment selector. Explicit egress rules prevent a compromised pod from exfiltrating data to an external IP.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Full NetworkPolicy with default-deny">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: networking.k8s.io/v1
kind: NetworkPolicy
metadata:
  name: api-network-policy
  namespace: production
spec:
  podSelector:
    matchLabels:
      app.kubernetes.io/name: api
  policyTypes:
    - Ingress
    - Egress

  ingress:
    # Allow from ingress controller
    - from:
        - namespaceSelector:
            matchLabels:
              kubernetes.io/metadata.name: ingress-nginx
      ports:
        - protocol: TCP
          port: 8000

    # Allow from other api pods (for health checks)
    - from:
        - podSelector:
            matchLabels:
              app.kubernetes.io/name: api
      ports:
        - protocol: TCP
          port: 8000

  egress:
    # Allow to database
    - to:
        - podSelector:
            matchLabels:
              app.kubernetes.io/name: postgres
      ports:
        - protocol: TCP
          port: 5432

    # Allow to Redis
    - to:
        - podSelector:
            matchLabels:
              app.kubernetes.io/name: redis
      ports:
        - protocol: TCP
          port: 6379

    # Allow DNS (required)
    - to:
        - namespaceSelector: {}
          podSelector:
            matchLabels:
              k8s-app: kube-dns
      ports:
        - protocol: UDP
          port: 53
]]></code>
      </example>

      <section name="network-policy-checklist">
        <checklist>
          <check>NetworkPolicy denies all ingress by default (no ingress rules = deny all ingress).</check>
          <check>NetworkPolicy denies all egress by default.</check>
          <check>Explicit ingress rules for required traffic.</check>
          <check>Explicit egress rules (DNS, required services).</check>
          <check>DNS egress rule present (UDP 53 to kube-dns).</check>
          <check>NetworkPolicy verified: kubectl get networkpolicy -n namespace.</check>
        </checklist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="policy-tools">
      <list>
        <item>Kyverno — Kubernetes-native policy engine, YAML policies, generates resources, validates admission.</item>
        <item>OPA Gatekeeper — Rego-based policies for complex admission control.</item>
        <item>Polaris — best practices validation, built-in checks, dashboard, score &gt; 80% is good baseline.</item>
        <item>kubectl apply --dry-run=server — validate manifests against admission webhooks before apply.</item>
        <item>kubeconform — offline YAML schema validation, fast in CI.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="pre-production-security-checklist">
      <checklist>
        <check>kubectl apply --dry-run=server passes.</check>
        <check>Kyverno/OPA policies pass.</check>
        <check>Polaris audit passes with score &gt; 80%.</check>
        <check>YAML linted (kubeconform, kubeval).</check>
        <check>Namespace PSS labels set.</check>
        <check>Container security context complete (all 6 fields).</check>
        <check>Dedicated ServiceAccount created.</check>
        <check>No secrets in ConfigMaps or plain env values.</check>
        <check>NetworkPolicy applied with default-deny.</check>
        <check>DNS egress rule present.</check>
      </checklist>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://kubernetes.io/docs/concepts/security/pod-security-standards/"/>
      <link href="https://kubernetes.io/docs/concepts/services-networking/network-policies/"/>
      <link href="https://kyverno.io/"/>
      <link href="https://open-policy-agent.github.io/gatekeeper/"/>
      <ref slug="k8s-deployment-workloads"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
