<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="use-case-modeling">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-modeling</domain>
    <summary>Technique for expressing functional requirements as actor-system interaction sequences with main, alternative, and exception flows that map directly to testable scenarios.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>use-cases</tag>
      <tag>functional-requirements</tag>
      <tag>actor-goals</tag>
      <tag>scenario-modeling</tag>
      <tag>requirements-traceability</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Use Case Modeling</title>

    <summary>A technique for expressing functional requirements as actor-system interaction sequences. Each use case captures WHO achieves WHAT goal with the system and HOW the system responds across normal, alternative, and exception flows. Use case names follow Verb+Noun convention; each has preconditions, a main flow (5-9 steps), alternative flows, exception flows, and postconditions.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Requirements written as feature lists omit actor context, miss edge cases, and produce untestable specs. Use cases force the BA to name a concrete actor and trace every path — including failures — before development starts. Each flow maps directly to a test path, closing the gap between "specified" and "testable".</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Functional requirements for transactional systems (line-of-business apps, regulated software) before development starts</item>
        <item>Multiple actor types interact with the system and cross-actor collisions have already caused bugs</item>
        <item>Compliance/audit context (FDA 21 CFR Part 11, SOX) requiring actor-goal → flow → code → test traceability</item>
        <item>Legacy system migration where screens are reverse-engineered into a controlled spec</item>
        <item>Test engineers need a deterministic scenario source for end-to-end test design</item>
        <item>Pre-development alignment when stakeholders speak features and developers need flows</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure discovery phase — Opportunity Solution Trees give better signal than premature formalization</item>
        <item>Agile teams operating well with user stories + acceptance criteria — UC specs duplicate work</item>
        <item>Pure data/analytics platforms where data flow models fit better than actor-goal sequences</item>
        <item>ML/LLM features with probabilistic responses — use cases assume deterministic system behavior</item>
        <item>Tiny CRUD apps with one actor and fewer than 10 screens — an acceptance criteria sheet is faster</item>
        <item>Event-driven systems where event topology matters more than actor goals; use event storming or BPMN</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="use-case-components">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every use case must identify: actor (who), goal (what), system boundary (what is in scope), and scenarios (how).</statement>
        <rationale>Missing any component produces an incomplete spec that cannot drive test case generation or traceability.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Actor types: primary actors initiate use cases to achieve their own goals; secondary actors support the system (external services, databases); system actors are automated timers or other systems.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="five-step-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 1 — Identify actors: list all human roles, external systems, and timers that interact with the system boundary.</statement>
        <rationale>Actors missed at this stage produce use cases with no owner and no test persona.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 2 — Identify use cases: for each actor ask what tasks they perform, what information they need, what they create or change, and what events trigger their actions. Name each use case Verb+Noun.</statement>
        <rationale>Verb+Noun naming enforces goal orientation and prevents feature-as-use-case mistakes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 3 — Create use case diagram: visualize actors outside the system boundary, use cases inside. Show include/extend/generalize relationships only when they de-duplicate 10 or more steps.</statement>
        <rationale>Premature relationship modeling is the #1 source of UC diagram errors; relationships should emerge, not be designed in advance.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 4 — Write use case specifications: document name, ID, description, actors, preconditions, main flow (5-9 steps), alternative flows, exception flows, postconditions, and business rules for each use case.</statement>
        <rationale>Specifications without exception flows miss 40%+ of real behavior and leave testing without negative-path guidance.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 5 — Validate with stakeholders: confirm all actor goals are covered, main flow is correct, alternatives are complete, exceptions are handled, and postconditions are observable.</statement>
        <rationale>Validation is cheapest before development; each missed exception discovered in testing costs 10x more to fix.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="relationship-types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use Include only when the included use case is always executed as part of the including use case and de-duplicates 10 or more steps across multiple use cases.</statement>
        <rationale>Include is misused ~80% of the time; most apparent includes are just consecutive steps within a single flow.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use Extend only when an optionally added behavior branches from a specific extension point in the base use case.</statement>
        <rationale>Extend adds complexity; if the extension is not truly optional and conditional, model it as an alternative flow instead.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use Generalization when a specialized actor or use case inherits all behavior of a parent and adds or overrides specific steps.</statement>
        <rationale>Generalization is the least-used relationship; apply only when the IS-A semantic is genuinely true.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="naming-and-structure">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use case names must be Verb+Noun (e.g. Place Order, Generate Report). Reject any name that is a noun only, a screen name, or contains UI elements.</statement>
        <rationale>Noun-only names describe system state, not actor goals; UI names couple the spec to a design that will change.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Main flow must have 5-9 steps. Fewer than 5 indicates a system function that belongs inside another use case; more than 9 indicates a use case that should be split.</statement>
        <rationale>Step-count uniformity enables comparison and traceability; unbounded length makes review and testing unmanageable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>One step = one actor action plus one system response. Apply this heuristic uniformly across all use cases in a project.</statement>
        <rationale>Inconsistent granularity makes cross-UC comparison and test-case generation unreliable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="required-flows">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every use case must have at least one alternative flow and at least one exception flow before it is accepted as complete.</statement>
        <rationale>Exception flows are the highest-value section; humans and agents skip them by default, leaving 40%+ of real behavior unspecified.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Postconditions must be observable system states (database record created, message sent, file written) — not user perceptions.</statement>
        <rationale>Unobservable postconditions cannot be verified by automated tests or acceptance criteria.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>System Response column must contain system-behavior verbs (validates, persists, emits, calculates) — never UI-rendering verbs (renders, shows, displays button).</statement>
        <rationale>UI verbs couple the spec to a specific design; system-behavior verbs remain stable across redesigns.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="quality-checklist">
      <checklist>
        <check>Each use case has a clear, named primary actor</check>
        <check>Use case name is Verb+Noun</check>
        <check>Preconditions are verifiable system states</check>
        <check>Main flow has 5-9 steps</check>
        <check>At least one alternative flow documented</check>
        <check>At least one exception flow documented</check>
        <check>Postconditions are observable</check>
        <check>Business rules are referenced, not embedded</check>
        <check>Reviewed and signed off by stakeholders</check>
      </checklist>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs write the happy path and stop, omitting alternative and exception flows.</description>
        <reason>Force at least one alternative and one exception in the output schema; reject any output that omits them.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Drafter agents insert UI details ("displays popup") even after being told not to.</description>
        <reason>Add a post-generation regex check for UI nouns (button, modal, popup, screen, click) and bounce matching drafts.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents hallucinate actors that are UI elements (Header, Sidebar) rather than human or system roles.</description>
        <reason>Constrain actor type to {human, system, timer} in the output schema and reject anything else.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Drafting 10+ use cases in a single LLM call — accuracy collapses due to template repetition errors.</description>
        <reason>Chunk one UC per call; combine only at the index-generation step.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="place-order-example">
      <example type="good" title="UC-101: Place Order">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Main Flow:
| Step | Actor Action                        | System Response                               |
|------|-------------------------------------|-----------------------------------------------|
| 1    | Customer initiates checkout         | System displays order summary with totals     |
| 2    | Customer confirms shipping address  | System calculates shipping cost               |
| 3    | Customer selects payment method     | System presents payment entry form            |
| 4    | Customer submits payment details    | System validates payment with payment gateway |
| 5    | Customer confirms order             | System creates order, reduces inventory,      |
|      |                                     | emits confirmation email                      |

Alternative Flow AF-1: New Shipping Address
At step 2, customer enters a new address.
System validates format and saves address to customer profile.
Return to step 2 with updated address selected.

Exception Flow EX-1: Payment Declined
At step 4, payment gateway returns decline response.
System displays error "Payment could not be processed" with error code.
Customer may retry with same or different payment method; flow resumes at step 3.

Postconditions (success): Order record created with status Confirmed;
  inventory decremented for each line item; confirmation email delivered.
Postconditions (failure): Cart preserved; no inventory change; no charge.
        ]]></code>
        <note>Primary Actor: Customer. Preconditions: customer is logged in; cart has at least one item. Note: postconditions are observable states, not user perceptions.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="actor-goal-mapping-example">
      <example type="good" title="Actor-Goal Mapping Example">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Actor           | Use Case               | Type    |
|-----------------|------------------------|---------|
| Customer        | Browse Products        | Primary |
| Customer        | Place Order            | Primary |
| Customer        | Track Shipment         | Primary |
| Admin           | Manage Inventory       | Primary |
| Payment Gateway | Process Payment        | System  |
| Warehouse System| Reserve Inventory      | System  |

Relationship: Place Order <<includes>> Process Payment
Rationale: every order must process payment; de-duplicates the 4-step
payment validation flow that would otherwise appear in Place Order,
Renew Subscription, and Top-Up Account.
        ]]></code>
        <note>E-commerce system — actor-to-use-case index used to verify complete coverage.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="anti-patterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Feature as use case: "Display order screen" — no actor goal, no system behavior.</description>
        <reason>A use case must describe a goal an actor achieves, not a screen the system renders. Rename to "View Order Details" and add actor, flows, postconditions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Overly abstract use case: "Use the system" — no specific goal, untestable.</description>
        <reason>Abstract use cases cannot produce test cases; every use case must deliver a specific, measurable outcome for a named actor.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Main flow with 20 steps — two distinct actor goals bundled in one use case.</description>
        <reason>Split at the natural goal boundary. Apply the step-count rule: any main flow exceeding 9 steps is a splitting signal.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-failure-modes">
      <p>Use case bloat: teams generate UC-001..UC-200 documents that nobody re-reads. Useful UCs cap at approximately 30 per release; beyond that, hierarchy collapses.</p>
      <p>LLMs over-include UI details ("user clicks blue button") which couple the spec to a specific design — agent prompts must explicitly forbid UI verbs and require system-behavior verbs.</p>
      <p>Include and extend are misused approximately 80% of the time in human-authored UCs; LLMs amplify the confusion. Prefer flat UCs unless the include/extend genuinely de-duplicates 10+ steps.</p>
      <p>Step granularity drifts across calls. Without a fixed step-counting heuristic, LLM output is even more uneven.</p>
      <p>Exception flows are the highest-value section and the one humans skip; LLMs default to "Happy path looks great, please review" unless explicitly forced to enumerate failure modes.</p>
      <p>Use cases assume a closed system boundary. Microservices / mesh architectures with shifting boundaries make "the system" ambiguous and UCs misleading.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive use case modeling as a four-stage pipeline (extract actors → enumerate goals → draft specs → validate completeness), each stage a discrete subagent invocation with structured I/O. Use Haiku for template-filling stages (actor extraction, main-flow drafting), Sonnet for review/validation/exception generation, Opus only for cross-UC relationship modeling (include, generalize). Persist artifacts as markdown UC specs under .aidocs/feature/use-cases/UC-NNN-slug.md with YAML front-matter for indexing, and emit a use-case-index.md at the feature level. The BA / PM stays human-in-the-loop on actor identification (cheapest place to fix mistakes) and on relationship modeling (highest cost of getting wrong).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Recommended subagents: faion-sdd-executor-agent once UC specs stabilize, hand off as input to spec/design generation in .aidocs/backlog/feature/. UC-NNN IDs become traceability anchors in spec.md and test-plan.md. Custom actor-extractor-agent (Haiku) input: project brief / existing screens / API surface. Output: JSON list of actors with type (primary/secondary/system) and one-line goal each. Custom uc-drafter-agent (Haiku) input: one actor + one goal + system context. Output: UC spec markdown filling the template. Forbid UI verbs in system prompt. Custom uc-reviewer-agent (Sonnet) input: a draft UC. Output: gap report keyed to the 9-item quality checklist. Required to flag missing exception flows. Custom uc-relationship-agent (Opus) input: full UC set. Output: include / extend / generalization graph with rationale per edge. Run last.</statement>
        <rationale>Specialized agents with different models reduce rework and improve quality across the pipeline.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pin the system boundary in the system prompt before every drafting call. "The System" must resolve to a concrete service / app / API surface, not a vague "the platform".</item>
        <item>Cap main flow at 5-9 steps. Fewer than 5 indicates likely a system function, not a UC. More than 9 indicates should split or delegate via include.</item>
        <item>Forbid UI nouns in System Response column ("renders modal", "shows blue button"). Replace with system-behavior verbs ("validates", "persists", "emits event"). Enforce in the LLM prompt as a hard rule.</item>
        <item>Always require at least one alternative flow and one exception flow before accepting a UC as "complete". Agents skip these by default.</item>
        <item>Use the same step-counting heuristic across all UCs (one actor action + one system response = one step). Without it, comparison and traceability collapse.</item>
        <item>Store UCs as markdown with YAML front-matter (id, name, primary_actor, status, version). The front-matter feeds index/traceability scripts and CI checks.</item>
        <item>Treat the UC index as the source of truth for test scaffolding: each UC main flow yields 1 happy-path test, each AF/EX yields 1 negative-path test. Generate test stubs from the index.</item>
        <item>Validate UC names with a regex: verb + noun only. CI fails the PR if a UC violates the convention.</item>
        <item>Re-run the reviewer agent on the full UC set whenever a new UC lands; relationship inference (include) is fragile and needs the global view.</item>
        <item>Keep UI mockups out of UC files. Link from front-matter (mockup_url:) instead. The UC outlives the design system; the design system does not outlive the UC.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs default to writing the happy path and stopping.</description>
        <reason>Always force ≥1 alternative + ≥1 exception flow in the schema; reject outputs that omit them.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Drafter agents invent UI details ("displays popup confirmation") even when told not to.</description>
        <reason>Add a post-generation regex check (button|modal|popup|screen|click) and bounce drafts that match.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Step granularity drifts across calls.</description>
        <reason>Pin the heuristic in the system prompt ("one step = one actor action + one system response") AND validate step count post-hoc.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Relationship inference (include, extend, generalization) is the highest-error part.</description>
        <reason>Run only Opus, only after all UCs are drafted, and require rationale per edge.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs hallucinate actors that are really UI elements ("Header", "Sidebar").</description>
        <reason>Force actor type in {human, system, time} in the JSON schema; reject anything else.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Long context tempts "draft 30 UCs in one call".</description>
        <reason>Accuracy collapses past approximately 5 UCs per call due to template repetition errors. Chunk one UC per call.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents conflate primary and secondary actors.</description>
        <reason>Make actor_type required and validate that exactly one primary actor is set per UC.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Reviewer agents grade their own drafts too generously.</description>
        <reason>Use a different model family (or at minimum a different system prompt with adversarial framing) for review than for drafting.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Generate test cases from this UC" produces redundant tests when include is used.</description>
        <reason>Resolve includes inline before test generation, or de-duplicate by step ID.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/use-case-spec.md" purpose="Full use case specification shell (ID, actors, preconditions, main/alt/exception flows, postconditions, business rules)"/>
      <template path="templates/use-case-diagram.md" purpose="Diagram notation template listing actors, use cases, and relationships"/>
      <template path="templates/uc-drafter-prompt.txt" purpose="LLM prompt for drafting one UC with hard rules (verb+noun, 5-9 steps, no UI nouns, required exception flows)"/>
      <template path="templates/uc-reviewer-prompt.txt" purpose="LLM prompt for scoring a UC against quality checklist, output JSON"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="decision-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="interface-analysis"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
