<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SOC 2 Control Map Vendor Side Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every vendor-side SOC 2 control map must satisfy so audit prep is a verifiable gap analysis instead of a panic project.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-criteria-row-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The map MUST cover all five Trust Services Criteria (Security, Availability, Processing Integrity, Confidentiality, Privacy) even if some are out of scope; out-of-scope criteria are explicitly marked, never silently omitted.</statement>
      <rationale>Faion has SAST/DAST/supply-chain knowledge in pieces but the control-map artefact lining them up against TSC is absent. Auditors expect to see every TSC addressed (in-scope or formally out-of-scope) — a missing section forces a re-submission and stretches a 4-week prep into 6.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[| TSC                  | In scope? | Notes |
|----------------------|-----------|-------|
| Security             | Yes       | Core controls below |
| Availability         | Yes       | Customer SLA depends on it |
| Processing Integrity | Yes       | Required by enterprise buyer |
| Confidentiality      | Yes       | Customer data is sensitive |
| Privacy              | No        | No PII processed; auditor letter on file |]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-evidence-per-control" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every claimed control MUST cite (a) the implementing methodology / system AND (b) the exact evidence artefact the auditor will request (log export, screenshot, ticket, config file).</statement>
      <rationale>Vendors fail audits not because controls are missing but because evidence cannot be produced in the audit window. Coupling each control to a named evidence artefact converts the map into an evidence-collection plan.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[Control CC7.1 (Detection of unauthorized changes)
- Implementation: SAST + DAST + signed commits (see pro/infra/cve-exception-template)
- Evidence: weekly SAST report exports from GitHub Advanced Security,
  retained 12 months in evidence-vault/soc2-2026/CC7.1/]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every control row MUST name a single accountable owner (handle) responsible for maintaining the control AND producing the evidence; team-only ownership is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>SOC 2 auditors interview named control owners; mapping a control to "the engineering team" guarantees nobody knows it at audit time. A single named human ensures the control is actually living, not just documented.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-quarterly-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Gaps (TSC requirements without an implementing control) MUST be listed explicitly with a target close-date and remediation owner; controls cannot be silently marked "compensating" without naming the compensating control.</statement>
      <rationale>Hidden gaps are the most common audit-fail pattern. Forcing an explicit gap list with owner + date converts pre-audit denial into a managed remediation backlog and gives leadership a credible go/no-go signal for the audit window.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-gap-tracked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The map MUST carry a last_reviewed date and be re-walked at least every 90 days; control maps older than 90 days are treated as stale and cannot be presented to an auditor without refresh.</statement>
      <rationale>SOC 2 Type 2 evaluates a window (typically 6 or 12 months); a stale control map at audit time means the auditor will discover drift independently and the engagement extends. Quarterly refresh keeps the map and the evidence collection synchronised.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
