<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Internal Linking Graph Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed in solo internal-link audits. Each pairs symptom + root cause + fix keyed to a methodology rule.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="fm-orphans-untouched" severity="high">
      <symptom>Audit shows 11 orphans; founder publishes the graph anyway because "they get search traffic, so they're fine".</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Misread of orphan signal">Orphan = no inbound INTERNAL link; the page leaks equity even with external referrals.</root-cause>
      <fix>Add ≥1 inbound link from a sibling spoke OR fold the page into the closest cluster OR de-index. Validator rejects audit with orphans non-empty. Rule r4.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-exact-match-overload" severity="high">
      <symptom>Hub URL ranks position 14 for the head term; site has 22 internal links to that URL all using the exact head-term anchor.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Anchor-text over-optimisation">Founder copied-pasted the same anchor across every link insertion.</root-cause>
      <fix>Diversify to ≥3 surface forms per target (head term, partial match, descriptive sentence, brand+term). Rule r5.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-hub-bloat" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Hub page has 87 inbound links but only 6 outbound spokes; PageRank pools at the hub without flowing back to the cluster.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Hub-as-deadend antipattern">Founder treats hub as the cluster's destination, not the gateway.</root-cause>
      <fix>Add explicit outbound links from hub to each spoke in the cluster overview section. Confirm bidirectional flow. Rule r2 + r6.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-missing-hub-backlinks" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Cluster hub ranks well but spokes underperform; spokes have inbound from sibling spokes but none from the hub itself.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Hub link-out ommission">Hub copy treats spokes as "see also" footers (chrome) instead of in-body links.</root-cause>
      <fix>Move spoke references into the hub body as in-body links. Footer modules do not satisfy r3. Rule r3 + r6.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
