<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Hybrid Search Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for hybrid retrieval config.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="rrf-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default fusion is Reciprocal Rank Fusion with k=60. Switch to linear combination ONLY when RRF is measurably worse on a held-out set AND team can normalise + tune.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cormack et al. 2009 RRF paper; LlamaIndex retrieval benchmarks">RRF uses rank positions only, ignoring score magnitudes. Linear combination needs min-max or z-score normalisation; without it, BM25's unbounded scores dominate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="native-over-manual" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prefer native hybrid endpoints (Qdrant `FusionQuery`, Weaviate `hybrid`, Pinecone sparse-dense, ES knn+BM25) over manual two-call fusion in application code.</statement>
      <rationale source="Qdrant / Weaviate docs">Manual fusion = two network calls + two failure modes + custom RRF impl. Native endpoints do it in one call with fewer corner cases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="query-adaptive-alpha" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When using linear fusion, alpha is computed per-query: quoted phrase → 0.2; numeric / product code → 0.3; ≤ 3-token query → 0.5; natural-language ≥ 4 tokens → 0.7.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft Bing hybrid; internal RAG benchmarks">A fixed alpha is suboptimal across query distributions; a lightweight classifier adds negligible overhead but lifts precision by 5-10 pts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rerank-top100" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When cross-encoder reranker is enabled, fetch top-100 from fusion and rerank to top-10. Never feed only top-10 to the reranker.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cohere Rerank docs; bge-reranker benchmarks">Reranker can only re-order what it sees; small candidate pools cap its upside and waste its 50-100 ms cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="precision-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hybrid config ships only if precision@10 ≥ 0.85 on the held-out set AND p99 latency ≤ budget. Below floor, fall back to the simpler retriever rather than ship hybrid.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal RAG audits">Hybrid that fails its precision floor is added complexity for no value. Better to ship the simpler retriever and re-eval at the next corpus refresh.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
