<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-creative-principles" title="Meta Creative: AIDA Framework, Formats, Visual Rules, Copy Structure">
  <summary>AIDA-driven rules for Meta ad creative: format selection, scroll-stopping visuals, benefit-led copy with hook formulas, and placement-specific specs.</summary>

  <section title="Format Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with static images, add video once you find a winning angle, use carousel for multi-product or multi-benefit showcases.</statement>
      <rationale>Static images are fastest to produce and test. Video requires more production investment; spending it before knowing the winning angle wastes resources. Carousel works when multiple options increase relevance for different segments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Static image: 1080x1080 (1:1) or 1080x1920 (9:16). Best for simple messages and fast iteration.</item>
      <item>Video: 15-30 seconds, vertical (9:16) or square (1:1). Best for storytelling, demos, testimonials.</item>
      <item>Carousel: 2-10 images, 1080x1080. Best for product catalogs or feature lists.</item>
      <item>Stories/Reels: 1080x1920, 15 seconds max. Best for full-screen, native-looking content.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Visual Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the 3-second rule: video must hook within 3 seconds; image must communicate the core message within 3 seconds.</statement>
      <rationale>The average user scrolls past an ad in 1.7 seconds on mobile. If the visual does not stop the scroll immediately, no copy or CTA will ever be read.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>What stops the scroll: faces with strong emotion, before/after contrasts, product in action, bold high-contrast colors, text overlays (concise). What fails: stock photos that look obviously staged, busy compositions with multiple competing focal points, low contrast, overly small subject matter.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always produce both 1:1 and 9:16 format variants for every creative concept.</statement>
      <rationale>Feed placements favor square/portrait; Stories and Reels require 9:16 full-screen. Running a 1:1 creative in Stories shows letterboxing, which signals "this is an ad" and reduces engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Copy Structure">
    <p>Primary text character limits: ~125 characters shown before "See more" — hook must land in those first 125. Headline: 40 characters, benefit-focused. Description: 30 characters, optional support.</p>
    <p>Hook formulas that perform consistently:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Question hook: "Tired of [problem]?" — activates recognition and stops self-identifying prospects.</item>
      <item>Bold claim: "We increased [metric] by 400%" — credible if the number is specific and defensible.</item>
      <item>Curiosity: "This simple change doubled our [result]" — creates information gap.</item>
      <item>Social proof: "10,000+ [audience] are using this" — reduces risk by social validation.</item>
      <item>Direct benefit: "Get [outcome] in [timeframe]" — high clarity, works for transactional offers.</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Benefit-led copy vs feature-focused copy for the same product.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
POOR (feature-focused):
"Our software uses AI to analyze your marketing data.
Features include dashboard, reports, integrations."

BETTER (benefit-led):
"Stop guessing which marketing works.

You're spending $10K+ on ads. But which ones actually drive sales?

[Product] shows you in 60 seconds:
- Which campaigns are profitable
- Where you're wasting money
- What to do next

10,000+ marketers use it daily.

Start free →"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Opening the primary text with the company name or product name.</description>
      <reason>The first line must be a hook that grabs the reader's attention. Company names convey no value to a cold audience; they are only useful after the hook has earned the reader's attention.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-testing-and-fatigue.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/image-ad-spec.md"/>
    <link path="templates/video-ad-script.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
