<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-formula" title="RICE Formula: Factor Definitions, Fixed Scales, and Score-Inflation Antipatterns">
  <summary>The RICE formula components, the fixed value scales for Impact and Confidence, and the antipatterns that inflate scores and destroy cross-feature comparability.</summary>

  <section title="Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>RICE Score = (Reach × Impact × Confidence) / Effort. Higher score = higher priority. Never modify the formula structure — adding weights or exponents destroys cross-quarter comparability.</statement>
      <rationale>The formula's simplicity is its strength. Modifications make it impossible to compare scores across teams or quarters.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Reach">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reach = users affected per quarter. Every Reach value must cite the analytics query, dashboard, or proxy metric used to derive it. "Everyone" and "all users" are not valid values.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs fabricate plausible-looking Reach numbers. Requiring a citation makes fabrication detectable and forces the scorer to check actual data.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Impact">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use only the five standard values: 3 (massive), 2 (high), 1 (medium), 0.5 (low), 0.25 (minimal). Do not add intermediate values. Tie Impact to a specific user-facing metric (conversion, retention, activation).</statement>
      <rationale>Adding intermediate values (1.5, 0.75) destroys cross-feature comparability. The five-point scale forces meaningful distinctions. Impact=3 must be reserved for core differentiators; co-sign required.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Impact scored as 1.7 "because it's between medium and high." The intermediate value makes it impossible to compare this feature against others scored in prior quarters.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Confidence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use only three values: 100% (shipped data on the same surface), 80% (some data, reasonable assumptions), 50% (opinions, limited data). Drop one tier for each unknown: no user research, technical unknowns, never done before, external dependencies.</statement>
      <rationale>100% Confidence is almost always wrong. Reserving it for shipped-data-only situations prevents the entire dataset from clustering at 80% which makes the factor meaningless.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Effort">
    <rule>
      <statement>Effort = person-months, including design, dev, QA, docs, and a 30% buffer for unknown integrations. Engineers must own the Effort column — PM estimates are systematically 2-3x too low.</statement>
      <rationale>Effort is the divisor; underestimating it inflates the score and produces a misleading priority ranking that collapses when sprint planning reveals actual capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Cross-team comparison using the same Reach unit: "Reach = 10K" means different things for free-tier vs paid-tier customers.</description>
    <reason>Comparing RICE scores across segments with different conversion rates mixes apples and oranges. Partition by segment before scoring.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Effort estimated by PM without engineering input, producing scores that look good until sprint planning.</description>
    <reason>PM effort estimates are optimistic by construction. Engineer ownership of the E column is structural, not optional.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-process.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/rice-scorecard.md"/>
    <link path="templates/rice-rank.sh"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
