<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="RICE Scoring Process: Six Steps, Sanity Check, and Strategic Veto">
  <summary>The six-step RICE scoring process, the sanity check, the strategic veto rule, and the quarterly re-scoring cadence.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: List Candidates">
    <rule>
      <statement>Gather all candidate features with a one-paragraph problem statement each before scoring begins. Score the problem statement, not the feature title.</statement>
      <rationale>Scoring vague feature titles produces vague scores. The problem statement forces the scorer to articulate who is affected and why, grounding the R and I estimates.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Score Each Factor">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score in batches of 8-10 items maximum. Quality drops sharply after 10. Randomize order within each batch and average two independent passes to prevent anchoring on the first item.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs anchor on the first item scored and bias subsequent scores relative to it. Randomization across passes neutralizes this effect.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store raw R/I/C/E inputs and rationale alongside the final score. The score alone is unauditable; rationale enables future calibration.</statement>
      <rationale>Without stored rationale, post-ship actuals cannot be compared against estimates, making quarterly calibration impossible.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Calculate RICE">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the formula: (R × I × C) / E. Treat confidence as a decimal (80% = 0.8). Sort highest to lowest.</statement>
      <rationale>Treating confidence as a percentage (80) instead of a decimal (0.8) produces scores 100x larger and loses the relative weighting between confidence levels.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/rice-rank.sh">Bash script that reads a CSV and outputs sorted RICE scores with the computed column.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Sanity Check">
    <rule>
      <statement>After sorting, ask: "Does this ranking feel wrong?" Investigate items where the gut diverges from the score — the score is probably right and the gut is anchored on a wrong assumption. Document the investigation.</statement>
      <rationale>Sanity checks catch data errors (wrong Reach unit, Effort in days instead of months). Documenting the investigation builds calibration discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Apply Strategic Veto">
    <rule>
      <statement>After sorting, the PM may promote one strategic bet that ranks lower than its score suggests. Document the veto rationale explicitly. Strategic veto is limited to one item per quarter.</statement>
      <rationale>RICE does not encode dependencies, sequencing, or strategic narrative. A single veto slot preserves the score discipline while allowing human judgment on moat-building investments.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Re-score Quarterly">
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-score the full backlog quarterly. Re-score individual features immediately when their underlying assumption is invalidated — not at the next quarterly cycle. Track post-ship actuals (real Reach, real Effort) to calibrate next quarter's estimates.</statement>
      <rationale>A score based on stale assumptions misleads roadmap planning. Immediate re-scoring on assumption change prevents cascading prioritization errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Re-scoring retroactively to "explain" why a shipped feature succeeded.</description>
      <reason>Retroactive scoring destroys the calibration data needed to improve future estimates. Keep original scores immutable; add actuals as a separate column.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-formula.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/rice-decision-record.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
