<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Edge and CDN Strategy Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Edge and CDN Strategy methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-cache-key-includes-vary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cache keys MUST include the headers / query params that vary the response: Accept-Language, Accept-Encoding, auth boundary, A/B test cohort. Excluded headers documented.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloudflare cache-key best practices">Wrong cache key serves the wrong response to the wrong user (privacy leak + correctness bug).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-origin-shielding-on" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Origin shielding MUST be enabled: requests from edges hit a regional shield first, which consolidates origin pulls. Single-shield bottleneck risk mitigated via multi-shield setup for high-volume tenants.</statement>
      <rationale source="Fastly / Cloudflare shielding docs">Without shielding, every edge fetches from origin = origin overload during cache-miss storms.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-edge-auth-single-place" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Auth MUST be enforced at edge OR origin, not both. If at edge, edge passes verified identity to origin (signed JWT, mTLS). Origin trusts edge identity via shared secret / mTLS.</statement>
      <rationale source="edge-auth patterns; zero-trust">Split auth doubles bug surface; one-place auth with handoff is cleaner.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-fallback-bypass-dns" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DNS MUST have a configured edge-bypass record (e.g. origin.acme.com) reachable when edge is degraded. Runbook documents the bypass procedure.</statement>
      <rationale source="DR continuity patterns">Edge platforms have outages; bypass DNS keeps service alive while edge recovers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-per-request-cost-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per-request edge-compute cost MUST be budgeted (e.g. $0.0001 / request median, $0.001 / request 99p). Cost &gt; budget triggers a review (cold-start growth, regex catastrophic, log volume).</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps for edge">Edge bills surprise teams; per-request budget is the early-warning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-cache-hit-ratio-monitored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cache hit ratio MUST be monitored per route. &lt; 70% on cacheable routes triggers a cache-key review.</statement>
      <rationale source="CDN performance tuning">Low hit ratio = CDN spending without offload benefit; cache-key misconfiguration is the usual cause.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
