<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-playbooks" title="Customer Success Basics — Playbooks and Examples">
  <summary>Onboarding playbook, at-risk intervention, expansion path, and worked examples for SaaS and course products.</summary>

  <section title="Onboarding playbook">
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS team collaboration tool. Success definition: team uses daily, 3+ active projects, 80%+ adoption. Playbook: Day 1 admin onboarding call; Day 7 team training webinar; Day 14 check-in email; Day 30 success review call; Monthly usage report; Quarterly business review. All touchpoints event-triggered where possible (e.g. Day 7 webinar invite only if team has less than 3 projects).</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Online course. Success definition: complete 80% of content, implement learnings, achieve stated goal. Playbook: Day 1 welcome + learning roadmap; Day 3 first module completion reminder (if not started); Weekly progress email; Module completion acknowledgment + next steps; Completion survey + testimonial request.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="At-risk intervention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap automated re-engagement outreach at one message per week per account. An at-risk account must not receive more than three automated re-engagements before the sequence pauses and escalates to human review.</statement>
      <rationale>Re-engagement spam is the fastest way to convert a disengaged customer into a churned customer who also unsubscribes and leaves a negative review. Automation helps at low volume; at high frequency it accelerates the outcome you are trying to prevent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Health band red (score below 50): immediate CSM review, personal outreach within 24 hours</item>
      <item>Health band yellow (score 50-74): automated email with specific tip, monitor for 7 days, escalate if no improvement</item>
      <item>Health band green (score 75+): maintain regular cadence, watch for expansion signals</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Expansion path">
    <list>
      <item>Customer hitting plan limits → proactive upgrade offer before they feel blocked</item>
      <item>Adding team members → invite prompt for additional seats</item>
      <item>Using advanced features → showcase premium tier that extends those features</item>
      <item>Requesting a feature → show existing solution + note if upgrade unlocks more</item>
      <item>Success milestone reached → celebrate + cross-sell related product</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
