<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Dormant Lead Reactivation Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules grounding service-business reactivation. Each pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="segment-distinct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Contacts MUST be segmented into exactly one of {past-client, lost-proposal, nurture-lead}. Mixed-segment sequences are forbidden — each segment gets its own sequence.</statement>
      <rationale source="Service-business reactivation audit Q1 2026">Past clients have prior context that nurture leads lack; bundling them produces tone that fits neither.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="max-3-touches" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A reactivation sequence MUST be ≤3 touches per contact within a quarter. After touch 3, the contact is killed or moved to long-term nurture.</statement>
      <rationale source="Service-business response-rate studies">Beyond 3 touches, additional sends produce more unsubs than replies; small lists punish over-touch.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="consent-reconfirm-first-touch" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For contacts in EU / UK / California jurisdictions with consent older than 18 months, touch 1 MUST be a consent re-confirmation (single-question), not an offer.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR / UK GDPR / CCPA guidance">Stale consent + offer = unlawful processing in those jurisdictions; re-confirmation is the lesser-harm path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="prior-context-reference" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every touch MUST reference the specific prior interaction (project name, proposal date, last conversation topic). Generic "hope you're well" openings are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — reactivation A/B tests">Personalized references convert at 3-5× generic openings on small lists.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="outcome-recorded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After each touch + sequence end, the contact's outcome MUST be recorded as one of {engaged, killed, pending}. Pending after touch 3 auto-converts to killed at quarter end.</statement>
      <rationale source="Pipeline-hygiene practice">Without outcome recording, the same dormants get re-targeted every quarter with diminishing returns.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
