<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Lemon Squeezy Ops Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed in indie LS operations. Each pairs symptom + root cause + fix keyed to a methodology rule.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="fm-double-vat" severity="high">
      <symptom>EU buyer reports being charged VAT twice — once via LS checkout, once on the founder's separate invoice. Refund request + complaint.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="MoR misunderstanding">Founder kept the pre-LS invoicing flow active even after enabling LS as Merchant of Record.</root-cause>
      <fix>Disable parallel VAT invoice for LS-source orders. LS receipt is the legal invoice. Refund duplicate VAT; apology email. Rule r2.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-license-bypass" severity="high">
      <symptom>Subscription software pirated days after launch; same hard-coded key in cracked builds.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="License API not enabled">License key embedded in the binary; no online validation.</root-cause>
      <fix>Enable LS License API per variant; validate at startup + daily cadence; revoke compromised keys on refund. Rule r3.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-dunning-gap" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Monthly involuntary churn spike — failed renewals not recovered, MRR drops despite no voluntary cancels.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Single-touch dunning">Only T+1 reminder configured; no T+4 / T+8 follow-up.</root-cause>
      <fix>Wire 3-email sequence per templates/dunning-sequence.md. Expect 35-45% recovery on failed cards. Rule r4.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-affiliate-drop" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Affiliates quit the program within 30 days; commission tracker shows clicks but few conversions per affiliate.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Commission band misaligned">commission_pct set below 30% — affiliates view the program as not worth promoting.</root-cause>
      <fix>Raise commission to 35-45% (within r5 band). Re-invite affiliates with updated terms. Document rationale if band is intentionally exceeded.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
