<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="scope-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Define, baseline, and control project scope to prevent uncontrolled expansion. Produces scope statement, requirements with MoSCoW priority, and traceability matrix.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>scope</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>change-control</tag>
      <tag>traceability</tag>
      <tag>scope-creep</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Scope Management</title>
    <summary>Define, baseline, validate, and control project scope to prevent uncontrolled expansion. Scope management produces a scope statement (objectives, deliverables, exclusions, constraints, assumptions), a requirements document with MoSCoW priorities, and a traceability matrix linking every requirement to design, build, and test. The rule: write exclusions before inclusions — explicit "not in scope" prevents 80% of scope disputes.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Scope creep consumes budget and schedule while remaining invisible until too late. Without a baseline, there is no way to evaluate change requests objectively — every "small addition" appears free. A requirements traceability matrix (RTM) stored as YAML in source control (not a Word doc) stays live across the project and survives tool migrations.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Project initiation: drafting scope statement, requirement collection, baselining</item>
        <item>Mid-project change requests where impact assessment must precede approval</item>
        <item>Multi-stakeholder programs with conflicting priorities (MoSCoW + traceability)</item>
        <item>Contracted/fixed-price work where every out-of-scope item is a margin event</item>
        <item>Requirements traceability for regulated domains (medtech, fintech, government)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Continuous-discovery agile product — use rolling outcomes instead of scope baselines</item>
        <item>Pure research/spike work where scope is the question, not the input</item>
        <item>Internal tools with fewer than 10 users where formal sign-off is theater</item>
        <item>Crisis incident response — incident scope is "stop the bleeding", not a PMP doc</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Core Concepts">
      <list>
        <item>Product Scope — features and functions of the deliverable</item>
        <item>Project Scope — all work required to deliver the product scope</item>
        <item>Scope Baseline — approved scope statement + WBS + WBS dictionary</item>
        <item>Scope Creep — expansion without formal approval; always has cost and schedule impact</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Write exclusions before inclusions in every scope statement.</statement>
        <rationale>Explicit "not in scope" clauses prevent 80% of scope disputes because ambiguity resolves in the direction of whatever the stakeholder assumed was included.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Requirement Types">
      <p>Collect and classify requirements before writing the scope statement:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Business — why the project exists (e.g., "increase revenue 20%")</item>
        <item>Stakeholder — what each stakeholder needs ("executive dashboard")</item>
        <item>Solution/Functional — system capabilities ("calculates order totals automatically")</item>
        <item>Transition — change management, data migration, training</item>
        <item>Non-Functional — performance, security, usability constraints</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every must-have requirement needs a verifiable acceptance criterion before baselining.</statement>
        <rationale>Requirements without AC are unverifiable. Tautological ACs ("system shall display the page when the page is displayed") must be rejected; force concrete, testable conditions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Scope Control">
      <rule>
        <statement>Baseline scope at end of planning; every subsequent change goes through Change Control with cost/schedule/risk delta.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a baseline there is no objective reference — every change claim becomes a negotiation. Baseline freezes the reference; changes are measured against it.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Capture every "while you're at it" request as a formal Change Request; never absorb silently.</statement>
        <rationale>Silent absorption is the primary mechanism of gold-plating. Making every addition visible creates an audit trail and forces trade-off decisions before work starts.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Verbal scope agreements without written scope statement sign-off.</description>
        <reason>Undocumented promises are interpreted differently by each party. At project end, everyone argues about what was supposed to be built based on their memory.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Vague scope language: "make it better", "improve performance".</description>
        <reason>Vague scope cannot be accepted, rejected, or measured. Every acceptance criterion must have a numeric or observable condition.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Scope Creep Prevention">
      <list>
        <item>Written scope statement with sponsor sign-off</item>
        <item>Formal Change Control process communicated at kickoff</item>
        <item>Stakeholder sign-off on scope before development starts</item>
        <item>Regular scope baseline reviews at phase gates</item>
        <item>Professional "no" process: acknowledge → explain scope constraint → offer alternative (future phase) → document decision</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Traceability Matrix">
      <rule>
        <statement>Store the RTM as YAML or CSV in source control, not as a Word document.</statement>
        <rationale>An RTM that lives in a Word doc becomes orphaned after sprint 2. Source-control storage means agents and humans can edit it, diffs are reviewable, and it survives tool migrations.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Every row in the RTM must carry: requirement ID, source stakeholder, design reference, code reference, test reference, and current status. A must-have requirement missing any of these is a gap.</p>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[- id: FR-01
  type: functional
  statement: "System calculates order totals automatically on item add/remove"
  priority: must
  source: "Sales Manager (interview 2026-04-01)"
  acceptance_criteria: "Order total updates within 200ms with no page reload"
  design_ref: "design/checkout-flow.md#totals"
  code_ref: "src/cart/calculator.py"
  test_ref: "tests/test_cart.py::test_total_update"
  status: done]]></code>
        <note>UUIDs or content-hash IDs prevent renumbering when requirements are regenerated by agents.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="MoSCoW Rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply a quota: no more than 60% of requirements may be "Must".</statement>
        <rationale>Without a cap, stakeholders mark everything Must and scope becomes uncontrollable. A 60% Must quota forces explicit prioritization trade-offs.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Must — delivery-blocking; project fails if absent; requires AC and owner</item>
        <item>Should — high value but not delivery-blocking; could move to phase 2</item>
        <item>Could — nice-to-have; absorbed only if capacity permits after Must and Should</item>
        <item>Won't — explicitly deferred or excluded; prevents "assumed in scope" disputes</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>A Must requirement must never have status "Won't".</statement>
        <rationale>This combination means the project will fail by definition. Detect early and force a sponsor decision: descope the Must or cancel the project.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Gotchas">
      <rule>
        <statement>Freeze canonical requirement text and require diff-based edits; do not regenerate from scratch.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs paraphrase requirements into different wording on each pass. Regenerating produces a new document with different IDs and wording — breaking all downstream traceability links.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Force "priority" as a required JSON field in extraction prompts; agents silently drop it otherwise</item>
        <item>Tautological ACs ("system shall work correctly when it works correctly") must be rejected by the validator</item>
        <item>Agent-extracted requirements drop source stakeholder attribution — require it as a non-nullable field</item>
        <item>For regulated work, agents must not redact source quotes from RTM; auditors need original wording</item>
        <item>Gold-plating: cap NFR generation to requirements with an explicit named source — reject agent-invented NFRs</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>A requirements-extractor subagent reads stakeholder input (interviews, emails, slack threads, RFPs), normalizes into business/stakeholder/solution/transition/non-functional buckets with MoSCoW priorities, and emits a requirements doc. A scope-validator agent checks completeness (every "must" has acceptance criteria, every deliverable has an owner). A change-impact agent evaluates incoming change requests across schedule, cost, risk, and downstream dependencies. PM signs off; agent writes ADR. Pair with business-analyst and sdd-planning skills.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools and Services">
      <rule>
        <statement>Requirements and traceability data must be machine-readable and version-controlled.</statement>
        <rationale>Word documents and spreadsheets detached from version control become immediately stale. YAML/CSV in git enables agent edits, diffs, and audit trails.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Key tools for scope management:</p>
      <list>
        <item>pandoc — Convert RTM/scope docs across formats (Word, PDF, MD)</item>
        <item>marp / mkdocs — Publish scope docs as a versioned site</item>
        <item>gh — Track scope items as GitHub Issues with "requirement" label</item>
        <item>jira (CLI) — Sync requirements as Jira issues, link to deliverables</item>
        <item>dot (Graphviz) — Render dependency / traceability graphs</item>
        <item>csvkit — Manipulate RTM CSVs</item>
      </list>
      <p>SaaS platforms: Jama Connect (REST API), IBM DOORS Next (OSLC API), Helix RM (Perforce), Confluence (REST API), Notion (partial API support), ReqView (OSLC/ReqIF), Aha! (REST API), Modern Requirements (Azure DevOps add-on).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Write exclusions before inclusions — saying "no" up front prevents 80% of scope disputes</item>
        <item>Every scope item has: source stakeholder, AC, owner, traceability ID — no exceptions</item>
        <item>Baseline scope at end of planning; subsequent changes go through change control with cost/schedule/risk delta</item>
        <item>Use MoSCoW with quotas (e.g., max 60% must) to force prioritization</item>
        <item>For agile contexts, use "outcome scope" (KPI movement) over "feature scope" (list)</item>
        <item>RTM lives in source control as YAML/CSV, not a Word doc — agents and humans both edit</item>
        <item>Capture every "while you're at it" gold-plating attempt as a CR; do not absorb silently</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/requirements-doc.md" purpose="Requirements document (business, stakeholder, functional, non-functional)"/>
      <template path="templates/scope-statement.md" purpose="Scope statement with deliverables, boundaries, constraints, assumptions"/>
    </templates>
    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/trace-check.py" purpose="Flag must-have requirements missing design/test coverage in RTM CSV"/>
      <script path="scripts/moscow-lint.py" purpose="Enforce MoSCoW invariants (no MUST without AC, no MUST+Wont)"/>
    </scripts>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="raci-matrix"/>
      <ref slug="wbs-creation"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards/pmbok"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/standards/babok/"/>
      <link href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8049936"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
