<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-five-metrics" title="The Five DORA Metrics">
  <summary>Definitions, elite/high/medium/low benchmarks, and how to measure each of the five DORA metrics.</summary>

  <section title="Metric Overview">
    <p>DORA metrics measure software delivery performance across two dimensions: throughput (how fast) and stability (how safe). Elite teams deploy 973x more frequently and recover 6570x faster than low performers. High throughput and high stability are not a trade-off — elite teams achieve both simultaneously.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure all five metrics together. Never optimize one in isolation: high deployment frequency with rising CFR signals a process problem, not improvement.</statement>
      <rationale>DORA research shows that teams gaming single metrics (e.g., deploying more often without fixing quality) regress on stability. The five metrics form an interdependent system.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Deployment Frequency">
    <p>How often code is successfully deployed to production. Measures throughput.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Elite: multiple times per day (on-demand)</item>
      <item>High: weekly to monthly</item>
      <item>Medium: monthly to 6 months</item>
      <item>Low: less than once every 6 months</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure production deployments only. Do not count deploys to dev/staging environments.</statement>
      <rationale>Staging deployments are not customer-impacting. Mixing them inflates the metric and masks the actual delivery frequency visible to users.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Lead Time for Changes">
    <p>Median time from a code commit being merged to that commit running in production. Measures throughput.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Elite: less than 1 hour</item>
      <item>High: 1 day to 1 week</item>
      <item>Medium: 1 to 6 months</item>
      <item>Low: more than 6 months</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure from merge commit timestamp to production deployment timestamp. Use median, not mean — outliers from feature flags or delayed releases distort mean values.</statement>
      <rationale>Median is resistant to outliers caused by long-running feature branches or scheduled release windows that do not represent normal delivery flow.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Change Failure Rate">
    <p>Percentage of production deployments that result in a degraded service requiring remediation (hotfix, rollback, patch). Measures stability.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Elite: 0–15%</item>
      <item>High: 16–30%</item>
      <item>Medium: 31–45%</item>
      <item>Low: greater than 45%</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Correlate incidents with deployments within a 24-hour window. A deployment that causes an incident within 24 hours counts as a failed change.</statement>
      <rationale>The 24-hour window captures both immediate failures and delayed manifestations (e.g., memory leaks) while excluding pre-existing issues unrelated to the release.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Time to Restore Service (MTTR)">
    <p>Median time from when an incident starts affecting users to when the service is fully restored. Measures stability.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Elite: less than 1 hour</item>
      <item>High: less than 1 day</item>
      <item>Medium: 1 day to 1 week</item>
      <item>Low: more than 1 week</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Reliability (Fifth Metric)">
    <p>Added in 2023. Measures whether the team meets its own reliability targets (SLOs). Not a single number — it is a boolean: did the service meet its SLO targets this period?</p>
    <list>
      <item>Elite: consistently exceeds SLO targets</item>
      <item>High: meets SLO targets</item>
      <item>Medium: partially meets targets</item>
      <item>Low: below targets</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define explicit SLO targets (availability, latency P99, error rate) before tracking Reliability. Without targets, the metric cannot be evaluated.</statement>
      <rationale>Reliability requires a defined threshold. Teams that have not defined SLOs cannot meaningfully track whether they are meeting them.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
