<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-implementation" title="DORA Metrics Implementation">
  <summary>Data collection strategy, tooling options, anti-patterns, and the minimum viable setup for each metric.</summary>

  <section title="Data Collection Sources">
    <rule>
      <statement>Automate data collection from CI/CD pipelines, version control, and incident management. Never collect DORA metrics manually — manual data degrades within weeks as teams skip updates.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual data collection introduces selection bias (teams report favorable metrics) and sustains a maintenance burden that eventually leads to abandonment. Automated collection from event sources is authoritative and continuous.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Deployment Frequency: CI/CD pipeline success events (GitHub Actions, GitLab CI, ArgoCD PostSync hooks)</item>
      <item>Lead Time: merge commit timestamp + deployment event timestamp from VCS and CI</item>
      <item>Change Failure Rate: incident management events (PagerDuty, Opsgenie) correlated with deployment events within 24h</item>
      <item>MTTR: incident open/close timestamps from PagerDuty, Opsgenie, or ServiceNow</item>
      <item>Reliability: SLO compliance from Prometheus (availability, error rate, latency P99)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Tooling Options">
    <list>
      <item>Sleuth: purpose-built DORA tracking; connects to GitHub/GitLab, PagerDuty, Jira; best for DORA-focused teams</item>
      <item>LinearB: DORA plus engineering productivity metrics; good for teams wanting broader metrics</item>
      <item>Faros AI: custom metrics and data warehousing; best for data-driven teams building custom pipelines</item>
      <item>GitHub Insights: built-in for GitHub users; covers Deployment Frequency and Lead Time natively</item>
      <item>GitLab Value Stream Analytics: built-in for GitLab users; covers all four original DORA metrics</item>
      <item>Custom Prometheus + Grafana: full control, requires custom event tracking pipeline; best when data stays on-prem</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Minimum Viable Setup">
    <p>Start with Deployment Frequency and Lead Time — both come from CI/CD data already collected. Add CFR after 30 days once you have an incident correlation baseline. Add MTTR when incident management tooling is connected.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Wait 30 days before committing to Savings Plans or Reserved Instances based on DORA data. Wait 30 days before reporting DORA baselines to leadership.</statement>
      <rationale>Fewer than 30 days of data yields unreliable baselines. Seasonal variations, sprint cycles, and deployment windows need multiple samples to produce a representative median.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using DORA metrics for individual performance reviews or team comparison without context.</description>
      <reason>DORA measures team/system outcomes, not individual contribution. Teams with different domain complexity, technical debt, or size have incomparable baseline metrics. Punitive use causes gaming: teams split large deployments into trivial changes to inflate Deployment Frequency.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Optimizing Deployment Frequency without watching Change Failure Rate.</description>
      <reason>Deploying more often with inadequate test coverage raises CFR. High-frequency + high-CFR = more outages, not better delivery. The metrics must be tracked and improved together.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting targets based on industry benchmarks without establishing your own baseline first.</description>
      <reason>An organization at Low performance cannot jump to Elite. Setting unrealistic targets creates pressure to game metrics rather than improve systems. Set targets as 20-30% improvement from current baseline, not as absolute Elite thresholds.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="AI Tooling Impact (2025)">
    <p>The 2025 DORA Report found that AI adoption improves throughput metrics (faster code generation, review) but increases delivery instability (higher CFR). Teams must invest in seven capabilities to capture AI value without degrading stability:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Internal data accessible to AI systems</item>
      <item>Working in small batches</item>
      <item>Continuous integration with fast feedback</item>
      <item>Trunk-based development</item>
      <item>Comprehensive test automation</item>
      <item>Deployment automation</item>
      <item>Monitoring and observability</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
