<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="competitor-analysis Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for competitor-analysis. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Identify all three competitor types: direct (same product, same audience), indirect (different product, same problem), and future (emerging or could pivot). Target 5-10 direct, 3-5 indirect, 2-3 future.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Analysing only direct competitors misses the substitutes customers actually use and the entrants who will arrive in 18 months.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plot each competitor on a 2-axis matrix (price vs feature breadth) and identify empty quadrants or underserved positions before selecting your own positioning.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Empty quadrants reveal market gaps; overcrowded quadrants signal where differentiation is hardest. Visual mapping surfaces the whitespace that a feature list alone obscures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Analyse each competitor across all 8 dimensions. Do not skip dimensions—missing ones leave blind spots that surface in the gap analysis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A partial analysis produces a partial gap table. Investors and customers will probe the dimensions you skipped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Differentiate on a competitor weakness, not on feature parity. Scrape 1-star reviews and convert the top 3 complaints into your positioning message.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Copying competitors produces table-stakes features. Converting their biggest complaints into your headline creates a concrete, testable claim that resonates with dissatisfied users already searching for alternatives.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write a positioning statement in the canonical template form before finalizing the gap analysis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Forces the team to articulate the differentiation concretely and reveals whether the gap identified is actually usable as messaging.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin target geography in every prompt and reject any competitor whose primary market differs from your target region.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without geography pinning, agents return competitors ranked by Google's global SERP, which skews toward US companies even when the user's market is EU or APAC.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run per-competitor snapshot tasks in parallel, synthesis serially. Cuts wall-clock by 5-8x and isolates per-competitor context windows.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each competitor's pricing page, review scrape, and feature list is independent. Parallelising collection then serialising synthesis is the only pattern that scales beyond 5 competitors without context degradation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Seed the competitor list with humans + customer interviews before agents—agents over-index on Google's first page and miss "what my friend uses".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Algorithmic discovery is fast but biased. Human seed lists capture the substitutes customers actually use.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Force the agent to cite a URL for every factual cell (price, founding year, employee count); reject any cell without a source.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sourced claims are auditable. Unsourced cells are liabilities in investor meetings and marketing copy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run snapshot agents in parallel (one per competitor), synthesis serially. Cuts wall-clock by 5-8x and isolates per-competitor context.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each competitor's pricing page, review scrape, and feature list is independent. Parallelising collection then serialising synthesis is the only pattern that scales beyond 5 competitors without context degradation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always include "future" competitors (AI startups, big-tech adjacencies)—they are the real threat in 18 months.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Current market leaders do not predict category shifts. Future competitors require a concrete signal (job posting, acquisition, beta product) but must not be omitted.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep the matrix to ≤8 dimensions; more columns degrade the gap analysis signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Excessive dimensions dilute focus and make visual patterns harder to spot.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-run quarterly with the same template; diff the markdown to see which competitors moved.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Quarterly re-runs surface pricing escalations, feature launches, and team growth. A diff between two snapshots is more actionable than a one-time matrix.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store the seed competitor list in version control (.aidocs/product_docs/_competitors.yml) so re-runs are reproducible.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Reproducibility enables credible quarterly diffs and prevents drift in competitor selection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mark every estimated number with ~ or (est.) and never let the agent strip those hedges in the synthesis pass.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unhedged estimates in a published matrix damage credibility. Investors and customers expect transparency about data quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
