<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Competitor Analysis Framework">
  <summary>Five-step systematic framework: identify competitor types, map positioning, analyse across 8 dimensions, find gaps, define differentiation.</summary>

  <section title="Competitor Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify all three competitor types: direct (same product, same audience), indirect (different product, same problem), and future (emerging or could pivot). Target 5-10 direct, 3-5 indirect, 2-3 future.</statement>
      <rationale>Analysing only direct competitors misses the substitutes customers actually use and the entrants who will arrive in 18 months.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Sources for discovery: Google "[problem] solution", Product Hunt category search, G2/Capterra category browse, "Alternatives to [known competitor]", Reddit "What do you use for [problem]?", direct customer interviews.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Positioning Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Plot each competitor on a 2-axis matrix (price vs feature breadth) and identify empty quadrants or underserved positions before selecting your own positioning.</statement>
      <rationale>Empty quadrants reveal market gaps; overcrowded quadrants signal where differentiation is hardest. Visual mapping surfaces the whitespace that a feature list alone obscures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Axes: Premium vs Budget (vertical), Narrow vs Broad feature set (horizontal). Quadrants: Specialized/High Value, Enterprise/High Price, Niche/Underserved, Mass Market/Crowded.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="8-Dimension Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Analyse each competitor across all 8 dimensions. Do not skip dimensions — missing ones leave blind spots that surface in the gap analysis.</statement>
      <rationale>A partial analysis produces a partial gap table. Investors and customers will probe the dimensions you skipped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Product — what features exist, what is missing</item>
      <item>Pricing — model, tiers, effective monthly cost for 1 user billed monthly</item>
      <item>Positioning — target audience, headline message</item>
      <item>Technology — stack, integrations, API availability</item>
      <item>Traction — estimated users, revenue proxy, growth signal</item>
      <item>Team — size, expertise, funding</item>
      <item>Marketing — channels, content cadence, ad spend signals</item>
      <item>Weaknesses — 1-star reviews, forum complaints, missing features</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Gap Analysis">
    <p>Five gap types to identify: feature gap (they do not have it), quality gap (they do it poorly), audience gap (they do not serve this segment), price gap (they are too expensive for some), experience gap (UX or onboarding is painful).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Differentiate on a competitor weakness, not on feature parity. Scrape 1-star reviews and convert the top 3 complaints into your positioning message.</statement>
      <rationale>Copying competitors produces table-stakes features. Converting their biggest complaints into your headline creates a concrete, testable claim that resonates with dissatisfied users already searching for alternatives.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Differentiation Statement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write a positioning statement in the canonical template form before finalizing the gap analysis.</statement>
      <rationale>Forces the team to articulate the differentiation concretely and reveals whether the gap identified is actually usable as messaging.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
For solo freelancers
Who need simple project tracking
TaskLite is a project management tool
That focuses on single-person workflows
Unlike Asana or Monday
We have no team features, just personal productivity
]]></code>
      <note>Naming the competitor makes the claim testable and immediately clear to the target customer.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-gotchas.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/competitor-report.md"/>
    <link path="templates/competitor-snapshot.md"/>
    <link path="templates/scrape-competitor.sh"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
