<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Competitor Analysis Examples">
  <summary>Two worked examples (note-taking app, email marketing) and a common-mistakes table showing the correct fix for each failure mode.</summary>

  <section title="Example: Note-Taking App">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Market: personal knowledge management. Competitors analysed: Notion, Obsidian, Roam Research (direct); Apple Notes, Google Docs (indirect); AI writing tools (future).</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| Competitor | Strength         | Weakness              | Opportunity           |
|------------|------------------|-----------------------|-----------------------|
| Notion     | All-in-one       | Slow, complex         | Speed, simplicity     |
| Obsidian   | Local-first      | Steep learning curve  | Easier onboarding     |
| Roam       | Backlinks        | Expensive, dated UI   | Better UX, lower price|

Positioning: "For busy professionals who want fast, simple notes with linking.
Unlike Notion, we're single-purpose and lightning fast.
Unlike Obsidian, we work great out of the box."
]]></code>
      <note>Gap chosen: experience gap (speed and simplicity). Messaging names specific competitors to make the claim credible.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example: Email Marketing for Solopreneurs">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Gap discovered through pricing analysis: all tools price by subscriber count, creating early paywalls for solopreneurs under 1000 subscribers.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Opportunity: "Generous free tier (5000 subscribers), solo-focused features, no team complexity"
Gap type: Price gap + audience gap — no tool focuses on sub-1000 subscriber solo operators.
]]></code>
      <note>Price gap and audience gap combined. Competitor pricing analysis identified the tier ladder, not just features.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Analysing only direct competitors and omitting indirect and future types.</description>
      <reason>Indirect competitors are what customers actually use today; future competitors are the real threat in 18 months. Missing both produces a false sense of whitespace.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Surface-level analysis limited to homepage copy without digging into pricing pages, reviews, and feature documentation.</description>
      <reason>Pricing footnotes (annual lock-in, seat minimums, transaction fees) and 1-star review themes contain more actionable signal than marketing copy.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>One-time analysis with no refresh schedule.</description>
      <reason>A competitor matrix is stale within 60-90 days. Pricing, feature flags, and team size change frequently. Schedule quarterly re-runs with the same template to produce a diff.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Copying competitors' features rather than differentiating on their weaknesses.</description>
      <reason>Feature parity produces table stakes, not a positioning story. Your differentiation is their weakness as expressed in customer complaints.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
