<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="competitor-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for competitor-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Analysing only direct competitors and omitting indirect and future types.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Indirect competitors are what customers actually use today; future competitors are the real threat in 18 months. Missing both produces a false sense of whitespace.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Surface-level analysis limited to homepage copy without digging into pricing pages, reviews, and feature documentation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pricing footnotes (annual lock-in, seat minimums, transaction fees) and 1-star review themes contain more actionable signal than marketing copy.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>One-time analysis with no refresh schedule.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A competitor matrix is stale within 60-90 days. Pricing, feature flags, and team size change frequently. Schedule quarterly re-runs with the same template to produce a diff.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Copying competitors' features rather than differentiating on their weaknesses.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feature parity produces table stakes, not a positioning story. Your differentiation is their weakness as expressed in customer complaints.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Accepting funding figures, employee counts, or revenue estimates without a verified source.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without Crunchbase API access, agents invent plausible numbers. Mitigation: hard rule "if Crunchbase API unavailable, write 'unknown'—never estimate". Mark every unverified number with "(est.)".</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Accepting a pricing number without checking effective monthly cost for 1 user billed monthly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Shown price excludes annual lock-in, seat minimums, and transaction fees. Always ask "what is the effective monthly price for 1 user, billed monthly?" before accepting any pricing cell.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Trusting G2 or Capterra star ratings as objective quality signals.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Paid placement skews stars upward; incentivised reviews under-report weaknesses. Cross-check with Reddit and Hacker News sentiment before quoting any rating.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Listing 5+ future competitors with no concrete signal (job posting, acquisition, beta product).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents over-list "Google could enter here" type future competitors. Cap at 2-3 and require one concrete signal per future competitor or it inflates the threat map.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Dumping raw scrapes from 10+ competitor websites into a single synthesis prompt.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Context overflows degrade gap analysis quality. Pre-summarise each competitor to the snapshot template (one Task call per competitor), then synthesise the summaries in a final pass.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
