<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-gotchas" title="Competitor Analysis Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Critical agent failure modes: hallucinated numbers, pricing-page footnotes, geography drift, context overflow on 10+ competitors.</summary>

  <section title="Data Fabrication">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Accepting funding figures, employee counts, or revenue estimates without a verified source.</description>
      <reason>Without Crunchbase API access, agents invent plausible numbers. Mitigation: hard rule "if Crunchbase API unavailable, write 'unknown' — never estimate". Mark every unverified number with "(est.)".</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Accepting a pricing number without checking effective monthly cost for 1 user billed monthly.</description>
      <reason>Shown price excludes annual lock-in, seat minimums, and transaction fees. Always ask "what is the effective monthly price for 1 user, billed monthly?" before accepting any pricing cell.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Trusting G2 or Capterra star ratings as objective quality signals.</description>
      <reason>Paid placement skews stars upward; incentivised reviews under-report weaknesses. Cross-check with Reddit and Hacker News sentiment before quoting any rating.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Scope and Geography">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Listing 5+ future competitors with no concrete signal (job posting, acquisition, beta product).</description>
      <reason>Agents over-list "Google could enter here" type future competitors. Cap at 2-3 and require one concrete signal per future competitor or it inflates the threat map.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin target geography in every prompt and reject any competitor whose primary market differs from your target region.</statement>
      <rationale>Without geography pinning, agents return competitors ranked by Google's global SERP, which skews toward US companies even when the user's market is EU or APAC.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Context Management">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Dumping raw scrapes from 10+ competitor websites into a single synthesis prompt.</description>
      <reason>Context overflows degrade gap analysis quality. Pre-summarise each competitor to the snapshot template (one Task call per competitor), then synthesise the summaries in a final pass.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run per-competitor snapshot tasks in parallel, synthesis serially. Cuts wall-clock by 5-8x and isolates per-competitor context windows.</statement>
      <rationale>Each competitor's pricing page, review scrape, and feature list is independent. Parallelising collection then serialising synthesis is the only pattern that scales beyond 5 competitors without context degradation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-the-Loop Checkpoints">
    <list>
      <item>Approve the seed competitor list before deep dives — agents over-index on Google's first page and miss "what my friend uses".</item>
      <item>Review per-competitor snapshots for hallucinated facts before the gap analysis runs.</item>
      <item>Sign off on the differentiation statement before it lands in marketing copy.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
