<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GovTech FOIA / Records-Retention BA Pack Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every GovTech FOIA / Records-Retention BA Pack application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-records-retention-schedule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every data-creating feature has a documented retention schedule: classification × duration × disposal method. No 'we'll figure it out later'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Records-retention violations trigger statutory penalties; pre-launch schedule is the only safe artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-foia-export-flow" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>FOIA-eligible records have an export flow specified at design time: format, redaction process, response SLA per jurisdiction.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Post-launch FOIA requests cost 5-10× to satisfy when export was not designed; design-time prep is mandatory.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-wcag-aa-minimum" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>WCAG 2.1/2.2 AA is the floor (US Section 508, EU EN 301 549, UK PSBAR). Test with axe + manual screen-reader + keyboard-only.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Automated tests catch 30-40% of issues; manual is required by law in most jurisdictions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-procurement-clause-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Read procurement contract clauses BEFORE design: data-residency, sub-processors, audit rights, IP ownership, FedRAMP/ATO requirements where applicable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Public procurement contracts often have non-obvious clauses (audit-on-demand, source-code escrow); BA must flag at design time.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-public-comment-period" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicable, design assumes a public-comment period (often 30-60 days) for major changes. Build in advance.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Public-sector launches frequently delayed by un-anticipated comment periods; design-time awareness avoids surprises.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>