<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="trend-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>Identify emerging market trends using STEEP framework and weighted Trend Strength Score. Filter signal from noise to position entry at optimal adoption-curve stage with counter-signal critic.</summary>
    <category>research</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>trend-analysis</tag>
      <tag>market-research</tag>
      <tag>competitive-intelligence</tag>
      <tag>market-timing</tag>
      <tag>adoption-curve</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Trend Analysis</title>
    <summary>A systematic pipeline for identifying and evaluating emerging market trends before acting on them. Uses the STEEP framework (Social/Technology/Economic/Environmental/Political) and a weighted 5-criterion Trend Strength Score to filter signal from noise and position entry at the optimal adoption-curve stage.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Entrepreneurs either chase every trend (shiny-object syndrome) or ignore trends completely. Without a structured scoring method — with a counter-signal critic and a mandatory two-week sanity gap — agents default to "pursue" on every trend and invent supporting numbers. The fan-out/fan-in pipeline grounds every evidence row in a cited source URL.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-niche selection: deciding if a vertical has tailwind before committing 6+ months.</item>
        <item>Quarterly portfolio review: re-scoring active bets against fresh signals.</item>
        <item>New-product wedge hunting: pairing STEEP output with personal-fit filter.</item>
        <item>Competitor threat scan: detecting stage shifts (early → mainstream → decline).</item>
        <item>Content/SEO planning: catching search-term inflection before incumbents arrive.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Sub-week tactical decisions (today's content topic, a single ad creative).</item>
        <item>Validating an already-paying problem — customer interviews beat trend extraction here.</item>
        <item>Deeply local B2B niches where no public signal source exists (Trends/HN/PH all blank).</item>
        <item>When you already have product-market fit — trend-hopping is the failure mode this warns against.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="trend-types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Classify every trend as Fad (weeks-months), Trend (2-5 years), Megatrend (decades), or Shift (permanent) before scoring it — solopreneur sweet spot is the Trend category.</statement>
        <rationale>Fads do not sustain a business. Megatrends and Shifts are too broad to carve a defensible niche quickly. 2-5 year trends offer the largest opportunity window relative to required investment.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Fad: weeks to months (fidget spinners, NFT art)</item>
        <item>Trend: 2-5 years (remote work tooling, no-code platforms)</item>
        <item>Megatrend: decades (aging population, climate adaptation)</item>
        <item>Shift: permanent (internet adoption, mobile-first)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="lifecycle-and-timing">
      <rule>
        <statement>Enter just before mainstream adoption — after the Early Adopter stage confirms demand but before incumbents have locked distribution.</statement>
        <rationale>Innovator stage: too early, no market. Late mainstream: commoditization and shrinking margins. The Early-to-Mainstream inflection is where CAC is still low and pricing power exists.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Innovator: define category — risk: too early, no market</item>
        <item>Early adopter: high margins — risk: must educate the market</item>
        <item>Early mainstream: growth — risk: competition increasing (optimal entry point)</item>
        <item>Late mainstream: volume — risk: commoditization</item>
        <item>Decline: niche/legacy — risk: shrinking market</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="steep-framework">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply the STEEP framework (Social, Technology, Economic, Environmental, Political) to every trend before scoring; accept "n/a" for irrelevant dimensions rather than padding.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents fill all five STEEP cells even when Environmental is irrelevant — forcing irrelevant cells produces noise that inflates the score. Explicit "n/a" is honest and faster to audit.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Social: How are behaviors and values changing? Which demographics are shifting?</item>
        <item>Technology: What new tech enables this trend? What capabilities became cheap enough?</item>
        <item>Economic: What financial forces drive it? What cost arbitrages exist?</item>
        <item>Environmental: How does sustainability affect adoption? Are there regulatory tailwinds?</item>
        <item>Political: What regulations impact it? Which governments are accelerating or blocking?</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="trend-strength-score">
      <rule>
        <statement>Compute the weighted Trend Strength Score (growth rate 25%, adoption stage 20%, incumbent count 15%, investment activity 20%, personal fit 20%) before the counter-signal critic runs; treat any score above 4.0 as requiring an adversarial review pass.</statement>
        <rationale>Bullish-only pipelines recommend "pursue" on every trend. A high score without a counter-signal critic is a confirmation bias loop.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>AI Agents trend scored in 2024: Google Trends +500% in 6 months (growth 5/5), Early mainstream stage (stage 4/5), 50+ incumbents (incumbents 2/5), $2B+ funding (investment 5/5), personal fit varies by team (fit 3/5). Weighted total: 4.1/5 — triggers adversarial review.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Accepting a 5/5 score on all criteria without a single cited source URL — the rubric becomes a self-reinforcing fantasy, not a decision tool.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="technology-signals">
      <list>
        <item>Hacker News (Algolia API): developer sentiment and new-tool discussion — free, no key, 30-day window</item>
        <item>Product Hunt (GraphQL API): new products and category emergence — free tier available</item>
        <item>GitHub (REST API): star velocity as adoption proxy — filter by created date, sort by stars</item>
        <item>arXiv (pip install arxiv): paper counts as research-momentum signal — category + date filter</item>
        <item>VC blogs (RSS): investment thesis patterns — lagging but high-signal (a16z Big Ideas, etc.)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use GitHub star velocity (new repos in last 180 days + top star count) as an early technology-trend signal, not absolute star count.</statement>
        <rationale>Absolute star count rewards incumbents. Star velocity captures acceleration — the signal that matters for timing entry.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="market-signals">
      <list>
        <item>Google Trends (pytrends): search interest over time — smoothed on low-volume terms, splits on term renames</item>
        <item>Exploding Topics: curated emerging topics with growth rate — good seed source, Pro plan has API</item>
        <item>Crunchbase / PitchBook: funding velocity — paid API, hard gate if key missing (fail loudly)</item>
        <item>LinkedIn Jobs / Indeed: skill keyword volume — hiring volume is strongest lagging-validation signal</item>
        <item>Gartner Hype Cycle / Forrester: authoritative for B2B but lag inflection by 12-18 months</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Score deltas, not absolutes: last-month vs this-month change in HN hits / star velocity beats raw counts.</statement>
        <rationale>Absolute counts reward historical incumbents. Month-over-month deltas surface accelerating momentum regardless of baseline.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="consumer-signals">
      <list>
        <item>Reddit (PRAW): subreddit subscriber growth and post velocity — free API, strong for validating intensity</item>
        <item>TikTok Creative Center: emerging consumer behaviors — limited API, scrape with care</item>
        <item>Amazon bestsellers: product category shifts — no API, manual or Playwright scrape</item>
        <item>App Store rankings: category leader emergence — Apptopia/Sensor Tower API for trend data</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="source-limitations">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Letting the agent pick its own sources for numeric evidence.</description>
        <reason>Unconstrained source selection collapses to "search Google, cite first SEO-spam page". Pin the allow-list of authoritative sources in the system prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using Google Trends on a low-volume term without checking if the term was recently renamed.</description>
        <reason>"AI agent" and "agentic AI" split the trend curve. Synonym-merge before scoring to avoid treating the same trend as two different signals.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating a single viral HN or Reddit thread as a trend confirmation.</description>
        <reason>Require >= 3 independent sources before stage-promoting a trend. One viral post is a data point, not a trend.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="pipeline-architecture">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run trend analysis as a fan-out/fan-in pipeline: one orchestrator dispatches per-source collectors in parallel; a synthesizer normalizes them into STEEP and Trend-Strength tables; a counter-signal critic runs before the recommendation is written.</statement>
        <rationale>Serial collection is slow. The counter-signal critic is non-negotiable — a bullish-only pipeline will recommend "pursue" on every trend regardless of underlying strength.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>faion-market-researcher-agent: orchestrator, owns STEEP + scoring rubric and final report</item>
        <item>web-search-collector (Haiku): runs WebSearch/WebFetch against signal sources, returns JSON rows only — no reasoning</item>
        <item>data-quantifier (Sonnet): converts raw source dumps into Google Trends deltas, GitHub star-velocity, funding totals</item>
        <item>counter-signal-critic (Sonnet): adversarial agent — searches for cooling indicators, failed precedents, regulatory blockers</item>
        <item>personal-fit-scorer (Haiku): applies the user's skill/audience/interest filter from a memory file</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Orchestrator prompt — strict JSON schema with source_url required field:</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are the trend-analysis orchestrator. Analyze trend "{TREND}".
Output ONLY this JSON schema:
{
  "trend": "...",
  "category": "fad|trend|megatrend|shift",
  "stage": "innovator|early|mainstream|decline",
  "evidence": [{"metric":"","value":"","yoy":"","source_url":""}],
  "steep": {"social":"","tech":"","econ":"","env":"","political":""},
  "score": {"growth":1-5,"stage":1-5,"incumbents":1-5,"investment":1-5,"fit":1-5,"weighted_total":0-5},
  "counter_signals": ["..."],
  "recommendation": "pursue|monitor|skip",
  "next_review": "YYYY-MM-DD"
}
Rules: every numeric field MUST cite source_url. If unknown, write "unknown" — never estimate.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Counter-signal critic prompt — adversarial, returns 3-7 bullets with source URLs:</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are the counter-signal critic. Given trend "{TREND}" and the prior bullish report,
search for: (a) declining adjacent metrics, (b) regulatory threats,
(c) prior cycle failures with same shape, (d) incumbent moats that prevent entry.
Return 3-7 bullets, each with a source URL.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run trend analysis monthly on a recurring cadence — first run alone is near-useless. Trend strength is read from the slope across runs.</statement>
        <rationale>A single snapshot cannot distinguish a spike from a trend. Monthly deltas reveal acceleration or cooling. First-run data is baseline only.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply the personal-fit filter before scoring, not after. Filter 100 trends to 10 by fit, then score the 10.</statement>
        <rationale>Scoring 100 trends and rejecting on fit at the end wastes 90% of scoring compute and tempts the agent to recommend fit-mismatched trends anyway.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Enforce a two-week sanity gap — never act on a trend the same session it was discovered. Log it, re-evaluate on the next dashboard run.</statement>
        <rationale>Recency bias causes immediate action on trends that cool within 2 weeks. The gap filters ephemeral spikes from sustained signals.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Anchor every number to a URL. Reject unsourced rows from agent output — this kills the #1 hallucination class.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs invent CAGRs and funding totals with full confidence. Force JSON schema with source_url required; reject rows without it.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep a kill-list memory. Trends marked "skip" with reason persist across sessions, so the orchestrator does not re-recommend them.</statement>
        <rationale>Without memory, the pipeline surfaces the same dismissed trends monthly, wasting compute and user attention.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Collapse near-duplicate terms before scoring. "AI agent", "agentic AI", "AI agents" point at the same trend — synonym-merge.</statement>
        <rationale>Without merging, the same trend fragments across multiple signal sources, inflating the apparent breadth of supporting evidence.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Numeric hallucination: LLMs invent CAGRs and funding totals. Force JSON schema with source_url required; reject rows without it.</item>
        <item>Stale training data: model reports 2023 funding rounds as current. Always wire WebSearch/WebFetch and check current_date against returned URLs.</item>
        <item>STEEP padding: agents fill all five cells even when Environmental is irrelevant. Accept "n/a" as valid.</item>
        <item>Recommendation drift toward "pursue": default LLM tone is optimistic. Counter-agent + forced skip budget (reject &gt;= 40% of trends per run) counteract this.</item>
        <item>Date-window mismatch: one source returns 30-day, another YoY. Normalize windows in the collector layer.</item>
        <item>Token blowup: never paste full HTML/JSON into the synthesizer — collectors must return &lt;= 20-row distilled records.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="failures-and-limitations">
      <p>Survivorship bias in sources: HN/PH/Crunchbase over-index on dev-tooling and SF-flavored startups; consumer-physical and emerging-market trends barely register.</p>
      <p>Lagging signal mistaken for leading: Gartner Hype Cycle and McKinsey reports trail the actual inflection by 12-18 months.</p>
      <p>Google Trends noise: Tiny-volume terms get smoothed to zero; new terms have no historical baseline; a term rename (e.g., "AI agent" vs "agentic AI") splits the curve.</p>
      <p>STEEP scoring is subjective: Two analysts score the same trend 3.0 and 4.5 — without rubric anchors, the framework becomes self-reinforcing.</p>
      <p>Counter-trend blindness: The framework rewards "X is rising" but rarely surfaces "Y collapsed adjacent to X" (e.g., crypto winter killing Web3 dev tools).</p>
      <p>LLM hallucinated stats: When agents answer "what is the CAGR of X?" without grounding, they confidently invent numbers — every figure must be source-anchored.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/trend-report.md" purpose="Trend Analysis Report: summary, evidence table, STEEP, competitive landscape, recommendation"/>
      <template path="templates/trend-signals.py" purpose="Multi-source collector: Google Trends (pytrends), HN Algolia, GitHub repo search"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://trends.google.com/trends/"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/GeneralMills/pytrends"/>
      <link href="https://www.producthunt.com/api"/>
      <link href="https://hn.algolia.com/api"/>
      <link href="https://docs.github.com/en/rest/search"/>
      <link href="https://explodingtopics.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.cbinsights.com/research/"/>
      <link href="https://a16z.com/big-ideas/"/>
      <link href="https://www.gartner.com/en/research/methodologies/gartner-hype-cycle"/>
      <link href="https://www.crunchbase.com/api"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
