<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-patterns" title="Core Compose Patterns">
  <summary>Essential Docker Compose patterns for production: no version field, health checks on every service, depends_on with service_healthy condition, resource limits, and restart policies.</summary>

  <section title="Modern Compose File">
    <rule>
      <statement>Omit the version: field entirely. Name the file compose.yaml (not docker-compose.yml). Use the docker compose CLI (not docker-compose). Pin image tags to specific versions, never latest.</statement>
      <rationale>The version: field is obsolete in Compose v2 and triggers deprecation warnings. compose.yaml is the canonical modern filename. Unpinned latest tags cause silent breaking changes on docker compose pull.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using version: "3.9" at the top of compose.yaml and naming the file docker-compose.yml.</description>
      <reason>Both are legacy patterns. version: is ignored by modern Compose and adds confusion about which features are available.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Health Checks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define a healthcheck on every service. Use depends_on with condition: service_healthy (not service_started). Set start_period generously — at least 60s for databases on first boot when no volume exists yet.</statement>
      <rationale>Without health checks, depends_on: service_started only waits for the container process to start, not for the service to be ready. The app will connect to the database before it accepts connections, causing startup failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
services:
  db:
    image: postgres:16-alpine
    healthcheck:
      test: ["CMD-SHELL", "pg_isready -U $POSTGRES_USER -d $POSTGRES_DB"]
      interval: 10s
      timeout: 5s
      retries: 5
      start_period: 60s

  app:
    depends_on:
      db:
        condition: service_healthy
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Resource Limits">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set deploy.resources.limits for every service from day one. Without limits, a single runaway container can exhaust all host memory, killing all other services. Resource limits require cgroups v2 (verify with: docker info | grep "Cgroup Driver").</statement>
      <rationale>A container with no memory limit will use all available host RAM before the OOM killer terminates it, taking down other containers in the process.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
services:
  app:
    deploy:
      resources:
        limits:
          cpus: "1.0"
          memory: 512M
          pids: 100
        reservations:
          cpus: "0.25"
          memory: 128M
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Restart Policies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use restart: unless-stopped for long-running services (not always). always restarts even during intentional maintenance stops. Use restart: "no" for one-shot init containers.</statement>
      <rationale>unless-stopped allows graceful maintenance without constant restart loops. A service stopped with docker compose stop stays stopped, unlike always which restarts it immediately.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Destructive Operations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running docker compose down -v in production or without explicit confirmation.</description>
      <reason>The -v flag deletes all named volumes including database data. This is irreversible. Agents must never run this command against production without explicit operator confirmation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
