<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-networking" title="Compose Networking">
  <summary>Custom bridge networks for container isolation, internal: true for database tiers that must not reach the internet, service discovery by service name, and network project naming to avoid cross-project collisions.</summary>

  <section title="Custom Networks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define custom named networks instead of using the default bridge. Mark database networks as internal: true to prevent containers on that network from making outbound internet connections.</statement>
      <rationale>The default bridge network gives every container network access and puts all containers on the same flat network. Custom networks enforce tier separation (frontend, backend, database) and prevent database containers from making outbound connections.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
networks:
  frontend:
    driver: bridge
  backend:
    driver: bridge
  db-network:
    driver: bridge
    internal: true  # No outbound internet access

services:
  nginx:
    networks: [frontend]
  app:
    networks: [frontend, backend]
  db:
    networks: [db-network, backend]
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Service Discovery">
    <rule>
      <statement>Services reach each other by service name as hostname. Use service names in connection strings: postgres://db:5432/app, redis://redis:6379/0. Never use container IP addresses — they change on restart.</statement>
      <rationale>Docker Compose creates DNS entries for each service on shared networks. Service names are stable across restarts; IP addresses are not.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Project Name Collisions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set COMPOSE_PROJECT_NAME in the .env file or use the -p flag when running docker compose to give each project a unique name. Without it, two projects with the same service names create network name conflicts.</statement>
      <rationale>Compose uses the directory name as the default project name. Two projects in directories with the same name (e.g., both named "app") will create conflicting network names.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
