<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="regulatory-compliance-2026">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>Accessibility law matrix 2026: ADA Title II (US April 2026), EAA (EU June 2025/2030), Section 508, AODA, UK/AU. Deadlines, WCAG standards, VPAT, enforcement, exemptions.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>regulatory</tag>
      <tag>compliance</tag>
      <tag>legal</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
      <tag>wcag</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Regulatory Compliance 2026</title>
    <summary>Regional accessibility law matrix for 2026: ADA Title II (US government, April 2026 deadline), European Accessibility Act (EU e-commerce + banking, June 2025/2030), Section 508, AODA (Canada), and equivalent frameworks in the UK, Australia, and Asia-Pacific. Covers deadlines, WCAG standard mappings, documentation requirements (VPAT/ACR, accessibility statements), enforcement penalties, and exemptions.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Non-compliance risks vary by region: US ADA lawsuits average $5,000-$75,000 in settlements plus $50,000-$200,000 in legal fees; EU EAA fines reach 4% of annual revenue. Regulations differ in scope, standard version (WCAG 2.0 vs 2.1 vs EN 301 549), and enforcement mechanism. A single compliance checklist does not cover all jurisdictions; organizations must identify which regulations apply and what documentation is required.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Determining which accessibility standard (WCAG 2.0/2.1/2.2, EN 301 549) applies to a given product and jurisdiction.</item>
        <item>Writing or auditing accessibility statements, VPATs, and ACRs.</item>
        <item>Setting up ongoing monitoring, training, and procurement standards for ADA/EAA compliance.</item>
        <item>Assessing risk before a product launch in a new region.</item>
        <item>Responding to a DOJ complaint or EU enforcement action.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Technical WCAG implementation — use `wcag-22-compliance` or `a11y-testing`.</item>
        <item>AT runtime testing — use `testing-with-assistive-technology`.</item>
        <item>XR/spatial products — apply WCAG + W3C XAUR; no dedicated regulation yet.</item>
        <item>Internal-only tooling with no public-facing interface — most regulations apply to public-facing services only.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="united-states">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>US government entities must comply with ADA Title II at WCAG 2.1 AA by April 24, 2026 (large entities, 50K+ population) or April 24, 2027 (smaller entities).</statement>
        <rationale>DOJ final rule published March 2024. Non-compliance exposes state/local agencies to DOJ investigation, private lawsuits, and loss of federal funding.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="US regulation matrix">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Regulation         | Scope                              | Deadline         | Standard         | Enforcement
ADA Title II (DOJ) | State/local government              | Apr 2026 (large) | WCAG 2.1 AA      | DOJ + lawsuits
ADA Title III      | Private businesses (courts)         | Ongoing          | WCAG 2.0/2.1 AA  | Private lawsuits
Section 508        | Federal agencies                    | Now              | WCAG 2.0 AA      | Agency oversight
CVAA               | Video, communications               | Now              | WCAG 2.0 AA      | FCC
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="european-union">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>EAA requires WCAG 2.1 AA (via EN 301 549) for new e-commerce, banking, transport, and e-book products from June 28, 2025; existing products have until June 28, 2030.</statement>
        <rationale>EU member states set their own enforcement; fines up to 4% of annual revenue. Web Accessibility Directive already applies to all public-sector websites.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="EU regulation matrix">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Regulation                   | Scope                                    | Deadline              | Standard
EAA                          | E-commerce, banking, transport, e-books  | Jun 2025 (new)        | EN 301 549 (~WCAG 2.1 AA)
                             |                                          | Jun 2030 (existing)   |
Web Accessibility Directive  | Public-sector websites and apps          | Now                   | EN 301 549
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <p>EAA explicitly covers: e-commerce websites, banking services (ATMs, web, mobile), electronic communications, transport (ticketing, apps), e-books, and consumer-facing services.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="canada-uk-australia-apac">
      <example type="good" title="Global regulation matrix">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Jurisdiction | Regulation                    | Standard        | Status
Canada (ON)  | AODA                          | WCAG 2.0 AA     | Now
Canada (Fed) | ACA                           | WCAG 2.1 AA     | Now / 2025
UK           | Equality Act 2010             | WCAG 2.1 AA*    | Now (*recommended)
UK (public)  | Public Sector Bodies Regs     | WCAG 2.1 AA     | Now
Australia    | Disability Discrimination Act | WCAG 2.1 AA     | Now (recommended)
Japan        | JIS X 8341-3                  | WCAG 2.0 based  | Now
Israel       | IS 5568                       | WCAG 2.0 AA     | Now
Brazil       | e-MAG                         | WCAG 2.0 based  | Now
India        | GIGW                          | WCAG 2.0+       | Government sites
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="accessibility-statement">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every public-facing product must publish an accessibility statement that includes conformance level, known limitations, contact information, and the date of the last review.</statement>
        <rationale>Required by ADA Title II (DOJ rule), EU Web Accessibility Directive, and EAA. The statement is the primary compliance evidence regulators and plaintiffs request first.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Conformance level stated (e.g., "Partially conformant with WCAG 2.1 Level AA").</item>
        <item>Known limitations listed — vague "ongoing effort" language is not sufficient.</item>
        <item>Contact mechanism for accessibility issues (email, phone, or form).</item>
        <item>Date of last statement update.</item>
        <item>Feedback/complaint process described.</item>
        <item>Alternative access methods noted if applicable.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="vpat-acr">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Produce a Voluntary Product Accessibility Template (VPAT) — also called an Accessibility Conformance Report (ACR) — for every product used in government or enterprise procurement; update annually or after major changes.</statement>
        <rationale>US Section 508 and ADA Title II procurement standards require VPAT evidence. EU public sector procurement increasingly requires EN 301 549 ACRs. Without one, vendors are excluded from bids.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>All WCAG criteria addressed (pass / partial / not supported / not applicable).</item>
        <item>Evidence of conformance cited per criterion.</item>
        <item>Known issues documented with remediation timeline.</item>
        <item>Updated annually or on major version changes.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="accessibility-policy">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Organizations must maintain an internal accessibility policy documenting organizational commitment, responsible parties, testing cadence, training requirements, and procurement standards.</statement>
        <rationale>DOJ consent decrees and EU member state enforcement demand evidence of systemic process, not one-off fixes. Policy is the paper trail that proves ongoing effort.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Responsible parties identified (owner, team).</item>
        <item>Testing cadence: automated CI, quarterly manual audits, annual comprehensive audit.</item>
        <item>Training requirements per role (dev, designer, content, procurement).</item>
        <item>Procurement standards — VPAT required from all software/service vendors.</item>
        <item>Complaint and escalation process.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="enforcement-united-states">
      <example type="bad" title="US enforcement and penalties">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Consequence                      | Typical Range
Private lawsuit settlement       | $5,000 - $75,000+
Legal fees (plaintiff)           | $50,000 - $200,000+
Consent decree + monitoring      | Multi-year compliance program
DOJ investigation                | Reputational + remediation cost
Loss of federal funding          | For government entities
        ]]></code>
        <note>Thousands of ADA web lawsuits filed annually. Serial plaintiffs target e-commerce, banking, and healthcare.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="enforcement-european-union">
      <example type="bad" title="EU enforcement and penalties">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Consequence                          | Notes
Fine up to 4% of annual revenue      | Per member state enforcement
Product withdrawal from market       | If non-conformant after deadline
Prohibition of services              | Regulator order
Compensation to affected individuals | Civil action
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="enforcement-other-jurisdictions">
      <list>
        <item>Canada: Complaints to CRTC or provincial accessibility commissioners.</item>
        <item>UK: Unlawful discrimination claims under Equality Act 2010.</item>
        <item>Australia: Complaints to Australian Human Rights Commission.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="valid-exemptions">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Exemptions are narrow, must be individually documented, and always require an accessible alternative to be provided.</statement>
        <rationale>Regulators and courts reject blanket exemptions. Each exemption needs a written justification, scope limitation, and alternative access path.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-existing content — content published before the compliance deadline and not subsequently altered.</item>
        <item>Archived content — clearly marked as archived, not updated, not relied on for active services.</item>
        <item>Third-party content not under organizational control — must still provide an accessible alternative.</item>
        <item>Undue burden — must document why compliance is an undue financial or administrative burden AND provide an alternative.</item>
        <item>Fundamental alteration — compliance would change the fundamental nature of the service; must be documented and alternative provided.</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Claiming "undue burden" without a documented cost analysis and alternative access plan.</description>
        <reason>Courts and regulators reject undocumented exemptions; the burden of proof is on the organization claiming the exemption.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Aim at WCAG 2.2 AA now even though regulation cites 2.1 — minimal cost to over-deliver, easier to defend.</item>
        <item>Publish the Accessibility Statement at a stable URL (`/accessibility`); link from footer on every page.</item>
        <item>Treat VPAT-ACR as a living document, refresh on major releases or annually whichever is sooner.</item>
        <item>Keep evidence-of-conformance: dated test reports, AT logs, user-test recordings (with consent) — discoverable in lawsuit.</item>
        <item>Insert accessibility into procurement: VPAT required, remediation timelines in contract, audit rights.</item>
        <item>Train every developer + designer + content owner annually; track completion (regulators ask).</item>
        <item>When a complaint arrives, respond inside 48 hours with substantive engagement — settlement leverage rests on response history.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agents drive the *paperwork* — accessibility statements, VPAT-ACR drafts, procurement-clause libraries, training-tracking spreadsheets, and quarterly-audit calendars — and a regulatory-compliance triage that maps a product's markets to a deadline matrix. They do **not** make compliance determinations; final sign-off is legal counsel + accessibility lead. Pair with `wcag-22-compliance` for the technical criteria checklist and `testing-with-assistive-technology` for evidence-of-conformance.</p>
      <p>Regulatory landscape changes mid-year — DOJ rule clarifications, EAA member-state transpositions, new state laws (CA AB 1757, NY S6047). The README's table can drift; agents must verify dates from primary sources before use. "WCAG 2.1 AA" is the floor in most rules, but some courts apply WCAG 2.2 by default — under-specifying a deliverable target invites trouble. Exemptions (undue burden, fundamental alteration, archived content) are narrow and fact-specific; agents over-claim them. US ADA Title III still has no formal regulation for private businesses; case law (Robles v. Domino's) governs — agents cannot reason from rules alone. Procurement clauses must be mirror-tight; LLM-drafted contract language without legal review is a liability.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <list>
        <item>`vpat-tools` (community) — Markdown ↔ VPAT 2.5 templates.</item>
        <item>`axe-core` + `pa11y-ci` — Generate evidence-of-conformance test reports.</item>
        <item>`lighthouse-ci` — Accessibility scores attached to PR + budgets.</item>
        <item>Pandoc + Word/PDF templates — Render Accessibility Statement / VPAT to required formats.</item>
        <item>OPA (Open Policy Agent) — Encode procurement / accessibility policy as code.</item>
        <item>GitHub Actions / GitLab CI — Wire continuous a11y monitoring evidence.</item>
        <item>Deque axe Auditor / Manage (SaaS) — Tracks remediation against WCAG / EN 301 549.</item>
        <item>SiteImprove (SaaS) — Enterprise compliance crawl + reporting.</item>
        <item>Level Access (SaaS + services) — Managed compliance program; agents draft for counsel review.</item>
        <item>TPGi ARC / JAWS Inspect (SaaS) — JAWS-led testing evidence.</item>
        <item>Fable Tech Labs (SaaS) — Real-user evidence for VPAT remarks.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Agents conflate ADA Title II (public sector) and Title III (private) — keep them separate.</item>
        <item>LLMs cite outdated standards (WCAG 2.0 AA) by training-data inertia; force WCAG 2.2 AA in every prompt.</item>
        <item>Generated VPAT remarks tend to overstate conformance — require "Partially Supports" / "Does Not Support" justifications grounded in tests.</item>
        <item>Exemption claims (undue burden, fundamental alteration) get inserted casually; force agents to cite the specific § and provide rationale.</item>
        <item>Region coverage drifts (Quebec law differs from federal Canada; CA AB 1757 specifics; Texas HB 4090) — agents miss state/provincial nuance.</item>
        <item>Penalty figures are quoted as gospel ($75,000 first offense, $150,000 subsequent for ADA) — those are DOJ ranges, not damages from private suits; agents conflate.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoints: every published Accessibility Statement, every VPAT shipped to a customer, every procurement clause, every response to a complaint or demand letter.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/accessibility-statement.txt" purpose="Accessibility statement template covering conformance status, known limitations, contact, and date."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.ada.gov/resources/2024-03-08-web-rule/"/>
      <link href="https://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=1202"/>
      <link href="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_en/301500_301599/301549/"/>
      <link href="https://www.section508.gov/"/>
      <link href="https://www.itic.org/policy/accessibility/vpat"/>
      <link href="https://webaim.org/articles/laws/"/>
      <link href="https://accessibilitycanada.ca/"/>
      <link href="https://www.gov.uk/guidance/accessibility-requirements-for-public-sector-websites-and-apps"/>
      <ref slug="wcag-22-compliance"/>
      <ref slug="a11y-testing"/>
      <ref slug="testing-with-assistive-technology"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
