<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Launch RACI Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Launch RACI Template methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="one-accountable-per-row" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each workstream row MUST have exactly one Accountable (A); rows with zero or multiple A entries are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI canonical practice (PMBOK 7, BABOK 3)">multiple A's mean nobody is accountable in practice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r-and-a-may-overlap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Responsible (R) and Accountable (A) MAY be the same person; rows where R is empty are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI canonical practice">R-empty means 'nobody is doing the work', which is the failure mode RACI exists to prevent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-per-assignment" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every named assignment MUST cite the source (engagement charter, role-card, prior-launch retro); un-sourced names are flagged 'verify-before-launch'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion launch retros 2026-Q1">names dragged in by the agent without source are the #1 cause of 'I never agreed to that' on launch day.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="workstreams-cover-pre-day-post" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Workstream list MUST cover pre-launch (T-14 to T-1), launch-day (T0), and post-launch (T+1 to T+14) phases; RACIs that stop at T0 are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Launch-retro pattern bank">most launch failures happen post-T0 and have no owner because RACI stopped at the launch event.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="consulted-and-informed-distinct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Consulted (C) implies two-way dialogue before action; Informed (I) implies one-way after action; mixing them is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI canonical practice">C/I conflation degrades the artefact into a contact list and the lead loses signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rehearsal-validates-raci" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>At least one launch rehearsal MUST validate the RACI end-to-end before T0; rehearsal findings update the RACI in writing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — launch rehearsals retros">RACIs that haven't been rehearsed have a high defect rate at first contact with launch reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
