<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-overview" title="Overview and core principle">
  <summary>Brainstorm orchestrates a diverge-converge-review loop with N=10 research subagents, a single synthesis pass, and M=8 adversarial reviewers. The orchestrator owns phase selection, parallelism, consent gating, and final tier assembly; subagents do all generation and critique behind versioned prompt files.</summary>

  <section title="Core principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Multi-agent diverge-converge-review beats a single-pass ideation answer when the user wants a prioritized, reviewer-validated list of recommendations.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-pass ideation anchors on the first plausible answer the model sees. Distinct personas in independent generation spread the search; consensus counting separates signal from noise; adversarial review prevents rubber-stamping. Empirical anchors: MultiColleagues (ECIS 2025), A-MEM (arXiv 2502.12110), IBIS-based brainstorming (ACM 2024), Six Thinking Hats, Brainwriting.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Research agents MUST be launched in parallel with distinct personas and identical output schema, never with the same prompt repeated N times.</statement>
      <rationale>Identical prompts collapse N agents into one — the diversity that justifies the cost vanishes. Distinct personas (by domain, lens, or Six Thinking Hats role) force independent search paths.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Role split">
    <p>The orchestrator does five things only: gate on user consent (Phase 0), pick the persona assignment strategy, dispatch waves of subagents respecting the parallel limit, run the synthesis pass between phases, and assemble the final tiered output. Generation and critique live entirely in subagents.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Orchestrator: consent gate, persona assignment, wave dispatch, parallelism cap, synthesis, tier assembly.</item>
      <item>Research subagents (10): independent diverge-phase generators, distinct personas, exactly 30 recommendations each in `state -&gt; problem -&gt; solution -&gt; impact` shape.</item>
      <item>Reviewer subagents (8): adversarial critique, each assigned a single attack vector (feasibility, security, architecture, DX, cost-benefit, missing perspectives, domain depth, prioritization synthesis).</item>
      <item>Synthesis pass: deduplicate clusters, count consensus across research agents, rank by impact, emit priority tiers.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Language convention">
    <rule>
      <statement>User-facing strings (consent-gate AskUserQuestion payload, final summary captions) use Ukrainian. Code, prompt files, persona descriptions, reviewer attack vectors, and intermediate artifacts use English.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixed-language prompts degrade subagent reliability; the user-facing surface stays Ukrainian for politeness. Token cost: English internals save ~30% over Ukrainian.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Reference anchors">
    <reference path="../../../../../.aidocs/conventions/workflows/workflow-spec.md">Authoritative workflow spec — phase quad-block, idempotency, output contract.</reference>
    <reference path="../sdd-batch-orchestrator/">Reference workflow implementation that brainstorm output frequently feeds into (plan-phase ideation).</reference>
  </section>
</text>
