<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-personas" title="Persona assignment for research agents">
  <summary>Distinct personas are the entire point of the diverge phase. The orchestrator picks one of three assignment strategies (by domain, by Six Thinking Hats, or by lens) and assigns each of the 10 research agents a unique persona drawn from that strategy. Mixing strategies in a single brainstorm is allowed only when the task spans &gt;1 axis (e.g. cost-optimization audit needs both domain and lens coverage).</summary>

  <section title="Why distinct personas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every research agent MUST receive a persona unique within its brainstorm.</statement>
      <rationale>Identical personas collapse 10 agents into 1: the recommendations are nearly identical, consensus counting becomes meaningless, and the cost of running 10 agents buys nothing over running one. Distinct personas force independent search paths and yield the diversity that the synthesis pass actually has signal to extract.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>The persona MUST be specific enough to bias the agent's search, not generic (&quot;senior engineer&quot; is generic; &quot;Django ORM specialist who has debugged N+1 in production&quot; is specific).</statement>
      <rationale>Generic personas yield generic ideas. Specific personas yield ideas only that persona would think of, which is the entire point of the diverge phase.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Strategy A: by domain">
    <p>Use when the task is a technical audit, architecture exploration, or feature ideation where domain expertise drives idea quality. Assign one persona per domain, picking 10 from the relevant subset.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Frontend specialist (FE framework, component design, a11y, perf budgets).</item>
      <item>Backend specialist (API design, ORM, business-logic isolation).</item>
      <item>Infrastructure / DevOps (deploy, CI/CD, observability, cost).</item>
      <item>Security engineer (authn/authz, sec headers, secrets, threat model).</item>
      <item>UX / interaction designer (information architecture, affordance, error states).</item>
      <item>Data / ETL specialist (schema, idempotency, batch vs stream).</item>
      <item>Product manager (jobs-to-be-done, metric tree, roadmap fit).</item>
      <item>QA / test engineer (test pyramid, flake budget, coverage gaps).</item>
      <item>Cost optimizer (cloud spend, vendor lock, right-sizing).</item>
      <item>Documentation / DevEx (onboarding, internal tooling, paved paths).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Strategy B: by Six Thinking Hats">
    <p>Use when the task is decision exploration with explicit trade-offs (architecture choice, vendor selection, build vs buy). Assign personas by hat plus four extension personas to reach 10.</p>
    <list>
      <item>White hat (facts and data only — no opinions).</item>
      <item>Red hat (intuition and emotion — gut reactions).</item>
      <item>Black hat (judgment and caution — what could go wrong).</item>
      <item>Yellow hat (optimism and benefits — what could go right).</item>
      <item>Green hat (creativity and alternatives — what else is possible).</item>
      <item>Blue hat (process and meta — how to decide, not what to decide).</item>
      <item>Extension: skeptic (epistemic conservative, wants evidence).</item>
      <item>Extension: pragmatist (ship-it bias, optimizes for time-to-value).</item>
      <item>Extension: maximalist (long-term bet, optimizes for ceiling).</item>
      <item>Extension: minimalist (least-effort, optimizes for floor).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Strategy C: by lens">
    <p>Use when the task is broad improvement / &quot;what should we fix in X&quot; and stakeholder coverage matters more than domain depth. Each persona is a stakeholder lens with explicit priorities.</p>
    <list>
      <item>End user (cares about: speed, clarity, working features).</item>
      <item>Power user (cares about: keyboard shortcuts, bulk ops, escape hatches).</item>
      <item>New user (cares about: onboarding, defaults, error recovery).</item>
      <item>Solo developer (cares about: maintenance burden, debug time, toil).</item>
      <item>Future maintainer (cares about: documentation, naming, lock-in).</item>
      <item>Business owner (cares about: revenue, cost, retention, churn).</item>
      <item>Operations (cares about: SLO, on-call burden, incident MTTR).</item>
      <item>Security / compliance (cares about: data exposure, audit trail).</item>
      <item>Investor / stakeholder (cares about: growth signal, defensibility).</item>
      <item>Competitor (cares about: where you are weakest — adversarial frame).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Strategy selection">
    <p>Pick by task class:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Technical audit of an existing codebase → Strategy A (by domain).</item>
      <item>Architecture / vendor / build-vs-buy decision → Strategy B (Six Thinking Hats).</item>
      <item>Improvement plan / &quot;what should we fix&quot; / cost optimization → Strategy C (by lens).</item>
      <item>Mixed task (e.g. cost-optimization audit) → mix two strategies, keeping personas distinct across the combined set.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
