<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-reviewer-roles" title="Reviewer roles and attack vectors">
  <summary>Phase 3 launches exactly 8 reviewer subagents, each assigned one attack vector from the required list. One vector per reviewer prevents the &quot;polite generalist&quot; failure mode. Optional roles may be added when the domain warrants. Every reviewer prompt is adversarial: find what is wrong, not what is right.</summary>

  <section title="Why one vector per reviewer">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each reviewer MUST be assigned exactly one attack vector and explicitly told to ignore the other vectors.</statement>
      <rationale>A reviewer asked to evaluate everything ends up evaluating nothing — the prompt becomes &quot;is this generally good?&quot; which is rubber-stamping. A reviewer told to attack only feasibility produces a sharp, useful critique on feasibility. Coverage comes from running 8 single-vector reviewers in parallel, not from one reviewer covering 8 vectors.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Reviewer prompts MUST be adversarial in framing: &quot;find what breaks&quot;, &quot;find hidden costs&quot;, &quot;find missing perspectives&quot; — never &quot;review and confirm&quot;.</statement>
      <rationale>Adversarial framing produces actionable critique. Confirmatory framing produces &quot;LGTM&quot; comments that the synthesis pass cannot use to re-tier.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Required reviewer roles (eight vectors)">
    <list>
      <item>Feasibility &amp; Effort — looks for: unrealistic estimates, hidden dependencies, ordering violations, work that requires upstream changes the plan does not account for.</item>
      <item>Security — looks for: gaps introduced by recommendations, missing minimum-viable hardening (authn, authz, secrets, sec headers, audit log), threat-model coverage.</item>
      <item>Architecture — looks for: coherence of the recommendation set, contradictions between recs, ordering that creates throwaway work, layering violations.</item>
      <item>Solo Dev / DX — looks for: maintenance burden per rec, toil added vs removed, on-call impact, debug time cost, paved-path violations.</item>
      <item>Cost-Benefit — looks for: actual dollar impact (cloud, vendor, time), ROI rank, hidden costs (training, migration, vendor lock), recommendations whose payback is &gt;12 months.</item>
      <item>Missing Perspectives — looks for: what the diverge phase missed (user-facing features if the recs are infra-heavy, data/ETL if the recs are app-only, operations if the recs are dev-only).</item>
      <item>Domain Expert — looks for: deep-dive on the top-ranked recommendation, surfaces domain-specific risks the generalists missed, validates the proposed mechanism.</item>
      <item>Prioritization Synthesis — looks for: final ordering with all reviewer feedback integrated, explicit tier moves with rationale, devil's-advocate items the user should still see.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Optional reviewer roles">
    <p>Add when the domain warrants. Each optional role still gets exactly one attack vector. Total reviewer count may rise to 10, never above.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Accessibility — looks for: WCAG violations introduced, keyboard / screen-reader regressions.</item>
      <item>Regulatory / compliance — looks for: GDPR / HIPAA / PCI exposure, data residency, retention policy violations.</item>
      <item>Performance — looks for: latency budget violations, N+1 patterns, payload-size regressions.</item>
      <item>Internationalization — looks for: hardcoded strings, locale-specific formatting bugs, RTL breaks.</item>
      <item>Observability — looks for: metric / log / trace gaps the recommendations leave behind.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Reviewer output contract">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every reviewer MUST emit a verdict per recommendation: KEEP / DEMOTE / DROP, with one-line rationale and a tier suggestion if KEEP.</statement>
      <rationale>The Phase 4 re-tiering pass needs structured input. Free-form prose cannot drive the tier moves; per-rec verdicts can.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
