<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="05-anti-patterns" title="Anti-patterns to avoid">
  <summary>Failure modes that destroy the value of multi-agent brainstorm. Each is reject-on-sight: the orchestrator MUST detect and prevent them before launching agents.</summary>

  <section title="Diverge-phase smells">
    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT launch 10 research agents with identical prompts.</statement>
      <rationale>Identical prompts collapse 10 agents into 1. The recommendations cluster tightly, consensus counting becomes a tautology (10/10 because they all wrote the same thing), and the cost of running 10 agents buys nothing. Distinct personas are non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT use generic personas like &quot;senior engineer&quot;, &quot;experienced developer&quot;, &quot;product expert&quot;.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic personas yield generic ideas. The whole point of persona assignment is to bias the agent's search toward ideas only that persona would surface. A specific persona (&quot;Django ORM specialist who has debugged N+1 in production&quot;) produces specific ideas; a generic persona produces a bland average.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT scale agent count above 12 to &quot;get more coverage&quot;.</statement>
      <rationale>Empirical sweet spot is 10-12. Above 12, marginal coverage drops sharply while cost and synthesis-pass complexity rise linearly. More agents do not equal more signal — they equal more noise the synthesis pass has to filter.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT let research agents see each other's output during diverge.</statement>
      <rationale>Cross-pollination causes anchoring on whichever agent finishes first. Independence is the entire point of multi-agent diverge — the moment agents see each other, they converge prematurely and the converge phase has nothing left to do.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Review-phase smells">
    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT use generic review prompts like &quot;please review this document&quot; or &quot;evaluate these recommendations&quot;.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic prompts yield rubber-stamping: the reviewer reads the recommendations, finds nothing obviously wrong, and replies &quot;LGTM&quot;. The output is decorative. Adversarial framing (&quot;attack from vector X&quot;, &quot;find what breaks&quot;) produces actionable critique.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT launch reviewers that share an attack vector or perspective.</statement>
      <rationale>Two reviewers both attacking &quot;feasibility&quot; produce two near-identical critiques and leave seven other vectors uncovered. One vector per reviewer, eight required vectors covered exactly once.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT skip re-tiering in Phase 4.</statement>
      <rationale>If reviewer feedback does not change tier assignments, the review phase was decorative and the cost was wasted. Re-tiering is the artifact that makes the review load-bearing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Consent-gate smells">
    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT skip Phase 0 when the user did not explicitly request a brainstorm.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-routed brainstorm without consent burns the user's quota and trust on output they did not ask for. The orchestrator is allowed to over-trigger; Phase 0 is the safety net. Skipping Phase 0 is a contract violation, not a shortcut.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT carry &quot;Run brainstorm&quot; consent across sessions.</statement>
      <rationale>Consent is per-session. A user who approved brainstorm yesterday has not approved today's brainstorm. Re-ask.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Output smells">
    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT present a single option / single recommendation as the brainstorm output.</statement>
      <rationale>The user asked for diverge-converge precisely because they wanted alternatives. A single option discards the entire reason for running 18 agents. Always present a tiered list with explicit alternatives, even when one option is clearly preferred.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT omit the &quot;why defer&quot; rationale for backlog items.</statement>
      <rationale>The user needs to see what was rejected and why, not just what survived. Without &quot;why defer&quot;, the same idea gets re-litigated next quarter. The rationale is the artifact that prevents that.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>MUST NOT skip the self-evaluation pass at the end of Phase 4.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-evaluation (Coverage / Novelty / Actionability / Bias / User-focus) is a cheap groupthink detector. If novelty is low or bias is &quot;infrastructure-only&quot;, the persona assignment failed and the next brainstorm should adjust. Skipping the eval blinds the orchestrator to its own failure modes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
