<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Growth Referral Programs Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six testable rules grounding Growth Referral Programs. Each rule pairs a binary statement, a rationale, and a source. Decision tree branches in 06-decision-tree.xml reference these ids.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="preconditions-hold" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before running Growth Referral Programs, every item in the AGENTS.md 'Applies If' list must hold; if any fails, the methodology must be skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Dropbox / Airbnb referral case studies">Methodologies executed outside their preconditions produce plausible-looking but invalid output. Running the gate prevents wasted cycles.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="output-contract-binding" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The producing agent MUST emit an artefact validating against content/02-output-contract.xml's JSON Schema; any field outside the schema is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 content-completion design">Hard schema is the only mechanical interlock between a synthesising LLM and downstream consumers; prose contracts get reinterpreted.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every output produced by this methodology MUST name a single human owner with edit rights and a review deadline.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian — documentation governance">Orphan artefacts rot; named ownership is the only durable mechanism for keeping the artefact current.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="deviation-log" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any deviation from the canonical procedure MUST be logged with a one-line rationale and surfaced at the next retro.</statement>
      <rationale source="Deming — Out of the Crisis (PDCA)">Undocumented deviations destroy institutional memory; PDCA requires a written delta.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="human-checkpoint" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before any binding downstream action driven by this output (publish, send, rollout, commit), a named human reviewer MUST sign off.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 safety design">LLM outputs are first drafts; the human checkpoint is the safety gate against hallucinated commitments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If 'Applies If' evaluates false OR 'Skip If' evaluates true, the agent MUST NOT run Growth Referral Programs; it returns an action=skip envelope and yields control to the parent workflow.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 decision-tree contract">Explicit skip exit prevents agents from forcing the methodology into incompatible contexts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Sources">
    <reference>Dropbox / Airbnb referral case studies</reference>
    <reference>Reforge — referral mechanics</reference>
    <reference>ReferralCandy / Friendbuy — operational guides</reference>
    <reference>Anti-fraud — referral abuse patterns</reference>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
