<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-board-setup" title="Trello Board Structure and Card Anatomy">
  <summary>Core patterns for structuring Trello boards: list naming with WIP limits, card anatomy, and label system.</summary>

  <section title="Board Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep boards to 5–7 lists maximum; embed WIP limits directly in list names.</statement>
      <rationale>Visual scanning degrades beyond 7 lists; embedding WIP limits ("In Progress [WIP:3]") makes limits visible to humans and queryable by agents without a separate config file.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Basic kanban: Backlog, To Do (This Sprint), In Progress [WIP:3], In Review [WIP:2], Done</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Enhanced: Icebox, Backlog, Ready for Dev, In Development [WIP:3], Code Review [WIP:2], QA [WIP:2], Done, Archive</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using 10+ lists to model every possible state.</description>
      <reason>Board becomes unreadable; WIP limits are meaningless across too many stages.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Card Anatomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use custom fields (Story Points, Sprint) instead of encoding metadata in card titles.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents can query custom fields directly via API with customFieldItems=true; parsing metadata from titles requires fragile string matching.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>One deliverable per card; use checklists for subtasks, not separate cards.</statement>
      <rationale>Atomic cards keep WIP limits meaningful and flow metrics accurate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/card-feature.md">Feature card description template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/card-bug.md">Bug report card template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Label System">
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit labels to 8–12; use one type label per card (Feature OR Bug, not both).</statement>
      <rationale>Over-labeling creates noise; type exclusivity makes pie-chart reporting accurate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Type labels: Feature (green), Bug (red), Tech Debt (orange), Docs (purple). Priority labels: P0-Critical (red), P1-High (orange), P2-Medium (yellow), P3-Low (blue). State labels: Blocked (black), Quick Win (lime).</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Creating labels per team member or per sprint.</description>
      <reason>Labels multiply unboundedly; use custom fields for sprint and assignee metadata instead.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Fields">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define custom fields: Story Points (number), Sprint (dropdown), Estimate (dropdown: XS/S/M/L/XL), Component (dropdown), PR Link (text).</statement>
      <rationale>Custom fields enable agent queries and reporting without text parsing; dropdown fields prevent free-text variants.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
