<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-automation" title="Trello Butler Automation and Power-Ups">
  <summary>Butler rules, board buttons, essential Power-Ups, and Trello REST API patterns for automation.</summary>

  <section title="Butler Automation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Butler rules for mechanical card moves; use Butler buttons for triggered multi-step workflows that require human initiation (Start Work, Submit for Review, Archive Completed).</statement>
      <rationale>Rules run automatically and should be reserved for deterministic transitions; buttons give humans control over multi-step state changes that should not run without intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Rule: "When all checklists on a card are completed → move card to Done." Button: "Start Work → move to In Development + add me + set due date 3 working days."</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Using Butler to auto-move cards to Done based on due date passing — this archives incomplete work silently.</note>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/butler-rules.yaml">Butler automation rule and button examples</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Essential Power-Ups">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable these Power-Ups in order of value: Butler (automation), Custom Fields (metadata), Card Aging (stale detection), Calendar (due date visualization). Add GitHub and Slack only if the team actively uses both.</statement>
      <rationale>Free and Standard plans allow 1 Power-Up on free tier; prioritize automation and metadata over visualization. Card Aging surfaces stale work passively without a separate process.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Trello REST API">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always request customFieldItems=true when fetching cards that need custom field values; resolve member IDs to names via GET /1/members/{id} before producing human-readable reports.</statement>
      <rationale>The default card response omits custom field values; member IDs are UUIDs that agents must resolve to names for any report a human will read.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Archive cards via PUT /1/cards/{id}?closed=true; never delete cards.</statement>
      <rationale>Archived cards remain queryable via GET /boards/{id}/cards?filter=closed for history and metrics; deleted cards are unrecoverable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Registering webhooks per card instead of per board.</description>
      <reason>Per-card webhooks must be re-registered whenever a card is copied or the board is recreated; board-level webhooks catch all card events in one stream.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
