<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="DR Drill Scenario Library Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the DR Drill Scenario Library methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-library-not-single-scenario" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DR library MUST contain at least 6 scenarios covering: region loss, db logical corruption, secret-store loss, identity provider outage, vendor breach, ransomware. Single-scenario libraries are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO 22301; FFIEC Business Continuity Handbook">Real disasters are not 'last drill again'; library coverage forces the team to practice uncommon scenarios.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-declaration-criteria-objective" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each scenario MUST have objective declaration criteria (metric, log pattern, vendor alert). Subjective declaration ('feels bad') is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="ICS-style declaration patterns">Subjective declaration causes drills to drift to 'familiar' incidents; objective criteria force the right scenario.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-restore-validation-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each scenario MUST include a restore-validation step with explicit pass criteria (data integrity check, transaction replay, user-facing smoke test). 'Service is up' alone is not validation.</statement>
      <rationale source="backup-verification-dr methodology">Services come up with empty DBs; data integrity is the real recovery metric.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-rotation-calendar" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Scenarios MUST rotate on a published calendar (one scenario per quarter minimum). The same scenario MUST NOT run two quarters in a row.</statement>
      <rationale source="DR program management">Rotation prevents the team from over-rehearsing one scenario and under-preparing for others.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-post-mortem-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every drill produces a post-mortem within 7 days, regardless of outcome. Post-mortem references the scenario id + lists gaps + assigns gap-fix tickets with owners.</statement>
      <rationale source="blameless postmortem culture">Without post-mortem, drills become check-the-box; the gap is the value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-vendor-scenario-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Library MUST include at least one scenario where a primary vendor (cloud, CDN, identity provider, payment processor) is unavailable for &gt;4h. Drill exercises the actual fallback path.</statement>
      <rationale source="vendor-risk-matrix; recent vendor postmortems">Vendor outages are inevitable; teams that drill cloud-only-as-self learn nothing about vendor dependence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
