<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Roadmap Drift Detection Checklist Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every weekly roadmap-drift check must enforce. These are HARD rules — a softer review is not a drift check, it is a status update.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-cycle-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The drift check runs on a fixed weekly cadence (same weekday, same window) for as long as the roadmap is published. Skipped cycles are recorded as "skipped: reason" — never silently dropped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice">Drift detection only works if the sampling interval is constant. Irregular cadence makes deltas non-comparable across weeks and lets the PM unconsciously avoid checking when things are slipping.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-five-axis-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each cycle scores all five axes — scope (committed vs shipped), schedule (milestone date delta), confidence (band shift), dependency (blocker status delta), narrative (what the team now says vs what the roadmap still says). A check that omits any axis is rejected as incomplete.</statement>
      <rationale source="Multi-axis diagnostics">Single-axis status (e.g. "we are on schedule") hides drift on other axes. The narrative axis specifically catches the silent-killer case where the team has informally written off a milestone but the roadmap still shows it as committed.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-named-owner-per-delta" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every non-zero delta names a single accountable owner (handle or org role) and a next-action verb. Plural ownership ("the team will look at it") is rejected; "owner: pending" is allowed for exactly one cycle then auto-escalates.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI / single-throat-to-choke">Without a named owner a drift item is just a complaint. The one-cycle "pending" allowance lets the PM file the delta the moment it is observed without waiting for an owner conversation; the auto-escalation prevents indefinite parking.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-signed-confidence-delta" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Confidence deltas are recorded with a sign and a magnitude band (e.g. "-1 band: high→medium"), not as free-form prose. Unsigned or unbanded confidence change is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Falsifiable artefacts">Free-form confidence language ("we feel slightly less sure") cannot be trended, charted, or compared cycle-over-cycle. Signed band deltas turn confidence into a tracked metric and surface the case where confidence quietly degrades for 3 weeks before any date moves.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-escalation-threshold" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any of the following triggers an out-of-band stakeholder note within 24h, not "we will mention it next review": scope-delta &gt;15% of cycle scope, schedule-delta &gt;1 sprint on any committed milestone, confidence drop of 2+ bands, or 2 consecutive cycles of same-direction drift on the same axis.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-surprise principle">Roadmap credibility dies from surprise, not from bad news. Hard thresholds remove PM discretion to "wait and see" — the same drift that erodes trust when surfaced late builds trust when surfaced early.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example>
    <description>Cycle output for week 2026-W19, project "Pricing v2".</description>
    <code language="markdown">
# Drift Record W19
- cycle: 2026-W19 (Monday pulse)
- previous: 2026-W18
- axes:
  - scope:       committed=8 items, shipped=6, delta=-25% → ESCALATE (rule r5)
  - schedule:    "Beta open" planned W20 → now W21, delta=+1 sprint → ESCALATE
  - confidence:  high → medium, signed_delta=-1 band
  - dependency:  legal review still blocking, no change (2nd cycle same) → ESCALATE
  - narrative:   team standup says "beta is now a feature flag, not a launch" — roadmap still says "public beta launch" → MISMATCH
- owners:
  - scope:       @pm (talk to design lead about over-commit)
  - schedule:    @eng-lead (re-baseline W21)
  - dependency:  @pm (escalate to legal)
- next_check: 2026-W20 Monday 10:00
    </code>
  </example>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../backlog-hygiene-cron-checklist/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../product-manager/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
