<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Error Message Principles and Error Type Handling">
  <summary>Three-part error message framework (what/why/how), placement rules, and handling patterns for validation, system, 404, and network errors.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Part Error Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every error message must answer three questions: what happened, why it happened, and how to fix it.</statement>
      <rationale>Users cannot act on "Error occurred." They need context (what/why) to understand the problem and a specific action (how) to resolve it. Missing any part creates a dead end.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Express errors in plain language. Use no error codes, no technical terms, no blame language directed at the user.</statement>
      <rationale>Technical codes and blame language ("you entered invalid data") shift cognitive burden to the user without helping them recover. Plain language with a calm, helpful tone preserves trust and reduces support load.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every error above cosmetic severity must include a recovery action as a button or link, not as a text instruction.</statement>
      <rationale>"Try again" as a clickable button requires zero interpretation. "Please try again" as text requires the user to figure out how. Buttons also confirm the recovery path is available right now.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Placement Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place form field errors inline, adjacent to the problematic field. For multi-field forms, also show a top-of-form summary with link anchors to each error.</statement>
      <rationale>Inline placement eliminates the need to search. Summaries help users understand scope before scrolling. Both together serve keyboard and screen-reader users who may not reach inline messages before submitting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Show system errors (failed operations) as a modal or top banner with a retry action and, where relevant, a fallback action (e.g., Work Offline).</statement>
      <rationale>System errors affect the whole operation, not one field. Modal or banner placement signals scope. Two actions (retry + fallback) avoid dead ends when retry is likely to fail again.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Error Type Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Validation errors: show immediately on blur or as the user types; place inline next to the field; message = what is wrong plus exactly how to fix it.</statement>
      <rationale>Early feedback prevents users from completing a form incorrectly. Immediate inline placement removes the need to remember which field had the problem after submission.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>404 Not Found: show a full-page message explaining the page is gone or the URL is wrong; provide links to home, search, and 2-3 common destinations.</statement>
      <rationale>Dead-end 404 pages are one of the highest abandonment points. Recovery links keep users in the product and give them a concrete next step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Network errors: show a banner with connection status and a Retry button; offer an offline mode if the product supports it.</statement>
      <rationale>Network errors are transient. Users need a clear retry path and visibility into whether the product is still usable offline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never rely on color alone for error indication. Pair color with an icon and text. Use ARIA live regions so screen readers announce errors on state change. Move focus to the error summary or first error field.</statement>
      <rationale>Color-only errors are invisible to color-blind users and screen readers. Focus management is required so keyboard users do not have to search for the error after a failed submission.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
