<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>
  <section name="journald-patterns">
    <summary>journalctl query patterns for solo-developer VPS service log inspection and incident investigation.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Use --user flag for systemd user services; omit it only for system units like nginx or docker.</statement>
      <rationale>User services run under loginctl linger sessions and their logs are scoped separately. Using system-level journalctl silently returns no output for user services.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer -p err over grepping for "ERROR" strings; journald priority filtering is structured and faster.</statement>
      <rationale>Application logs may write "error" as a string without setting priority. -p err captures systemd-level failures like OOM kills and service crashes regardless of application log format.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section name="common-queries">
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Follow a user service in real-time
journalctl --user -u nero-core -f

# Last 50 lines of a user service
journalctl --user -u nero-core -n 50

# Errors from last 2 hours across all nero services
journalctl --user -u 'nero-*' -p err --since "2 hours ago" --no-pager

# Kernel OOM kills
journalctl -k --since "1 hour ago" | grep -i "out of memory"

# Service restart events
journalctl --user -u nero-core | grep -E "(Started|Stopped|Failed)"

# JSON output for scripted analysis
journalctl --user -u nero-core -o json --since "1 hour ago"

# Count errors per service in last 24h
for svc in nero-core nero-channel-web nero-channel-tg; do
    count=$(journalctl --user -u "$svc" -p err --since "24 hours ago" --no-pager 2>/dev/null | wc -l)
    echo "$svc: $count errors"
done
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Wrong: omits --user, returns nothing for user services
journalctl -u nero-core -f

# Wrong: grep on raw text is fragile and slow
journalctl --user -u nero-core | grep -i error

# Wrong: no --no-pager in scripts causes blocking
journalctl --user -u nero-core | wc -l
        ]]></code>
        <note>Always add --no-pager in scripts. Use -p for priority filtering, not grep on message text.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="filter-reference">
      <list>
        <item>-u — filter by unit name; supports glob patterns like 'nero-*'</item>
        <item>--user — scope to user-session units (loginctl linger must be enabled)</item>
        <item>-p err — priority filter: emerg, alert, crit, err, warning, notice, info, debug</item>
        <item>--since / --until — time window; accepts "2 hours ago", "today", ISO timestamps</item>
        <item>-f — follow (tail -f equivalent)</item>
        <item>-n N — last N lines</item>
        <item>-o format — output format: short, short-iso, json, cat (message only)</item>
        <item>-b / -b -1 — current boot / previous boot</item>
        <item>-k — kernel messages (dmesg equivalent via journald)</item>
        <item>--disk-usage — show total journal storage consumed</item>
        <item>--no-pager — never paginate; required in all scripts</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section name="journald-configuration">
    <summary>journald.conf settings to limit disk consumption and ensure logs survive reboots.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Set Storage=persistent so logs survive reboots; default volatile storage loses all history on each boot.</statement>
      <rationale>Incident investigation almost always needs logs from the previous boot cycle. Volatile storage makes post-reboot debugging impossible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Cap SystemMaxUse at 10% of total disk; for a 100G VPS, 2G is a reasonable ceiling.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a cap, a single chatty service can fill the disk. journald enforces the cap automatically, rotating oldest logs first.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <reference path="templates/journald.conf">journald.conf with size caps, persistence, compression, rate limiting</reference>
  </section>

  <section name="docker-log-rotation">
    <summary>Configure Docker daemon to rotate container logs before they consume unbounded disk space.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Always configure Docker daemon.json with max-size and max-file before starting any long-running containers.</statement>
      <rationale>Docker's default log driver (json-file) has no rotation. A single high-volume container can fill the disk silently.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "log-driver": "json-file",
  "log-opts": {
    "max-size": "10m",
    "max-file": "3"
  }
}
      ]]></code>
      <note>Place at /etc/docker/daemon.json. Restart Docker after changes: sudo systemctl restart docker. Existing containers use old settings until recreated.</note>
    </example>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Starting containers without log rotation configured.</description>
      <reason>A container logging 1MB/minute fills a 100G disk in 70 days. With no rotation, the only fix is manual cleanup under incident pressure.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section name="logrotate">
    <summary>logrotate configuration for application log files written outside journald.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Use delaycompress with compress so the currently active log file is never compressed while it may still be written to.</statement>
      <rationale>Compressing an open file corrupts it. delaycompress ensures only the previous rotation's file gets compressed.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <reference path="templates/logrotate-app.conf">logrotate config for /var/log/nero-*.log with daily rotation, 14-day retention</reference>
  </section>
</text>
