<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>
  <section name="telegram-alerting">
    <summary>Telegram bot alerting pattern for solo-developer VPS: send function, alert-on-failure wrapper, and FLOW autonomous monitoring schedule.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Store TELEGRAM_BOT_TOKEN and TELEGRAM_CHAT_ID in ~/.env (chmod 600), never hardcoded in scripts.</statement>
      <rationale>Scripts in ~/bin or /usr/local/bin may be world-readable. Credentials in .env are loaded at runtime and never committed to version control.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Make the notify function accept both a positional argument and stdin so it composes with pipes.</statement>
      <rationale>Pipeline composition (command | notify-telegram.sh) is the most common usage pattern in monitoring scripts. Argument form is convenient for one-liners.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Truncate messages to 4000 characters before sending; Telegram rejects messages over 4096 chars.</statement>
      <rationale>Long error output from a failing script will silently fail to deliver if not truncated, defeating the alerting purpose.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <reference path="templates/notify-telegram.sh">Telegram send script with stdin/arg modes, .env loading, 4000-char truncation</reference>

    <section name="alert-on-failure-pattern">
      <rule>
        <statement>Wrap any critical script in an alert-on-failure pattern: run the command, alert only on non-zero exit.</statement>
        <rationale>This keeps alerting logic out of individual scripts and makes alert behavior composable via cron.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# In cron: alert if backup script fails
0 3 * * * /home/nero/bin/backup.sh || notify-telegram.sh "Backup FAILED on $(hostname) at $(date '+%H:%M')"

# Wrapper function
alert_on_failure() {
    local task_name="$1"; shift
    if ! "$@" 2>&1; then
        notify-telegram.sh "ALERT: *${task_name}* failed on $(hostname) at $(date '+%H:%M')"
    fi
}

alert_on_failure "Daily Backup" /home/nero/bin/backup.sh
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section name="flow-schedule">
    <summary>FLOW-style autonomous monitoring schedule: silent on success, alerts only on anomalies.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>FLOW hourly checks must be silent on success; only send Telegram alerts when issues are detected.</statement>
      <rationale>An hourly "all OK" message would send 24 Telegram messages per day per server. Alert fatigue destroys the value of monitoring.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>FLOW daily reports send unconditionally at a fixed time regardless of issue state.</statement>
      <rationale>The daily report provides baseline visibility: uptime, resource trends, error count, backup status. It confirms monitoring is working even on quiet days.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section name="cron-schedule">
      <list>
        <item>Hourly (0 * * * *): silent health check, alert only on problems</item>
        <item>Daily 22:00 (0 22 * * *): full report with uptime, resources, errors, backup status</item>
        <item>Weekly Mon 7:00 (0 7 * * 1): trends, capacity, weekly error count</item>
        <item>@reboot: startup heartbeat after 30s service stabilization</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="cron"><![CDATA[
# Hourly health check (alert only on problems)
0 * * * * /home/nero/workspace/scripts/flow-hourly.sh >> /var/log/nero-flow.log 2>&1

# Daily report (22:00)
0 22 * * * /home/nero/workspace/scripts/flow-daily.sh >> /var/log/nero-flow.log 2>&1

# Startup heartbeat (boot + 35s for service stabilization)
@reboot sleep 35 && /home/nero/workspace/scripts/startup-heartbeat.sh >> /var/log/nero-startup.log 2>&1
      ]]></code>
    </example>

    <reference path="templates/flow-hourly.sh">FLOW hourly: service checks, Docker checks, disk/memory, OOM detection, silent on success</reference>
    <reference path="templates/flow-daily.sh">FLOW daily: uptime, per-service memory, Docker status, resources, 24h error count, backup age</reference>
  </section>

  <section name="alert-content-guidelines">
    <summary>What to include in alert messages for fast incident triage.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Every alert must include: hostname, timestamp, what failed, severity. Daily reports include uptime and backup status.</statement>
      <rationale>Without hostname, alerts from multiple servers are ambiguous. Without timestamp, alert delivery delay is invisible. Without what-failed, triage requires SSH before understanding scope.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
FLOW ALERT nero 13:00:
- nero-core is DOWN
- API health check failed

Daily Report: 2026-03-21 22:00
Host: nero
Uptime: up 15 days, 3 hours
Services: nero-core active (847MB), nero-channel-web active (185MB)
Resources: CPU 1.2 load | RAM 8.5G/30G | Disk 29%
Errors (24h): 3
Backup: 20260321_030000 (285MB, 19h ago)
      ]]></code>
    </example>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Sending raw script output or stack traces as Telegram alerts.</description>
      <reason>Telegram messages render poorly for long text. Raw stack traces exceed the 4096-char limit and get dropped silently. Summarize failures, attach details to logs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
