<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="micro-mvps">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>Extremely small experiments (hours to days) that validate one assumption before engineering. Pre-register numeric success criteria before launching to isolate falsifiable, high-impact hypotheses.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>product-validation</tag>
      <tag>experiments</tag>
      <tag>assumption-testing</tag>
      <tag>mvp</tag>
      <tag>learning</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Micro-MVPs</title>

    <summary>Micro-MVPs are extremely small, high-signal experiments (hours to days) that validate one specific assumption before committing engineering time. The rule: pre-register the success criterion as a number before launching; if a "micro" MVP takes longer than one week to build, it is not micro.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Traditional MVPs take weeks or months to build, wasting runway when the core assumption is wrong. Micro-MVPs isolate the riskiest assumption and test it at minimal cost — a landing page tests demand, a Stripe Payment Link tests willingness-to-pay, a Wizard-of-Oz tests workflow fit — each costing hours rather than weeks.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Validating one specific assumption (demand, willingness-to-pay, workflow fit) before committing engineering time</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF stage where every shipped feature is a learning bet, not a delivery</item>
        <item>Validating a new segment for an existing product (fake-door, smoke-test)</item>
        <item>Solo or 2-person team with limited capacity — micro-MVPs preserve runway</item>
        <item>Founder is "in love with a feature" — a micro-MVP is the cheapest way to disprove the hypothesis</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Post-PMF feature work for an established product where users expect polish — fake-door damages trust</item>
        <item>Compliance, security, or infrastructure work — there is no demand to validate</item>
        <item>Teams with no monitoring/instrumentation — you cannot learn from the experiment without measurement</item>
        <item>Brand-sensitive launches where being seen running an experiment is reputational risk</item>
        <item>B2B enterprise sales cycles where a "video demo" is table stakes, not a validation experiment</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="experiment-types">
      <p>Six micro-MVP types with effort, what each validates, and the conditions under which each is the right choice.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Landing page (1 day): validates demand and messaging. Use when the core question is "do people want this?" Measure: signup or waitlist conversion rate against a pre-registered threshold.</statement>
        <rationale>A landing page with a CTA isolates demand signal from product quality signal. The Dropbox 3-minute video generated a 75K waitlist from 5K overnight at cost of video production time only.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Concierge (1 week): validates workflow fit and value delivery. Use when the question is "does this process actually help users?" A human manually delivers the service. Measure: task completion rate, willingness to return.</statement>
        <rationale>Concierge MVPs reveal process failures before automating them. Automating a broken workflow is more expensive than discovering it is broken during manual delivery.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Wizard of Oz (days): validates UX and willingness to pay. The user sees a polished interface; humans operate the backend manually. Limit to approximately 50 concurrent users before manual operation collapses.</statement>
        <rationale>Decouples UX validation from automation cost. Answers "would users pay for this experience?" without building the engine.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Video demo (hours): validates interest and virality. Use for consumer products where the value is immediately demonstrable. Measure: shares, comment sentiment, waitlist signups.</statement>
        <rationale>Video is the cheapest signal for "does this concept resonate?" not "does this work?" Do not use as a willingness-to-pay signal.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Fake door (hours): validates feature demand. Show a button or menu item for a non-existent feature. Measure: click-through rate. Requires ethical unwind: inform users the feature does not exist yet.</statement>
        <rationale>Fake doors measure intent, not interest. A user who clicks "Export to CSV" intended to use it. Plan the ethical unwind before launch — users who discover the deception lose trust.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Smoke test / Stripe Payment Link (days): validates price sensitivity and willingness to pay. Show a pricing page with a real checkout. The only reliable willingness-to-pay signal is the credit-card moment.</statement>
        <rationale>Self-reported willingness to pay (surveys) overstates actual behavior by 3-5x. A Stripe checkout with real money is the only honest signal.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Dropbox video MVP">
        <note>Dropbox assumed people wanted easy file sync. Micro-MVP: 3-minute video explaining the concept. Result: waitlist from 5K to 75K overnight. Cost: only video production time. Validated demand before writing a single line of sync code.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Concierge at scale">
        <note>Running a concierge MVP beyond 50 concurrent users without automating anything. The team discovers it is now operating a service business, not validating a product hypothesis.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="process">
      <p>Sequential steps from identifying the riskiest assumption to the pivot/persevere/next-assumption decision.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 1 — Identify the riskiest assumption. Rank assumptions by: (a) falsifiability — can it be tested cheaply? (b) impact if wrong — would the product fail? The riskiest assumption is high impact AND currently unverified.</statement>
        <rationale>Testing a low-impact assumption cheaply wastes a week. Testing an unfalsifiable assumption wastes indefinitely. The intersection of high-impact and falsifiable is where micro-MVPs produce the best ROI.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 2 — Design the smallest experiment to test that specific assumption. One assumption per experiment. Cap experiment cost at one week of work. If building it takes longer, decompose further.</statement>
        <rationale>Compound experiments yield ambiguous results. If the hypothesis is wrong, you cannot identify which assumption failed. Single-assumption experiments produce clean decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 3 — Pre-register the success criterion before building anything. Define the metric, threshold, minimum sample size, and traffic source. Commit this in a file or document before any traffic touches the asset.</statement>
        <rationale>Deciding the threshold after seeing the data is post-hoc rationalization. Pre-registration forces honesty about what "success" means before survivorship bias sets in.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 4 — Run the experiment. Duration: hours to days. Plan the ethical unwind before launch, especially for fake-door experiments collecting user data.</statement>
        <rationale>The ethical unwind (what happens to signups if the product is not built) must be planned before launch, not after. A 200-email waitlist with no follow-up is a trust violation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 5 — Analyze results against the pre-registered criterion. Allow at most one extension of up to 7 additional days if the sample size is insufficient. After one extension, make a decision on available data.</statement>
        <rationale>Indefinite extensions are equivalent to not having a success criterion. The hard cap forces a decision even under uncertainty, which is the point of the experiment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 6 — Decide: pivot (assumption was wrong, try a different approach), persevere (assumption validated, build), or move to next assumption (this one is not the bottleneck). After three failed micro-MVPs on the same problem space, drop the problem space.</statement>
        <rationale>Three failed experiments on a problem space is evidence the problem is not worth solving, not that the experiments are poorly designed. Sunk-cost bias keeps teams iterating past the signal.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <p>Failure modes that produce invalid learning or waste resources, with root causes.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Validation theatre: a beautifully designed landing page with no distribution plan. The page converts at 0.1% from cold ads but the team declares "validated."</description>
        <reason>The traffic source determines the signal quality more than the asset does. The same page hits 10% on Hacker News Show HN and 0.5% on cold ads. Require an explicit traffic source in the pre-registration before any asset is built.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Compound experiments: testing two assumptions simultaneously (e.g. demand AND price sensitivity on the same landing page).</description>
        <reason>When the hypothesis is wrong, you cannot identify which assumption failed. Single-assumption experiments produce actionable decisions; compound experiments produce ambiguous data that justifies continuing.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Post-hoc threshold setting: deciding whether the experiment "succeeded" after seeing the conversion data.</description>
        <reason>Survivorship bias makes any result look like it was close to success. Pre-registration removes the ability to move the goalposts after seeing the outcome.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Inflated asset bundle: building case studies, customer logos, and testimonials for a one-week experiment.</description>
        <reason>A micro-MVP needs a headline, sub-headline, three value-prop bullets, and a CTA. Additional content delays launch and adds signal noise. Cap copy explicitly.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Fake-door experiment with no ethical unwind plan. Users click "Get Early Access" and receive no follow-up.</description>
        <reason>Trust violation. Transparency is required: inform users the feature does not exist yet and offer them something real (a waitlist, a refund, a free trial). Plan this before launch.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Declaring "inconclusive, extend" after every failed experiment. Maximum one 7-day extension; then make a decision on available data.</description>
        <reason>Indefinite extensions are equivalent to having no success criterion. The purpose of the experiment is to produce a decision under uncertainty, not to wait for certainty.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration">
      <p>How autonomous agents integrate micro-MVP methodologies into product workflows.</p>

      <p>A hypothesis-extraction agent reads the product brief and surfaces the riskiest unverified assumption with a one-line falsifiability statement. An experiment-design agent picks the cheapest micro-MVP type (landing / video / fake-door / Wizard-of-Oz / concierge / smoke-test) matched to that assumption, plus a numeric success criterion set before launch. An asset-build agent generates the landing copy / fake-door UI / video script. After launch, a measurement agent reads analytics and answers a single question: "did the criterion clear?" Human owns the pivot/persevere/next-assumption call.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents: A hypothesis-extractor agent (Opus) — strategy work; ranking risky assumptions is high-leverage. A copy/asset-build agent (Sonnet) — writes the landing / video script / FAQ for the experiment. An analytics-reader agent — connects to Plausible / Mixpanel / GA4 and reports against the pre-registered criterion. faion-mlp-impl-planner-agent — once an experiment validates, plans the real build.</p>

      <p>Prompt pattern for hypothesis extraction: "Product brief: &lt;brief&gt;. List 3-5 unverified assumptions ranked by: Falsifiability (can we test it cheaply?) Impact if wrong (would the product fail?) Output: ranked list, with the riskiest at top. For #1, propose 2 candidate experiments (type, cost in days, success criterion). The success criterion must be a number set BEFORE running the experiment."</p>

      <p>Prompt pattern for asset generation: "For experiment &lt;name&gt; with success criterion &lt;metric&gt;=&lt;threshold&gt;: Generate the minimum viable assets: Headline (max 12 words) Sub-headline (one sentence stating the outcome, not the feature) 3-bullet value prop Single CTA copy Reject any output that names internal features rather than user outcomes."</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Core principles for running successful micro-MVP experiments.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Pre-register the success criterion. If you decide the threshold after seeing the data, you are post-hoc rationalizing.</statement>
        <rationale>Pre-registration removes bias and prevents goalpost-moving.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Cap experiment cost at 1 week. If a "micro" MVP takes longer, it is not micro.</statement>
        <rationale>Extended timelines undermine the core value proposition of rapid validation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Plan the ethical unwind before launch — what happens to the 200 emails on a fake-door waitlist?</statement>
        <rationale>Ethical planning prevents trust violations and reputational damage.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>One assumption per experiment. Compound experiments yield ambiguous results.</statement>
        <rationale>Clean causality requires isolating variables.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>The traffic source matters more than the asset. Same landing page hits 10% on Hacker News and 0.5% on cold ads.</statement>
        <rationale>Distribution and audience quality dominate asset quality in determining signal.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Smoke-test pricing with a Stripe Payment Link before building checkout — the "credit-card moment" is the only reliable willingness-to-pay signal.</statement>
        <rationale>Real payment behavior trumps self-reported intention surveys by 3-5x.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>After 3 failed micro-MVPs on the same problem space, drop the problem space, not the experiment design.</statement>
        <rationale>Repeated failure on the same problem signals the problem is not worth solving, not that the methodology is broken.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Common failure modes when LLMs design or execute micro-MVPs.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs ship "validation theatre" — beautifully written landing pages with no real distribution plan. Force the prompt to include a traffic-source section.</description>
        <reason>Language models optimize for coherent prose, not distribution strategy. Without explicit prompting, they produce polished but untestable outputs.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Models hallucinate plausible conversion-rate benchmarks ("industry standard is 8%"). Require citation or omit; otherwise the success criterion is anchored on fiction.</description>
        <reason>Plausible-sounding numbers get cached into decision-making even when unsourced.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents will inflate the asset bundle (case studies, logos, testimonials) for a 1-week experiment. Cap copy length explicitly.</description>
        <reason>Without constraints, models default to comprehensive design, not minimal validation.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Post-experiment, agents have a strong bias to declare "inconclusive, extend." Force the decision rule with a hard cap (e.g. max 1 extension).</description>
        <reason>Models optimize for narrative coherence; inconclusive results generate more coherent extended narratives than hard decisions.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Human-in-loop checkpoint: pre-registration commit before any traffic touches the asset. Agents can draft, humans must approve.</description>
        <reason>Pre-registration integrity requires human sign-off; agents cannot bind themselves to thresholds.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Human-in-loop checkpoint: ethical unwind plan must be human-signed, especially for fake-door experiments that collect data.</description>
        <reason>Ethical compliance requires human accountability.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Do not let the agent run the post-mortem alone — it tends to weave a coherent narrative regardless of result, masking learning.</description>
        <reason>Models prioritize narrative closure over accurate causal inference.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/experiment-preregistration.yaml" purpose="Pre-registration card: hypothesis, type, success criterion, ethical unwind, decision rule"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/lessons-from-dropbox"/>
      <link href="https://www.ideou.com/blogs/inspiration/the-power-of-tiny-tests"/>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
