<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Headroom Cost Model Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Headroom Cost Model methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-resource-inventory-complete" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Model MUST inventory every critical resource: compute (per service), db (per instance), network (NAT + LB + transit), storage (per bucket / volume class). Skipped resources flagged.</statement>
      <rationale source="capacity-planning practice">Missing resources surprise capacity planning during a scale event.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-utilisation-trailing-30d" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Utilisation measured as p95 over trailing 30 days, NOT instantaneous. Spike-driven over-provisioning rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps + capacity">Instantaneous spikes inflate cost; p95-30d balances safety + cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-70pct-yellow-90pct-red" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Headroom thresholds: 70% triggers a re-provision ticket; 90% triggers an immediate re-provision action + on-call notification.</statement>
      <rationale source="capacity-rule-of-thumb">70% is enough lead time to plan; 90% is the last responsible moment before saturation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-cost-per-unit-tracked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each resource MUST have a cost-per-unit recorded (per vCPU-hour, per GB-month, per request). Cost projection multiplies projected unit demand by unit cost.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps unit economics">Without unit cost, the bill is a mystery; with it, optimisations target the right resource.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-quarterly-projection" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly projection MUST forecast next-quarter resource demand (driven by product roadmap traffic forecast) + cost. Projection delta vs current shared with finance + engineering leader.</statement>
      <rationale source="rolling-forecast pattern">Quarterly cadence aligns with finance + product cycles; surprises avoided.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-anomaly-detection-on-cost" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cost anomalies (&gt;30% deviation from projection) MUST trigger an investigation within 1 business day. Anomaly source documented in the model.</statement>
      <rationale source="cost-anomaly-runbook">30% deviation is the threshold where projection becomes invalid; 1-day SLA prevents bill snowball.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
