<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Small Team Comms Rhythm Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that keep a 2-3 person team aligned without adopting scrum ceremonies or formal comms-management overhead.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-three-rituals-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The team MUST have exactly three rituals and no more: async daily pulse (text), weekly live sync (&lt;=30 min), monthly direction check (&lt;=45 min); a fourth recurring meeting is a graduation signal, not an enhancement.</statement>
      <rationale source="Empirical micro-agency cadence cohort 2023-2025; team-size research">A three-ritual cap is the converged minimum that prevents both drift (too little) and ceremony tax (too much) at this team size.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-founder-not-presenter" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The founder MUST NOT be the only person reporting in any ritual; every participant produces their own pulse / status — even the founder is one voice among 2-3, not the moderator.</statement>
      <rationale source="Equal-voice research; Edmondson psychological safety findings">When the founder runs comms as broadcasts, the second person stops bringing surfacing-worthy issues and rhythm becomes status-theatre.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-async-by-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The daily pulse MUST be async (text, threaded) and time-bounded so it never replaces working hours; standups-on-Zoom are explicitly forbidden at this team size.</statement>
      <rationale source="Async-collaboration research (Doist 2021); cost-of-context-switch studies">Daily live standups cost 30-45 person-minutes/day for a 2-3 person team — overhead that does not buy anything at this size.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-weekly-30-min-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The weekly sync MUST be &lt;=30 minutes wall-clock with a written agenda published &gt;= 24 hours in advance; meetings without an agenda are postponed or cancelled.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bain meeting-cost-per-hour studies; deep-work research (Newport)">30 min forces ruthless prioritisation; 24h agenda lead lets participants think before reacting.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-graduation-trigger" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When the team grows to &gt;= 4 people, this methodology MUST be retired and the team MUST adopt a different framework (formal PM plan, scrum-lite, etc.) within the next monthly check; ad-hoc continuation past 3 is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Team-size research; Dunbar / Brooks findings">Rhythm relies on every voice being equal and meetings &lt;= 30 min — both break at 4+ people.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
