<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-overview" title="Surveys Overview">
  <summary>What UX surveys are, the four survey types, when to use and when not to use, and the six-step process from objective to analysis.</summary>

  <section title="Definition">
    <p>Surveys collect structured data from many users through standardized questions. They quantify user attitudes, preferences, and experiences — answering "what" and "how much" at scale, which qualitative methods cannot do efficiently.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Survey Types">
    <list>
      <item>Satisfaction: measure happiness with the product — CSAT, NPS, CES.</item>
      <item>Task-based: post-task feedback after a specific flow — SUS, SEQ.</item>
      <item>Preference: compare options — A vs B choice.</item>
      <item>Exploratory: understand usage patterns and behaviors at scale.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="When To Use vs Not">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use surveys to quantify what you already know qualitatively, or to triage at scale. Do not use them to answer "why" questions — that requires interviews.</statement>
      <rationale>Surveys give statistical confidence but no causal explanation. Using a survey to find out why users churn produces a list of surface symptoms, not root causes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not launch a survey with fewer than 100 expected responses. With smaller samples, confidence intervals are too wide to act on.</statement>
      <rationale>A sample of 30 produces a 95% CI of ±18 percentage points on a proportion. That range is wider than most meaningful differences you are trying to detect.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Process Steps">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place demographics at the end, not the start. Begin with low-effort, high-relevance questions to build respondent investment.</statement>
      <rationale>Opening with demographics signals a corporate census rather than a conversation about the respondent's experience. Completion rates drop by 10-15% when demographics lead.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: define clear research objective — one primary question the survey must answer.</item>
      <item>Step 2: choose question types (multiple choice, rating scale, ranking, open-ended, matrix).</item>
      <item>Step 3: write questions — one concept per question, neutral wording, exhaustive options.</item>
      <item>Step 4: design flow — intro, screening, easy questions, core questions, demographics, thank you.</item>
      <item>Step 5: pilot test with 5-10 representative users before launch; fix confusion and measure completion time.</item>
      <item>Step 6: analyze — compute response rate, run quantitative statistics, code open-ended themes, segment results.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
