<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-standard-metrics" title="Standard UX Survey Metrics">
  <summary>NPS, SUS, CSAT, and SEQ: exact question wording, scoring formulas, published benchmarks, and when each metric applies.</summary>

  <section title="Lock Standard Wording">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never paraphrase the question wording for NPS, SUS, SEQ, or CES. Use the exact published text, scale anchors, and order. Any deviation invalidates comparison against published benchmarks.</statement>
      <rationale>Standardized UX metrics are benchmarkable because thousands of studies use identical wording. A single word change shifts mean scores by 0.3-1.5 points on a 7-point scale — more than most meaningful product changes you are trying to detect.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Net Promoter Score">
    <rule>
      <statement>NPS question: "How likely are you to recommend [product] to a friend or colleague?" on a 0-10 scale. Score = % Promoters (9-10) minus % Detractors (0-6). Passives (7-8) are excluded.</statement>
      <rationale>NPS range is -100 to +100. Industry average is approximately 32. Above 50 is excellent. Below 0 means more detractors than promoters. Segment before interpreting — overall NPS hides divergent cohort experiences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Report NPS with confidence interval: "NPS = 42 ± 6 (n=200)" gives stakeholders actionable signal. "NPS = 42" alone creates false precision.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="System Usability Scale">
    <rule>
      <statement>SUS uses 10 specific alternating-polarity questions on a 1-5 Likert scale. Score = (sum of odd-item scores - 5) + (25 - sum of even-item scores), multiplied by 2.5. Range: 0-100. Average: 68. Above 80: excellent.</statement>
      <rationale>SUS is the most-validated usability scale with published benchmarks from 500+ studies. The alternating-polarity design prevents straightlining. Using only some of the 10 questions invalidates the score entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="CSAT">
    <rule>
      <statement>CSAT question: "How satisfied are you with [X]?" on a 1-5 or 1-7 scale. Score = (count of satisfied responses / total responses) x 100.</statement>
      <rationale>CSAT is task-specific and moment-specific — use it immediately after a specific interaction, not as a general product measure. Delayed CSAT measures recency effects, not the target interaction.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Single Ease Question">
    <rule>
      <statement>SEQ question: "Overall, how easy or difficult was this task?" on a 1-7 scale ("Very difficult" to "Very easy"). Administer immediately after each task in usability testing. Published average: 5.5.</statement>
      <rationale>SEQ is a single-item validated scale for measuring per-task ease. It correlates well with multi-item scales and takes 10 seconds to complete. Use it after every task in usability tests to build a per-task ease profile.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
