<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-question-design" title="Survey Question Design">
  <summary>Question types, bias detection rules (leading, double-barreled, vague), good vs bad question examples, and response-rate factors.</summary>

  <section title="Question Types">
    <list>
      <item>Multiple choice: fixed options — best for frequency, category membership. Analysis: percentages.</item>
      <item>Rating scale: measure intensity (1-5, 1-7, 1-10) — best for satisfaction, ease, confidence. Analysis: mean, median.</item>
      <item>Ranking: prioritization among options — best for feature importance. Analysis: weighted order.</item>
      <item>Open-ended: exploration and verbatim voice — best for "what else?" and discovery. Analysis: thematic coding.</item>
      <item>Matrix: multiple items on the same scale — best for feature comparison. Analysis: per-item mean.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include at least one open-ended question per survey. Quantitative data tells you what; verbatim responses tell you why in users' own language.</statement>
      <rationale>The highest-value product insights in survey data consistently come from open-text fields. NPS score alone tells you little; the "why" open-text reveals the top promoter driver and top detractor complaint.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Bias Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Check every drafted question for four bias types before launch: leading (suggests an answer), double-barreled (two concepts), vague (undefined terms), and loaded (emotive language). Rewrite any question scoring above 0 on any dimension.</statement>
      <rationale>Question wording dominates survey results. Two well-meaning researchers writing the same survey produce statistically different scores. LLM-drafted questions over-use jargon and double-barreled phrasing — expect to rewrite 30% of agent-generated questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Double-barreled: asks about two concepts in one question — speed and accuracy.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
BAD: "How satisfied are you with the speed and accuracy of search results?"
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Leading: implies a positive sentiment before asking.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
BAD: "How much do you love our new feature?"
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Vague: undefined referent and undefined frequency.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
BAD: "How often do you use it?"
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Clear, single concept, defined terms, neutral wording.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
GOOD: "How often do you use the search feature?"
- Never
- Less than once a week
- 1-3 times per week
- Daily
- Multiple times per day
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Response Rate Factors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep surveys under 5 minutes / 10-15 questions for general audiences; under 2 minutes for in-product micro-surveys. Every additional minute of completion time reduces response rate by 5-10%.</statement>
      <rationale>Long surveys have steep dropout that disproportionately removes casual users who engage least. The resulting sample over-represents power users and unhappy users, making the data unrepresentative.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Length: shorter surveys have higher response rates. Aim for under 5 minutes.</item>
      <item>Incentive: increases response rate but may attract non-target respondents on general panels.</item>
      <item>Timing: mid-week (Tuesday-Thursday), mid-day produces highest response rates.</item>
      <item>Mobile-friendly: many respondents complete on phone — test the survey at 390px viewport.</item>
      <item>Clear purpose: explain why the participant should respond and how results will be used.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
