<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="VUI Design Process">
  <summary>Six-step process for designing voice user interfaces, from use-case selection through Wizard of Oz validation.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Use Cases">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select voice for hands-free tasks, quick commands, simple queries, accessibility needs, and multitasking contexts only — not for complex data entry, private information, or browsing.</statement>
      <rationale>Voice adds a second interaction modality with significant design cost; applying it where it has no advantage over touch or keyboard wastes that investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Write Sample Dialogues">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write natural conversation scripts for happy path and top 3 error paths before designing any intent schema or building any NLU model.</statement>
      <rationale>Dialogue-first design grounds the schema in real language. Schema-first design produces idealized utterances that do not match natural speech, leading to poor NLU coverage in production.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Example happy path: User: "Set a timer for 15 minutes" / System: "Timer set for 15 minutes, starting now."</p>
    <p>Example error path: User: "Order pizza" / System: "Sure! Which pizza place? You've ordered from Papa's Pizza and Domino's before."</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Define Intents and Slots">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define each intent with required and optional slots, then generate at least 10 utterance variations per intent before NLU training; 20+ is the practical minimum for production.</statement>
      <rationale>Underrepresented utterance variation is the primary cause of NLU production failures. Agents generating training data produce syntactically varied but semantically homogeneous utterances — add real user quotes from research.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Intent structure: name, description, required slots (with reprompt if missing), optional slots, sample utterances, response template.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Design Prompts">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep system prompts under 20 words for smart speakers, under 15 for IVR, under 30 for screen+voice hybrids; read every prompt aloud before approving.</statement>
      <rationale>Text that reads naturally in a document is often awkward when spoken; prompt length limits enforce spoken-word conventions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use implicit confirmation for low-risk actions and explicit confirmation for irreversible ones — never confirm every action (users abandon verbose confirmation flows).</statement>
      <rationale>Confirmation overhead is the leading cause of voice feature abandonment; calibrate confirmation strategy to action risk, not to developer anxiety.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Handle Errors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design a 3-attempt error recovery chain: 1st attempt rephrase the prompt; 2nd attempt offer examples; 3rd attempt offer a fallback path (agent transfer, visual alternative, or different action).</statement>
      <rationale>A missing third-attempt fallback leaves users stranded with no exit; they abandon the feature and do not return.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Error types to handle: no input, speech not recognized, intent not understood, slot value invalid, confirmation denied</item>
      <item>Never use "I'm sorry" as a standalone response — it acknowledges the error without offering resolution</item>
      <item>Never use URLs in voice prompts — they are unusable in audio context</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Test with Users">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run Wizard of Oz testing (human playing system role) before any NLU training — intent schemas generated without real utterance data have poor production coverage.</statement>
      <rationale>WoZ testing captures natural speech variation, accent patterns, and implicit slot omissions that agent-generated utterance sets miss entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Test with at least 3 different accents and 2 ambient noise levels before shipping to production.</statement>
      <rationale>STT recognition accuracy varies significantly across accents and noise levels; lab testing in a quiet studio is not representative of real-world usage.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/voice-flow.md">Full voice flow documentation template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-writing.md">Prompt design template with reprompt levels</reference>
  <reference path="scripts/vui-lint.py">Linter for dialogue scripts: prompt length, anti-patterns</reference>
</text>
