<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="VUI Design — Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Worked dialogue examples and antipatterns for voice user interface design.</summary>

  <section title="Good Dialogue Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Food ordering — happy path: "Order my usual from Papa's Pizza" / "I'll place your usual order: a large pepperoni and a 2-liter Coke for delivery. That's $18.50. Should I place the order?" / "Yes" / "Order placed. Delivery in about 35 minutes." Explicit confirmation for high-value irreversible action; response confirms all order details before execution.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Food ordering — error recovery: "Order pizza" / "Sure! Which pizza place? You've ordered from Papa's Pizza and Domino's before." / "Papa's" / "What would you like from Papa's Pizza?" System guides slot filling without demanding all information upfront; uses history to narrow disambiguation.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Smart home — utterance variation: "Turn off the living room lights" / "Lights off in the living room" / "Living room lights off" / "Kill the lights in the living room" — all map to Intent: ControlLight, Slots: room=living room, action=off. Design accepts natural language variation, not just canonical phrasing.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hollow apology as error response: "I'm sorry, I didn't understand that. Please try again."</description>
      <reason>Acknowledges the error without offering resolution. User does not know what to say differently. Use instead: "I didn't catch that. You can say a size like 'medium' or 'large'." — acknowledgment plus concrete guidance.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Prompt too long: "Hello! Welcome to Pizza Palace, the best pizza in town! We have so many great options today! What can I get for you?" (25+ words)</description>
      <reason>Long prompts in audio context cause users to forget the question before they can respond. Speakers optimize for silence-filling; good VUI designers optimize for response elicitation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>URL in voice prompt: "You can find more information at www.pizzapalace.com/menu."</description>
      <reason>URLs are unusable in audio context. Users cannot transcribe a URL they hear. Use instead: "I'll send the menu link to your phone."</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Missing third-attempt fallback: system loops back to the original prompt after the second failed attempt with no alternative path offered.</description>
      <reason>Users stranded with no exit path abandon the voice feature entirely and do not return. The third attempt must always offer a different modality (human agent, visual fallback, different action).</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Single-utterance intent training: NLU model trained on one example phrase per intent.</description>
      <reason>Production NLU models with fewer than 10 utterances per intent fail on natural speech variation, accent differences, and informal phrasing. Coverage requires diversity of form, not just accuracy of one canonical form.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
