<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="voice-ui-basics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for voice-ui-basics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Hollow apology as error response: "I'm sorry, I didn't understand that. Please try again."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Acknowledges the error without offering resolution. User does not know what to say differently. Use instead: "I didn't catch that. You can say a size like 'medium' or 'large'." — acknowledgment plus concrete guidance.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Prompt too long: "Hello! Welcome to Pizza Palace, the best pizza in town! We have so many great options today! What can I get for you?" (25+ words)</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Long prompts in audio context cause users to forget the question before they can respond. Speakers optimize for silence-filling; good VUI designers optimize for response elicitation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>URL in voice prompt: "You can find more information at www.pizzapalace.com/menu."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>URLs are unusable in audio context. Users cannot transcribe a URL they hear. Use instead: "I'll send the menu link to your phone."</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Missing third-attempt fallback: system loops back to the original prompt after the second failed attempt with no alternative path offered.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Users stranded with no exit path abandon the voice feature entirely and do not return. The third attempt must always offer a different modality (human agent, visual fallback, different action).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Single-utterance intent training: NLU model trained on one example phrase per intent.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Production NLU models with fewer than 10 utterances per intent fail on natural speech variation, accent differences, and informal phrasing. Coverage requires diversity of form, not just accuracy of one canonical form.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
