<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="generative-ui-design Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for generative-ui-design. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Generate 3–5 variants per brief, not 1. Single-variant generation anchors the team too early and forecloses design space exploration.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The purpose of generative UI is to expand the option space cheaply. A single variant is no better than having a designer start from scratch — it still anchors the conversation to one direction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat generated UI as a zero-cost rough draft. Critique aggressively; accept nothing without review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generated output that is accepted without critique carries forward AI defaults (generic aesthetics, missing accessibility, deprecated patterns) into production.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run axe-cli or equivalent on all generated HTML before presenting to stakeholders.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generated UIs that look accessible routinely have broken focus order, missing live regions, and contrast failures. Automated check is mandatory before any stakeholder presentation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin design tokens explicitly in every generation prompt. Without them, AI defaults to generic Bootstrap-like aesthetics.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI generation models have no brand knowledge; explicit token references (color names, type scale, spacing) are the only way to anchor output to the design system.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep generated components isolated from the production codebase until manually reviewed and refactored.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generated code frequently uses deprecated APIs, missing responsive breakpoints, and incorrect composition patterns; direct merge without review introduces technical debt.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mark all AI-generated components with a comment: "AI-generated — review before production".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unmarked AI-generated code becomes invisible in the codebase; marking enables future audits and prevents accidental promotion to production.</rationale>
    </rule>
  
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the Applies-If preconditions are not met OR any Skip-If disqualifier holds.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory skip leaf">Decision-tree leaves must reference a rule id. The skip leaf needs a real rule so non-applicable inputs route cleanly out instead of producing false-positive verdicts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
