<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-gke-patterns" title="GCP GKE Cluster Patterns">
  <summary>Regional cluster rules, node pool strategies, and security configuration (Workload Identity, Binary Authorization, Shielded Nodes).</summary>

  <section title="Cluster Type Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deploy GKE Standard or Autopilot clusters as REGIONAL (not zonal) with a minimum of 3 zones for production; use Autopilot when teams want to avoid node management overhead.</statement>
      <rationale>Zonal clusters are single points of failure — a zone outage takes the cluster control plane offline. Regional clusters survive individual zone failures with no downtime.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the REGULAR release channel for production clusters; avoid RAPID channel in production due to less-tested releases.</statement>
      <rationale>REGULAR channel receives tested Kubernetes versions with a minimum 2-week bake period. RAPID receives new versions immediately with less production validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable Workload Identity on all clusters; use per-namespace Kubernetes Service Accounts bound to GCP service accounts; never use node-level service account keys.</statement>
      <rationale>Workload Identity eliminates node metadata server access for service account keys. It provides per-workload identity rather than per-node, following least privilege.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable Binary Authorization with ATTESTOR_BASED policy; require vulnerability scan attestation from Container Analysis before deployment to production.</statement>
      <rationale>Binary Authorization prevents unscanned or unsigned images from running in production, enforcing the supply chain security requirements for SOC2/PCI compliance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable Shielded Nodes with Secure Boot on all node pools; enable Dataplane V2 (eBPF) for network policy enforcement.</statement>
      <rationale>Shielded Nodes verify node integrity against bootkit and rootkit attacks. Dataplane V2 provides granular network policy enforcement at the kernel level.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Node Pool Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Remove the default node pool after cluster creation; use dedicated node pools with autoscaling for each workload tier (system, application, batch); add taints to Spot node pools.</statement>
      <rationale>The default node pool has fixed configuration unsuitable for production. Dedicated pools allow per-workload machine type, autoscaling bounds, and preemption policies.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure Spot VM node pools with a Spot:OnDemand taint for fault-tolerant batch workloads; use resource quotas per namespace to prevent runaway autoscaling.</statement>
      <rationale>Spot VMs cost 60-91% less than On-Demand but can be preempted with 30-second notice. Taints ensure only workloads designed for preemption land on Spot nodes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Single-zone GKE clusters for production workloads.</description>
      <reason>A zone outage takes the entire cluster offline — control plane and all worker nodes. Regional clusters survive zone failures with automatic rescheduling.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
