<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-database-patterns" title="GCP Database Patterns">
  <summary>Cloud SQL HA configuration, read replica patterns, AlloyDB vs Spanner decision, and backup rules.</summary>

  <section title="Cloud SQL High Availability">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always set availability_type = REGIONAL for production Cloud SQL instances; enable PITR (point-in-time recovery) with 30-day retention; disable public IP.</statement>
      <rationale>ZONAL instances have no automatic failover — a zone outage requires manual intervention. REGIONAL provides automatic failover to a standby in a different zone within 60 seconds.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable Query Insights and set logging flags: log_checkpoints, log_connections, log_disconnections, log_lock_waits for PostgreSQL; enable deletion protection on production instances.</statement>
      <rationale>Query Insights identifies slow queries without performance overhead. Connection and lock logging provides the audit trail required for compliance. Deletion protection prevents accidental drops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure SSL enforcement (require_ssl = true); use Private Service Connect for connections from GKE, never expose Cloud SQL via public IP.</statement>
      <rationale>Public IP Cloud SQL instances are frequently found in security audits. Private connectivity eliminates the attack surface for credential stuffing and brute-force attacks.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Read Replicas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create read replicas in the same region as the primary for read-heavy workloads; create cross-region replicas for disaster recovery when RPO is under 1 hour.</statement>
      <rationale>Same-region replicas add no cross-region data transfer costs and reduce primary load. Cross-region replicas provide an independent copy for DR failover.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Database Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Cloud SQL PostgreSQL for standard OLTP workloads; use AlloyDB for PostgreSQL-compatible workloads requiring 2x+ query throughput; use Spanner for global multi-region consistency with 99.999% SLA.</statement>
      <rationale>AlloyDB delivers 2x transactional and 100x analytical throughput over Cloud SQL via columnar engine. Spanner provides external consistency across regions at significantly higher cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Cloud SQL with availability_type = ZONAL in production.</description>
      <reason>ZONAL provides no automatic failover. A zone outage requires manual promotion of a replica, causing 5-30 minutes of downtime depending on replication lag.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
