<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-microservices-data" title="GCP Microservices and Data Pipeline Patterns">
  <summary>Cloud Run patterns, Pub/Sub with DLQ, Dataflow streaming, and BigQuery partitioning rules.</summary>

  <section title="Cloud Run Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Cloud Run for stateless HTTP workloads; bind each Cloud Run service to a dedicated service account with minimal IAM roles; set concurrency and CPU allocation based on workload type.</statement>
      <rationale>Per-service accounts enable auditing of which service accessed which resource. Incorrect concurrency leads to cold start storms (too low) or memory exhaustion (too high).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable VPC connector or Direct VPC egress for Cloud Run services that need to access Cloud SQL, Memorystore, or internal services; do not expose internal APIs via public Cloud Run URLs.</statement>
      <rationale>VPC egress routes Cloud Run traffic through the VPC, enabling access to private resources without public exposure or NAT gateway costs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pub/Sub Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure a dead-letter topic on every Pub/Sub subscription with max_delivery_attempts = 5; use exactly-once delivery for financial and idempotency-critical workflows.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a dead-letter topic, messages that fail processing are retried indefinitely, blocking the subscription and delaying subsequent messages. DLT enables failure inspection and replay.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Push subscriptions (Cloud Run, Cloud Functions) for event-driven workloads; use Pull subscriptions for batch consumers that need to control processing rate.</statement>
      <rationale>Push subscriptions trigger immediately on message arrival. Pull subscriptions give consumers control over throughput and prevent overloading downstream systems.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Dataflow and BigQuery">
    <rule>
      <statement>Partition BigQuery tables on ingestion date or a high-cardinality timestamp field; cluster on the most common filter columns; use Reservations for critical queries.</statement>
      <rationale>Partitioning reduces bytes scanned per query by 10-100x. Clustering further reduces data scanned within partitions. On-demand pricing without reservations can create unpredictable costs for large queries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Design Dataflow pipelines to be idempotent and restartable; use checkpointing for streaming pipelines; define watermarks for late-arriving data handling.</statement>
      <rationale>Dataflow workers can fail and restart mid-job. Non-idempotent pipelines produce duplicate records on restart. Watermarks define when a window is considered complete.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Pub/Sub subscription without a dead-letter topic for production workloads.</description>
      <reason>A single bad message can block an entire subscription if there is no DLT to absorb it after max retries. The subscription falls arbitrarily behind with no alerting mechanism.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
