<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Threads Basics — Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the Threads Basics methodology + two self-routing anchors. Each pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-cadence-3-to-10-per-day" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post at minimum 3×/day; optimal 7-10×/day. Reply to the first wave of comments within the first hour of each post for algorithm boost.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta product comms; Threads engagement reports 2024-2026">Threads rewards reply velocity, not just post volume. Accounts that post but do not reply plateau within weeks; replies drive reach more than the post itself.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-no-cross-post-verbatim" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never cross-post X/Twitter content verbatim. Rewrite for Threads' conversational register (warmer, less ironic, no link-thread formatting).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal SMM audits Q1 2026">Twitter irony and thread formatting don't translate. Verbatim X content reads as out-of-place and suppresses engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-no-auto-post" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agents MUST NOT auto-post via unofficial scheduling APIs. Drafts are ranked by the agent and posted manually by the operator within prime windows.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta automation policy 2024-2026">No stable scheduling API exists at the start of 2026. Meta is aggressive about automation detection — unofficial schedulers get accounts flagged.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-character-cap-500" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Drafts MUST be ≤500 characters; validate length programmatically after generation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Threads UI constraints; LLM character-count reliability data">LLMs are unreliable at character-count limits. Over-length posts fail silently or look unprofessional on Threads' compact format.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-engagement-bait" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Forbidden phrases in every draft: "comment X for Y", "tag a friend", "follow for more". Drafts containing any banned phrase are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta moderation guidelines">These phrases are flagged by Meta and suppress reach. Explicitly prohibit them in every prompt.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-hook-bigram-rotation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hook bigram rotation: no draft may reuse the same opener bigram ("Hot take", "Honest question", "Real talk") more than once per weekly content pack.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal SMM audits Q1 2026">Hook repetition reduces engagement. Enforce banned-bigram lists in the prompt to force variety across the pack.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-pillar-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every draft MUST carry a content-pillar tag (Opinions / Value / Questions / Personal / Curated). Cap agent-generated posts at 50% of weekly volume — the other 50% comes from operator's lived context.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal SMM audits Q1 2026">Without pillar tags, agents drift toward whatever style won last week. The algorithm rewards authentic conversation, not publishing volume.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold (audience overlaps Instagram demographics, brand voice allows hot takes + personal stories, team can reply within first hour), execute the daily content-pack ideation + ship procedure from `04-procedure.xml`.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's affirmative leaf.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Skip-If condition is present (no Instagram-overlapping audience, brand voice forbids conversational register, no reply capacity, heavily-regulated industry), do NOT apply this methodology. Route to `growth-linkedin-strategy` or `growth-twitter-x-growth`.</statement>
      <rationale source="self-routing rule">Anchor for the decision tree's skip leaf.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
