<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="devops-platform-idp-core Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for devops-platform-idp-core. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An IDP MUST provide all six core components: Self-Service Portal (provision without tickets), Golden Paths (opinionated templates for common patterns), Service Catalog (discover and manage services), Environment Management (automated setup for dev/staging/prod), Policy Enforcement (security and compliance automation), and Developer Documentation (centralized, searchable knowledge base). Partial implementations that omit the Service Catalog or Golden Paths reduce adoption below the 50% threshold required for ROI.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each component addresses a distinct developer friction category. A portal without a catalog forces developers to discover services through Slack. Golden paths without a portal are just documentation. Policy enforcement without self-service creates a new gating bottleneck identical to the ticket queue being replaced.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat the platform as a product: assign a product owner, measure developer adoption (target greater than 50% new services via golden paths), run quarterly NPS surveys (target greater than 7/10), and maintain a public roadmap. Platform teams MUST NOT operate as a purely reactive ops function.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Platforms built without product discipline accumulate features no one uses and miss the pain points developers actually have. Spotify Backstage succeeded because Spotify ran it as an internal product with a dedicated team and user research, achieving 2.3x GitHub activity increase among frequent users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Golden paths MUST be opinionated but optional. They MUST NOT be mandatory guardrails that block deviation. Provide a documented escape hatch for every golden path so non-standard use cases can proceed without platform team involvement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mandatory golden paths recreate the ticket queue. Spotify's key decision was "nudge toward best practices without forcing compliance" — this preserved autonomous engineering culture and drove voluntary adoption above 89% for the new-service template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The platform MUST provide transparent abstraction: self-service access to infrastructure WITHOUT hiding the underlying systems. Developers MUST be able to inspect what the platform provisions (e.g., view the generated Terraform or Kubernetes manifests). Black-box abstractions are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">When platform abstractions are opaque, debugging becomes impossible and trust collapses. Developers abandon the platform and provision directly, creating shadow infrastructure that the platform team cannot maintain or secure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>IDP architecture MUST follow five layers in order: (1) Developer Experience — portals, CLIs, IDE integrations; (2) Golden Paths — templates, scaffolding, self-service workflows; (3) Platform APIs — standardized interfaces for infrastructure; (4) Orchestration — pipeline-based (linear CI/CD-style for simple deployments) or graph-based (dependency-aware for complex enterprise architectures); (5) Infrastructure — cloud resources, Kubernetes, networking. Each layer MUST expose an API to the layer above; no cross-layer direct calls.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Layer isolation allows swapping orchestration backends (e.g., migrating from pipeline-based to graph-based Crossplane as complexity grows) without rebuilding the developer experience layer. Cross-layer coupling is the primary cause of "big bang" platform rewrites.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select IDP tooling in this priority order: (1) Service catalog first (Backstage for open-source orgs; Port or Cortex if commercial scorecards are needed); (2) one golden path template per top-3 developer use case; (3) orchestration backend only after the catalog proves adoption. Do NOT deploy Backstage plus Crossplane plus Humanitec simultaneously in the first 90 days — tool sprawl kills platform adoption before it starts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each additional tool multiplies integration surface and on-call burden. Spotify started with the catalog alone; the scaffolder (golden paths) came six months later. Starting with all tools forces developers to learn too much at once and pushes NPS negative.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>AI agents running on the platform MUST be provisioned through the same self-service golden paths as human-initiated workloads, with RBAC, resource quotas, and governance policies. AI workloads MUST NOT bypass the platform's policy enforcement layer. Predictive FinOps controls MUST be applied to AI inference workloads at provisioning time, not post-hoc.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI workloads have non-deterministic resource consumption patterns that make post-hoc cost controls insufficient. Platforms without AI governance policies in 2026 face runaway inference costs and compliance failures in regulated industries.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
