<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spatial-ui-patterns">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Four anchor types (world, head, body, hand) for spatial UI with ergonomic rules, window management, and platform-specific notes for visionOS, Quest, HoloLens, Android XR.</summary>
    <category>spatial</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>spatial-ui</tag>
      <tag>xr</tag>
      <tag>panel-anchoring</tag>
      <tag>window-management</tag>
      <tag>visionos</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Spatial UI Patterns</title>

    <summary>Panel anchoring, window management, and interaction rules for 3D/XR interfaces (visionOS, Meta Horizon OS, HoloLens, Android XR). Four anchor types — world-locked, head-locked, body-locked, hand-attached — each with distinct use cases, ergonomic constraints, and platform-specific APIs.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Traditional 2D components break in 3D space: wrong anchor choice causes arm fatigue, FOV violations, or interaction conflicts. Explicit anchor rules and comfort checks (distance 0.5-2 m, eccentricity ≤30°, touch target ≥4 cm) prevent the most common failures before prototyping.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing UI for visionOS, Meta Quest/Horizon OS, HoloLens, Magic Leap 2, or Android XR.</item>
        <item>Porting 2D apps to spatial environments and choosing panel anchoring strategy.</item>
        <item>Defining window-management rules (snap, group, dock, spatial recall).</item>
        <item>Reviewing existing XR UIs for fatigue, near-field clutter, or FOV violations.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>2D mobile/desktop UIs — patterns assume 3D positioning and head/hand tracking.</item>
        <item>Handheld AR (ARKit on iPhone) — different interaction model; anchoring rules diverge.</item>
        <item>VR-only games with bespoke diegetic UI — system patterns may conflict with game fiction.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="anchor-type-definitions">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Assign every panel exactly one anchor type before prototyping; do not defer anchoring to implementation.</statement>
        <rationale>Anchor type determines interaction model, platform API, and ergonomic constraints. Changing it late requires redesigning transitions and input mappings.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>World-locked panels must remain fixed in physical space; use for reference content that the user returns to across movement.</statement>
        <rationale>World-locked panels feel grounded and reduce cognitive load for information the user consults repeatedly (maps, documentation, dashboards).</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Head-locked panels must be reserved for transient notifications only; never use head-locked for primary navigation.</statement>
        <rationale>Head-locked content follows gaze constantly, causing visual fatigue and disorientation within minutes. Transient use (under 5 seconds) is the only safe pattern.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Body-locked panels are the default for menus and tools used while moving; anchor to torso forward direction, not head orientation.</statement>
        <rationale>Body-locked UI stays accessible without constant arm raising and does not drift with head turns, making it comfortable for extended use.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Hand-attached UI must cover no more than two high-frequency actions (e.g., mode toggle, undo); do not build a full toolbar on the hand.</statement>
        <rationale>A hand that becomes a toolbar is always occupied. More than two actions causes the user to search the hand surface, breaking flow.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ergonomic-constraints">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Place world-locked and body-locked panels at 0.5-2 m distance and within 30° eccentricity from forward gaze.</statement>
        <rationale>Outside this envelope, users must rotate their head or lean, causing fatigue. The 30° eccentricity limit aligns with comfortable reading range without head movement.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Set the minimum touch target size to 4 cm in spatial UI; smaller targets are unreachable with reliable pinch or ray accuracy.</statement>
        <rationale>Unlike touchscreen where a fingertip anchors the touch, spatial interaction uses ray casting or hand tracking with inherent jitter; 4 cm is the empirical floor.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Hand-attached panels must be placed 0.25-0.5 m from the user's eye point; outside this range hand tracking loses precision.</statement>
        <rationale>Hand tracking cameras have a working volume; panels outside it produce tracking dropout and unreachable targets.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="platform-notes">
      <p>visionOS, Meta Horizon OS, and Android XR have diverging anchor vocabularies. Platform-to-anchor mapping:</p>
      <list>
        <item>visionOS: windows (world/body), volumes (world), immersive spaces (full environment)</item>
        <item>Horizon OS: panels (world/body/hand), surfaces (world snap)</item>
        <item>Android XR: spatial panels (world/body), AR anchors (world via ARCore)</item>
        <item>HoloLens/MRTK3: slate (world), follow (body), tag-along (head-locked lite)</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>When targeting multiple XR platforms, define anchoring in platform-agnostic terms (world/head/body/hand) and map to platform APIs separately.</statement>
        <rationale>Platform-specific anchor names differ enough to cause translation errors if mixed in design documents.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="window-management-rules">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Support at minimum: snap to surfaces, group related windows, minimize to dock, and spatial memory (restore to last position).</statement>
        <rationale>Users who place windows deliberately form spatial memory; losing positions on app restart breaks the mental model and forces repetitive layout work.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Persist spatial memory per-user across sessions, not per-app-launch; store anchor positions in platform world-anchor APIs.</statement>
        <rationale>Per-launch spatial memory resets positions on every cold start, eliminating the ergonomic benefit of allowing users to arrange their workspace.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Provide a "recenter" gesture or voice command that returns body-locked UI to the comfortable default position.</statement>
        <rationale>Users physically drift during extended sessions. Body-locked content that started centered drifts relative to the user's new forward direction; recenter corrects this without requiring the user to close and reopen panels.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Animate panel summon and dismiss with a spatial origin anchor (from the body or hand that invoked it); do not use instant pop-in.</statement>
        <rationale>Instant appearance without a spatial origin disorients users — the panel seems to appear from nowhere. Animating from a source provides spatial context.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="multi-window-layout">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Consult platform manifests for window count and GPU memory limits before allowing users to open more than 3 simultaneous panels.</statement>
        <rationale>Quest and Android XR impose OS-level limits on concurrent window count and GPU memory; exceeding them causes crashes or degraded rendering that the app cannot recover from gracefully.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Group logically related windows (e.g., inspector + canvas) so they can be moved and dismissed together.</statement>
        <rationale>Independent movement of tightly coupled panels breaks layout coherence and forces users to reorganize relationships repeatedly.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="comfort-and-depth-hierarchy">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use depth as a secondary hierarchy signal after color and typography, not as a primary one.</statement>
        <rationale>Many users have reduced stereo acuity (including a significant fraction with amblyopia or monocular vision); depth-first hierarchy excludes them and fails gracefully only if color/typography carry the signal too.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Test panel placement with at least 5 users including short and tall participants; ergonomic defaults assume a 50th-percentile adult standing.</statement>
        <rationale>A 160 cm user and a 195 cm user experience very different comfort envelopes for the same world-locked panel. Seated users have additional constraints on forward reach and upward gaze.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always verify input modality availability before proposing gaze+pinch, voice, or hand-tracking combinations.</statement>
        <rationale>Voice and gaze are hardware-gated on some Quest variants; controller-only configurations on HoloLens change the entire interaction model. Proposing unsupported modalities produces a build that fails on the target device.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Head-locked primary navigation — a persistent menu that follows gaze at all times.</description>
        <reason>Causes visual fatigue within minutes; blocks the view of world content; violates Apple visionOS and Meta Horizon OS design guidelines explicitly.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Placing any UI closer than 0.5 m from the user's eye point.</description>
        <reason>Content within 0.5 m is in the vergence-accommodation conflict zone; eyes cannot focus comfortably and the user experiences eye strain within seconds.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Requiring constant arm raising to interact with world-locked UI above eye level.</description>
        <reason>Gorilla arm fatigue sets in after 30-60 seconds of raised-arm interaction; UI above the horizontal midline must be transient or reachable by gaze+pinch, not by reaching up.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pin SDK versions explicitly in every prompt when generating visionOS or Quest code; require the agent to cite API references.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs frequently emit deprecated APIs (e.g., OVRPlugin calls renamed in 2024+). Without version pinning, generated code compiles against documentation, not the installed SDK.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Declare coordinate system assumptions explicitly in every code generation prompt: visionOS (Y-up, right-handed, meters), Unity (Y-up, left-handed, meters), Unreal (Z-up, cm).</statement>
        <rationale>Converting at the wrong layer breaks panel placement in ways that are not obvious until runtime; agents must not assume a coordinate system.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Require USDZ/USD scene mutations to be validated via usdcat before accepting agent output.</statement>
        <rationale>USD authoring is finicky; agents produce syntactically plausible but semantically broken scenes that fail to load silently.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="accessibility-gaps">
      <p>Spatial UI accessibility (color blindness, low vision, motor impairments, vestibular sensitivity) is under-served by the methodology. Agents must escalate to the accessibility-specialist methodology in parallel when designing for diverse users.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Flag any spatial UI specification that does not address vestibular sensitivity; provide a reduced-motion mode for all animated panel transitions.</statement>
        <rationale>Spatial animations (panel summon, recenter, fly-in) trigger vestibular discomfort in users with motion sensitivity, a common condition that is easy to mitigate with a preference toggle.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration">
      <p>Spatial UX work has more constraints than freedom — agents are useful for constraint checking, not for creative anchoring decisions. Pipeline: (1) panel-classifier infers the right anchor type from a panel's content+behavior spec, (2) comfort-checker verifies placement against angular/distance/FOV constraints per platform, (3) interaction-mapper proposes input modalities (gaze+pinch, hand ray, controller). Always pair with human prototyping in-headset — agents cannot feel arm fatigue.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: panel-classifier (sonnet; given content type + persistence requirements, recommends world/head/body/hand-locked anchor and rationale); comfort-checker (haiku; deterministic checks — FOV ≤ 30° eccentric, panel distance 0.5-2 m, eye-line ±15° — against a spec); xr-input-mapper (sonnet; suggests gestures/voice/gaze for a given affordance, per platform); xr-flow-author (sonnet; writes step-by-step user flows including head/hand state transitions).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <list>
        <item>xcrun simctl (visionOS Sim): Boot/run visionOS simulator from CLI (developer.apple.com/visionos)</item>
        <item>unity hub CLI: Build XR projects (XR Interaction Toolkit) (docs.unity3d.com/Packages/com.unity.xr.interaction.toolkit)</item>
        <item>meta-spatial-sdk CLI: Build/deploy to Quest devices (developer.oculus.com/documentation/spatial-sdk)</item>
        <item>adb: Sideload + log Quest/Android XR apps (developer.android.com/tools/adb)</item>
        <item>openxr-runtime (Monado): OSS XR runtime for testing (monado.freedesktop.org)</item>
        <item>wave (HTC Vive Wave SDK CLI): Multi-device XR builds (developer.vive.com/resources/vive-wave)</item>
        <item>usdz-tools / usdpython: Author/inspect USDZ assets for visionOS panels (github.com/PixarAnimationStudios/USD)</item>
      </list>
      <p>SaaS services: Apple Reality Composer Pro (limited file-format scriptability); Unity XR Interaction Toolkit (OSS, de facto cross-platform XR layer); Unreal OpenXR (OSS, heavier weight, fewer mobile options); Meta Spatial SDK (yes, Gradle/CLI); Microsoft MRTK3 (OSS, Unity packages); ShapesXR (limited collaborative authoring); Bezi / Gravity Sketch (limited, export to GLTF/USD).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Default to body-locked menus for tools used while moving and world-locked for reference content; head-locked is reserved for transient notifications, never for primary nav.</item>
        <item>Reserve hand-attached UI for one or two high-frequency actions (mode toggle, undo). More than that and the hand becomes a busy toolbar.</item>
        <item>Test panel placement with at least 5 users including short and tall — methodology's "ergonomic" defaults are based on a 50th-percentile adult.</item>
        <item>Animate panel summon/dismiss with a spatial "from-source" anchor (origin point on the body or hand) — instant pop-in disorients.</item>
        <item>Use depth as a secondary hierarchy after color/typography, not a primary one — many users have reduced stereo acuity.</item>
        <item>Provide a "recenter" gesture/voice command that returns body-locked UI to a comfortable default — users drift, content should not.</item>
        <item>Preserve spatial memory across sessions: persist anchor positions per-user, not per-app-launch.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/comfort-check.ts" purpose="TypeScript function that flags panels outside the ergonomic envelope."/>
      <template path="templates/panel-classifier-prompt.txt" purpose="Prompt for a panel-classifier subagent (world/head/body/hand)."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/designing-for-visionos"/>
      <link href="https://developer.oculus.com/resources/oculus-design-guidelines"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/windows/mixed-reality/mrtk-unity"/>
      <link href="https://www.khronos.org/openxr/"/>
      <link href="https://nngroup.com/articles/spatial-ui/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
