<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-case-studies" title="Funnel Optimization Case Studies">
  <summary>Five before/after case studies demonstrating funnel optimization outcomes across SaaS, e-commerce, mobile, B2B, and subscription products.</summary>

  <section title="SaaS Signup Funnel">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Problem: 2% overall conversion. Homepage to Pricing: 80% drop (value prop unclear). Pricing to Signup: 60% drop (confusing pricing). Fixes: clearer homepage headline (+15% to pricing), simplified pricing 3 to 2 tiers (+25% signup), "Start free" emphasis (+10% trial start). Result: 2.0% to 3.8% overall (+90%).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="E-commerce Checkout">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Problem: 60% cart abandonment. Root causes by share: 35% shipping cost surprise, 25% account creation required, 20% payment form friction. Fixes: show shipping on product page (-15% abandonment), add guest checkout (-20% abandonment), express checkout (Apple Pay/Google Pay) (+12% completion).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Mobile App Onboarding">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Problem: Only 15% of installs reach core action. Onboarding had 3 screens causing progressive drop. Solution: reduce to 1 welcome screen, skip directly to core action, show tips contextually. Result: 15% to 42% core action rate (+180%).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="B2B Lead Generation">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Problem: 0.35% blog-to-demo conversion. Fixes: CTA changed from "Download whitepaper" to "Get free checklist" (+25% clicks), form fields reduced from 8 to 3 (+40% completion), A/B tested email subjects (+15% open rate), added demo video in email (+20% demo requests). Result: 0.35% to 0.98% (+180%).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Subscription Trial">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Problem: 5% trial-to-paid conversion. Users not experiencing value in first 3 days; no reminder emails; payment friction. Fixes: onboarding email sequence Days 1/3/5/7 (+20% Day-7 active), time-to-value checklist in app (+15% activation), pre-authorize payment card (+25% conversion). Result: 5% to 9.5% (+90%).</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
