<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-issue-patterns" title="Common Drop-off Issues, Root Causes, and Solutions">
  <summary>Diagnostic patterns mapping observed drop-off symptoms to root causes and proven solution approaches.</summary>

  <section title="Issue Pattern Map">
    <list>
      <item>High homepage bounce: value prop unclear — A/B test headlines, add social proof above fold</item>
      <item>Form abandonment: too many fields — reduce to 3-5 critical fields only</item>
      <item>Low activation: no guidance after signup — add onboarding checklist and contextual tooltips</item>
      <item>Cart abandonment: surprise shipping costs — show total cost upfront on product page</item>
      <item>Email verification drop: delayed or spam-filtered emails — improve deliverability, add resend option</item>
      <item>Trial-to-paid drop: value not demonstrated — improve activation, add usage-based upgrade prompts</item>
      <item>Mobile permission denial: scary permission prompts — explain why each permission is needed before requesting</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="SaaS-Specific Patterns">
    <list>
      <item>Homepage to Pricing drop (60-80%): value prop unclear — clarify headline to one outcome</item>
      <item>Trial to Activation drop (40-60%): onboarding friction — reduce steps, add aha-moment shortcut</item>
      <item>Activated to Paid drop (90-95%): pricing or value mismatch — add upgrade prompts at limit moments</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="E-commerce Patterns">
    <list>
      <item>Product to Cart drop (80-90%): browsing intent, not buying intent — add urgency, clearer benefits</item>
      <item>Cart to Checkout drop (40-60%): shipping or account friction — show costs early, offer guest checkout</item>
      <item>Checkout to Payment drop (20-30%): trust or security concerns — add trust badges, security copy</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Mobile App Patterns">
    <list>
      <item>Install to First Open drop (10-30%): permission request on launch — delay until after value shown</item>
      <item>Onboarding screen drop (20-30% per screen): too much friction — cut to one essential screen</item>
      <item>First Session to Return drop (50-70%): no habit formed — implement Day 1 push notification with re-engagement hook</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Optimizing steps that already meet "great" benchmarks while ignoring steps below "good."</description>
    <reason>Effort spent on a step at 80% conversion (already great) produces less gain than fixing a step at 20% conversion (well below good). Always benchmark first.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
