<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="secrets-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>devops-engineer</domain>
    <summary>Eliminate static credentials via cloud identity (IRSA, Workload Identity, OIDC) and short-lived dynamic secrets from a backend; use ESO as the Kubernetes bridge.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>secrets</tag>
      <tag>vault</tag>
      <tag>kubernetes</tag>
      <tag>oidc</tag>
      <tag>eso</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Secrets Management</title>
    <summary>Secrets management in 2025-2026 means eliminating static, long-lived credentials: apps authenticate via cloud identity (IRSA, Workload Identity, OIDC) and receive short-lived dynamic credentials from a secrets backend. Kubernetes integration uses External Secrets Operator (ESO) as the standard bridge between any backend and pod-level secret injection. Rotation must be automated on a 30-day or shorter cycle.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Static secrets stored in environment variables or Kubernetes native Secrets (base64, not encrypted at rest by default) are the most common breach vector. Dynamic secrets from Vault's database engine issue credentials that expire in minutes — a compromised secret becomes useless before an attacker can act. OIDC-based auth for CI/CD (GitHub Actions, GitLab CI) eliminates long-lived service account keys entirely.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Application needs database credentials, API keys, or TLS certificates at runtime</item>
        <item>Kubernetes workloads require secrets without storing them as native K8s Secrets in plain base64</item>
        <item>CI/CD pipelines must authenticate to cloud providers without stored access keys</item>
        <item>Compliance requires secret rotation, audit logging, and access control (SOC2, HIPAA, PCI-DSS)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Development-only local environment — .env files are acceptable; do not add Vault overhead</item>
        <item>Secrets that are truly public (public API keys, non-sensitive config values) — use ConfigMaps, not secrets backends</item>
        <item>Single-cloud project where the cloud provider's native secrets service (AWS Secrets Manager, GCP Secret Manager) covers all use cases — adding Vault is unnecessary operational overhead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="secret-lifecycle">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every secret must have an owner, a rotation schedule, and an audit log — secrets without these three properties are unmanaged liabilities.</statement>
        <rationale>Unrotated secrets that are breached remain valid indefinitely. Without an audit log, breach investigation cannot determine when and which secrets were accessed.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Creation: generate with sufficient entropy (min 128-bit); never use predictable values</item>
        <item>Storage: encrypted at rest in a secrets backend; never in code, .env files, or ConfigMaps</item>
        <item>Access: RBAC with audit logging; each service gets its own identity, not shared credentials</item>
        <item>Rotation: automated 30-day max cycle; applications must handle rotation without restart</item>
        <item>Revocation: immediate revocation capability; test the revocation path before production</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="dynamic-vs-static-secrets">
      <rule>
        <statement>Prefer dynamic secrets (Vault database engine, cloud IAM short-lived tokens) over static secrets wherever the target system supports it.</statement>
        <rationale>Dynamic secrets are issued per-request with a short TTL (minutes to hours). A compromised dynamic credential expires before an attacker can typically exploit it. Static secrets are valid indefinitely until manually rotated.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Vault database secrets engine: application requests PostgreSQL credentials, Vault creates a role with 15-minute TTL, credentials are valid only for that request lifecycle. On expiry, the role is automatically revoked.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Shared DATABASE_URL in .env file with a password that was last rotated 18 months ago and is used by 5 different services.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="tool-selection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use HashiCorp Vault for multi-cloud or hybrid environments; use the cloud provider's native secrets service (AWS Secrets Manager, GCP Secret Manager, Azure Key Vault) for single-cloud workloads.</statement>
        <rationale>Vault adds operational overhead (HA cluster, unseal management, upgrades). If all workloads are in AWS, the operational simplicity of AWS Secrets Manager outweighs Vault's cross-cloud capabilities.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>HashiCorp Vault: multi-cloud, dynamic secrets, complex PKI, regulated industries</item>
        <item>AWS Secrets Manager: AWS-native, managed rotation for RDS/Redshift, pay-per-secret</item>
        <item>External Secrets Operator: Kubernetes bridge — syncs any backend into K8s Secrets</item>
        <item>SOPS: GitOps workflows, encrypts files in repos, no runtime server required</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cicd-secrets">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use OIDC-based authentication for CI/CD pipelines (GitHub Actions id-token, GitLab CI JWT) to eliminate long-lived service account keys entirely.</statement>
        <rationale>Service account keys stored in CI secrets rotate infrequently and are accessible to all pipeline users. OIDC tokens are issued per-run, expire in 15 minutes, and are scoped to the specific repository and branch.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Storing cloud provider access keys (AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID, GCP_SA_KEY) as CI/CD secrets.</description>
        <reason>Long-lived keys exposed in logs or to pipeline contributors grant persistent access. OIDC eliminates this risk entirely with no key to steal.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="external-secrets-operator">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use External Secrets Operator (ESO) as the standard Kubernetes integration layer — it supports all major backends (AWS SM, GCP SM, Azure KV, Vault) with a unified API.</statement>
        <rationale>Native Kubernetes Secrets are base64-encoded, not encrypted at rest by default. ESO syncs from an encrypted backend and recreates the K8s Secret automatically on rotation, without restarting pods.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# ClusterSecretStore — backend connection
apiVersion: external-secrets.io/v1beta1
kind: ClusterSecretStore
metadata:
  name: aws-secrets-manager
spec:
  provider:
    aws:
      service: SecretsManager
      region: us-east-1
      auth:
        jwt:
          serviceAccountRef:
            name: external-secrets-sa
            namespace: external-secrets
---
# ExternalSecret — specific secret sync
apiVersion: external-secrets.io/v1beta1
kind: ExternalSecret
metadata:
  name: db-credentials
  namespace: production
spec:
  refreshInterval: 1h
  secretStoreRef:
    name: aws-secrets-manager
    kind: ClusterSecretStore
  target:
    name: db-credentials
    creationPolicy: Owner
  data:
    - secretKey: password
      remoteRef:
        key: prod/app/db
        property: password
]]></code>
      </example>
      <reference path="templates/eso-secret-store.yaml">Complete ESO ClusterSecretStore + ExternalSecret example</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="irsa-workload-identity">
      <rule>
        <statement>On AWS EKS, use IRSA (IAM Roles for Service Accounts) to bind a Kubernetes ServiceAccount to an AWS IAM role — no AWS credentials in pods or Secrets.</statement>
        <rationale>IRSA uses OIDC token exchange: the pod presents a K8s JWT, AWS STS exchanges it for temporary credentials scoped to the IAM role. Credentials auto-rotate every hour.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: v1
kind: ServiceAccount
metadata:
  name: app-sa
  namespace: production
  annotations:
    eks.amazonaws.com/role-arn: arn:aws:iam::123456789012:role/app-prod-role
]]></code>
        <note>The IAM role trust policy must allow sts:AssumeRoleWithWebIdentity from the OIDC provider and restrict the sub claim to the specific namespace:serviceaccount.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="security-hardening">
      <rule>
        <statement>Enable envelope encryption for etcd using a KMS provider key — base64 encoding in native Secrets is not encryption.</statement>
        <rationale>Without envelope encryption, anyone with etcd access (backup files, etcd snapshots) can read all Kubernetes Secrets in plaintext after a simple base64 decode.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never log secrets: ensure application code masks credential values in logs and that Kubernetes audit logs do not capture Secret data.</statement>
        <rationale>Secrets in logs are effectively unencrypted and distributed — logs go to ELK/Loki, S3, and potentially third-party log aggregators.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Storing secrets in ConfigMaps because they are easier to manage.</description>
        <reason>ConfigMaps have no access control differentiation from regular config. Any pod that can read ConfigMaps in a namespace can read all secrets stored there.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <reference path="templates/vault-policy.hcl">Vault policy template with least-privilege path scoping</reference>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/eso-secret-store.yaml" purpose="ESO ClusterSecretStore + ExternalSecret for AWS Secrets Manager"/>
      <template path="templates/vault-policy.hcl" purpose="Vault policy template with least-privilege path scoping"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-audit.txt" purpose="LLM prompt for auditing secrets posture"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
