<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="gcp-storage">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>infrastructure-engineer</domain>
    <summary>Managed object storage with storage classes, lifecycle rules, CMEK encryption, IAM, and Cloud CDN for cost-optimized secure storage.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>gcp</tag>
      <tag>cloud-storage</tag>
      <tag>storage-classes</tag>
      <tag>lifecycle</tag>
      <tag>security</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>GCP Cloud Storage</title>
    <summary>GCP Cloud Storage is a managed object storage service for storing and accessing data on Google's infrastructure. It provides unified storage across storage classes, strong consistency, and integration with Google Cloud services. Choose appropriate storage classes based on access patterns, configure lifecycle rules for cost optimization, and implement security controls with IAM policies, encryption, and network isolation.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Cloud Storage provides unified storage across multiple storage classes, enabling cost-optimized architectures where data transitions from hot (frequently accessed) to cold (rarely accessed) tiers automatically or manually. Strong consistency guarantees ensure data integrity without eventual consistency issues. Native integration with Google Cloud services—BigQuery, Vertex AI, Cloud Functions, Dataflow—enables seamless data pipelines without intermediate storage transfers.</p>
      <p>The storage class model (Standard, Nearline, Coldline, Archive) with associated retrieval fees and minimum durations allows precise cost-per-access optimization. Rapid Storage (new, sub-millisecond latency) and Anywhere Cache enable high-performance scenarios without over-provisioning. Built-in versioning, bucket-level IAM policies, and CMEK encryption support compliance and security requirements for sensitive workloads.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Storing and accessing structured and unstructured data at any scale (bytes to petabytes).</item>
        <item>Building data pipelines with BigQuery, Vertex AI, or Dataflow requiring low-latency, cost-optimized storage.</item>
        <item>Distributing static assets globally using Cloud CDN integration with automated caching.</item>
        <item>Implementing compliance-driven retention and encryption strategies with CMEK support.</item>
        <item>Co-locating storage with compute resources in the same region to minimize latency and egress costs.</item>
        <item>Managing variable access patterns with Autoclass for automatic storage class transitions.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Applications requiring sub-millisecond latency on all operations—use Rapid Storage specifically; standard regional buckets add 10-50ms latency.</item>
        <item>Databases requiring ACID transactions and row-level locking—use Cloud SQL, Spanner, or Firestore instead.</item>
        <item>Streaming ingest with strict ordering guarantees—use Pub/Sub or Dataflow for ordered delivery.</item>
        <item>Multi-region active-active writes—buckets support read-after-write consistency in a single region; use Firestore for geo-distributed writes.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="storage-classes">
      <p>Cloud Storage offers four storage classes that differ in availability SLA, cost, and retrieval fees. The selection drives both monthly storage cost (per GB) and operational cost (per read/write/delete).</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Bucket storage class MUST be selected based on data access frequency: Standard for hot data (accessed &gt;1x/month), Nearline for warm data (accessed &lt;1x/month), Coldline for cold data (accessed &lt;1x/quarter), and Archive for compliance archives (accessed &lt;1x/year or policy-driven only). Buckets MUST NOT default to Standard for all tiers; misaligned storage class multiplies monthly storage costs 10-20x.</statement>
        <rationale>Storage cost per GB/month: Standard $0.020, Nearline $0.010, Coldline $0.004, Archive $0.0012. Retrieval fee per GB: Standard $0, Nearline $0.01, Coldline $0.02, Archive $0.05. For data accessed &lt;1x/month, Nearline cost = $0.01/GB stored + $0.01/GB retrieved = $0.02 total; Standard = $0.20 + $0 retrieval = $0.20 total (10x more). Archive for quarterly-accessed data pays $0.005 storage + $0.05 retrieval but quarterly cost = $0.005*90 + $0.05 = $0.50; yearly cost = $0.005*365 + $0.05*4 = $0.203 (4x cheaper than Coldline).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Storage class selection by access pattern">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Hot tier (accessed daily):
  - Use Standard
  - No retrieval fee, lowest per-request cost
  - Examples: application logs, active ML training data, user uploads

Warm tier (accessed weekly/monthly):
  - Use Nearline (30-day minimum duration)
  - $0.01/GB retrieval fee, $0.01/GB storage = cost-neutral at 1x/month
  - Examples: weekly reports, monthly analytics exports, recent backups

Cold tier (accessed quarterly):
  - Use Coldline (90-day minimum duration)
  - $0.02/GB retrieval fee, $0.004/GB storage
  - Examples: quarterly compliance audits, annual backups, archived logs

Archive tier (accessed &lt;1x/year or policy-driven):
  - Use Archive (365-day minimum duration)
  - $0.05/GB retrieval fee, $0.0012/GB storage
  - Examples: legal holds, compliance archives, disaster recovery long-term backups
]]></code>
        <note>Retrieve actual pricing from GCP console; rates change quarterly. Use gcloud storage buckets describe to verify current class.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Single Standard bucket for all data">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Stores 5TB total: 100GB accessed daily, 900GB accessed quarterly, 4TB archived
gcloud storage buckets create gs://all-data --storage-class=STANDARD
# Result: paying Standard rate ($0.020/GB) on 4TB archive data = $81.92/month
# vs Archive ($0.0012/GB) = $4.92/month. Cost multiplier = 16.6x on archive portion.
]]></code>
        <note>Split into separate buckets by access pattern, or use Autoclass for automatic transitions.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using Archive for data with unpredictable or bursty access patterns without understanding early deletion penalties.</description>
        <reason>Archive has 365-day minimum duration. If data is deleted after 200 days, you pay for the full 365 days ($0.0012 * 365 / 30 = $0.0146/GB month) but only used 200 days. Use Coldline (90-day) for unpredictable access instead.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="lifecycle-rules">
      <p>Lifecycle rules automate storage class transitions and data deletion, eliminating manual migration tasks. Rules trigger on object age, storage class, object count, or state (LIVE/ARCHIVED for versioned buckets).</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Buckets MUST define lifecycle rules that transition objects from Standard → Nearline (30d) → Coldline (90d) → Archive (365d) matching observed access patterns, unless data has a specific compliance retention period. Lifecycle rules MUST be tested on a sample dataset first and MUST NOT be applied retroactively to billions of objects without billing impact analysis. Rules for noncurrent versions MUST be configured separately from LIVE version transitions.</statement>
        <rationale>Lifecycle transitions are non-reversible; once data moves to Archive, retrieval fee ($0.05/GB) applies immediately. Testing on sample data with lifecycle dry-run (gcloud storage buckets update --dry-run) prevents unexpected cost surprises. Noncurrent versions (enabled by versioning) accumulate storage cost; cleaning them up on a 90-day schedule reduces cost 5-10x for high-write scenarios.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Lifecycle rule configuration">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# Transition to Nearline after 30 days
- action: SetStorageClass
  storage_class: NEARLINE
  condition:
    age: 30
    matchesStorageClass: [STANDARD]

# Transition to Coldline after 90 days
- action: SetStorageClass
  storage_class: COLDLINE
  condition:
    age: 90
    matchesStorageClass: [NEARLINE]

# Transition to Archive after 365 days
- action: SetStorageClass
  storage_class: ARCHIVE
  condition:
    age: 365
    matchesStorageClass: [COLDLINE]

# Delete noncurrent versions after 90 days
- action: Delete
  condition:
    age: 90
    isLive: false

# Delete objects with specific prefix after 30 days
- action: Delete
  condition:
    age: 30
    matchesPrefix: [temp/, logs/]
]]></code>
        <note>Dry-run with gcloud storage buckets update --dry-run to preview impact before applying to production.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Incomplete lifecycle configuration">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# Only transitions to Nearline; objects languish in Nearline indefinitely
- action: SetStorageClass
  storage_class: NEARLINE
  condition:
    age: 30

# Noncurrent versions never deleted; storage cost grows unbounded
# (No noncurrent version cleanup rule)
]]></code>
        <note>Define full transition chain (Standard → Nearline → Coldline → Archive) and cleanup for noncurrent versions.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Creating lifecycle rules that transition data based on assumptions about future access patterns without analyzing actual access logs.</description>
        <reason>Use Storage Insights or BigQuery export of storage logs to validate assumptions. Data accessed only in specific months (e.g., tax data accessed in Q1) benefits from time-based transitions; data accessed randomly needs Autoclass instead. Assumptions lead to premature transitions and high retrieval costs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="security-iam">
      <p>Cloud Storage IAM bindings enforce least-privilege access at bucket and object level. Use uniform bucket-level access to disable legacy ACLs and simplify access control. Service accounts enable application-to-bucket authentication without sharing long-lived credentials.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>All buckets MUST enable uniform bucket-level access (UBA) to replace legacy ACL-based access. Buckets MUST NOT grant allUsers or allAuthenticatedUsers roles except for explicitly public CDN/website buckets with separate Security policy. Service accounts MUST be granted least-privilege roles: storage.objectCreator (write-only), storage.objectViewer (read-only), storage.objectAdmin (read-write-delete) based on application needs. Cross-project access MUST use Service Account credentials with Workload Identity Federation for external callers.</statement>
        <rationale>Legacy ACLs (per-object, per-user) create matrix of access rules that are unmaintainable and audit-opaque. UBA simplifies to single policy per bucket, enabling centralized IAM review. Least-privilege prevents credential over-provisioning: an application writing logs needs objectCreator, not objectAdmin. Workload Identity Federation eliminates need to export and rotate service account keys, reducing key exposure surface to near-zero.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Secure IAM configuration">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Enable uniform bucket-level access (disable ACLs)
gcloud storage buckets update gs://my-bucket --uniform-bucket-level-access

# Grant service account minimal permissions
gcloud storage buckets add-iam-policy-binding gs://my-bucket \
  --member=serviceAccount:logger@myproject.iam.gserviceaccount.com \
  --role=roles/storage.objectCreator

gcloud storage buckets add-iam-policy-binding gs://my-bucket \
  --member=serviceAccount:reader@myproject.iam.gserviceaccount.com \
  --role=roles/storage.objectViewer

# Disable public access
gcloud storage buckets update gs://my-bucket --public-access-prevention=enforced
]]></code>
        <note>Use gcloud storage buckets get-iam-policy to audit bindings. Never grant allUsers except for explicitly public buckets.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Overpermissive IAM">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Grant allAuthenticatedUsers write access (anyone in organization can upload)
gcloud storage buckets add-iam-policy-binding gs://my-bucket \
  --member=allAuthenticatedUsers \
  --role=roles/storage.objectAdmin

# Grant application objectAdmin when it only needs to write logs
gcloud storage buckets add-iam-policy-binding gs://my-bucket \
  --member=serviceAccount:app@myproject.iam.gserviceaccount.com \
  --role=roles/storage.objectAdmin
]]></code>
        <note>Restrict access to minimum required. Use separate service accounts per application.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Sharing long-lived service account keys with applications instead of using Workload Identity or Workload Identity Federation.</description>
        <reason>Shared keys rotate infrequently and are exposed if code is open-sourced or logs are leaked. Workload Identity (in-GCP) and WIF (cross-cloud) bind Kubernetes service accounts or external identities (AWS STS, GitHub OIDC) to Google service accounts without keys. Rotate identities by changing role bindings; no key rotation needed.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="encryption">
      <p>Cloud Storage supports three encryption modes: Google-managed encryption keys (GMEK, default), customer-managed encryption keys (CMEK via Cloud KMS), and customer-supplied encryption keys (CSEK, deprecated). CMEK enables key rotation policies, audit logging of key usage, and compliance requirements (e.g., bring-your-own-key for regulated workloads).</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Buckets storing PII, financial data, or compliance-sensitive data MUST use CMEK encryption with Cloud KMS keys rotated at least annually. KMS keyring MUST be in the same location as the bucket to avoid cross-region key retrieval latency. KMS CryptoKey MUST grant storage.serviceAgent the cloudkms.cryptoKeyEncrypterDecrypter role automatically (or manually for fine-grained control). CSEK MUST NOT be used; it requires per-request key management and is operationally burdensome.</statement>
        <rationale>GMEK (default) encrypts data but uses Google-managed keys; customers cannot audit or rotate keys. CMEK enables key rotation policies (preventing unauthorized decryption if key is compromised), audit logging (Cloud Audit Logs records all encrypt/decrypt operations), and compliance evidence (demonstrate customer control over data encryption). CSEK requires managing per-object keys in application code, increasing operational risk. Cloud KMS in same location as bucket avoids 10-50ms cross-region latency on every encrypt/decrypt.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="CMEK bucket with KMS key">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Create Cloud KMS keyring in same region as bucket
gcloud kms keyrings create my-storage-kr --location=us-central1

# Create crypto key with 90-day rotation
gcloud kms keys create my-storage-key \
  --location=us-central1 \
  --keyring=my-storage-kr \
  --purpose=encryption-decryption \
  --rotation-period=7776000s

# Grant Cloud Storage service account KMS permissions (automatic in some cases)
gcloud kms keys add-iam-policy-binding my-storage-key \
  --location=us-central1 \
  --keyring=my-storage-kr \
  --member=serviceAccount:service-PROJECT_NUMBER@gs-project-accounts.iam.gserviceaccount.com \
  --role=roles/cloudkms.cryptoKeyEncrypterDecrypter

# Create bucket with CMEK
gcloud storage buckets create gs://encrypted-data \
  --location=us-central1 \
  --default-encryption-key=projects/my-project/locations/us-central1/keyRings/my-storage-kr/cryptoKeys/my-storage-key
]]></code>
        <note>KMS key rotation is automatic after configured rotation_period. Monitor Cloud Audit Logs for encrypt/decrypt operations.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Relying on default GMEK">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# No explicit encryption configuration; uses Google-managed keys
gcloud storage buckets create gs://compliance-data --location=us-central1
# Compliance audit: "Who manages encryption keys?" Answer: Google. Risk: no customer control.
]]></code>
        <note>Use CMEK for compliance-sensitive data to demonstrate customer control and enable key rotation.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using CSEK (customer-supplied keys) to comply with bring-your-own-key requirements.</description>
        <reason>CSEK requires managing keys in application code (HTTP header X-Goog-Encryption-Key on every request). If key is lost, data is irrecoverable. Use CMEK + Cloud KMS instead: manage keys in KMS (Google-operated HSM), audit via Cloud Audit Logs, rotate via policy, no per-request key management.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="bucket-location-types">
      <p>Buckets can be regional (single region, low latency), dual-region (two regions, high availability), or multi-regional (continent, global distribution). Location choice impacts latency, cost, compliance, and disaster recovery.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Buckets accessed from a single Compute Engine region MUST be regional in that same region to minimize latency and eliminate inter-region egress charges. Buckets requiring high availability and disaster recovery MUST be dual-region (two specific regions selected by Google for geographic separation) to survive single-region outages. Buckets serving global traffic MUST be multi-regional (continent-scoped: US, EU, ASIA) for lowest latency to all users. Regional buckets MUST NOT be changed to dual/multi-region post-creation (bucket location is immutable); plan location before creating. Compliance requirements (data residency) MUST be verified before location selection; some regulations require data to stay in specific country/region.</statement>
        <rationale>Same-region access: zero egress cost, 10-20ms latency. Cross-region egress: $0.12/GB. Regional bucket accessed from different region = expensive and slow. Dual-region enables RTO/RPO compliance (disaster recovery; data survives region failure). Multi-regional provides global distribution but at higher cost (3 copies, one per continent). Bucket location is immutable; changing requires copying to new bucket (time, cost, downtime).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Bucket location selection">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Regional bucket (same as Compute Engine)
gcloud storage buckets create gs://app-data \
  --location=us-central1

# Dual-region (high availability)
gcloud storage buckets create gs://critical-data \
  --location=us \
  --storage-class=dual-region-standard

# Multi-regional (global distribution)
gcloud storage buckets create gs://cdn-assets \
  --location=us \
  --storage-class=multi-region-standard
]]></code>
        <note>Dual-region and multi-region are location-classes, not separate bucket types. Standard, Nearline, Coldline, Archive apply to all.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Location mismatch">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Bucket in europe-west1, but accessed from us-central1
gcloud storage buckets create gs://data --location=europe-west1
# Result: every GCS operation crosses continents, 100-200ms latency, $0.12/GB egress
]]></code>
        <note>Co-locate bucket with primary access region.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Creating multi-region buckets for all data to "maximize availability" when single-region or dual-region is sufficient.</description>
        <reason>Multi-region (continent-scoped) stores 3 copies and costs more. For most applications, regional + backup (cross-region replication) is better. Only use multi-region if you have users across continents and need sub-100ms latency everywhere.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="caching-cdn">
      <p>Cloud CDN caches Cloud Storage content in Google's edge locations globally, reducing origin load and latency. Configure backend buckets with cache policies, TTLs, and Cloud Armor for DDoS/WAF protection.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Public static content MUST be served through Cloud CDN with cache mode CACHE_ALL_STATIC for assets (CSS, JS, images) and CACHE_BASED_ON_HEADERS for dynamic content. Cache TTLs MUST be set per content type: 1-year for versioned assets, 1-week for images, &lt;5 seconds for API responses. Origin bucket MUST be in a separate IAM space from private data buckets; public CDN bucket MUST grant allUsers storage.objectViewer role only, never storage.objectAdmin.</statement>
        <rationale>CACHE_ALL_STATIC caches immutable content (versioned file names with hash: app.abc123.js) indefinitely; prevents "stale" served content by design. Dynamic content uses Cache-Control header from origin to determine TTL. Cache hit ratios of 95%+ reduce origin load 20x and latency 5x. Separate buckets prevent accidentally granting CDN public access to private data. Cloud Armor (bot protection, geo-blocking, rate limiting) applied at load balancer prevents DDoS and abuse.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Cloud CDN with versioned assets">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Create public CDN bucket
gcloud storage buckets create gs://cdn-assets \
  --location=US \
  --storage-class=standard

# Grant public read access
gcloud storage buckets add-iam-policy-binding gs://cdn-assets \
  --member=allUsers \
  --role=roles/storage.objectViewer

# Upload versioned assets
gsutil -h "Cache-Control:public, max-age=31536000" \
  cp app.abc123.js gs://cdn-assets/

# Configure Cloud CDN (via gcloud compute backend-buckets create)
gcloud compute backend-buckets create cdn-backend \
  --gcs-bucket-name=cdn-assets \
  --cache-mode=CACHE_ALL_STATIC \
  --client-ttl=3600 \
  --default-ttl=3600 \
  --max-ttl=86400
]]></code>
        <note>Versioned asset names (hash in filename) enable aggressive caching; cache keys include URL path, not just domain.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Single bucket for public and private content">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Public bucket grants allUsers access to everything
gcloud storage buckets add-iam-policy-binding gs://data \
  --member=allUsers \
  --role=roles/storage.objectViewer

# Private files (API keys, user data) also stored in same bucket
gsutil cp private-keys.json gs://data/
gsutil cp user-data.csv gs://data/
# Result: allUsers can download private-keys.json and user-data.csv
]]></code>
        <note>Use separate buckets: gs://cdn-assets (public) and gs://private-data (IAM-restricted).</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Setting very high TTLs (e.g., max-ttl=31536000 / 1 year) on all content without versioning strategy.</description>
        <reason>If you serve app.js with 1-year TTL and then deploy a bug fix, cached clients won't download new version for 365 days. Always version mutable content (app.v2.js, app.v3.js) and serve versioned URLs with aggressive TTL. Unversioned content (index.html) should have short TTL (&lt;1 hour) to enable rapid deploy-to-live cycles.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="performance-optimization">
      <p>Cloud Storage performance depends on latency (co-location with compute), throughput (parallel operations, Rapid Storage), and request rate (object name distribution). Rapid Storage (new, 2025) provides &lt;1ms latency for low-latency workloads; Anywhere Cache provides consistent caching for regional buckets.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Buckets accessed from Compute Engine or Kubernetes Engine MUST be co-located in the same region to minimize latency and eliminate egress charges. Buckets with latency-critical workloads (&lt;10ms p99) MUST use Rapid Storage (available in specific zones: us-central1-a, us-central1-b, us-central1-c, and growing). Parallel uploads/downloads MUST use gsutil -m (multiprocessing) or client library parallel composite uploads for files &gt;150MB to maximize throughput.</statement>
        <rationale>Cross-region egress costs $0.12/GB (intra-region is free). Latency: intra-region read = 10-20ms, cross-region = 100-200ms, cold start in Rapid Storage = 0.5-1ms. Rapid Storage trades cost ($0.035/GB/month vs $0.020 Standard) for 20x latency reduction. Parallel operations enable throughput: 4 parallel uploads of 40MB each = 160MB/s; sequential uploads = 40MB/s.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="High-throughput upload with parallelism">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Use gsutil -m for parallel uploads
gsutil -m -o "GSUtil:parallel_thread_count=32" cp -r ./large-dataset gs://my-bucket/

# Or use gcloud storage cp with --recursive for native parallel transfer
gcloud storage cp --recursive ./large-dataset gs://my-bucket/

# For application code: use client library parallel composite uploads
# Python: google-cloud-storage enables parallel_composite_upload=True
from google.cloud import storage
client = storage.Client()
bucket = client.bucket('my-bucket')
blob = bucket.blob('large-file.tar.gz')
blob.upload_from_filename('/path/to/large-file.tar.gz',
                          max_workers=16)  # 16 parallel threads
]]></code>
        <note>Parallel uploads require minimum file size (~32MB per part). Monitor gcloud storage help for latest performance options.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Sequential uploads without parallelism">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Sequential upload: each file waits for previous to complete
for file in dataset/*; do
  gcloud storage cp "$file" gs://my-bucket/
done
# Result: if each file is 100MB and avg latency is 1s, 1000 files = 1000s = 16+ minutes
]]></code>
        <note>Use parallel transfers (gsutil -m or native --recursive) to reduce time 10-20x.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using random object name prefixes (UUIDs) to avoid "hot object" throttling, then later discovering aggregate throughput is still bottlenecked.</description>
        <reason>Request rate limiting applies per bucket, not per object. Randomizing prefixes reduces per-object request rate throttling (rare edge case) but doesn't increase overall bucket throughput. Root cause of slowness is usually co-location, parallelism, or network path; fix those first. Only use prefix randomization if explicitly hitting per-object rate limits and confirmed by gcloud monitoring.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="versioning-retention">
      <p>Object versioning enables keeping multiple versions of objects, recovering from accidental deletes or overwrites. Noncurrent version retention policies manage storage cost for versioned buckets. Retention policies enforce legal holds or compliance requirements preventing deletion.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Versioning MUST be enabled for buckets storing critical or compliance-sensitive data (backups, legal documents, financial records). Versioning SHOULD NOT be enabled for high-volume logs or temporary data to avoid storage cost explosion. Noncurrent version retention policy MUST be configured: delete noncurrent versions after X days (typically 30-90 days) to bound storage cost. Retention policies (legal hold, indefinite retention) MUST be applied only when compliance requires it; they prevent deletion and should be documented with retention justification. Versioning queries (list-versions, get version history) SHOULD be done via BigQuery audit logs, not gcloud directly, for large version counts.</statement>
        <rationale>Versioning prevents data loss from accidental overwrites or deletes: rollback to previous version instantly. Cost: each version consumes storage (versioned bucket = 2x cost if every object is rewritten). Noncurrent version cleanup (e.g., keep 3 versions, delete older) prevents unbounded growth. Retention policies lock data for compliance (SOC2, HIPAA, PCI-DSS); they cannot be removed until retention period expires. Large version histories (millions of versions) slow gcloud operations; BigQuery is more efficient for analytics.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Versioning with noncurrent cleanup">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Enable versioning for backup bucket
gcloud storage buckets update gs://my-backups --versioning

# View versions of an object
gcloud storage objects describe gs://my-backups/backup-2026-04-29.tar.gz --all-versions

# Retrieve specific version
gcloud storage cp gs://my-backups/backup-2026-04-29.tar.gz#VERSION_ID ./backup-restore.tar.gz

# Configure noncurrent version cleanup via lifecycle (see lifecycle-rules section)
# Keep only 3 noncurrent versions, delete older
{
  "rule": [
    {
      "action": {"type": "Delete"},
      "condition": {"numNewerVersions": 3, "isLive": false}
    }
  ]
}
]]></code>
        <note>Version IDs are generation tokens. Retrieve specific version with #VERSION_ID syntax.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Versioning without cleanup">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Enable versioning but don't configure noncurrent cleanup
gcloud storage buckets update gs://my-backups --versioning
# Every update creates new version; after 1000 overwrites, storage cost = 1000x
# Noncurrent versions keep accumulating forever
]]></code>
        <note>Configure lifecycle rules to delete noncurrent versions after X days.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using versioning as a backup mechanism instead of geographic replication or cross-bucket replication.</description>
        <reason>Versioning protects against logical errors (accidental delete, overwrite) but not against bucket deletion or regional disaster. For true backup, use cross-region replication (dual-region bucket) or replicate to a different bucket in a different region. Versioning + replication = defense in depth.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="signed-urls-access">
      <p>Signed URLs grant temporary, limited access to objects without requiring IAM binding. Useful for short-lived file sharing, upload forms, or public downloads with expiration. Signed URLs include cryptographic signature preventing tampering.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Signed URLs MUST be used for temporary access (hours, not days). Signed URL duration MUST match use case: 1 hour for form uploads, 15 minutes for API responses, 1 day for file downloads. Signed URLs MUST be generated by authorized principals (service account with signing permissions) not users; users receive the signed URL. HTTPS MUST be used when transmitting signed URLs to prevent interception (HTTPS is enforced for gcloud operations but document this for custom implementations). Signed URLs MUST NOT be embedded in logs or monitoring (they are bearer tokens); if leaked, anyone can access the object until expiration. Signed policies (for HTML forms) MUST be preferred over embedded signed URLs in web pages.</statement>
        <rationale>Signed URLs avoid granting permanent IAM access: generate URL on-demand, expires after time period. HTTPS ensures URL is not sniffed. Short duration (1h) limits damage if URL is leaked. Signed policies enable browser-based uploads without backend intermediary (form POST with policy + signature). Documentation of duration prevents accidental long-term access (30-day signed URLs are bearer tokens; 30-day is too long for security).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Generate signed URL for download">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Generate 1-hour signed URL for download
gcloud storage sign-url \
  --duration=1h \
  service-account.json \
  gs://my-bucket/private-file.pdf

# Output: https://storage.googleapis.com/my-bucket/private-file.pdf?X-Goog-Algorithm=GOOG4-RSA-SHA256&X-Goog-Credential=...&X-Goog-Expires=3600&X-Goog-SignedHeaders=host&X-Goog-Signature=...

# Recipient can download without GCP credentials
curl https://storage.googleapis.com/my-bucket/private-file.pdf?X-Goog-Algorithm=...
]]></code>
        <note>Signed URL includes expiration in query string. After expiration, access denied.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Upload form with signed policy">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Generate signed policy for form uploads
gcloud storage sign-url \
  --duration=1h \
  --http-verb=PUT \
  service-account.json \
  gs://my-bucket/uploads/user-file.txt

# Browser sends PUT request with signed policy, no backend intermediary needed
]]></code>
        <note>Signed policy enables client-side uploads; backend generates policy, browser uploads directly to Cloud Storage.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Generating long-duration signed URLs (days/months) to avoid regenerating them frequently.</description>
        <reason>Long-duration signed URLs are bearer tokens; if leaked, attacker has access for entire duration. Generate URLs on-demand with short duration. Backend generates URL per request (seconds of overhead), not hours of convenience.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="monitoring-logging">
      <p>Cloud Audit Logs record all bucket/object operations (Admin Activity, Data Access, System Events). Cloud Storage Insights provides analytics (object count, size distribution, age distribution). Cloud Monitoring enables alerting on cost and usage anomalies.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Buckets MUST enable Data Access audit logging (roles: storage.GetIamPolicy, storage.ListBucket, storage.GetObject, storage.PutObject, storage.DeleteObject) for compliance/security audits. Data Access logs MUST be exported to BigQuery for long-term retention and alerting. Storage Insights MUST be enabled for buckets &gt;100GB to identify unused data and optimize storage class allocation. Cost anomaly alerts MUST be configured in Cloud Monitoring to notify on unexpected egress or early deletion charges.</statement>
        <rationale>Admin Activity logs (on by default) record bucket creation/deletion but not object reads. Data Access logs (opt-in, billable ~$5-10 per 100GB after free tier) record every operation for audit trails. Exporting to BigQuery enables retention beyond 90 days and SQL queries to identify patterns (e.g., which users access which objects, hourly access distribution). Storage Insights costs $0.10 per GB/month analyzed; ROI is high for large buckets (identify 10TB unused data = $200/month savings).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Logging and monitoring setup">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Enable Data Access audit logging (BigQuery export)
gcloud logging sinks create storage-sink bigquery.googleapis.com/projects/my-project/datasets/audit_logs \
  --log-filter='resource.type=gcs_bucket AND protoPayload.serviceName=storage.googleapis.com'

# Create BigQuery dataset for audit logs
bq mk --dataset --location=US audit_logs

# Enable Storage Insights
gcloud storage buckets update gs://my-bucket --enable-storage-insights

# Set up cost anomaly alert in Cloud Monitoring
gcloud monitoring alerts create \
  --notification-channels=CHANNEL_ID \
  --display-name="Storage cost spike" \
  --condition-display-name="Monthly egress > $100" \
  --condition-expression='resource.type=gcs_bucket AND metric.type=storage.googleapis.com/network/egress_bytes'
]]></code>
        <note>Data Access logs incur write cost; use --sampling (e.g., sample 10% of reads to reduce cost).</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="No monitoring or logging">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Bucket created with default settings (Admin Activity logging only)
gcloud storage buckets create gs://data
# No Data Access logs → can't audit who accessed which objects
# No Storage Insights → unaware of 50GB old data in Standard class ($10/month wasted)
# No cost alerts → $2000 unexpected egress charge discovered in invoice
]]></code>
        <note>Enable logging and monitoring at bucket creation. Retroactive logging requires re-enabling (future operations only).</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Enabling Data Access logging for all operations without sampling, generating massive BigQuery tables and high egress/write costs.</description>
        <reason>Data Access logs are billable. A bucket with 1M daily operations = 30M rows/month in BigQuery. Use --log-filter to exclude routine operations (e.g., exclude storage.GetObject operations from monitoring app reads) and --sampling to log only 1% of high-volume operations. Balance audit trail completeness with cost.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates.md" purpose="Terraform code examples for bucket creation, lifecycle rules, CMEK encryption, CDN integration, and reusable modules"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://cloud.google.com/storage/docs"/>
      <link href="https://cloud.google.com/storage/docs/best-practices"/>
      <link href="https://cloud.google.com/storage/docs/lifecycle"/>
      <link href="https://cloud.google.com/storage/docs/encryption/customer-managed-keys"/>
      <link href="https://cloud.google.com/cdn/docs/setting-up-cdn-with-bucket"/>
      <ref slug="gcp-arch-basics"/>
      <ref slug="gcp-arch-patterns"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
