<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Project Closure Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the project-closure methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="signed-acceptance-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Obtain written sign-off from the accepting authority for every deliverable before declaring closure complete. Silence does not equal acceptance.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK 7 Closure; ISO 21502">Ambiguous completion creates re-opened projects, warranty disputes, and resource limbo. A signed artefact is the only auditable evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="acceptance-criteria-precede-closure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Acceptance criteria must be observable and agreed before closure starts — they cannot be written retrospectively to match delivered output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit practice">Retrospective criteria always pass; they destroy the value of the gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="lessons-before-dispersal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conduct lessons learned before the team disperses; schedule it at project kickoff as a fixed deliverable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Retrospective facilitation practice">Memories fade within days and teams scatter to new projects within hours of delivery; a session two weeks post-close captures platitudes, not facts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="staged-decommission" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decommission infrastructure in stages: read-only first, then revoke writes, then deprovision. Default to 30-day soft-delete before hard deletion.</statement>
      <rationale source="SRE / change-management practice">Staged decommission allows recovery if handover is incomplete; hard-deletion of cloud resources risks irreversible data loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="access-revocation-after-handover" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sequence access revocation after operations handover acknowledgement — never revoke before the receiving team confirms readiness.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operations handover playbooks">Premature revocation breaks ongoing operations and is harder to reverse than to delay.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cancellation-rationale-signed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For cancelled projects, document the cancellation rationale in a signed document with the sponsor's name.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field experience">Cancelled project rationale is the most frequently lost institutional knowledge; same idea resurfaces 18 months later with the same failure mode.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Project still has open scope, unresolved issues, or unsigned acceptance — resolve those first</item>
      <item>Operational or run-rate work with no defined endpoint — use service transition documents instead</item>
      <item>Long-tail support work after handover — that is operations, not project closure</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
