<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-closure-steps" title="Seven Project Closure Steps">
  <summary>Ordered closure steps from deliverable acceptance through team recognition, with rules for each gate.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Verify Deliverable Acceptance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Obtain written sign-off from the accepting authority for every deliverable before declaring the project closed. Silence does not equal acceptance.</statement>
      <rationale>Ambiguous completion status creates re-opened projects, warranty disputes, and resource limbo. A signed artefact is the only auditable evidence of acceptance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Acceptance criteria must be observable and agreed before closure starts — they cannot be written retrospectively to match the delivered output.</statement>
      <rationale>Retrospective criteria are subjective and always pass; they destroy the value of the gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/deliverable-acceptance.md">Deliverable acceptance form with criteria table</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Administrative Closure">
    <list>
      <item>Financial: process final invoices, close purchase orders, return unused budget, reconcile final costs (flag delayed net-60 vendor invoices as pending — do not auto-zero)</item>
      <item>Resource: release team members, return equipment, revoke access permissions, notify resource managers</item>
      <item>Contract: send termination letters, archive agreements, complete warranty/support handover</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Sequence access revocation after operations handover acknowledgement — never revoke before the receiving team confirms readiness.</statement>
      <rationale>Premature access revocation during handover breaks ongoing operations and is harder to reverse than to delay.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Lessons Learned">
    <rule>
      <statement>Conduct the lessons learned session before the team disperses, not after. Schedule it at project kickoff as a fixed deliverable.</statement>
      <rationale>Memories fade within days and teams scatter to new projects within hours of a delivery. A lesson-learned session two weeks post-close captures platitudes, not facts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store lessons in a queryable format (structured YAML or database), not in a slide deck. Each lesson: what happened, root cause, recommendation, project context.</statement>
      <rationale>Slide decks are never searched; structured lessons are findable by project type, risk category, or team name.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Steps 4-7: Archive, Report, Transition, Recognise">
    <rule>
      <statement>Archive project documents in a structure that matches future search intent: Planning, Execution, Technical, Contracts, Closure. Tag with project type and key outcomes.</statement>
      <rationale>Unstructured archives are effectively deleted — nobody finds them. Structure by intended reuse, not by creation order.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Decommission infrastructure in stages: read-only first, then revoke writes, then deprovision. Default to 30-day soft-delete before hard deletion.</statement>
      <rationale>Staged decommission allows recovery if handover is incomplete. Hard-deletion of cloud resources without a hold period risks irreversible data loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include a team recognition event. Budget it from kickoff as a project line item, not as an afterthought when budgets are exhausted.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping recognition damages future engagement and signals that completion is the PM's success, not the team's.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/closure-checklist.md">Complete closure checklist by category</reference>
  <reference path="templates/closure-audit.py">Python auditor for closure_checklist.yaml</reference>
</text>
