<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-closure-types" title="Closure Variants and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Four closure types (normal, early success, cancelled, integration) and the agent failure modes that produce incomplete or fraudulent closure records.</summary>

  <section title="Closure Types">
    <list>
      <item>Normal — objectives met, full closure process applies</item>
      <item>Early (success) — objectives met ahead of schedule, accelerated closure with same gate sequence</item>
      <item>Early (cancelled) — document completed work percentage, recover reusable assets, record cancellation rationale formally to prevent same idea resurfacing without learning</item>
      <item>Integration — project absorbed into operations, transition-focused closure with extra emphasis on runbooks, monitoring handover, and CMDB updates</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>For cancelled projects, document the cancellation rationale in a signed document with the sponsor's name. An informal "we changed direction" leaves the next team without context.</statement>
      <rationale>Cancelled project rationale is the most frequently lost institutional knowledge; it reappears as the same initiative 18 months later with the same failure mode.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent marks closure complete based on issue-tracker "Done" state alone.</description>
      <reason>Done status is self-reported by the team. Acceptance requires a signed artefact from the accepting authority — a different party with independent verification.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent generates lessons learned from ticket history and meeting minutes without human contribution.</description>
      <reason>Agent-generated lessons are pattern-matched platitudes from training data, not project-specific facts. Require quoted contributions attributed to named participants.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent sets final cost to zero because no open invoices appear in the system.</description>
      <reason>Net-60 vendor invoices arrive after project close. Final cost must be flagged as "pending invoices" until the invoice window closes, not auto-zeroed.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent publishes the closure packet without access control.</description>
      <reason>Closure packets contain salaries, vendor rates, and customer data. Restrict access before agents publish or distribute.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/handover.md">Operations handover document template</reference>
</text>
