<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="continuous-discovery Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for continuous-discovery. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Implement all six cadence levels (daily signal collection, weekly interviews, weekly competitor monitoring, weekly assumption testing, bi-weekly OST synthesis, monthly research review) or the practice degrades to a research graveyard.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Assumption testing is the first step teams skip because it feels slower than shipping. Without an explicit weekly slot backed by a scheduled agent, it disappears within a month.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use cheap models (Haiku) for daily mechanical collection, Sonnet for weekly structured synthesis, Opus only for bi-weekly+ pattern recognition—never invert this.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opus on daily ticket triage burns tokens for no marginal value. The cadence model matches cost to the depth of reasoning required at each stage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Wire cadence agents via cron/systemd timers on NERO; use the loop skill or schedule skill for managed triggers—do not run on demand only.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Continuous discovery requires consistency. On-demand execution produces sporadic data that cannot reveal trends over time. Scheduled agents create the rhythm that makes the practice work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use this exact XML prompt structure for every cadence agent—roles, inputs, rules, and task—with the Torres framework constraints hardcoded in the rules block.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents trained on generic UX content drift into "validation theater" and solution mining without explicit Torres-vocabulary constraints. Hardcoding the rules block prevents terminology drift across agent runs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ban the word "validated" from all agent prompts and outputs—use "assumption tested" or "evidence found" instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Torres explicitly rejects "validation theater". Agents trained on generic UX content conflate validation (proving a hypothesis) with testing (gathering evidence). The word ban forces the right framing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require N &gt;= 5 observations across at least 2 independent sources before any finding is published—reject completions that violate this rule.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs love to declare "insights" from thin signal. A single viral Slack thread or one angry review is not a pattern. Five observations across two source types is the minimum for a credible signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Force "opportunity vs solution" classification at intake; reject any item phrased as a feature ("add filter X") and re-prompt for the underlying need.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Teams revert to solution mode under time pressure. The explicit classification at intake, backed by rejection, maintains discovery discipline even when stakeholders deliver solution-shaped requests.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score opportunities on (frequency × severity × addressability), not gut feel; emit numeric scores and surface deltas week-over-week.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Gut-feel prioritization in OSTs is unauditable. Numeric scores with week-over-week deltas reveal which opportunities are gaining or losing urgency and enable evidence-based ranking.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Add an explicit lint step that flags any term in agent output not present in the last 20 interview transcripts—agents trained on internal docs use jargon that users do not.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Internal jargon in opportunities ("improve the onboarding wizard UX") signals that the agent is reasoning from product assumptions, not from the user's mental model. The transcript lint catches this before it enters the OST.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin one Outcome at the OST root before any opportunity work—without it agents drift into solution mining.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opportunityless trees collapse into unordered feature wishlists. A single metric-based outcome (e.g., "W1 activation rate: 30% to 45%") focuses all subsequent discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain an open-assumptions.md register; every opportunity branched into a solution must spawn at least one assumption with a falsifiable test.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a hypothesis register, solution work proceeds without discovery grounding. Each solution must answer "what assumption does this test?"</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rotate the human reviewer of synthesis output weekly—agents anchor on patterns; humans catch curse-of-knowledge.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A single reviewer produces blind spots. Weekly rotation surfaces assumptions that the regular reviewer stopped questioning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap interview synthesis to 5 themes per session; more = noise. Discovery-synthesizer aggregates across sessions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Too many themes per session dilute signal. Aggregating across multiple sessions reveals true patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every research-reviewer monthly pass must produce a kill list (parked/dead opportunities)—without pruning, OSTs collapse under their own weight.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opportunities accumulate faster than they are resolved. A monthly kill list keeps the tree shallow and iterable and prevents discovery from becoming a graveyard.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tie discovery output to delivery: reference opportunity IDs in PR titles and SDD spec.md ("spec cites opp_xxx").</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Discovery output without delivery linkage has no feedback loop. Referencing opportunity IDs in code commits and specs enables retrospective analysis of which discoveries led to shipped features.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r16" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Token budget: cap weekly synth at ~30k tokens, monthly at ~80k; otherwise opus costs balloon.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unbounded context for opus synthesis costs spiral. Preset budgets force compression of inputs and keep economics sustainable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
