<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Continuous Discovery Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Continuous Discovery methodology. Every rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale, plus the universal skip-this-methodology gate.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="six-cadence-levels" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Implement all 6 cadence levels (daily signal/ticket, weekly interview + competitor + assumption, bi-weekly OST, monthly review) or the practice degrades into a research graveyard.</statement>
      <rationale source="Teresa Torres, Continuous Discovery Habits (2021)">Assumption testing is the first step teams skip; without a scheduled slot it disappears in 4 weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="model-tier-by-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Haiku for daily mechanical collection; Sonnet for weekly synthesis; Opus only for bi-weekly+ pattern recognition.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anthropic — Building Effective Agents">Opus on daily triage burns tokens for no marginal value; the cadence must match reasoning depth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ban-validated-word" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ban the word 'validated' in agent prompts and outputs; use 'assumption tested' or 'evidence found' instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Torres, Continuous Discovery Habits">Torres explicitly rejects validation theater; the word ban forces the right framing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="n5-across-2-sources" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require N&gt;=5 observations across at least 2 independent sources before any 'finding' is published; reject completions that violate this.</statement>
      <rationale source="Torres + internal — Q1 2026 schema-enforcement">LLMs declare insights from thin signal; one Slack thread is not a pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="opportunity-vs-solution-intake" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Force opportunity-vs-solution classification at intake; reject feature-shaped requests ('add filter X') and re-prompt for the underlying need.</statement>
      <rationale source="Torres, OST chapter">Teams revert to solution mode under pressure; the rejection rule maintains discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="score-freq-x-sev-x-addr" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score opportunities on frequency x severity x addressability; emit numeric scores with week-over-week deltas.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — OST scoring policy">Gut-feel prioritization is unauditable; deltas reveal urgency shifts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="curse-of-knowledge-lint" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lint every agent output for terms not present in the last 20 interview transcripts.</statement>
      <rationale source="Torres + internal jargon audits">Internal jargon in opportunities signals reasoning from product assumptions, not user mental models.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="monthly-kill-list-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every monthly research-review pass MUST produce a kill list (parked/dead opportunities); without pruning OSTs collapse under their own weight.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Q4 2025 OST autopsy">Opportunities accumulate faster than they resolve; pruning keeps the tree iterable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only if all entries in `## Applies If` hold and none of `## Skip If` triggers; otherwise abort and route to the correct methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — decision tree minimum form">A misrouted methodology produces wrong-shape output; the explicit skip rule is the universal default branch from the decision tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
