<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="continuous-discovery Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for continuous-discovery as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Recruiting fatigue: weekly interviews require a recurring source—without infrastructure the cadence collapses by week 4.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mitigation: in-app prompt, customer panel, Userinterviews.com, or a scheduled recruiter agent. Recruiting infrastructure is a prerequisite for continuous discovery at scale.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Curse-of-knowledge bias persists if the same trio interprets every interview—internal assumptions lock in.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Rotate observers, use Looppanel/Dovetail tagging across team members. Different reviewers catch blind spots.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Assumption testing is often skipped because it feels slower than shipping.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without an explicit weekly slot it disappears. Use the scheduled assumption-tester agent and review results in weekly synthesis.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>AI synthesis hallucinates patterns from small N—LLM declares "insight" from &lt;5 interviews without human cross-tag.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Never let an LLM declare an "insight" from &lt;5 observations across &lt;2 sources. Schema enforcement: reject completions violating N&gt;=5 rule.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>OSTs rot when not pruned—opportunities accumulate; monthly archival is skipped.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Opportunities accumulate faster than resolved. Require monthly kill list from research-reviewer; without pruning OSTs collapse under weight.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Discovery output without delivery linkage becomes a research graveyard.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every opportunity must trace to either a tested assumption or a deliberate "park" decision. Tie to delivery: reference opp IDs in PR titles and spec.md.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs invent "insights" from thin signal without enforcing N&gt;=5 rule in schema.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Reject completions that violate N&gt;=5. Schema enforcement is the only reliable guard—prompt instructions alone are insufficient.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Transcription tools mis-attribute speakers; agents conflate interviewer leading questions with user statements.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Strip interviewer turns before synthesis. Only user statements should feed the interview-synthesizer.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Models hallucinate competitor changelog entries when scraping fails; competitor-monitor outputs invented features.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require explicit URL + fetched-at timestamp in every competitor-monitor row. No updates without a source.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Daily Haiku watchers overwrite the insight log instead of appending atomically.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use atomic append + lock file, never Write. Concurrent watcher runs without locking corrupt the log and lose audit trail.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Bi-weekly synthesizer with full week's context can exceed context window.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-summarize per-day with Haiku, feed summaries to Opus. Full-week raw context overflows and silently truncates.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Subagents that write to Dovetail/Notion via API create duplicate notes if retried without idempotency.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require idempotency keys (hash of source URL + date) for all API writes. Retries without idempotency multiply notes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Assumption-tester proposes "ship and measure" as a valid test type.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>That is delivery, not discovery. Constrain to: smoke test, fake door, prototype, Wizard of Oz, concierge, Mom Test, data dive.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Long-running cron agents accumulate state drift; schema validation is never run.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Have research-reviewer run monthly schema-validation pass over OST + assumptions register. Prevents entropy.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Privacy: raw PII transcripts fed to non-zero-retention models.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use Anthropic ZDR-eligible endpoints or strip PII pre-prompt. Interview transcripts are sensitive data.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Recruitment automation violates panel ToS (Userinterviews limits weekly batch size).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Rate-limit at agent level. Check service ToS and adjust cadence to comply.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
