<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-task-format" title="Task Format v2.0 and INVEST Validation">
  <summary>The canonical TASK_*.md format with all required fields, INVEST validation criteria, three worked complexity examples, file action reference, and dependency type reference.</summary>

  <section title="Required Fields">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every TASK_*.md must contain all these fields in order: ID (TASK-NNN), Phase, Wave, Description (2-3 sentences), Traces To (AD-X and FR-X), Depends On, Blocks, Complexity (simple/normal/complex), Context Estimate, Acceptance Criteria, Files table (Action/File/Purpose), Technical Notes, Tests checklist.</statement>
      <rationale>The executor agent parses TASK files mechanically. Missing fields cause the executor to either halt or proceed with wrong assumptions. Including FR-X and AD-X text inline means the executor does not need to load spec.md or design.md during execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/task-template.md">Blank TASK_*.md skeleton with all required fields and placeholder comments.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Complexity Levels">
    <list>
      <item>simple: 10-30k tokens — single file, clear pattern, minimal dependencies. Example: database migration, utility function.</item>
      <item>normal: 30-60k tokens — multiple files, some integration, standard patterns. Example: API endpoint, service class.</item>
      <item>complex: 60-100k tokens — multiple components, integration logic, edge cases. Example: E2E tests, complex business logic.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never assign two complex tasks to the same wave. Execution failures on complex tasks create blocking situations for all dependent waves.</statement>
      <rationale>Complex tasks have the highest failure probability. Serializing them in separate waves ensures a failure in one does not block a parallel sibling.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="INVEST Validation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply INVEST validation to every task after generation. A task that fails any criterion must be rewritten before being moved to todo/.</statement>
      <rationale>INVEST failures at planning time are cheap to fix; the same failures discovered mid-execution cause session aborts and rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Independent: no code dependencies on other incomplete tasks. Can be assigned to an isolated agent context.</item>
      <item>Negotiable: implementation details are flexible. "User can register" is negotiable; "Use bcrypt version 5.1.0" is not.</item>
      <item>Valuable: has a clear business value or enables a specific FR. "Enables FR-001" is sufficient for infrastructure tasks.</item>
      <item>Estimable: effort estimate is possible. "~50k tokens, normal complexity" is estimable; "some time" is not.</item>
      <item>Small: fits within 100k token context budget. If not, split it.</item>
      <item>Testable: AC items have observable, pass/fail outcomes. "Returns 201 status" is testable; "works correctly" is not.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Dependency Types">
    <list>
      <item>FS (Finish-to-Start): most common. Task B starts when Task A finishes. Example: database migration FS API handler.</item>
      <item>SS (Start-to-Start): Task B can start when Task A starts. Example: UI mockup SS frontend implementation.</item>
      <item>FF (Finish-to-Finish): Task B finishes when Task A finishes. Example: testing FF documentation.</item>
      <item>SF (Start-to-Finish): rare. Task B finishes when Task A starts. Example: old system SF new system migration.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>When in doubt, use FS. Document non-FS dependency types explicitly with a reason — most dependencies are FS and agents generate SS/FF/SF incorrectly.</statement>
      <rationale>Incorrect dependency types cause waves to be sequenced wrong, eliminating parallelism or creating false serial ordering.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="File Actions Reference">
    <list>
      <item>CREATE: new file needed. Example: CREATE src/handlers/auth/register.ts</item>
      <item>MODIFY: add to existing file. Example: MODIFY src/routes/auth.ts — Add registration route</item>
      <item>DELETE: remove file. Example: DELETE src/deprecated/old-auth.ts</item>
      <item>RENAME: change file path. Example: RENAME src/utils/hash.ts to src/utils/crypto.ts</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
