<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-ac-rules" title="Acceptance Criteria Rules and Critical Path">
  <summary>Rules for writing testable AC items, good vs bad AC examples, critical path structure, and Technical Notes guidelines for task files.</summary>

  <section title="AC Writing Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every AC item must be an observable outcome with a specific, measurable value. HTTP status codes, database state assertions, or measurable values are acceptable. Vague phrases are not.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague ACs cannot be mechanically verified by the executor. "Works correctly" leaves the success determination to the agent, which may mark a failing task as done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
**Acceptance Criteria:**
- [ ] POST /api/auth/register returns 201 on success
- [ ] Response includes valid JWT token (verified with jwt.verify)
- [ ] Password is bcrypt hashed in database (SELECT query confirms)
- [ ] Duplicate email returns 409 with error message
- [ ] Invalid email format returns 400 with validation errors
]]></code>
      <note>Each item is specific, references an observable outcome, and has a clear pass/fail condition.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
**Acceptance Criteria:**
- [ ] Registration works correctly
- [ ] Handles errors properly
- [ ] Follows best practices
- [ ] Code is clean
]]></code>
      <note>Vague, subjective, not measurable. No clear test procedure. Multiple interpretations possible.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Write Tests checklist separately from functional ACs. Use the Tests section for unit/integration/E2E items so test coverage is explicit and distinct from behavioral requirements.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing test requirements with behavioral ACs obscures which ACs require code changes and which require test additions. The executor can address them separately.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Critical Path">
    <rule>
      <statement>Mark the critical path (longest dependency chain) explicitly in the implementation plan. The executor will optimize for parallelism but may miss the longest chain without explicit marking.</statement>
      <rationale>Unidentified critical path causes misallocation of wave priorities. The longest chain determines the minimum elapsed sessions for the feature; shortening it has more impact than any non-critical task optimization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Critical Path: TASK-001 (15k) -> TASK-003 (45k) -> TASK-005 (30k) -> TASK-007 (75k)
Total: ~165k tokens across 4 serial tasks
Parallel path: TASK-002 -> TASK-004 -> TASK-006 (joins at TASK-007)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Technical Notes Guidelines">
    <rule>
      <statement>Technical Notes must cite the exact file path and pattern to follow, not generic advice. Write them after Wave 1 is complete for later-wave tasks, not speculatively.</statement>
      <rationale>Speculative Technical Notes written before Wave 1 execution become stale when implementation patterns differ from design assumptions. They mislead the executor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Good: "Use Joi for validation (see constitution.md section Standards)"</item>
      <item>Good: "Follow error handling pattern in src/handlers/user.ts lines 45-67"</item>
      <item>Bad: "Use best practices for security"</item>
      <item>Bad: "Make sure to handle errors properly"</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents generating task files write "Depends on: None" even when implicit data dependencies exist (e.g., handler task that needs a database migration).</description>
      <reason>Implicit dependencies not declared cause wave ordering to place the handler before the migration. Validate that database migration tasks always precede handler tasks.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
