<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Quality Attributes Framework Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the quality-attributes methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale; the final rule is the skip-this-methodology gate referenced by the decision tree.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-scenario-shape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every NFR MUST be captured as an ATAM-style scenario: Source, Stimulus, Environment, Artefact, Response, Measure. Bare adjectives ('fast', 'secure') MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bass / Clements / Kazman — Software Architecture in Practice.">The 6-field shape forces numeric Response and Measure; adjectives cannot be tested.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-cover-iso25010-categories" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST cover Performance, Reliability, Security, Maintainability, Scalability, Usability, and Compliance categories (omit a category only when explicitly out of scope, with reason).</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO/IEC 25010 quality model.">ISO 25010 is the de-facto NFR taxonomy; gaps usually mean the attribute is implicit and gets misaligned.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-prioritise-with-utility-tree" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Scenarios MUST be prioritised in a utility tree (high / medium / low importance × high / medium / low difficulty). High-importance × low-difficulty scenarios MUST be implemented first; high × high require an ATAM session.</statement>
      <rationale source="ATAM — Architecture Tradeoff Analysis Method.">Without explicit prioritisation every scenario looks equal and engineering capacity is mis-allocated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-sli-slo-from-scenarios" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each high-priority scenario MUST be translated into one Service Level Indicator with a numeric SLO target; SLOs MUST be testable in CI / production monitoring.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE — SLO chapter.">Scenarios live in a doc; SLIs/SLOs live in monitoring; without translation the NFR is never enforced.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-name-tradeoff-conflicts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST name at least 2 cross-attribute conflicts (e.g. perf vs cost, security vs usability) and a resolution rule for each.</statement>
      <rationale source="ATAM tradeoff identification.">Unnamed conflicts surface as ad-hoc decisions later; named conflicts produce stable, auditable trade-off rules.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When prerequisites hold (stakeholders, goals, current SLIs, compliance matrix), apply r1 → r2 → r3 → r4 → r5 and emit the spec.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology design — gate rule.">Order encodes risk: shape first, coverage second, prioritisation third, monitoring fourth, trade-offs last.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do NOT use when (a) prototype / no contractual NFR, (b) internal CLI, (c) NFR spec already current. Exit with note.</statement>
      <rationale source="Preconditions — skip gate.">NFR ceremony in these contexts wastes review.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
