<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="risk-assessment">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>market-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Identify, score, and mitigate demand, competition, pricing, trend, and channel risks. Each risk row cites evidence from market research files, ensuring auditable decision gates.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>risk-assessment</tag>
      <tag>market-research</tag>
      <tag>demand-risk</tag>
      <tag>competitive-risk</tag>
      <tag>pricing-risk</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Risk Assessment (Market-Researcher Lens)</title>
    <summary>Market-risk assessment identifies, scores, and mitigates demand, competition, pricing, trend, and channel risks before committing to a segment or pricing strategy. Every risk row must cite a paragraph or table from an existing market research file — no row may rely on general knowledge. This ensures the register stays grounded in evidence and can be automatically validated.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Entrepreneurs either ignore risks until they materialize or paralyze themselves without structure. Standard H/M/L scoring collapses four distinct pricing failure modes into one row and anchors demand risk on TAM rather than the validated wedge. A citation-enforced register surfaces these hidden exposures and connects each High-priority row to a concrete trigger metric already in the company's dashboard.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-entry go/no-go on a new market segment when TAM/SAM/SOM exists but demand evidence is thin</item>
        <item>Pricing strategy decision: before locking a price point, score demand-elasticity and anchor-competitor risk</item>
        <item>Launch-readiness review for a positioning or category bet</item>
        <item>After a competitor raises a Series B or ships a copycat: re-score competitive-displacement and pricing-pressure rows</item>
        <item>Channel-dependence audit when more than 40% of pipeline comes from one channel</item>
        <item>Pivot evaluation: comparing two segment options requires a structured market-risk delta</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure technical, team, financial, or operational risk — use the generic `researcher/risk-assessment` variant or `pro/pm/pm-traditional/risk-management/`</item>
        <item>Idea stage with fewer than 5 problem interviews — demand-risk score is uncalibrated; run continuous discovery first</item>
        <item>B2B deals where risk is per-account, not per-market — use account-level deal-risk frameworks</item>
        <item>Solo side projects under $1k of committed spend — overhead exceeds expected loss</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="citation-requirement">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every risk row must cite a paragraph or table from an existing market research file (market-research.md, competitive-analysis.md, pricing-research.md, trend-analysis.md, niche-evaluation.md). No row may cite general knowledge.</statement>
        <rationale>Uncited risk rows are opinion, not analysis. Citation enforcement makes the register auditable, prevents stale scores, and forces re-run when source documents change.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="risk-sub-categories">
      <p>Five market-risk sub-categories with scoring rules:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Demand: market too small, poor timing, no validated wedge (note: score against the validated wedge, not the TAM)</item>
        <item>Competition: incumbent copies feature, well-funded rival enters, adjacent player pivots in (include not-yet-entered threats)</item>
        <item>Pricing: split into four sub-rows — commoditization, price war, anchor mismatch, willingness-to-pay collapse</item>
        <item>Trend: technology obsolescence, regulatory shift, macro headwind reversing the adoption curve</item>
        <item>Channel: single-channel dependence (auto High-prob when one channel exceeds 40% of pipeline)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="probability-impact-scoring">
      <rule>
        <statement>Score probability and impact independently on H/M/L (3/2/1), multiply for Risk Score (1-9). Force at least 2 rows at H/H (score 9) and at least 2 rows at L/L (score 1) — reject balanced-looking registers where every row is M/M.</statement>
        <rationale>Symmetric scoring (all Med/Med) is the most common agent bias; forcing distribution prevents false balance and surfaces real exposure.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>High probability: more than 50% chance in the planning horizon</item>
        <item>Medium probability: 20-50% chance</item>
        <item>Low probability: below 20% chance</item>
        <item>High impact: existential threat to the segment or pricing model</item>
        <item>Medium impact: major setback requiring significant resource reallocation</item>
        <item>Low impact: minor inconvenience, resolved within one sprint</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="response-strategies">
      <p>Risk response strategies include:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Avoid: eliminate the risk entirely (high prob + high impact); typically means not entering a segment or not adopting a channel</item>
        <item>Mitigate: reduce probability or impact (medium risks); requires concrete actions with named owners</item>
        <item>Transfer: shift to insurance, contracts, or SLAs (low probability, high impact)</item>
        <item>Accept: document and monitor (low risks)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pair every High-priority row with exactly one of: kill-decision criterion, pivot criterion, or budget reallocation criterion. A risk row without a connected action is decoration.</statement>
        <rationale>Risk registers that document threats without decision criteria are never acted on; the action criterion turns a log into a decision trigger.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="trigger-metrics">
      <rule>
        <statement>Trigger metrics must be observable in the company's existing dashboard. "ARPU drops below $X for 2 consecutive months" works; "market sentiment shifts" does not.</statement>
        <rationale>Unobservable triggers are never fired; the contingency plan is never activated; the risk register provides false security.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="five-step-process">
      <p>Five-step market-risk assessment process:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Step 1 — Enumerate risks: run the enumeration agent against market-research.md, competitive-analysis.md, pricing-research.md; require minimum 2 risks per sub-category (demand, competition, pricing, trend, channel)</item>
        <item>Step 2 — Red-team pre-mortem: run a market-specific pre-mortem with 3 failure branches (segment did not materialize, competitor won, price elasticity broke the model)</item>
        <item>Step 3 — Score with citations: apply prob x impact; every cell must cite a specific paragraph or table from the source files; reject rows without citations</item>
        <item>Step 4 — Human review: owner accepts or rejects each row and assigns a trigger metric already visible in the company dashboard</item>
        <item>Step 5 — Persist and schedule: save as market-risk-register.md; re-run enumeration and pre-mortem passes monthly or on any commit to source research files</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="pre-mortem-technique">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run the pre-mortem with 3 distinct agent personas (skeptical customer, well-funded competitor, regulator or platform owner) rather than a single agent pass. Consolidate outputs; do not average them.</statement>
        <rationale>A solo agent run produces a single failure narrative that confirms the briefing document's tone. Multiple adversarial personas surface independent failure paths that the enumeration pass misses.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Demand risk scored against TAM rather than the validated wedge</description>
        <reason>A large TAM with no validated entry wedge is the highest-loss failure mode; anchoring on TAM produces artificially low demand-risk scores.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Pricing risk collapsed into one row instead of four sub-rows</description>
        <reason>Aggregating four distinct failure modes (commoditization, price war, anchor mismatch, WTP collapse) into one row averages them and hides the real exposure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Channel-dependence risk scored Medium when one channel exceeds 40% of pipeline</description>
        <reason>Any single channel above 40% should be auto-scored High probability unless 3+ years of stable retention evidence exists.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Risk register updated only at project kick-off</description>
        <reason>Stale registers are worse than none; they create false security. Re-run at minimum monthly and on every commit to source research files.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent quotes multi-billion-dollar TAM and scores demand risk Low</description>
        <reason>Force the prompt to score against the validated wedge (named buyer segment, confirmed problem, pipeline evidence), not the TAM ceiling.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent uses stale competitor lists from training data</description>
        <reason>Require the agent to re-read competitive-analysis.md and verify competitor domains via faion-domain-checker-agent before citing any competitive risk row.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent mitigation language defaults to "diversify channels", "monitor competitors", "iterate pricing"</description>
        <reason>Ban these phrases; require action verb + named owner + measurable trigger + budget cap. Vague mitigations are never executed.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent ships "Avoid" response on market risk autonomously (e.g., killing a segment)</description>
        <reason>Avoid-strategy responses mean killing a segment, geo, or pricing tier — never let an agent execute this unattended. Hard human-in-the-loop gate required.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Risk IDs change every agent run (R1..Rn renumbered)</description>
        <reason>Use a stable hash of the risk statement or instruct the agent to diff-merge against the existing register; changing IDs break longitudinal tracking.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/risk-register.md" purpose="Risk register template with high/medium/low priority tables and contingency plan format"/>
      <template path="templates/pre-mortem.md" purpose="Pre-mortem facilitation template with failure-mode consolidation and risk conversion table"/>
      <template path="templates/market-risk-lint.sh" purpose="Bash script that enforces citations from market-research files on every register row"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
