<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-question-bank" title="STAR Question Bank by Competency">
  <summary>STAR question bank across five core competencies with probing follow-ups per question.</summary>

  <section title="Leadership questions">
    <list>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you led a team through a significant change." → Probe: "What resistance did you encounter and how did you handle it?"</item>
      <item>"Describe a situation where you had to motivate an underperforming team member." → Probe: "What was the outcome for that person 3 months later?"</item>
      <item>"Give an example of when you made an unpopular decision." → Probe: "What would you do differently in hindsight?"</item>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you had to delegate an important task." → Probe: "How did you ensure quality without micromanaging?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Problem-solving questions">
    <list>
      <item>"Describe a complex problem you solved at work." → Probe: "Walk me through your decision-making process at the hardest moment."</item>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you had to make a decision with incomplete information." → Probe: "What would have changed if you had waited for more data?"</item>
      <item>"Give an example of when you identified a problem before others noticed." → Probe: "How did you validate that it was actually a problem?"</item>
      <item>"Describe a time you had to troubleshoot under pressure." → Probe: "How did you manage your own stress while solving it?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Communication questions">
    <list>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you had to deliver difficult news to stakeholders." → Probe: "What was their reaction and how did you manage it?"</item>
      <item>"Describe a situation where you had to persuade someone who disagreed." → Probe: "What argument ultimately changed their position?"</item>
      <item>"Give an example of when you had to explain something complex simply." → Probe: "How did you know they truly understood?"</item>
      <item>"Tell me about a miscommunication and how you resolved it." → Probe: "What systemic change did you make to prevent recurrence?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Collaboration questions">
    <list>
      <item>"Describe a successful cross-functional project you contributed to." → Probe: "What was YOUR specific contribution vs. the team's?"</item>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you had a conflict with a colleague." → Probe: "How is your relationship with that person today?"</item>
      <item>"Give an example of when you had to work with someone whose style differed from yours." → Probe: "What did you adapt and what did you hold firm on?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Adaptability questions">
    <list>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you had to adapt to a major change at work." → Probe: "What was the hardest part of the adjustment?"</item>
      <item>"Describe a situation where priorities suddenly shifted." → Probe: "What did you do about work you had already committed to?"</item>
      <item>"Tell me about a time you failed and how you responded." → Probe: "What specifically would you do differently?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/star-scorecard.md">Scorecard template with per-question S/T/A/R evidence fields.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/hiring-manager-guide.md">Before/during/after interview checklist for hiring managers.</reference>
</text>
