<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules-and-gotchas" title="STAR Method Agent Rules">
  <summary>Hypothetical-block rule, pronoun-shift detection, result quantification, agent scoring prohibition, and legal constraints.</summary>

  <section title="Core agent rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Block hypothetical answers. When a candidate answers with "I would..." trigger the probe: "Can you give me a specific past example of when you did this?" Do not score hypothetical answers; mark as NOT_STAR.</statement>
      <rationale>Hypothetical answers have near-zero predictive validity per behavioral psychology research. Accepting them inflates scores for candidates who are good at reasoning about what they should do, not what they actually did.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag pronoun shifts. When an answer uses "we" throughout with no first-person Action statement, trigger the probe: "What did YOU personally do in this situation?" Mark answers as "pronoun_we_only" in transcript analysis.</statement>
      <rationale>Team re-attribution is the most common STAR inflation path. Candidates may legitimately use "we" for shared work but must identify their specific contribution before the Action is scoreable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always close on Result. For any answer that describes actions without an outcome, use the mandatory probe: "What was the end result?" An answer without R is incomplete regardless of S/T/A quality.</statement>
      <rationale>Result quantification is the primary defense against coaching-site rehearsed STAR answers. Specific numbers (30% reduction, $2M saved) are harder to fabricate and easier to verify in reference checks.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring prohibition">
    <rule>
      <statement>Agents must not assign numeric scores to candidate STAR responses. Agents may extract component spans, flag missing components, and quote verbatim evidence. Numeric scores are always human-assigned.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM scoring rewards fluency and polish, systematically disadvantaging non-native speakers and neurodiverse candidates. The legal liability of automated employment scoring without bias audit is substantial.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Question generation rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap at one competency per question. Reject any double-barreled question ("Tell me about a time you led a team AND resolved conflict"). One question, one competency, 3-5 questions per 45-minute round.</statement>
      <rationale>Double-barreled questions allow candidates to answer only the part they are strong on, producing incomplete evidence for both competencies simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Weight question generation explicitly to avoid leadership/communication clustering. Force at least one question per round covering execution, technical depth, or delivery under constraint.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs default to leadership and communication questions; execution and technical depth are under-covered by default, producing STAR banks that miss critical signals for IC roles.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Session design rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Send candidates a 1-page STAR prep brief before the interview loop. This raises the floor for non-native speakers without raising the ceiling for native-speaker candidates.</statement>
      <rationale>STAR storytelling style disadvantages candidates unfamiliar with the format. Pre-briefing reduces communication-style bias without compromising the competency signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Live-coaching prompts sent to candidates during a real interview.</description>
      <reason>Coaching a candidate mid-interview is equivalent to fraud — it eliminates the comparative basis for the evaluation and creates legal exposure.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/star-completeness.py">Deterministic STAR completeness checker before LLM transcript analysis.</reference>
</text>
