<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="vr-design-patterns">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>6DoF VR design patterns: teleport-first locomotion, world-locked UI, seated mode, comfort settings, accessibility by disability category, 90 FPS motion-to-photon.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>vr</tag>
      <tag>immersive-design</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
      <tag>design-patterns</tag>
      <tag>comfort</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>VR Design Patterns for Accessibility and Comfort</title>

    <summary>Design patterns for fully-immersive 6DoF VR covering environment anchoring (ground plane, horizon, stable reference objects), locomotion menu (teleport default + smooth opt-in), UI placement (world-locked or body-locked, 1.5-3 m, eye-level, no head-lock), comfort settings (vignette, snap turn, FOV cap, seated mode), and accessibility parity across disability categories. Minimum 14-16 pt text, 90 FPS / 20 ms motion-to-photon, teleport-as-default.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Head-locked UI causes immediate nausea; smooth locomotion without teleport excludes wheelchair users and motion-sensitive users; no seated mode excludes a large population; text below 14 pt is unreadable even at 4K per eye. These are common mistakes that ship repeatedly because agents and developers default to web/mobile conventions. Teleport-first defaults and world-locked UI solve the most frequent failure modes.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing fully-immersive VR experiences (Quest 2/3/Pro, PSVR2, Valve Index, PICO 4, Vision Pro full-immersion mode).</item>
        <item>Choosing locomotion and UI placement strategy.</item>
        <item>Implementing comfort settings: vignette, snap turn, FOV cap, seated mode, height calibration.</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing VR title for accessibility and motion-sickness risk.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>AR/passthrough/MR — use `ar-design-patterns` and `immersive-design-principles` instead.</item>
        <item>360-degree video in Cardboard-style viewers — constrained interaction, not 6DoF.</item>
        <item>Mixed-reality productivity with passthrough — use `immersive-design-principles` blended-mode territory.</item>
        <item>WebXR mobile sessions where 90 FPS is unreachable.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="grounding-elements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep the floor/ground plane visible at all times with consistent appearance. Never float the user in a void without a stable reference surface.</statement>
        <rationale>Loss of ground reference causes immediate disorientation; the ground plane is the primary spatial anchor for the vestibular system in VR.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Maintain a stable, expected horizon position. The horizon provides orientation and reduces nausea independently of the ground plane.</statement>
        <rationale>An unstable horizon forces the vestibular and visual systems into conflict, the primary mechanism of VR sickness.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Include at least one stable reference object (cockpit in vehicle sims, dashboard in driving, wrist-mounted UI) that moves with the user and is always visible.</statement>
        <rationale>Fixed reference objects provide a visual rest point that decouples perceived self-motion from environment motion, reducing visual-vestibular mismatch.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="scale">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use 1:1 real-world scale for familiar objects (doors 2 m, tables 70-75 cm, chairs 45 cm, average human height). When using intentionally different scale, make the difference unambiguous and provide a human-scale reference object.</statement>
        <rationale>Ambiguous scale breaks depth perception and comfortable interaction distance; users reach for objects at the wrong distance when scale cues are inconsistent.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="lighting">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use consistent lighting that matches real-world expectations for time of day; keep light sources visible; ensure shadows enhance depth. Avoid extremes: too dark breaks visibility, too bright causes discomfort.</statement>
        <rationale>Inconsistent lighting undermines depth perception and increases the cognitive load needed to understand the environment.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="boundaries-and-safety">
      <rule>
        <statement>Implement a guardian/chaperone system: visual boundary at wall approach, controller haptic warning, audio alert option, experience pause on boundary crossing, easy re-centering action.</statement>
        <rationale>Physical collisions with real-world objects cause injury; guardian systems are required by all major platform certification programmes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Define minimum play space requirements at first launch; warn if the space is too small and offer a seated alternative automatically.</statement>
        <rationale>Room-scale experiences designed without space constraints exclude users in smaller rooms and create safety hazards.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="locomotion">
      <rule>
        <statement>Default to teleportation plus snap turn. Smooth locomotion and smooth turning are opt-in only, with vignette automatically enabled when the user activates them.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents and developers default to smooth locomotion as the "modern" option; teleport must be pinned as default to protect motion-sensitive users and wheelchair users.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Teleportation (high comfort): best for general movement, seated users, and wheelchair users. Should be the default.</item>
        <item>Walking/room-scale (high comfort for non-disabled): limited to the physical play area; excludes wheelchair users by design — always pair with teleport.</item>
        <item>Controller/smooth movement (medium comfort): exploration use case; requires vignette and speed cap when enabled.</item>
        <item>Vehicle/seat (high comfort): seated experiences; wheelchair-friendly.</item>
        <item>Flying (low-medium comfort): specific use cases only; highest nausea risk; offer vignette and speed limits.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always offer a seated mode that makes every interaction reachable without standing. Test with a wheelchair-user proxy before shipping.</statement>
        <rationale>Seated mode is the most commonly skipped accessibility feature in room-scale VR; agents will omit it without an explicit check.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/comfort-defaults.json">Comfort-defaults schema with locomotion, turn, vignette, UI, accessibility, and performance fields</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="ui-placement">
      <rule>
        <statement>Place UI panels at 1.5-3 m from the user, at eye level (sitting or standing), curved to match the viewing angle. Never head-lock any UI element.</statement>
        <rationale>Head-locked UI causes immediate nausea because it moves with every head motion; world-locked or body-locked UI stays stable relative to the environment or the user's body.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Minimum text size in VR is 14-16 pt; test readability at the actual 2 m viewing distance. Web/mobile point sizes do not transfer to VR.</statement>
        <rationale>Text that reads fine on a monitor is unreadable in a VR headset at viewing distance; agents generate text sizes from web/mobile experience and must be corrected.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Prefer diegetic UI (holographic displays, wrist-mounted, screens on objects) where it fits the narrative. Reserve non-diegetic UI (pause menus, settings, HUDs) for meta-level interactions with clear visual distinction from the world.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixed diegetic and non-diegetic without clear distinction breaks presence and increases cognitive load.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="interaction-and-spatial-audio">
      <rule>
        <statement>Implement gaze-plus-confirm selection (gaze highlights the object, button press or dwell confirms) as an accessible baseline interaction that works without hand precision.</statement>
        <rationale>Gaze selection works from a distance, is accessible to users with reduced hand mobility, and requires no controller precision.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Confirm every button press with a spatial audio cue and synchronized haptic feedback. Add 3D-positioned audio cues for out-of-view events.</statement>
        <rationale>Multimodal feedback confirms interactions for users who may not see or feel a single modality; spatial audio for off-screen events prevents missing critical signals.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="vision-accessibility">
      <list>
        <item>High contrast mode toggle.</item>
        <item>Large text options (minimum 14-16 pt; verify at actual VR viewing distance, not on monitor).</item>
        <item>Color-blind safe palette as an option; test designs with deuteranopia, protanopia, and tritanopia simulations.</item>
        <item>Audio descriptions for all informative visual-only elements.</item>
        <item>Screen-reader integration is experimental in most VR platforms; document known gaps explicitly.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="hearing-accessibility">
      <rule>
        <statement>Add visual captions in 3D space for every audio-cued event. Caption size and position must be adjustable by the user.</statement>
        <rationale>Spatial audio is the primary feedback channel in VR for many critical events; deaf and hard-of-hearing users need visual equivalents.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Haptic feedback synchronized with sounds.</item>
        <item>Visual flash indicators for directional audio alerts from off-screen sources.</item>
        <item>Per-source volume controls (separate sliders for music, SFX, voice, UI).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="mobility-accessibility">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every interaction in the experience must be reachable from a seated position. Explicitly test the interaction reach envelope for a seated player before shipping.</statement>
        <rationale>Room-scale designs assume standing; seated-mode parity requires deliberate design of interaction distances and heights.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Teleportation available for all movement (not only as an afterthought comfort option).</item>
        <item>Voice commands mapped to all primary actions (select, menu, pause, help).</item>
        <item>Controller-free hand tracking as an optional input mode.</item>
        <item>Adjustable height offset to accommodate different sitting heights and postures.</item>
        <item>All content reachable within a standard wheelchair-accessible interaction arc.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cognitive-accessibility">
      <list>
        <item>Simplified UI mode with reduced information density and fewer simultaneous choices.</item>
        <item>Clear, step-by-step tutorials; no assumed prior VR experience from first-time users.</item>
        <item>Pauseable at any point with no time pressure during the paused state.</item>
        <item>Difficulty adjustment where content difficulty varies.</item>
        <item>Memory aids: contextual hints, progress indicators, reminders of the current objective.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="testing-requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Test with at least one person prone to motion sickness, one wheelchair user (or seated-only tester), and one first-time VR user before any public release.</statement>
        <rationale>Developer familiarity with XR normalizes discomfort and novelty; the three tester profiles reveal distinct failure modes that internal teams miss.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run at least one 30-minute extended-session test; short demos hide fatigue, drift, and cumulative discomfort that only appear over time.</statement>
        <rationale>Comfort problems compound over time; a 10-minute demo that feels fine can produce nausea and arm fatigue at minute 25.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Default locomotion = teleport + snap turn; smooth options gated behind explicit user opt-in with FOV vignette on.</item>
        <item>Always provide a seated mode that reaches every interaction — wheelchair-user parity, not afterthought.</item>
        <item>Minimum 14–16 pt text in VR (smaller is unreadable even at 4K per eye); test at 2 m viewing distance.</item>
        <item>World-lock or body-lock UI; never head-lock. Diegetic where it makes narrative sense.</item>
        <item>Frame budget is non-negotiable: drop visual fidelity before dropping below 90 FPS.</item>
        <item>Run hardware-IPD calibration step at first launch; a wrong IPD nukes comfort regardless of design.</item>
        <item>Test with first-time VR users — experienced devs underestimate locomotion difficulty.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Agents recommend "smooth locomotion for immersion" as default — pin teleport-as-default in your prompt.</item>
        <item>LLMs forget seated mode in room-scale designs; require explicit seated-parity check on every interaction.</item>
        <item>Generated text sizes default to web/mobile pt — multiply by ~1.5x for VR readability.</item>
        <item>Agents propose head-locked HUDs from gaming experience — explicitly forbid head-lock; require world or body lock.</item>
        <item>Spatial-audio recommendations are often described but not specced — require Wwise/FMOD event names or equivalent.</item>
        <item>Comfort-claim hallucinations ("reduces nausea by X%") — strip unsupported numbers.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoints: motion-sensitive tester pass, wheelchair-user parity check, IPD calibration QA, 30-min extended-session test.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <list>
        <item>Patterns assume 90 FPS @ &lt;20 ms motion-to-photon — mobile/standalone may not hit that and recommendations break.</item>
        <item>"Comfort" framings are population-level; ~5–10 % of users get sick on rated-comfortable experiences.</item>
        <item>Hand tracking guidance lags devices — Quest 3 hand tracking is more capable than Quest 2 and patterns conflate them.</item>
        <item>Screen-reader story is still experimental in VR — recommendations here are aspirational.</item>
        <item>Multi-user social VR adds harassment + safety patterns this methodology does not cover.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/comfort-defaults.json" purpose="Comfort-defaults JSON schema for VR (locomotion, turn, comfort, UI, accessibility, performance)."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.oculus.com/resources/bp-overview/"/>
      <link href="https://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id=1537149895"/>
      <link href="https://docs.unity3d.com/Packages/com.unity.xr.interaction.toolkit@latest"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xaur/"/>
      <link href="https://gameaccessibilityguidelines.com/"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/gaming/accessibility/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
