<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="design-docs-patterns">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd</domain>
    <summary>Design doc writing patterns: format selection, required sections, non-goals rule, alternatives quality bar, ADR extraction, SDD lifecycle integration.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>design-docs</tag>
      <tag>sdd</tag>
      <tag>architecture</tag>
      <tag>writing</tag>
      <tag>patterns</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Design Docs Patterns</title>

    <summary>Write a design document before implementing any feature that takes more than one engineering day. Use lightweight Google-style (1-4 pages: context, goals, non-goals, proposed solution, alternatives, open questions) for team-scoped work. Use heavier formats (Amazon 6-pager, Uber RFC) only for cross-org or executive-audience decisions. Always include a non-goals section and at least two genuine alternatives — not strawmen. Set a review deadline when circulating.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Design documents catch design flaws when changes are cheap (before code is written), build consensus across teams, and create a record of why decisions were made. Writing forces clarity: the act of explaining a design in prose exposes gaps that discussion alone misses. LLM-generated design docs sound authoritative while missing domain-specific constraints — always require a human review pass.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Any feature taking more than one engineering day</item>
        <item>Cross-cutting changes affecting multiple modules, services, or teams</item>
        <item>Requirements that are unclear or conflicting — writing exposes gaps</item>
        <item>Generating design.md in the SDD lifecycle (spec → design → test-plan → impl-plan)</item>
        <item>Before proceeding to implementation-plan.md generation — design must be marked Approved</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Bug fixes with obvious root cause and one-line solution — PR description is sufficient</item>
        <item>Prototypes and spikes where output is discarded regardless of design quality</item>
        <item>Work taking less than a few hours — overhead exceeds benefit</item>
        <item>Solo purely internal refactors with identical external behavior</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="when-to-write-a-design-doc">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Write a design document for any feature that takes more than one engineering day, spans multiple PRs or modules, or where requirements are unclear. Skip it for bug fixes with an obvious solution, prototypes where output is discarded, and work under a few hours.</statement>
        <rationale>Design documents catch design flaws when changes are cheap (before code is written). The act of writing forces clarity: gaps that seem obvious in conversation become visible in prose. The overhead is justified only when the feature is complex enough that silent assumptions could cause rework.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Write: feature takes > 1 engineering day</item>
        <item>Write: change is cross-cutting or multi-PR</item>
        <item>Write: high security or privacy implications</item>
        <item>Write: API changes affecting other teams</item>
        <item>Write: requirements are unclear or conflicting</item>
        <item>Skip: bug fix with obvious single-line solution (PR description is sufficient)</item>
        <item>Skip: prototype or spike where code will be discarded</item>
        <item>Skip: internal refactor with identical external behavior under a few hours</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="format-selection">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use the lightweight Google-style format (1-4 pages) for team-scoped and org-scoped work. Use heavyweight formats (Amazon 6-Pager, Uber RFC) only for cross-org or executive-audience decisions requiring formal sign-off. The format should match the audience and stakes — over-engineering the format wastes time without adding value.</statement>
        <rationale>Lightweight docs take hours to write and review; heavyweight docs take days. Applying a 6-pager format to a team-scoped change adds bureaucratic friction without improving the outcome. Conversely, a lightweight doc for a cross-org infrastructure change may fail to reach the right decision-makers or surface all risks.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Lightweight (1-4 pages): internal team or org change, rapid iteration context</item>
        <item>Full design doc (Google-style, 5-10 pages): cross-team service or new product feature</item>
        <item>Amazon 6-Pager: strategic initiative, executive review, narrative format required</item>
        <item>Uber RFC: formal approval required, service SLAs, platform change</item>
        <item>ADR: single architectural decision to record permanently in-repo</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="design-doc-lifecycle">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>A design doc moves through states: DRAFT → REVIEW → APPROVED → IMPLEMENTING → IMPLEMENTED → ARCHIVED. The APPROVED state is the gate before any implementation begins — proceeding before approval means implementation may need to be redone after review feedback.</statement>
        <rationale>The lifecycle state provides an explicit handshake between design and implementation. Without it, engineers start coding on a draft that is still under review, creating merge conflicts between feedback changes and in-flight code.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>DRAFT: author writes initial version, may share informally</item>
        <item>REVIEW: circulate to stakeholders, collect feedback, iterate</item>
        <item>APPROVED: required approvers sign off; doc is authoritative</item>
        <item>IMPLEMENTING: referenced during development; update if design changes</item>
        <item>IMPLEMENTED: feature shipped; doc becomes historical record</item>
        <item>ARCHIVED: doc superseded or system deprecated</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="sdd-integration">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>In the SDD lifecycle, design.md is generated after spec.md is approved (90%+ confidence). The design doc must reach APPROVED status before proceeding to test-plan.md generation. The design doc answers HOW to build; it must not answer WHAT (that belongs in spec.md).</statement>
        <rationale>Keeping spec and design as separate artifacts prevents conflation of requirements with implementation. If a reviewer changes the implementation approach, only design.md is updated — the spec (the contract) remains stable. This separation also allows the spec to survive a design rewrite when a better approach is discovered.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="llm-generated-design-docs">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating an LLM-generated design doc as authoritative without a human review pass. LLMs produce confident-sounding text that may be missing domain-specific constraints, organizational context, or real trade-offs.</description>
        <reason>LLMs pattern-match to generic design doc templates and fill in plausible-sounding content. They lack knowledge of your specific system constraints, team norms, and organizational history. A human review pass is mandatory to catch incorrect assumptions before the doc influences implementation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="required-sections">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every design doc must contain: overview (1-2 paragraphs), context/background, goals (specific and measurable), non-goals (explicit), proposed solution/design, alternatives considered (minimum 2 genuine alternatives), cross-cutting concerns, and open questions. Missing any of these signals an incomplete doc.</statement>
        <rationale>Each required section serves a distinct purpose: overview provides entry-point clarity, non-goals prevent scope creep, alternatives document the reasoning behind the chosen approach, and open questions track unresolved risks. Omitting any of them means future readers must reconstruct reasoning from context, and reviewers cannot give informed sign-off.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Overview: 1-2 paragraphs; readable by someone unfamiliar with the project</item>
        <item>Context and background: current system state, constraints, what led to this</item>
        <item>Goals: specific and measurable success criteria</item>
        <item>Non-goals: explicit list of what is out of scope</item>
        <item>Proposed design: architecture, data model, API contracts, key decisions</item>
        <item>Alternatives considered: at least 2 with pros, cons, rejection rationale</item>
        <item>Cross-cutting concerns: security, privacy, scalability, reliability, observability</item>
        <item>Open questions: unresolved items with owners</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="non-goals-rule">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Include a non-goals section in every design doc. List at least two explicit non-goals. Non-goals must be real scope boundaries — not obvious statements that nobody would expect. When reviewers raise "have you considered X?", the answer is either in the design or in the non-goals.</statement>
        <rationale>Non-goals prevent scope creep discussions during review and implementation. When a non-goal is not written down, every reviewer asks the same question independently. Explicitly stating non-goals sets boundaries that allow the team to focus the review on the actual proposed scope.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Real non-goals that set scope boundaries">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Non-Goals

- Real-time collaboration (multiple editors on the same doc simultaneously) — planned for v2
- Mobile-native UI — web-responsive layout is sufficient for initial release
- Offline-first caching — requires service worker infrastructure not yet in place
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Obvious non-goals that add no value">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Non-Goals

- We are not building the entire product at once
- We will not rewrite everything in a new language
        ]]></code>
        <note>These are obvious and add no value. Non-goals must be specific scope boundaries that readers might actually assume are in scope.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="alternatives-quality-bar">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Include at least two genuine alternatives — not strawmen. Each alternative must have: a brief description, honest pros, honest cons, and a clear "why not chosen" rationale. Always include "do nothing" as an alternative when applicable.</statement>
        <rationale>Strawman alternatives (alternatives that are obviously worse) signal that the author avoided the hard thinking. Genuine alternatives show that tradeoffs were seriously considered. The "why not chosen" rationale is the most important part: it documents the reasoning that future engineers can use to revisit the decision if constraints change.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Genuine alternatives with honest trade-offs">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Alternatives Considered

### Alternative 1: Event-driven with message queue

Use Kafka to decouple the write pipeline from downstream consumers.

- Pros: consumers can scale independently; producer is not blocked by slow consumers
- Cons: adds operational complexity (Kafka cluster); introduces at-least-once delivery
- Why not chosen: our current scale (100 RPS) does not justify the Kafka overhead; revisit if we exceed 10k RPS

### Alternative 2: Synchronous polling by consumers

Consumers poll an API endpoint for new records every 30 seconds.

- Pros: no new infrastructure; simple to implement and debug
- Cons: up to 30s latency; polling adds unnecessary load at low event rates
- Why not chosen: 30s latency violates NFR-2 (sub-5s delivery requirement)
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="review-process">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Set a review deadline when circulating a design doc. Cap required reviewers at 5-7. For async review, specify comment format expectations in the distribution message. For synchronous review, start with 10-20 minutes of silent reading before discussion.</statement>
        <rationale>Design docs without a deadline stay in "in review" indefinitely. Too many required reviewers causes diffusion of responsibility — everyone assumes someone else will catch the issue. Silent reading at the start of a review meeting eliminates the presentation overhead and ensures all reviewers have actually read the doc before discussion.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="adr-extraction">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>After a design doc is approved, extract each significant architectural decision into a separate Architecture Decision Record (ADR) committed to the repository. Link the ADR from the design doc. ADRs are immutable once accepted; the design doc can evolve but the ADR records the decision as made.</statement>
        <rationale>Design docs evolve and may be archived or updated over time. ADRs are permanent records that explain why the codebase is structured the way it is. Without ADRs, engineers inherit code with no context for the decisions behind it, leading to repeated debates about settled questions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="ADR extraction from design doc">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Architecture Decisions

The following decisions from this design doc have been extracted as ADRs:
- [ADR-042: Database choice — PostgreSQL over MongoDB](../decisions/adr-042-database.md)
- [ADR-043: API versioning — URL path over header](../decisions/adr-043-api-versioning.md)
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>When generating a design doc with an LLM, always require: (1) a human review pass before marking APPROVED; (2) at least two genuine alternatives, not placeholder text; (3) cross-cutting concerns filled with project-specific content, not generic boilerplate. Reject docs where these sections contain only template placeholders.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs pattern-match to design doc templates and generate authoritative-sounding but generic content. The most dangerous failure mode is a doc that looks complete but contains no actual domain-specific constraints. The three checks above catch the most common LLM failure patterns: missing review, strawman alternatives, and uncustomized boilerplate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Sending a design doc to stakeholders without a human reviewing the LLM-generated content for accuracy. LLMs produce confident text that may contain incorrect assumptions about system constraints, organizational context, or technical feasibility.</description>
        <reason>LLM-generated docs sound authoritative while potentially missing the domain knowledge that makes a design doc valuable. A human review pass is the only way to catch incorrect assumptions before they are baked into the implementation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/design-doc-lightweight.md" purpose="Google-style lightweight design doc template (1-4 pages) with all required sections"/>
    </templates>

  </content>
</methodology>
