<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Benefits Realization Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Benefits Realization. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="quantified-benefit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every benefit MUST have a quantified target metric, baseline value, target value, and named business owner BEFORE project approval. Soft benefits without a metric do not count.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI Benefits Realization Management Framework">Soft benefits cannot be tracked or disputed. Mandatory quantification at approval time forces honest claims and creates accountability before work begins.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="baseline-frozen" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Baseline values MUST be frozen in writing with date and source query before launch. Subsequent measurements compare against the locked baseline; redefinition is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Thorp, The Information Paradox (1998)">A redefinable baseline destroys measurability. Locking T-0 values keeps the benefit comparable across reporting periods.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="owner-is-business-stakeholder" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Benefit owner MUST be a business stakeholder, NOT the project manager. PM hands off ownership at go-live; orphan benefits decay.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bradley &amp; Cantwell, Benefits Realization Management (2010)">PMs move to the next project. Adoption and process change — the primary enablers of realization — require an owner who outlasts the PM tenure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="attribution-pre-registered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For any benefit where attribution is contested, a control cohort or counterfactual model MUST be pre-registered before launch. Post-hoc attribution is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brodersen et al., CausalImpact (Google, 2015)">Post-hoc attribution is unresolvable without a pre-planned counterfactual. Difference-in-differences requires a control group defined before intervention.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="portfolio-cap-anti-double-count" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Claimable benefits MUST be capped at portfolio level. The same revenue lift cannot be claimed across two concurrent projects in the same portfolio.</statement>
      <rationale source="McKinsey Digital — measuring digital transformations (2024)">Double-counting inflates portfolio ROI and destroys credibility. CFO/PMO sign-off on benefits above a materiality threshold prevents the failure mode.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Benefits Realization fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Benefits Realization outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
