<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="backup-cloud-aws Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for backup-cloud-aws as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Enabling Object Lock + S3 lifecycle policies without testing their interaction — a lifecycle rule can delete objects that Object Lock should protect.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Object Lock and lifecycle rules interact: a lifecycle noncurrent_version_expiration rule can attempt to delete locked versions. AWS will reject the delete request but may silently skip it, leaving locked but orphaned versions that consume storage. Always test on a non-prod bucket with short retention values before applying to production.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates AWS Backup resource selection without selection_tag, causing the plan to match zero resources silently (no error, no backups).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>AWS Backup selection with no tag filter and no explicit resources list matches nothing. Always validate the selection produces at least one resource in a test plan before relying on it for production.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates cross-account restore IAM policy missing `kms:Decrypt` on the source key in the target account, producing a restore that fails with AccessDenied on the encrypted recovery point.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cross-account restores need the target account's role to assume the source KMS key's trust policy. Agents output happy-path policies that miss this KMS trust. Always validate restore in the target account, not just write success in the source.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent sets up S3 Object Lock + lifecycle noncurrent_version_expiration without testing their interaction on a non-prod bucket, relying on logic alone.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Object Lock and lifecycle policies interact in non-obvious ways. A lifecycle rule attempting to delete a locked version is silently skipped by S3, which can leave orphaned locked versions consuming unbounded storage. Always test on a non-prod bucket with short retention values (minutes/hours) before applying to production.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
