<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="topical-authority">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>seo-manager</domain>
    <summary>Build topical authority through topic clusters: one pillar page plus supporting subtopic articles, all internally linked to signal expertise.</summary>
    <category>seo</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>topical-authority</tag>
      <tag>content-strategy</tag>
      <tag>pillar-cluster</tag>
      <tag>seo</tag>
      <tag>semantic-search</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Topical Authority</title>

    <summary>Build topical authority by covering an entire subject comprehensively through topic clusters: one pillar page (broad overview) plus supporting articles (subtopics), all internally linked. Google's ranking algorithm rewards sites that demonstrate comprehensive domain expertise over those targeting isolated keywords.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Keyword density stopped correlating with rankings when Google introduced semantic search and BERT/MUM. The algorithm now assesses whether a site is a credible, comprehensive source on a topic. A site with 30 tightly linked articles on RAG outranks a site with one article optimized for "RAG tutorial" — because the cluster signals genuine expertise rather than keyword targeting.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Planning a new content area and wanting to establish authority quickly</item>
        <item>Existing content exists but rankings have plateaued despite on-page optimization</item>
        <item>Building a pillar-cluster content strategy from scratch</item>
        <item>Evaluating which topics to invest in based on authority-building ROI</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-page or micro-sites with no room for content clusters</item>
        <item>When the bottleneck is technical SEO, not content depth — fix crawlability first</item>
        <item>For time-sensitive news/event content where topical depth is not the ranking factor</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="core-model">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Structure content as topic clusters: one pillar page (broad overview of the topic) supported by multiple cluster articles (specific subtopics), with bidirectional internal links between them.</statement>
        <rationale>Google's algorithms assess topical coverage, not just individual keyword optimization. A cluster of 10-30 interlinking articles on RAG signals deeper expertise than a single article — even one highly optimized for the target keyword.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="RAG Topical Cluster">
        <note>Pillar: "Complete Guide to RAG" linking to cluster articles: "What is RAG?", "RAG vs Fine-tuning", "RAG Architecture Patterns", "RAG Evaluation Methods", "RAG Tools Comparison", "RAG Case Studies"</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Publishing standalone articles targeting individual keywords without cluster structure</description>
        <reason>Without topical coverage depth, individual articles compete against established authorities that already cover the full topic — a fight you lose unless your domain has equivalent overall authority.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="content-depth">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Answer all related questions, cover edge cases, and update content regularly — comprehensive coverage signals topical expertise more than article length alone.</statement>
        <rationale>Google's "helpful content" evaluation rewards content that fully satisfies user intent. Thin cluster articles that repeat what the pillar already covers dilute rather than amplify authority.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Content depth requirements by article type:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Pillar page: comprehensive overview, 2000+ words, links to all cluster articles</item>
        <item>Cluster articles: deep coverage of specific subtopic, link back to pillar and related clusters</item>
        <item>Answer "People Also Ask" questions within the cluster</item>
        <item>Cover edge cases and advanced scenarios in dedicated cluster articles</item>
        <item>Update cluster articles when the topic evolves — stale content degrades authority</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="external-authority-signals">
      <p>Signals that amplify topical authority beyond internal linking:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Quality backlinks to pillar and cluster pages</item>
        <item>Brand mentions in industry publications</item>
        <item>Social signals and expert citations</item>
        <item>Author credentials and expertise signals (About page, author bios)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="internal-linking-structure">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Link from pillar to all cluster articles; link from each cluster article back to the pillar and to related clusters; use keyword-rich anchor text that describes the destination content.</statement>
        <rationale>Internal linking distributes PageRank across the cluster and signals to Google that these pages form a related content group. Anchor text reinforces keyword relevance without the manipulation risk of external anchor text over-optimization.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Internal linking best practices:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Every cluster page links back to pillar with primary keyword anchor</item>
        <item>Pillar links to all cluster pages with descriptive anchor text</item>
        <item>Cluster pages link to related clusters to strengthen the topical web</item>
        <item>Use consistent link text across the cluster for the same concept</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developers.google.com/search/docs/beginner/how-search-works"/>
      <link href="https://www.searchenginejournal.com/topic-clusters-pillar-content/"/>
      <ref slug="seo-techniques"/>
      <ref slug="growth-seo-link-building"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
