<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="topical-authority">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>seo-manager</domain>
    <summary>Build topical authority via pillar-cluster: one pillar plus 8-30 interlinked subtopic articles. Includes inventory, gap analysis, linking, and verification.</summary>
    <category>seo</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
    <tags>
      <tag>topical-authority</tag>
      <tag>content-strategy</tag>
      <tag>pillar-cluster</tag>
      <tag>seo</tag>
      <tag>semantic-search</tag>
      <tag>internal-linking</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Topical Authority</title>

    <summary>Build topical authority by covering an entire subject comprehensively through topic clusters: one pillar page (broad overview) plus 8-30 supporting subtopic articles, all internally linked, refreshed at least every 6 months. Google's helpful-content and semantic-search systems reward sites that demonstrate end-to-end domain expertise over those targeting isolated keywords.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Keyword density stopped correlating with rankings when Google introduced semantic search, BERT, MUM, and the helpful-content system. Modern ranking assesses whether a site is a credible, comprehensive source on a topic ("topic embedding fit"). A site with 30 tightly linked articles on RAG outranks a site with one article optimised for "RAG tutorial" because the cluster signals end-to-end expertise. AI Overviews and zero-click search amplify this effect: only sites recognised as topical authorities are quoted as sources.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Launching a new content area and wanting to establish authority within 3-6 months</item>
        <item>Existing content exists but rankings have plateaued despite on-page optimisation</item>
        <item>Building a pillar-cluster strategy from scratch in a vertical with strong incumbents</item>
        <item>Evaluating which topics to invest in based on authority-building ROI</item>
        <item>AI Overviews / generative-search citations are the primary traffic goal</item>
        <item>Trigger phrase from user: "rankings flat", "competitor outranks us", "build authority", "pillar page", "content cluster", "topic map"</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-page or micro-sites with no room for content clusters</item>
        <item>Bottleneck is technical SEO, not content depth — fix crawlability, indexation, Core Web Vitals first</item>
        <item>Time-sensitive news/event content where freshness, not depth, drives rankings</item>
        <item>Local-intent SERPs dominated by Google Business Profile (use local SEO methodology)</item>
        <item>Domain has DR &lt; 10 and no backlinks — invest in foundational link-building first</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <how-to>
      <step>Pick the seed topic. Run `/faion topical-authority` and capture the user's seed term (e.g. "RAG", "headless commerce"). Confirm it has 1k+ monthly searches and is broad enough for 10+ subtopics.</step>
      <step>Inventory existing content. Crawl the site (Screaming Frog, sitemap, or `find . -name "*.md"`) and produce a CSV of `url,title,target_keyword,word_count,last_updated`. Mark which already touch the seed topic.</step>
      <step>Build the topic map. Use the prompt template below to brainstorm 20-40 candidate subtopics. Filter to 8-30 that have search demand and clear intent (informational, commercial, transactional).</step>
      <step>Identify the pillar. Pillar = broadest informational query (e.g. "What is RAG"). 2000-4000 words, covers every cluster article at one paragraph each, links out to all of them.</step>
      <step>Map gaps vs. inventory. For each subtopic, mark CREATE (new article) or UPDATE (existing article needs expansion). Assign one canonical URL per subtopic — never two articles competing.</step>
      <step>Draft cluster articles. 800-1800 words each. Each must answer 3+ "People Also Ask" questions for that subtopic, link back to pillar with primary-keyword anchor, link to 2-4 related cluster articles.</step>
      <step>Wire internal links. Pillar → all clusters with descriptive anchors. Each cluster → pillar (primary keyword anchor) + 2-4 sibling clusters. Use the linking template (see commands).</step>
      <step>Add structured data. JSON-LD `Article` on every page, `BreadcrumbList`, `FAQPage` on cluster articles that include FAQ blocks, `Author` with sameAs.</step>
      <step>Submit and monitor. Submit updated sitemap to Google Search Console. Track impressions/clicks per cluster page weekly via GSC API. Refresh content every 6 months or when SERP shifts.</step>
      <step>Build external signals. Earn 1-3 backlinks per cluster (digital-PR, guest posts, HARO). Track brand mentions and author citations.</step>
      <step>Run verification. Execute the verify block below; gates must pass before declaring the cluster shipped.</step>
    </how-to>

    <section name="core-model">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Structure content as topic clusters: one pillar page (broad overview of the topic) supported by 8-30 cluster articles (specific subtopics), with bidirectional internal links between them.</statement>
        <rationale>Google's helpful-content and semantic-relevance systems assess topical coverage, not just individual keyword optimisation. A cluster of 10-30 interlinking articles on RAG signals deeper expertise than a single article — even one highly optimised for the target keyword. AI Overviews preferentially cite recognised topical authorities.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="RAG Topical Cluster">
        <note>Pillar: "Complete Guide to RAG" (3000 words) → cluster articles: "What is RAG?", "RAG vs Fine-tuning", "RAG Architecture Patterns", "Chunking Strategies for RAG", "Embedding Model Selection", "Vector Database Comparison", "RAG Evaluation Metrics", "RAG Reranking Methods", "RAG Failure Modes", "RAG Production Case Studies", "RAG Cost Optimisation". Each cluster links back to pillar + 2-4 sibling clusters.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Publishing standalone articles targeting individual keywords without cluster structure</description>
        <reason>Without topical coverage depth, individual articles compete against established authorities that already cover the full topic — a fight you lose unless your domain has equivalent overall authority.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Two articles targeting the same query (keyword cannibalisation)</description>
        <reason>Splits link equity, confuses Google's ranking signal, dilutes click-through. One canonical URL per subtopic; 301-redirect or merge duplicates.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="content-depth">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Answer all related questions, cover edge cases, and refresh content at least every 6 months — comprehensive coverage signals topical expertise more than article length alone.</statement>
        <rationale>Google's helpful-content evaluation rewards content that fully satisfies user intent. Thin cluster articles that repeat what the pillar already covers dilute rather than amplify authority.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Content depth requirements by article type:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Pillar page: comprehensive overview, 2000-4000 words, links to all cluster articles, includes TOC + jump-links</item>
        <item>Cluster articles: 800-1800 words, deep coverage of specific subtopic, link back to pillar and 2-4 related clusters</item>
        <item>Answer 3+ "People Also Ask" questions per cluster article</item>
        <item>Cover edge cases and advanced scenarios in dedicated cluster articles</item>
        <item>Update cluster articles at least every 6 months — stale content degrades authority and AI Overview citation rate</item>
        <item>Include first-hand expertise signals: original screenshots, code samples, benchmark numbers, case-study results</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="external-authority-signals">
      <p>Signals that amplify topical authority beyond internal linking:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Quality backlinks to pillar and cluster pages (target DR ≥ 30 referring domains)</item>
        <item>Brand mentions in industry publications (use Google Alerts + monitor Reddit/Hacker News/X)</item>
        <item>Social signals and expert citations (LinkedIn shares by domain experts carry weight)</item>
        <item>Author credentials and expertise signals: detailed About page, author bios with sameAs to LinkedIn/X/GitHub, JSON-LD `Person` markup</item>
        <item>Citations in AI Overviews / Perplexity / ChatGPT search — track via brand-name + topic queries</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="internal-linking-structure">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Link from pillar to all cluster articles; link from each cluster article back to the pillar and to 2-4 related clusters; use keyword-rich anchor text that describes the destination content.</statement>
        <rationale>Internal linking distributes PageRank across the cluster and signals to Google that these pages form a related content group. Anchor text reinforces keyword relevance without the manipulation risk of external anchor text over-optimisation.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Internal linking best practices:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Every cluster page links back to pillar with primary keyword anchor</item>
        <item>Pillar links to all cluster pages with descriptive anchor text</item>
        <item>Cluster pages link to 2-4 related clusters to strengthen the topical web</item>
        <item>Use consistent link text across the cluster for the same concept</item>
        <item>Avoid generic anchors ("click here", "this article") — use the destination's primary keyword</item>
        <item>One link per anchor target per page (no duplicate links to the same URL)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <prompt purpose="topic-map-generation"><![CDATA[
You are an SEO content strategist. Given the seed topic "<SEED>" build a pillar-cluster topic map.

Output a JSON object:
{
  "pillar": {
    "title": "...",
    "primary_keyword": "...",
    "search_intent": "informational",
    "target_word_count": 3000
  },
  "clusters": [
    {
      "title": "...",
      "primary_keyword": "...",
      "search_intent": "informational|commercial|transactional",
      "target_word_count": 1200,
      "people_also_ask": ["...", "...", "..."],
      "internal_links_to": ["pillar", "cluster-slug-1", "cluster-slug-2"]
    }
  ]
}

Requirements:
- 8-30 clusters that collectively cover the topic exhaustively.
- No two clusters target overlapping keywords (avoid cannibalisation).
- Mix intents: ~60% informational, ~30% commercial, ~10% transactional.
- Each cluster includes 3+ "People Also Ask" questions sourced from real SERPs.
- Every cluster links back to pillar plus 2-4 sibling clusters.
]]></prompt>

    <prompt purpose="cluster-article-brief"><![CDATA[
Write a content brief for cluster article "<CLUSTER_TITLE>" within the "<PILLAR_TITLE>" cluster.

Required sections:
1. Target keyword + 3-5 secondary keywords
2. Search intent + target SERP feature (snippet, AI Overview, video, local)
3. Outline (H2/H3) covering all "People Also Ask" questions
4. Internal links: 1 to pillar (anchor: primary keyword of pillar), 2-4 to siblings (specify destination URLs)
5. External authoritative citations (3-5, with URLs)
6. JSON-LD schema type (Article, HowTo, FAQPage)
7. First-hand expertise signal to include (original screenshot, benchmark, code sample, case study)
8. Word count target: 800-1800
]]></prompt>

    <commands>
      <command name="inventory-content"><![CDATA[# Crawl site and produce inventory CSV
# Option A: Screaming Frog (GUI, free up to 500 URLs)
# Option B: command-line crawl from sitemap
curl -s https://example.com/sitemap.xml | \
  grep -oP '(?<=<loc>)[^<]+' | \
  while read url; do
    title=$(curl -s "$url" | grep -oP '(?<=<title>)[^<]+' | head -1)
    wc=$(curl -s "$url" | sed 's/<[^>]*>//g' | wc -w)
    echo "\"$url\",\"$title\",\"$wc\""
  done > content-inventory.csv]]></command>
      <command name="check-internal-links"><![CDATA[# Verify each cluster page links back to pillar and to N siblings
PILLAR_URL="https://example.com/guide-to-rag/"
for url in $(cat cluster-urls.txt); do
  html=$(curl -s "$url")
  links_to_pillar=$(echo "$html" | grep -c "$PILLAR_URL")
  internal_links=$(echo "$html" | grep -oP 'href="https://example\.com[^"]+' | sort -u | wc -l)
  echo "$url pillar=$links_to_pillar internal=$internal_links"
done]]></command>
      <command name="detect-cannibalisation"><![CDATA[# Find pages targeting the same keyword in title
awk -F',' 'NR>1 {print $2}' content-inventory.csv | \
  tr '[:upper:]' '[:lower:]' | sort | uniq -c | sort -rn | \
  awk '$1 > 1 {print "CANNIBAL:", $0}']]></command>
      <command name="check-content-age"><![CDATA[# Flag cluster articles older than 6 months
find content/ -name "*.md" -mtime +180 -print | \
  while read f; do
    echo "STALE: $f $(stat -c %y "$f" | cut -d' ' -f1)"
  done]]></command>
      <command name="gsc-impressions"><![CDATA[# Pull last 28 days impressions per cluster URL via GSC API
# Requires: gcloud auth + GSC property verified
python3 -c "
from googleapiclient.discovery import build
from google.oauth2 import service_account
creds = service_account.Credentials.from_service_account_file('sa.json',
  scopes=['https://www.googleapis.com/auth/webmasters.readonly'])
service = build('searchconsole', 'v1', credentials=creds)
req = {'startDate':'2026-04-01','endDate':'2026-04-28','dimensions':['page'],'rowLimit':100}
r = service.searchanalytics().query(siteUrl='https://example.com/', body=req).execute()
for row in r.get('rows', []):
    print(row['keys'][0], row['impressions'], row['clicks'])
"]]></command>
    </commands>

    <checklist>
      <check>Seed topic confirmed with 1k+ monthly searches and 10+ subtopic candidates</check>
      <check>Existing content inventory CSV produced (`content-inventory.csv`)</check>
      <check>Topic map JSON generated with 1 pillar + 8-30 clusters, no keyword overlap</check>
      <check>Each cluster has search intent classified and 3+ PAA questions captured</check>
      <check>Pillar page is 2000-4000 words and links to every cluster</check>
      <check>Every cluster article is 800-1800 words and links back to pillar with primary-keyword anchor</check>
      <check>Every cluster article links to 2-4 sibling clusters</check>
      <check>JSON-LD `Article` (or `HowTo`/`FAQPage` where applicable) on every page</check>
      <check>Author bio with sameAs links present on every page</check>
      <check>No keyword cannibalisation (one canonical URL per subtopic, verified via `detect-cannibalisation`)</check>
      <check>Sitemap submitted to Google Search Console after publish</check>
      <check>Content-refresh schedule recorded (every 6 months) per cluster article</check>
      <check>External signals plan: ≥1 backlink target identified per cluster</check>
    </checklist>

    <verify>
      <step>Run `detect-cannibalisation` command — output must be empty (no duplicate target keywords).</step>
      <step>Run `check-internal-links` — every cluster URL must report `pillar≥1` and `internal≥3`.</step>
      <step>Run `check-content-age` — output should be empty for cluster articles less than 6 months old; if any STALE lines appear, schedule a refresh task.</step>
      <step>Validate JSON-LD on pillar + 3 random clusters via `curl -s URL | grep 'application/ld+json'` and paste into Schema.org validator (https://validator.schema.org/) — must return 0 errors.</step>
      <step>Confirm sitemap.xml contains every pillar+cluster URL: `curl -s sitemap.xml | grep -c '&lt;loc&gt;'` should equal expected count.</step>
      <step>Within 14-28 days post-publish, query GSC API (`gsc-impressions` command) — pillar should show ≥100 impressions and ≥50% of clusters should show non-zero impressions. If not, audit indexation (`site:example.com/cluster-slug/` in Google).</step>
      <step>Quarterly check: pull GSC for cluster URLs; if average position drops &gt;5 places or impressions drop &gt;30% MoM, trigger content refresh.</step>
      <step>Track AI Overview citations: search `&lt;seed-topic&gt;` related queries in Google + Perplexity + ChatGPT search; record whether brand is cited. Goal: ≥1 citation within 90 days of cluster shipping.</step>
    </verify>

    <warning>Do not publish all clusters in one day. Stagger over 4-12 weeks so Google's crawl budget can index gradually and you can refine on early signals. Bulk-publishing 30 thin pages can trigger helpful-content demotions.</warning>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developers.google.com/search/docs/fundamentals/creating-helpful-content"/>
      <link href="https://developers.google.com/search/docs/appearance/structured-data"/>
      <link href="https://www.searchenginejournal.com/topic-clusters-pillar-content/"/>
      <ref slug="seo-techniques"/>
      <ref slug="growth-seo-link-building"/>
      <ref slug="google-ai-overviews-optimization"/>
      <ref slug="zero-click-search-adaptation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
