<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-reference" title="20-Methodology Reference">
  <summary>Cheat-sheet reference for 20 research methodologies extracted from SKILL.md v1.1. For full framework, templates, and agent patterns, use the per-methodology folder.</summary>

  <section title="Idea Generation Methods">
    <rule>
      <statement>For full content of any methodology listed here, open its dedicated folder under pro/research/researcher/ or pro/research/market-researcher/. This reference is abridged.</statement>
      <rationale>Fields here are stubs. The per-methodology folder carries the complete framework, examples, templates, and agent-integration gotchas.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>idea-generation — 7 Ps framework (Pain, Passion, Profession, Process, Platform, People, Product). Score each idea: Market size + Your fit + Urgency, max 15. Top 3 scores proceed to validation. Agent mode: ideas.</item>
      <item>paul-graham-questions — 4 questions: What is tedious but necessary? What is surprisingly hard? What do you build for yourself? What would you pay for that does not exist? Agent mode: ideas.</item>
      <item>pain-point-research — Complaint audit, workaround inventory, tool stack analysis, time tracker. Score: frequency 30%, intensity 30%, current solutions 20%, ability to solve 20%. Agent mode: ideas.</item>
      <item>niche-evaluation — 5-dimension scoring: Market size, Competition, Barriers, Monetization, Your fit (1-5 each, max 25). Proceed: 20-25. Caution: 15-19. Needs pivot: 10-14. Pass: below 10. Agent mode: niche.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Market Analysis">
    <list>
      <item>market-research-tam-sam-som — TAM (total addressable), SAM (serviceable), SOM (obtainable Year 1). Three methods: top-down, bottom-up, value theory. SOM typically 1-5% of SAM. Agent mode: market.</item>
      <item>trend-analysis — Macro (5-10yr), industry (2-5yr), micro (6-24mo) trend categories. Assess: growth drivers, adoption curve position, threats, timing (too early / just right / too late). Agent mode: market.</item>
      <item>competitor-analysis — Identify direct, indirect, future competitors. Map on positioning matrix. Analyse 8 dimensions. Find gaps (feature, quality, audience, price, experience). Differentiation statement. Agent mode: competitors.</item>
      <item>competitive-intelligence — Feature inventory across top 5 competitors. Feature matrix (Y/P/N per competitor). Gap categories: nobody has it, 1-2 have it (opportunity), everyone has it (table stakes). Validate gap before building. Agent mode: competitors.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="User Research">
    <list>
      <item>user-interviews — Problem, solution, usability interview types. 45-min structure: warm-up, current state, pain exploration, solution probing, wrap-up. Golden rules: talk less than 20%, ask about past behavior not future intent. Agent mode: validate.</item>
      <item>jobs-to-be-done — JTBD statement: When I [situation], I want to [action], so I can [outcome]. Three job dimensions: functional, emotional, social. Hiring and firing framework. Agent mode: personas.</item>
      <item>persona-building — 5 components: demographics, behaviors, pain points, goals, verbatim quote. Types: primary, secondary, negative. Minimum 5-10 interviews before building. Agent mode: personas.</item>
      <item>problem-validation — 5 criteria: frequency weekly+, intensity 7+/10, willingness to pay, search volume exists, competition exists. Evidence types: verbatim quotes (strong), forum discussions (medium), competitor existence (weak). Agent mode: validate.</item>
      <item>pain-point-mining — Sources: Reddit, Twitter, app reviews, Quora, forums, LinkedIn. Search patterns: "[keyword] frustrating" site:reddit.com, "[competitor] alternative" site:reddit.com. Collect 50+ mentions, categorize by theme, count frequency. Agent mode: pains.</item>
      <item>customer-interview-framework — 4 interview types by stage: discovery, problem, solution, usability. Flow: warm-up, context, deep dive, concept test, wrap-up. Question types: open, probing, clarifying, summary. Anti-patterns: leading questions, future hypotheticals, pitching. Agent mode: validate.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Business Model Planning">
    <list>
      <item>niche-viability-scoring — 5-criteria weighted model: Market size 25%, Competition 20%, Barriers 20%, Profitability 20%, Your fit 15%. Score 1-10 with justification. Decision thresholds: 7.5+ strong, 5.5-7.4 caution, 3.5-5.4 risks, below 3.5 pass. Agent mode: niche.</item>
      <item>business-model-research — Red vs Blue Ocean. Four actions framework: Eliminate, Reduce, Raise, Create. Strategy canvas: X-axis key competing factors, Y-axis offering level. Find uncontested space. Agent mode: niche.</item>
      <item>value-proposition-design — Customer profile: jobs, pains, gains. Value map: products/services, pain relievers, gain creators. FIT = pain relievers address top pains + gain creators enable top gains. Focus on pains rated 8+/10. Agent mode: personas.</item>
      <item>pricing-research — Six models: freemium, subscription, usage-based, one-time, tiered, per-seat. Selection criteria: value delivery, usage patterns, customer type, competition, marginal cost. Research: list 5 competitors pricing, calculate value delivered, Van Westendorp survey, test with early users. Agent mode: pricing.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Naming and Domains">
    <list>
      <item>project-naming — 7 strategies: descriptive, invented, compound, metaphor, portmanteau, alliteration, acronym. Good name criteria: easy to spell, pronounce, memorable, domain available (.com preferred), no trademark conflicts, works internationally. Generate 20+ candidates before checking availability. Agent mode: names.</item>
      <item>domain-availability — Check priority: .com (essential), .io (acceptable for tech), .co (alternative), GitHub username, Twitter handle, LinkedIn page. Alternative strategies: add "get"/"try" prefix, "app"/"hq" suffix, different TLD. Agent: faion-domain-checker-agent.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
