<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="diary-study-basics Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for diary-study-basics. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose the study type based on what triggers a relevant event for your research question.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each type captures different behavioral signals. Mixing types within one study produces incommensurable data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap study duration at 10-21 days for most products; 28+ days only for true habit-formation research.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Participant fatigue causes 30-50% entry dropout after day 10 in studies without strong re-engagement. Studies longer than 3 weeks lose late entries to "same as yesterday" responses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each diary entry must take under 3 minutes to complete. If the form is longer, split into a quick log and a weekly deep-dive.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Entry burden is the top predictor of dropout. Participants with demanding forms disengage before the study reaches the habit-formation window.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define research questions before selecting study type or duration. The questions determine whether a diary study is the right method at all.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Diary studies answer temporal and contextual questions. Using them for questions better answered by interviews or analytics wastes 2-4 weeks of participant effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use the five-field entry structure for every study: When (date/time), Where (location/context), What (what happened), How (emotional state), Why (participant's interpretation).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These five fields capture the complete context needed for temporal and contextual analysis. Omitting "Why" produces entries that describe events without meaning; omitting "Where" prevents contextual pattern analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Screen participants for willingness to self-document consistently, not just availability. Participants who journal regularly complete studies at 2x the rate of those who do not.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The biggest predictor of dropout is unfamiliarity with self-documentation. Selection bias from motivated self-reporters is real but acceptable compared to 50% dropout from unscreened participants.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conduct a live onboarding session with each participant before the diary period starts. Test their understanding of the entry format with a practice entry.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Participants who submit a practice entry during onboarding complete 40% more entries than those who only read instructions. The practice entry surfaces confusion before it becomes dropout.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use rolling synthesis, not batch analysis. Run a theme-synthesis pass weekly from day 3 so emerging patterns can generate follow-up questions while participants are still active.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Late synthesis produces a complete retrospective analysis of an unprobed dataset. Themes identified by day 7 become the raw material for exit interview questions on day 14.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Participant fatigue: dropoff after day 7-10 unless re-engaged. Studies &gt;3 weeks lose 30-50% of entries.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Study duration and entry format directly impact completion. Shorter, lighter studies with multimodal options yield richer datasets than longer, text-heavy ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Selection bias: people willing to journal twice daily for a month are not your average user.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Screen for journaling comfort and consistency as a research variable, not a bug. Acknowledge selection bias in findings interpretation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Self-report drift: entries early in the study are detailed; late entries become "same as yesterday".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Quality metrics like entry length and detail are signals of engagement and thoroughness. Weight late entries lower or re-engage participants at mid-study.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Recall bias on event-contingent prompts: "log every time you used the app" → users batch-log at end of day, losing in-the-moment context.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Immediate prompts (push notifications, random signal-contingent) reduce recall drift. Trade-off: more interruption for better fidelity. Choose based on research question priorities.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap the study at 10-21 days for most products; 28+ days only for true habit-formation research.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Longer studies add data overhead without proportional insight gain. Study duration should match research question temporal scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send mid-study check-in calls (15 min) to catch confusion and rebuild commitment. This single intervention lifts compliance noticeably.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Human contact mid-study signals that effort matters and gives participants a chance to clarify confusion before they disengage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pay in tranches: e.g. 30% on completion of week 1, 70% at study end. Pre-paid full incentive correlates with mid-study dropout.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Incentive structure shapes completion. Staged incentives maintain commitment through the middle slump.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r16" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mix entry formats: text + photo + 30-sec voice. Different participants engage with different modalities; mixed corpora are richer for synthesis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Multimodal intake captures context that single-modality studies miss (visual environments, vocal tone, emotional state).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r17" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always conclude with an exit interview (30-45 min) per participant; the diary entries become the interview script.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Exit interviews validate diary findings, surface misinterpretations, and provide narrative context for quantitative patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
