<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Diary Study Basics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Diary Study Basics methodology. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; the last rule binds the decision tree skip path.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="anchor-evidence-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every non-trivial field in the produced artefact MUST carry &gt;=1 verbatim citation from an auditable source (URL, transcript_id, ticket id, dashboard snapshot). Fields with no anchor are rejected as fabrication.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice for Diary Study Basics">LLMs cheerfully invent plausible values without inputs; verbatim anchoring makes the artefact falsifiable and a downstream reviewer can re-pull the source.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="owner-and-last-touched" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every artefact MUST carry a single named owner and an ISO-8601 `last_touched` timestamp. Generic owners ("team", "us", "tbd", "n/a") and empty timestamps are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene (PMBOK 7 Tailoring)">Un-owned artefacts metastasize and the operator stops trusting the whole library; a named owner is the minimum precondition for follow-through.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="template-version-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each filled instance MUST record `template_version` matching the methodology frontmatter at write time. Downstream consumers parse legacy artefacts against this version, never against "latest".</statement>
      <rationale source="Schema-evolution practice from Avro / Protobuf">Templates without version pinning become a one-way ratchet; old instances become unreadable when the template drifts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="human-checkpoint-before-binding-action" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before any binding action driven by this artefact (commit, send, ramp, freeze, escalation, ledger write, contract sign), a named human reviewer MUST approve. The agent surfaces a `ready_for_review` flag and never sets `status=approved` itself.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — agent autonomy boundaries">Self-approval defeats the human checkpoint and the audit trail. The status enum exists precisely to make the human signature observable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-when-prerequisites-missing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the prerequisites in the AGENTS.md table cannot all be satisfied, the agent MUST skip the methodology and emit a structured `skip` decision pointing to the missing prerequisite, not produce a degraded artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — methodology-degradation audits">Degraded artefacts pollute the library because they look complete; an explicit skip preserves the audit signal that the question was asked.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When the decision tree routes to `skip-this-methodology`, the agent MUST emit a structured `skip` decision (with reason + suggested-sibling) rather than running the methodology under degraded conditions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — decision-tree contract">The decision tree is the only place that knows the routing; skipping must be observable so the orchestrator can log the routed-elsewhere path.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
