<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-overview" title="Diary Study Overview">
  <summary>What diary studies are, the three study types, when to use and when not to use, and key design decisions.</summary>

  <section title="Definition">
    <p>A diary study is a longitudinal research method where participants record experiences, behaviors, and thoughts in the moment or shortly after, over an extended period. It captures real-world context that lab studies erase and reveals how behavior evolves over time.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Study Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose the study type based on what triggers a relevant event for your research question.</statement>
      <rationale>Each type captures different behavioral signals. Mixing types within one study produces incommensurable data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Interval-contingent: entries at fixed times (daily, weekly) — for routine behaviors and scheduled usage.</item>
      <item>Event-contingent: entries when a specific event occurs — for specific interactions and triggered behaviors.</item>
      <item>Signal-contingent: entries on random prompts — for capturing natural moments without scheduling bias.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="When To Use vs Not">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use diary studies when the behavior spans multiple days and context matters. Do not use them when you need findings within two weeks or for rare events.</statement>
      <rationale>Minimum useful diary period is 7-14 days. Studies of rare events produce too few entries per participant to identify patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Good for: understanding context, behavior over time, habit formation, experience evolution, real-world patterns.</item>
      <item>Not good for: quick insights, immediate feedback, rare events, usability details, controlled comparisons.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Design Decisions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap study duration at 10-21 days for most products; 28+ days only for true habit-formation research.</statement>
      <rationale>Participant fatigue causes 30-50% entry dropout after day 10 in studies without strong re-engagement. Studies longer than 3 weeks lose late entries to "same as yesterday" responses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Each diary entry must take under 3 minutes to complete. If the form is longer, split into a quick log and a weekly deep-dive.</statement>
      <rationale>Entry burden is the top predictor of dropout. Participants with demanding forms disengage before the study reaches the habit-formation window.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Duration: days, weeks, or months depending on the behavior under study.</item>
      <item>Frequency: daily, event-based, or random signal.</item>
      <item>Format: dedicated app, SMS, email, paper — choose based on participant tech comfort.</item>
      <item>Entry format: text, photo, video, rating — mix modalities for richer corpora.</item>
      <item>Questions: structured (faster to complete) or open (richer but harder to synthesize).</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
