<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-planning" title="Diary Study Planning">
  <summary>Planning steps: defining research questions, making design decisions, building the entry template, and recruiting and onboarding participants.</summary>

  <section title="Research Questions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define research questions before selecting study type or duration. The questions determine whether a diary study is the right method at all.</statement>
      <rationale>Diary studies answer temporal and contextual questions. Using them for questions better answered by interviews or analytics wastes 2-4 weeks of participant effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>How do behaviors change over time?</item>
      <item>What triggers product usage?</item>
      <item>How does context affect experience?</item>
      <item>What is the journey from novice to expert?</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Entry Template Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the five-field entry structure for every study: When (date/time), Where (location/context), What (what happened), How (emotional state), Why (participant's interpretation).</statement>
      <rationale>These five fields capture the complete context needed for temporal and contextual analysis. Omitting "Why" produces entries that describe events without meaning; omitting "Where" prevents contextual pattern analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/entry-daily.md">Daily entry template with location picker, satisfaction rating, and open fields.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/entry-event.md">Event-contingent entry template with trigger, goal, outcome, and optional photo.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Recruitment">
    <rule>
      <statement>Screen participants for willingness to self-document consistently, not just availability. Participants who journal regularly complete studies at 2x the rate of those who do not.</statement>
      <rationale>The biggest predictor of dropout is unfamiliarity with self-documentation. Selection bias from motivated self-reporters is real but acceptable compared to 50% dropout from unscreened participants.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Representative of target users in goals and context, not just demographics.</item>
      <item>Committed for the full duration — screen for this explicitly.</item>
      <item>Comfortable with the capture method (app, SMS, paper).</item>
      <item>Access to the capture device throughout the study period.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Onboarding">
    <rule>
      <statement>Conduct a live onboarding session with each participant before the diary period starts. Test their understanding of the entry format with a practice entry.</statement>
      <rationale>Participants who submit a practice entry during onboarding complete 40% more entries than those who only read instructions. The practice entry surfaces confusion before it becomes dropout.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/study-plan.md">Full study plan skeleton covering all planning decisions.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
