<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Diary Study Examples">
  <summary>Two worked examples showing study design, entry prompts, findings, and insights for a 14-day onboarding study and a 30-day cross-device study.</summary>

  <section title="Example 1: New User Onboarding">
    <example type="good">
      <note>14-day interval-contingent study of new app users. Research question: how does understanding evolve from day 1 to day 14?</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Daily entry prompt (event-contingent):
- What did you do with the app today?
- Anything confusing?
- Anything you discovered?
- How confident do you feel using it? (1-5)

Findings by phase:
- Days 1-3: Focus on core features, confusion about navigation structure.
- Days 4-7: Discovery of secondary features, "aha moments" with advanced functions.
- Days 8-14: Established usage patterns emerge; some features never accessed.

Key insight: Users form stable habits by day 7.
Features unused by day 14 are almost never subsequently adopted.
Implication: onboarding must surface key features within the first 7 days.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example 2: Cross-Device Usage">
    <example type="good">
      <note>30-day event-contingent study of cross-device behavior. Research question: when and why do users switch devices?</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Entry prompt (triggered each device switch):
- What device did you use?
- Why this device and not another?
- What were you trying to do?
- Screenshot if possible.

Findings by time-of-day:
- Morning: phone (quick checks, 1-3 minutes per session).
- Work hours: desktop (complex tasks, sustained sessions).
- Evening: tablet (browsing, reading, media consumption).

Switching triggers:
- Task complexity drives desktop shift (forms, multi-step processes).
- Location drives mobile shift (commute, waiting, movement).
- Content type drives tablet shift (video, long reads).

Implication: design the mobile experience for task completion
under 60 seconds; desktop for multi-step workflows.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use rolling synthesis, not batch analysis. Run a theme-synthesis pass weekly from day 3 so emerging patterns can generate follow-up questions while participants are still active.</statement>
      <rationale>Late synthesis produces a complete retrospective analysis of an unprobed dataset. Themes identified by day 7 become the raw material for exit interview questions on day 14.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Per-entry classification prompt pattern for agent coding.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Entry: {text}
Attached media: {image_caption_if_any}
Classify: usable | vague | off-topic.
If usable, extract:
  trigger, context (location/time/mood),
  task, outcome (success/failure/partial),
  notable_quote.
Return JSON.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Weekly synthesis prompt for identifying theme evolution.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Entries from week {n}, segment {seg}: {entries_json}
Identify 3-5 emergent themes.
For each: theme, count of entries supporting,
  representative quote with participant_id,
  change vs week {n-1}.
Flag themes weakening (strong last week, absent this week).
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
