<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="diary-study-basics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for diary-study-basics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Voice entries with PII (addresses, names, financial info) transcribed to cloud LLM without local processing first.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Transcribe locally (Whisper) before any cloud LLM step. dscout and similar SaaS hold raw audio — verify data residency before uploading.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM theme synthesis over-clusters early entries; agent flattens evolution across the study.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force per-week themes and require the model to surface "themes that emerged this week vs prior weeks" so evolution isn't flattened.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Vision models miss the actual subject when captioning image entries.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pair vision caption with the participant's text caption — never rely on the vision model alone.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Reminder fatigue: automated nudges feel spammy after the third unanswered prompt.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Switch to a single human-style check-in DM after two missed days, or adjust entry expectations with the participant.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Compliance metrics ("X entries received") hide entry quality.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run a quality classifier and report "usable entries" separately. Flag entries that are vague, off-topic, or repetitive.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent autonomously decides to extend the study or ask additional questions mid-study.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Protocol changes mid-study invalidate cross-participant comparison and need researcher approval. Agents should flag themes but not modify protocol.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
