<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules">
  <rule testable="true">Run a 4-step daily loop in this order: CAPTURE (1 line in build log while the work is fresh), HOOK (rewrite the line using one swipe-file pattern), SHIP (one post to your primary platform), LOG (record link + impressions in the cadence sheet); skipping any step breaks the compounding.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Cap daily writing at 30 minutes; if a post is not ready by minute 30, ship a draft of the capture line raw — consistency beats polish, and shipped imperfect data feeds future calibration.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Designate one PRIMARY platform (X, IH, or LI) and at most two SECONDARY platforms; same content fans out to all three with platform-native reformatting, never the same text pasted.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Weekly anchor: every Friday publish a longer-form newsletter or build-log thread that bundles the week's 5 daily posts into a coherent story; weeks without an anchor decay 40% in retention.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Track only three metrics in the cadence sheet: posts-shipped (count), follower delta (weekly), and qualified replies (DMs / comments asking about the product); vanity metrics like likes are excluded so the founder optimizes the right signal.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Schedule one mandatory rest day per week with NO posting; cadence without rest is the burnout failure mode; missed rest days are tracked and trigger a review at 4 consecutive weeks.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Quarterly review: if qualified-replies-per-week has not grown for two consecutive months, the cadence is fine but the hook bank is stale — rotate hooks and platforms, do not abandon the cadence.</rule>
  <example>Indie hacker shipping a Stripe analytics SaaS, primary = X, secondaries = IH + newsletter. Tuesday: CAPTURE "added MRR cohort export"; HOOK using "before/after" pattern → "Yesterday: customers exported MRR by hand. Today: one click. Demo:"; SHIP 9:30 with 12-sec screen recording; LOG impressions = 4.1k, replies = 6, follows = 9. Friday anchor: newsletter "5 things I shipped this week" bundles Tuesday's tweet with 4 others. Saturday: rest day enforced.</example>
</text>
