<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-formats-and-rules" title="AC Formats, Coverage Rules, and Stable IDs">
  <summary>Two AC formats (Given/When/Then and rule-based), the six coverage categories every story must address, stable ID convention, and INVEST-level quality rules.</summary>

  <section title="Stable ID Convention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign every acceptance criterion a stable ID in the format AC-FEATURE-NN (e.g., AC-LOGIN-01) before writing the criterion text. IDs are the spine joining spec.md, test-plan.md, PR description, CI report, and changelog.</statement>
      <rationale>Without stable IDs, cross-referencing AC across spec, test plan, and CI is manual and brittle. IDs enable automated coverage verification via ac-coverage.sh.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Continue IDs from the existing set in the feature; never reset to 01 when adding criteria to an existing story. Pass existing_ac_ids to the authoring agent to prevent collisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Duplicate or reset IDs break the traceability chain. The authoring prompt receives the current max ID and increments from there.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Given/When/Then Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use GWT format for user-facing behaviour: Given [precondition], When [action], Then [observable outcome]. One Then assertion per scenario unless the assertions are truly inseparable observations of the same state change.</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple unrelated Then assertions in one scenario hide which assertion failed and make the test harder to name. Split when assertions diverge.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Avoid And chains longer than 3 items in Given. Long preconditions hint that the scenario should be a higher-level test or that the state setup belongs in a Background block.</statement>
      <rationale>Long Given chains couple the test to setup details that change independently of the behaviour being tested, making AC brittle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/ac-bdd.md">GWT AC template with scenario structure and non-functional sections.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Rule-Based Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use rule-based checklists for system constraints: "The system must [behaviour]", "The system must not [behaviour]", "When [condition], system must [behaviour]". Every item must be independently testable.</statement>
      <rationale>Rule-based format is clearer for constraint-heavy stories (validation, security, performance) where the scenario structure adds boilerplate without clarity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/ac-rule-based.md">Rule-based AC template covering functional, validation, error, performance, and security criteria.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Coverage Categories">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every story must have at least one criterion per applicable category: happy (what happens when everything works), error (what happens when things go wrong), boundary (limits and edge cases). Security and performance criteria are required when applicable.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents overfit to the happy path. A ratio of error/boundary/security AC to happy-path AC below 1:2 is a smell. Explicitly requiring coverage categories prevents this.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Negative cases must represent at least 30% of total AC for any story. If the count falls below this, the authoring agent must generate additional error and boundary criteria before finalizing.</statement>
      <rationale>Real systems fail in more ways than they succeed. Under-coverage of failure modes is the most common cause of regression post-deploy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Behaviour Level Enforcement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep all criteria at behaviour level. Reject any criterion containing: database table names, ORM model names, framework route paths, class names, or function names.</statement>
      <rationale>Implementation-coupled AC break whenever the implementation changes, even when the behaviour does not. The BA-agent must post-process with a regex denylist and reject violators before writing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Performance and security NFRs written in AC must be paired with a named verification tool or periodic gate in the test plan (k6, Artillery, Lighthouse CI). Write "performance: verifiable via [tool]" or remove the criterion.</statement>
      <rationale>Unverifiable NFRs (response under 200ms with no test) are theatre that wastes stakeholder review time and creates false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
