<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SERP Intent Classification Rubric Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every SERP Intent Classification Rubric application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-closed-set-classes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Primary intent MUST be one of exactly four classes: Informational (I), Comparative (C), Transactional (T), Navigational (N). Custom classes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Open-ended intent vocabularies become noise; a closed set is the only way to keep the rubric repeatable across taggers.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-serp-evidence-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every classification MUST cite ≥2 independent SERP signals (page-type distribution, SERP features, related searches, snippet word patterns).</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Gut-feel intent tags are wrong ~30% of the time on long-tail queries; SERP-evidence anchoring makes classification falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-secondary-optional" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A secondary intent MAY be tagged ONLY if ≥30% of top-10 results clearly serve a different class.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Auto-adding secondaries dilutes the contract for drafters.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-intent-mix-split" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When two distinct intent classes share comparable SERP weight, recommend SPLIT — produce two briefs, not a hedged 'covers both'.</statement>
      <rationale source="ahrefs.com/blog/search-intent">Hedged content serves neither audience; splitting at classification time is cheaper than rewriting.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-ambiguous-blocker" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If SERP top-10 has &lt;3 dominant page types AND no clear SERP features, tag intent=AMBIGUOUS and block content production pending user research.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion intent-mix audit 2026">Drafting on ambiguous SERPs is gambling; the right move is research.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-brand-vs-generic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Navigational MUST distinguish brand-N (specific company/product) from category-N (generic 'best CRM'); mis-tagging generic queries as brand-N is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="moz.com/blog/search-intent">Generic queries surfacing brand pages are Comparative or Transactional, not Navigational.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
