<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SERP Intent Classification Rubric Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules that force every target query through an evidence-anchored intent classification before drafting. Unanchored intent tags = AI slop downstream.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-closed-set-classes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The primary intent MUST be one of exactly four classes: Informational (I), Comparative (C), Transactional (T), Navigational (N). Custom classes ("educational-transactional") = REJECT. Sub-types are allowed inside each class (e.g. I:how-to / I:definition / C:vs / C:best-list / T:buy / T:tool-signup) but the primary letter is one-of-four.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Open-ended intent vocabularies become noise; teams disagree on labels. A closed set is the only way to keep the rubric repeatable across taggers.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-serp-evidence-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every classification MUST cite at least TWO independent SERP signals: (a) page-type distribution in top-10 (blog / comparison / product / docs / video / forum), (b) SERP features present (featured snippet / PAA / shopping / image pack), (c) "related searches" framing, (d) snippet word patterns ("how", "best", "vs", "buy"). Classification without evidence = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Gut-feel intent tags are wrong ~30% of the time on long-tail queries. SERP-evidence anchoring is what makes the classification falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-secondary-intent-optional-not-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A secondary intent MAY be tagged ONLY if ≥ 30% of top-10 results clearly serve a different class than the primary. Otherwise secondary intent stays empty. Defaulting to secondary = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Auto-adding secondaries dilutes the contract for drafters. Secondary intent should only appear when the SERP itself is split.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-intent-mix-split-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If a query genuinely serves two distinct intent classes with comparable SERP weight (e.g. half informational, half transactional), the rubric MUST recommend SPLIT — produce two briefs, one per intent — not a hedge "covers both" classification.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Hedged content serves neither audience. Splitting at classification time is cheaper than rewriting after the article fails to rank.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-ambiguous-query-blocker" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If SERP top-10 has fewer than 3 dominant page types and no clear SERP features, the rubric MUST tag intent=AMBIGUOUS and block content production pending user research (interviews, GSC query data, paid-search intent data). Forcing a classification on ambiguous SERPs = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Ambiguous SERPs are usually emerging or thin topics. Drafting blindly is gambling; the right move is research, not classification by gut.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-brand-vs-generic-disambiguation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Navigational intent MUST distinguish brand-N (a specific company/product) from category-N (a generic site type like "best CRM"). Generic queries tagged Navigational because the SERP shows brand pages are misclassified — they are Comparative or Transactional. Mis-tagging brand-N = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">"Best CRM" surfaces brand pages, but the user is comparing, not navigating. Conflating these wastes effort building branded content for non-brand queries.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example title="Classification output">
      <text>query="hubspot vs pipedrive"  primary=C:vs  secondary=null  evidence=[top-10: 7 comparison-blog, 2 brand-pages, 1 review-site | features: featured_snippet=comparison_table, PAA=present, video=absent | related: "hubspot vs salesforce", "pipedrive review"]  recommendation: SINGLE_BRIEF  drafter_contract: comparison table mandatory, "best for whom" verdicts mandatory</text>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../search-intent-to-brief/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../seo-manager/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
