<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="k8s-limitrange">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>infrastructure-engineer</domain>
    <summary>Apply LimitRange to every namespace to set per-container default requests/limits, enforce min/max bounds, and prevent individual containers from monopolizing cluster resources.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>kubernetes</tag>
      <tag>limitrange</tag>
      <tag>namespace-policy</tag>
      <tag>resource-governance</tag>
      <tag>multi-tenancy</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>infra</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="k8s-resource-requests-limits"/>
      <ref slug="k8s-resource-quota"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Kubernetes LimitRange — Per-Container Resource Governance</title>

    <summary>A LimitRange is a namespace-scoped policy that enforces resource constraints at the individual container or pod level. It provides automatic defaults (so containers without explicit resources still get sensible values), minimum/maximum bounds (preventing extremes), and optional limit-to-request ratio caps. Every namespace in a multi-tenant or production cluster MUST have a LimitRange. Without one, containers that omit the resources block receive BestEffort QoS and can consume unlimited node resources.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>LimitRange solves two distinct problems. First, the defaults problem: developers frequently omit the resources block in container specs. Without a LimitRange, those containers become BestEffort and destabilize the cluster under memory pressure. With a LimitRange default set, omitted resources are filled in automatically by the admission controller. Second, the bounds problem: even when developers set resources, they may set values that are too large (monopolizing a node) or too small (causing immediate OOMKill). LimitRange min/max reject out-of-range specs at admission time, before a pod is ever scheduled.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Every namespace in a production or shared cluster — create LimitRange as part of namespace provisioning.</item>
        <item>When developers frequently forget to set resources on containers (defaults solve this automatically).</item>
        <item>When a container is being OOMKilled immediately at startup — check if LimitRange max is lower than the required memory.</item>
        <item>When a single container is consuming an entire node — set LimitRange max.cpu and max.memory.</item>
        <item>When enforcing commit to a CPU overcommit policy — use maxLimitRequestRatio.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-pod test namespaces where you explicitly manage every container's resources — LimitRange adds admission overhead with no value.</item>
        <item>When all workloads already have explicit resources and you only need aggregate caps — use ResourceQuota alone.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="limitrange-types">
      <p>LimitRange supports three resource types: Container (most common), Pod (aggregate), and PersistentVolumeClaim (storage). Each type has independent min/max/default/defaultRequest fields.</p>
      <rules>
        <rule>
          <statement>Create a Container-type LimitRange in every namespace. At minimum, set default and defaultRequest for cpu and memory so containers without explicit resources receive sensible values instead of BestEffort QoS.</statement>
          <rationale>The admission controller applies LimitRange defaults at pod creation time. This is a backstop for developer omissions and makes cluster behavior predictable regardless of spec completeness.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Set LimitRange max.cpu and max.memory to prevent single-container monopoly. Recommended: max.cpu = 4-8 (depending on node size), max.memory = 8Gi-16Gi. Specs exceeding max are rejected at admission with a clear error.</statement>
          <rationale>Without an upper bound, a misconfigured container (e.g., requests: memory: 128Gi) silently creates an unschedulable pod. Bounds make the misconfiguration visible immediately rather than after failed scheduling.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Set defaultRequest lower than default limit: defaultRequest.cpu = 100-250m, default.cpu = 500m-1000m; defaultRequest.memory = 128-256Mi, default.memory = 256-512Mi. This gives containers that omit resources a Burstable QoS by default.</statement>
          <rationale>A container that receives defaultRequest = default would get Guaranteed QoS by accident, reserving node resources that may not be needed. Burstable is the correct default for unknown workloads.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section name="limitrange-ratio">
      <p>The maxLimitRequestRatio field caps how much a limit can exceed a request for a given resource, preventing extreme overcommit in the namespace.</p>
      <rules>
        <rule>
          <statement>Use maxLimitRequestRatio.cpu to cap CPU overcommit (recommended: 4-10x). Use maxLimitRequestRatio.memory to cap memory overcommit (recommended: 2-4x). Memory overcommit is more dangerous than CPU overcommit because memory pressure causes OOMKill, not throttling.</statement>
          <rationale>CPU is compressible (throttle, not kill); memory is not. Allowing 10x CPU overcommit is survivable; allowing 10x memory overcommit on a node means the node will OOMKill pods under full utilization.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section name="environment-profiles">
      <p>LimitRange values differ meaningfully between development and production environments. Production should be strict; development should be permissive to avoid blocking exploratory work.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Development: low defaults (cpu: 200m, memory: 256Mi), generous max (cpu: 2, memory: 4Gi), no maxLimitRequestRatio.</item>
        <item>Staging: medium defaults (cpu: 500m, memory: 512Mi), moderate max (cpu: 4, memory: 8Gi), ratio 4:1 CPU, 2:1 memory.</item>
        <item>Production: higher defaults (cpu: 1, memory: 1Gi), strict max (cpu: 4, memory: 8Gi), ratio 4:1 CPU, 2:1 memory.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <example type="good" title="Standard production LimitRange">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: v1
kind: LimitRange
metadata:
  name: default-limits
  namespace: production
spec:
  limits:
  - type: Container
    default:
      cpu: 500m
      memory: 512Mi
    defaultRequest:
      cpu: 100m
      memory: 128Mi
    min:
      cpu: 50m
      memory: 64Mi
    max:
      cpu: "4"
      memory: 8Gi
    maxLimitRequestRatio:
      cpu: "10"
      memory: "4"
]]></code>
    </example>

    <example type="good" title="Pod-level and storage LimitRange">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# Pod-level aggregate cap (all containers combined)
apiVersion: v1
kind: LimitRange
metadata:
  name: pod-limits
  namespace: production
spec:
  limits:
  - type: Pod
    max:
      cpu: "8"
      memory: 16Gi
    min:
      cpu: 100m
      memory: 128Mi
---
# Storage PVC cap
apiVersion: v1
kind: LimitRange
metadata:
  name: storage-limits
  namespace: production
spec:
  limits:
  - type: PersistentVolumeClaim
    min:
      storage: 1Gi
    max:
      storage: 100Gi
]]></code>
    </example>

    <example type="good" title="Development namespace (relaxed)">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: v1
kind: LimitRange
metadata:
  name: dev-limits
  namespace: development
spec:
  limits:
  - type: Container
    default:
      cpu: 200m
      memory: 256Mi
    defaultRequest:
      cpu: 50m
      memory: 64Mi
    max:
      cpu: "2"
      memory: 4Gi
]]></code>
    </example>

    <example type="good" title="Production strict with maxLimitRequestRatio">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: v1
kind: LimitRange
metadata:
  name: prod-limits
  namespace: production
spec:
  limits:
  - type: Container
    default:
      cpu: "1"
      memory: 1Gi
    defaultRequest:
      cpu: 250m
      memory: 256Mi
    min:
      cpu: 100m
      memory: 128Mi
    max:
      cpu: "4"
      memory: 8Gi
    maxLimitRequestRatio:
      cpu: "4"      # Limit cannot exceed 4x request
      memory: "2"   # Limit cannot exceed 2x request
  - type: Pod
    max:
      cpu: "8"
      memory: 16Gi
]]></code>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="LimitRange default exceeds max">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
spec:
  limits:
  - type: Container
    default:
      cpu: "8"        # WRONG: default exceeds max
      memory: 32Gi
    max:
      cpu: "4"
      memory: 8Gi
]]></code>
      <note>The API server rejects this configuration. Default must be &lt;= max and &gt;= min, and defaultRequest must be &lt;= default.</note>
    </example>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Creating a LimitRange but omitting min values, relying only on max.</description>
      <reason>Without min, containers can set requests of 1m CPU and 1Mi memory, guaranteeing scheduling on a node that cannot actually satisfy meaningful work. Min enforces a floor that makes scheduling decisions honest.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Using identical LimitRange values across production and development namespaces.</description>
      <reason>Production defaults should be higher (reflecting real workload needs and reducing BestEffort accidents); development defaults should be lower (reducing wasted cluster resources for exploratory work). Same values mean one environment is always misconfigured.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting default.memory too high so containers with no resources spec immediately exhaust namespace ResourceQuota.</description>
      <reason>If 20 containers each inherit a 4Gi default limit from LimitRange, and the namespace quota is limits.memory: 20Gi, a single deployment of 6 replicas exhausts the quota. LimitRange defaults must be sized against the namespace's ResourceQuota and expected pod count.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <checklist>
      <check>Create LimitRange for every namespace (production, staging, development, team namespaces).</check>
      <check>Set sensible defaults for containers without explicit resources (prevents BestEffort QoS).</check>
      <check>Define min/max bounds to prevent extremes (too small = crash, too large = monopoly).</check>
      <check>Set defaultRequest lower than default limit to produce Burstable QoS by default.</check>
      <check>Test pod creation without explicit resources — verify defaults are applied.</check>
      <check>Test rejection of oversized containers (request cpu: 100 should fail).</check>
      <check>Verify LimitRange defaults are consistent with namespace ResourceQuota capacity.</check>
      <check>Document LimitRange values and rationale for the team.</check>
    </checklist>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/limitrange-profiles.yaml" purpose="LimitRange templates for development, staging, and production environments."/>
    </templates>

    <prompt purpose="Generate LimitRange for environment"><![CDATA[
Generate a LimitRange for a [development/staging/production] namespace with:

Environment: [dev/staging/production]
Team size: [small/medium/large]
Workload types: [web services, workers, databases, etc.]

Requirements:
- Prevent resource hogging by single containers
- Ensure minimum resources for stability
- Set sensible defaults for forgetful developers
- Allow burst for variable workloads

Output: Complete LimitRange YAML with comments explaining each value.
]]></prompt>

    <prompt purpose="Audit LimitRange consistency with ResourceQuota"><![CDATA[
Audit this namespace configuration:

LimitRange:
[PASTE LIMITRANGE YAML]

ResourceQuota:
[PASTE RESOURCEQUOTA YAML]

Check:
1. LimitRange defaults align with quota capacity
2. Max limits don't exceed quota
3. Defaults won't cause immediate quota exhaustion
4. Storage limits match actual needs
5. Object counts are reasonable

Output: Audit report with findings and remediation steps.
]]></prompt>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="k8s-resource-requests-limits"/>
      <ref slug="k8s-resource-quota"/>
      <link href="https://kubernetes.io/docs/concepts/policy/limit-range/"/>
      <link href="https://www.perfectscale.io/blog/kubernetes-resource-quotas-limit-ranges"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
