<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-frameworks" title="Nine Minimum Product Frameworks">
  <summary>The nine minimum-product frameworks, each mapped to its purpose and primary use condition.</summary>

  <section title="Framework Catalogue">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose the framework before scoping. The choice determines what "minimum" means for your release.</statement>
      <rationale>Each framework optimises for a different success criterion. Defaulting to MVP in a crowded consumer market produces a product users ignore.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>MVP — Minimum Viable Product: test core assumptions. Use when entering a new market with an unvalidated idea.</item>
      <item>MLP — Minimum Lovable Product: create emotional connection. Use in crowded markets where differentiation is experience.</item>
      <item>MMP — Minimum Marketable Product: generate first revenue. Use in B2B and enterprise sales contexts.</item>
      <item>MAC — Minimum Awesome Component: build one killer feature. Use when feature-based differentiation is the strategy.</item>
      <item>RAT — Riskiest Assumption Test: validate the biggest risk. Use on high-uncertainty projects before any build.</item>
      <item>MDP — Minimum Delightful Product: exceed expectations. Use for premium positioning.</item>
      <item>MVA — Minimum Valuable Product: deliver business value to the buyer. Use in enterprise ROI-focused contexts.</item>
      <item>MFP — Minimum Functional Product: prove technical feasibility. Use for complex infrastructure or novel tech.</item>
      <item>SLC — Simple, Lovable, Complete: balance simplicity and polish. Use for consumer apps needing immediate full-loop value.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Insight">
    <rule>
      <statement>In crowded markets, an MVP that is merely "viable" will fail. Users already have "good enough" solutions; you need "awesome" or "lovable" to earn a switch.</statement>
      <rationale>Market density changes the minimum bar. A blue-ocean product can be rough; a red-ocean product must clear an existing quality floor before users will try it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
