<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-decision-matrix" title="Framework Decision Matrix">
  <summary>Market-condition to framework mapping with rationale for each selection.</summary>

  <section title="Primary Decision Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Blue ocean, unvalidated demand: use MVP or RAT. Validate existence of the problem before investing in experience.</statement>
      <rationale>No competing solutions means users will tolerate rough UX to get any solution at all. Validation cost is low, so run RAT first and MVP second.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Red ocean, many competitors: use MLP or MAC. Users must prefer your product over existing alternatives on day one.</statement>
      <rationale>Switching cost is real. A barely-functional product in a crowded market has no gravitational pull; you need either superior experience (MLP) or a single dominant feature (MAC).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Enterprise B2B: use MMP or MVA. Revenue and clear ROI story are required before procurement will sign.</statement>
      <rationale>Enterprise buyers need a business case. "Viable" and "lovable" are secondary to "provably valuable to the organisation's goals".</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Consumer, emotion-driven purchase: use MLP or MDP. The product must feel right on first use to generate word-of-mouth.</statement>
      <rationale>Consumer apps succeed on referral loops. Delight drives sharing; functional-but-bland does not.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Technical uncertainty (novel infrastructure, new integration): use MFP first, then expand. Prove it can work before proving it is loved.</statement>
      <rationale>Investing in UX and delight before technical feasibility is confirmed wastes resources if the technical approach fails.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Selection Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying MVP to every product regardless of market context.</description>
      <reason>"MVP" as a default ignores market conditions. In competitive markets it produces products that users dismiss before forming a habit.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Choosing MLP or MDP for an unvalidated problem.</description>
      <reason>Investing in delight before validating demand is expensive misdirection. Polish a product nobody wants is still a product nobody wants.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
