<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-antipatterns" title="Agentic brainstorming antipatterns">
  <summary>Four common failure modes in agent-driven ideation: circular scoring bias, premature convergence, semantic clustering errors, and positional bias in large lists.</summary>

  <section title="Circular scoring bias">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using the same agent that generated the ideas to also dot-vote or rank them.</description>
      <reason>The generating agent has higher confidence in ideas it produced with higher certainty in the first pass. Self-scoring compounds this into a self-reinforcing ranking with no independent judgment.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Scoring must be done by a separate agent or human. The generating agent provides the list; a fresh agent or human applies the scoring rubric.</statement>
      <rationale>Separation of generation and evaluation is the most important architectural rule in agentic brainstorming pipelines.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Premature convergence">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Including evaluation language ("good idea because...", "this works better than option B") in the generation prompt.</description>
      <reason>The model self-censors and produces fewer, safer ideas. The generation pass becomes a mixed pass that produces a filtered list masquerading as a brainstorm.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Generation prompt must contain only: problem statement, constraints, format instructions, and quantity target. No evaluation language.</statement>
      <rationale>Strict format enforcement (numbered list only, no explanations) prevents evaluation language from contaminating output even when the model defaults to justification.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Semantic clustering failures">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Accepting cluster assignments without human review, particularly when two conceptually distinct approaches share domain vocabulary.</description>
      <reason>Cosine similarity clusters by word overlap. "Automate onboarding email sequence" and "Automate onboarding task assignment" may cluster together despite being architecturally different solutions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Positional bias in large lists">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Passing a list of 50+ ideas to a scoring prompt in a single call.</description>
      <reason>Ideas in positions 1-15 receive systematically higher scores than identical ideas in positions 35-50 due to positional bias in LLM attention. The first batch is not comparable to the last batch.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Chunk idea lists into batches of 25 for scoring. Score each batch against the rubric independently, then compare top-scored ideas across batches in a final pass.</statement>
      <rationale>Chunking equalizes positional treatment. Cross-batch comparison in the final pass is a manageable 25-item set with no positional artifact.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
