<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Review Facilitation Script Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Design Review Facilitation Script. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-three-round-format" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Feedback is structured in three rounds in strict order: clarify-questions → critique → suggest-alternatives; mixing rounds is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Critique-method literature">Mixing rounds produces noise: clarifying questions get answered with critique, critique gets answered with alternatives, alternatives lose grounding.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-review-ask-up-front" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Designer states the review-ask in a single sentence at meeting open; reviewers must keep feedback on that scope.</statement>
      <rationale source="Facilitation-discipline practice">Without a stated ask, reviewers default to &apos;all my opinions&apos;; the ask focuses the room.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-one-must-fix-per-reviewer" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>In the triage round each reviewer picks exactly one must-fix item; designer commits or explicitly declines with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-velocity convention">Unbounded must-fix lists produce backlog rot; one-per-reviewer forces priority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-commit-or-decline-on-the-spot" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Designer commits or explicitly declines each must-fix item before meeting close; &apos;I&apos;ll think about it&apos; is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-velocity convention">Deferred decisions recur in the next review; commit/decline ends the loop.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-action-list-routed-to-tracker" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Committed must-fix items are created as tracker tickets in the same meeting; verbal-only commitments are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-folklore convention">Verbal commitments evaporate; tracker tickets create a trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-design-review-facilitation-script.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
