<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Pulse Survey — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for the 4-question morale pulse, anonymity, alert thresholds, and PM SLA.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-four-question-cap" testable="true">
      <statement>The pulse asks EXACTLY 4 questions, no exceptions: (Q1) eNPS "How likely are you to recommend this team as a place to work? 0-10", (Q2) workload 1-10, (Q3) autonomy 1-10, (Q4) clarity 1-10. Adding a 5th question drops response rate ~12pp per added question.</statement>
      <rationale source="Officevibe Pulse research, Tinypulse cohort data">Response rate is the dominant variable. 4 questions hit a 75-85% completion rate; 7+ questions drop to 30-50%. Trend signal requires consistent response rate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-anonymity-floor" testable="true">
      <statement>Aggregate results MUST be hidden until ≥ 3 respondents AND ≥ 60% of team has responded. Team size &lt; 5 → suppress per-axis median, report only "responded / not responded" counts.</statement>
      <rationale source="Differential privacy practice / Gallup small-group recommendation">N-of-1 or N-of-2 reports are de-anonymising; team members can identify whose answer drove the alert. Suppression rule is the social contract that keeps response rate sustainable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-alert-thresholds" testable="true">
      <statement>An alert fires when ANY of: (a) eNPS aggregate dropped &gt; 20 points in 1 sprint, (b) median on any axis &lt; 6, (c) response rate dropped below 50% (silent disengagement signal). Alert triggers a manager 1:1 with each team member within 48 business hours.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gallup Q12 alert-threshold studies + Lencioni distressed-team patterns">eNPS drop &gt; 20 is the leading indicator of attrition by 6-12 weeks. Median &lt; 6 means &gt; 30% of team is unhappy. Response-rate collapse precedes both.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-action-sla" testable="true">
      <statement>If alert fired, PM MUST schedule (and complete) 1:1s with all team members within 48 BUSINESS HOURS of alert. If 1:1s cannot happen, the SURVEY MUST PAUSE until the PM is ready to act. Running pulse without acting destroys trust faster than not running pulse.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tinypulse 2019 trust-decay study">Teams that experience "feedback theatre" (asked, no action) churn 2.5× faster than teams not surveyed at all. The pause rule prevents anti-survey damage.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-retaliation" testable="true">
      <statement>Survey aggregate must NEVER tie scores back to individuals, even when team size + technical channel make it possible. PM must publicly state the no-retaliation policy at every pulse launch and treat any 1:1 information as confidential.</statement>
      <rationale source="OSHA whistleblower protections / EEOC retaliation guidance">Retaliation kills the system AND has legal exposure. The verbal commitment is part of the methodology, not an HR add-on.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="The 4-question template">

    <example type="good" title="Pulse text (verbatim)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1) On a scale of 0-10, how likely are you to recommend this
   team as a place to work?    (eNPS)

2) On a scale of 1-10, how is your workload this week?
   (1 = drowning, 10 = ideal)

3) On a scale of 1-10, how much autonomy do you have over
   what you work on?

4) On a scale of 1-10, how clear are the goals for this sprint?

Optional comment box: "anything you want me to know?"
      ]]></code>
      <note>~60 seconds, single question per axis. Comment box is OPTIONAL — required comment box would drop response rate.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Survey scope creep (r1 violation)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
1) eNPS
2) workload
3) autonomy
4) clarity
5) "Do you feel valued by your manager?"
6) "How is your relationship with peers?"
7) "How do you rate the company benefits?"

7 questions. Response rate drops to ~40%. Trend data is noise.
PM cannot tell whether morale changed or sample changed.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1 cap is hard. New axes go in a quarterly engagement survey, not the weekly pulse.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
