<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SEO Audit Runbook Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every SEO Audit Runbook application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them. Plus a skip-methodology rule for decision-tree leaves that exit the methodology.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-crawl-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 1 (Crawl) MUST produce: full URL inventory, status-code distribution, orphan-URL list, duplicate-title/description list. Missing any artefact = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="Foundation phase">Without a current crawl, every subsequent phase analyses stale data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-on-page-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 2 (On-Page) MUST sample at least the top-100-traffic URLs by GSC clicks and audit each against on-page-seo-checklist-2026. Findings filed with URL + checklist-item-id + severity. &lt;Top-100 = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="Pareto sampling">Top-traffic URLs concentrate revenue; on-page issues there have outsize fix-impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-content-decay-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 3 (Content Decay) MUST compare GSC clicks/impressions audit-window vs prior equivalent window, flag URLs with ≥30% decline still ranking top-20, assign each to {refresh, merge, delete, redirect}.</statement>
      <rationale source="Highest-ROI lever">Decay is the highest ROI for established sites and the easiest to skip.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-links-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 4 (Links) MUST audit: internal-link graph for orphan/under-linked top-of-funnel pages, external backlink growth/loss, toxic-backlink candidates (if any). All three sub-audits required.</statement>
      <rationale source="Defensible audit">Internal-only misses link-loss attacks; external-only misses internal cluster gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-tech-seo-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 5 (Tech-SEO) MUST verify: Core Web Vitals (field data, not lab), indexability (robots.txt, X-Robots-Tag, canonical chains), structured-data validation, hreflang for multilingual, mobile parity. Lab CWV = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field-data floor">Lab numbers mislead on real-user performance and lose engineering credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-report-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 6 (Report) MUST emit executive summary (≤1 page), findings backlog ranked by ICE or RICE, recommended sequencing (quick wins ≤30 days, structural ≤60), sign-off block. Unranked backlog = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-ready output">Unranked backlogs rot in Notion; ranking turns the audit into work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the decision tree resolves to a skip branch — preconditions are not met OR an adjacent methodology fits better.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-tree discipline">Skipping cleanly preserves the integrity of the rubric; misapplied methodologies produce false positives downstream.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
