<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SEO Audit Runbook Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules — one per audit phase — that govern a repeatable annual SEO audit. Skipping any phase ships a partial audit that misleads the prioritisation backlog.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-crawl-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 1 (Crawl) MUST produce: (a) full URL inventory from a desktop crawler (Screaming Frog / Sitebulb / Lumar) capped at the live sitemap, (b) status-code distribution, (c) orphan-URL list (in crawl, not in sitemap; in sitemap, not in crawl), (d) duplicate-title / duplicate-description list. Missing any artefact = phase REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Without a current crawl, every subsequent phase analyses stale data. Orphan + duplicate detection is the cheapest 80/20 win an audit produces.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-on-page-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 2 (On-Page) MUST sample at least the top-100-traffic URLs (by GSC clicks) and audit each against `on-page-seo-checklist-2026`. Findings MUST be filed with URL + checklist-item-id + severity (P0/P1/P2). Sampling fewer than top-100 = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Top-traffic URLs concentrate revenue; on-page issues there have outsize fix-impact. Auditing low-traffic URLs first is a common time-sink.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-content-decay-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 3 (Content Decay) MUST compare GSC clicks/impressions for the audit window vs the prior equivalent window, flag URLs with ≥30% decline that still rank in top-20, and assign each to one of {refresh, merge, delete, redirect}. Decay phase WITHOUT decision per URL = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Decay is the highest ROI for established sites and the easiest to skip. Forcing a per-URL decision turns a list into work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-links-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 4 (Links) MUST audit: (a) internal-link graph for orphan / under-linked top-of-funnel pages, (b) external backlink growth/loss over the window from Ahrefs/SEMrush/Majestic, (c) toxic-backlink candidates flagged for disavow review (if any). All three sub-audits required.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Internal-link audits alone miss external link-loss attacks; external-only audits miss internal cluster gaps. Both are required for a defensible audit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-tech-seo-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 5 (Tech-SEO) MUST verify: Core Web Vitals (CrUX or PageSpeed Insights field data, not lab), indexability (robots.txt, X-Robots-Tag, canonical chains), structured-data validation (Rich Results Test for top templates), hreflang for multilingual sites, and mobile parity. Field data, not lab data, is the floor.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Lab CWV (Lighthouse synthetic) misleads on real-user performance; Google ranks on field data. Auditors who use lab numbers lose credibility with engineering.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-report-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase 6 (Report) MUST emit a single document with: executive summary (≤ 1 page), findings backlog ranked by ICE or RICE score, recommended sequencing (quick wins first 30 days, structural fixes next 60), and a sign-off block (auditor + recipient + date). Reports without a ranked backlog = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Unranked findings backlogs rot in Notion. Ranking + sequencing is what turns the audit from a deliverable into actual work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example title="Finding entry">
      <text>id: F-014  phase: content-decay  url: /blog/best-crm-2024  observation: clicks ↓ 58% vs prior 12mo, still ranks #6 for primary query  decision: refresh  proposed_action: update with 2026 entities + new SERP-features table  ICE: I=8 C=8 E=7 → score=448  owner: @content-lead  due: sprint+2</text>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../seo-manager/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../../../solo/marketing/on-page-seo-checklist-2026/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../../../solo/marketing/search-intent-to-brief/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
