<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-cohort-types" title="Cohort Types and Retention Table Reading Guide">
  <summary>Three cohort types (acquisition, behavioral, feature), what each reveals, and how to read a cohort retention table including the diagonal effect.</summary>

  <section title="Cohort Types">
    <list>
      <item>Acquisition cohort: group by signup period (week/month). Use for: tracking retention trends over time, measuring product quality improvement, comparing channel quality.</item>
      <item>Behavioral cohort: group by action taken (e.g. completed onboarding vs skipped). Use for: finding valuable user behaviors to drive in onboarding, validating activation hypotheses.</item>
      <item>Feature cohort: group by feature used in first N days. Use for: identifying "magic features" that predict retention, prioritizing feature adoption in onboarding flow.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every acquisition cohort review with at least one behavioral cohort; acquisition cohorts show what, behavioral cohorts show why.</statement>
      <rationale>Acquisition trends alone cannot identify what to fix; behavioral cohorts reveal the specific actions that separate high-retention from low-retention users.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Reading a Cohort Table">
    <p>Table structure: row = cohort (signup period), column = day since joining, cell = % of cohort still active. Always show absolute cohort size alongside percentages.</p>
    <list>
      <item>reading rows: how a single cohort ages over time</item>
      <item>reading columns: comparing the same time point across different cohorts (trend direction)</item>
      <item>reading diagonals: moving diagonally down-left shows the current state — each diagonal cell represents what that cohort's users are doing "today"</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Show the absolute cohort size next to every retention rate; a "30%" cell built on n=20 is anecdote, not data — grey-label it "underpowered".</statement>
      <rationale>Small cohort percentages have high sampling variance; displaying only the percentage creates false confidence in unstable numbers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Insights from Each Cohort Type">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Acquisition cohort: D30 improving from 12% (Oct) to 18% (Jan) → product quality or onboarding is improving. Investigate what changed in Nov-Jan to understand the cause.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Behavioral cohort: users completing onboarding (n=1500) have D30=45% vs skipped (n=2500) D30=15% → 3x lift. Priority: increase onboarding completion rate, not add features.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Feature cohort: users who invited a teammate in week 1 retain at D90=38% vs non-inviter D90=10% → "collaboration" is a magic feature. Priority: prompt team invite in onboarding.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
