<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-analysis-rules" title="Cohort Analysis Rules and Failure Modes">
  <summary>Mandatory rules for valid cohort analysis: minimum cohort size, diagonal effect, survivorship bias, magic-feature fallacy, and time-zone correctness.</summary>

  <section title="Minimum Cohort Size">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use weekly cohorts for early-stage products; switch to monthly once signup volume exceeds 10k per week. Suppress or grey-label cohorts with fewer than 100 users.</statement>
      <rationale>Too-granular cohorts produce wild percentage swings from small sample sizes; the trend noise overwhelms the signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Diagonal Effect">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never compare D90 retention across cohorts until every cohort in the comparison has at least 90 days of history.</statement>
      <rationale>The diagonal effect: newest cohorts have incomplete observable history. A D90 comparison that includes a 30-day-old cohort is meaningless — the cell is empty, not zero.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Survivorship Bias">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not use retained users to define "valuable behaviors" — filter to only users who were active at signup, not those who survived to D30, before computing behavioral cohorts.</statement>
      <rationale>The survivorship bias / magic-feature fallacy: if you define feature users as "users who used feature X and stayed", you have already filtered out churned users who also used it. Any feature correlates with retention when computed this way.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Time Zone Correctness">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use explicit timezone and a date floor in all cohort SQL; a signup at 23:55 UTC and a first event at 00:05 UTC creates a phantom D1 event — enforce UTC floor(event_date) = floor(signup_date) for day 0.</statement>
      <rationale>Timezone bugs are the most common source of incorrect D1 retention inflating by 10–30%.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Agent Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Confusing "retained" (still active in window) with "returned" (came back on exact day N).</description>
      <reason>The two definitions produce very different numbers; always pin the definition in the prompt and verify the SQL.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using SUM where COUNT(DISTINCT user_id) is needed.</description>
      <reason>SUM counts events, not users; a multi-event session inflates the count. Agents default to SUM in naive SQL.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Claiming a behavioral cohort finding proves causation ("feature X caused the lift").</description>
      <reason>Behavioral cohort analysis is correlational — redirect to ab-testing-basics for causal claims.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
