<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="mlp-planning Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for mlp-planning. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All core features must score 4+ on all four layers before claiming MLP status. Delight (Layer 4) cannot compensate for gaps in Functional (1), Reliable (2), or Usable (3).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Delight applied to a broken or confusing product amplifies the frustration — users notice the personality of a product that still crashes or loses their data more acutely than they would on a dull product.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>MLP = MVP + delight. Not more features — better experience of existing features. Audit before building; most products reach MLP by polishing the core, not by adding functionality.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Adding features to a sub-MLP product increases surface area for friction without addressing the root cause: the existing interactions are not good enough to generate retention.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require at least one delight idea per category from the audit before picking the sprint focus. Agents default to Personality and Celebration; Speed and Anticipation are underrepresented without forcing.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Speed is the cheapest and most underrated delight lever — performance budgets on the core action produce retention lift with zero UX redesign cost. Forcing coverage prevents category tunnel-vision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score each polish task as Pain × Frequency × Visibility. If any factor is hard to estimate, use additive scoring (Pain + Frequency + Visibility) to avoid a single zero zeroing out a real opportunity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The multiplicative formula breaks down when any dimension is genuinely uncertain — a low-frequency interaction that causes severe pain still deserves consideration, but a zero in Frequency produces a score of zero multiplicatively.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
