<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="MLP Planning Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Four-layer Minimum Lovable Product audit (Functional -&gt; Reliable -&gt; Usable -&gt; Delightful) for evolving an MVP that users call 'fine' into one they love and recommend.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="four-layer-audit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>MLP plan MUST audit all four layers (Functional, Reliable, Usable, Delightful) and assign a score 0-5 per layer with cited evidence (metric or quote).</statement>
      <rationale source="Aarron Walter — Designing for Emotion; Henrik Kniberg MLP essay">Single-layer focus on broken Functional/Reliable layers wastes budget; full audit prevents top-of-pyramid investment on a shaky base.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="delight-only-when-base-ge-3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Delight investments are forbidden when Functional or Reliable score &lt; 3. Fix the base first.</statement>
      <rationale source="Maslow-style needs hierarchy applied to product">Delight on a buggy product amplifies frustration; users notice polish on broken flows more, not less.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="emotion-evidence-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Delight items MUST cite verbatim user quotes or moment-of-truth observations, not designer opinion.</statement>
      <rationale source="Continuous discovery / customer-development">Designer-opinion delight ships features the team loves and users don't notice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="retention-curve-as-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>MLP success metric is the Day-30 retention curve, not feature throughput. The plan MUST define the curve target before sprint kickoff.</statement>
      <rationale source="Andrew Chen — Mobile App Retention research">Without a curve target, MLP work shows up as activity, not impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="delight-sprint-bounded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each delight sprint MUST be &lt;=2 weeks with a single named theme (onboarding, empty-state, completion). Open-ended delight work decays into polish-by-vibe.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — MLP retro audits">Open-ended delight backlogs accumulate but ship slowly; bounded sprints force scope and ship-rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — pre-MVP without Functional shipped; commodity competing on price; B2B with buyer != user; Day-30 retention already &gt;40%), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
