<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="MLP Four-Layer Framework">
  <summary>Defines the four-layer MLP model, MVP vs MLP comparison, five delight categories, polish priority formula, and five-step planning process for evolving a viable product into a lovable one.</summary>

  <section title="Four-Layer Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>All core features must score 4+ on all four layers before claiming MLP status. Delight (Layer 4) cannot compensate for gaps in Functional (1), Reliable (2), or Usable (3).</statement>
      <rationale>Delight applied to a broken or confusing product amplifies the frustration — users notice the personality of a product that still crashes or loses their data more acutely than they would on a dull product.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Layer 1 — Functional: core job gets done, no blocking bugs, acceptable performance.</item>
      <item>Layer 2 — Reliable: consistent experience, error handling, edge cases covered, works as expected every time.</item>
      <item>Layer 3 — Usable: easy to learn, efficient to use, minimal friction, good defaults.</item>
      <item>Layer 4 — Delightful: emotional satisfaction, surprising moments, premium feel, shareable moments.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="MVP vs MLP">
    <list>
      <item>MVP goal: validate. MLP goal: retain and generate word of mouth.</item>
      <item>MVP focus: functionality. MLP focus: experience on top of that functionality.</item>
      <item>MVP emotion: "it works." MLP emotion: "I love it."</item>
      <item>MVP word of mouth: unlikely. MLP word of mouth: likely.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>MLP = MVP + delight. Not more features — better experience of existing features. Audit before building; most products reach MLP by polishing the core, not by adding functionality.</statement>
      <rationale>Adding features to a sub-MLP product increases surface area for friction without addressing the root cause: the existing interactions are not good enough to generate retention.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Five Delight Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Speed: faster than expected — instant search results, sub-100ms interactions.</item>
      <item>Simplicity: easier than expected — one-click checkout, zero-configuration defaults.</item>
      <item>Personality: unexpected charm — clever copywriting, brand-consistent micro-copy.</item>
      <item>Anticipation: knows what users need before they ask — smart defaults, pre-filled fields.</item>
      <item>Celebration: acknowledges user success — confetti on completion, "you've earned $X" summaries.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require at least one delight idea per category from the audit before picking the sprint focus. Agents default to Personality and Celebration; Speed and Anticipation are underrepresented without forcing.</statement>
      <rationale>Speed is the cheapest and most underrated delight lever — performance budgets on the core action produce retention lift with zero UX redesign cost. Forcing coverage prevents category tunnel-vision.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Polish Priority Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each polish task as Pain x Frequency x Visibility. If any factor is hard to estimate, use additive scoring (Pain + Frequency + Visibility) to avoid a single zero zeroing out a real opportunity.</statement>
      <rationale>The multiplicative formula breaks down when any dimension is genuinely uncertain — a low-frequency interaction that causes severe pain still deserves consideration, but a zero in Frequency produces a score of zero multiplicatively.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-Step Planning Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Audit: score each core feature 1-5 on all four layers using current user verbatims and session replay as evidence. Do not score against aspirations.</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Identify opportunities: cluster negative-but-not-blocking feedback ("works but underwhelming") by delight category.</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Prioritize: rank by Pain x Frequency x Visibility, max 12 items.</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Define MLP criteria: write numeric completion criteria before starting (e.g., Day-30 retention target, NPS target, core action time budget).</item>
      <item>Step 5 — Plan the gap: build a sprint-by-sprint polish backlog, time-box each delight sprint at 2 weeks maximum.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/mlp-plan.md">MLP planning document with feature audit, delight opportunities, polish backlog, completion criteria, and measurement plan.</reference>
  <reference path="scripts/audit-to-backlog.sh">Bash: converts mlp-gap-finder JSON into Linear issues with Pain x Freq x Vis priority.</reference>
</text>
