<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="MLP Planning Examples">
  <summary>Note-taking app and invoicing tool MVP-to-MLP transformations with before/after tables, layer-by-layer improvements, and retention outcomes.</summary>

  <section title="Note-Taking App: MVP to MLP">
    <example type="good">
      <note>MVP state: create, edit, delete notes; basic formatting; functional but bland. Day-30 retention: 18%. NPS: 30.</note>
      <note>Layer 2 (Reliable): added auto-save with visual confirmation. Eliminated "did it save?" anxiety.</note>
      <note>Layer 3 (Usable): added keyboard shortcuts for common actions; quick capture from any screen.</note>
      <note>Layer 4 (Delight/Speed): smooth animations on state transitions; sub-50ms search.</note>
      <note>Layer 4 (Delight/Personality): "Zen mode" for focused writing; clever empty states with contextual prompts.</note>
      <note>Layer 4 (Delight/Celebration): satisfying sound on note save (opt-in).</note>
      <note>Result: Day-30 retention increased 40% (from 18% to 25%); NPS from 30 to 55. Core action time decreased 30%.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Invoicing Tool: MVP to MLP">
    <example type="good">
      <note>MVP state: create invoices, send to clients. Functional but clunky. Core action (send invoice) takes 4 minutes. Day-30 retention: 35%.</note>
      <note>Layer 2 (Reliable): payment confirmation notifications with push and email fallback.</note>
      <note>Layer 3 (Usable): templates pre-filled from past invoices; client auto-fill from contact database.</note>
      <note>Layer 4 (Delight/Celebration): animated celebration screen on payment received with amount summary.</note>
      <note>Layer 4 (Delight/Anticipation): "You've earned $X this month" dashboard tile; proactive invoice reminder suggestions.</note>
      <note>Result: users create 2x more invoices per month; NPS 60; core action time reduced from 4 minutes to 90 seconds.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Adding more features to an MVP instead of polishing existing ones to MLP threshold.</description>
      <reason>Feature addition expands surface area for friction without addressing the root retention problem. Most MVPs reach MLP by improving the core 3 features to Layer 4, not by adding a 4th feature.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Surface-level polish (new colors, marketing copy) while ignoring interaction quality (latency, defaults, error recovery).</description>
      <reason>Visual polish is visible but does not compound; interaction quality (speed, anticipation, recovery) affects every session and compounds with usage frequency.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping numeric MLP completion criteria before starting delight work.</description>
      <reason>Without exit criteria, "MLP" expands indefinitely — teams keep polishing without shipping. The criteria are the commitment mechanism that ends the sprint.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Generic delight (confetti everywhere) not tailored to the user persona.</description>
      <reason>B2B enterprise users find confetti unprofessional; Japanese users find animated celebrations intrusive. Delight must be calibrated to the specific persona's emotional context.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
