<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="mlp-planning Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for mlp-planning as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Adding more features to an MVP instead of polishing existing ones to MLP threshold.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feature addition expands surface area for friction without addressing the root retention problem. Most MVPs reach MLP by improving the core 3 features to Layer 4, not by adding a 4th feature.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Surface-level polish (new colors, marketing copy) while ignoring interaction quality (latency, defaults, error recovery).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Visual polish is visible but does not compound; interaction quality (speed, anticipation, recovery) affects every session and compounds with usage frequency.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping numeric MLP completion criteria before starting delight work.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without exit criteria, "MLP" expands indefinitely — teams keep polishing without shipping. The criteria are the commitment mechanism that ends the sprint.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Generic delight (confetti everywhere) not tailored to the user persona.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>B2B enterprise users find confetti unprofessional; Japanese users find animated celebrations intrusive. Delight must be calibrated to the specific persona's emotional context.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
