<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Retainer Conversion Script Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every project-to-retainer conversion attempt must follow.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-three-touchpoint-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exactly 3 touchpoints in the final 4 weeks: week N-4 (seed), week N-2 (proposal), week N (close). Earlier than N-4 reads as pushy; later than N-1 the client has already moved on.</statement>
      <rationale source="Jonathan Stark - pricing creativity timing studies; Blair Enns 'Win Without Pitching'">Service-business retainer conversions follow a 3-touch pattern in the win-without-pitching school. Fewer than 3 underseeds the idea; more than 3 reads as sales-y and damages the relationship. The 4-week window aligns with most clients' procurement / budget approval cycles.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-anchor-on-atrophy-not-benefits" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Touchpoint 1 names 3-5 concrete things that will atrophy without ongoing attention — never lists "benefits of retaining us". Loss frame, not gain frame.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kahneman &amp; Tversky, Prospect Theory (1979)">Loss aversion is 2x stronger than equivalent gain framing. "Your SEO rankings will decay without monthly content" lands harder than "we can keep improving your SEO". Specific atrophy items also pass the "this guy actually understands my business" test which generic benefits don't.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-tiered-offer-anchor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Touchpoint 2 presents 3 tiers (good/better/best). The middle tier is the target — it's anchored higher by the "best" tier above it. Never present a single price.</statement>
      <rationale source="Dan Ariely, Predictably Irrational - decoy pricing (2008); McKinsey B2B pricing research">Single-price offers force a binary yes/no. Three-tier offers shift the conversation to "which tier" — a meta-yes. McKinsey 2023 B2B pricing data: tiered offers convert 35-45% vs. 18-25% for single-price proposals in service businesses.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-clean-no-allowed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A "no" at touchpoint 2 or 3 is a valid outcome. Respond with gratitude and a referral ask — never extend the cadence to 4-5 touchpoints. Pushing past a no destroys 2-3 future referrals.</statement>
      <rationale source="Chris Voss, Never Split the Difference - 'no' is information">Persistence past a clear no in service business is the #1 source of the "agency people are sleazy" brand. Accepting no gracefully and asking "anyone else you know who might need this?" yields 0.3-0.7 referrals per clean exit (Bain SMB sales data, 2024).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-discount-first-conversation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The first time the client says "the price is high", you do NOT offer a discount. You ask a question: "compared to what?" or "which tier feels closest?" Discounting reflexively trains the client that your price is negotiable and tells them you don't believe in your own number.</statement>
      <rationale source="Win Without Pitching - 12 proclamations; Stark - 'never negotiate against yourself'">Service businesses with sub-20 clients can't afford a discount-trained pipeline. Asking "compared to what" surfaces the real objection (often it's scope, not price). Conversion data: agencies that held price for &gt; 5 minutes after first objection closed at 70% the original number; those that discounted in &lt; 60 seconds closed at 60%.</rationale>
    </rule>

      <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Touchpoint 1 - seed message (week N-4)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Subject: Quick note as we approach handoff

Hi {client},

We're 4 weeks out from project end and I wanted to flag a few things that
will need attention after we wrap:

1. Content publishing cadence — without weekly review the editorial calendar
   typically drifts within 6 weeks.
2. Plugin / dependency updates — security patches need a monthly cycle.
3. Performance regressions — JS bundle creep, image asset bloat.

I'm not pitching anything today — wanted to make sure these are on your radar
in case you're planning to handle them in-house. Happy to chat next week
about options if it'd help.

— {you}
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 (timing), r2 (atrophy frame), r5 (no pitch, no price).</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Touchpoint 1 - premature pitch">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Subject: Special offer for ongoing support!

Hi {client},

Since we're finishing the project, I'd like to offer you our maintenance
retainer at $3,000/month, which includes weekly reports, priority support,
and a 20% discount if you sign this month.

Problem: violates r2 (benefits frame, not atrophy), r3 (single price not tiered),
r5 (discount in first touch).
Result: client reads as sales-y, ghosts.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Premature pitch pattern destroys the relationship and the retainer.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
