<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-reports-metrics" title="Essential Reports, Key Metrics, and Quality Score">
  <summary>Which Google Ads reports to use, what each metric means, how to interpret Quality Score, and how to segment for deeper diagnosis.</summary>

  <section title="Essential Reports">
    <list>
      <item>Overview Dashboard — high-level performance snapshot</item>
      <item>Campaigns tab — campaign-level metrics, budget pacing</item>
      <item>Keywords tab — keyword performance, Quality Scores</item>
      <item>Search Terms (Keywords → Search Terms) — actual queries triggering ads</item>
      <item>Ads and Assets — RSA performance, ad strength</item>
      <item>Auction Insights — competitive position, impression share vs. competitors</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Impressions — reach potential; low = increase budget or broaden targeting</item>
      <item>CTR — ad relevance; low = improve ad copy or tighten keyword targeting</item>
      <item>Quality Score (1-10) — overall health; low = improve ads + landing pages + CTR</item>
      <item>Conversion rate — landing page effectiveness; low = optimize landing page</item>
      <item>CPA — cost efficiency; high = reduce bids, add negatives, improve quality</item>
      <item>Impression Share — market capture fraction; low = increase budget or bids</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define CPA and ROAS targets before launching; optimize toward these metrics, not clicks or CTR.</statement>
      <rationale>Clicks and CTR are proxies, not outcomes. An account with high CTR and no conversions is failing. Defining success metrics upfront prevents optimizing for vanity numbers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Score">
    <p>Quality Score is a 1-10 per-keyword composite of three components:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Expected CTR — predicted click rate for this keyword</item>
      <item>Ad relevance — keyword-to-ad copy match</item>
      <item>Landing page experience — post-click user experience and relevance</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track Quality Score weekly per keyword; a QS drop predicts CPA spikes 1-2 weeks ahead and signals tighter ad group theming or landing page work is needed.</statement>
      <rationale>Quality Score affects both ad rank and CPC. A declining QS means you pay more for the same position. Catching it weekly allows corrective action before costs spike significantly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Segment Analysis">
    <list>
      <item>Device: mobile vs. desktop performance — adjust bids by device</item>
      <item>Time: day-of-week and hour patterns — dayparting adjustments</item>
      <item>Network: Search vs. Search Partners — often partners have worse CTR and CPA</item>
      <item>Location: geographic performance — exclude or increase bids by region</item>
      <item>Audience: audience layer performance — bid adjustments by audience</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Segment by device and network before making any campaign-level conclusion; mobile and Search Partners often skew the aggregate and hide different performance drivers.</statement>
      <rationale>A campaign with "bad" average CPA may have excellent desktop CPA and terrible mobile CPA. Aggregates mask the diagnosis. Device segmentation is the first split to run.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
