<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-optimization-cycle" title="Optimization Cycle: Search Terms, Actions, and Schedule">
  <summary>Weekly search terms triage process, optimization actions by symptom, budget reallocation logic, and reporting cadence (daily/weekly/monthly).</summary>

  <section title="Search Terms Triage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Review the Search Terms report weekly; filter by cost above $5 and classify each term as: relevant+converting (add as keyword), relevant+non-converting (monitor), irrelevant (add as negative).</statement>
      <rationale>A weekly search-terms triage is the highest-ROI optimization action in Google Ads. Irrelevant clicks waste budget on impossible conversions. Adding high-converting terms as keywords improves Quality Score.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping search terms review for more than 2 weeks.</description>
      <reason>Search term drift accumulates rapidly. After 2 weeks without triage, a budget-hungry irrelevant query can consume 10-20% of total spend before anyone notices.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="templates/weekly-report.py">GAQL helper that pulls search terms with cost above threshold and zero conversions for negative keyword candidates</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Optimization Actions by Symptom">
    <list>
      <item>Low impressions: increase budget, broaden match types, review bid floors</item>
      <item>Low CTR: rewrite headlines, tighten ad groups, test new value props</item>
      <item>Low Quality Score: tighten keyword-to-ad copy match, improve landing page relevance</item>
      <item>Low conversion rate: optimize landing page, verify conversion tracking fires</item>
      <item>High CPA: add negatives, reduce bids on poor segments, improve quality</item>
      <item>Low impression share: increase budget (if budget-lost), increase bids (if rank-lost)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Make major structural changes (bid strategy, campaign restructure, audience rebuild) no more than once a month; each major change resets Smart Bidding learning.</statement>
      <rationale>Smart Bidding requires 7-14 days after significant changes to restabilize. Frequent major changes keep campaigns in perpetual learning and prevent stable performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Budget Reallocation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reallocate budget from campaigns over CPA target with high impression share to campaigns under CPA target with low impression share.</statement>
      <rationale>A campaign performing well below target with low impression share is constrained by budget, not efficiency. Shifting budget there captures more high-value conversions at a lower cost than fixing an over-target campaign.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Campaign A: $100/day, CPA $20 (target $25), 80% impression share — already saturated; hold spend. Campaign C: $50/day, CPA $15 (target $25), 40% impression share — increase to $100/day. More conversions at lower CPA from additional budget.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Reporting Schedule">
    <list>
      <item>Daily (5 min): check spend pacing, look for anomalies, ensure no disapprovals</item>
      <item>Weekly (30 min): full performance review, search terms triage, add negatives, bid adjustments, Quality Score review</item>
      <item>Monthly (1 hour): trend analysis, competitive review via Auction Insights, budget reallocation, strategy assessment</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always compare period-over-period AND year-over-year; seasonal effects mask real performance changes when only looking at 7-day vs. prior-7-day.</statement>
      <rationale>A 20% CPA increase in December vs. November may simply reflect seasonal demand shifts. Year-over-year comparison reveals whether the change is a real efficiency problem or expected seasonality.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
