<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="helm-advanced Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for helm-advanced. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Library charts MUST have type: library in Chart.yaml and MUST NOT contain values.yaml or templates/*.yaml resources (no deployments, services, etc.; only _helpers.tpl). Library chart names MUST use common- or lib- prefix to signal non-deployable status. Dependent charts MUST declare the library in Chart.yaml dependencies section. Library templates MUST use named templates ({{ define "libname.helper" }}) to avoid accidental output. Library charts MUST NOT be installed directly (helm install will fail if type: library is set). Documentation MUST clearly explain which templates are exported and how to use them in dependent charts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">type: library prevents accidental direct installation (Helm rejects it) and signals to other developers that this chart is a dependency. Named templates prevent output; only explicit {{ include }} calls render content. Prefix (common-, lib-) signals intent in dependency lists. Library charts reduce duplication: 10 app charts each with identical naming/labeling logic = 1 library + 10 apps using it. Maintenance: one place to fix naming bugs or add new labels.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hook resources MUST be annotated with helm.sh/hook, helm.sh/hook-weight (integer for execution order), and helm.sh/hook-delete-policy (before-hook-creation or hook-succeeded). Database migration hooks MUST run pre-upgrade to ensure schema changes are applied before app restart (prevents 5xx errors from mismatched schema). Hooks MUST be idempotent: running the same hook twice must produce the same result (use init containers to check if migration already applied, rather than failing on duplicate). Test hooks (helm.sh/hook: test) MUST validate deployed release (connectivity, health, basic functionality) with exit code 0 = success, non-zero = failure. Hooks MUST inherit Release.Name and Release.Namespace from parent chart to avoid naming conflicts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hooks are useful for automation: migrations pre-upgrade, health checks post-install, cleanup pre-delete. Hook weight (negative to positive) orders execution: weight -5 before weight 0. Idempotency prevents failures on re-runs (Helm retries if hook fails). Test hooks provide continuous validation: after helm install, helm test validates the deployment works. Naming with Release.Name ensures hooks don't conflict when multiple releases coexist.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test pods MUST be stored in templates/tests/ directory with descriptive names (test-connection.yaml, test-smoke.yaml). Each test pod MUST have restartPolicy: Never and exit code 0 on success. Tests MUST validate core functionality (connectivity, health checks, basic operations) not implementation details. Test pod names MUST include {{ include "myapp.fullname" . }} to avoid conflicts. Tests MUST be run in CI/CD pipeline after every deployment (helm install → helm test → if fails, rollback). Documentation MUST list test coverage and what each test validates.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tests run after install/upgrade, confirming the deployment is healthy before marking it complete. Exit code 0 = test passes; non-zero = test fails. Test pods are temporary (helm.sh/hook-delete-policy: hook-succeeded cleans them up after completion). Tests in CI prevent broken deployments from reaching production. Core functionality tests are more valuable than implementation details (test "GET /health returns 200" not "ConfigMap mounted at /etc/config").</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Umbrella charts MUST declare all dependencies in Chart.yaml with exact versions and repositories. Each dependency MUST be gated by a condition (condition: postgresql.enabled) to support optional components. Values MUST be scoped by dependency name (postgresql.*, backend.*, frontend.*) to avoid collisions. Global values (imageRegistry, imagePullSecrets) MUST be defined in .global namespace and referenced by dependent charts. Umbrella charts MUST be used only for related components with shared deployment lifecycle; independent services MUST NOT be bundled. Documentation MUST list all dependencies, their versions, and configuration options.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Umbrella charts simplify deployments: helm install myapp umbrella-chart deploys app + database + cache in one shot. Conditions enable staging (PostgreSQL disabled; use managed Cloud SQL) vs development (PostgreSQL included). Global values prevent duplication: registry defined once, inherited by all subcharts. However, umbrella charts create tight coupling; don't use if services need independent release cycles or are managed by different teams.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Templates MUST include checksum/config annotations on Deployment/StatefulSet pod templates to force restarts when ConfigMap or Secret changes (prevents stale config). Required values MUST use {{ required "message" .Values.critical_value }} to provide clear error on missing configuration. Resources (PVC, databases, persistent data) MUST be annotated with helm.sh/resource-policy: keep to prevent deletion on release uninstall. All templates MUST pass helm lint in CI/CD before merge; linting MUST enforce naming conventions, required fields, and no deprecated APIs. Charts MUST use values.schema.json to define configuration structure, types, and validation rules for IDE support and early error detection.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Checksum annotations (sha256sum of ConfigMap/Secret) trigger pod recreation when config changes; without them, pods continue using old mounted config until manually restarted. Required values catch typos early ("mistmatch" in -f values.yaml file name = clear error, not silent no-op). Resource protection prevents accidental data loss: uninstalling app chart should NOT delete its database. Helm lint in CI prevents merging broken charts. values.schema.json enables VS Code/IDE validation before deployment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Templates MUST use named helpers ({{ include "..." }}) for DRY compliance; avoid repeating YAML snippets. Complex conditionals (3+ levels) MUST be refactored into separate partials or require clear documentation. Template functions (default, required, toYaml, nindent) MUST escape YAML correctly (toYaml | nindent for nested objects). Checksum annotations MUST be included on Deployment/StatefulSet pod templates to force restarts when ConfigMap/Secret changes (without manual pod deletion). Required values MUST be validated with {{ required "message" .Values.field }} for clear error messages. Comments in templates MUST explain non-obvious logic to aid future maintainers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Named helpers reduce duplication and enable reusability. Complex conditionals reduce readability; split into smaller partials. YAML escaping (toYaml | nindent) prevents malformed manifests. Checksums on pod templates force restarts automatically when config changes (without checksum, pods use cached mounted ConfigMap). required() fails fast with clear error, not silent failures. Comments document intent: why this conditional exists, what values it expects.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hooks MUST be idempotent: running the same hook twice produces same result (migrations check if already applied, cleanup removes stale resources). Hook jobs MUST have backoffLimit: 0 or 1 to fail fast on error (no retries). Hook deletion policy MUST be specified: hook-succeeded (cleanup after success), before-hook-creation (delete old hook before creating new one). Hooks MUST log output for debugging; use kubectl logs on hook pod to diagnose failures. Pre-upgrade hooks MUST run before pod restart (weight: -5) to apply schema migrations before app start. Post-install/test hooks MUST validate deployed release works (connectivity, health checks). Hooks MUST NOT rely on external systems (APIs, databases) being fully ready; add retry logic in hook script (not Helm retry).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Idempotency prevents cascade failures on retries: if migration hook runs twice, second run detects "already applied" and succeeds. backoffLimit: 0 prevents Kubernetes from retrying failed hooks automatically (retry once = two failures, confusing operator). Hook deletion policy prevents accumulating stale hook pods. Logging enables debugging. Pre-upgrade hooks run before app deployment, preventing 5xx errors from schema mismatch. Post-install tests confirm deployment succeeded. External dependency handling in script (poll loop with timeout) is safer than relying on Kubernetes readiness probes being ready before hook runs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Library charts MUST have type: library in Chart.yaml to prevent direct installation. Library charts MUST NOT contain values.yaml or deployable templates (no deployment.yaml, service.yaml). Library charts MUST contain only _helpers.tpl with named templates ({{ define "libname.something" }}). Dependent charts MUST declare library in dependencies section with file://../library-chart path (for co-located development) or HTTP repository URL (for published libraries). Library templates MUST use clear naming: libname.fullname, libname.labels, libname.selectorLabels to signal intent. Documentation MUST explain which templates are exported and how dependent charts use them via {{ include }}.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">type: library prevents accidental installation (Helm rejects it). Named templates-only prevents output; library doesn't deploy anything, just provides reusable template functions. Co-location (file://) enables rapid development; HTTP repo enables external teams to depend on published library. Clear naming signals library intent: libname.* is from library, not local templates. Documentation enables dependent charts to discover and use exported functions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pod specs MUST run as non-root user (securityContext.runAsNonRoot: true, runAsUser: 1000). Containers MUST have read-only root filesystem (readOnlyRootFilesystem: true) with writable tmpfs for temp files. Capabilities MUST be dropped except those explicitly needed (securityContext.capabilities.drop: ALL, add: [NET_BIND_SERVICE]). Secrets MUST NOT be stored in values.yaml; use external secret manager (Vault, Sealed Secrets, AWS Secrets Manager) with operator injecting secrets at deploy time. Network Policies MUST restrict pod-to-pod communication (allow only necessary ingress/egress). RBAC MUST grant minimum necessary permissions (avoid wildcard *). Pod Security Standards (PSS) SHOULD be enforced at namespace level (baseline, restricted). Documentation MUST explain security posture and compliance (PCI-DSS, HIPAA, SOC2) supported by chart.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Non-root user prevents container escape escalating to host root. Read-only filesystem prevents malware persistence. Dropped capabilities reduce attack surface. External secret managers prevent secrets in Git. Network Policies segment traffic. RBAC prevents lateral movement. PSS labels (restricted = stricter, baseline = permissive) enforce pod security org-wide. Documentation enables operators to assess compliance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All charts MUST pass helm lint with no warnings (strict mode). Chart templates MUST be validated with helm template to verify manifest output. Deployed manifests MUST be validated server-side (helm install --dry-run=server) against actual cluster API version. Helm tests MUST confirm deployed release is functional (connectivity, health, basic operations). Test results MUST be captured in CI logs for debugging. Integration tests SHOULD verify inter-chart communication in umbrella deployments (app can reach database, cache). All validation MUST run in CI/CD; only passing charts are mergeable. Documentation MUST list validation steps and failure troubleshooting.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">helm lint catches YAML errors, deprecated APIs, missing fields early. helm template verifies templating without contacting cluster (safe, fast). --dry-run=server validates against actual API version (catches API compatibility issues). Helm tests confirm app health post-deploy (pod may start but service unreachable). Integration tests in umbrella charts verify subcharts communicate correctly. CI gates prevent broken charts reaching production. Documentation enables operators to understand and reproduce validation locally.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Release history MUST be preserved (do not delete releases) for audit and rollback capability. Release status MUST be checked with helm status and kubectl describe pod before diagnosing failures. Hook failures MUST be inspected via kubectl logs on hook pod. Failed pods MUST be described to identify missing resources, permission errors, or image issues. Cluster events (kubectl get events -n NAMESPACE) provide often-missed context: ImagePullBackOff, InsufficientMemory, etc. Rollback MUST be tested in staging before applying to production. Performance issues MUST be measured (kubectl top pod, Prometheus metrics) not assumed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Release history enables instant rollback to known good state. helm status shows current release state and recent changes. kubectl describe reveals resource issues (missing ConfigMap, RBAC error, image not found). Logs show application errors. Cluster events capture system-level issues (memory pressure, storage errors) that pod logs don't show. Performance debugging without measurement is guesswork; measure, hypothesize, fix, measure again.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Umbrella charts MUST declare all dependencies in Chart.yaml with exact versions. Global values MUST be defined for shared config (imageRegistry, imagePullSecrets) accessible by subcharts via .global namespace. Subchart values MUST be scoped by dependency name (postgresql.*, redis.*) to prevent collisions. Each dependency MUST be optional via condition (condition: postgresql.enabled) to support different deployment topologies (dev: embedded PostgreSQL, prod: managed Cloud SQL). Umbrella chart MUST NOT contain templates/ directly (no deployments, services); dependencies provide all deployable resources. Documentation MUST list all dependencies, their versions, and configuration options with examples.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Exact versions ensure reproducible installs; flexible ranges introduce hidden breaking changes. Global values prevent duplication: registry defined once, inherited by all subcharts via .global. Scoped values prevent naming collisions: postgresql.replicas and redis.replicas coexist without conflict. Conditions enable topology flexibility: same chart works in dev (embedded DB) and prod (managed DB). Subcharts providing all templates prevents umbrella from managing both infrastructure and subcharts (separation of concerns). Documentation enables operators to understand and customize multi-service deployments.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
