<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="helm-advanced Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for helm-advanced as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating a library chart so generic it tries to support all possible Kubernetes manifests (Deployment, StatefulSet, Job, CronJob, etc.) with deeply nested conditionals.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A library that generates any resource type with any configuration is no longer a library; it's a meta-templating engine. Keep libraries focused: "shared naming conventions" or "pod security policies" or "common labels". If you find yourself writing 100+ lines of conditionals in _helpers.tpl, split into focused libraries or question whether Helm is the right tool.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using hooks for operations that should be handled by Kubernetes controllers or sidecar patterns.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hooks are good for one-time setup (migrations, smoke tests). For ongoing operations (metrics collection, log shipping, secret rotation), use init containers, sidecar containers, or Kubernetes operators. Hooks run at specific lifecycle points; controllers run continuously.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Tests that succeed without actually validating anything (e.g., echo "OK" as test command).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tests should validate actual deployment health. A test that always passes is worse than no test; it gives false confidence. Test at least: connectivity (service is reachable), health checks (app reports healthy), or basic functionality (GET /api/health, database query, etc.).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating an umbrella chart that requires complex inter-chart communication or ordering (e.g., backend must wait for database to initialize).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Helm is not an orchestrator. It deploys all charts in parallel. If ordering is required (app waits for database), use init containers (initContainer that waits for database to be ready) or readiness probes (app reports not ready if database unavailable), not Helm hooks. For truly complex orchestration, use Kubernetes operators.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping helm lint in CI or linting with --strict disabled because some warnings fail the build.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Helm lint catches real issues: deprecated API versions, missing required fields, misnamed resources. Warnings should be addressed (e.g., missing NOTES.txt, no app version in labels). Disabling --strict is a code smell; fix the warnings instead. Lint should be a required CI gate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Using template evaluation ({{ tpl .Values.template . }}) to dynamically load template strings from values.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Templating values makes debugging difficult: errors occur at runtime, not at chart development time. Values become code, breaking separation of data and logic. Avoid {{ tpl }};  keep values simple (strings, numbers, objects), not templates. If you need dynamic logic, implement it in Kubernetes controllers or use Kustomize for post-Helm transformation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating a single library chart so generic it supports all Kubernetes resources with deep conditional logic.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A library serving all use cases becomes unmaintainable. Keep libraries focused: "naming conventions", "common labels", "pod security policies". If you find yourself writing 100+ lines of conditionals, split into focused libraries or question if Helm templating is the right tool for such complexity. Kustomize or Kubernetes controllers may be better for advanced composition.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Running container as root (UID 0) to simplify permission issues.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Root container = container escape = host root access. Fix permission issues by running as dedicated user, not root. Use initContainer (runs as root once) to change file ownership, then run main app as non-root.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping --dry-run=server validation because "lint should catch everything".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>helm lint catches syntax and structure errors. It does NOT validate against actual Kubernetes API version or custom resources (CRDs). A chart valid in 1.20 may fail in 1.28 if API changed. Always run --dry-run=server against target cluster version.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Rollback without understanding why the upgrade failed, then rolling back again immediately.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Rollback is emergency recovery, not diagnosis. Always understand root cause before rolling back. If you roll back without fixing root cause, the same failure will occur on next upgrade. Diagnose (why did it fail?), fix root cause, then upgrade again.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
