<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-conversion-optimization Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-conversion-optimization. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Follow the research-before-testing rule: run heatmaps, session recordings, and 5+ user interviews before writing a single A/B test hypothesis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Random changes produce random results. Research anchors hypotheses to real user friction, which lifts win rate from ~30% to ~50% per test.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use the PIE framework to prioritize: score each opportunity on Potential (impact headroom), Importance (traffic volume), and Ease (implementation cost), then divide by 3. Test highest-scoring opportunities first.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">High-traffic pages with large drop-offs and low-effort fixes return value fastest; PIE prevents teams from polishing low-traffic pages.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Establish baseline metrics per funnel stage before starting any CRO work: landing page bounce rate target below 50%, signup form completion above 30%, pricing CTA click rate above 5%, checkout completion above 60%, visitor-to-customer 1-5%.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without baselines, test results have no reference frame and post-test "lift" claims are unverifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every test hypothesis must follow this template: "We believe that [change] will cause [effect] because [rationale]. We will measure this by [metric] and consider it successful if [target]."</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Pre-registration prevents post-hoc rationalization. Hypotheses without explicit success criteria inflate false-positive rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not declare a winner until: 100+ conversions per variant, 2+ weeks of runtime covering weekly cycles, and 95%+ statistical significance. Never peek at results before the minimum sample is reached.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stopping early at ~80% confidence inflates the false-positive rate from 5% to ~30%, polluting the learning library with phantom wins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a 30-day holdback cell (95% rollout + 5% control) after shipping winners to monitor novelty regression.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Winners often regress 30+ days post-launch; holdback cells catch regressions before they fully erode the gain.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep traffic assignment user-id-hashed, not session-based, and monitor for test pollution: bot traffic, consent-banner disruption, and cross-test contamination before calling results.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Session-based assignment allows the same user to see both variants; bot traffic and consent banners silently inflate or deflate exposure counts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document every test result — winner, loser, or inconclusive — with: name, date, hypothesis, change, metric result, lift percentage, what generalizes, what does not, and next test idea.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Teams that maintain a learning library double their annual win rate by avoiding repeated experiments and building on prior knowledge.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
