<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="CRO Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete CRO wins demonstrating the research-first approach, plus antipatterns that invalidate test results.</summary>

  <section title="Worked Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Signup form: 15% → 27% completion (+45% lift).</note>
      <p>Research: heatmaps showed hesitation at password field; session recordings showed confusion about requirements; exit surveys cited "too many fields". Hypothesis: reducing to email-only signup (set password later) will increase form completion because it removes the most-cited friction point. Result: 45% lift, no negative impact on activation.</p>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Pricing page: 2% → 3.3% trial conversion over two sequential tests.</note>
      <p>Research: users wanted easy plan comparison; FAQ questions revealed feature confusion; mobile layout was broken. Three tests: (1) comparison table — no impact; (2) FAQ section added — +15%; (3) mobile redesign — +20% on mobile segment. All three run to full significance; mobile segmented separately from desktop.</p>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Stopping tests early when results look good at 80% confidence.</description>
      <reason>At 80% confidence the false-positive rate is ~30%, not 5%. "We have a winner" declared on day 4 pollutes the learning library with phantom gains.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using heatmaps as the only research source before forming hypotheses.</description>
      <reason>Heatmaps reveal where users click but not why they leave. Pair with session recordings and exit surveys to triangulate intent; heatmap-only hypotheses have a lower win rate.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Copying "best practice" changes from industry case studies without local research.</description>
      <reason>Urgency timers and social-proof-above-fold tactics fail to replicate without local data confirming the same friction exists in your specific audience.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running a major redesign as an A/B test.</description>
      <reason>Multivariate changes cannot isolate which element caused any measured effect; use user research and prototype testing instead.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No learning library entry after a test concludes — win or loss.</description>
      <reason>Without documentation, teams re-run the same failed tests and lose accumulated institutional knowledge. The library is the primary long-term asset of a CRO program.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
