<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Recognition Over Recall Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every recognition-over-recall application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-recognition-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prefer recognition-based UI patterns over recall-based ones whenever design permits. Recall is only acceptable for power-user surfaces with confirmed user expectation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen — Heuristic #6">Recognition has lower cognitive cost and faster reaction time; defaulting to recall externalises load onto users.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-options-visible" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Make options visible: show common actions in toolbars / navigation. Do NOT hide them in right-click menus or kebab overflows.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — discoverability research">Hidden actions are undiscoverable for users who do not know to look for them.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-context-carry-over" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>In multi-step flows, show a persistent summary of all prior selections visible alongside the current step.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — multi-step form research">Cross-screen recall burden is invisible in static reviews; it shows up in usability testing as repeated back-button use.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-icon-with-label" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pair every icon with a text label. Tooltips alone are insufficient; use tooltips only in space-constrained areas where label cannot fit.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — icon usability">Icons-only require recall of meaning; even "universal" icons fail across populations.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-tooltip-bounds" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tooltips MUST be ≤7 words, shown on hover with a 300ms delay. Longer tooltips are documentation, not affordance.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — tooltip research">Longer tooltips become unreadable in flow; tooltips compete with help.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-autocomplete" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Add autocomplete to every search and command input; show at least 5 recent items immediately on focus.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — autocomplete research">Recents and suggestions convert recall to recognition, the highest-ROI UX change for search surfaces.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-recents-fresh" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Recent items MUST update immediately after use. A stale list is worse than no list because it teaches users not to trust it.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — recents reliability">Trust in the recents UI is fragile; one stale entry loses the affordance.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r8-icon-allowlist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The audit MUST consume an icon allowlist (universally recognised exceptions: magnifying-glass, X-close, etc.). Findings against allowlisted icons are dropped to severity-0 (informational) only.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — icon recognition research">Without an allowlist the audit drowns in noise for icons that are in fact recognised.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
