<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>
  <section name="backup-strategy">
    <summary>3-2-1 backup strategy for solo-developer VPS: what to back up, what to skip, retention policy, and RPO/RTO targets.</summary>

    <rule>
      <statement>Follow the 3-2-1 rule: 3 copies, on 2 different media, with 1 stored offsite.</statement>
      <rationale>Server disk failure and accidental deletion are the most common data loss scenarios; they are both solved by local backups. Datacenter-level events (fire, provider outage) require offsite. Any fewer than 3 copies creates a single point of failure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section name="what-to-backup">
      <list>
        <item>PostgreSQL database — critical, daily, pg_dump -Fc</item>
        <item>Redis RDB snapshot — important, daily, docker cp</item>
        <item>.env / secrets — critical, on change via restic</item>
        <item>nginx configs and SSL certificates — important, on change</item>
        <item>systemd unit files — important, on change</item>
        <item>WireGuard config — important, on change</item>
        <item>SSH sshd_config — important, on change</item>
        <item>Crontab — important (crontab -l)</item>
        <item>Application attachments / uploads — daily via restic</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="what-to-skip">
      <list>
        <item>Application code — already in Git, clone from GitHub on restore</item>
        <item>Python .venv directories — rebuilt from requirements.txt</item>
        <item>Docker images — pulled from registry</item>
        <item>RabbitMQ messages — transient by design</item>
        <item>node_modules, build artifacts — regenerated at deploy time</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="retention-policy">
      <list>
        <item>Local backups: keep last 14 days, delete older via find -mtime +14</item>
        <item>Offsite (restic): --keep-daily 7 --keep-weekly 4 --keep-monthly 6</item>
        <item>7 daily snapshots cover recovery from the most common scenario: "yesterday worked, today is broken"</item>
        <item>4 weekly + 6 monthly cover slow-burn issues discovered weeks later</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="rpo-rto">
      <list>
        <item>RPO (max data loss): up to 24 hours of database changes with daily backups</item>
        <item>RTO (recovery duration): 60-90 minutes with a documented runbook on a pre-provisioned server</item>
        <item>Reduce RPO to 1 hour by running pg_dump hourly and keeping only the last 24 hourly dumps locally</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <rule>
      <statement>Set up backups before any production data lands on the server, not after the first incident.</statement>
      <rationale>The cost of setting up backups is fixed and small. The cost of data loss is unbounded. Waiting until after the first incident guarantees at least one incident with no recovery path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <reference path="templates/backup.sh">Full daily backup script: PostgreSQL + Redis + configs + restic upload + retention</reference>
    <reference path="templates/verify-backup.sh">Verify latest backup: dump integrity, age check, required files present</reference>
  </section>
</text>
