<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-firefly-rules" title="Adobe Firefly Capabilities and Rules">
  <summary>Firefly feature map per Creative Cloud application, commercial framework, and key API constraints.</summary>

  <section title="Capabilities by Application">
    <list>
      <item>Photoshop — Generative Fill, Background Removal</item>
      <item>Illustrator — Text-to-Vector</item>
      <item>Premiere — AI editing assistance</item>
      <item>Express — Template generation</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Commercial Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Firefly when commercial IP safety is required; document the generation ID alongside each asset.</statement>
      <rationale>Firefly is trained on licensed content with clear usage terms. Generation IDs enable audit trails and regeneration if model versions change. Storing IDs prevents orphaned assets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include a human review checkpoint before promoting any Firefly asset to production.</statement>
      <rationale>Generated images frequently need manual refinement to match brand-specific visual language. Automated selection of generated images for production is not acceptable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-define a prompt template approved by the brand team; agents fill variables, never freeform prompts.</statement>
      <rationale>Brand-specific style prompts are not reproducible across model updates. Pre-approved templates constrain variation to acceptable range and prevent prompt injection into the commercial asset pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Storing presigned URLs from the API instead of downloading immediately.</description>
      <reason>Generated image presigned URLs expire in approximately 1 hour. Always download immediately and write to stable storage.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Trusting empty outputs array as a success.</description>
      <reason>Content moderation blocks can return HTTP 200 with an empty outputs array. Always validate that outputs length is greater than 0 before treating a call as successful.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Passing user-provided freeform text directly to Firefly.</description>
      <reason>Unsanitized user input can trigger moderation blocks or inject unintended prompt content into a commercial asset pipeline. Sanitize and route through the pre-approved template only.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
