<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="adobe-firefly-integration Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for adobe-firefly-integration as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Storing presigned URLs from the API instead of downloading immediately.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generated image presigned URLs expire in approximately 1 hour. Always download immediately and write to stable storage.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Trusting empty outputs array as a success.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Content moderation blocks can return HTTP 200 with an empty outputs array. Always validate that outputs length is greater than 0 before treating a call as successful.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Passing user-provided freeform text directly to Firefly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unsanitized user input can trigger moderation blocks or inject unintended prompt content into a commercial asset pipeline. Sanitize and route through the pre-approved template only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Synchronous loops without rate-limit backoff.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Firefly API rate limits (typically 10 req/s) require exponential backoff. Latency per generation is 2–8s; synchronous tight loops will exhaust limits and fail.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Not monitoring credit consumption.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Credit consumption is opaque for automated pipelines; large batches exhaust allotments quickly. Monitor per-project with a dashboard and alert before budget exhaustion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
