<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SDD Workflows Navigation Hub Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every workflows (navigation hub) application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-route-does-not-author" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>This methodology MUST emit a route record only — it MUST NOT author spec / design / plan content. Authoring is the responsibility of `workflow-spec-phase`, `workflow-design-phase`, and `writing-implementation-plans`. A route record that contains spec/design/plan body content is a violation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-responsibility SDD design">Mixing routing with authoring creates duplication and conflicts when the authoring methodologies evolve. The router stays small and stable; the authors carry the heavy logic.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-status-from-frontmatter" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Phase computation MUST read `status` fields from doc frontmatter (yaml). The router MUST NOT infer phase from filename or directory location alone — those are unreliable signals. Missing frontmatter is treated as `Draft`.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD audit-trail research">Filenames lie; renames happen; directory states lag. Frontmatter is the contract. Reading it directly is the only reliable signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-one-active-phase" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each feature has EXACTLY ONE active phase at a time. The active phase is the earliest phase whose required input doc is not yet Accepted. If spec Accepted + design Draft → active phase is Design. If spec Draft → active phase is Spec regardless of what else exists.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD lifecycle research">Concurrent-phase authoring is the leading cause of spec-design drift. The "earliest-non-Accepted-input" rule is the simple invariant that prevents it.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-blocker-naming" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the route cannot resolve (e.g., no feature directory, malformed docs, conflicting status), the route record MUST name the specific blocker. Vague messages ("cannot route", "error") are forbidden — they force the caller to re-investigate.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD orchestrator data">Specific blockers cut median time-to-unblock by 3-5x because the caller can act without re-discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-next-methodology-resolvable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The `next_methodology` field MUST be a real path under `skills/faion/knowledge/&lt;tier&gt;/&lt;group&gt;/&lt;slug&gt;/` that exists on disk. Placeholder strings or empty values are forbidden — the caller will dispatch this path directly.</statement>
      <rationale source="SDD dispatcher data">Stub paths produce immediate dispatch failure. A pre-validated path keeps the orchestration loop unbroken.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-00 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
