<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-support-hierarchy" title="Support Hierarchy: Self-Serve to Proactive">
  <summary>The four-level support hierarchy, SLA targets by plan tier, escalation path, and the self-serve-first rule.</summary>

  <section title="Self-Serve First Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build FAQ and knowledge base before adding any async support channel. 70-85% of support volume can be deflected by a well-built self-serve layer.</statement>
      <rationale>Every ticket that reaches a human could have been answered by documentation. Self-serve assets scale infinitely; human support does not. Building it first prevents backlog from the first day.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>If the same question is asked 5+ times, add it to the FAQ immediately. If the same bug is reported repeatedly, prioritize the fix over any other support activity.</statement>
      <rationale>Recurring tickets indicate a product or documentation gap. Answering the same question repeatedly without fixing the root cause is an inefficient use of support time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Solopreneur SaaS with 50 knowledge base articles: 70% self-service resolution, 30 tickets/week handled in 5 hours total, 4.7/5 CSAT. Self-serve investment paid back in under 2 months.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="SLA Tiers">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Respond to the first ticket from any paying customer within 4 hours regardless of SLA tier. First impressions determine churn risk at the critical early-adoption stage.</statement>
      <rationale>New paying customers form their support experience opinion within the first interaction. A fast first response builds confidence that the product is maintained.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Free users: 24-48 hours response time</item>
      <item>Paid (low tier): 4-24 hours</item>
      <item>Paid (high tier): 4 hours + live chat during business hours</item>
      <item>Enterprise: 1-4 hours + dedicated support contact</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Escalation Path">
    <list>
      <item>Level 1: Self-service (docs, FAQ)</item>
      <item>Level 2: Standard support (email or async chat)</item>
      <item>Level 3: Technical escalation (founder or senior engineer)</item>
      <item>Level 4: Emergency (product down, data loss — incident process, not support queue)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Legal, financial, fraud, and data deletion requests must route directly to human queue. Agents must never handle these automatically.</statement>
      <rationale>These topics have regulatory implications (GDPR, PCI-DSS, consumer protection law) that require human judgment and legal accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/support-policy.md">Support policy doc with channels, SLA by plan, and escalation contacts</reference>
  </section>
</text>
