<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-processes-and-patterns" title="Support Processes, Pattern Detection, and Product Feedback Loop">
  <summary>Ticket categorization, resolution tracking metrics, product feedback loop from support data, communication tips, and agent guardrails.</summary>

  <section title="Ticket Categorization">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Categorize every ticket as: bug-blocking (critical), bug-non-blocking (high), how-to (medium), feature-request (low), general-feedback (low). Track volume by category weekly.</statement>
      <rationale>Category distribution is a leading product signal. How-to tickets above 20% of volume for a specific feature indicate a UX problem, not a documentation gap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>If how-to tickets for a specific feature exceed 20% of volume, that feature needs UX work. More documentation for a confusing flow does not fix the confusion.</statement>
      <rationale>Documentation treats the symptom. Fixing the UX removes the root cause and permanently reduces support load for that flow.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/ticket-patterns.py">Count tickets by category from CSV export and output weekly volume summary</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Resolution Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>First response time target: under 4 hours (shows attentiveness)</item>
      <item>Resolution time target: under 24 hours</item>
      <item>First contact resolution target: above 70% (efficiency signal)</item>
      <item>CSAT target: above 4.5/5</item>
      <item>Tickets per customer over time: should be decreasing (product improvement signal)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Communication Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never let an agent send a response with a specific commit, deadline, or "we will fix this by [date]" — those require human sign-off on feasibility.</statement>
      <rationale>Commitment to a deadline without verifying engineering capacity creates a new customer expectation that, if missed, causes more churn than the original bug.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Bug report: "Thanks for reporting. I'll look into this." — not "That shouldn't happen"</item>
      <item>Feature request: "Great idea. I've added it to our list." — not "We won't build that"</item>
      <item>Angry customer: "I understand the frustration. Let me fix this." — not "Calm down"</item>
      <item>User error: "Easy to miss. Here's how it works..." — not "You did it wrong"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Guardrails">
    <rule>
      <statement>Agents must not mark tickets as resolved automatically. Only draft the response; resolution confirmation requires human action.</statement>
      <rationale>A ticket marked resolved without customer confirmation produces a false CSAT signal and may leave the customer's issue unresolved, increasing churn risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Inject tone guidelines explicitly: "friendly, empathetic, first-person" for consumer products. Agents default to neutral-formal, which underperforms for consumer support.</statement>
      <rationale>Tone mismatch in support responses reduces CSAT and increases escalations. Consumer customers expect warmth; enterprise customers expect professionalism. Both require explicit guidance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/weekly-review.md">Weekly support review template with volume, performance metrics, top issues, and action items</reference>
  </section>
</text>
