<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo SaaS Legal Docs Pack Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules for the minimum legal-doc pack a solo SaaS must publish before activating billing.</summary>

  <section title="Doc-pack rules">

    <rule id="r1-five-docs-minimum" testable="true">
      <statement>Five documents MUST be live at stable URLs before the first paid charge: (1) Terms of Service, (2) Privacy Policy, (3) Refund / Cancellation Policy, (4) Cookie Banner + Cookie Policy, (5) basic Data Processing Addendum available on request. Missing any one of the five blocks billing activation.</statement>
      <rationale>Stripe / Paddle risk reviews and GDPR complaints both check for this minimum set. Shipping with 4 of 5 in place is functionally the same as shipping with 0 — the missing one is the one auditors find.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-no-template-without-edit" testable="true">
      <statement>Every document is based on a named, dated source (e.g., "Iubenda generator 2026-04", "Stripe Atlas ToS 2025-12") AND edited to insert: legal entity name, jurisdiction, billing platform name, support email, refund-window in days. Forbidden: pasting a template with `[COMPANY NAME]` placeholders unedited.</statement>
      <rationale>Unedited placeholders signal "no one reviewed this" to risk teams and regulators. The edit pass forces the founder to confirm each clause applies to their actual product.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-billing-gate" testable="true">
      <statement>The billing platform's checkout flow MUST link to the live ToS + Privacy URLs from the checkout page, and the founder MUST verify these URLs return HTTP 200 from a fresh incognito session before flipping billing live. A CI / pre-launch checklist enforces the URL check.</statement>
      <rationale>404s on legal URLs are a common Stripe risk-review trigger and a self-inflicted GDPR exposure. A pre-flight URL check catches the regression after the third deploy renames the page slug.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-jurisdiction-named" testable="true">
      <statement>Each document names exactly one governing jurisdiction (state / country) and one dispute-resolution mechanism. "International", "where applicable", or unfilled placeholders are rejected. The jurisdiction matches the legal entity's place of incorporation, NOT the founder's residence if different.</statement>
      <rationale>Unspecified jurisdiction defaults to wherever the customer sues, eliminating the legal-entity protection. Named jurisdiction is what makes the entity wrapper meaningful.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-monitored-contact" testable="true">
      <statement>Each document lists a single contact email (`legal@` or `support@` on the product's own domain) that is monitored daily. Personal Gmail addresses are forbidden; aliases that bounce or auto-reply with "we got it" without human follow-up are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>GDPR data-subject requests, DMCA notices, and Stripe risk replies arrive at the legal contact. Unmonitored addresses convert response-time SLAs into automatic violations.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <code lang="txt"><![CDATA[
LEGAL-DOC PACK STATUS  (pre-launch gate)
- ToS                  https://app.example.com/legal/terms       [200 OK]  v2026-05-12
- Privacy Policy       https://app.example.com/legal/privacy     [200 OK]  v2026-05-12
- Refund Policy        https://app.example.com/legal/refunds     [200 OK]  v2026-05-12
- Cookie Policy        https://app.example.com/legal/cookies     [200 OK]  v2026-05-12
- DPA (on request)     legal@example.com (template 2026-05-12)             v2026-05-12
Entity:        Example Labs Ltd, registered Estonia (15998877)
Jurisdiction:  Estonia, ICC arbitration
Contact:       legal@example.com (monitored, daily)
Billing flip:  BLOCKED until all 5 rows = OK
]]></code>
    <note>Five docs, fresh-cache URL check, named entity + jurisdiction, monitored contact. Billing activation depends on this status block.</note>
  </example>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Founder copies a Notion ToS template, leaves "Last updated: [DATE]" and "[COMPANY NAME]" untouched, links it from the footer, and goes live.</description>
    <reason>Violates r2 (unedited placeholders) and r4 (no jurisdiction). Stripe risk-review will flag within 30 days; GDPR exposure unbounded.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
