<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-client-config" title="SSH Client Configuration">
  <summary>~/.ssh/config patterns for solo developers: global security defaults, per-host entries, ProxyJump for multi-hop access, connection multiplexing, and CI/CD restricted deploy keys.</summary>

  <section title="Global Client Defaults">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set these global defaults in ~/.ssh/config under Host *: HashKnownHosts yes, IdentitiesOnly yes, AddKeysToAgent yes, ServerAliveInterval 60, ControlMaster auto with ControlPath and ControlPersist 600.</statement>
      <rationale>IdentitiesOnly prevents SSH from trying all keys in the agent (causes "Too many authentication failures"). ControlMaster multiplexes connections, making subsequent SSH calls to the same host near-instant (important for agents that open many parallel sessions).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/ssh-client-config">Full ~/.ssh/config template with all host entries</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="ProxyJump vs Agent Forwarding">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use ProxyJump (-J or ProxyJump in config) instead of ForwardAgent for multi-hop SSH. Never enable ForwardAgent globally — only per trusted host if absolutely required.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent forwarding exposes local SSH keys on the intermediate host. If that host is compromised, all keys in the agent are accessible. ProxyJump tunnels the connection without any key material touching the intermediate host.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# ~/.ssh/config
Host prod
    HostName 10.0.1.10
    User nero
    Port 22
    ProxyJump jump.example.com
    IdentityFile ~/.ssh/id_ed25519

# Usage: ssh prod  (automatically tunnels through jump host)
# SCP:   scp file.txt prod:/tmp/
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="CI/CD Restricted Deploy Keys">
    <rule>
      <statement>Restrict CI/CD SSH keys in authorized_keys with command= to run only the deploy script, plus no-port-forwarding, no-X11-forwarding, no-agent-forwarding, no-pty.</statement>
      <rationale>A CI/CD key with full shell access is a major security risk. The command= restriction ensures the key can only trigger the deploy script, regardless of what the CI pipeline sends as the command.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# ~/.ssh/authorized_keys
command="/home/nero/workspace/deploy/deploy.sh all",no-port-forwarding,no-X11-forwarding,no-agent-forwarding,no-pty ssh-ed25519 AAAAC3... github-actions-deploy
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Permissions">
    <list>
      <item>chmod 700 ~/.ssh</item>
      <item>chmod 600 ~/.ssh/config</item>
      <item>chmod 600 ~/.ssh/id_ed25519</item>
      <item>chmod 644 ~/.ssh/id_ed25519.pub</item>
      <item>chmod 600 ~/.ssh/authorized_keys</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Create ~/.ssh/sockets/ directory for connection multiplexing before using ControlPath. SSH will fail to create the control socket if the directory does not exist.</statement>
      <rationale>ControlPath uses a directory that must exist beforehand. mkdir -p ~/.ssh/sockets is a one-time setup step.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
