<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="technical-debt-management Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for technical-debt-management. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Distinguish Prudent Deliberate debt (conscious shortcut with plan to fix) from Reckless debt (no design awareness). Only prudent debt is acceptable.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Reckless debt — "no time for design" or "what's a design?" — compounds without a paydown trigger. Prudent deliberate debt has a known cost and a plan.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test debt is not optional: untested code cannot be safely refactored. Prioritize test debt before structural refactoring.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Refactoring untested code produces regressions that are invisible until production. Tests are the safety net that makes all other paydown possible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score each debt item on four factors (1-5 each): Interest (how much it slows velocity), Contagion (does it spread?), Effort (cost to fix), Alignment (proximity to planned work). Priority = (Interest x Alignment) / Effort.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Interest × Alignment / Effort identifies debt that is hurting us now AND can be fixed cheaply because we're already touching that code. This is the lowest marginal-cost paydown strategy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Allocate 15-20% of sprint capacity continuously to debt paydown rather than saving it for "debt sprints".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Debt sprints allow debt to re-accumulate between them. Sustained 15-20% allocation keeps the interest rate stable and builds the habit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Make debt visible with money, not adjectives: "this costs 6 dev-days per quarter" beats "this is bad code".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Non-technical stakeholders cannot prioritize "bad code" against features. Quantified business impact creates the case for allocation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every new reckless debt item added to the register must link to an Architectural Decision Record explaining why it was accepted.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Debt without a decision record has no paydown trigger. ADR creates accountability and makes the cost explicit to whoever incurred it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply debt paydown changes via PR; never auto-merge debt-paydown commits.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Debt fixes change production behavior. Auto-merged paydown bypasses review and can introduce regressions or break consumers of refactored APIs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Paydown capacity allocation (the % of sprint dedicated to debt) is engineering-leadership territory. Agents propose; humans approve.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Changing the allocation ratio affects feature velocity visible to stakeholders. It requires trade-off authority that agents do not have.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
