<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-debt-process" title="Technical Debt Management Process and Agent Workflow">
  <summary>Six-step debt management process from visibility through prevention, agent pipeline, and human-in-loop checkpoints.</summary>

  <section title="Process Steps">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Make visible — tag items in tracker, keep a register, add code comments (TODO/FIXME with ticket links)</item>
      <item>Step 2: Quantify — measure time tax (dev-days slowed per quarter), risk (what could break), opportunity cost (what features are blocked)</item>
      <item>Step 3: Prioritize — score on Interest/Contagion/Effort/Alignment, rank</item>
      <item>Step 4: Allocate — 15-20% continuous + quarterly focused time for architectural work</item>
      <item>Step 5: Pay down strategically — fix during related feature work, fix highest-interest first, fix blocking debt first</item>
      <item>Step 6: Prevent new debt — Definition of Done includes "no new debt added", code review catches it</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Make debt visible with money, not adjectives: "this costs 6 dev-days per quarter" beats "this is bad code".</statement>
      <rationale>Non-technical stakeholders cannot prioritize "bad code" against features. Quantified business impact creates the case for allocation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every new reckless debt item added to the register must link to an Architectural Decision Record explaining why it was accepted.</statement>
      <rationale>Debt without a decision record has no paydown trigger. ADR creates accountability and makes the cost explicit to whoever incurred it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Pipeline">
    <list>
      <item>repo-surveyor (sonnet) — runs static analysis tools, assembles raw signals (churn, complexity, TODOs, stale deps)</item>
      <item>debt-classifier (sonnet) — reviews signals + PR comments, classifies into 6 types, scores 4 factors</item>
      <item>debt-prioritizer (opus, quarterly) — intersects scored register with roadmap, proposes paydown sequence</item>
      <item>boy-scout-reviewer (haiku, per-PR) — inline cleanup suggestions with 30-min scope cap</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply debt paydown changes via PR; never auto-merge debt-paydown commits.</statement>
      <rationale>Debt fixes change production behavior. Auto-merged paydown bypasses review and can introduce regressions or break consumers of refactored APIs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent proposing big-bang rewrites as the "fix approach" for debt items.</description>
      <reason>LLMs bias toward rewrites. Prompt constraint: minimal local change, avoid diffs over 20 lines without explicit justification.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent auto-upgrading dependencies with semver-major version bumps.</description>
      <reason>Breaking changes in major upgrades require consumer testing. Route to humans and require breaking-change detection before any major upgrade is applied.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="scripts/debt-survey.sh">Quarterly repo survey: git churn, radon, TODO/FIXME, outdated deps, coverage gaps.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/sprint-debt-budget.md">Sprint-level debt work log: budget, items, owners, outcomes.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-Loop Checkpoints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Paydown capacity allocation (the % of sprint dedicated to debt) is engineering-leadership territory. Agents propose; humans approve.</statement>
      <rationale>Changing the allocation ratio affects feature velocity visible to stakeholders. It requires trade-off authority that agents do not have.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
