<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design System Governance Core Rules">
  <summary>The non-negotiable rules that turn a design system into a governed product instead of a shared dependency graveyard.</summary>
  <section title="Operating model">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Three contribution paths are defined and published: core (system-team only), contrib (any product team via RFC + core review), and local-fork (product team owns indefinitely, never promoted to core). Every new component PR is labelled with one path; PRs without a path are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Undefined contribution paths produce two failure modes: every product team waits for the core team (bottleneck) or every team forks (drift). Explicit paths route work to whichever is cheapest for each change class.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Any change to a public component API (props, events, slots, tokens consumed) requires an RFC merged before the implementation PR. The RFC names: motivation, alternatives considered, breaking-or-additive classification, migration plan, deprecation window. Implementation PRs without a linked merged RFC fail CI.</statement>
      <rationale>API changes ripple through every consuming product. An RFC gate is the only mechanism that surfaces consumers' objections before the change ships and prevents the system team from optimising in isolation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Breaking changes use a fixed deprecation window of at least 2 minor versions before removal. The deprecated API emits a console warning, the docs carry a migration snippet, and a codemod (when feasible) is published alongside the deprecation announcement.</statement>
      <rationale>"Sunset next quarter" without a codemod creates a permanent migration debt — consumers schedule it after the deadline and either negotiate an extension or skip the upgrade entirely. Codemods + window + warning is the only combination that converges.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Breaking-change communication runs on three channels with a published cadence: a release-notes entry on every minor, a deprecation summary at the start of every quarter, and a direct DM/email to each consuming team's design+eng leads when the deprecation window opens. Skipping any channel resets the window.</statement>
      <rationale>Consuming teams discover breaking changes one at a time on different cadences. Multi-channel comms is how the system team converts "we announced it" into "the consumers actually knew".</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The governance doc itself is versioned and reviewed quarterly with a named owner. Changes to the governance model (e.g. shortening the deprecation window) follow the same RFC rules as a breaking-change component PR.</statement>
      <rationale>Governance that changes by Slack thread is no governance. Treating the governance doc as a public API stops the system team from rewriting the rules mid-migration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
RFC-0042: rename Button `kind` prop to `variant`
- classification: breaking
- alternatives: keep `kind` (rejected — diverges from tokens spec)
- migration: codemod rename-button-kind.cjs ships with v2.4.0
- deprecation window: v2.4 (warn) → v2.5 (warn louder) → v3.0 (remove)
- direct comms: design leads of web/ios/android notified 2026-05-12
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
v3.0 release notes: Button now uses `variant` instead of `kind`. Please update.
]]></code>
      <note>No RFC, no codemod, no window, no direct comms — half the product teams will fork the v2 Button and the system splits.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
