<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-structure" title="OST Node Taxonomy and Tree Rules">
  <summary>Defines the four OST node types, their constraints, evidence requirements, and the opportunity-vs-solution discipline that prevents the most common failure mode.</summary>

  <section title="Node taxonomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every tree has exactly one Outcome node at the root — a measurable product or business goal with an explicit metric.</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple outcomes in one tree create a hydra: teams cannot prune branches when priorities conflict.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Opportunity nodes must be phrased in customer language describing a problem or unmet need, not a feature or solution.</statement>
      <rationale>Solution-phrased opportunities ("add export button") collapse the discovery process; they skip validation of whether the need exists.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every Opportunity node must carry at least two evidence references (interview IDs, support ticket IDs, or analytics segment IDs) or be marked unvalidated and scheduled for pruning.</statement>
      <rationale>Evidence references are the only signal that distinguishes a real customer need from a brainstorm item.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Solution nodes are mutually exclusive within an opportunity: pick one to test, not all simultaneously.</statement>
      <rationale>Testing multiple solutions at once prevents attribution of results to a specific solution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Experiment nodes require a written kill criterion (hypothesis, method, success metric, sample size, status). Without a kill criterion, experiments never end.</statement>
      <rationale>Open-ended experiments consume resources indefinitely and produce ambiguous results.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep tree depth at most 4 levels: Outcome → Opportunity → Solution → Experiment.</statement>
      <rationale>Deeper trees indicate scope confusion; the extra levels are almost always sub-opportunities or sub-experiments that should be sibling nodes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Opportunity vs. solution discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>A node is an Opportunity if it describes a customer problem in customer language. A node is a Solution if it describes a product response. Run a node-classifier lint before adding any node.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams under delivery pressure reclassify solutions as opportunities to skip validation; a classifier subagent rejects or rewrites ambiguous nodes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Opportunity node: "Add bulk export button"</description>
      <reason>This is a solution, not a customer need. Rewrite as: "Users lose data when browser crashes before they can download."</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Opportunity node: "Users want speed"</description>
      <reason>Too vague to have evidence; cite specific interview IDs or rewrite with a concrete scenario.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Tree as structured data">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain the OST as YAML or JSON (not only as a Miro/FigJam diagram) so agents can edit the data and humans review the visual rendering.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents flatten parent-child semantics when editing a diagram directly; the YAML/JSON is the canonical source of truth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/ost.yaml">Agent-editable OST schema with outcome, opportunities, solutions, and experiments</reference>
  </section>
</text>
