<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-workflow" title="OST Build, Prune, and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>Cadence for building and maintaining an OST over time, agentic subagent patterns, and common failure modes when agents edit the tree.</summary>

  <section title="Build and refresh cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a tree review every two weeks: archive validated/dead branches with a date, flag opportunities with no supporting evidence after 30 days.</statement>
      <rationale>Trees grow into unreadable wallpaper without a pruning cadence; stale branches consume planning attention without delivering signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Connect each experiment to a delivery ticket and an instrumentation plan; without both, the experiment cannot be measured.</statement>
      <rationale>An experiment without instrumentation produces results that cannot be attributed to the intervention.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Agents maintain tree hygiene (classify nodes, surface stale branches, cluster duplicate opportunities, generate experiment briefs); discovery decisions stay human.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent-proposed opportunities without evidence IDs are fiction; the agent's role is curation, not ideation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Prompt for opportunity extraction from interviews:</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Given the OST YAML below and 12 new interview snippets, propose new opportunity
nodes (<=1 sentence each, customer language, no solutions). For each, list the
snippet IDs supporting it. Reject any duplicates of existing opportunities
(cosine similarity >=0.85).
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Prompt for solution and experiment generation:</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Given opportunity O.users-cant-find-export, generate three candidate solutions
ranging from low to high investment. For each, propose one experiment:
assumption, method, success criterion, sample size, duration.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent proposes opportunities without evidence IDs ("users want speed").</description>
      <reason>LLMs generate plausible-sounding needs from prior knowledge; require evidence IDs from a known source store before accepting any opportunity node.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent synthesizes experiment outcomes from prior knowledge before evidence is logged.</description>
      <reason>Require explicit "results: TBD" on all experiments until real data is recorded.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent bulk-imports interview snippets without deduplication, flooding the tree with near-identical opportunities.</description>
      <reason>Force a similarity check (cosine >= 0.85 threshold) before adding any evidence or opportunity node.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent overwrites hand-edits in Miro when syncing from YAML.</description>
      <reason>Require optimistic concurrency (etag/version field) on every Miro API write call.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
