<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Monthly Billing Batch Routine Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Monthly Billing Batch Routine methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="monthly-anchor-date" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Batch fires on a fixed monthly anchor (e.g. 1st business day) every active month; missed months MUST be acknowledged with reason, never silently skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Form-discipline practice (FASB ASC 605)">skipping a month silently corrupts the ledger and the founder loses cash-flow visibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="two-sided-batch" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each batch carries BOTH customer_invoices[] AND contractor_payouts[]; emitting one without the other is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion agency-ops audits 2026-Q1">decoupling the two sides hides margin compression; the routine exists to surface it monthly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-per-line" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every non-zero customer invoice line AND every contractor payout MUST cite a source (timesheet, deliverable, SoW clause); un-anchored lines are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice for billing automation">agent-driven batching invents plausible amounts; anchoring keeps it auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="margin-row-computed-not-input" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Margin row (invoices - payouts) MUST be computed by the script from the line items, not accepted as agent-supplied input; manual override requires founder sign-off and a comment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-fudge practice">agent-supplied margin smooths over real compression; force the math from line items.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="founder-approval-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Batch status approved_to_send MUST come from the founder (named reviewer), never the agent; auto-approval is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Self-approval anti-pattern (Faion safety policy)">self-approval defeats the human checkpoint and the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="reconciled-with-prior-month" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Batch MUST include a prior_month_delta block reconciling outstanding invoices and unpaid payouts from the prior month; gaps without delta are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reconciliation practice (FASB)">without prior-month delta the founder loses visibility into rolling A/R and A/P.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
