<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-frameworks" title="BA Methodologies Detail — 12 Enterprise Frameworks">
  <summary>Purpose and four-step process for each of the 12 BA frameworks: governance through solution limitation assessment.</summary>

  <section title="1. Governance Framework">
    <p>Purpose: establish decision-making processes for requirements. Defines who can approve, who can escalate, and how changes are controlled.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define decision rights, change control process, prioritization rules, and approval documentation before any requirements are baselined.</statement>
      <rationale>Without governance, scope changes are approved ad hoc and no one can explain why a requirement was added or removed; audit trails collapse.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/governance-framework.md">Decision authority matrix and change control process template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="2. Communication Planning">
    <p>Purpose: ensure effective communication of BA information to the right audiences in the right format and frequency.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify audience, information need, format, frequency, and channel for each stakeholder group before the project begins. Validate the plan at each phase.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a communication plan, critical information reaches the wrong people at the wrong time; sponsors get developer-level detail and developers get executive summaries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/communication-plan.md">Audience matrix and key messages template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="3. Elicitation Preparation">
    <p>Purpose: prepare effectively for elicitation activities by defining scope, selecting techniques, and preparing materials before sessions begin.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Define scope — what information is needed, what decisions will be made, what is out of scope.</item>
      <item>Select techniques — match technique to information type and stakeholder preferences.</item>
      <item>Prepare logistics — schedule sessions, book resources, prepare environment.</item>
      <item>Create materials — question guides, visual aids, prototypes or mockups.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="4. Requirements Maintenance">
    <p>Purpose: keep requirements accurate and useful over the full project lifecycle through version control, attribute management, and periodic quality monitoring.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Version control — baseline management, change history tracking.</item>
      <item>Attribute management — status (draft/approved/implemented), priority, owner, source.</item>
      <item>Quality monitoring — periodic reviews, consistency checks, completeness validation.</item>
      <item>Archival strategy — when to archive, what to retain, access policies.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="5. Change Impact Analysis">
    <p>Purpose: assess the scope, effort, risk, and stakeholder impact of a proposed requirement change before it is approved or rejected.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Complete all five impact dimensions — scope, effort, risk, stakeholder impact, and decision support — before recommending accept, reject, or defer.</statement>
      <rationale>Partial impact analysis leads to under-scoped change requests; effort or risk assessments without the other dimensions produce recommendations that surprise the team at implementation time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/change-impact.md">Change impact analysis template with scope, effort, risks, recommendation</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="6. Current State Analysis">
    <p>Purpose: understand the existing environment — business context, capabilities, technology landscape, stakeholders, and pain points — before defining the future state.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require a context-loading step (document analysis, transcript ingest) before running any current-state framework. An agent cannot produce a valid SWOT for a company it knows nothing about.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs generate plausible-but-wrong current-state descriptions when no ground truth is provided; hallucinated baselines produce strategies that address problems the organization does not have.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/current-state.md">Current state assessment: business context, capability assessment, SWOT</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="7. Future State Definition">
    <p>Purpose: define the desired future state through vision statement, SMART goals, required capabilities, success metrics, and constraints.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every success metric must have a baseline value and a target value. Metrics without baselines cannot prove improvement.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents fabricate plausible industry-standard KPIs when not required to cite sources; require a datasource path for every metric and reject metrics without baselines.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/future-state.md">Future state vision: goals, capability roadmap, constraints, assumptions</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="8. Risk Analysis">
    <p>Purpose: identify and assess risks to the change initiative using probability-impact scoring and define response strategies.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Attach an evidence column to every risk (incident history, expert judgment, similar project, none). Reject high-impact risks with evidence: none in reviews.</statement>
      <rationale>Probability and impact scores without evidence are guesses; agents consistently assign P/I scores based on plausibility rather than evidence, producing a risk register that looks complete but contains no actionable signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/risk-register.md">Risk register with probability, impact, score, response, owner</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="9. Change Strategy Planning">
    <p>Purpose: develop the optimal approach for achieving the future state through gap analysis, solution options, transition planning, readiness assessment, and business case.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Map every identified gap to a named solution option before scoring options. Options not mapped to gaps are feature proposals, not strategy.</statement>
      <rationale>Solution options analysis without explicit gap linkage produces a preference list rather than a strategy; the recommendation becomes subjective rather than traceable to the change rationale.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/change-strategy.md">Gap analysis, solution options, and transition roadmap template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="10. Requirements Architecture">
    <p>Purpose: organize requirements into a coherent structure through viewpoints (business/user/technical/operational), decomposition hierarchy, dependency mapping, and completeness check.</p>
    <reference path="templates/requirements-architecture.md">Viewpoints, requirement hierarchy, and dependency table template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="11. Solution Options Analysis">
    <p>Purpose: evaluate and recommend the best solution option using weighted criteria scoring across strategic fit, technical feasibility, cost, time to value, and risk.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Calibrate scoring weights with human stakeholders before the agent applies them. Return recommendation as PENDING_HUMAN_REVIEW until explicit go-ahead is given.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents score every option 3-4 to appear neutral, destroying discriminating power. The 25/20/20/20/15 default weights are illustrative; sponsors must declare their actual weights before the scores are meaningful.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/solution-options.md">Weighted scoring matrix and recommendation template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="12. Solution Limitation Assessment">
    <p>Purpose: identify and address current solution limitations through defect identification, root cause analysis, impact assessment, and remediation options evaluation.</p>
    <reference path="templates/solution-limitations.md">Limitation identification, root cause, impact, and remediation template</reference>
  </section>
</text>
