<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Funnel Basics Framework Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `Funnel Basics Framework` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="biggest-absolute-loss-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The next optimization step MUST be the transition losing the most absolute users, not the lowest-conversion-rate transition. Lowest-conversion-rate prioritisation is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Funnel-prioritisation audit 2024-2026">Easy-step optimisation captures small wins; biggest-absolute-loss prioritisation captures the order-of-magnitude wins.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="step-events-named-pre-launch" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each funnel step MUST have a documented analytics event name with stakeholder sign-off BEFORE any optimization decision. Mid-flight renames are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Funnel-instrumentation audit">Ambiguous step names cause tracking inconsistencies; pinning events upstream prevents diagnosis from data-rot.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="min-30-day-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Measurement MUST cover ≥ 30 days AND ≥ 100 users per step. Decisions on smaller windows are flagged as hypothesis-only.</statement>
      <rationale source="Statistical-validity audit">Short windows miss weekly patterns; small samples mislead diagnosis.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="if-then-because-hypothesis" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every change MUST be drafted as IF/THEN/BECAUSE: &apos;IF we change X, THEN metric Y improves by Z%, BECAUSE diagnosis-based reason&apos;. Hand-wave changes are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Hypothesis-quality audit">Un-grounded hypotheses fail at 70%; IF/THEN/BECAUSE forces grounding in diagnosis.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="ice-scored-prioritisation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hypotheses MUST be ICE-scored (Impact / Confidence / Ease) before testing. Highest-ICE goes first. Random / vibes-based prioritisation is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ICE-prioritisation audit">Without scoring, teams test what&apos;s easy; ICE-anchored prioritisation captures the high-leverage tests first.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>