<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Funnel Optimization 7-Phase Process">
  <summary>The 7-phase process for systematically improving conversion: map, measure, find drop, diagnose, hypothesize, test, repeat.</summary>

  <section title="Phase Sequence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always fix the step with the largest absolute user loss first, not the step with the lowest percentage conversion.</statement>
      <rationale>A step losing 6,500 users at 35% conversion outweighs a step losing 300 users at 9% conversion, even though the percentage looks worse on the smaller step.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Phase 1: Map the Funnel">
      <rule>
        <statement>Define every step from first touch to goal, name each step with an event name, and get stakeholder agreement before measuring.</statement>
        <rationale>Ambiguous step definitions cause tracking inconsistencies that make drop-off analysis unreliable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>SaaS signup funnel with concrete event names at each step: page_view_home, cta_clicked, signup_form_viewed, email_submitted, email_verified, profile_completed, first_action_completed.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 2: Measure Each Step">
      <rule>
        <statement>Collect minimum 30 days of data and segment by traffic source, device, and new vs. returning before drawing conclusions.</statement>
        <rationale>Short windows miss weekly patterns; unsegmented data hides that mobile users drop at different steps than desktop users.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 3: Find the Biggest Drop">
      <rule>
        <statement>Rank transitions by absolute users lost, not by drop percentage. Prioritize the transition with the highest user count lost.</statement>
        <rationale>A 65% drop at step 1→2 losing 6,500 users is higher priority than a 30% drop at step 6→7 losing 461 users.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 4: Diagnose the Cause">
      <p>Use multiple diagnostic methods: session recordings reveal user behavior; heatmaps show attention areas; exit surveys capture stated reasons; user interviews provide depth.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Landing to CTA: unclear value prop, poor design, slow load</item>
        <item>CTA to form: too many fields, scary commitment language</item>
        <item>Form to submit: technical errors, confusing UX</item>
        <item>Submit to verify: email in spam, long delay</item>
        <item>Onboarding to activation: too complex, no guidance, value not shown</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 5: Generate Hypotheses">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write every hypothesis in IF/THEN/BECAUSE format: "If we [change X], then [metric] will improve by [Y%], because [diagnosis-based reason]."</statement>
        <rationale>Vague hypotheses cannot be falsified; format enforces that each hypothesis is grounded in diagnosis, not guesswork.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 6: Test and Iterate">
      <rule>
        <statement>Prioritize hypotheses with ICE (Impact x Confidence x Ease). Test the highest ICE score first. Score 20-30 means test immediately.</statement>
        <rationale>Without scoring, teams test what is easiest to build, not what will move the metric most.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section title="Phase 7: Repeat">
      <rule>
        <statement>After implementing a winner, move to the next biggest drop-off transition. Track cumulative conversion improvement over time.</statement>
        <rationale>Funnel optimization is a continuous loop, not a one-time project.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Funnel Types">
    <list>
      <item>Marketing: Impression → Click → Landing Page → Signup → Activation → Purchase</item>
      <item>SaaS: Visit → Signup → Onboarding → Activation → Engagement → Conversion → Retention</item>
      <item>E-commerce: Visit → View Product → Add to Cart → Checkout Start → Payment → Confirmation</item>
      <item>Mobile App: App Store → Download → Open → Onboarding → Core Action → Retention → Monetization</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
