<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Client Firing and Graceful Offboarding Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `Client Firing and Graceful Offboarding` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="friction-log-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The decision MUST cite ≥ 3 documented friction events from the last 90 days (date, summary, evidence link). &apos;Vibes&apos; or single events forbidden as firing rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="Client-relationship postmortem corpus">Vibes-based firings cause founders to second-guess for months; the 3-event threshold both protects the client (no rash decisions) and the founder (clean rationale on file).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="notice-period-honoured" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Notice period MUST match the contract clause (or 30 days minimum if silent). Same-day terminations are forbidden except for safety / harassment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract dispute audit 2024-2026">Same-day terminations escalate to legal disputes; honouring notice keeps the exit clean.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="handoff-document-shipped" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Offboarding MUST ship a handoff document (creds, runbooks, asset inventory, ongoing-task status) signed by founder and client before the relationship ends.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal offboarding audit">Un-documented handoffs cause 30-60 days of follow-up emails after termination; the signed handoff doc kills the long-tail.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="referral-alternative-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Where applicable, the offboarding artefact MUST name at least one referral alternative the client can engage. &apos;You&apos;ll figure it out&apos; is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Graceful-exit case studies">Naming an alternative converts most clients from adversarial to grateful; their next call is to the alternative, not to small-claims.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="post-mortem-recorded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Within 14 days of offboarding completion, founder MUST record a post-mortem (what to avoid in intake, what to clarify in contract, ICP refinement). Postmortem-skipped means the next bad client comes through the same door.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal ICP refinement corpus">Skipped post-mortems mean repeated bad-fit intakes; the 14-day window forces founder to extract the lesson while fresh.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>