<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="pm-framework-focus-areas">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-agile</domain>
    <summary>PMBOK 8 Focus Areas organize project lifecycle work. Five stages: Initiating, Planning, Executing, Monitoring &amp; Controlling, Closing. Tailor coverage by project type, size, and compliance.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>pmbok</tag>
      <tag>focus-areas</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>lifecycle</tag>
      <tag>project-governance</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="seven-performance-domains"/>
      <ref slug="six-core-principles"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>PMBOK 8 Focus Areas</title>

    <summary>PMBOK 8 replaces Process Groups with five method-agnostic Focus Areas — Initiating, Planning, Executing, Monitoring &amp; Controlling, Closing — distributed across 40 non-prescriptive processes. Focus areas answer "when in the project lifecycle" (orthogonal to the seven performance domains which answer "what area of work"). Teams tailor which focus areas need full treatment vs. light coverage based on project type, size, and regulatory regime.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Process groups from PMBOK 6 implied a sequential, waterfall flow that felt alien to agile and iterative teams. Focus areas preserve the lifecycle anchors (start, middle, close) without prescribing execution order — allowing Scrum sprints to map into Executing while planning happens iteratively inside each sprint rather than once upfront.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Replacing PMBOK 6 process groups in PMO documentation; focus areas are method-agnostic.</item>
        <item>Mapping agile ceremonies to a process-group equivalent for stakeholders trained on PMBOK 6.</item>
        <item>Building a project audit rubric — each focus area becomes one section.</item>
        <item>Onboarding new PMs from PMP-aligned curricula since 2023.</item>
        <item>Tailoring conversations: "what's required at each focus area for this project size?"</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure agile teams that already operate with Scrum/Kanban events — overlaying focus areas adds bureaucracy.</item>
        <item>Highly regulated environments still mandating PMBOK 6 process groups verbatim.</item>
        <item>Day-to-day execution detail — focus areas are framework-level, not task-level.</item>
        <item>Single-person solo work — overhead exceeds value.</item>
        <item>Replacement for actual deliverables; focus areas are organizing concepts, not artifacts you ship.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="focus-area-definitions">
      <p>PMBOK 8 replaces Process Groups with five method-agnostic Focus Areas that organize the 40 non-prescriptive processes across any delivery lifecycle.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Map agile ceremonies to focus areas for stakeholders trained on PMBOK 6 — Sprint Planning → Planning, Sprint → Executing, Daily/Demo → Monitoring &amp; Controlling, Retro → Closing-of-iteration.</statement>
        <rationale>Provides a common vocabulary between agile teams and PMO leadership without forcing waterfall sequencing onto iterative work.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="initiating">
        <p>Establish vision, purpose, and organizational alignment. Not just a kickoff meeting — includes business case, project charter, and sponsor sign-off.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Predictive: project charter, stakeholder register, business case</item>
          <item>Agile: vision statement, product goals, initial backlog seeding</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="planning">
        <p>Define the approach, build estimates, and identify risks. In agile, Planning recurs inside every sprint rather than once upfront.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Predictive: WBS, requirements baseline, schedule, budget, risk register</item>
          <item>Agile: backlog, user stories with acceptance criteria, sprint plan, release roadmap</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="executing">
        <p>Perform work to achieve objectives. The largest consumer of project effort; in agile this maps directly to sprint execution.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Predictive: work packages, procurement, resource coordination</item>
          <item>Agile: sprint development, integration, deployment automation</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="monitoring-and-controlling">
        <p>Track performance, manage changes, and enable informed decisions. In agile, daily standups and demo reviews serve this function continuously.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Predictive: EVM, baseline comparison, change control log</item>
          <item>Agile: velocity tracking, burn-up charts, defect rate, demo feedback</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="closing">
        <p>Formal completion, lessons learned, and acceptance. The most frequently skipped focus area in continuous-flow product work.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Predictive: final reports, acceptance signatures, lessons-learned document</item>
          <item>Agile: sprint retrospective, release retrospective, knowledge transfer</item>
        </list>
        <rule>
          <statement>Block project archive until at least one Closing artifact (lessons-learned, formal acceptance, or retrospective summary) exists.</statement>
          <rationale>Without enforcement, Closing never happens in agile or product-mode work; lessons-learned vanish and the same mistakes repeat in the next project.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="common-failure-modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using focus areas as a glorified table of contents without the seven Performance Domains as the orthogonal axis.</description>
        <reason>Focus areas answer "when" (lifecycle position); without domains answering "what area," the framework produces empty section headers with no substance.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Placing the same artifact in multiple focus areas because boundaries are fuzzy.</description>
        <reason>Single-home tagging is required for analytics; double-counting inflates effort reporting and obscures where the team actually spends time.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating "40 non-prescriptive processes" as freedom to define 40 custom process names.</description>
        <reason>Without org-level standardization, each PM invents their own subset and inter-team audits become impossible.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="tailoring-by-project-type">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pair focus areas with the seven Performance Domains on an orthogonal axis: focus areas answer "when in the lifecycle," domains answer "what area of work."</statement>
        <rationale>Used alone, focus areas produce empty section headers; used alone, domains produce concurrent work without a temporal anchor. Together they produce a complete project structure.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="small-project">
        <p>Small Project (S)</p>
        <list>
          <item>Initiating: charter.md (1 page)</item>
          <item>Planning: spec.md + risk-register.md (light)</item>
          <item>Executing: status-reports/ folder</item>
          <item>Monitoring &amp; Controlling: metrics.md (minimal)</item>
          <item>Closing: lessons-learned.md (required even for small projects)</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="medium-project">
        <p>Medium Project (M)</p>
        <list>
          <item>Full artifact set per focus area; 3-5 documents each</item>
          <item>Explicit change log under Monitoring &amp; Controlling</item>
          <item>Formal acceptance document under Closing</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="regulated-project">
        <p>Regulated Project</p>
        <list>
          <item>All focus areas require documented artifacts regardless of team preferences</item>
          <item>Initiating must include business case, sponsor sign-off, and regulatory scope statement</item>
          <item>Closing requires auditable acceptance signature and archived project record</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="agile-team-mapping">
      <p>For agile teams who resist PMO framing, map ceremonies to focus areas to provide a common vocabulary with leadership:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Sprint Planning → Planning focus area</item>
        <item>Sprint Execution → Executing focus area</item>
        <item>Daily Standup + Sprint Demo → Monitoring &amp; Controlling focus area</item>
        <item>Sprint Retrospective → Closing focus area (iteration-level)</item>
        <item>Product Discovery → Initiating focus area (ongoing)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not double-document: if a sprint review serves Monitoring &amp; Controlling, do not require a separate M&amp;C report for the same period.</statement>
        <rationale>Double-documentation is the most common reason agile teams reject PMO frameworks; removing it increases adoption without reducing auditability.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="subagent-patterns">
      <section name="focus-area-scaffolder">
        <p>Generates a per-focus-area folder tree from project metadata (type, size, regulated flag).</p>
        <example type="good">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are focus-area-scaffolder. Inputs: project type (string), size (S/M/L), regulated (bool).
Output a Markdown directory tree under docs/ with one folder per focus area
(initiating, planning, executing, monitoring-controlling, closing). For each folder,
list 3-5 required documents tailored to the inputs. Mark optional with "(optional)".
]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section name="coverage-checker">
        <p>Scans a corpus, reports completeness per focus area, flags silently empty areas.</p>
        <example type="good">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are focus-area-coverage-checker. Scan <corpus>. For each focus area, report:
- Status: COVERED | PARTIAL | MISSING
- Evidence: list of documents found (or "none")
- Gap: what is missing for PARTIAL/MISSING
Do not infer coverage from document titles alone; verify content exists.
]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A scaffolding agent generates a tailored project document tree (folders or wiki sections) from project metadata: type, size, regulatory regime → which focus areas need full treatment, which can be light. A coverage agent runs across an existing project corpus and reports which focus areas have artifacts and which are silently empty. A close-out agent fires when a project is marked done and forces a Closing-focus-area artifact (lessons learned, retrospective summary, formal acceptance) to be produced before archive.</p>

      <section name="recommended-subagents">
        <list>
          <item>focus-area-scaffolder — outputs a per-focus-area folder/section template based on project metadata.</item>
          <item>focus-area-coverage-checker — scans a corpus, reports completeness per focus area, flags gaps.</item>
          <item>closing-enforcer — blocks project archive until Closing artifacts exist; publishes lessons-learned to a shared repo.</item>
          <item>phase-tagger — auto-labels new docs / commits / tickets with their focus area for later analytics.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="prompt-pattern">
        <p>You are focus-area-scaffolder. Inputs: project type (string), size (S/M/L), regulated (bool). Output a Markdown directory tree under docs/ with one folder per focus area (initiating, planning, executing, monitoring-controlling, closing). For each folder, list 3-5 required documents tailored to the inputs. Mark optional with "(optional)".</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>mkdocs — Render the focus-area folder tree as a project site (https://www.mkdocs.org)</item>
        <item>tree — Show generated scaffold for review (apt install tree)</item>
        <item>pandoc — Convert focus-area docs to PDF for governance audits (https://pandoc.org)</item>
        <item>ripgrep — Fast search for focus-area tags in commits / docs (https://github.com/BurntSushi/ripgrep)</item>
        <item>yq — Maintain a focus-areas.yaml manifest per project (https://github.com/mikefarah/yq)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <list>
        <item>Confluence (SaaS) — Yes, REST API. One space per project, one parent page per focus area.</item>
        <item>Notion (SaaS) — Yes, REST API. Database-of-databases per focus area.</item>
        <item>SharePoint + OneNote (SaaS) — Yes, Graph API. Common in PMOs already on Microsoft.</item>
        <item>Wiki.js / BookStack (OSS) — Yes, REST API. Self-hosted alternatives for compliance/sovereignty.</item>
        <item>Project Online (MS) (SaaS) — Yes, REST API. Heavy PPM with focus-area / phase awareness.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Tag every commit and ticket with its focus area; later analytics show where the team actually spends effort vs. where they should.</item>
        <item>Pair focus areas with the 7 Performance Domains on the orthogonal axis — focus areas tell you "when", domains tell you "what".</item>
        <item>Keep focus-area boundaries intentionally fuzzy at the team level; codify them only at portfolio/audit level.</item>
        <item>Audit Closing every quarter for active long-running products; without forcing it, lessons-learned never happen.</item>
        <item>For agile teams, map: Sprint Planning → Planning, Sprint → Executing, Daily/Demo → Monitoring &amp; Controlling, Retro → Closing-of-iteration.</item>
        <item>Don't double-document: if a sprint review covers Monitoring &amp; Controlling, a separate "M&amp;C report" is waste.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>The README is sparse; agents will pad with PMBOK 6 process-group content and confuse focus areas with process groups. Pin terminology in the system prompt: "5 focus areas, NOT 5 process groups."</item>
        <item>"Non-prescriptive processes" prompt agents to invent 40 process names; constrain output to org-defined subset.</item>
        <item>Closing is the most forgotten focus area in agent outputs; force a check that Closing has at least one artifact before approval.</item>
        <item>Boundary-fuzziness causes agents to put the same artifact in multiple focus areas; require single-home tagging.</item>
        <item>Agents producing a scaffold tend to over-create files; cap at 3-5 docs per focus area as default.</item>
        <item>"Initiating" is over-equated to "kickoff meeting" — remind agents it includes business case, charter, sponsor sign-off.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/scaffold_focus_areas.sh" purpose="Shell script: creates a docs/ tree with one folder and default artifacts per focus area."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards"/>
      <ref slug="seven-performance-domains"/>
      <ref slug="six-core-principles"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
