<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-models" title="Four PLG Models with Canonical Examples">
  <summary>Freemium, free trial, open core, and usage-based — best-fit conditions, conversion triggers, and real-world examples for each model.</summary>

  <section title="Model 1: Freemium">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use freemium when the product has low marginal cost per user, network effects, and a mass market TAM where virality can compound. Define upgrade triggers before launching: usage limits, feature gates, user limits, or collaboration needs.</statement>
      <rationale>Without predefined upgrade triggers, freemium free tiers often become permanently free: users have no natural moment to convert because they never hit a wall tied to demonstrated value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Slack freemium: 10K message history, 10 integrations, 1:1 video. Aha moment: first channel message with teammates in under 5 minutes. 30%+ teams convert to paid; 143% net revenue retention.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Notion freemium: unlimited personal pages, limited team blocks. Aha moment: first useful page created and shared. Viral loop: templates shared publicly, each view is product exposure.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Model 2: Free Trial">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use free trial when the product is complex, has clear ROI, or has high switching costs that require time to evaluate. Target trial-to-paid conversion of 15%+ (baseline) or 25%+ (strong). Optimize via free-trial-optimization methodology.</statement>
      <rationale>Free trials work when users need time to experience value but will not experience it on a permanently limited free tier. Complex B2B products with high implementation cost are canonical free-trial cases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Zoom freemium + usage-based: unlimited 1:1 calls, 40-minute group limit. Aha moment: first successful video call in under 2 minutes. Growth 10M → 300M daily participants; low CAC through word-of-mouth.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Model 3: Open Core">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use open core for developer tools and infrastructure products with a strong self-host community. Choose the license carefully — BSL (Business Source License) and SSPL have materially different community and enterprise adoption effects. Never recommend open core without a license-strategy callout.</statement>
      <rationale>License-shift risk (MongoDB SSPL, HashiCorp BSL) creates community backlash that can permanently reduce enterprise adoption pipeline. License choice is irreversible at scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Model 4: Usage-Based">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use usage-based pricing only when a single quantitative value metric exists that aligns with customer perceived value (compute hours, API calls, transactions, queries). Refuse usage-based recommendation if no clean value metric is identifiable.</statement>
      <rationale>Usage-based pricing without a clear value metric creates unpredictable billing that confuses customers. The metric must feel fair and proportional to value received.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Calendly freemium: 1 event type free → multiple event types + team scheduling on paid. Viral loop: every meeting booked exposes recipients to the product ("Powered by Calendly"). TTV: 3 minutes to first booking.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
