<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-fit-and-flywheel" title="PLG Fit Matrix, Flywheel, and Hybrid Motion">
  <summary>6-factor fit matrix for choosing PLG vs sales-led vs hybrid, the PLG flywheel as a mental model (not a metric pipeline), and the hybrid PLG+sales ACV cutoff.</summary>

  <section title="Fit Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before recommending a PLG model, score the product against all 6 factors: complexity (simple/intuitive = 1), decision-maker (end user = 1), price (under $50K/year = 1), TTV (minutes to hours = 1), trial feasibility (easy to try = 1), market size (large TAM = 1). Score 5-6 = pure PLG; 3-4 = hybrid PLG + sales; below 3 = sales-led with PLG signals only.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping the matrix leads LLMs to default-recommend freemium for almost any SaaS product regardless of fit. The matrix forces explicit checks against the documented failure modes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For hybrid PLG + sales, use ACV $1K/month as the cutoff: below = self-serve closes the loop; above = sales-assist motion with PQL handoff to an SDR. Make this threshold explicit in every hybrid recommendation.</statement>
      <rationale>The PLG-vs-Sales-Led comparison table in README flattens product-led-sales (PLS) reality. Most modern PLG at $1K-$50K ACV needs a sales-assist motion that pure PLG analysis misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/plg-fit-scorer.py">Dataclass scoring product against 6-factor fit matrix</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="The PLG Flywheel">
    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>Treat the PLG flywheel (acquisition → activation → engagement → monetization → expansion → referral) as a mental model for explaining the growth loop, not as a measurement framework. Route to plg-metrics for actual instrumentation and KPI definitions.</statement>
      <rationale>The flywheel diagram is directionally correct but is not a pipeline with measurable handoffs. Presenting it as a metric framework produces unmeasurable "stage health" reporting that does not drive decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM recommends freemium for every SaaS product without running the fit matrix.</description>
      <reason>Freemium fails for complex products, high-ACV products, and products where decision-makers are not end users. The fit matrix walk-through is mandatory before model recommendation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Extrapolating "Slack did X, therefore we should do X" without checking for network effects, viral coefficient, and market distribution differences.</description>
      <reason>Canonical examples (Slack, Zoom, Notion) are survivor-biased mega-cases with distribution dynamics most products cannot replicate. Treat them as anchor points only; replace with peer comps in actual recommendations.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Recommending open core without naming the license and its downstream adoption risk.</description>
      <reason>License-shift risk (BSL, SSPL) is irreversible at scale and permanently affects enterprise pipeline. Cannot be omitted from an open-core recommendation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
