<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Doc Writing Process Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Design Doc Writing Process. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-four-passes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Writing flow has four passes (skeleton, draft, review, sign-off); skipping a pass is a process violation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — design-doc audit">One-shot writeups skip review or rush sign-off; explicit passes prevent that.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-gate-per-pass" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each pass has a gate (skeleton review, draft review, comment resolution, sign-off); next pass cannot start until gate is cleared.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stage-gate workflow theory">Gates prevent half-finished drafts from leaking downstream.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-reviewer-assigned-before-draft" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reviewer is assigned at skeleton-review time, not after draft is done.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — late-reviewer audit">Late reviewer assignment compresses review time and reduces feedback quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-review-sla-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Review SLA is captured in the artefact (hours from draft-ready to first comment).</statement>
      <rationale source="Async-review practice">Without SLA, drafts stall; explicit SLA forces accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-comment-resolution-tracked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every reviewer comment is resolved (accepted, rejected with reason, deferred with reason); unresolved comments block sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="Code-review-style practice">Unresolved comments leak into impl; explicit resolution prevents that.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-sign-off-recorded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sign-off records author + reviewer handle + date; verbal sign-off is not recorded.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-trail practice">Verbal sign-off cannot be reconstructed during incident post-mortem.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md &quot;Applies If&quot; do not all hold, OR any &quot;Skip If&quot; disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-design-doc-writing-process.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
