<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<methodology slug="backlog-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>Maintain prioritized backlog using DEEP (Detailed, Emergent, Estimated, Prioritized) with four buckets: Ready, Upcoming, Backlog, Icebox. Type tags, user stories, Given/When/Then AC required.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>backlog</tag>
      <tag>product-management</tag>
      <tag>grooming</tag>
      <tag>prioritization</tag>
      <tag>deep-invest</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Backlog Management</title>

    <summary>Maintain a prioritized, healthy list of work connected to product goals using the DEEP principle (Detailed at top, Emergent at bottom, Estimated, Prioritized) and four buckets: Ready, Upcoming, Backlog, Icebox. Every item must have a type tag (feature/bug/tech_debt/research), a user story in As-a/I-want/So-that format, and Given/When/Then acceptance criteria before it can enter the Ready bucket. Run weekly grooming; archive items with 180+ days of inactivity.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Backlogs become dumping grounds when treated as storage rather than strategic tools. Without type tags and explicit promotion criteria, every item looks equal and planning degrades into opinion contests. The 180-day archive rule and the 2-sprint cap on Ready items keep the signal-to-noise ratio high and prevent refinement work from being wasted on low-probability items.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Backlog has crossed ~80 items and signal is degrading; weekly grooming has lapsed.</item>
        <item>Multiple input streams (support, sales, eng, ideas) need triaging into a single ranked list.</item>
        <item>Refining the top of backlog into Ready items before sprint planning.</item>
        <item>Auditing backlog health (DEEP/INVEST compliance) before a quarterly review.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF prototype phase with fewer than 20 items — a simple Trello/Notion list is sufficient.</item>
        <item>One-off project with fixed scope and end date — use a WBS or kanban board instead.</item>
        <item>When the team will not run weekly grooming; an unmaintained managed backlog is a longer dumping ground.</item>
        <item>Replacing prioritization frameworks — backlog management organizes items; RICE/MoSCoW prioritizes them. Run prioritization first.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="deep-principle">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply DEEP to every backlog: Detailed (top-of-backlog items have AC and estimates), Emergent (bottom items stay rough), Estimated (all Ready items are sized), Prioritized (every item has an explicit rank).</statement>
        <rationale>Treating bottom-of-backlog items with the same detail as top items wastes refinement time. DEEP matches detail investment to delivery probability.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="invest-principle">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every Ready item must satisfy INVEST: Independent (no hidden dependencies), Negotiable, Valuable (explicit user benefit), Estimable, Small (fits in one sprint), Testable (has Given/When/Then AC).</statement>
        <rationale>Items that fail INVEST become sprint killers — they block other work (not Independent), cannot be completed in one cycle (not Small), or fail review (not Testable).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ready item has no acceptance criteria, or AC is a restatement of the title.</description>
        <reason>Untestable AC makes sprint planning slow and definition-of-done review impossible.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="four-bucket-model">
      <rule>
        <statement>Maintain exactly four buckets: Ready (next 1-2 sprints, fully refined), Upcoming (1-3 sprints, defined with some detail), Backlog (future, rough ideas), Icebox (parked, low probability). Enforce explicit promotion criteria between buckets.</statement>
        <rationale>Without defined buckets and promotion criteria, all items look equal and planning degrades to whoever speaks loudest.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap Ready at 2 sprints of team capacity (~8-25 items). Below 8 means insufficient pipeline; above 25 means refinement is being wasted on items that may never ship.</statement>
        <rationale>Ready items beyond 2-sprint capacity will be re-refined when they finally reach sprint planning, making the earlier work waste.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="item-quality">
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag every item with exactly one type: feature, bug, tech_debt, or research. Mixed-type backlogs cannot be reasoned about or correctly prioritized.</statement>
        <rationale>Type tags are required for capacity allocation decisions (ratio of feature to tech debt), health metrics, and agent-based triage.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Source-link every item to its origin (ticket URL, customer quote, dashboard chart). Items without a source are archive candidates at the next grooming.</statement>
        <rationale>Sourceless items cannot be validated or traced back when stakeholders ask "why did we build this?"</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Item: "Add autocomplete to product search — As a customer I want to see suggestions as I type so I find products faster. Given I type 2 characters, when I pause, then I see top 5 suggestions. Estimate: M. Source: support-ticket-4521."</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Item: "Better search — Search doesn't work well." No story, no AC, no source, no estimate.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="capture">
      <rule>
        <statement>Capture from all sources (feature requests, bug reports, tech debt, research outcomes, stakeholder input, team ideas) quickly and without evaluation. Evaluate at grooming, not at intake.</statement>
        <rationale>Evaluation at intake creates a bottleneck and discourages submission. Capture quickly; triage in batch at the weekly grooming session.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="groom-weekly">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a weekly grooming session (1-2 hours): review new items, refine top items, re-prioritize based on latest learning, archive stale items. Grooming skipped once starts a degradation loop.</statement>
        <rationale>A backlog that is not groomed weekly accumulates noise faster than signal. One missed session doubles the next session's load.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prioritize">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply a documented prioritization method (RICE, MoSCoW, or stack ranking) and re-run it when: new information arrives, goals change, or sprint planning begins. Never leave priority implicit.</statement>
        <rationale>Implicit priority means the backlog reverts to insertion order or loudest-voice order at sprint planning.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="refine">
      <rule>
        <statement>For top-of-backlog items: break into stories no larger than one sprint, add Given/When/Then acceptance criteria, estimate, and resolve all blockers. An item is Ready only when it meets all four criteria.</statement>
        <rationale>Items missing any of the four criteria will cause sprint planning delays or mid-sprint scope discovery.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Acceptance criteria pasted verbatim from feature requests or support tickets.</description>
        <reason>Customer-sourced AC is typically ambiguous prose, not testable Given/When/Then statements. Unreviewed AC causes failed sprint review.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="cleanup">
      <rule>
        <statement>Archive items with 180+ days of inactivity (unless priority is P1). Merge items with title similarity above 0.85 after human review. Delete confirmed duplicates. Target: stale ratio below 10%.</statement>
        <rationale>Stale items degrade signal-to-noise and make backlog size metrics meaningless. The 180-day rule provides an objective threshold that avoids "nobody dares delete" paralysis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat auto-archive as a proposed status, not direct deletion. Archive proposal requires human approval before any item with linked PRs or customer commitments is removed.</statement>
        <rationale>Auto-archive of items with external commitments creates support and trust issues. Human approval on the archive list is the safety gate.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Pitfalls and limitations when agents participate in backlog management:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Models generate AC like "User should be able to use the feature successfully." Require ≥2 G/W/T statements with concrete subjects.</item>
        <item>Stories collapse to "As a user…" because no persona is given; inject persona context per refinement.</item>
        <item>Sizing from an LLM is inconsistent across runs; treat it as relative within one batch only, never as absolute estimates.</item>
        <item>Auto-merge by title similarity false-positives on plurals/synonyms; always require human approval before merging issues with linked PRs.</item>
        <item>Auto-archive is the most dangerous op; archive should be a separate "proposed" status, not direct deletion.</item>
        <item>Multi-tenant backlogs (multiple products) confuse agents; partition by product before refinement.</item>
        <item>Token cost: refining 50 items ≈ 30–40k tokens output; chunk in 10s.</item>
        <item>Drift between backlog tracker and refined doc — always write back to the source of truth, never keep a parallel JSON.</item>
        <item>INVEST principle is often violated with "Independent" — agents will introduce hidden dependencies. Add a `dependencies` field and validate in the linter.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Practices that keep backlogs healthy and agent-manageable:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Tag every item with type (feature/bug/tech_debt/research). Mixed-type backlogs cannot be reasoned about.</item>
        <item>Maintain four buckets — Ready, Upcoming, Backlog, Icebox — and enforce promotion criteria; otherwise the bucket model is decoration.</item>
        <item>Archive aggressively (180-day rule). The cost of re-creating a forgotten idea is lower than the cost of confusion from stale items.</item>
        <item>Acceptance criteria as Given/When/Then. Anything else fails sprint planning.</item>
        <item>Cap top-of-backlog to ~2 sprints of capacity. Beyond that, refinement is wasted work.</item>
        <item>Run a monthly health check with metrics. Trend matters more than absolute numbers.</item>
        <item>Pair with prioritisation method; a backlog without a documented prioritisation method drifts to whoever speaks loudest.</item>
        <item>Source-link every item to its origin (ticket URL, customer quote, dashboard chart). No source ⇒ archive candidate.</item>
      <item>Maintain velocity trend charts to detect degradation over time. Teams should expect 5-10% variance sprint-to-sprint; systematic decline indicates backlog or process issues.</item><item>Separate backlog management from backlog refinement roles when team grows. One person should own triage and cleanup; another owns Ready bucket quality and acceptance criteria authoring.</item></list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/health-check.md" purpose="Backlog health check: snapshot, counts by status and type, health metrics table, actions." />
      <template path="templates/grooming-agenda.md" purpose="Weekly grooming session agenda with triage table, refinement section, and cleanup log." />
      <template path="templates/backlog-item.md" purpose="Full backlog item template with story, Given/When/Then criteria, estimate, and priority." />
      <template path="templates/validate-backlog.py" purpose="Python linter: checks ready items for AC, size, and INVEST shape; flags stale ratio." />
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.romanpichler.com/blog/make-your-product-backlog-deep/" />
      <link href="https://www.atlassian.com/agile/scrum/backlogs" />
      <link href="https://scrumguides.org/scrum-guide.html" />
      <link href="https://linear.app/blog" />
    <link href="https://www.atlassian.com/team-playbook" /><ref slug="prioritization-frameworks" /></see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>