<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-planning" title="Product Launch Planning">
  <summary>Launch types, an 8-week countdown timeline, four required components, and a launch day sequence for coordinating a product introduction.</summary>

  <section title="Launch Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose launch type based on risk and audience size: soft launch (limited audience, low risk) → beta launch (early adopters, medium risk) → full launch (public, high risk). Do not skip stages for high-risk products.</statement>
      <rationale>Full public launches are hard to walk back. A soft or beta launch lets you fix critical issues before they affect reputation at scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="8-Week Countdown">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start planning 6–8 weeks before launch day. T-8: define strategy. T-6: create assets. T-4: build pre-launch audience. T-2: finalize coordination. T-1: final checks. T-Day: execute. T+1: monitor and respond. T+2: retrospective.</statement>
      <rationale>Launches planned in the final week lack pre-launch audience, have untested assets, and produce no momentum. The 8-week timeline is the minimum for a coordinated launch with measurable impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Four Required Components">
    <rule>
      <statement>Positioning and messaging must be locked before asset creation. Key message, value proposition, target audience, and differentiation all need to be agreed before writing copy.</statement>
      <rationale>Assets built before messaging alignment diverge and require rework. Messaging is the foundation; assets are the expression.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Minimum viable launch assets: landing page, demo or screenshots, announcement email, social posts, basic documentation. All must be ready at T-2.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing assets on launch day create a gap between awareness (the announcement) and conversion (the landing page). Even one missing asset breaks the funnel.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Build a pre-launch audience before launch day: waitlist, email subscribers, social following, community relationships. The audience determines the floor for Day 1 metrics.</statement>
      <rationale>A launch to zero audience produces zero traction regardless of product quality. Pre-launch audience building is the highest-leverage activity in the 8-week window.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Coordinate internally before going public: support team briefed, on-call engineer named, monitoring dashboards ready, social media accounts active and monitored.</statement>
      <rationale>Launch day without internal coordination produces delayed responses to issues and confusion about who owns what. Each role needs to know its responsibilities before T-Day.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Launch Day Timing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Launch on Tuesday or Wednesday, not Friday. For Product Hunt, launch at 12:01 AM Pacific Time to maximize voting window.</statement>
      <rationale>Friday launches run into the weekend news cycle. Product Hunt voting resets at midnight PT; launching at 12:01 AM gives the maximum 24-hour window for votes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/launch-plan.md">Full launch plan template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/launch-day-checklist.md">Launch day hour-by-hour checklist</reference>
</text>
