<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-launch Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-launch as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Planning starts the week before launch day.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>One week is not enough to build a pre-launch audience, create and review assets, coordinate partners, or set up monitoring. Minimum: 6 weeks for a meaningful launch, 8 weeks for a high-impact one.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Launching on a Friday.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Friday launches lose the Monday-Tuesday news cycle. Most journalists and influencers are not covering tech news Friday afternoon. Tuesday-Wednesday gives the full week's coverage window.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Same message posted verbatim to every channel.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Twitter audiences, email subscribers, and LinkedIn followers have different contexts and norms. Copy-pasting produces content that feels wrong in each channel and reduces engagement in all of them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>No pre-launch audience — the product is announced to a cold start.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without an email list, waitlist, or community following, Day 1 signups depend entirely on algorithm and press pickup — both unreliable. Building even 500 subscribers before launch transforms the baseline metric.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>No monitoring on launch day — the team is focused on announcements, not product health.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Launch day is peak load and peak visibility for bugs. Server errors and broken flows during the announcement window permanently affect conversion. Assign a dedicated on-call engineer before posting anything.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>No post-launch retrospective.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Launch learnings are the highest-value data point for the next launch. What channel outperformed, which asset under-converted, what the team would change — all disappear if not captured within 2 weeks.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
