<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="onboarding-30-day">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>hr-recruiter</domain>
    <summary>Structured first-30-day onboarding framework: orientation, foundation, deep-dive with first deliverable. Every plan must define one meaningful milestone: contribution, not training completion.</summary>
    <category>onboarding</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>onboarding</tag>
      <tag>new-hire</tag>
      <tag>30-day-plan</tag>
      <tag>milestones</tag>
      <tag>retention</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>30-Day Onboarding Phase</title>
    <summary>Structured first-30-day onboarding framework covering orientation (Week 1), foundation building (Week 2), and deep-dive with first deliverable (Weeks 3-4). The testable rule: every 30-day plan must define exactly one meaningful milestone (first PR, first sales call, first resolved ticket) — "completed all training" is not a valid milestone because it measures activity, not contribution.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>20% of voluntary turnover happens within the first 45 days. BambooHR research links structured onboarding to 82% higher retention and 70% faster productivity ramp. The single-milestone rule forces managers and new hires to agree on what "good" looks like at Day 30, preventing the "set and forget" pattern where the plan becomes a shelf document with no measurable outcome.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Generating role-specific 30-day plans (engineer, sales, support) from a universal template plus team runbook.</item>
        <item>Producing pre-boarding and Day 1 packets: welcome email, equipment checklist, week 1 calendar invites, required doc links.</item>
        <item>Tracking onboarding completion across new hires via HRIS/LMS APIs and surfacing "behind plan" cases to managers.</item>
        <item>Drafting personalized check-in agendas (Day 7, 14, 30) based on hire progress.</item>
        <item>Synthesizing 30-day survey responses across cohorts to identify systemic issues.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Companies under 20 employees where each onboarding is bespoke — structured templates become overhead rather than support.</item>
        <item>Senior executives (VP/CXO) — their onboarding is high-touch stakeholder-mapping work that template structures cannot capture.</item>
        <item>Contract or contingent workers with engagements shorter than 30 days.</item>
        <item>Active reorg or RIF — build the plan after stabilization, not during.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="phase-objectives">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The 30-day phase has one primary objective: build foundation of knowledge and relationships. Do not assign production ownership in the first 30 days; shadow first, contribute second.</statement>
        <rationale>20% of voluntary turnover happens within the first 45 days. Effective structured onboarding (82% retention improvement per BambooHR) requires deliberate sequencing, not front-loading responsibilities.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Days 1-7 (Orientation): HR paperwork, IT setup, meet direct team, manager 1:1 on role expectations, review company docs.</item>
        <item>Days 8-14 (Foundation): required training modules, shadow key workflows, meet cross-functional stakeholders, primary tools.</item>
        <item>Days 15-30 (Deep Dive): understand current projects, review past work, identify gaps, begin small tasks with guidance.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="single-milestone-rule">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every 30-day plan must define exactly one meaningful milestone: the first PR shipped, the first sales call completed, the first support ticket resolved. "Completed all training" is not a valid milestone.</statement>
        <rationale>Activity-based milestones measure compliance, not contribution. A contribution milestone creates a shared definition of success and prevents "set and forget" plans that no one revisits.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Software Engineer — 30-Day Milestone">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[Ship first PR to production (typo fix, documentation, or small bug fix
guided by team lead). PR must pass CI and receive at least one approved review.]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Bad milestone">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[Complete all required LMS training modules by Day 30.]]></code>
        <note>This measures activity (course clicks), not contribution. A new hire can complete all training and still be lost on Day 31.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="check-in-schedule">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run three structured check-ins during the 30-day phase: Day 7 (first week experience), Day 14 (buddy/navigation), Day 30 (milestone assessment). Each check-in has a written agenda prepared in advance.</statement>
        <rationale>Check-ins without written agendas default to "how's it going?" — which produces no actionable information and misses blocked items that are invisible to managers.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Day 7: manager 1:1 — first week experience, blockers, questions.</item>
        <item>Day 14: buddy check — navigation questions, culture, team dynamics.</item>
        <item>Day 30: manager review — milestone assessment, 60-day goals, satisfaction rating.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="role-specific-examples">
      <p>Concrete 30-day plans for software engineer and sales representative roles with role-specific milestones. Software engineer: Dev environment setup, codebase walkthrough, shadow code reviews, understand deployment process, attend team ceremonies. Ship first PR to production with at least one approved review and passing CI as the Day 30 milestone. Sales representative: CRM setup and access, product deep dive training, shadow 5+ discovery calls, learn sales methodology, study competitor comparison sheets, complete product certification assessment with score >=80% as the milestone.</p>
      <example type="good" title="Software engineer 30-day plan">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[# Software Engineer — Days 1-30

Week 1:
- [ ] Dev environment setup (laptop, Docker, local DB, SSH keys)
- [ ] Codebase walkthrough with team lead (3h session, recorded)
- [ ] Meet product manager: roadmap overview (30 min)
- [ ] Complete architecture overview docs
- [ ] Review coding standards, PR template, and CI pipeline

Week 2:
- [ ] Fix first small bug (guided by team lead, tracked in Jira)
- [ ] Shadow 3+ code review sessions
- [ ] Understand deployment process end-to-end
- [ ] Meet design partner: understand UX workflow

Weeks 3-4:
- [ ] Submit first PR to production (any green-field area)
- [ ] Attend all team ceremonies (standup, planning, retro)
- [ ] Identify one area where docs or tooling could be improved

30-Day Milestone: Ship first PR to production with >=1 approved review and passing CI.]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Sales representative 30-day plan">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[# Sales Representative — Days 1-30

Week 1:
- [ ] CRM setup and access (Salesforce, Outreach, LinkedIn Sales Nav)
- [ ] Product deep dive training (8h course + live demo with AE)
- [ ] Shadow 5+ discovery calls with senior reps

Week 2:
- [ ] Learn sales methodology (MEDDIC/SPICED as applicable)
- [ ] Understand ICP and buyer personas (product marketing deck)
- [ ] Study top 3 competitor comparison sheets
- [ ] Shadow 5+ additional calls (mix of discovery + demo)

Weeks 3-4:
- [ ] Review top 10 recorded call library
- [ ] Complete product certification assessment
- [ ] Meet marketing, CS, and SE stakeholders (internal discovery)

30-Day Milestone: Pass product certification with score >=80%. Secondary: complete 20 shadowed calls.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-integration-rules">
      <p>Agentic workflow for 30-day onboarding: A new-hire trigger (ATS "Hired" event or HRIS "Started" status) fires the onboarding agent. It pulls the role's universal 30-day template plus team-specific addendum, customizes per hire (manager name, buddy, pre-assigned project), creates Notion/Confluence onboarding doc, schedules calendar invites for week 1, and posts a Slack DM thread with Day 1 checklist. A scheduled agent runs daily to check progress (LMS completion, 1:1 attendance) and flags lag to the manager. Day 7/14/30 check-in agents send a short survey, summarize results, and prep talking points for the manager 1:1.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Never auto-schedule calendar invites without reading freebusy data first. Always check for conflicts before generating an .ics file or sending invites.</statement>
        <rationale>Auto-scheduled invites without freebusy checks produce double-bookings on Day 1, creating a bad first impression that is difficult to recover from.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Day 1 agenda: working laptop, accounts configured, lunch with team. No heavy training modules on Day 1.</statement>
        <rationale>First impressions are sticky. A new hire who spends Day 1 watching compliance videos and waiting for IT access remembers that experience. Functional setup + human connection on Day 1 drives 30-day satisfaction scores.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Onboarding plans may contain manager-only information (project codenames, customer names, team rosters). Enforce visibility boundaries — do not include restricted information in new-hire-visible onboarding documents.</statement>
        <rationale>New hires do not have the same information access as managers on Day 1. Including restricted details in their onboarding doc creates an unauthorized disclosure.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>HRIS data sent to LLM prompts for onboarding plan generation must comply with GDPR and local data protection rules. Do not send personal data across jurisdictions without verified legal basis.</statement>
        <rationale>Personal data (name, role, manager, project assignment) crossing borders into LLM API calls may require data processing agreements not yet in place for new-hire data.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Best practices for new-hire 30-day plans: Pre-boarding (offer-accepted to start date) is when 20% of new hires churn; build a 2-week pre-start touchpoint cadence. Day 1 priorities focus on working equipment, access, and team connection over training depth. Document onboarding in the same place new hires will work daily (Notion/Confluence), not in HR-only tools. Buddy must not be the manager; pick a peer who started 6-12 months ago and remembers the pain points. Set ONE meaningful Day 30 milestone (first PR, first sales call, first ticket resolved); avoid "completed all training" theater. Survey at Day 14 and Day 30 with no more than 5 questions; longer surveys get less than 40% response rates. Capture systemic issues across cohorts; one new hire's complaint is anecdote, three is a pattern requiring process change.</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Including "review company values" or "explore documentation" without linking to a specific page or resource.</description>
        <reason>Generic tasks are busywork that new hires complete by opening a random wiki page. Every task must point to a named resource; agents should fail loudly if the resource link is missing from the input context.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Applying US-style "celebrate Day 1" high-energy onboarding tone to DE/JP/UA new hires without localization.</description>
        <reason>Onboarding formality norms differ significantly across cultures. An overly casual, celebrations-heavy tone lands awkwardly in markets where professional distance is expected in the first weeks.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs cargo-culting generic onboarding tasks without ingesting team-specific runbooks, producing generic output.</description>
        <reason>Without actual workflow tools, team structure, and runbook context, agents auto-generate placeholder tasks that don't reflect the real onboarding experience. Require team-specific runbook input before generating a 30-day plan.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Calendar invites for week 1 generated without timezone awareness and conflict checking, producing overlapping events.</description>
        <reason>Agents auto-scheduling without read access to calendars create double-bookings and look unprofessional. Always validate freebusy before generating .ics invites.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/30-day-plan.md" purpose="Universal 30-day plan template with week-by-week structure and success criteria."/>
      <template path="templates/bootstrap-newhire.sh" purpose="Agent entry point: generate plan from inputs and create GitHub issue for manager."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.bamboohr.com/resources/guides/onboarding"/>
      <link href="https://resources.workable.com/tutorial/30-60-90-day-plan"/>
      <link href="https://www.shrm.org/topics-tools/tools/toolkits/onboarding-new-employees"/>
      <ref slug="onboarding-60-90-day"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
