<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="continuous-discovery">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>Teresa Torres framework embedding discovery into weekly rhythm: daily signals, weekly interviews and assumption testing, bi-weekly OST synthesis, monthly review via cron-driven multi-agent pipeline.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>continuous-discovery</tag>
      <tag>product-discovery</tag>
      <tag>teresa-torres</tag>
      <tag>opportunity-solution-tree</tag>
      <tag>agents</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Continuous Discovery (Teresa Torres)</title>

    <summary>Teresa Torres' framework for embedding product discovery into the weekly delivery rhythm: daily signal collection (analytics, tickets), weekly customer interviews (2-3), weekly competitor monitoring, weekly assumption testing, bi-weekly OST synthesis, monthly research review. Implemented as a cron-driven multi-agent pipeline that writes to .aidocs/product_docs/discovery/.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Discovery treated as a one-time project-start activity produces stale insights within weeks. Markets with 6-month half-life on user-need validity (AI tools, fintech, dev tooling) require an always-on opportunity backlog. The agent cadence keeps cheap models (Haiku) on daily mechanical tasks and Opus only on bi-weekly+ pattern recognition, preventing token-cost blowout.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Live products with active users where signal volume exceeds what a human PM can review unaided.</item>
        <item>Product Trio (PM + designer + engineer) workflows needing a weekly cadence of customer touchpoints.</item>
        <item>Markets with 6-month half-life on user-need validity.</item>
        <item>Solopreneur stacks where one operator must simulate trio coverage via subagents.</item>
        <item>After a launch when growth slows and the "solution that worked 6 months ago no longer works" pattern must be detected.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF zero-to-one with no users yet—start with customer-development or jobs-to-be-done.</item>
        <item>Compliance-bound enterprise sales where contract cycles are 6-18 months.</item>
        <item>Hardware/regulated medical where each iteration ships in months.</item>
        <item>Crisis mode (active outage, churn cliff)—switch to root-cause work first.</item>
        <item>When stakeholders demand "validated" answers from a single interview—Torres explicitly rejects validation theater.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="discovery-cadence">
      <p>Six-level cadence from daily mechanics to monthly strategic review, with specific output files at each stage.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Implement all six cadence levels (daily signal collection, weekly interviews, weekly competitor monitoring, weekly assumption testing, bi-weekly OST synthesis, monthly research review) or the practice degrades to a research graveyard.</statement>
        <rationale>Assumption testing is the first step teams skip because it feels slower than shipping. Without an explicit weekly slot backed by a scheduled agent, it disappears within a month.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Daily: analytics review, support ticket triage → insight-log.md, ticket-themes.md</item>
        <item>Weekly: 2-3 user interviews → interview-notes/YYYY-MM-DD.md</item>
        <item>Weekly: competitor monitoring → competitor-changes.md</item>
        <item>Weekly: assumption testing → assumption-results.md</item>
        <item>Bi-weekly: synthesis session → opportunity-solution-tree.md updated</item>
        <item>Monthly: research review → research-report.md, archived-opportunities.md</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="subagent-pipeline">
      <p>Eight-subagent pipeline with model selection, cadence, and input/output specifications.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use cheap models (Haiku) for daily mechanical collection, Sonnet for weekly structured synthesis, Opus only for bi-weekly+ pattern recognition—never invert this.</statement>
        <rationale>Opus on daily ticket triage burns tokens for no marginal value. The cadence model matches cost to the depth of reasoning required at each stage.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>analytics-watcher (Haiku, daily): PostHog/Amplitude exports, GA4 anomalies → insight-log.md daily entry</item>
        <item>support-triage (Haiku, daily): Intercom/Zendesk/Linear tickets last 24h → theme cluster + count + severity</item>
        <item>competitor-monitor (Haiku, weekly): RSS, changelog scrapes, ProductHunt, G2 reviews → competitor-changes.md diff</item>
        <item>interview-scheduler (Sonnet, weekly): user segment criteria, recruit pool → recruit list + outreach drafts</item>
        <item>interview-synthesizer (Sonnet, per call): Otter/Fireflies/Looppanel transcript → tagged notes, JTBD pulls, quotes</item>
        <item>assumption-tester (Sonnet, weekly): open assumptions list, OST leaves → test design + result rubric</item>
        <item>discovery-synthesizer (Opus, bi-weekly): all weekly outputs → updated OST, opportunity scores</item>
        <item>research-reviewer (Opus, monthly): all synthesis outputs → strategic memo, kill list, doubled-down list</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="scheduling">
      <p>Scheduling continuous discovery agents via cron, systemd, or managed triggers to maintain consistent cadence.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Wire cadence agents via cron/systemd timers on NERO; use the loop skill or schedule skill for managed triggers—do not run on demand only.</statement>
        <rationale>Continuous discovery requires consistency. On-demand execution produces sporadic data that cannot reveal trends over time. Scheduled agents create the rhythm that makes the practice work.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>All agents write to .aidocs/product_docs/discovery/. The bi-weekly synthesizer reads the full week's outputs and updates the OST in place.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="canonical-prompt-pattern">
      <p>Canonical XML prompt structure hardcoded with Torres framework constraints to prevent agent drift into validation theater or solution mining.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use this exact XML prompt structure for every cadence agent—roles, inputs, rules, and task—with the Torres framework constraints hardcoded in the rules block.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents trained on generic UX content drift into "validation theater" and solution mining without explicit Torres-vocabulary constraints. Hardcoding the rules block prevents terminology drift across agent runs.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Standard Cadence Agent Prompt Pattern">
        <code lang="xml"><![CDATA[
<role>You are the {agent}. Continuous Discovery (Torres) practitioner.</role>

<inputs>
  <since>{ISO8601 last-run timestamp}</since>
  <signals>{paths to analytics/tickets/transcripts}</signals>
  <ost>{path to opportunity-solution-tree.md}</ost>
  <assumptions>{path to open-assumptions.md}</assumptions>
</inputs>

<rules>
  - Tag every observation with: source, user_segment, frequency, severity (1-5).
  - Distinguish OPPORTUNITY (unmet need) from SOLUTION (proposed feature). Reject solution-shaped input.
  - Never declare "validated" from a single signal. Require N>=5 across >=2 sources.
  - Surface curse-of-knowledge risk: flag claims that assume internal jargon.
  - Output JSON matching schema {schema_path}, plus a markdown digest <= 60 lines.
</rules>

<task>{cadence-specific instruction}</task>
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="key-rules-for-all-agents">
      <p>Torres vocabulary constraints and evidence thresholds that prevent hallucination and validation theater.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Ban the word "validated" from all agent prompts and outputs—use "assumption tested" or "evidence found" instead.</statement>
        <rationale>Torres explicitly rejects "validation theater". Agents trained on generic UX content conflate validation (proving a hypothesis) with testing (gathering evidence). The word ban forces the right framing.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Require N >= 5 observations across at least 2 independent sources before any finding is published—reject completions that violate this rule.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs love to declare "insights" from thin signal. A single viral Slack thread or one angry review is not a pattern. Five observations across two source types is the minimum for a credible signal.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Force "opportunity vs solution" classification at intake; reject any item phrased as a feature ("add filter X") and re-prompt for the underlying need.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams revert to solution mode under time pressure. The explicit classification at intake, backed by rejection, maintains discovery discipline even when stakeholders deliver solution-shaped requests.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Score opportunities on (frequency × severity × addressability), not gut feel; emit numeric scores and surface deltas week-over-week.</statement>
        <rationale>Gut-feel prioritization in OSTs is unauditable. Numeric scores with week-over-week deltas reveal which opportunities are gaining or losing urgency and enable evidence-based ranking.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="curse-of-knowledge-guard">
      <p>Lint step to detect internal jargon that signals agent reasoning from product assumptions rather than user mental models.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Add an explicit lint step that flags any term in agent output not present in the last 20 interview transcripts—agents trained on internal docs use jargon that users do not.</statement>
        <rationale>Internal jargon in opportunities ("improve the onboarding wizard UX") signals that the agent is reasoning from product assumptions, not from the user's mental model. The transcript lint catches this before it enters the OST.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ost-hygiene-best-practices">
      <p>Operational practices for maintaining healthy Opportunity Solution Trees over time.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pin one Outcome at the OST root before any opportunity work—without it agents drift into solution mining.</statement>
        <rationale>Opportunityless trees collapse into unordered feature wishlists. A single metric-based outcome (e.g., "W1 activation rate: 30% to 45%") focuses all subsequent discovery.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Maintain an open-assumptions.md register; every opportunity branched into a solution must spawn at least one assumption with a falsifiable test.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a hypothesis register, solution work proceeds without discovery grounding. Each solution must answer "what assumption does this test?"</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Rotate the human reviewer of synthesis output weekly—agents anchor on patterns; humans catch curse-of-knowledge.</statement>
        <rationale>A single reviewer produces blind spots. Weekly rotation surfaces assumptions that the regular reviewer stopped questioning.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Cap interview synthesis to 5 themes per session; more = noise. Discovery-synthesizer aggregates across sessions.</statement>
        <rationale>Too many themes per session dilute signal. Aggregating across multiple sessions reveals true patterns.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every research-reviewer monthly pass must produce a kill list (parked/dead opportunities)—without pruning, OSTs collapse under their own weight.</statement>
        <rationale>Opportunities accumulate faster than they are resolved. A monthly kill list keeps the tree shallow and iterable and prevents discovery from becoming a graveyard.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Tie discovery output to delivery: reference opportunity IDs in PR titles and SDD spec.md ("spec cites opp_xxx").</statement>
        <rationale>Discovery output without delivery linkage has no feedback loop. Referencing opportunity IDs in code commits and specs enables retrospective analysis of which discoveries led to shipped features.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Token budget: cap weekly synth at ~30k tokens, monthly at ~80k; otherwise opus costs balloon.</statement>
        <rationale>Unbounded context for opus synthesis costs spiral. Preset budgets force compression of inputs and keep economics sustainable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>CLI tools for orchestration, signal collection, and research repository management.</p>

      <list>
        <item>claude (Claude Code): orchestrate subagents via Task tool; slash commands per cadence (/discovery-daily, /discovery-weekly, /discovery-synth)</item>
        <item>gh: pull GitHub issue feedback as signal source; gh issue list --label feedback --json feeds support-triage</item>
        <item>posthog CLI / amplitude-cli: pull funnel + retention deltas; pipe into analytics-watcher</item>
        <item>linear CLI: query bug+feature requests; tag against OST opportunity nodes</item>
        <item>otter / fireflies / tldv API: fetch transcripts of completed interviews; auto-feed interview-synthesizer</item>
        <item>dovetail API (/v1/notes, /v1/tags): push tagged quotes from synthesizer</item>
        <item>userinterviews.com API: automate weekly recruit batches</item>
        <item>slack CLI / webhook: post weekly synthesis digest to product channel</item>
        <item>cron / systemd timers / launchd: run cadence agents on schedule; on NERO use loop skill or schedule skill for managed triggers</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-platforms">
      <p>Paid and open services for interview management, transcription, and research repository.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Dovetail: REST + webhooks; repository + AI tagging; Magic AI summaries 2025+</item>
        <item>Looppanel: REST; AI interview analysis, auto-tagging, JTBD extraction</item>
        <item>Condens: Synthesis; lighter than Dovetail; good for solo PMs</item>
        <item>EnjoyHQ (acquired by Userinterviews): REST; repository + recruit unification</item>
        <item>Userinterviews.com: REST; panel access, scheduling, incentives</item>
        <item>Userlytics / UserTesting: REST; moderated/unmoderated tests for weekly assumption tests via prototypes</item>
        <item>Maze: REST; fast assumption tests (quant + qual) for weekly cadence</item>
        <item>Notion: REST; OST + opportunity backlog home</item>
        <item>Airtable: REST; lightweight insight DB if not on Dovetail</item>
        <item>PostHog: REST + SQL; self-hostable; feeds analytics-watcher with daily funnel deltas</item>
        <item>Amplitude: REST; hypothesis-aligned cohorts</item>
        <item>Intercom / Zendesk / HelpScout: REST; support ticket source for daily theme clustering</item>
        <item>Otter / Fireflies / tl;dv: REST; transcription for async interview synthesis</item>
        <item>ProductBoard: REST; insight → opportunity linkage (optional; OSTs duplicate most value)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas-and-failures">
      <p>Critical failure modes and mitigation patterns specific to continuous discovery agent pipelines.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Recruiting fatigue: weekly interviews require a recurring source—without infrastructure the cadence collapses by week 4.</description>
        <reason>Mitigation: in-app prompt, customer panel, Userinterviews.com, or a scheduled recruiter agent. Recruiting infrastructure is a prerequisite for continuous discovery at scale.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Curse-of-knowledge bias persists if the same trio interprets every interview—internal assumptions lock in.</description>
        <reason>Rotate observers, use Looppanel/Dovetail tagging across team members. Different reviewers catch blind spots.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Assumption testing is often skipped because it feels slower than shipping.</description>
        <reason>Without an explicit weekly slot it disappears. Use the scheduled assumption-tester agent and review results in weekly synthesis.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>AI synthesis hallucinates patterns from small N—LLM declares "insight" from &lt;5 interviews without human cross-tag.</description>
        <reason>Never let an LLM declare an "insight" from &lt;5 observations across &lt;2 sources. Schema enforcement: reject completions violating N>=5 rule.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>OSTs rot when not pruned—opportunities accumulate; monthly archival is skipped.</description>
        <reason>Opportunities accumulate faster than resolved. Require monthly kill list from research-reviewer; without pruning OSTs collapse under weight.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Discovery output without delivery linkage becomes a research graveyard.</description>
        <reason>Every opportunity must trace to either a tested assumption or a deliberate "park" decision. Tie to delivery: reference opp IDs in PR titles and spec.md.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs invent "insights" from thin signal without enforcing N>=5 rule in schema.</description>
        <reason>Reject completions that violate N>=5. Schema enforcement is the only reliable guard—prompt instructions alone are insufficient.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Transcription tools mis-attribute speakers; agents conflate interviewer leading questions with user statements.</description>
        <reason>Strip interviewer turns before synthesis. Only user statements should feed the interview-synthesizer.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Models hallucinate competitor changelog entries when scraping fails; competitor-monitor outputs invented features.</description>
        <reason>Require explicit URL + fetched-at timestamp in every competitor-monitor row. No updates without a source.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Daily Haiku watchers overwrite the insight log instead of appending atomically.</description>
        <reason>Use atomic append + lock file, never Write. Concurrent watcher runs without locking corrupt the log and lose audit trail.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Bi-weekly synthesizer with full week's context can exceed context window.</description>
        <reason>Pre-summarize per-day with Haiku, feed summaries to Opus. Full-week raw context overflows and silently truncates.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Subagents that write to Dovetail/Notion via API create duplicate notes if retried without idempotency.</description>
        <reason>Require idempotency keys (hash of source URL + date) for all API writes. Retries without idempotency multiply notes.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Assumption-tester proposes "ship and measure" as a valid test type.</description>
        <reason>That is delivery, not discovery. Constrain to: smoke test, fake door, prototype, Wizard of Oz, concierge, Mom Test, data dive.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Long-running cron agents accumulate state drift; schema validation is never run.</description>
        <reason>Have research-reviewer run monthly schema-validation pass over OST + assumptions register. Prevents entropy.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Privacy: raw PII transcripts fed to non-zero-retention models.</description>
        <reason>Use Anthropic ZDR-eligible endpoints or strip PII pre-prompt. Interview transcripts are sensitive data.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Recruitment automation violates panel ToS (Userinterviews limits weekly batch size).</description>
        <reason>Rate-limit at agent level. Check service ToS and adjust cadence to comply.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ost-schema.json" purpose="OST node schema: id/type/parent/evidence/status fields for git-tracked tree."/>
      <template path="templates/analytics-watcher.py" purpose="Agent SDK daily watcher: fetches PostHog + tickets, appends to insight-log.md."/>
      <template path="templates/crontab.txt" purpose="Cron schedule for four discovery cadences (daily/weekly/bi-weekly/monthly)."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.producttalk.org/continuous-discovery-habits">Teresa Torres, Continuous Discovery Habits (2021)—canonical text</link>
      <link href="https://www.producttalk.org/podcast">ProductTalk Podcast—2025–2026 episodes on AI in discovery</link>
      <link href="https://www.producttalk.org/opportunity-solution-tree">Torres' Opportunity Solution Tree deep dives</link>
      <link href="https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/claude-code/sub-agents">Anthropic Claude Agent SDK docs—agents, structured outputs, scheduled triggers</link>
      <link href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/inspired/9781119387503/">Marty Cagan, Inspired / Empowered—adjacent product-trio practices</link>
      <link href="https://www.looppanel.com/">Looppanel—AI-assisted interview synthesis</link>
      <link href="https://www.dovetailapp.com/">Dovetail—research repository with Magic AI 2025+</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
