<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-overview" title="Legal Compliance — Sub-component Map">
  <summary>Routing guide for the legal compliance domain: maps common founder situations to the correct sub-methodology.</summary>

  <section title="Sub-components">
    <p>Legal compliance for online businesses is split into two focused methodologies to keep each loadable and actionable on its own.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Load ops-legal-basics for foundation work (entity choice, policy drafting, IP, contracts). Load ops-legal-compliance-checklist for stage-by-stage implementation tracking and auditing.</statement>
      <rationale>Splitting foundation knowledge from implementation tracking allows an agent to load only what the task requires, avoiding token waste.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Situation routing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use this routing table to select the correct sub-methodology before starting any legal compliance task.</statement>
      <rationale>Routing errors (e.g. going straight to the checklist without reading the policy framework) produce incomplete outputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Setting up business entity → ops-legal-basics (Step 1: structure)</item>
      <item>Drafting Terms or Privacy policies → ops-legal-basics (Step 2: policies)</item>
      <item>Understanding GDPR/CCPA obligations → ops-legal-basics (Step 3: regulations)</item>
      <item>Protecting brand / trademark → ops-legal-basics (Step 4: IP)</item>
      <item>Contractor or customer agreements → ops-legal-basics (Step 5: contracts)</item>
      <item>Pre-launch compliance review → ops-legal-compliance-checklist (Day 1)</item>
      <item>Post-launch compliance audit → ops-legal-compliance-checklist (Month 1)</item>
      <item>Ongoing policy maintenance → ops-legal-compliance-checklist (Ongoing)</item>
      <item>Website legal page audit → ops-legal-compliance-checklist (Website Requirements)</item>
      <item>Policy update process → ops-legal-compliance-checklist (Policy Update Process)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent safety constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always mark any agent-generated policy text as draft requiring attorney review before publication.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM-drafted Terms or Privacy policies may hallucinate legal references, omit jurisdiction-mandatory clauses, or import US terms into non-US contexts. Publishing without counsel review is malpractice exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every agent task on legal compliance must declare the jurisdiction set (e.g. US-only, US+EU, US+EU+UK) before generating any output.</statement>
      <rationale>The same data flow can be lawful in one jurisdiction and unlawful in another. Undeclared jurisdiction produces silently wrong guidance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent auto-applies a single cookie-banner pattern across all markets.</description>
      <reason>EU requires opt-in; CCPA requires opt-out; Quebec Law 25 is hybrid. One pattern violates at least one regime.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent auto-publishes policy changes without a redline + human review gate.</description>
      <reason>Silent policy edits hide changes from counsel, create litigation risk, and may violate user notification obligations.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../ops-legal-basics/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../ops-legal-compliance-checklist/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../ops-tax-basics/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
