<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Gcp Iam Design Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for the gcp-iam-design methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale + concrete remediation hook.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="folder-level-bindings" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cross-cutting IAM bindings (security viewer, billing user, network admin) MUST be applied at folder level and inherited, never per-project.</statement>
      <rationale source="IAM best-practices">Per-project bindings drift; folder-level bindings stay consistent and auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="least-privilege-roles" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use predefined roles tailored to the action, not basic roles (`Owner`, `Editor`, `Viewer`) on production resources.</statement>
      <rationale source="GCP IAM docs">Basic roles grant excessive permissions and violate least-privilege.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="workload-identity-federation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>External CI/CD (GitHub Actions, GitLab) MUST use Workload Identity Federation; long-lived service-account JSON keys are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="GCP WIF docs">Static SA keys are the largest single source of GCP credential leaks; WIF eliminates the static credential entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="conditional-bindings" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sensitive bindings (Owner, IAM admin, Secret Manager admin) MUST carry IAM Conditions restricting resource, time, or source IP where applicable.</statement>
      <rationale source="IAM Conditions docs">Conditions narrow exposure of the most powerful roles without losing operational flexibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="impersonation-instead-of-keys" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Developers and tooling MUST impersonate service accounts via short-lived tokens, never download SA JSON keys.</statement>
      <rationale source="GCP SA impersonation docs">Impersonation is auditable and revocable; downloaded keys leak in repos, dotfiles, and incident drives.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the input fails ALL "Applies If" preconditions or matches ANY "Skip If" disqualifier, do not apply this methodology — route the task to the adjacent sibling instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Even flat checklists need an explicit skip leaf in the decision tree; this rule is the universal terminal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
