<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Backup Verification + Disaster Recovery Drills Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the backup-verification-dr methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced by the decision tree.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="restore-drill-cron" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every backup pipeline MUST be exercised by an automated restore drill at least weekly; the drill MUST restore to a fresh disposable target and run a verification query (row-count, checksum, smoke test).</statement>
      <rationale source="DORA Reliability research, Internal DR drill program">Backups never tested at restore time fail at restore time; the &gt;50% failure rate is repeatedly measured across audit programs.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="alert-on-stale-backup" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Backup age MUST be observable as a Prometheus metric (`backup_age_seconds`) and alert when it exceeds 1.5x the expected interval.</statement>
      <rationale source="Prometheus best practices, SRE Workbook ch.4">An invisible stalled cron leaves the team certain backups are running while the file in S3 ages for weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="alert-on-size-anomaly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Backup size MUST be observable as a Prometheus metric (`backup_size_bytes`); alert on &gt; 50% drop vs 7-day median.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal incident review">Sudden size collapse indicates the dump truncated, the source pruned data, or the script lost a flag.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="dr-runbook-as-code" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DR procedure MUST be a versioned runbook (Markdown with tagged steps) the agent can execute; ad-hoc tribal-knowledge restore is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal incident review">On-call without a runbook produces non-deterministic restore times and risks data loss from one-off shell improvisation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="rpo-rto-measured" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each drill MUST emit `dr_rpo_seconds_actual` and `dr_rto_seconds_actual` metrics; alert when actual &gt; 1.2x target.</statement>
      <rationale source="DORA Reliability metric">Without measured RPO/RTO the team can claim any objective; ground truth is the drill timer.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If no backup pipeline is in place yet, this methodology MUST be skipped — produce the backup pipeline first (`backup-database-postgres`, `backup-filesystem-restic`, etc.).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal DR review">Verification methodology applied to no backups is theatre.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
