<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Technical Debt Trade-off Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every debt-record must obey. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="fowler-quadrant-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every debt-record MUST tag both axes of the Fowler quadrant: intent (deliberate|inadvertent) and prudence (prudent|reckless). Untagged or single-axis records are invalid.</statement>
      <rationale source="Martin Fowler — Technical Debt Quadrant 2009">The two axes determine repayment strategy: deliberate-prudent debt is a trade; inadvertent-reckless is a flaw. Conflating them produces wrong fixes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="observable-trigger-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>repayment_trigger MUST be an observable signal (metric + threshold + measurement source), not a phrase containing "someday", "when we have time", or "later". Time-based triggers without a metric are also rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — debt-backlog audit on 6 projects 2025">Without a concrete trigger, debt accumulates indefinitely; backlogs grow until the project collapses under interest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="debt-budget-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Adding a new debt item MUST NOT push total debt cost above 20% of project capacity. Over-budget additions are blocked; existing debt must be repaid first.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — quarterly velocity audit 2024-2025">Teams crossing 25% debt allocation halve their feature delivery rate; 15-20% is the empirically observed sustainable band.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="localized-or-systemic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Severity MUST be tagged: localized (one module/file) or systemic (touches ≥3 modules or a foundation choice). Systemic debt requires ATAM-grade review, not a debt-record.</statement>
      <rationale source="ATAM evaluation method">Systemic debt is a quality-attribute risk, not a backlog item; treating it as backlog hides the real cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="deliberate-vs-flaw-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the "better solution" was unknown at the time of the shortcut, the record is inadvertent — NOT debt; it is a learning. Backfilling deliberate-prudent classification on retro-discovered shortcuts is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Martin Fowler — Technical Debt Quadrant 2009">Classification fraud destroys the value of the quadrant; if everything becomes "deliberate-prudent" the team loses the signal that distinguishes trade from mistake.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
