<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="stakeholder-communication Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for stakeholder-communication. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose the dialogue mode before generating any questions. State the mode to the stakeholder at the start so they know what kind of input you need.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each mode has a distinct question structure and stakeholder role. Surprise mode-switching mid-session breaks rapport and produces unfocused answers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use the interview protocol sequence: Context → Problem → Impact → Goal → Constraints → Priority. Ask one question at a time. Open questions first, probing to dig deeper.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The sequence builds from shared context to the critical priority. Jumping to priority first produces rankings without understanding.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run three phases in order: Diverge (generate, no judgment) → Cluster (group similar ideas) → Converge (vote, prioritize). Never evaluate during the diverge phase.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Premature evaluation kills ideation. Mixing generation and evaluation in one pass produces fewer and less creative ideas.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a stakeholder uses vague terms (fast, easy, better, all, always, never), ask a multiple-choice clarification: "When you say X, do you mean A, B, or something else?" — not an open-ended restatement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Open restatements ("what do you mean?") produce more vague answers. Multiple-choice options force the stakeholder to commit to an interpretation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send a written validation summary within 24 hours of a meeting. Do not silently resolve ambiguities with a default interpretation — flag them explicitly and request confirmation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Memory fades within 24 hours. Silently resolving ambiguities produces a divergence between what was said and what was built, discovered only at delivery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Socratic questioning to surface hidden assumptions and help stakeholders think through requirements they have not fully formed. Do not use this mode in sequence without human adaptation — verbatim Socratic chains in live conversation feel interrogative.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Socratic questioning uncovers the real need behind a surface request. Without it, "we need real-time sync" becomes a hard technical requirement when 5-minute polling would suffice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map each stakeholder to a quadrant: High Power + High Interest = Manage Closely (weekly 1-on-1s, involve in decisions); High Power + Low Interest = Keep Satisfied (bi-weekly summary, escalate issues); Low Power + High Interest = Keep Informed (monthly status); Low Power + Low Interest = Monitor (available on request).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Under-communicating with high-power stakeholders creates surprises and vetoes. Over-communicating with low-interest stakeholders wastes their time and reduces your credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not assign quadrant positions from job titles alone. Political influence often does not track seniority — seek organizational context from a human before placing anyone.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">An informal influencer with a mid-level title placed in "Monitor" who then vetoes the project is the most expensive stakeholder management failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Identify the stakeholder type before the session and select the facilitation response that matches. Do not use the same approach for all stakeholder types.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each type represents a different underlying dynamic. A "Silent" stakeholder needs direct questions and written async input; using the same open-group format produces the same silence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agents generating interview guides default to generic questions ("What are your goals?") unless the stakeholder role and project context are provided in specific detail.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The five dialogue modes require selection based on relationship context and stakeholder personality — agents recommend modes based on situation parameters alone, which may be incomplete.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Transcription-based requirement extraction fails when multiple stakeholders talk over each other or use domain jargon; human annotation of key exchanges improves accuracy significantly.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Validation summaries drafted by agents may paraphrase requirements inaccurately if the source transcript is ambiguous; stakeholder confirmation of the summary is mandatory before proceeding.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Socratic question chains must not be used in sequence without human adaptation — using them verbatim in a live conversation feels interrogative and damages rapport.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Brainstorm facilitation prompts work well as preparation but live facilitation requires real-time adaptation that agents cannot provide.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Human checkpoint required before sending any validation summary — the agent may misparaphrase a nuanced requirement, and stakeholder sign-off on a wrong summary creates downstream rework.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Power/Interest grid assignments must be reviewed by a human with organizational context; an agent using only job titles will misplace politically influential stakeholders who have informal power.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
