<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-dialogue-modes" title="Five stakeholder dialogue modes">
  <summary>Select one dialogue mode per conversation: Interview, Brainstorm, Clarification, Validation, or Socratic. Mixing modes in one session produces incoherent structure; Interview questions and Socratic questions have fundamentally different structure and must not be interleaved.</summary>

  <section title="Mode selection rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose the dialogue mode before generating any questions. State the mode to the stakeholder at the start so they know what kind of input you need.</statement>
      <rationale>Each mode has a distinct question structure and stakeholder role. Surprise mode-switching mid-session breaks rapport and produces unfocused answers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Mode 1: Interview — requirements gathering">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the interview protocol sequence: Context → Problem → Impact → Goal → Constraints → Priority. Ask one question at a time. Open questions first, probing to dig deeper.</statement>
      <rationale>The sequence builds from shared context to the critical priority. Jumping to priority first produces rankings without understanding.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Open: "Tell me about your current workflow" — explore</item>
      <item>Probing: "Why is that important?" — dig deeper</item>
      <item>Clarifying: "What do you mean by X?" — remove ambiguity</item>
      <item>Hypothetical: "What if you could do Y?" — envision</item>
      <item>Summary: "So you're saying...?" — confirm</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Mode 2: Brainstorm — generating options">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run three phases in order: Diverge (generate, no judgment) → Cluster (group similar ideas) → Converge (vote, prioritize). Never evaluate during the diverge phase.</statement>
      <rationale>Premature evaluation kills ideation. Mixing generation and evaluation in one pass produces fewer and less creative ideas.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Diverge prompts: "What else could we try?", "What would the opposite approach be?", "What would a competitor do?"</item>
      <item>Cluster: group semantically similar ideas, name each cluster</item>
      <item>Converge: dot voting (3-5 dots per person), impact/effort scoring</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Mode 3: Clarification — resolving ambiguity">
    <rule>
      <statement>When a stakeholder uses vague terms (fast, easy, better, all, always, never), ask a multiple-choice clarification: "When you say X, do you mean A, B, or something else?" — not an open-ended restatement.</statement>
      <rationale>Open restatements ("what do you mean?") produce more vague answers. Multiple-choice options force the stakeholder to commit to an interpretation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Definition: "What do you mean by 'user-friendly'?"</item>
      <item>Boundary: "What's included? What's excluded?"</item>
      <item>Example: "Can you give me a specific example?"</item>
      <item>Metric: "How would we measure success?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Mode 4: Validation — confirming understanding">
    <rule>
      <statement>Send a written validation summary within 24 hours of a meeting. Do not silently resolve ambiguities with a default interpretation — flag them explicitly and request confirmation.</statement>
      <rationale>Memory fades within 24 hours. Silently resolving ambiguities produces a divergence between what was said and what was built, discovered only at delivery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/validation-email.md">Post-meeting validation email template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Mode 5: Socratic — probing assumptions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Socratic questioning to surface hidden assumptions and help stakeholders think through requirements they have not fully formed. Do not use this mode in sequence without human adaptation — verbatim Socratic chains in live conversation feel interrogative.</statement>
      <rationale>Socratic questioning uncovers the real need behind a surface request. Without it, "we need real-time sync" becomes a hard technical requirement when 5-minute polling would suffice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Socratic dialogue collapsing a hard requirement to a simpler solution</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Stakeholder: "We need real-time sync."
You: "What do you mean by 'real-time'?" (Clarifying)
S: "Instant updates when data changes."
You: "What's driving that requirement?" (Assumption)
S: "Users complain about stale data."
You: "How stale? Minutes? Hours?" (Evidence)
S: "Actually... a few minutes would be fine."
You: "What would happen if we sync every 5 minutes?" (Implication)
S: "That could work, and it's much simpler."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-socratic-chain.txt">Prompt for generating a Socratic question chain</reference>
  </section>
</text>
