<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-stakeholder-mapping" title="Power/Interest grid and difficult stakeholder types">
  <summary>The power/interest grid determines communication frequency and channel per quadrant; stakeholder type (silent, dominant, negative, absent, changing) requires a specific facilitation response.</summary>

  <section title="Power/Interest grid">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map each stakeholder to a quadrant: High Power + High Interest = Manage Closely (weekly 1-on-1s, involve in decisions); High Power + Low Interest = Keep Satisfied (bi-weekly summary, escalate issues); Low Power + High Interest = Keep Informed (monthly status); Low Power + Low Interest = Monitor (available on request).</statement>
      <rationale>Under-communicating with high-power stakeholders creates surprises and vetoes. Over-communicating with low-interest stakeholders wastes their time and reduces your credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not assign quadrant positions from job titles alone. Political influence often does not track seniority — seek organizational context from a human before placing anyone.</statement>
      <rationale>An informal influencer with a mid-level title placed in "Monitor" who then vetoes the project is the most expensive stakeholder management failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Difficult stakeholder types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify the stakeholder type before the session and select the facilitation response that matches. Do not use the same approach for all stakeholder types.</statement>
      <rationale>Each type represents a different underlying dynamic. A "Silent" stakeholder needs direct questions and written async input; using the same open-group format produces the same silence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Silent (won't share): direct questions addressed by name, written async input before the meeting</item>
      <item>Dominant (talks over others): use brainwriting or round robin to enforce equal turn-taking</item>
      <item>Negative (shoots down ideas): "Yes, and..." facilitation rule; Reverse Brainstorm to channel criticism productively</item>
      <item>Absent (misses meetings): async input requests, written summary with confirmation required</item>
      <item>Changing (shifts requirements): require written confirmation per requirement; maintain a dated change log</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Accepting verbal agreement from a "Changing" stakeholder without a written confirmation.</description>
    <reason>Verbal agreements are repudiated under project pressure. A written confirmation email creates a dated record that prevents requirement drift from becoming a dispute.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <reference path="templates/requirement-capture.md">Requirement capture card with validation status</reference>
  <reference path="templates/meeting-prep.md">Stakeholder meeting prep card</reference>
</text>
