<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spec-advanced-guidelines">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd-planning</domain>
    <summary>Advanced guidelines for writing comprehensive specs for complex, mission-critical features with traceability chains and measurable acceptance criteria.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>specifications</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>acceptance-criteria</tag>
      <tag>nfr</tag>
      <tag>traceability</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Spec Advanced Guidelines</title>
    <summary>Advanced guidelines for writing comprehensive specs for complex, mission-critical features. Full specs have 14 sections: Overview, Problem Statement, Personas, User Stories, Functional Requirements, NFRs, Acceptance Criteria, Out of Scope, Assumptions, Dependencies, Related Features, Skills, Open Questions, Appendix. NFRs must be measurable (&lt; 200ms p95, 99.9% uptime). Acceptance criteria must cover happy path + errors + edge cases + performance + security. Every FR must trace to a user story, every AC to an FR.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Generic specs produce ambiguous tasks that agents interpret inconsistently. Personas prevent "As a user" antipatterns. Measurable NFRs prevent "system should be fast" antipatterns. Out of Scope prevents scope creep from recurring in every planning session. Traceability chains (FR → US → AC) are the primary quality gate for spec completeness.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Complex features with multiple user types or roles</item>
        <item>Features with significant NFRs (performance, security, scalability targets)</item>
        <item>Features with external system dependencies or API contracts</item>
        <item>Mission-critical features affecting core business metrics</item>
        <item>Features requiring cross-role alignment (dev + product + design)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Simple CRUD with no business logic (use minimal spec: Overview + 1-2 stories + basic AC)</item>
        <item>Trivial UI copy changes (inline comment sufficient)</item>
        <item>Internal refactoring without external behavior change (use design doc only)</item>
        <item>Experimental features under development (use lightweight hypothesis spec)</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="required-sections">
      <rule>
        <statement>A full spec must include all 14 sections: Overview, Problem Statement, User Personas, User Stories, Functional Requirements, Non-Functional Requirements, Acceptance Criteria, Out of Scope, Assumptions and Constraints, Dependencies, Related Features, Recommended Skills, Open Questions, Appendix.</statement>
        <rationale>Omitting any section creates a predictable gap: no Personas → generic user stories; no Out of Scope → scope creep in every session; no Assumptions → conflicting implementations.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Problem Statement must answer: Who (target user group), Problem (what they face), Impact (business or user cost), Solution (high-level approach), Success Metric (how to measure the feature succeeded).</statement>
        <rationale>A problem statement without a success metric produces a feature with no clear done criterion. Agents and developers optimize toward undefined targets without it.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="persona-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write 2-3 personas with name, role, goals, pain points, and usage context. Reference personas by name in user stories and acceptance criteria.</statement>
        <rationale>Named personas prevent "As a user" stories that apply to nobody specifically. Referencing them in AC forces scenario specificity.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Persona defined in section 3 but never referenced in user stories or AC.</description>
        <reason>Orphan personas provide no filtering signal. If a persona is not referenced in at least one user story, either the persona is unnecessary or the user stories are too generic.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="traceability-chain">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every Functional Requirement must trace to at least one User Story (FR-X → US-Y). Every Acceptance Criterion must trace to at least one FR (AC-Z → FR-X). No FR may exist without a US parent. No AC may exist without an FR parent.</statement>
        <rationale>Orphan requirements indicate either gold-plating (FR with no user story) or untestable design (FR with no AC). The chain ensures every requirement serves a stated user need and has a verifiable completion check.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[### FR-001: Add item to cart
Traces to: US-001 (As Sarah, I want to add products to cart with one click)

**AC-001** (validates FR-001):
Given Sarah is on a product page,
When she clicks "Add to Cart",
Then the cart count increments by 1 and a confirmation toast appears.

**AC-002** (validates FR-001):
Given the product is out of stock,
When Sarah clicks "Add to Cart",
Then the button is disabled and shows "Out of Stock".]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="out-of-scope-documentation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every Out of Scope item must include: feature name, one-sentence reason it is excluded, and a "when" (Phase N, v2, never). Do not include items without all three fields.</statement>
        <rationale>Items without explicit exclusion reasoning re-emerge in every planning session. The "when" prevents permanent exclusion from being confused with deferred scope.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="nfr-measurability">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every NFR must specify: quantifiable target, measurement approach (how to measure), and validation method (how to test). NFRs without quantifiable targets must be rejected and rewritten before spec approval.</statement>
        <rationale>"System should be fast" is not an NFR — it is a preference. Without a number, neither developers nor agents can know when the requirement is met.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[### NFR-001: Add to Cart Latency
**Requirement:** Add to cart operation SHALL complete in < 200ms at p95.
**Measurement:** Client-side total time from click to UI update (Performance API).
**Priority:** Must
**Validation:** Load test with 500 concurrent users, measure p95 latency.]]></code>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent writes NFR as "The system should handle high traffic" or "Response times should be acceptable".</description>
        <reason>LLMs produce qualitative NFR language because they lack knowledge of the specific system's performance profile. Require the agent to propose a specific number and explicitly mark it [estimate] — then the human validates or corrects the target.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="acceptance-criteria-coverage">
      <rule>
        <statement>For each functional requirement, acceptance criteria must cover: happy path, at least one error case, at least one edge case (boundary condition or empty state). For security-sensitive FRs, add an unauthorized access scenario.</statement>
        <rationale>Specs with only happy path AC produce features that break on first error condition in production. The coverage matrix forces specification of failure behavior before implementation begins.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use Given-When-Then format for all acceptance criteria. Avoid free-form prose AC. "Works correctly" is not an acceptance criterion.</statement>
        <rationale>Given-When-Then enforces testability. Each field maps directly to a test: Given = test setup, When = action, Then = assertion. Prose AC requires interpretation, causing inconsistent test coverage.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>AC covers only the happy path for all FRs, with no error or edge cases.</description>
        <reason>Agents default to positive-case thinking. Explicitly require error scenarios for every FR that involves user input, external calls, or state transitions. Ask: "What happens when this fails?"</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="assumptions-documentation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Document every assumption that, if wrong, would require a spec change. Format: "Assumption: [statement]. If wrong: [consequence]."</statement>
        <rationale>Hidden assumptions are the primary source of mid-development spec surprises. Making the "if wrong" consequence explicit accelerates discovery of invalid assumptions during review.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/spec-full-template.md" purpose="14-section full spec stub with all required sections"/>
      <template path="templates/check-traceability.sh" purpose="Shell script to verify FR → US → AC coverage"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
