<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Testimonial Harvest — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that turn end-of-engagement into a reliable 3-artifact harvest pipeline.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-three-triggers" testable="true">
      <statement>The SOP fires on EXACTLY 3 triggers per engagement: (T1) final deliverable shipped (T+0), (T2) invoice paid (T+0-14), (T3) 30-day check-in (T+30). Triggers must run regardless of operator mood — automate via project-close webhooks.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brennan Dunn — Double Your Freelancing / Patrick McKenzie">Solo operators forget testimonial requests when energy is spent on shipping. Pre-committed triggers convert intention into recurring system, lifting harvest yield from ~10% to ~60%.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-three-outputs" testable="true">
      <statement>Each engagement yields THREE artifacts: (a) WRITTEN quote (mandatory, from 3Q script), (b) LOOM 60-90s video (request only — never required), (c) one OUTCOME METRIC (number + unit + period). All three asked but not all three required for "harvest closed".</statement>
      <rationale source="Conversion-rate cohort data (Wynter, Profitwell)">Mixed-media testimonials convert 2-4× higher than text-only. Asking for video at the same time as quote doubles video yield vs asking later.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-kill-at-90d" testable="true">
      <statement>If no harvest after 90 days from closure, mark `harvest_status: lost` and STOP outreach. Outreach attempt 4+ damages relationship more than it improves yield (Sean D'Souza cohort).</statement>
      <rationale source="Sean D'Souza follow-up research / Brennan Dunn cohort data">Yield curve flattens at 3 attempts. Continued asks become pestering and erode the chance of referrals from the same customer.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-nps-gate" testable="true">
      <statement>Harvest fires ONLY if engagement closure NPS ≥ 7 OR no documented friction event. NPS &lt; 7 routes to `post-mortem` workflow, not harvest. Asking unhappy customers for testimonials produces lies or rebuke.</statement>
      <rationale source="Frederick Reichheld — The Ultimate Question (NPS origin)">Promoters (9-10) and high-passive (7-8) produce credible testimonials. Detractors (0-6) either refuse or provide quotes that prospects detect as forced. Gate is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-consent-layering" testable="true">
      <statement>Consent is harvested PER ARTIFACT and per USE: written quote may be approved for site but not LinkedIn; video may be approved for case study but not paid ads. `HarvestRecord` MUST track each (artifact, usage) pair.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art. 7 specific-consent requirement + FTC endorsement guides">"Can I use this?" is too coarse. Customers grant blanket consent reluctantly. Per-usage consent gets MORE consent and is legally defensible.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Harvest pipeline timeline">

    <example type="good" title="Engagement closed → 90-day harvest window">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
T+0 (deliverable shipped):
  → send 3Q script email (per solo-testimonial-extraction-script)
  → outcome: written quote (if reply lands within 7 days)

T+0 to T+14 (invoice paid trigger):
  → send "I'd love a 60-90s Loom — here's a 3-prompt script" email
  → outcome: Loom (if recorded within 7 days)

T+30 (check-in trigger):
  → send "how is it going since launch? any specific numbers
     worth sharing?" email
  → outcome: metric (revenue, time, error rate, conversion)

T+90: kill (mark harvest_status: lost) if missing artifacts
      ]]></code>
      <note>3 triggers spread over time avoid spam-feel. Each ask aligns with a natural moment in the relationship.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="One-shot ask 6 months later (r3 violation)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Engagement closed January. Operator needs site refresh in July.
"Hey, could you write me a testimonial for the work we did
6 months ago?"

Yield: ~5%. Customer barely remembers details. Reply (if any)
is generic ("great working with you").
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1 + r3 violation. Fresh memory + scheduled triggers produce 10× the yield.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
