<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-sizing" title="Market Sizing">
  <summary>TAM/SAM/SOM calculation rules with bottom-up enforcement and divergence flagging.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Every TAM number must carry source, year, and geography in the same line. Reject standalone dollar figures with no provenance.</statement>
    <rationale>Top-down numbers from Gartner/Statista are routinely inflated 3-10x. LLMs parrot fabricated CAGRs with high confidence. Citation in the same line is the minimum defense against hallucinated market sizes.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Always run sizing top-down AND bottom-up. Flag divergence above 2x as a research gap — do not average or pick the more favorable number.</statement>
    <rationale>Divergence above 2x signals a definitional mismatch, a data quality problem, or a constraint that was not applied consistently. Averaging hides the problem; flagging forces investigation before the number enters a deck or a spec.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Definitions">
    <list>
      <item>TAM: total revenue if you captured 100% of everyone who could ever buy — the ceiling, not the plan</item>
      <item>SAM: portion of TAM reachable given real constraints (geography, language, industry, company size, tech stack)</item>
      <item>SOM: realistic market share capturable in 3-5 years given budget, brand, and competition</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Bottom-Up Calculation Steps">
    <list>
      <item>Find countable potential customers: LinkedIn search, industry database, platform API</item>
      <item>Estimate the percentage reachable with the current marketing budget and channel mix</item>
      <item>Apply a realistic conversion rate (trial, then paid) from comparable products</item>
      <item>Multiply by price to arrive at Year 1 and Year 3 SOM in dollars</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Validation">
    <list>
      <item>Can you name 100 specific target companies or individuals? If not, the SAM is not specific enough</item>
      <item>Can you explain the operational path to the SOM? If not, the SOM is aspirational, not a plan</item>
      <item>Does the bottom-up match the top-down within 2x? If not, document the specific constraint causing the gap</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/market-sizing.md">Market sizing template with top-down and bottom-up sections</reference>
</text>
