<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-competitor-discovery" title="Competitor Discovery and Mapping">
  <summary>Competitor types, mapping process, URL-evidence requirement, and whitespace identification.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Cap the competitor list at 20 named entries with working URLs. Longer lists are hallucination magnets — nobody reads them and the data quality degrades past 20.</statement>
    <rationale>Agents happily produce 40 competitor names when asked for a comprehensive list. Beyond 20, entries are increasingly invented, merged, or mischaracterized. A tight, URL-verified list is more actionable than an exhaustive fiction.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Reject any competitor entry without a working URL. Require URL plus a screenshot or page text as evidence that the product currently exists.</statement>
    <rationale>Web-search agents invent product names, merge two products into one, or cite discontinued products as active competitors. URL verification is the minimum bar for a credible competitive landscape.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Competitor Types (map all four)">
    <list>
      <item>Direct: same solution, same problem, same customer — most visible, most cited</item>
      <item>Indirect: different solution, same problem (e.g., Slack vs. Email for team communication)</item>
      <item>Substitute: alternative approach entirely (e.g., outsource vs. software)</item>
      <item>Potential: companies that could enter with their existing capabilities and distribution</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a dedicated brainstorm step for substitute and potential competitors before locking the list. Agents routinely miss these two categories without an explicit prompt.</statement>
      <rationale>Substitute and potential competitors drive the most strategic surprises (e.g., Notion entering Evernote's market, Cursor entering Copilot's space). They are invisible to competitive analysis that only scans existing product categories.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Whitespace Identification">
    <rule>
      <statement>Make whitespace claims falsifiable: link to the specific competitor pricing pages and changelogs confirming the gap exists. A whitespace claim without evidence is a hypothesis, not a finding.</statement>
      <rationale>Unfalsifiable whitespace claims drive product decisions based on assumptions that collapse on first customer call. Evidence-backed whitespace survives early customer validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/competitive-landscape.md">Competitor landscape table with direct, indirect, and whitespace sections</reference>
</text>
