<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="market-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for market-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Running only top-down sizing without a bottom-up cross-check</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Top-down numbers from analyst reports are the ceiling, not the plan. Without a bottom-up check, the SOM is detached from operational reality and cannot be defended to investors or the team.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Feature-matrix based on live pages without a snapshot</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A live-page feature matrix cannot be reproduced 6 months later, cannot be diffed to show competitive movement, and is immediately stale as competitors ship.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Declaring whitespace without review-site evidence of buyer demand</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feature gaps can be intentional. Without buyer demand evidence, a whitespace claim leads to building features nobody needs while ignoring the actual gaps buyers care about.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Using a competitor list that omits indirect and substitute competitors</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Indirect and substitute competitors are the most common source of disruption. A list of only direct competitors produces a false sense of the competitive moat.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent conflates "market size" (revenue) with "user count" and reports them interchangeably</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>SAM in dollars and SAM in seats are different artifacts with different implications for pricing and GTM. Always demand explicit units in every market-size assertion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent cites CAGR with two decimal places without a source</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Treat any CAGR more precise than the nearest 5% as fabricated unless it has a source URL and a page number. Real analyst reports round to one decimal place; invented numbers have false precision.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent silently truncates pricing tables from long SaaS landing pages</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Web-fetch tools cut off page content; pricing tables at the bottom of long pages are omitted. Pass --only-main-content and verify that the output includes the full pricing section.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent cites Gartner or Forrester reports it cannot access because they are paywalled</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>An agent that cannot access a source will sometimes return a confident summary anyway. Require a public URL or mark the source as "(source unverified)"; never accept a paywalled citation without the original text.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent's feature-matrix pass degrades after 10 competitors in long context</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Chunk the matrix to 5 competitors per invocation and merge the JSON. Long-context degradation causes missed features and incorrect Y/N/P assignments past the 10-competitor mark.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent marks a single-channel SAM as "100% reachable" without a CAC ceiling</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every channel has a ceiling — the total reachable accounts via that channel at a given CAC. Without a ceiling, the GTM plan exceeds the actual addressable population.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
