<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-feature-matrix" title="Feature-Gap Matrix">
  <summary>Feature inventory across top 5 competitors, gap classification, and validation requirements before declaring a whitespace.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Snapshot competitor sites before running the feature matrix. The data layer must be reproducible 6 months later — a matrix built from live pages has no baseline to diff against.</statement>
    <rationale>Competitors ship weekly. A feature-matrix assertion from memory or a live page is immediately stale and cannot be audited. Dated snapshots enable the quarterly diff that surfaces actual movement.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Feature Classification">
    <list>
      <item>Table stakes (Y at all top-5 competitors): required to compete; building these is cost of entry, not differentiation</item>
      <item>Opportunity (Y at 1-2 competitors, N or P at others): candidate for differentiation — validate demand before building</item>
      <item>Validate demand (N at all competitors): may be a gap or may be intentional — check reviews for evidence of demand before claiming whitespace</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Gap Validation Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cite at least 5 corroborating reviews or forum posts for every gap declared as an "opportunity." A gap without demand evidence is a hypothesis, not a finding.</statement>
      <rationale>Feature gaps can be intentional (too hard, not profitable, out of scope for the target segment) or unintentional. Review evidence distinguishes between the two and validates that customers actually want the missing feature.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Check G2, Capterra, and Reddit for review text mentioning the missing feature</item>
      <item>Check competitor community forums and roadmap request boards for vote counts</item>
      <item>Check if the gap is listed in any competitor's public roadmap (if so, it may close before you can ship)</item>
      <item>Verify why competitors lack the feature: technical difficulty, low priority, or not aware of demand</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Matrix Refresh Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>A feature matrix older than 90 days is decorative — flag and re-run before using in any decision.</statement>
      <rationale>SaaS competitors ship bi-weekly. A 90-day-old matrix has missed 6+ sprint cycles per competitor. Using it for product decisions means building toward a landscape that no longer exists.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/feature-matrix.md">Feature matrix and gap validation templates</reference>
  <reference path="templates/competitors-snapshot.sh">Script that freezes competitor URLs as dated markdown snapshots</reference>
</text>
