<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Persona Building Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Persona Building methodology. Every rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale, plus the universal skip-this-methodology gate.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="three-personas-exactly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ship exactly 3 personas: primary, secondary, negative; not more, not fewer.</statement>
      <rationale source="Adele Revella, Buyer Personas (2015)">Two personas miss the disqualifier (negative); &gt;3 fragments GTM messaging.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="five-cited-quotes-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every persona MUST cite &gt;=5 verbatim interview quotes; quotes from a single interview do not count as 5.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — persona audit Q1 2026">Single-source personas are fiction; cross-interview citations are the minimum evidence floor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="jtbd-not-demographic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Personas are written around JTBD (job-to-be-done) statements, not age/income demographics alone.</statement>
      <rationale source="Clayton Christensen, Competing Against Luck (2016)">Demographics weakly predict purchase behaviour; jobs predict it strongly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kill-criteria-block" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every persona MUST include a kill-criteria block naming traits that disqualify a user from being this persona.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Q3 2025 persona-drift audit">Without kill criteria, the persona slowly absorbs every user type.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-pain-priority" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Top-3 pains MUST be ranked, not equal-weighted; pain #1 drives onboarding copy.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — landing-page A/B history">Equal-weighted pains produce diluted copy that addresses none of them well.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only if all entries in `## Applies If` hold and none of `## Skip If` triggers; otherwise abort and route to the correct methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — decision tree minimum form">A misrouted methodology produces wrong-shape output; the explicit skip rule is the universal default branch from the decision tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
