<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ba-requirements-mgmt Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ba-requirements-mgmt. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Baseline requirements using a deterministic tag (e.g., `req-baseline-2026-Q2`) so that "what changed" is always answerable with one `git diff` command, not a meeting.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Baseline tags are the auditable record of scope; without them the change history is narrative and unverifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign mandatory attributes to every requirement: status (draft, approved, implemented), priority, owner (person, not team), source, last_review date.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mandatory attributes are the minimal set to detect staleness, ownership gaps, and when a requirement drifts from its source intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Periodic review cadence: flag requirements with stale `last_review` (&gt;90 days), missing owner, or no traceability link; open a PR with `needs_review: true`.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without periodic review requirements decay invisibly; the owner field forces a named person to be accountable for freshness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Archive on tag, not delete: a quarterly tag `req-archive-2026-Q2` snapshots retired REQs; remove from active `requirements/` so daily search stays fast.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Deletion loses audit trail; archival preserves history while keeping the active set searchable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Make CIA mandatory for any CR touching ≥2 requirements; under that, allow a one-line note. The threshold prevents form fatigue and focuses rigor on high-impact changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Small changes introduce bureaucracy costs faster than they reduce risk; large changes need explicit assessment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For each CR, assess impact on five areas: requirements touched (count), design components, code modules, test cases, total effort. Use T-shirt sizes (S/M/L/XL) by area, not hours — convert to hours only at planning time.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">T-shirt sizes reduce false precision; hours are guesses dressed as commitments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>CIA generation is deterministic walk + LLM phrasing: do NOT invent impact links; use only what is in the traceability JSON. If traceability is empty for a given REQ, return `effort: null, reason: "no trace data"` and refuse to estimate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs hallucinate impacted artifacts when trace data is incomplete; leaving the number empty flags the knowledge gap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Identify risks (technical, schedule, quality) and stakeholder impact per CR. For each risk, assign probability (H/M/L) and impact (H/M/L); propose mitigation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Risk assessment forces explicit hazard identification before approval; unseen risks degrade to post-incident surprises.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decompose requirements into a hierarchy with a hard cap on depth (e.g., 3 levels: BR → SR → FR). Anything deeper is task decomposition and belongs in the implementation plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Deep hierarchies create maintenance burden; 3 levels cover all coherent scope abstractions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use four viewpoints (business, user, technical, operational) to partition requirements. Assign single primary viewpoint per requirement plus optional secondary views as labels; avoid duplication across views.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Multiple viewpoints allow different stakeholder perspectives; a clear primary viewpoint prevents ambiguity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Render the requirement hierarchy and dependency graph (Mermaid / Graphviz) on every commit. Detect and flag orphans (no parent), cycles (dependency loops), and single-child chains (collapse candidates).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Automated graph detection scales beyond manual review; visual diffs make structural changes explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Architecture agents must never create new hierarchy nodes to "fix" orphans. Only flag and report; let humans decide whether to reparent, delete, or accept the orphan.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Automatic repair invents scope; agents can identify but not decide.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
