<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-cold-outreach Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-cold-outreach. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Qualify every prospect on five criteria before adding to the list: Pain (has the problem you solve), Budget (can afford), Authority (can decide), Timing (current priority), Reach (contact info obtainable).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sending to unqualified prospects wastes send quota and damages domain reputation. A tight 100-prospect list outperforms a bloated 1,000-prospect list on every metric.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start with 100–200 highly targeted prospects, not thousands. Scale volume only after validating a sequence that achieves 10%+ reply rate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">High volume with an unproven sequence burns deliverability reputation. Validate messaging at low volume first, then automate scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose personalization level based on deal size: Batch (30 sec, company name only) for under $500 ACV; Light (2 min, recent news or post) for $500–5K ACV; Deep (10 min, specific pain from research) for $5K+ ACV.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Deep personalization at low ACV produces negative ROI — the research time exceeds the customer value. Batch personalization at high ACV signals you haven't done homework and reduces reply rate by 50%+.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep the entire cold email to 5 sentences or fewer: subject (4–6 words), personalized opening (1–2 sentences), value prop (2–3 sentences), CTA (1 sentence). No company history, no feature lists.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Longer emails have lower read rates. Prospects decide in 3 seconds whether to read or delete. Every extra sentence is a reason to stop reading.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send a 5-email sequence: initial (Day 0), bump (Day 3), new angle (Day 7), case study (Day 14), break-up (Day 21). Do not stop after the first email — 80% of replies come from follow-ups.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cold outreach data consistently shows that 5+ touchpoints are required for most replies. Single-email campaigns leave the majority of potential responses on the table.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never send cold outreach from your primary domain. Use a separate domain (e.g., tryproduct.com vs product.com). Warm it up for 2–4 weeks before sending at scale. Configure SPF, DKIM, and DMARC before first send.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">If cold outreach domain gets blacklisted, primary domain email remains unaffected. Missing SPF/DKIM causes 20–40% of emails to land in spam regardless of content quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send fewer than 50 emails/day per inbox when starting. Increase by 10–20/day each week. Use email verification (NeverBounce, ZeroBounce) to keep bounce rate below 2%.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">High daily volume from a new inbox triggers spam filters. Bounce rate above 3% degrades sender score rapidly and can trigger blacklisting within days.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
