<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-targeting-and-research" title="Prospect Targeting and Research">
  <summary>ICP criteria for cold outreach (BANT + Reach); prospect sources by channel; three levels of personalization with time cost.</summary>

  <section title="Ideal Prospect Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Qualify every prospect on five criteria before adding to the list: Pain (has the problem you solve), Budget (can afford), Authority (can decide), Timing (current priority), Reach (contact info obtainable).</statement>
      <rationale>Sending to unqualified prospects wastes send quota and damages domain reputation. A tight 100-prospect list outperforms a bloated 1,000-prospect list on every metric.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with 100–200 highly targeted prospects, not thousands. Scale volume only after validating a sequence that achieves 10%+ reply rate.</statement>
      <rationale>High volume with an unproven sequence burns deliverability reputation. Validate messaging at low volume first, then automate scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Prospect Sources">
    <list>
      <item>LinkedIn Sales Navigator — B2B, specific roles and industries. Filter by company size, title, and geography.</item>
      <item>Industry lists (Clutch, G2, Product Hunt) — curated niches, often with direct contact context.</item>
      <item>Job boards (LinkedIn Jobs, Indeed) — companies hiring for a specific role reveal that the function exists and has budget.</item>
      <item>Trigger events (Crunchbase, news) — recent funding, new CTO hire, product launch create natural outreach hooks.</item>
      <item>Competitive displacement (BuiltWith, G2 reviews) — competitors' customers who have pain points with current solution.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Personalization Levels">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose personalization level based on deal size: Batch (30 sec, company name only) for under $500 ACV; Light (2 min, recent news or post) for $500–5K ACV; Deep (10 min, specific pain from research) for $5K+ ACV.</statement>
      <rationale>Deep personalization at low ACV produces negative ROI — the research time exceeds the customer value. Batch personalization at high ACV signals you haven't done homework and reduces reply rate by 50%+.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Research Sources per Prospect">
    <list>
      <item>LinkedIn profile and recent posts — current priorities, recent achievements, interests.</item>
      <item>Company blog and news — recent product launches, partnerships, pain points mentioned.</item>
      <item>Twitter/X activity — opinions, frustrations, topic engagement.</item>
      <item>Job postings — reveals what's being built, what's broken, what skills are missing.</item>
      <item>Podcast appearances — deep interview content; quote their exact words back.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
