<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-infrastructure-and-metrics" title="Deliverability Infrastructure and Metrics">
  <summary>Technical email deliverability setup (separate domain, warmup, SPF/DKIM/DMARC); metrics benchmarks; two real campaign examples.</summary>

  <section title="Deliverability Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never send cold outreach from your primary domain. Use a separate domain (e.g., tryproduct.com vs product.com). Warm it up for 2–4 weeks before sending at scale. Configure SPF, DKIM, and DMARC before first send.</statement>
      <rationale>If cold outreach domain gets blacklisted, primary domain email remains unaffected. Missing SPF/DKIM causes 20–40% of emails to land in spam regardless of content quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Send fewer than 50 emails/day per inbox when starting. Increase by 10–20/day each week. Use email verification (NeverBounce, ZeroBounce) to keep bounce rate below 2%.</statement>
      <rationale>High daily volume from a new inbox triggers spam filters. Bounce rate above 3% degrades sender score rapidly and can trigger blacklisting within days.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Metrics Benchmarks">
    <list>
      <item>Delivery rate: good 95%+, great 99%+. Below 90% means deliverability problem — stop and fix infrastructure before continuing.</item>
      <item>Open rate: good 40%+, great 60%+. Below 30% means subject lines or sender name need work.</item>
      <item>Reply rate: good 10%+, great 25%+. Below 5% means personalization or value prop is not landing.</item>
      <item>Meeting booked rate: good 3%+, great 10%+. The final metric that matters.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Real Campaign Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS outreach to marketing managers at e-commerce companies: 500 prospects, personalized on recent company news.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
List: 500 prospects (LinkedIn Sales Nav)
Personalization: Light (company news + pain signal)
Sequence: 5 emails over 3 weeks

Results:
  Open rate: 45%
  Reply rate: 12%
  Meeting rate: 3%
  Customers acquired: 5 ($25K ARR)
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Consulting services outreach to CTOs at Series A startups: 200 prospects, trigger-based (recent funding).</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
List: 200 prospects (Crunchbase)
Trigger: Funding announcements
Personalization: Deep (5 min/email)

Results:
  Open rate: 60%
  Reply rate: 25%
  Meeting rate: 10%
  Clients acquired: 3 ($15K each = $45K)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No personalization — sending the same template to everyone.</description>
      <reason>Reads as spam. Personalization is what distinguishes cold outreach from email blasts. Even batch-level personalization (company name, industry) improves open rates by 20–30%.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Sending from primary domain without warmup.</description>
      <reason>A single spam complaint can blacklist the primary domain, breaking all transactional email (receipts, notifications, support replies).</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
