<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Build vs Buy Decision Framework Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the trade-off-build-vs-buy methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale; the final rule is the skip-this-methodology gate referenced by the decision tree.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-strategic-differentiation-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build MUST be chosen only when the capability creates documented competitive differentiation. Capabilities that competitors can replicate by checkbook MUST default to Buy.</statement>
      <rationale source="Wardley mapping; build/buy classic literature.">Engineering capacity is finite; spending it on commodity capability sacrifices the differentiating roadmap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-three-year-tco" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision MUST compute 3-year TCO for Build, Buy, and Hybrid. TCO MUST include engineering, maintenance (20-30% of build / yr), infra, integration, training, support, and exit cost.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gartner TCO playbooks; SaaS-vs-build studies.">1-year TCO usually favours Buy; 3-year often shifts; without modelling, the dominant cost is invisible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-vendor-exit-plan-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Buy / Hybrid decisions MUST include an exit plan: data export format + cadence, contract clauses for early termination, alternative provider list. Lock-in without exit plan is a defect.</statement>
      <rationale source="SaaS exit-cost case studies.">Vendor lock-in shows up at renewal time as a price spike; the only defence is a credible exit option.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-buy-pilot-with-success-criteria" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Buy decisions MUST be preceded by a time-boxed pilot with explicit pass/fail criteria. A 'we tried it and it worked' verbal report MUST NOT substitute.</statement>
      <rationale source="Vendor evaluation case studies.">Sales-demo capability rarely matches operational fit; pilot with criteria catches the gap before the multi-year contract.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-record-rejected-and-trigger" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ADR MUST list rejected options with quantified reasons and a review trigger (vendor price increase &gt; X%, capability becomes commodity, build-cost projection 50% off).</statement>
      <rationale source="MADR practice.">Without rejected + trigger, the next architect cannot reconstruct the reasoning and the decision drifts unchallenged.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When prerequisites hold (capability, forecast, vendor shortlist, build estimate), apply r1 → r5 and emit the ADR.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology design — gate rule.">Order encodes risk: differentiation first, TCO second, exit third, pilot fourth, trigger last.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do NOT use when (a) core IP must be built, (b) commodity must be bought, (c) pre-revenue exploration. Exit with note.</statement>
      <rationale source="Preconditions — skip gate.">Build/buy ceremony where the answer is forced wastes review time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
