<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="workflows Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for workflows as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents drift into implementation during spec phase, solving HOW instead of defining WHAT.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents default to action-oriented thinking. Enforce "WHAT not HOW" strictly in the spec prompt and reject spec documents that contain architectural decisions (those belong in design).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Context window exhaustion mid-phase causes the agent to silently drop requirements, producing incomplete specs or designs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Break large features into sub-specs before execution begins. If a feature requires 60k tokens for the spec alone, split it into two or three smaller spec documents before entering design.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>The "one task, one focus" rule is violated: research ("figure out how") is combined with implementation ("build it") in a single agent call.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents degrade when context is mixed between research and execution. These are two separate tasks with separate quality gates: (1) research phase outputs a design.md; (2) implementation phase executes it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Phase transition confidence scores are self-assessed; an overconfident agent moves to design with an incomplete spec.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add a reviewer sub-agent as a check. The orchestrating agent should invoke a second pass from a fresh agent with prompt "Review this spec for completeness against the acceptance criteria. List gaps." before proceeding.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>`session.md` is written at phase boundaries but crashes occur between phases, leaving inconsistent state (session.md says "in design" but no design.md exists).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always re-read session.md at session start and validate that claimed artifacts exist. If they do not, ask the user whether to roll back to the previous phase or re-run the incomplete phase.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Workflow state stored in markdown files can diverge if multiple agents write concurrently without locking.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use file-based locking (flock) when multiple agents run in parallel. The primary agent acquires a lock on .aidocs/memory/session.md before reading or writing it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
