<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Docker Layer Caching, Image Optimization, and Core Principles">
  <summary>Layer caching strategy, base image selection, CMD vs ENTRYPOINT, image optimization techniques, networking, volume types, and anti-patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Layer Caching Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place dependency installation before source code COPY so dependency layers are cached across code changes.</statement>
      <rationale>Docker invalidates cache for a layer and all subsequent layers when any input changes. Source code changes on every commit; dependency files change rarely. Copying dependencies first preserves the expensive install layer across most builds.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="dockerfile"><![CDATA[
# Invalidates pip install cache on every code change
COPY . .
RUN pip install -r requirements.txt
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="dockerfile"><![CDATA[
# pip install cached; only invalidated when requirements.txt changes
COPY requirements.txt .
RUN pip install --no-cache-dir -r requirements.txt
COPY . .
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Base Image Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use -slim for production balance; use Alpine or Distroless for maximum size reduction and security.</statement>
      <rationale>Full images (python:3.12, ~900MB) include tools unnecessary in production and expand the attack surface. Distroless (~30MB) contains only the runtime and app; no shell means no interactive exploitation path.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Full (python:3.12, ~900MB): development and debugging only</item>
      <item>Slim (python:3.12-slim, ~150MB): production balance — recommended starting point</item>
      <item>Alpine (python:3.12-alpine, ~50MB): minimal size, musl libc (test compatibility)</item>
      <item>Distroless (gcr.io/distroless/python3, ~30MB): maximum security, no shell</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="CMD vs ENTRYPOINT">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always use exec form (JSON array syntax) for CMD and ENTRYPOINT; never shell form in production.</statement>
      <rationale>Shell form runs via /bin/sh -c, which becomes the PID 1 process. The shell does not forward SIGTERM to the child process, causing ungraceful shutdowns and missed graceful-drain windows in Kubernetes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="dockerfile"><![CDATA[
CMD python app.py   # shell form — SIGTERM not forwarded
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="dockerfile"><![CDATA[
ENTRYPOINT ["./docker-entrypoint.sh"]
CMD ["gunicorn", "app:app", "--workers", "4"]
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Multi-Stage Builds">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use multi-stage builds to exclude build-time tooling from the runtime image.</statement>
      <rationale>Build tools (compilers, test runners, dev dependencies) can be 10x the size of the runtime artifact. Multi-stage copies only the compiled binary or production packages into a minimal runtime image, reducing size 50-90% and eliminating build tools from the attack surface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/Dockerfile.python">Multi-stage Python production Dockerfile</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Volume Types">
    <list>
      <item>Named volume (mydata:/app/data): persistent data, managed by Docker, survives container removal</item>
      <item>Bind mount (./src:/app/src): development use, source code or config files from host</item>
      <item>tmpfs (--tmpfs /tmp): temporary data, sensitive in-memory data, not persisted to disk</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using the latest tag for base images or pushed images.</description>
      <reason>latest is mutable — a base image update can change behavior without any change to the Dockerfile. Pin specific versions (python:3.12.7-slim) for reproducible builds.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running containers as root user.</description>
      <reason>Root inside container maps to root on host if namespace isolation is bypassed. Create a non-root user in the Dockerfile and set USER before the final CMD.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Storing secrets in ENV instructions or build ARGs.</description>
      <reason>ENV values are visible in docker inspect, image history, and any process that reads /proc/self/environ. Use Docker secrets, runtime environment injection, or an external vault at container startup.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Missing HEALTHCHECK in production images.</description>
      <reason>Without HEALTHCHECK, orchestrators (Kubernetes, ECS, Swarm) cannot distinguish a running-but-broken container from a healthy one. Containers stuck in crash-loops with no readiness signals cause silent traffic loss.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
