<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-value-and-models" title="Value Analysis and Pricing Models">
  <summary>How to quantify value delivered, apply the value-capture formula, select the right pricing model, and benchmark against competitors.</summary>

  <section title="Value Quantification">
    <rule>
      <statement>Quantify value delivered before looking at competitor prices; anchor on value to prevent pricing in a race to the bottom.</statement>
      <rationale>Competitor-anchored pricing is a commodity strategy. Value-based anchoring reveals how much more or less than the market your product justifies.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the value-capture formula: Max Price = (Value Delivered x Capture Rate) - Switching Cost. Typical capture rate: 10-20% for enabling tools, 30-50% for revenue-generating tools.</statement>
      <rationale>The 10-20% rule is folklore — not a calibrated number. High-leverage revenue-generating tools capture much more. Use the formula as a floor, not a ceiling.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Tool saves 5 hours/week
User time value: $50/hour
Monthly value: 5 x $50 x 4 = $1,000/month
Capture 10%: $100/month max price
Capture 20%: $200/month max price
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <list>
      <item>Time saved — hours per week x hourly rate x 4 weeks.</item>
      <item>Money saved — direct cost reduction per month.</item>
      <item>Money earned — new revenue enabled per month.</item>
      <item>Risk reduced — estimated cost of prevented problems.</item>
      <item>Quality improved — cost of doing this worse without the tool.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Pricing Model Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose the pricing model that scales with the customer's value consumption; subscription for ongoing use, usage-based for variable consumption, one-time for discrete deliverables.</statement>
      <rationale>Misaligned pricing models create friction at renewal. Customers who use a subscription product only once per quarter will churn; usage-based retains them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Subscription — best for sticky ongoing-value tools (most SaaS).</item>
      <item>One-time — best for discrete deliverables: courses, templates, guides.</item>
      <item>Usage-based — best for variable consumption: API calls, storage, seats added.</item>
      <item>Freemium — best for PLG products where network effects or viral spread matters.</item>
      <item>Tiered — best when customer segments have clearly different needs and budgets.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Competitor Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build a pricing matrix for at least 5 competitors with entry, mid, and pro tier prices and feature gating before finalizing your own structure.</statement>
      <rationale>The competitive context sets customer expectations and defines what "normal" looks like in the market. Pricing outside the range requires explicit positioning justification.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Passing a single scraped pricing page snapshot to an analyzer agent and treating it as current.</description>
      <reason>Competitor pricing is A/B tested per visitor and changes frequently. Always pass freshly-scraped HTML; stale data misprices the product.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
