<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Internal Linking Graph Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every internal-link graph spec must enforce. Hard rules; designed to prevent orphans, exact-match-anchor overload, hub bloat, and missing hub backlinks.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-one-hub-per-topic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each topic cluster has exactly 1 hub page. Multiple hub candidates for the same topic are forbidden — pick one and link the others as spokes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Topical-authority research; Google E-E-A-T documentation">Split hubs dilute the cluster's link equity and confuse the crawler about which page should rank for the head term.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-min-four-spokes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each hub has ≥4 spokes (cluster member pages). Clusters with &lt;4 spokes are merged into a sibling cluster or absorbed into the hub itself.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cluster-sizing benchmarks for solo content sites">Hubs with fewer than 4 spokes do not register as topical-authority signals to the crawler; the cluster reads as a one-off page.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-min-two-inbound-per-spoke" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every spoke has ≥2 inbound internal links: 1 from the hub + ≥1 from a sibling spoke in the same cluster.</statement>
      <rationale source="Link-equity flow research">Pages with only the hub as inbound source rank but do not transmit equity to siblings. ≥2 inbound creates lateral equity flow that lifts the whole cluster.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-zero-orphans" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Zero orphan pages: every indexable page has ≥1 inbound internal link from within its assigned cluster.</statement>
      <rationale source="Crawler-budget research; Ahrefs orphan-page audits">Orphan pages with search traffic are silent equity sinks — fix or de-index, never leave floating.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-anchor-diversity-three-forms" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each target URL has ≥3 distinct anchor-text surface forms across its inbound internal links. Exact-match-only anchors are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anchor-text over-optimisation studies; manual-action research">Exact-match-only anchors trigger over-optimisation flags and look algorithmic; diversified anchors read as natural.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-every-spoke-links-hub" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every spoke contains an explicit outbound link to its cluster's hub. The link appears in the body (not only in a sidebar / footer module).</statement>
      <rationale source="In-body link weighting research">Body links carry more weight than chrome links; without an explicit hub link, the cluster lacks the upward equity flow that the topology depends on.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies-If hold and no Skip-If trigger applies, walk the 6-step procedure end-to-end and run the validator before publishing the audit and fix plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory run leaf">Decision-tree run leaf for canonical execution path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the Applies-If preconditions are not met OR any Skip-If disqualifier holds.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory skip leaf">Decision-tree skip leaf for non-applicable inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
