<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026 Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Evaluate Figma's developer handoff (Dev Mode + Variables) as the decisive differentiator for product teams in 2026.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dev Mode and Variables are the primary reason product teams choose Figma over Adobe for UI/UX work; no equivalent exists in Creative Cloud.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not recommend Adobe XD as a current product. Adobe XD was deprecated in 2023; the current Adobe alternatives are Adobe Express and the broader Creative Cloud apps.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents frequently recommend Adobe XD as a current option — this is incorrect; recommending a deprecated product undermines credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Separate "UI product design" (Figma leads) from "marketing asset creation" (Adobe leads) when advising teams with both needs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hybrid is often the right call for teams that do both; recommending one platform for all use cases forces tradeoffs that the hybrid avoids.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quantify Figma library lock-in before recommending migration. Figma component libraries are not portable without significant rebuild.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Component library migration from Figma requires rebuilding every component in the target tool; this cost is systematically underestimated and frequently reverses migration decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit SSO, SCIM provisioning, and data residency requirements before enterprise recommendations. Both platforms differ significantly on these dimensions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Enterprise security and compliance requirements can disqualify a platform entirely regardless of feature score; these must be verified before presenting a recommendation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require human verification of all pricing figures before presenting to finance. Agent-generated cost calculations use list pricing; enterprise pricing is negotiated and can differ by 30 to 50 percent.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Presenting list pricing as enterprise pricing is a frequent cause of stakeholder distrust in tool recommendations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
