<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-platform-comparison" title="Figma vs Adobe: Platform Comparison 2026">
  <summary>Capability comparison, 2026 strategic positioning, key differentiators, and the dominant hybrid pattern.</summary>

  <section title="Strategic Positioning">
    <list>
      <item>Figma — end-to-end product development platform; AI-driven design + prototyping; developer handoff via Dev Mode + Variables; API-first; per-seat pricing</item>
      <item>Adobe Creative Cloud — content creation powerhouse; Firefly generative AI across all apps; enterprise licensing; multimedia production (print, video, illustration)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Differentiators 2026">
    <rule>
      <statement>Evaluate Figma's developer handoff (Dev Mode + Variables) as the decisive differentiator for product teams in 2026.</statement>
      <rationale>Dev Mode and Variables are the primary reason product teams choose Figma over Adobe for UI/UX work; no equivalent exists in Creative Cloud.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not recommend Adobe XD as a current product. Adobe XD was deprecated in 2023; the current Adobe alternatives are Adobe Express and the broader Creative Cloud apps.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents frequently recommend Adobe XD as a current option — this is incorrect; recommending a deprecated product undermines credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Dominant Hybrid Pattern">
    <p>Adobe Firefly for generative imagery + Figma as the collaborative canvas is the dominant hybrid pattern for mid-size product teams doing both UI/UX and marketing asset creation.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate "UI product design" (Figma leads) from "marketing asset creation" (Adobe leads) when advising teams with both needs.</statement>
      <rationale>Hybrid is often the right call for teams that do both; recommending one platform for all use cases forces tradeoffs that the hybrid avoids.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Lock-in Risk">
    <rule>
      <statement>Quantify Figma library lock-in before recommending migration. Figma component libraries are not portable without significant rebuild.</statement>
      <rationale>Component library migration from Figma requires rebuilding every component in the target tool; this cost is systematically underestimated and frequently reverses migration decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
