<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-decision-process" title="Decision Process and Agent Limitations">
  <summary>Weighted matrix methodology, migration risk assessment, and critical agent limitations for platform analysis.</summary>

  <section title="Decision Matrix Methodology">
    <p>Score each platform on weighted criteria: real-time collaboration (25%), AI-assisted UI design (20%), developer handoff (20%), asset/image generation (15%), print/brand production (10%), enterprise security/SSO (10%). Weight allocation must be adjusted per team context before scoring.</p>
    <reference path="templates/decision-matrix.md">Weighted scoring table for Figma vs Adobe across 7 criteria</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Enterprise Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Audit SSO, SCIM provisioning, and data residency requirements before enterprise recommendations. Both platforms differ significantly on these dimensions.</statement>
      <rationale>Enterprise security and compliance requirements can disqualify a platform entirely regardless of feature score; these must be verified before presenting a recommendation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require human verification of all pricing figures before presenting to finance. Agent-generated cost calculations use list pricing; enterprise pricing is negotiated and can differ by 30–50%.</statement>
      <rationale>Presenting list pricing as enterprise pricing is a frequent cause of stakeholder distrust in tool recommendations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent comparison includes Adobe XD as a current product.</description>
      <reason>Adobe XD was deprecated in 2023; correct to Adobe Express or Creative Cloud apps. This is a persistent agent error that must be explicitly checked.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent makes feature parity claims without citing a verifiable source and date.</description>
      <reason>Feature parity claims (e.g., "Figma now matches Adobe in vector tools") are frequently inaccurate by the time an agent is queried; require human fact-check against current product pages.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent underestimates migration effort for large Figma component libraries with complex variable/token structures.</description>
      <reason>Agents have no reliable model of Figma library migration complexity; always require a human estimate based on actual component and variable counts.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Prompt References">
    <reference path="templates/prompt-comparison.txt">Prompt for team-context comparison and weighted recommendation</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-migration.txt">Prompt for structured migration risk report</reference>
  </section>
</text>
