<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026 Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026 as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Recommending a single tool for teams with diverse needs (product designers, marketers, illustrators) and hoping "integrations" will bridge the gaps.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Forcing one tool on a team with both UI/UX and asset creation needs creates friction on both sides — product designers wait on render performance in Adobe, creatives struggle with Figma's simpler vector tools. Hybrid with a clear responsibility split is almost always more productive.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent comparison includes Adobe XD as a current product.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Adobe XD was deprecated in 2023; correct to Adobe Express or Creative Cloud apps. This is a persistent agent error that must be explicitly checked.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent makes feature parity claims without citing a verifiable source and date.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feature parity claims (e.g., "Figma now matches Adobe in vector tools") are frequently inaccurate by the time an agent is queried; require human fact-check against current product pages.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent underestimates migration effort for large Figma component libraries with complex variable/token structures.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents have no reliable model of Figma library migration complexity; always require a human estimate based on actual component and variable counts.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents underestimate the time and cost of hybrid workflow integration (Figma + Adobe + asset pipeline coordination).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hybrid setups sound pragmatic but add integration friction (file naming, export standards, team communication overhead, tool-switching context loss) that agents systematically underestimate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
