<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-trends-and-routing" title="BA Trends 2025-2026 and Routing Index">
  <summary>Six industry BA trends with definitions, critical success factors, skill-priority matrix, and routing map to the sibling methodologies that own actionable workflows for each trend.</summary>

  <section title="Six Key Trends">
    <list>
      <item>AI-enabled decision making: integrating AI/ML outputs into business decisions and requirements processes. Route to: ai-enabled-business-analysis/.</item>
      <item>Outcome-driven strategy: shifting from feature delivery to measurable business outcomes and OKRs. Route to: strategy-methods/, strategy-analysis/.</item>
      <item>Responsible innovation: ethical frameworks, bias detection, and governance for AI-driven products. Route to: modern-ba-framework/, ba-governance/.</item>
      <item>Operational resilience: continuity planning, failure-mode analysis, and resilience by design. Route to: solution-assessment/, ba-planning/.</item>
      <item>Digital trust: data privacy, security requirements, and stakeholder trust as explicit BA concerns. Route to: ba-governance/, requirements-validation/.</item>
      <item>Sustainability integration: ESG requirements and sustainability metrics as first-class BA artifacts. Route to: strategy-methods/, modern-ba-framework/.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Critical Success Factors">
    <list>
      <item>Data Quality: 60% of AI projects fail due to poor data — validate data sources before requirements are written.</item>
      <item>Business Process Clarity: 95% of enterprise AI fails without solid process documentation.</item>
      <item>Stakeholder Alignment: critical for adoption and value realization.</item>
      <item>Continuous Learning: technology evolution requires ongoing upskilling across all six trend areas.</item>
      <item>Ethical Framework: trust and governance are strategic differentiators, not compliance overhead.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Skill Priority Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat this matrix as a routing aid only; for actionable skill development, go to the methodology linked under each trend.</statement>
      <rationale>Skill priorities are contextual; the matrix tells you where to start, not what to do. Each trend maps to a dedicated methodology with full content.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>AI/ML Literacy — Critical, immediate. Route to: ai-enabled-business-analysis/.</item>
      <item>Data Analytics — High, immediate. Route to: data-driven-requirements/.</item>
      <item>Agile/Enterprise Agile Framework — High, ongoing. Route to: agile-ba-frameworks/.</item>
      <item>Process Mining — Medium, 12 months. Route to: process-mining-automation/.</item>
      <item>Automation Analysis — Medium, 12 months. Route to: process-mining-automation/.</item>
      <item>Strategic Thinking — High, continuous. Route to: strategy-analysis/, strategy-methods/.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../ai-enabled-business-analysis/">AI integration in BA workflows</link>
    <link path="../agile-ba-frameworks/">BA role in Scrum and scaled agile</link>
    <link path="../process-mining-automation/">RPA and intelligent automation</link>
    <link path="../data-driven-requirements/">Evidence-based requirements</link>
    <link path="../modern-ba-framework/">BA Framework updates for 2025-2026</link>
    <link path="../ba-strategic-partnership/">Innovation leadership</link>
  </see-also>
</text>
