<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="trend-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>market-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Identify emerging market trends from analyst reports, macro indicators, regulatory pipelines, and incumbent signals. Every numeric market-size row requires source URL and page citation.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>trend-analysis</tag>
      <tag>market-trends</tag>
      <tag>macro-indicators</tag>
      <tag>regulatory-analysis</tag>
      <tag>competitor-signals</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Trend Analysis (Market-Researcher Lens)</title>
    <summary>Trend analysis at the market-researcher level identifies emerging patterns from industry analyst reports, macroeconomic indicators, regulatory pipelines, and incumbent 10-K filings. Every numeric market-size or CAGR row must carry a source URL, publication year, and page number; reject any row that an agent produces from training data without a live citation.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Analyst reports lag real inflection by 12-24 months but still provide the confirming evidence investors require. Regulatory pipeline shifts (EU AI Act, MiCA, DSA) reshape market structure before any revenue KPI moves. 10-K risk-factor diffs signal incumbent fear before earnings. Without a structured citation-enforcement rule, LLMs fabricate CAGR numbers with high confidence. This is the highest-confidence/lowest-grounding sentence pattern in research automation.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-investment or vertical-selection for regulated categories (fintech, health, crypto, AI infra) where the policy clock dominates the product clock</item>
        <item>Annual strategic planning: mapping CAGR + concentration + regulatory pipeline against a 3-year revenue plan</item>
        <item>M&amp;A or partnership scan: spotting that an incumbent's moat is eroding because a rule is opening the market</item>
        <item>Re-pricing an existing offer after a macro shift (rates, FX, labour cost) moves customer willingness-to-pay</item>
        <item>Investor or board memo: produces the "market context" slide with cited analyst rows, not vibes</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure dev-tool or open-source category trends - the researcher variant (HN/PH/GitHub signals) is faster and cheaper</item>
        <item>Day-to-day content topic ranking - analyst-report cadence is quarterly, not weekly</item>
        <item>Pre-revenue idea screening - at idea stage, customer interviews beat IDC reports</item>
        <item>Narrow local-language B2B niches - Gartner/Forrester rarely cover segments below $500M outside US/EU</item>
        <item>When the goal is "find the next viral product" - analyst reports are explicitly lagging signals</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="trend-categories">
      <list>
        <item>Fad: weeks to months duration; no structural driver; avoid building a business on it</item>
        <item>Trend: 2-5 year window; structural driver exists (technology, demographics, regulation); the solopreneur sweet spot</item>
        <item>Megatrend: decade-scale; high certainty but slow to monetize; entry point is a specific sub-trend within it</item>
        <item>Shift: permanent structural change; treat as the new baseline, not an opportunity in itself</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="adoption-curve-stages">
      <p>Adoption curve stages and optimal entry timing:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Innovators: define the category; too early - no market exists yet, education cost dominates</item>
        <item>Early Adopters: high margins but you educate the market for competitors; viable if you have a distribution advantage</item>
        <item>Early Mainstream (optimal entry): market aware, solutions emerging, growth inflecting - enter here</item>
        <item>Late Mainstream: volume available but commoditization accelerating; viable only with cost or distribution moat</item>
        <item>Decline: shrinking market; enter only if you are serving a niche/legacy segment deliberately</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Require a quantitative anchor for any "Early Mainstream" claim: category spend at top 3 players, named buyer logos, or revenue data. Reject the label if only qualitative signals support it.</statement>
        <rationale>"Early Majority" labels are subjective and unfalsifiable without quantitative anchors. The same trend can look "early" or "late" depending on the analyst's framing and the segment chosen.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="steep-analysis-framework">
      <p>The STEEP analysis framework covers five dimensions of trend analysis:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Social: behavior and value shifts (e.g., remote-work normalization, privacy expectations, demographic aging)</item>
        <item>Technology: enabling tech and capability thresholds (e.g., GPT-4 function calling, WebAssembly, CRISPR)</item>
        <item>Economic: financial forces (e.g., interest-rate cycle, labor cost arbitrage, VC dry powder cycles)</item>
        <item>Environmental: sustainability factors and climate risk (e.g., carbon pricing, ESG mandates, supply-chain resilience)</item>
        <item>Political: regulatory landscape and policy pipeline (e.g., EU AI Act, MiCA, GDPR, FTC enforcement trends)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track the regulatory pipeline as a separate axis from STEEP-Political, with explicit stage (proposal / enacted / in-force) and effective date. Proposed rules are not yet constraints; enacted rules with a future effective date are the real driver.</statement>
        <rationale>Regulatory stage confusion is a major agent failure mode. A proposed rule treated as in-force leads to premature product decisions; an enacted rule with a near effective date treated as "proposal" causes compliance misses.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="trend-strength-scoring">
      <p>Five weighted criteria for trend strength scoring (0-5 scale):</p>
      <list>
        <item>Growth rate (25%): measured YoY from 3+ independent sources; reject single-source CAGR</item>
        <item>Adoption curve stage (20%): based on quantitative anchor, not label</item>
        <item>Number of well-funded incumbents (15%): proxy for competitive density</item>
        <item>Investment activity (20%): funding velocity and deal count from Crunchbase/PitchBook</item>
        <item>Personal fit and licensing (20%): skills, capital, and regulatory licence requirements</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply the personal-fit filter BEFORE presenting a high-scoring trend as an opportunity. A regulated category (broker-dealer, healthcare, gambling) with a strength score of 5/5 is unreachable without the required license.</statement>
        <rationale>A high trend-strength score in a licensed category is worthless without the license. Surfacing unlicensed opportunities wastes planning resources and creates false urgency.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="macro-indicator-sources">
      <p>Primary data sources for macro indicators:</p>
      <list>
        <item>FRED (St. Louis Fed): US and global macro series - GDP, CPI, employment, interest rates (fred.stlouisfed.org/docs/api/fred)</item>
        <item>World Bank Open Data: country-level development indicators, GNI, governance (data.worldbank.org)</item>
        <item>Eurostat: EU sector, labour, trade data (ec.europa.eu/eurostat, SDMX API)</item>
        <item>OECD.Stat: cross-country macro and tax series (stats.oecd.org, SDMX)</item>
        <item>IMF WEO and IFS: global macro forecasts and financial stability (imf.org/en/Publications/WEO)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Currency- and inflation-normalise all macro numbers. "$10B to $25B by 2030" in nominal dollars at 4% inflation is $20B in real terms - deflate before comparing across reports.</statement>
        <rationale>Nominal-vs-real confusion inflates growth projections and creates strategy plans calibrated to a market size that does not exist in real purchasing power.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="regulatory-pipeline-sources">
      <p>Primary sources for regulatory pipeline tracking:</p>
      <list>
        <item>EUR-Lex: EU legislation full text and status tracking (eur-lex.europa.eu, CELLAR API)</item>
        <item>US Federal Register: proposed and final rules with full diff (federalregister.gov/developers)</item>
        <item>SEC EDGAR: 10-K and 10-Q filings, risk-factor year-over-year diffs (sec.gov/edgar)</item>
        <item>regulations.gov API: US comment-period dockets</item>
        <item>UK FCA/Companies House: UK rule tracker and corporate filings</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply a two-quarter sanity gap on regulatory shifts. Never pivot the company on a proposed rule; wait for enacted-or-better stage before any resource commitment.</statement>
        <rationale>Proposed rules are withdrawn or substantially modified 30-50% of the time. Building compliance infrastructure or pivoting the product for a proposal that never passes wastes 6-12 months of runway.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="incumbent-momentum-signals">
      <p>Incumbent momentum indicators that signal market direction:</p>
      <list>
        <item>10-K risk factor diffs year-over-year: new language about a trend signals incumbents fear it - strongest cheap signal available</item>
        <item>Earnings-call transcripts: stage indicator is "we are evaluating" to "we are piloting" to "we are deploying at scale" across sequential calls</item>
        <item>LinkedIn hiring delta by role: hiring PMs for "AI features" or "data platform" signals roadmap direction 6-9 months ahead of product launch</item>
        <item>Crunchbase funding velocity: round size and pace changes for competitors in a category</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Require balanced earnings-call sampling: top-3 positive mentions plus top-3 cautionary mentions per call. Do not let the agent surface only bullish quotes.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs default to confirming the briefing document's tone. Mandating cautionary quotes forces the model to surface the risks incumbents acknowledge, not just the opportunities they promote.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="citation-enforcement">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every numeric market-size or CAGR row must carry source URL, publication year, and page number. Reject any row produced from LLM training data without a live citation.</statement>
        <rationale>"The X market is projected to reach $Y by 202Z at A% CAGR" is the highest-confidence/lowest-grounding sentence an LLM produces. Mandatory citation with page numbers is the only practical defense against fabricated analyst statistics.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="opportunity-matrix">
      <p>Two axes: Trend Strength (scored 1-5 per weighted criteria) and Your Ability to Execute (skills, capital, licensing). Optimal entry: high strength plus high execution ability. When trend strength is high but execution ability is low, build the missing skills before entering. Do not enter anyway and learn on the market's time.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="output-schema">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every agent-produced trend report must conform to the JSON schema with mandatory source_url, year, and page fields on every numeric row. Reject outputs missing these fields.</statement>
        <rationale>Schema enforcement is the only scalable way to prevent numeric hallucination across quarterly trend reports. Manual review cannot catch fabricated CAGRs at scale.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Trend report with required schema">
        <code lang="json"><![CDATA[{
  "trend": "AI coding assistants",
  "category": "trend",
  "stage": "early_mainstream",
  "market_size": [{
    "segment": "global developer tooling",
    "tam_usd": 28000000000,
    "cagr_pct": 24.5,
    "year": 2025,
    "source_url": "https://example-analyst.com/report-2025",
    "source_type": "gartner",
    "page": 14,
    "confidence": "med"
  }],
  "macro": [{"indicator": "FEDFUNDS", "value": 5.25, "unit": "%", "yoy_pct": -0.25, "region": "US", "source_url": "https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/FEDFUNDS"}],
  "regulatory": [{"rule_id": "EU-AI-ACT-2024", "jurisdiction": "EU", "stage": "enacted", "effective_date": "2025-08-02", "market_impact": "drag", "source_url": "https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32024R1689"}],
  "score": {"growth": 5, "stage": 4, "concentration": 3, "regulatory_clarity": 3, "macro_tailwind": 4, "fit": 4, "weighted": 3.9},
  "counter_signals": ["Large players (GitHub, OpenAI) have dominant distribution", "Commoditization risk within 18 months"],
  "recommendation": "pursue",
  "next_review": "2025-10-01"
}]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Entering a trend at peak (mainstream) when competition is already intense</description>
        <reason>Late mainstream entry requires a cost or distribution moat that most new entrants lack; the window for margin capture has closed.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Chasing every trend without a personal-fit filter</description>
        <reason>Trend strength without execution ability produces a business in a growing market that the founder cannot competitively serve.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No counter-signals in the trend report</description>
        <reason>A trend report without cooling indicators is a marketing document, not an analysis. At least 3 counter-signals are mandatory in every final report.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent cites a 2022 Gartner Hype Cycle as "this year's report"</description>
        <reason>Without WebFetch, the agent uses training-data reports as if they are current. Always check report_publish_date against current_date; reject reports older than 18 months for stage timing claims.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent fabricates CAGR percentages with two decimal places</description>
        <reason>Treat any CAGR more precise than the nearest 5% as fabricated unless it has a source URL and page number. Real analyst reports round to one decimal.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent sums incompatible TAMs (AI software, AI services, AI hardware) without noting double-counting</description>
        <reason>Require segment definitions to be quoted verbatim from each source before any summing; different reports use different definitional boundaries for "AI market."</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent defaults to US sources and misses EU regulatory pipeline leading indicators</description>
        <reason>Force a jurisdictions list in the orchestrator prompt; EU rules often precede US equivalents by 2-4 years and are the actual market-structure driver.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent extrapolates a 2-point trend ("usage-based went 20% to 38%") as a forward projection</description>
        <reason>Two data points are insufficient for any projection; require at least 8 quarters of data before publishing a trend line and labeling it as directional.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/trend-analysis-report.md" purpose="Full trend analysis report with STEEP analysis, competitive landscape, and opportunity assessment"/>
      <template path="templates/trend-monitoring-dashboard.md" purpose="Monthly trend watch dashboard for tracking multiple trends and logging new signals"/>
      <template path="templates/market-trend-signals.py" purpose="Python collector for macro series (FRED), US regulatory filings (Federal Register), and EU law (EUR-Lex)"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
