<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="user-story-mapping">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-modeling</domain>
    <summary>2D visualization of user stories by journey activities and priority. YAML source enables walking-skeleton releases with Markdown, Mermaid, and Miro outputs.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>user-story-mapping</tag>
      <tag>release-planning</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>user-journey</tag>
      <tag>backlog</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>User Story Mapping</title>
    <summary>Arranges user stories along two dimensions: horizontal (user journey activities and tasks in narrative verb-phrases) and vertical (priority from essential to nice-to-have). The result shows the complete user experience and enables release slicing into a walking skeleton (R1) plus enhancement releases. Map lives as YAML-in-git; renderers produce Markdown, Mermaid, and Miro outputs from that single source.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>A flat backlog has no journey context: release planning is arbitrary, important stories get lost, and the UX is fragmented because no one can see what a complete experience looks like. Story mapping forces a backbone (activities) before stories, and forces release lines (capacity-feasibility checked) before sprint planning. The walking skeleton discipline ensures R1 delivers a degraded-but-complete user journey rather than half of one activity done perfectly.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Flat backlog of 50-500 items with no journey context — agents reverse-engineer activities from titles.</item>
        <item>New product or module kick-off with personas and goals but no scope yet.</item>
        <item>Release planning for a 3-6 month roadmap that needs a walking-skeleton cut with thin-slice defense.</item>
        <item>Migration or replatforming — current journey mapped first, target journey overlaid to surface gaps.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder workshop prep — agents pre-populate a draft map so the workshop debates cuts, not vocabulary.</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing Jira backlog for journey coverage gaps.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-feature work (one screen, one form) — write 3 stories with AC and ship; mapping overhead exceeds value.</item>
        <item>Pure platform / API-only services with no end-user journey — use interface-analysis and use-case-modeling.</item>
        <item>Hard-deadline regulated work where scope is already defined by regulation.</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF zero-to-one where the journey changes weekly — prototype + customer development instead.</item>
        <item>Pure infrastructure / DevOps backlogs — non-user activities do not belong on a story map.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="what-is-user-story-mapping">
      <p>User Story Mapping is a technique for visualizing a product's features and stories along two axes: the horizontal axis represents the user journey flow through the product (activities, organized chronologically as the user would experience them), and the vertical axis represents priority (with the most essential stories at the top — the "walking skeleton" — and progressively less critical enhancements and nice-to-haves below). This 2D arrangement replaces a flat backlog list, making the user's complete experience visible and enabling better release planning through intentional slicing.</p>
      <p>The canonical artifact is map.yaml stored in version control. This YAML file describes the backbone (activities), tasks within each activity, stories within each task, and release boundaries. Agents and renderers can consume map.yaml to produce multiple views: Markdown matrices for stakeholder communication, Mermaid diagrams for visualization, Miro/FigJam JSON for workshop canvases, and Jira sync for issue tracking. The YAML source is the single source of truth; all visual outputs are generated from it.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="map-structure">
      <rule>
        <statement>Horizontal axis: backbone activities in narrative verb-phrases in the user's voice (e.g., "Find a place to stay", "Pay for the order"), ordered by user journey. Vertical axis: priority — walking skeleton stories at the top, enhancements below, nice-to-haves at the bottom.</statement>
        <rationale>Activities expressed as feature names ("Search", "Checkout") produce a 2D Jira view, not a narrative. Verb-phrases force user-voice framing and reveal journey gaps that noun-names hide.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Freeze backbone activities before adding tasks. Backbone changes invalidate everything below. Require explicit unfreeze flag to reorder activities within a planning cycle.</statement>
        <rationale>Activity churn mid-cycle forces task re-grouping and story re-assignment, wasting the most expensive agent work (the release-slicer pass).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Build one map per persona. If two personas share a journey, build two maps and derive a "shared backbone" view as a read-only overlay. Never start with a merged map.</statement>
        <rationale>Multi-persona merged maps produce one-size-fits-none stories. Persona-specific maps surface persona-specific gaps; the shared backbone derives from the union after both are stable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="walking-skeleton-contract">
      <rule>
        <statement>R1 (walking skeleton) must contain at least one story per backbone activity that delivers a complete, degraded-but-functional user journey end-to-end. Absence of any backbone activity in R1 is a contract violation, not a scope cut.</statement>
        <rationale>A release that covers 4 of 5 activities completely but skips one does not let users complete the journey. An incomplete journey produces no learning about the product's core value proposition.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>R1 capacity feasibility must be computed: sum of story points in R1 divided by (team velocity × sprint count) must be at most 1.0. Release-slicer must emit this ratio and refuse to mark R1 valid if it exceeds 1.0.</statement>
        <rationale>Capacity overrun in R1 is the most common cause of walking-skeleton failure. Explicit feasibility evidence prevents optimistic slicing.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag enabler stories (auth, payment infra, telemetry, analytics) explicitly with enabler: true and pin them as dependencies of journey stories, not as journey tasks. Enablers must not count toward backbone coverage.</statement>
        <rationale>Technical enablers are a prerequisite for journey stories but are not user-observable activities. Counting them as coverage masks an incomplete journey.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="slicing-strategy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Prefer vertical slicing (thin end-to-end slice covering all activities) over horizontal slicing (all tasks in one activity). Horizontal-first produces feature-factory releases with no complete journey.</statement>
        <rationale>Vertical slicing maximizes learning per release by enabling end-to-end user tests from day one. Horizontal slicing defers learning until all activities are complete — often much later.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Map-as-code: the canonical artifact is map.yaml in version control. Miro, Markdown tables, and FigJam exports are rendered from map.yaml; they are display surfaces, not sources of truth.</statement>
        <rationale>Visual tools are not queryable, diffable, or validatable. Tool fragmentation produces stale maps within days of a workshop. Code-as-source enables automated drift detection and Jira sync.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="six-agent-pipeline">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pipeline: backlog-ingester (haiku) → persona-resolver (sonnet) → activity-extractor (sonnet) → task-grouper (sonnet) → story-rewriter (sonnet) → release-slicer (opus). Each stage is gated by BA review before the next starts. Jira-syncer (haiku) runs on BA approval after release-slicer.</statement>
        <rationale>Haiku for ingestion and sync (pattern matching, API calls). Sonnet for structured authoring (personas, activities, tasks, stories). Opus only for release slicing — the only cross-cutting reasoning task where capacity, journey completeness, and outcome trade off simultaneously.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every agent emits YAML diffs against the current map.yaml, never full-tree rewrites. BA reviews diffs in PR form. Full rewrites are rejected because they obscure what changed and prevent conflict detection.</statement>
        <rationale>Diff-based updates preserve the BA's ability to review and reject individual changes. Full rewrites conflate unrelated changes and cannot be partially accepted.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Release-slicer (opus) must include backbone-coverage as a hard constraint: R1 must touch at least N-1 backbone activities where N is the total count. Capacity feasibility (story-points sum / velocity × sprints &lt;= 1.0) is also a hard constraint, not a soft guideline.</statement>
        <rationale>Opus optimizes for capacity over journey integrity by default. Hard constraints on backbone coverage and capacity feasibility prevent the two most common release-slicer failures.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="coverage-audit">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run the coverage-auditor (sonnet) weekly: compare story map backbone activities against the current Jira state and emit a coverage matrix with tasks without stories and stories without tasks. Re-digitize workshop output within 24 hours.</statement>
        <rationale>Maps go stale within 2 sprints if not owned. Weekly drift checks catch divergence before it accumulates into a rebuild. Workshop output not digitized within 24 hours is effectively lost.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="map-yaml-schema">
      <p>The map.yaml file contains the following top-level fields: product (identifier), persona (persona ID this map is for), outcome (the measurable product outcome and baseline/target metrics), backbone (array of activities), and releases (array of release definitions with capacity and walkign-skeleton flags). Each backbone activity contains id, verb (the user-voice verb-phrase), and tasks (array). Each task contains id, title, and stories (array). Each story contains id, user (persona), want (the desire), so_that (the rationale), release (R1/R2/R3), size (story points or t-shirt), ac_ref (reference to acceptance-criteria), status (ready/draft), depends_on (array of story IDs), and enabler (boolean flag for technical enablers). The schema enables queries (e.g., "list all R1 stories") and diffs (showing what changed between map runs) that flat backlogs cannot provide.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>One persona per map. If two personas share a journey, build two maps and merge as a derived "shared backbone" view; never start merged. Backbone first, frozen for the cycle — debate and lock activities before adding tasks. Activity churn invalidates everything below.</statement>
        <rationale>Multi-persona maps are unreadable; per-persona maps surface distinct journeys. Freezing the backbone prevents mid-cycle churn that invalidates task grouping and story assignments.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag enablers explicitly (auth, payment infra, telemetry) and pin them as dependencies of journey stories, not as journey tasks themselves. Walking skeleton is a contract — at least one story per backbone activity in R1, all linked to a single outcome metric. If you cannot articulate the outcome impact of R1, R1 is not ready.</statement>
        <rationale>Enablers are prerequisites but not user-observable activities. Walking skeleton is the thinnest slice that validates the product's core value proposition end-to-end. Explicit outcome tying ensures R1 has a measurable learning goal.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Quote-level provenance for story origin: every story carries source: interview/STR-091/q42 or source: ticket/JIRA-1234. Without this, "why is this in here?" debates eat workshops. Vertical slicing greater than horizontal — slicing off "all of activity 5 for R1" is a feature-factory antipattern. Force thin-slice end-to-end first, fatten later.</statement>
        <rationale>Provenance prevents mystery stories in maps. Vertical slicing delivers end-to-end learning faster than horizontal slicing.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Capacity feasibility is part of the slice — release-slicer must emit "story-points sum / velocity × sprints" and reject overrun. Map-as-code: YAML in git, PRs for changes, renderers regenerate Miro/Markdown. The visual surfaces are render targets, never the source of truth.</statement>
        <rationale>Explicit capacity evidence prevents optimistic releases. Code-as-source enables drift detection and prevents tool fragmentation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-run coverage-auditor weekly; workshop output digitized within 24 hours. A stale map is worse than no map. Pair USM with acceptance-criteria (for AC stubs) and sdd-planning (for the spec-to-tasks bridge). Token budget: cap activity-extractor and task-grouper at 80k tokens; release-slicer up to 200k for the full map plus capacity plus dependencies. Anonymize customer quotes before they enter the map repo — once it is in git, it is leaked.</statement>
        <rationale>Weekly audits catch drift before it becomes unmanageable. Same-day digitization captures workshop output while memory is fresh. Paired methodologies provide full coverage from vision to implementation. Token budgets prevent diluted agent focus. Anonymization prevents inadvertent data breaches.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="token-budget">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap activity-extractor and task-grouper at 80k context tokens. Cap release-slicer at 200k context tokens for the full map plus capacity plus dependency graph. If the map exceeds these limits, chunk by sub-journey (call activity) and stitch in a final orchestrator pass.</statement>
        <rationale>Unbounded context in the release-slicer produces diluted attention on capacity and dependency constraints. The 200k cap forces chunking that keeps constraint reasoning sharp.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-integrations">
      <p>CLI tools for story-map automation: jira-cli (ankitpokhrel) reads and writes Jira issues and epics; acli (Atlassian official) provides Jira Cloud CLI; linear-cli reads and syncs Linear backlogs; gh enables map-as-PR via GitHub; miro-api and FigJam REST push maps to workshop canvases; mermaid-cli renders map.yaml → SVG/PNG; pandoc converts Markdown → PDF/DOCX for stakeholders; yq queries and transforms map.yaml; whisper.cpp transcribes workshop recordings; ~/bin/tg-send notifies BAs of stale maps and drift.</p>
      <p>Services and integration platforms: Jira (Atlassian Cloud) is the most common backlog source with REST+acli support; Linear offers cleaner APIs than Jira with GraphQL support; ClickUp, Azure DevOps, and Shortcut support REST endpoints; StoriesOnBoard, Avion, and FeatureMap are purpose-built USM tools with Jira/Trello sync; Easy Agile User Story Maps is a Jira plugin; Miro, FigJam, and Mural are workshop canvases with REST/JSON export; Notion and Confluence persist narrative+tables with weak hierarchy support; Productboard and Aha! feed opportunities/strategy into maps; n8n, Zapier, and Tray enable Jira ↔ map.yaml ↔ Miro round-trips. Cron triggers: Monday 9am coverage-audit (drift check), Wednesday 2pm jira-resync (pull Jira state, refresh statuses), monthly archive stale map branches. Recommended subagents: backlog-ingester (haiku, on demand), persona-resolver (sonnet, per cycle), activity-extractor (sonnet, per cycle), task-grouper (sonnet, per cycle), story-rewriter (sonnet, per story batch), release-slicer (opus, per release planning), dependency-tagger (sonnet, pre-slice), coverage-auditor (sonnet, weekly), jira-syncer (haiku, on approval), map-renderer (haiku, on commit), workshop-prep (sonnet, pre-workshop), walking-skeleton-defender (opus, pre-release).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-gotchas-and-mitigation-strategies">
      <p>Activity-extractor over-fits to feature labels — produces "Search &amp; Browse" instead of "Find a place to stay". Require user-voice verb-phrases; reject noun-only activities. Story-rewriter inflates AC — emits 7 scenarios for a 1-point story. Cap at 3 AC scenarios; rest go to nice_to_have_ac. Persona-resolver collapses personas — "user" becomes the catch-all. Require >=2-feature differential between personas; reject otherwise.</p>
      <p>Release-slicer optimizes for capacity over journey integrity — produces R1 with 87/90 points but missing one backbone activity. Force backbone-coverage as a hard rule. Walking-skeleton inflation — opus pads R1 with "delight" stories. Constrain R1 to "minimum to validate outcome metric"; require removal justification per non-essential story. Dependency-tagger misses cross-stream enablers (auth, billing, analytics). Seed with a dependency taxonomy: auth, payment, infra, data, compliance, telemetry.</p>
      <p>Jira-syncer overwrites manual edits. Always two-way merge with conflict prompt; never blind overwrite. Story duplication — same story under two tasks. Dedup by source-ID + persona before commit. Capacity inflation — agent uses "best-week velocity" instead of rolling-3-sprint average. Force capacity input to be a 90-day median. Backbone reorder churn — agents reorder activities each run. Pin backbone order as immutable for the cycle; require explicit unfreeze: true to reorder.</p>
      <p>Persona drift — new persona spawned for every edge-case story. Persona changes go through persona-resolver + BA approval, not as a story-rewrite side-effect. Workshop seed bias — pre-populated stickies anchor the room. Keep agent-generated seed under 30% of total; tag them so the room knows what to challenge. Outcome amnesia — release-slicer ignores the outcome after first run. Re-pin outcome every prompt; reject slices missing outcome rationale per release. Slicing-strategy collapse — agent picks horizontal slicing because it is easier to articulate. Force "first slice must touch >=N-1 backbone activities".</p>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Activities expressed as feature names ("Search", "Checkout", "Profile") instead of verb-phrases in user voice ("Find a product", "Complete purchase", "Manage account settings").</description>
        <reason>Noun-names produce a 2D Jira view. Verb-phrases reveal journey sequence, user goals, and gaps. The activity-extractor must be constrained to reject noun-only activities.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Vertical priority dimension collapses to ranks 1, 2, 3 with no forcing function. Everything ends up in R1.</description>
        <reason>Without a release line tied to capacity (story-points sum / velocity × sprints &lt;= 1.0), priority is aspirational. The release-slicer must compute and enforce the capacity constraint.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Multi-persona stories merged into one map from the start ("shoppers + admins" in the same backbone).</description>
        <reason>Merged maps produce one-size-fits-none stories. Different personas have different journey sequences and different definitions of "essential". Always start per-persona; merge only after each is stable.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Walking skeleton inflation: R1 padded with "delight" stories because they are "already built".</description>
        <reason>Walking skeleton = minimum to validate the outcome metric. Every non-essential R1 item must provide a removal justification. The opus slicer must request this justification when adding stories beyond the minimum.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Workshop produces 200 stickies; nobody transcribes them within 24 hours. Map exists only on a wall or whiteboard.</description>
        <reason>Untranscribed workshops are effectively lost within days. Digitize to map.yaml within 24 hours; the workshop is prep for the canonical artifact, not the artifact itself.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Story-rewriter emits 7 acceptance-criteria scenarios for a 1-point story.</description>
        <reason>AC inflation bloats test-plan.md and slows CI. Cap at 3 GWT scenarios per story; additional scenarios go to a nice_to_have_ac bucket for later.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Backbone activities reordered by agents on every run, causing downstream task and story churn.</description>
        <reason>Pin backbone order as immutable for the cycle. Require explicit unfreeze flag to reorder. Agents must reject re-orderings that were not explicitly requested.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/map.yaml" purpose="YAML schema for story map: backbone, tasks, stories with release/size/depends_on/enabler fields."/>
      <template path="templates/map_to_jira.py" purpose="Python script syncing map.yaml to Jira: creates epics per activity, stories per leaf, labels per release and task."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-usm.xml" purpose="Structured XML agent prompt covering backbone rules, orphan handling, capacity feasibility, diff-only output."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="acceptance-criteria"/>
      <ref slug="use-case-modeling"/>
      <ref slug="business-process-analysis"/>
      <link href="https://jpattonassociates.com/the-new-backlog/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
