<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-spin-and-challenger" title="SPIN Selling and Challenger Sale Models">
  <summary>SPIN's four question types for uncovering and amplifying pain before presenting a solution, and the Challenger Sale's teach-tailor-take-control model for reshaping how the audience thinks about the problem.</summary>

  <section title="SPIN Selling">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never pitch the solution until Implication questions have made the problem feel urgent to the audience.</statement>
      <rationale>Rackham's research on 35,000 sales calls showed that Implication questions — not product descriptions — are the primary driver of decision-maker movement. Features presented before pain is amplified produce "that's interesting" responses, not decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Situation (S): understand current context — "How do you currently handle X?"</item>
      <item>Problem (P): uncover pain — "What challenges do you face with X?"</item>
      <item>Implication (I): amplify consequences — "What happens if this isn't solved?"</item>
      <item>Need-Payoff (N): lead to solution — "How would it help if you could...?"</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Selling a CI/CD pipeline to an engineering manager.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
S: "How do you currently deploy to production?"
   "Manual process, takes about 2 hours"

P: "What challenges does that create?"
   "Engineers hate it, we deploy less often"

I: "What happens when you deploy less often?"
   "Bigger releases, more bugs, more rollbacks"
   "How much does a rollback cost?"
   "Usually half a day of engineering time"

N: "If deployments took 10 minutes and were automatic,
    how would that change things?"
   "We could deploy daily, catch issues early..."
   → Now present the CI/CD solution
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Challenger Sale">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the Teach-Tailor-Take-Control sequence when the audience does not yet know they have a problem: share a surprising insight, connect it to their situation, then guide the decision.</statement>
      <rationale>Challengers win by reframing the buyer's understanding of their own problem. Mere problem-solvers compete on features; Challengers compete on perspective.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Teach: the reframe insight.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Most teams think more testing slows them down.
But data shows teams with >80% coverage deploy 3x faster.
Here's why: they catch bugs before production,
not during 2am incidents."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Tailor: connect to their context.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Connect the insight to:
- Their industry and company size
- Their specific challenges mentioned in Situation questions
- Their competitor pressures
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Take Control: guide the recommendation.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Based on what you've shared, I'd recommend option A.
Here's why..."

Don't be afraid to disagree if you have better data —
that's what makes it a recommendation, not a proposal.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
