<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-pitch-formats-and-objections" title="Pitch Formats, Audience Targeting, and Objection Handling">
  <summary>Elevator pitch template, audience-specific pitch structures, LAER objection handling model, and the most common pitching antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Elevator Pitch Template">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the 7-line elevator pitch template to ensure every pitch covers: target customer, problem, category, key benefit, competitor contrast, and differentiator.</statement>
      <rationale>Omitting any element produces a pitch that either confuses the audience about who this is for (no target), fails to establish urgency (no problem), or cannot be remembered (no differentiator).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/elevator-pitch.txt">Full elevator pitch template with 7-line and 10-second versions</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Audience-Specific Structures">
    <rule>
      <statement>Match pitch structure to the audience role: executives need business impact first, technical audiences need architecture before benefits, finance needs cost savings with payback period.</statement>
      <rationale>Each role has a primary decision filter. Leading with the wrong frame (e.g., technical architecture to an executive) triggers disengagement before the key point lands.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Executives: Problem (30s) → Solution (30s) → Impact (30s) → Ask (30s)</item>
      <item>Technical: Problem (1m) → Architecture (2m) → Demo (5m) → Integration (2m) → Questions</item>
      <item>Finance: Cost savings → TCO analysis → Payback period → Risk</item>
      <item>Users: Time savings → Ease of use → Daily workflow change</item>
      <item>Security: Compliance → Data protection → Audit trail</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/executive-pitch.txt">Executive pitch template (4 blocks, 30s each)</reference>
    <reference path="templates/one-pager.txt">One-pager template for complex proposals</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="LAER Objection Handling">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use LAER (Listen, Acknowledge, Explore, Respond) for every objection — never skip Explore before Responding.</statement>
      <rationale>Responding before exploring treats the stated objection as the real one. The real objection is usually different: "too expensive" often means "I don't see the ROI" not "we have no budget".</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Objection: "Too expensive"
L: Let them finish.
A: "That's a valid concern."
E: "Compared to what? What's the cost of not solving this?"
R: "Let's calculate the TCO including the current manual cost..."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Objection: "We tried before"
E: "What was different then? What would need to change for it to work now?"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Presentation Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure presentations as: Hook → Problem → Solution → Proof → Call to Action. End with a specific ask, never an open-ended close.</statement>
      <rationale>Presentations without a clear ask produce "let me think about it" deferrals. The ask defines what decision the audience is making.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Leading with the solution before establishing the problem.</description>
    <reason>Audiences who do not yet feel the pain perceive solutions as unnecessary complexity. Pain must be established first.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Asking "Does that make sense?" after presenting.</description>
    <reason>Invites a yes/no response that shuts down dialogue. Use "What questions do you have?" instead.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Using weak modal verbs: "I think we should...", "Maybe we could..."</description>
    <reason>Modality signals uncertainty, which undermines the recommendation. Use "I recommend..." and "Here's the plan..."</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
