<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Content Audit Process Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Content Audit Process application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-full-inventory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The audit MUST cover EVERY content URL in scope. Sampling is rejected (audits exist to find the buried bad pages).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">A sampled audit hides the systemic worst pages, which are precisely the ones the audit exists to find.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-multi-criterion-score" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every item MUST be scored against ≥4 criteria: accuracy, traffic, conversion, freshness (+ optional SEO, brand fit). Single-criterion audits are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Single-criterion (e.g., traffic-only) audits delete legally-required low-traffic pages or keep high-traffic outdated ones.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-six-actions-typed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each item MUST receive exactly one action: Keep | Update | Consolidate | Rewrite | Remove | Review. Untyped actions are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Typed actions map to downstream owners; untyped actions stall.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-impact-effort-priority" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The action plan MUST rank items by impact × effort. Unranked plans are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Without ranking the team executes the easy fixes; the high-impact ones rot.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-legal-hold-honoured" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Items under legal hold MUST be tagged and excluded from Remove actions. Removing legal-hold content is a hard fail.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Removing legal-hold content is a regulatory exposure; the tag must prevent the action.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
