<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Content Audit — Real Findings Examples">
  <summary>Concrete audit findings for blog and help center content, demonstrating action assignment logic.</summary>

  <section title="Blog Audit Finding">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Finding: 40% of blog posts are 3+ years old. Screenshots show old UI, pricing information is outdated, links are broken. Action: Update top 20 posts by traffic; archive low-traffic posts over 3 years old. Reasoning: High-traffic old posts are worth updating (Update); low-traffic old posts have no recovery path (Remove).</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Marking all old posts as Remove without checking traffic.</description>
      <reason>High-traffic posts that rank well in search may still drive significant value despite age. Removing them loses that value; updating recovers it.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Help Center Audit Finding">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Finding: 15 articles cover similar topics with conflicting answers. Issues: user confusion, SEO cannibalization between pages, maintenance overhead. Action: Consolidate into 5 comprehensive guides, redirect the 10 removed URLs. Reasoning: Overlapping coverage with conflicting information is the textbook Consolidate case.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Assigning Update to all 15 duplicate articles individually.</description>
      <reason>Updating duplicates preserves the fragmentation and SEO cannibalization; consolidation is the correct action when multiple pieces cover the same topic.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Action Decision Logic">
    <rule>
      <statement>When two or more content items cover the same topic, assign Consolidate — not Update — to all of them, then create a single canonical piece.</statement>
      <rationale>Updating duplicates separately leaves the duplication problem intact and increases maintenance burden.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign Remove only when the content has no recovery path: topic is obsolete, traffic is negligible, and no redirect target exists.</statement>
      <rationale>Premature removal of low-traffic content that covers unique topics removes search entry points without benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
