<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cloud Run Vpc Access Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for the cloud-run-vpc-access methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale + concrete remediation hook.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="use-connector-or-direct-egress" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reach private resources via either a Serverless VPC Access connector (gen1) or direct VPC egress (gen2). Pick exactly one — do not mix.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Run VPC docs">Mixing connector and direct egress creates undefined routing precedence and intermittent failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="least-privileged-egress-setting" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set `--vpc-egress=private-ranges-only` whenever the service only needs to reach private CIDRs; reserve `all-traffic` for services that also need internet egress through VPC.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Run VPC docs">`all-traffic` routes every packet through VPC NAT, inflating cost and pulling internet traffic through customer firewalls unnecessarily.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="connector-subnet-sized" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Serverless VPC Access connectors MUST be sized with min/max instances appropriate to throughput; the connector subnet must be a dedicated `/28`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Connector sizing docs">Undersized connectors throttle egress and silently degrade tail latency; shared subnets risk IP exhaustion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ingress-internal-when-private" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Internal-only services MUST set `--ingress=internal` (or `internal-and-cloud-load-balancing`) to block public traffic at the platform level.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Run ingress docs">Relying on IAM alone leaves a publicly reachable endpoint that can be probed; ingress=internal removes the attack surface entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="connector-shared-across-services" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Multiple Cloud Run services in the same region MAY share a single connector; do not create a connector per service.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Run VPC scaling docs">Per-service connectors waste IP space and quota; sharing is the supported pattern when throughput requirements stay within the connector's capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the input fails ALL "Applies If" preconditions or matches ANY "Skip If" disqualifier, do not apply this methodology — route the task to the adjacent sibling instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Even flat checklists need an explicit skip leaf in the decision tree; this rule is the universal terminal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
