<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-strategies" title="Kubernetes Deployment Strategies: Mechanics and Selection Guide">
  <summary>Strategy comparison table, mechanics of each strategy, Argo Rollouts vs native Kubernetes, and progressive delivery workflow.</summary>

  <section title="Strategy Comparison">
    <list>
      <item>Recreate: downtime yes, risk high, complexity low, resource cost low, rollback slow — development/migration only</item>
      <item>Rolling Update: no downtime, risk medium, complexity low, resource medium, rollback medium — standard production default</item>
      <item>Blue-Green: no downtime, risk low, complexity medium, resource high (2x), rollback instant — critical services needing full validation</item>
      <item>Canary: no downtime, risk very low, complexity high, resource medium, rollback instant — high-traffic systems with observability</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Rolling Update Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure maxUnavailable and maxSurge explicitly; never rely on defaults for production services.</statement>
      <rationale>Default values (25% each) may cause too-aggressive rollouts for services with tight SLAs. Conservative settings (maxUnavailable: 1, maxSurge: 2) ensure only one pod is unavailable at a time while allowing faster rollout.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
strategy:
  type: RollingUpdate
  rollingUpdate:
    maxUnavailable: 1    # conservative — only 1 pod unavailable at once
    maxSurge: 2          # 2 extra pods during rollout for speed
revisionHistoryLimit: 5  # keep 5 revisions for rollback
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Blue-Green with Argo Rollouts">
    <p>Blue-Green requires Argo Rollouts controller. Two services: activeService (production traffic) and previewService (test traffic). Promotion switches traffic instantly.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
spec:
  strategy:
    blueGreen:
      activeService: myapp-active
      previewService: myapp-preview
      autoPromotionEnabled: false   # require manual promotion for production
      scaleDownDelaySeconds: 30     # keep blue running 30s after switch for in-flight requests
      prePromotionAnalysis:         # optional: run analysis before promoting
        templates:
          - templateName: success-rate
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Canary with Metric-Driven Promotion">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always configure an AnalysisTemplate with concrete success thresholds before enabling automated canary promotion.</statement>
      <rationale>Canary without analysis is just a slow rolling update. The value comes from metric-gated promotion: if error rate exceeds threshold during any step, the rollout automatically aborts and reverts to stable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Canary steps: 5% for 5min → 25% for 10min → 50% for 15min → 100%. Analysis at each pause checks error rate and p99 latency.</note>
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
spec:
  strategy:
    canary:
      steps:
        - setWeight: 5
        - pause: {duration: 5m}
        - analysis:
            templates: [{templateName: success-rate}]
        - setWeight: 25
        - pause: {duration: 10m}
        - setWeight: 50
        - pause: {duration: 15m}
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Argo Rollouts vs Native Kubernetes">
    <list>
      <item>Native K8s: Rolling Update built-in, Blue-Green and Canary require manual scripting, no automated analysis</item>
      <item>Argo Rollouts: Blue-Green and Canary built-in, traffic management via Ingress or service mesh, automated Prometheus/Datadog analysis, metric-driven rollback, deep ArgoCD integration</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Tool Selection Guide">
    <list>
      <item>Simple apps, low traffic: Rolling Update with native K8s Deployment</item>
      <item>Critical apps needing instant rollback: Blue-Green with Argo Rollouts</item>
      <item>High-traffic, metric-driven: Canary with Argo Rollouts + Istio or NGINX</item>
      <item>GitOps workflow: any strategy with Argo Rollouts + Argo CD</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
