<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Risk Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the risk-management methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="track-opportunities-too" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track opportunities, not just threats; use symmetric response strategies (Exploit/Enhance/Share/Accept).</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBoK 7 risk domain">Risk registers listing only threats miss half the picture; an unmanaged opportunity is a threat of lost value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-owner-with-trigger" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every risk must have a named owner (a person, not 'the team') and explicit observable triggers.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI risk standard">Risks without owners are ignored; triggers convert abstract risks into actionable events.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="contingency-for-accept" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set contingency reserve = sum(EMV) of all Accepted threats; management reserve sits on top for unknown-unknowns.</statement>
      <rationale source="Risk-budgeting practice">Accepting a risk without provisioning is hoping, not managing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="source-quote-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each agent-identified risk must cite a specific quoted source from inputs; reject generic risks without evidence.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — risk-register quality audits">LLMs generate generic risks ('scope creep', 'team turnover') without grounding.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="weekly-15min-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Risk reviews are short (15 min) and frequent (weekly), not 2-hour quarterly drills.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field experience">Quarterly reviews find risks that have already become crises; weekly catches drift while affordable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="convert-materialised-to-issue" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a risk materialises, convert it to an Issue and remove it from the register.</statement>
      <rationale source="Register hygiene">Keeping it in both places inflates risk count and confuses status reporting.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Trivial internal task (1 person, under 1 week, no external dependency)</item>
      <item>Pure agile teams with strong incremental delivery — use 'top 5' sticky list</item>
      <item>Crisis already in progress — switch to incident response; add lessons after</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
