<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-risk-framework" title="Risk Management Framework">
  <summary>Risk types, four-step identification-to-monitoring process, threat and opportunity response strategies, and EMV-based contingency planning.</summary>

  <section title="Risk Types">
    <list>
      <item>Threat — negative risk; probability × impact = potential loss</item>
      <item>Opportunity — positive risk; probability × impact = potential gain; use Exploit/Enhance/Share/Accept strategies</item>
      <item>Known risk — identified and plannable; goes in the register with a response</item>
      <item>Unknown-unknown — cannot predict; rely on resilience design, not prevention</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track opportunities, not just threats; use symmetric response strategies (Exploit/Enhance/Share/Accept).</statement>
      <rationale>Risk registers that list only threats miss half the picture. Opportunities require active responses to capture; an unmanaged opportunity is a threat of lost value.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Four-Step Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Identify: brainstorm from charter + WBS + lessons learned + risk categories (technical, external, organizational, project); each risk needs a quoted source from inputs</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Analyze: qualitative P×I matrix for all; quantitative EMV = P_numeric × impact_USD for risks that will feed contingency reserves</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Plan Responses: assign a named owner and observable triggers; select response strategy; fund Accept responses with contingency</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Monitor: weekly 15-minute review; compare register vs current status reports; convert materialized risks to Issues and remove from register</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every risk must have a named owner (a person, not "the team") and explicit observable triggers.</statement>
      <rationale>Risks without owners are ignored. Triggers convert abstract risks into actionable events — without them, the risk stays abstract until it is already a crisis.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Response Strategies">
    <p>Threat strategies:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Avoid — eliminate the risk source (e.g., remove unproven technology from scope)</item>
      <item>Transfer — shift to third party via insurance, fixed-price contract, or warranty</item>
      <item>Mitigate — reduce probability or impact (e.g., cross-train backup, add automated tests)</item>
      <item>Accept — acknowledge and provision contingency equal to EMV; never accept without a budget line</item>
    </list>
    <p>Opportunity strategies:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Exploit — ensure the opportunity materializes (e.g., assign dedicated resource)</item>
      <item>Enhance — increase probability or impact (e.g., early market seeding)</item>
      <item>Share — partner with another party to maximize capture</item>
      <item>Accept — take it if it comes without special action</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set contingency reserve = sum(EMV) of all Accepted threats; management reserve sits on top for unknown-unknowns.</statement>
      <rationale>Accepting a risk without provisioning a contingency budget is hoping, not managing. EMV-based reserves give the sponsor a defensible number for the risk budget line.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/risk-register.md">Risk register table with all required fields</reference>
    <reference path="templates/risk-response-plan.md">Individual risk response plan template</reference>
    <reference path="scripts/risk-score.py">Deterministic P×I scorer and EMV calculator from risks.yaml</reference>
  </section>
</text>
