<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-risk-antipatterns" title="Risk Management Antipatterns and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Common risk register failures, misuse of response strategies, and agent-specific pitfalls in automated risk identification and scoring.</summary>

  <section title="Register Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Stale risk register never reviewed after creation.</description>
      <reason>A 6-month-old register is worse than none because it creates false confidence. Risks have resolved, new risks have emerged, and the register now misleads rather than informs. Weekly 15-minute reviews are mandatory.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using "Accept" response without a contingency budget line.</description>
      <reason>"Accept" is the most-abused response: it lets teams skip planning while pretending to manage the risk. Accepting without provisioning a reserve is hoping. Every Accept must map to a specific contingency amount equal to its EMV.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Double-tracking materialized risks as both a Risk and an Issue.</description>
      <reason>When a risk materializes, convert it to an Issue and remove it from the register. Keeping it in both places inflates the risk count and confuses status reporting.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting risk reviews as 2-hour quarterly events instead of 15-minute weekly sessions.</description>
      <reason>Quarterly reviews find risks that have already become crises. Weekly 15-minute reviews catch drift while corrective action is still affordable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require each agent-identified risk to cite a specific quoted source from inputs; reject generic risks without evidence.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs generate generic risks ("scope creep", "team turnover") without grounding in project specifics. Requiring a source quote forces actual analysis of the charter, WBS, and vendor list.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Probability ratings cluster around "Medium" — too safe; require justification per rating ("M because vendor missed last 2 SLAs in Q1")</item>
      <item>Numerical EMV implies false precision; always print confidence interval or skip dollar values in agent output if inputs lack dollar-denominated impact estimates</item>
      <item>Agent may merge distinct risks into one (loses owner clarity) or over-split one into many (inflates register); constrain via target count (8-15 risks for a 6-month project)</item>
      <item>Auto-closing risks based on absence of mention in status reports is wrong — no-mention is not evidence of resolution; require an explicit "closed by [person] on [date]" field</item>
      <item>Do not let an agent tag a risk as Accept without a budget/contingency line item — it must propose a specific dollar amount or token-effort equivalent</item>
      <item>Pair risk identification with Change Control: any approved change request triggers a risk re-rating pass</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
