<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="writing-specifications">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd-planning</domain>
    <summary>A 9-phase structured process for writing spec.md with SMART functional requirements, user stories, acceptance criteria, and explicit scope boundaries to prevent scope creep and establish a single written source of truth before design begins.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>specification</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>sdd</tag>
      <tag>smart-criteria</tag>
      <tag>user-stories</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>sdd</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Writing Specifications</title>

    <summary>A structured 9-phase process for writing spec.md — the document that answers "WHAT are we building and WHY?" before design or implementation begins. Covers problem analysis, user personas, user story mapping, SMART functional and non-functional requirements, Given-When-Then acceptance criteria, and explicit scope boundaries.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Projects fail when teams build the wrong thing because requirements are vague, stakeholders have different mental models, or there is no single written source of truth. A spec written with SMART criteria, FR traceability, and testable ACs reduces this risk: every FR has an ID, every AC has a pass/fail test, and out-of-scope items are explicitly named — preventing scope creep during design.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Feature is new and requirements have not been written down anywhere.</item>
        <item>Existing feature needs scope expansion and the current spec is absent or too vague to drive design.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder and developer have different mental models of what the feature does.</item>
        <item>Requirements exist informally (Slack messages, verbal agreements) and need to be formalized.</item>
        <item>Constitution is new and needs to capture tech decisions before development begins.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Bug report with a clear reproduction path — write a task directly, not a spec.</item>
        <item>Infrastructure change (server config, deployment pipeline) with no user-visible behavior.</item>
        <item>Feature already has an approved spec — open and amend it rather than rewriting from scratch.</item>
        <item>Experiment/spike where the output will determine whether to proceed at all.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="document-hierarchy">
      <p>A specification answers WHAT and WHY. A design answers HOW. An implementation plan answers IN WHAT ORDER. Never mix concerns across documents.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>A specification answers WHAT and WHY. A design answers HOW. An implementation plan answers IN WHAT ORDER. Never mix concerns across documents.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing implementation details into spec.md causes the spec to become stale when the design changes, and breaks the clean hand-off between phases.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Document responsibility table">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Specification  → WHAT and WHY?       → Requirements, user stories, acceptance criteria
Design         → HOW?                → Architecture, file structure, API contracts
Impl Plan      → IN WHAT ORDER?      → Tasks, dependencies, token estimates
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="nine-phase-writing-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Load constitution.md and completed feature specs BEFORE writing any requirements.</statement>
        <rationale>Requirements written without constitution context violate tech stack constraints. Reviewing done/ features surfaces patterns and prevents re-inventing resolved problems.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Phase 1: Load context — read constitution.md, features/done/, related specs in todo/in-progress/</item>
        <item>Phase 2: Problem analysis — define WHO, WHAT, WHY, IMPACT using SMART criteria</item>
        <item>Phase 3: User research — define minimum 2 personas with role, goal, pain points, context</item>
        <item>Phase 4: User story mapping — backbone, walking skeleton (MVP), phase 2 stories</item>
        <item>Phase 5: Use cases — for multi-step workflows, multiple actors, or complex validations</item>
        <item>Phase 6: Functional requirements — SMART requirements with MoSCoW, FR-X IDs, US traceability</item>
        <item>Phase 7: Non-functional requirements — measurable targets (no vague words)</item>
        <item>Phase 8: Acceptance criteria — Given-When-Then covering all scenarios with specific values</item>
        <item>Phase 9: Scope definition — explicitly list what IS and IS NOT in scope</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="smart-requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every functional requirement must satisfy SMART: Specific (one interpretation), Measurable (verifiable), Achievable (technically feasible), Relevant (traces to user need), and have a testable pass/fail criterion.</statement>
        <rationale>Vague requirements cannot be tested. "System should be fast" is untestable; "response time &lt; 500ms p95" is not.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad" title="Vague requirement — fails SMART">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[FR-001: System should be fast and handle user requests efficiently.]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="SMART requirement">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[FR-001: System SHALL return API responses within 500ms p95 under 100 concurrent users. [Must]]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="user-story-format">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every user story must include the "so that [benefit]" clause. A story without a benefit clause hides the value and cannot be prioritized.</statement>
        <rationale>The benefit clause is where business value lives. Stories without it get implemented based on assumed value, which is frequently wrong.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad" title="Missing benefit clause">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[US-001: As a user, I want to log in with my email.]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Complete user story">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[US-001: As a registered user, I want to log in with my email and password, so that I can access my personal account and saved data.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>"System should be fast" as a non-functional requirement.</description>
        <reason>Not measurable. Rewrite as: "Response time &lt; 500ms p95".</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No user personas defined.</description>
        <reason>Requirements written without personas are not grounded in user context and tend to describe system behavior rather than user needs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Requirements without FR-X IDs.</description>
        <reason>Unidentified requirements cannot be traced to design decisions or acceptance criteria.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Out of Scope section is empty or lists only obvious exclusions.</description>
        <reason>Out of Scope must name specific features that were discussed and explicitly rejected; generic exclusions do not prevent scope creep.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>AC items are not testable: "system should handle errors gracefully".</description>
        <reason>Acceptance criteria without Given-When-Then and specific values cannot be verified by a test.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="phase-by-phase-checklist">
      <section name="phase-1-load-context">
        <list>
          <item>Read .aidocs/constitution.md — project principles and tech stack</item>
          <item>Review features/done/ for completed feature patterns</item>
          <item>Identify related specs in features/todo/ or features/in-progress/</item>
          <item>Extract tech stack constraints and code standards</item>
          <item>Note existing patterns and architecture decisions</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-2-problem-analysis">
        <list>
          <item>Define problem with WHO/WHAT/WHY/IMPACT clearly</item>
          <item>Apply SMART criteria: Specific, Measurable, Achievable, Relevant, Time-bound</item>
          <item>Create business value statement linking user need to impact</item>
          <item>Define success metric that measures outcome</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-3-user-research">
        <list>
          <item>Define minimum 2 user personas with role, goal, pain points, context</item>
          <item>Map user activities and create story mapping backbone</item>
          <item>Identify walking skeleton (MVP) vs phase 2 stories</item>
          <item>Validate personas with stakeholders</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-4-requirements-definition">
        <list>
          <item>Write user stories in "As a...I want...so that" format</item>
          <item>Ensure each story follows INVEST principle</item>
          <item>Create functional requirements (FR-X) with MoSCoW prioritization</item>
          <item>Define non-functional requirements (NFR-X) with specific numeric targets</item>
          <item>Ensure all requirements are SMART and testable</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-5-acceptance-criteria">
        <list>
          <item>Write Given-When-Then scenarios covering happy path</item>
          <item>Write error handling scenarios</item>
          <item>Write boundary condition scenarios</item>
          <item>Use specific values — not "valid" or "fast"</item>
          <item>Ensure criteria are testable with pass/fail verification</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-6-scope-definition">
        <list>
          <item>Explicitly list what IS in scope</item>
          <item>Explicitly list what is NOT in scope with reason and timeline</item>
          <item>Define assumptions about user behavior and system constraints</item>
          <item>Identify dependencies on other features or systems</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-7-quality-gates">
        <list>
          <item>Verify all sections are complete (problem, personas, stories, FR, NFR, AC, scope)</item>
          <item>Check for ambiguous language (good, fast, easy, etc.)</item>
          <item>Validate traceability: each FR traces to a user story</item>
          <item>Confirm requirements are SMART and not solution-focused</item>
          <item>Ensure out-of-scope section names specific rejected features</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="phase-8-review-and-approval">
        <rule>
          <statement>Spec must reach Approved status before design begins. Never hand a Draft spec to an executor agent.</statement>
          <rationale>Design decisions made against unapproved requirements cause rework when requirements change during review.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Present specification to stakeholders for feedback</item>
          <item>Resolve open questions and gaps</item>
          <item>Update spec based on feedback</item>
          <item>Obtain formal approval before moving to design phase</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/bootstrap-feature.sh" purpose="Shell script to create the .aidocs/features/backlog/NN-slug/ directory and seed a blank spec.md."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.mountaingoatsoftware.com/books/user-stories-applied"/>
      <link href="https://gojko.net/books/specification-by-example/"/>
      <link href="https://www.ireb.org/en/cpre/fundamentals/"/>
      <link href="https://jtbd.info/"/>
      <link href="https://www.productplan.com/learn/product-requirements-document/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
