<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Project Closure Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed in real deployments. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern id="done-state-as-acceptance" severity="high">
      <symptom>Agent marks closure complete based on issue-tracker 'Done' state alone.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Field experience">'Done' is self-reported by the team; acceptance requires a signed artefact from the accepting authority — a different party with independent verification.</root-cause>
      <fix>Block closure until acceptance signature is captured with timestamp and signatory.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="agent-generated-lessons" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Agent generates lessons learned from ticket history and meeting minutes without human contribution.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Field experience">Agent-generated lessons are pattern-matched platitudes from training data, not project-specific facts.</root-cause>
      <fix>Require quoted contributions attributed to named participants; reject empty lessons files.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="auto-zeroed-final-cost" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Agent sets final cost to zero because no open invoices appear in the system.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Field experience">Net-60 vendor invoices arrive after project close; final cost must be flagged as 'pending invoices' until the invoice window closes.</root-cause>
      <fix>Mark final cost as provisional; close after the contractual invoice window.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="uncontrolled-closure-packet" severity="high">
      <symptom>Closure packet published without access control; contains salaries, vendor rates, customer data.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Field experience">Closure packets contain sensitive data routinely; default publication leaks PII.</root-cause>
      <fix>Apply project-charter access tier to closure packet; redact PII before broad distribution.</fix>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
