<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Interview Hot-Take Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Interview Hot-Take Template application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="thirty-minute-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hot-take MUST be written within 30 minutes of session end. Captures past the window are flagged 'delayed' and dropped one confidence band.</statement>
      <rationale source="Memory-decay research">Episodic memory of conversation degrades sharply past 30 minutes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="five-bullet-shape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hot-take is exactly 5 bullets: surprise / contradiction / quote / open question / next-step. Free-form prose is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Standardisation discipline">Fixed shape makes diff-able and feeds the downstream card pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="verbatim-strongest-quote" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The quote bullet is a verbatim line, with interviewee handle and timestamp. Paraphrases are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Verbatim-evidence practice">Paraphrases drift over time; verbatim survives.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-next-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The next-step bullet names a single action the interviewer commits to within 48 hours.</statement>
      <rationale source="GTD next-action discipline">Without named next-step the interview produces no downstream artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="linked-to-transcript" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hot-take carries a path/URL to the transcript or audio. Hot-takes without source links are dropped at synthesis.</statement>
      <rationale source="Traceability discipline">Untraceable hot-takes cannot be cross-checked or aggregated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
