<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-scrum-mapping" title="BA Activities in Scrum">
  <summary>BA activities per Scrum phase, Sprint 0 responsibilities, and ad-hoc clarification response-time target.</summary>

  <section title="Scrum Phase Mapping">
    <rule>
      <statement>BA activities must be distributed across all Scrum phases, not concentrated in Sprint 0. Sprint 0 establishes vision, roadmap, and initial backlog; all subsequent ceremonies require BA participation to maintain quality.</statement>
      <rationale>BAs who disappear after Sprint 0 produce an initial backlog that degrades as development teams interpret stories without expert BA support during execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Sprint 0: vision and roadmap facilitation, initial backlog creation from stakeholder sessions, acceptance criteria on the first 5-10 stories</item>
      <item>Backlog Refinement: user story elaboration, acceptance criteria authoring, models and wireframe review, dependency identification with other teams</item>
      <item>Sprint Planning: story clarification, dependency flagging, documenting sprint commitments with acceptance criteria confirmed</item>
      <item>Sprint Execution: ad-hoc clarification (target response under 30 minutes), prototype review, preparing next sprint backlog items</item>
      <item>Sprint Review: validate acceptance criteria are met, capture stakeholder feedback, update backlog with feedback-driven changes</item>
      <item>Retrospective: share BA process improvement observations, identify collaboration gaps between BA and developers or QA</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Ad-Hoc Clarification Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Respond to in-sprint developer or QA clarification requests within 30 minutes during working hours. Unresolved clarifications block development and cause sprint failure or unreviewed implementation decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Blocked developers make implementation decisions unilaterally; a 30-minute response target prevents this without requiring the BA to be on-call continuously.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/sprint-ba-activities.md">Sprint activity checklist for BA</reference>
</text>
