<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-safe-mapping" title="BA in Scaled Agile (SAFe)">
  <summary>SAFe level-to-BA-role mapping, key activities per level, and relevant certifications with market data.</summary>

  <section title="SAFe Level Mapping">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map BA responsibilities to SAFe levels: Team Level (BA acts as Product Owner — user stories, acceptance criteria, backlog management), Program Level (Senior BA / System Architect — domain modeling, feature analysis, cross-team dependency analysis), Large Solution Level (Solution Analyst — cross-ART coordination, capability definition), Portfolio Level (Enterprise BA — portfolio backlog grooming, strategic alignment, business case analysis).</statement>
      <rationale>SAFe does not define a BA role explicitly; without an explicit mapping, BA competencies are either lost (BA has no role) or duplicated (BA and PO both own the same artifacts).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Core BA Responsibilities Across SAFe">
    <list>
      <item>Bridge business and IT: translate business needs to technical requirements at all levels</item>
      <item>Facilitate communication: enable collaboration among stakeholders across ARTs and teams</item>
      <item>Prioritize by value: support value-based feature prioritization using WSJF or RICE at program level</item>
      <item>Define vision and roadmap: support Product Management with strategic direction and capability definition</item>
      <item>Ensure alignment: verify agile delivery aligns with business goals across the program increment</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Certifications">
    <list>
      <item>Agile Analysis Certification (AAC) — IIBA: 71% of BAs practice agile; AAC holders report 16% salary premium over non-certified</item>
      <item>SAFe Agilist (SA) — Scaled Agile: enterprise agile scaling, PI Planning facilitation</item>
      <item>SAFe Product Owner / Product Manager (POPM) — Scaled Agile: backlog management at Team and Program levels</item>
      <item>Certified Product Ownership Analysis (CPOA) — IIBA: product ownership analysis skills for BA-to-PO transition</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
