<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-techniques" title="Agile BA Techniques">
  <summary>Five agile BA techniques with when-to-use guidance: user story mapping, example mapping, story splitting, impact mapping, event storming.</summary>

  <section title="Technique Selection Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select agile BA techniques based on the problem being solved, not the ceremony. User story mapping for release planning and feature prioritization; example mapping for acceptance criteria clarification on a specific story; story splitting for epics that are too large for a sprint; impact mapping for connecting features to business goals; event storming for domain discovery and process modeling.</statement>
      <rationale>Applying a single technique to all BA problems produces mismatched outputs; the technique must fit the question being answered.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Technique Reference">
    <list>
      <item>User Story Mapping: visualize product as a user journey with stories organized by activity; use for release planning, identifying MVP scope, prioritizing by user flow rather than by feature</item>
      <item>Example Mapping: collaborative session (BA + dev + QA) using index cards — rules (yellow), examples (green), questions (red); use to clarify acceptance criteria on specific complex stories before sprint planning</item>
      <item>Story Splitting: decompose epics into implementable stories using 10 patterns (workflow steps, business rule variations, data complexity, interface complexity, performance, operations, test variations, defer system, defer capabilities, simple/complex); use any time a story cannot be completed within one sprint</item>
      <item>Impact Mapping: goal → actors → impacts → deliverables tree structure; use to connect a feature to a business goal and identify which actors must change behavior for the goal to be achieved</item>
      <item>Event Storming: sticky-note workshop discovering domain events (orange), commands (blue), aggregates (yellow), bounded contexts; use for domain discovery when building a new system or onboarding onto a complex existing domain</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
