<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Mobile UX Principles">
  <summary>Mobile-first thinking, mobile context factors, five key design principles, and iOS vs Android platform differences.</summary>

  <section title="Mobile-First Approach">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design for the smallest screen first, identify core content and features, then add enhancements for larger screens.</statement>
      <rationale>Designing for mobile first forces focus on essential content. Scaling down a desktop design produces a cramped, unusable result because mobile has fundamentally different input, attention, and network constraints.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Mobile Context Factors">
    <list>
      <item>Attention: partial attention, frequent interruptions — never rely on sustained focus.</item>
      <item>Time: short sessions, quick tasks — design for task completion in under 60 seconds for core flows.</item>
      <item>Location: variable environments (sun glare, one-handed use, movement).</item>
      <item>Connection: slow or unreliable network — 53% of users abandon if load exceeds 3 seconds.</item>
      <item>Input: touch, sometimes voice — no hover, no right-click, no precision pointer.</item>
      <item>Screen: small and varying sizes with high pixel density.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Five Key Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide exactly one primary action per screen.</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple competing actions force users to make decisions under the cognitive constraints of mobile context (partial attention, glare, movement). One primary action removes this decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Place primary actions in the thumb zone (lower third of screen).</statement>
      <rationale>Reachability for one-handed use is physical. Primary actions placed in the hard-to-reach upper zone increase task abandonment on phones held in the dominant hand.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Focus: one primary action per screen.</item>
      <item>Simplify: reduce choices and steps.</item>
      <item>Speed: fast loading, instant feedback.</item>
      <item>Reachability: important actions in the thumb zone (lower third).</item>
      <item>Context: leverage device capabilities (GPS, camera, biometrics).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Platform Differences">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow platform conventions for navigation, modals, and primary actions — do not port iOS patterns to Android or vice versa.</statement>
      <rationale>Users have strong mental models from their platform. Cross-platform pattern violations produce "feels wrong" friction that is impossible to attribute in usability tests but measurable in task success rates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Navigation: iOS uses bottom tab + back gesture; Android uses bottom nav + system back button.</item>
      <item>Touch targets: iOS minimum 44x44pt; Android minimum 48x48dp; spacing 8px between targets.</item>
      <item>Modals: iOS uses bottom sheets; Android uses full-screen overlays or dialogs.</item>
      <item>Primary actions: iOS right side of screen; Android floating action button.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
