<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-design-rules" title="Mobile Design Rules">
  <summary>Touch target sizing, thumb zone rules, navigation pattern selection, form best practices, gesture guidelines, and accessibility requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Touch Targets">
    <rule>
      <statement>Minimum touch target: 44x44pt (iOS) or 48x48dp (Android). Minimum spacing between targets: 8px. Apply to all interactive elements including links, icons, and checkboxes.</statement>
      <rationale>Human finger pad is 40-60px wide. Targets smaller than 44pt produce 30-50% higher error rates on touch input. Insufficient spacing causes adjacent-target mis-taps even when individual targets meet the minimum size.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="../../../../../../../../../../../skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/mobile-ux-basics/templates/touch-target-audit.js">Playwright script detecting touch targets below threshold at iPhone 13 viewport.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Navigation Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose navigation pattern based on section count: bottom tab bar for 3-5 main sections; hamburger menu only for many infrequently-accessed sections.</statement>
      <rationale>Bottom tab bar is the highest-discoverability mobile navigation pattern. Hamburger menus hide navigation and increase task completion time by 2-3 steps for any navigation action.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Bottom tab bar: 3-5 main sections with roughly equal usage frequency.</item>
      <item>Hamburger menu: many sections where most are rarely accessed.</item>
      <item>Tab bar: 2-5 content types within one section.</item>
      <item>Gesture navigation: supplement to visible controls, never the sole means of navigation.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Forms">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set the correct HTML input type for every form field. Use inputmode and autocomplete attributes to trigger the right keyboard and enable autofill.</statement>
      <rationale>Wrong keyboard type (e.g., alphabetic for phone number) is the highest-leverage 5-minute mobile fix. Users must dismiss and reopen keyboards when the wrong type appears, which inflates form abandonment by 10-20%.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Minimize required fields to the absolute minimum for the task.</item>
      <item>Show progress for multi-step forms.</item>
      <item>Enable autofill via correct autocomplete attributes.</item>
      <item>Show/hide password toggle on password fields.</item>
      <item>Clear, inline error messages immediately after invalid input.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Gestures">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always provide a visible alternative for every gesture. Never rely on a gesture as the sole way to trigger an action.</statement>
      <rationale>Gestures are invisible affordances. Users who do not discover them fall back to alternative paths or abandon the task. Discoverability requires a visible control paired with an optional gesture shortcut.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Tap: select or activate — always the primary interaction.</item>
      <item>Swipe horizontal: navigate or reveal actions — pair with visible navigation controls.</item>
      <item>Pull down: refresh — pair with a visible refresh button.</item>
      <item>Pinch: zoom — provide visible zoom controls for accessibility.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility">
    <rule>
      <statement>Respect prefers-reduced-motion media query on all animations. Flag components missing this handling in code review.</statement>
      <rationale>Vestibular disorders affect 35% of adults over 40. Animations that ignore reduced-motion preferences cause dizziness and nausea, making the product unusable for a significant subset of mobile users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Touch targets: 44x44pt minimum (doubles as accessibility requirement).</item>
      <item>Screen reader: VoiceOver (iOS) and TalkBack (Android) support required.</item>
      <item>Text size: respect system font-size settings; do not force fixed sizes.</item>
      <item>Color contrast: WCAG AA minimum (4.5:1 for normal text, 3:1 for large).</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
