<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-performance" title="Mobile Performance">
  <summary>Core Web Vitals targets, optimization techniques, CI audit strategy, and device testing matrix for mobile performance.</summary>

  <section title="Core Web Vitals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat Core Web Vitals as PR-blocking budgets: LCP below 2.5s, INP below 200ms, CLS below 0.1. Test on a Slow-3G throttle profile — the median real-world mobile connection is closer to Slow-3G than fast-4G.</statement>
      <rationale>53% of mobile users abandon pages taking more than 3 seconds to load. LCP is the primary user-perceived load metric. INP (Interaction to Next Paint) replaced FID in 2024 as the responsiveness standard. CLS measures layout stability — high CLS causes accidental taps on wrong elements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>LCP (Largest Contentful Paint): below 2.5s — largest visible content rendered.</item>
      <item>INP (Interaction to Next Paint): below 200ms — responsiveness to user input.</item>
      <item>CLS (Cumulative Layout Shift): below 0.1 — layout stability during load.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Optimization Techniques">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run audits at three viewports minimum: 360x640 (small Android), 390x844 (iPhone), 768x1024 (tablet). Single-viewport audits miss responsive breakpoint bugs.</statement>
      <rationale>Responsive sites have breakpoint-specific behavior. A touch-target that passes at iPhone size may fall below threshold at the 360px Android viewport where content reflows differently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Images: WebP format, responsive srcset, lazy loading, explicit width and height to prevent CLS.</item>
      <item>JavaScript: code splitting, defer non-critical, minimize bundle size.</item>
      <item>Network: service worker caching, CDN, Brotli compression.</item>
      <item>Loading states: skeleton screens instead of blank content areas during fetch.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="CI Integration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the median of 3 Lighthouse runs before failing a PR. Lighthouse scoring is non-deterministic on variable networks; a single run produces false failures.</statement>
      <rationale>Lighthouse variance is 5-15 points on performance score depending on CPU load and network simulation. A median-of-3 approach reduces false failures from CI infrastructure variability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Report both field data (CrUX, RUM) and lab data (Lighthouse) in performance reports. Lab-only reports create false confidence when real-user conditions differ from the test environment.</statement>
      <rationale>Lab tests use consistent throttling profiles. Real users have diverse device capabilities and network conditions. A 90th-percentile CrUX LCP of 4s on a page with a 2.2s Lighthouse LCP means your lab is not representative of your actual user population.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Testing Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Test on at minimum: one recent iPhone, one recent Android flagship, one budget Android (Moto G or equivalent). Budget Android is the highest-leverage device for catching performance regressions.</statement>
      <rationale>Budget Android devices have CPU speed 5-10x slower than flagship devices. Performance issues that are invisible on a Pixel 7 become critical failures on a Moto G. If your product has users in emerging markets, budget Android IS your median device.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>iPhone (recent model + one generation old): iOS platform behavior.</item>
      <item>Android flagship (Pixel or Samsung): Android platform behavior.</item>
      <item>Budget Android (Moto G or similar): performance on constrained hardware.</item>
      <item>Tablet (iPad, Android tablet): layout at larger mobile viewport.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
