<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Tax Basics for Solopreneurs Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `ops-tax-basics` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-monthly-set-aside-30pct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set aside approximately 30% of net profit into a dedicated tax-savings account MONTHLY. Quarterly catch-up from operating cash is forbidden; the discipline must be monthly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo-operator tax practice (IRS Pub 334; Patrick McKenzie postmortems)">Operators who postpone set-aside drain operating cash at quarterly estimate dates. Monthly set-aside isolates tax cash before it becomes spendable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-safe-harbor-quarterly" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Compute quarterly estimated payments using the IRS safe-harbor rule: 90% current-year tax OR 110% prior-year tax (for AGI &gt; 150k) — whichever is lower. Skipping safe-harbor leads to underpayment penalty.</statement>
      <rationale source="IRS estimated-tax rules (IRC § 6654; Pub 505)">Safe-harbor compliance avoids the IRS underpayment penalty regardless of how much the current-year income surprises. The 90/110 rule is the operating floor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-structure-decision-recorded" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The chosen business structure (sole prop / LLC / S-Corp / C-Corp) is captured in a written decision-record with the trade-offs evaluated (liability, tax, admin burden). Defaulting to sole prop without analysis is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Small-business legal-tax practice (Nolo, LegalZoom guides)">Structure choice affects self-employment tax exposure (S-Corp salary vs distribution split) and personal liability. A decision-record forces the trade-off analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-deductible-tracking-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track deductible expenses in a digital ledger with receipt links (home office %, business travel, software, contractor 1099 payments). Cash-only or memory-only tracking is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="IRS substantiation rules (IRC § 274)">The IRS rejects undocumented deductions on audit. Digital tracking is the only practical way to keep deduction integrity over a tax year.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-retirement-vehicle-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Name the tax-advantaged retirement vehicle in use (SEP-IRA / Solo 401k / HSA) and contribute before the year-end deadline. 'Will set up later' is forbidden as a placeholder for two consecutive years.</statement>
      <rationale source="Retirement-tax practice (IRC §§ 408(k), 401(k), 223; IRS Pub 560)">SEP-IRA / Solo 401k contributions are the single largest tax deferral available to solos. Skipping two consecutive years compounds opportunity cost and tax bill.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
