<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Beta-Cohort Recruitment Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that prevent the two recurring beta failures: a cohort full of friends-of-founder, and a cohort that disappears after week 2.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-icp-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sourcing MUST start from the written ICP and reject candidates who do not match. Friends, former colleagues, and network warm intros are eligible ONLY if they independently pass the ICP filter. Network proximity is not a qualification.</statement>
      <rationale source="Steve Blank, Four Steps to the Epiphany">Founders default to recruiting from their network because it is fast. The result is a cohort that politely uses the product to support the friendship, generating false-positive engagement signal and zero generalizable learning.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-screener-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every candidate MUST complete a written screener before the founder spends synchronous time. The screener tests: ICP fit (role, sizing), pain severity (last incident date), time budget (hours/week they will commit), and decision authority (can they actually deploy this?).</statement>
      <rationale source="User Interviews / Respondent recruitment research">Without a screener the founder front-loads cost on unqualified candidates. A 5-minute screener filters out the majority before either side invests time. It also creates a paper trail of who was rejected and why, useful when ICP refines later.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-signed-expectations" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before access is granted, the candidate signs the expectations one-pager (mutual NDA + cadence + exit terms). Verbal agreement does not count. The signed PDF or e-sign record is logged in the cohort tracker with date.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-partner program standards (e.g. Stripe, Snowflake early days)">Unsigned beta partners treat the program as optional. Signed partners treat it as a commitment. The signing ritual itself filters out half-interested participants and pre-builds the legal floor for shared confidential data.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-cadence-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The cadence is written into the expectations doc: e.g., weekly 30-minute sync for 6 weeks + async Slack/email channel. Missed touchpoints are logged; two consecutive missed syncs without a written reason trigger the exit ramp.</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer development practice (Cindy Alvarez, Lean Customer Development)">"We'll just keep in touch" cohorts evaporate inside three weeks. A pinned cadence with explicit miss-rules forces the founder to either save or graduate the partner — no zombie partners hovering in the tracker.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-exit-ramp" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The expectations doc MUST include an exit/graduation ramp: how the partner moves to paying customer (or off the program) at the end of the term. Options are pre-priced. Partners are not surprised by a bill or a kick-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="Y Combinator design-partner playbook">Beta partners who feel ambushed by pricing churn loud. Pre-pricing the conversion ramp converts the awkward "what happens next" conversation into a calendar event.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Screener question that filters for fit">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Q: When did your team last lose time to [pain X]?
Acceptable: "Last week", "Yesterday", "Twice a day"
Reject: "Sometimes", "We are anticipating problems", "Hypothetically"
      ]]></code>
      <note>Recency forces the candidate to recall a real incident; anticipated/hypothetical pain has no behavioral evidence.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Friend-of-founder pattern">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Cohort log:
- Partner 1: ex-colleague from previous startup
- Partner 2: founder's brother-in-law's CTO
- Partner 3: someone on the founder's Twitter who DM'd
ICP fit check: not performed; "they seemed enthusiastic"
      ]]></code>
      <note>Three partners, zero ICP screening. Engagement signal from this cohort is uninterpretable.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
