<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="design-system-success-factors">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Framework for evaluating design systems via four pillars: ownership, usable components, documentation, and adoption. Enables quarterly health checks and OKRs.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>design-systems</tag>
      <tag>ownership</tag>
      <tag>adoption</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Design System Success Factors</title>

    <summary>Design systems fail most often not from technical debt but from governance and adoption gaps: no single owner, documentation that drifts from source, components teams work around. A four-pillar model makes failure modes explicit and measurable, enabling quarterly health checks and OKR-setting for platform teams. The pillars are: clear ownership (dedicated responsible person/team), usable components (adoptable API and quality), strong documentation (findable and current), and real adoption (measured component coverage across products).</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Design systems fail most often not from technical debt but from governance and adoption gaps: no single owner, documentation that drifts from source, components teams work around. The four-pillar model makes failure modes explicit and measurable, enabling quarterly health checks and OKR-setting for platform teams.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Standing up a new design system or evaluating build vs. adopt vs. wrap.</item>
        <item>Quarterly health check on an existing system: ownership, adoption, contribution, debt.</item>
        <item>Diagnosing why a system is being ignored (low component coverage, parallel snowflake CSS).</item>
        <item>Pre-merger or rebrand audit when two systems must be unified.</item>
        <item>Setting OKRs/KPIs for a platform team.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>One-off marketing landing pages — a tokens file + Tailwind config is sufficient.</item>
        <item>Pre-product-market-fit prototyping — the pillars optimize for adoption, which assumes stable surface area.</item>
        <item>Teams with fewer than 3 designers and 1 frontend engineer — ownership pillar collapses, overhead exceeds value.</item>
        <item>Pure motion or brand-illustration systems — adoption metrics are not meaningful.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="four-pillars">
      <rule>
        <statement>Assign a single named owner or team with authority and accountability for the design system before any other work begins.</statement>
        <rationale>Systems with diffuse or absent ownership drift: no one decides breaking changes, documentation goes stale, and consumer teams lose trust and fork. Ownership is the first pillar because all others depend on it.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Components must be adoptable as-is by consumer teams without local overrides; if a component requires frequent customization to use, it is not usable enough.</statement>
        <rationale>High override rates indicate the component does not fit real use cases. Components that need workarounds get bypassed — driving snowflake CSS growth rather than coverage improvement.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Documentation must be discoverable and current; a page count that drifts from source code is worse than no documentation because it actively misleads consumers.</statement>
        <rationale>Stale docs erode trust faster than gaps. Consumers learn to distrust the docs and stop consulting them, creating a negative feedback loop where documentation becomes irrelevant.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat the system as a product with a roadmap and SLAs, not a side project; measure adoption monthly and publish coverage metrics visibly to consumer teams.</statement>
        <rationale>Peer visibility of coverage metrics outperforms top-down mandates for driving adoption. Teams that see their coverage percentage relative to peers improve it without explicit directives.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="mvp-launch-sequence">
      <p>Start with the minimum viable system: core interactive components, design tokens (color, spacing, typography), brand colors, and a small pattern library. Launch, stress-test with one consumer product, gather feedback, then grow iteratively. Launching too large creates debt before validation.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="adoption-metrics">
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure component coverage as the percentage of UI primitives (button, input, card, modal) sourced from the system versus implemented locally; count at the render site, not the import statement.</statement>
        <rationale>Import-level counting is gameable — a team may import the Button and use it once while implementing 40 custom buttons locally. Render-site AST scanning via ts-morph provides the actual usage picture.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Component coverage: % of UI primitives using system components vs local implementations</item>
        <item>Adoption rate: number of active consumer teams using the system package</item>
        <item>Contribution rate: external PRs merged to the system per quarter</item>
        <item>Bug/issue count: open issues by priority as a quality proxy</item>
        <item>Design-dev sync: % of semantic tokens matching between Figma and code</item>
      </list>
      <reference path="templates/ds-coverage.mjs">AST-based Node script counting system vs snowflake primitive usage across consumer apps</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-automatable-audit-areas">
      <p>Agents handle the measurable parts of the four pillars: documentation freshness (last-updated vs last-source-commit), token-design parity (Figma vs code), contribution telemetry (PR merge rates), and adoption scanning (AST import analysis across consumer repos). Ownership and "real adoption" framing require human review — agents cannot decide whether to fund a platform team.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pair every component release with a codemod (jscodeshift) that migrates consumers; documentation-only releases erode trust and drive forks.</statement>
        <rationale>Consumer teams that must manually migrate to a new API version lose confidence in the system's release discipline. Codemods remove the migration burden and increase actual adoption of new releases.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="coverage-probe-prompt-pattern">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Coverage: "Crawl the apps/ workspace. For each consumer app, list components imported from @org/ui, count usages, and list visual primitives (button, input, card, modal) implemented locally instead. Emit coverage.json with { app, system_uses, snowflake_uses, coverage_pct }."</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Docs freshness: "Given Storybook's index.json and the system's source src/components/*, list components with no Storybook story (docs gap) or whose story has not changed in 180+ days while source has."</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent fabricating adoption percentage by counting import statements without counting render sites.</description>
        <reason>A team may import the Button once and implement 40 custom buttons locally. Import-level counting inflates coverage metrics; render-site AST scanning (ts-morph) provides the actual figure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM generating components that re-implement existing system primitives because the catalogue was not provided as context.</description>
        <reason>Without the system's catalogue (Storybook index.json or package exports), the agent does not know what already exists and will write duplicate components that increase snowflake usage.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Token rename PRs from agents missing CSS-in-JS template literals and Tailwind config references.</description>
        <reason>AST token rename tools typically handle import paths and property access, but miss string-interpolated CSS-in-JS patterns and Tailwind config keys. Require a second-pass regex sweep before merging.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent-authored PRs merging to consumer app main branches without per-app release-train coordination.</description>
        <reason>Codemods to unrelated apps must respect their release schedules. Auto-merging into main of unrelated apps can ship breaking visual changes ahead of their release cycle.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Treat the system as a product with a roadmap, customers (consumer teams), and SLAs — not as a side-project of the platform team. Define adoption tiers (Bronze/Silver/Gold) per consumer app and publish them; peer pressure outperforms top-down mandates. Pair every component release with a codemod (jscodeshift) that migrates consumers; "documentation only" releases erode trust. Run a contribution day each quarter — measured contribution rate is meaningless without a working contribution path. Keep tokens and components in different release trains; tokens move slowly, components iterate. Make breaking changes loud (changesets `major`, codemod, deprecation warnings) and silent fixes silent (`patch`). Capture support-ticket categories per quarter; the dominant category is your next roadmap item.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <note>CLI tools: Style Dictionary (token build → CSS/JS/iOS/Android), Storybook + Chromatic (visual regression + docs), Backlight (token + component pipeline), zeroheight CLI (sync Figma libraries to docs), Knapsack (design-system platform CLI), jscodeshift / ts-morph (AST scanning for adoption metrics), Repo-stats / Sourcegraph (cross-repo usage queries), changesets (versioning + changelog discipline), Figma REST API (library publish / consumer counts).</note>
      <note>Services &amp; apps: Chromatic (SaaS, yes agent-friendly — CLI + GitHub Actions), zeroheight (SaaS, partial agent-friendly — REST API), Knapsack (SaaS, yes agent-friendly — CLI), Supernova.io (SaaS, yes agent-friendly — REST + CLI), Specify (SaaS, yes agent-friendly — REST + CLI), Tokens Studio (Figma plugin, limited), Backlight (SaaS, yes agent-friendly — CLI), Penpot (OSS, limited), Storybook OSS (yes agent-friendly), Figma Variables (SaaS, yes agent-friendly — REST API).</note>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Adoption rate defined as "% of teams using the package" hides depth of usage; teams may import once and override everything. The four pillars are necessary but not sufficient — they say nothing about API design, theming model, or release cadence. Component coverage is gameable — counting "Button" once vs counting every variant inflates the metric. "Strong documentation" can be confused with "lots of documentation"; success depends on findability and currency, not page count. The MVP-first lean does not work in regulated industries where accessibility/legal review must precede first release.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ds-coverage.mjs" purpose="AST-based Node script: counts system vs snowflake primitive usage across consumer apps."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://medium.com/eightshapes-llc"/>
      <link href="https://designsystemssurvey.sparkbox.com"/>
      <link href="https://spectrum.adobe.com"/>
      <link href="https://polaris.shopify.com"/>
      <link href="https://designsystemsrepo.com"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
