<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-checklist" title="The 10 readiness items">
  <summary>The canonical 10-item checklist. Each item is a binary tick with evidence link. Any unticked item blocks the in-progress → done transition.</summary>

  <section title="Item set">

    <rule id="i1-ac-evidence" testable="true">
      <statement>All ACs from spec.md have evidence (test id or screenshot reference) linked next to the checkbox.</statement>
      <rationale>An AC without a verifiable artefact is a claim, not a result. The link IS the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="i2-tasks-done" testable="true">
      <statement>All tasks moved to tasks/done/. tasks/todo/ and tasks/in-progress/ are empty.</statement>
      <rationale>An unmoved task means work the developer thinks is irrelevant — explicit close-out exposes the assumption.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="i3-commit-hygiene" testable="true">
      <statement>Commits are granular, follow `type(F0NN-T0N): ≤50 char title`, contain no Co-Authored-By line and no emoji.</statement>
      <rationale>Granular history is the release-notes raw material. Forbidden trailers and emoji break the repo policy hook.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="i4-ci-green" testable="true">
      <statement>CI is green: lint + typecheck + unit tests all pass on the feature branch.</statement>
      <rationale>Baseline machine check. Skipping it is the cheapest way to ship a regression.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="i5-api-tests" testable="true">
      <statement>API tests pass — REQUIRED ONLY when the feature touches backend.</statement>
      <rationale>Backend surface changes break contracts silently if not contract-tested.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="i6-playwright" testable="true">
      <statement>Playwright positive AND negative cases pass — REQUIRED ONLY when the feature has a user-facing flow.</statement>
      <rationale>Positive only proves the happy path. Negative catches the unsexy edges where regressions hide.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="i7-ui-ux-heuristics" testable="true">
      <statement>ui-ux-design.md heuristics reviewed — REQUIRED ONLY when the feature touches UI.</statement>
      <rationale>Heuristic audit catches affordance and feedback bugs before they reach the user.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="i8-spec-delta" testable="true">
      <statement>project-spec/ delta is drafted in the same PR, OR readiness.md explicitly states "no spec impact" with a one-line reason.</statement>
      <rationale>The same-PR rule from project-spec-structure. The escape hatch is loud on purpose.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="i9-surface-coupling" testable="true">
      <statement>Surface coupling reviewed: any new public surface (skill trigger, API path, CLI flag, exported name) has been checked against unrelated surfaces for accidental coupling.</statement>
      <rationale>F001→F002 lesson — two unrelated features collided through skill description overlap. Item makes the review explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="i10-deployed" testable="true">
      <statement>Feature is deployed to the host listed in project-spec/deploy.md (per the deploy-after-feature memory rule).</statement>
      <rationale>Done is "users can use it", not "the merge button was clicked". Closing the loop blocks ship-and-forget.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-quality-gates.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-surface-coupling.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
