<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-quality-gates" title="Conditional quality gates">
  <summary>Items 5, 6, 7 are conditional on what the feature actually touches. This file pins the conditions so the reviewer cannot waive the gate by claiming inapplicability without justification.</summary>

  <section title="Backend → API tests">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>If ANY file under the backend source tree changed, item 5 (API tests pass) MUST be ticked.</statement>
      <rationale>Even one line in a serializer can shift a contract. The git diff is the source of truth, not the developer's assessment of scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Feature touches `apps/billing/views.py` → API tests required → reviewer confirms `pytest apps/billing/tests/api/` passed in CI artefact.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="User-facing flow → Playwright pos+neg">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>If the feature has user-facing flow (page, form, button, command), item 6 requires AT LEAST one positive test case AND one negative test case per flow.</statement>
      <rationale>Positive only is a smoke test. Negative trumps positive for the boring edges — auth failure, network down, invalid input — which is where users actually break the product.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>"Playwright covers it" with one happy-path spec file and no negative cases.</description>
      <reason>Half the bugs hide on the path nobody automated. The pos+neg rule is the cheapest insurance.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="UI touched → ui-ux-design.md audit">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>If the feature renders or changes any visible UI element, item 7 requires a documented Nielsen 5 + Norman 2 audit in ui-ux-design.md before the box is ticked.</statement>
      <rationale>Heuristic audits cost minutes and catch the silent UX regressions that no unit test sees.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="../quality-gates/AGENTS.md">Stack-to-gate matrix; consumed when computing which items apply.</reference>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-checklist.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
