<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-surface-coupling" title="The surface-coupling review (F001 → F002 lesson)">
  <summary>Item 9 is the result of one specific historical failure. This file records the failure and the review protocol it triggered.</summary>

  <section title="The empirical anchor">
    <p>F001 in the faion plugin defined a skill trigger description. F002 later added an unrelated trigger description. The two descriptions overlapped at the keyword layer, so the auto-router fired the wrong skill for several user inputs. The bug was invisible at code-review because each PR only looked at its own diff. The fix was retrofitting an explicit surface-coupling review.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="What counts as a public surface">
    <list>
      <item>Skill description / triggers (the auto-router keys off these).</item>
      <item>API path or method signature exposed to clients.</item>
      <item>CLI flag, subcommand, or environment variable consumed externally.</item>
      <item>Public type/class/function name exported from a library boundary.</item>
      <item>Database table or column name read by downstream systems.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="The review protocol">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>For every public surface added or modified by the feature, grep the project for sibling surfaces in the same namespace and document — in readiness.md — that no collision exists OR that the collision is intentional and disambiguated.</statement>
      <rationale>The collision is invisible at single-PR review and only surfaces at runtime. Forcing the explicit grep moves the check left.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Adding skill `sdd-batch-orchestrator` → grep `description:` across `skills/faion/workflows/` → find sibling `sdd-promotion-gate-checklist`. Verify keyword overlap is minimal; if not, narrow one description.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Ticking item 9 because "this feature does not add a public surface" without naming what was checked.</description>
    <reason>The default answer to "any public surface?" is yes more often than people think — internal refactors expose types, CLI flags get added in passing. State what you checked, not just the conclusion.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-checklist.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
