<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ops-subscription-models">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>A framework for designing and operating subscription businesses: choose model type, structure tiers, instrument metrics, automate billing recovery, and manage the full customer lifecycle.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>subscription</tag>
      <tag>billing</tag>
      <tag>mrr</tag>
      <tag>churn</tag>
      <tag>ltv</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>operations</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Subscription Models</title>

    <summary>A framework for designing and operating subscription businesses: choose model type (SaaS, membership, replenishment, curation), structure tiers with strategic feature allocation, instrument MRR/churn/LTV metrics, automate billing recovery (dunning), and manage the full customer lifecycle from trial through win-back. Net Revenue Retention above 100% is the goal — meaning expansion revenue offsets churn.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>One-time sales require constant new acquisition; subscriptions create compounding recurring revenue. The mechanism: annual plans reduce churn (cash in, less friction to cancel), dunning automation recovers 20–40% of failed payments that would otherwise be silent churn, and lifecycle interventions (at-risk triggers, save offers) extend LTV at near-zero marginal cost.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Launching a SaaS, digital membership, or content platform.</item>
        <item>Converting an existing one-time-purchase product to recurring revenue.</item>
        <item>Churn rate is above 5%/month and root cause is unclear.</item>
        <item>Expansion revenue (upgrades) is zero — missing upsell/tier paths.</item>
        <item>Setting up billing infrastructure for the first time (Stripe, Paddle).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>One-time high-value services (consulting, agency work) where recurring isn't the model.</item>
        <item>Products with naturally episodic demand (event software, seasonal tools).</item>
        <item>When product has not yet demonstrated retention past 90 days — subscription without retention is an expensive churn machine.</item>
        <item>Physical product subscriptions without reliable supply chain — replenishment model requires fulfillment reliability.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="subscription-model-types">
      <p>Five subscription model types with best-fit guidance.</p>
      <list>
        <item>SaaS — software access. Users pay for ongoing access to a platform or tool. Best for: tools, platforms, productivity software.</item>
        <item>Membership — community or content access. Users pay for belonging and exclusive content. Best for: education, professional communities, newsletters.</item>
        <item>Replenishment — regular physical product delivery. Best for: consumables, personal care, food.</item>
        <item>Curation — curated selections delivered periodically. Best for: discovery products (book clubs, music, fashion boxes).</item>
        <item>Access — exclusive availability (not content, but priority or privilege). Best for: premium services, concierge products.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="billing-frequency-trade-offs">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Offer both monthly and annual billing. Present annual as "2 months free" (not "17% off"). For most SaaS, annual reduces churn by 3–5x compared to monthly-only.</statement>
        <rationale>Annual billing creates a 12-month commitment window before the next churn decision. "2 months free" is tangible (users can visualize two months); "17% off" is abstract.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="tier-structures">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use Good-Better-Best (max 4 tiers) as default. Free tier must be limited enough that a real user would want to upgrade within 30 days of hitting the limit.</statement>
        <rationale>Too-generous free tiers eliminate upgrade motivation. The most common subscription failure pattern is a free tier that fully satisfies the core use case.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Good-Better-Best for a SaaS tool">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Basic ($9/mo):  Core features, 100 items limit
Pro ($29/mo):   Full features, unlimited (anchor tier)
Team ($79/mo):  Collaboration + priority support
]]></code>
        <note>Core value limited on free, full access on Pro, collaboration on Team.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Usage + Base for API-driven product">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Base ($29/mo):  Platform access, 1K API calls included
Usage:          $0.01 per additional API call
]]></code>
        <note>Base covers fixed costs, usage covers variable.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="essential-metrics">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Track Net Revenue Retention (NRR) as the single health metric. NRR above 100% means expansion revenue exceeds churn; below 100% means the business is leaking faster than it's filling.</statement>
        <rationale>NRR captures both churn and expansion in one number. A business with 8% monthly churn but 12% expansion can grow despite the churn. NRR is the metric investors use to assess subscription business quality.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>MRR = sum of all monthly subscriptions (excluding one-time fees).</item>
        <item>ARR = MRR x 12 (for annual planning only; don't track day-to-day in ARR).</item>
        <item>Monthly churn rate = customers lost / customers at start of period.</item>
        <item>LTV = ARPU / monthly churn rate (higher ARPU and lower churn compound LTV significantly).</item>
        <item>LTV:CAC target = 3:1 minimum; 5:1 is healthy.</item>
        <item>NRR = (Starting MRR + Expansion MRR - Churn MRR) / Starting MRR x 100.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="billing-best-practices">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Implement dunning automation before launch: retry failed payments on Day 1, 3, and 7 with accompanying emails; downgrade to free on Day 10. This recovers 20–40% of would-be churned revenue.</statement>
        <rationale>15–25% of subscription cancellations are involuntary (expired cards, insufficient funds). Without automated recovery, this becomes silent permanent churn. Most customers with failed payments want to keep the subscription.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="dunning-sequence">
      <example type="good" title="5-step payment recovery flow">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Day 0:  Payment fails → log event
Day 1:  Email (friendly notice) + retry charge
Day 3:  Email (urgency) + retry charge
Day 7:  Email (final warning: access ends in 3 days) + retry
Day 10: Downgrade to free tier, data retained 30 days
Day 30: Win-back campaign email to churned users
]]></code>
        <note>Each step includes email + automatic retry attempt.</note>
      </example>
      <reference path="templates/dunning-emails.txt">3-email dunning sequence templates.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="common-billing-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>No annual billing option at launch.</description>
        <reason>Annual subscribers churn 3–5x less. Missing annual billing at launch means all early customers are monthly, with no commitment lock-in and no cash flow improvement.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Making cancellation difficult (multi-step forms, mandatory calls).</description>
        <reason>Difficult cancellation increases chargebacks, generates negative reviews, and is illegal in some jurisdictions. Easy cancellation builds trust and sometimes produces "saved" customers who were testing how painful it is.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="customer-lifecycle-stages-and-interventions">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Instrument lifecycle stage transitions and trigger interventions at each: onboarding email Day 1, check-in Day 3, conversion offer Day 7 (for trials); usage-drop alert for at-risk; save offer at cancellation; win-back at Day 30 post-churn.</statement>
        <rationale>Each lifecycle stage has a different intervention ROI. Day 1 onboarding email has the highest open rate of any email the user will ever receive (50–70%). At-risk outreach is cheaper than win-back.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Trial Day 1: welcome email + first value action prompt.</item>
        <item>Trial Day 3: check-in email — did they complete the first action? Help if not.</item>
        <item>Trial Day 7: conversion offer — limited-time or exclusive bonus for upgrading now.</item>
        <item>Active monthly: usage report email — show them the value delivered this month.</item>
        <item>At-risk (usage drop 50%+ week-over-week): proactive outreach, offer help session.</item>
        <item>Cancel request: save offer (discount, pause, downgrade) before confirming cancellation.</item>
        <item>Churned Day 30: win-back campaign — announce new feature or offer re-entry discount.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="example-saas-email-marketing-tool">
      <example type="good" title="Three-tier usage-based pricing; 115% NRR">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Tiers:
  Starter $19/mo:  1K contacts, 10K emails/mo
  Growth  $49/mo:  5K contacts, 50K emails/mo  (40% of users)
  Pro     $99/mo:  15K contacts, 150K emails/mo

Outcomes:
  40% choose Growth (anchor tier)
  Net Revenue Retention: 115%
  Monthly churn rate: 3%
  (Expansion from contact list growth offsets churn)
]]></code>
        <note>Three-tier usage-based pricing; 115% NRR achieved through expansion (users growing their contact lists).</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="example-developer-learning-membership">
      <example type="good" title="Freemium + two paid tiers">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Tiers:
  Free   $0:      Public content only
  Member $29/mo:  All courses + community
  VIP    $99/mo:  + Live sessions + mentorship

Outcomes:
  Free-to-paid conversion: 5%
  Annual retention (paid): 85%
  VIP = 2% of paid users, 15% of revenue
  (VIP LTV ~10x Member LTV)
]]></code>
        <note>Freemium + two paid tiers; small VIP tier generates outsized revenue share.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/subscription-model-doc.md" purpose="Model design document: type, billing, tiers, metric targets, lifecycle automation plan."/>
      <template path="templates/dunning-emails.txt" purpose="3-email payment recovery sequence (Day 1, Day 3, Day 7)."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://stripe.com/docs/billing/subscriptions/overview"/>
      <link href="https://chartmogul.com/blog/net-revenue-retention/"/>
      <link href="https://baremetrics.com/academy/saas-churn"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
