<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="requirements-prioritization">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>BA methodology for prioritizing requirements with MoSCoW, RICE, Kano, Value-Effort, WSJF. Multi-stakeholder conflict resolution, release scope, backlog ranking, vendor scoring templates.</summary>
    <category>ba</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>requirements-prioritization</tag>
      <tag>moscow</tag>
      <tag>rice</tag>
      <tag>kano</tag>
      <tag>babok</tag>
      <tag>business-analysis</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Requirements Prioritization</title>

    <summary>BABOK-aligned methodology for BA-as-facilitator of multi-stakeholder prioritization. Picks the right method (MoSCoW / RICE / Kano / Value-Effort / WSJF / weighted-sum), runs elicitation and reconciliation, and ties the output back to the requirements catalog and delivery (backlog rank or release scope). Includes templates for release scope decisions where the BA must shrink a 200-item requirement set to a 30-item MVP/MMR with defensible rationale.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>All requirements seem equally important. Stakeholders fight for their requirements. Everything is marked "high priority." Resources are spread thin trying to do everything. Without prioritization there is no focus on value, resource conflicts arise, ROI is delayed, and stakeholder frustration grows. Limited resources (time, money, people) require delivering value early. Not all requirements are equally important, and stakeholders have different perspectives that must be reconciled before commitment.</p>
      <p>The BA owns the prioritization process; agents own the artifacts. A locked method (MoSCoW / RICE / Kano / Value-Effort / WSJF / weighted-sum) applied consistently produces defensible results that auditors and escalation partners can trace. Without explicit method-picking and conflict reconciliation, prioritization devolves to HiPPO (Highest Paid Person's Opinion) and creates the false record that justifies undelivered scope.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Release scope decisions where the BA must shrink a 200-item requirement set to a 30-item MVP/MMR with a defensible rationale (regulated industries especially: auditors will ask "why this scope?").</item>
        <item>Cross-team backlog where Sales, Support, Engineering and Compliance each lobby for "their" items and the Product Owner needs an explicit method to break ties without drama.</item>
        <item>Vendor-RFP / RFI scoring where requirements are scored against multiple proposals — same matrix machinery, requirement IDs become rows.</item>
        <item>Pre-PI / pre-quarter prioritization in scaled agile (SAFe ART, LeSS) — WSJF over a 50–150 feature backlog where sequencing matters more than hard categories.</item>
        <item>After every elicitation wave when fresh requirements need to be slotted into the existing rank without reshuffling everything.</item>
        <item>When the team already produced a "everything is Must" MoSCoW and the BA needs a forcing function (RICE or weighted scoring) to break the tie.</item>
        <item>Whenever a stakeholder asks "why isn't my requirement in this release?" — the priority record is the answer.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Discovery phase before product-market fit — locking priorities on speculative requirements creates false rigor; use opportunity-solution-trees and continuous-discovery instead.</item>
        <item>Single-team, single-PO, &lt; 10 stories — a 1-D stack rank by the PO is faster than RICE.</item>
        <item>Pure cost optimization with quantified cash flows — go to NPV / payback, not 1-5 scoring which discards precision.</item>
        <item>Engineering-internal items (refactors, infra) — those need technical-debt-management criteria, not business-value scoring; BA does not own these.</item>
        <item>Hard regulatory deadlines — those are constraints, not priorities; route to the Won't/Must boundary mechanically and stop debating.</item>
        <item>When "the answer is already chosen" — a retrofitted prioritization to justify a decided scope damages BA credibility.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="problem">
      <p>All requirements seem equally important. Stakeholders fight for their requirements. Everything is marked "high priority." Resources are spread thin trying to do everything. The most valuable features are not delivered first. Without prioritization: no focus on value, resource conflicts, delayed ROI, stakeholder frustration.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>If all requirements are marked Must / High / Essential after elicitation, the prioritization has failed and must be re-run with a forcing function (RICE or weighted scoring that reveals relative cost and impact).</statement>
        <rationale>Default group behavior is to mark everything as highest priority. A credible prioritization must have a distribution (roughly 60% Must, 20% Should, 20% Could for MoSCoW); a flat ranking signals incomplete elicitation or groupthink and needs a method that surfaces trade-offs.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prioritization-framework">
      <p>The prioritization framework rests on six criteria: Business value (How much value does this provide?), Cost (How expensive to implement?), Risk (What is the risk of doing/not doing?), Dependencies (What must come first?), Urgency (Is there a deadline?), and Regulatory (Is it legally required?).</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Before scoring begins, the BA must lock the prioritization method and communicate the choice to all stakeholders. Switching methods mid-run is forbidden.</statement>
        <rationale>Method-shopping (run MoSCoW, switch to RICE when results displease) destroys BA credibility. Locking the method first prevents stakeholders from manipulating the outcome.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Effort estimate must be gathered from delivery (engineering) before value scoring from stakeholders. Scores without effort context produce "high value, unlimited cost" results that cannot be executed.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholders scoring business value with no constraint on cost estimate will rate speculative features as high-value. Coupling value scoring with effort prevents impossible scope and forces trade-off discussions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prioritization-criteria">
      <p>Six prioritization criteria form the foundation: Business value (How much value does this provide?), Cost (How expensive to implement?), Risk (What is the risk of doing/not doing?), Dependencies (What must come first?), Urgency (Is there a deadline?), and Regulatory (Is it legally required?). The choice of method determines which criteria are weighted and how.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Gather effort estimate from delivery (engineering) before value scoring from stakeholders. Scores without effort context produce "high value, unlimited cost" results that cannot be executed.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholders scoring business value with no constraint on cost estimate will rate speculative features as high-value. Coupling value scoring with effort prevents impossible scope and forces trade-off discussions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="method-selection">
      <p>Six methods cover the common patterns: MoSCoW for simple categorization, RICE for data-driven prioritization with four factors, Kano for customer satisfaction focus, Value-Effort for visual quadrant analysis, WSJF for scaled agile, and weighted scoring for multiple criteria.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>MoSCoW (Must ~60%, Should ~20%, Could ~20%, Won't = tracked for future) is best for release scope decisions with hard deadlines and clearer Must/Should boundaries. RICE is best for backlog prioritization with many items where relative trade-offs matter more than hard categories.</statement>
        <rationale>MoSCoW works when scope is constrained and the team can clearly articulate what breaks the release if excluded. RICE works when the backlog is large and two features at similar cost but different value need relative ranking.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Kano (Basic/Performance/Delighters) requires user research data (survey, interviews, market analysis) to assign categories. If user research data does not exist, do not attempt Kano — treat it as gut-feel scoring dressed up in academic language and use RICE instead.</statement>
        <rationale>Kano without data is a failure mode: the team guesses categories from the conference room, produces confident-sounding but unreliable results, and the BA gets blamed when reality diverges. RICE is more honest about uncertainty.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Value-Effort matrix (quadrant analysis: Quick Wins, Major Projects, Fill-Ins, Avoid) is good for visual stakeholder communication and organizational simplicity. WSJF (Weighted Shortest Job First, SAFe) is required in scaled agile contexts (ART, LeSS) where PI planning needs a method the whole organization recognizes.</statement>
        <rationale>Value-Effort is intuitive and forces discussion ("why is this in the Avoid quadrant?"), but it loses precision for tied items. WSJF is more sophisticated (includes risk, dependencies, time-sensitivity) and aligns with SAFe ceremonies if the organization is running them.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="moscow-method">
      <p>MoSCoW assigns requirements to categories: Must (essential, non-negotiable, ~60% of effort), Should (important, not critical, ~20% of effort), Could (nice to have, ~20% of effort), Won't (not this time, tracked for future). The distribution ensures scope is bounded and realistic.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>"Must" means the release fails without it. "Should" means significant value but the release can work around it. "Could" means low cost, low impact. "Won't" means explicitly excluded this iteration and revisited when capacity allows.</statement>
        <rationale>Definitions prevent scope creep. Every team will try to promote items to Must; clear operational definitions give the BA language to push back ("that's Should because we can ship without it if needed").</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>If Must > 60% of effort budget after initial assignment, the MoSCoW exercise has failed and must be re-run with a forcing function (RICE or weighted scoring) to break the tie.</statement>
        <rationale>Default group behavior assigns everything to Must. If the math shows Must is consuming 80% of effort, the prioritization is meaningless. Forcing function (like RICE) makes relative impact visible and surfaces which "Must" items are actually "Should".</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="MoSCoW for MVP with guidelines">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# MoSCoW Prioritization: E-commerce MVP

**Scope:** 3-month timeline

## Must Have (Essential)
- User registration and login
- Product catalog with search
- Shopping cart
- Checkout with payment processing
- Order confirmation email

## Should Have (Important)
- User reviews and ratings
- Wishlist functionality
- Order history and reordering
- Product recommendations
- Email notification preferences

## Could Have (Nice to Have)
- Social media sharing
- Gift cards
- Advanced search filters
- Product comparison
- Rating analytics

## Won't Have (Not This Time)
- Mobile native app
- Loyalty program (revisit in Q3)
- Live chat support (revisit if CAC exceeds $15)
- Third-party marketplace integration
        ]]></code>
        <note>Distribution: Must 60% (user flow closure), Should 20% (retention), Could 15% (engagement), Won't 5% (tracked for future). Hard boundary prevents creep.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Everything is marked Must. No boundaries. Team scope commitment is 150% of capacity.</description>
        <reason>No real prioritization occurs; the team commits to 100% scope and blames engineering when the deadline is missed. Enforce the ~60% rule numerically: if Must > 60% of effort budget, reject and re-run with RICE.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="rice-scoring">
      <p>RICE = (Reach × Impact × Confidence) / Effort. Reach is users per time period (quarter, month), Impact is 3 (massive) to 0.25 (minimal), Confidence is 100% (high) to 50% (low), Effort is person-months. Higher RICE score = higher priority. RICE works well for large backlogs with many items where relative ranking matters more than categorical buckets.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>RICE Reach estimate must be grounded in actual user data or user research. Confidence must be 50%, 80%, or 100% with written justification per row; default 100% is a sign teams are not thinking critically about uncertainty.</statement>
        <rationale>RICE produces confident-sounding but unreliable scores when Reach and Confidence are guesses. Forcing written justification prevents mechanical scoring and surfaces when data is actually missing.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For Impact, use the scale: 3 (massive, greater than 50% increase in metric), 2 (high, 25-50% increase), 1 (medium, 10-25% increase), 0.5 (low, less than 10% increase), 0.25 (minimal, less than 5% increase). Require the metric and baseline in the Impact justification.</statement>
        <rationale>Impact estimation is the most subjective RICE component. The scale must reference a measurable baseline (retention, revenue per user, conversion) to prevent teams from calling every feature "massive" impact.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="RICE scoring example with justification">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# RICE Scoring: Q2 Backlog

| Feature | Reach | Impact | Conf | Effort | RICE | Rank |
|---------|-------|--------|------|--------|------|------|
| Export to PDF | 5000/mo | 2 | 80% | 1 | 8000 | 1 |
| Dark mode | 3000/mo | 0.5 | 100% | 2 | 750 | 3 |
| Bulk upload | 200/mo | 3 | 80% | 1 | 480 | 4 |
| API webhooks | 500/mo | 3 | 50% | 3 | 250 | 5 |

**Justifications:**

- Export to PDF: Reach from feature analytics (5k/mo users using export button). Impact: 80% of exporters switch to PDF (from doc/CSV baseline). Confidence 80% because one NPS survey question supports this.
- Dark mode: Reach from survey (3k respondents asked). Impact 0.5 because retention studies show dark mode users stay 5% longer (minor). Confidence 100% — data is quantified.
- Bulk upload: Reach from sales CRM (200 Enterprise customers request). Impact 3 because bulk upload reduces their onboarding time from 3 days to 2 hours (massive process improvement). Confidence 80% — pilot with 4 customers validated.
        ]]></code>
        <note>The narrative justifications are the audit trail. "5000" alone is meaningless; "5000 users/mo hitting export button" is defensible. Confidence choice forces explicit data assessment.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Confidence inflation — teams default 100% on everything. No written justification per row.</description>
        <reason>The Effort divisor stops doing work if Confidence is always high. Without justification, high-confidence scores masquerade as data-driven when they're guesses. Force the choice: 50% (no data), 80% (one data point), 100% (quantified baseline and delta). Make teams write it down.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="kano-model">
      <p>Kano categorizes by user satisfaction curve: Basic (expected, absence causes dissatisfaction), Performance (more is better, linear satisfaction), Delighters (unexpected, create satisfaction), Indifferent (no impact), Reverse (presence causes dissatisfaction, remove).</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Kano requires user research data (survey asking "how would you feel if this feature was present / absent") to assign categories. If user research data does not exist, the team is guessing and should use RICE instead.</statement>
        <rationale>Kano without data is gut-feel scoring. The team guesses that "dark mode" is a delighter and "login" is basic, produces confident results, then ships dark mode first and watches adoption stall. Only survey data reveals the true categorization.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Kano prioritization with data">
        <note>User survey: "How would you feel if the API had webhooks?" Kano analysis: 70% said "very dissatisfied without it", 10% said "would be nice", 20% indifferent. Webhooks is Basic, not Delighter; must build first.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="value-effort-matrix">
      <p>Four quadrants: Quick Wins (high value, low effort → do first), Major Projects (high value, high effort → plan carefully), Fill-Ins (low value, low effort → if time), Avoid (low value, high effort → skip).</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Value-Effort works best as a visual stakeholder communication tool before moving to a more rigorous method (RICE for backlog rank, MoSCoW for release scope). Do not use it as the final prioritization artifact — it loses precision for tied items in the same quadrant.</statement>
        <rationale>Value-Effort is intuitive ("do the Quick Wins first") but two Major Projects at (8 value, 7 effort) and (9 value, 8 effort) both land in the same quadrant with no relative ranking. Use it to frame discussion, then apply RICE for the deterministic output.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-by-step-process">
      <p>Five steps drive the prioritization workflow: (1) Choose Prioritization Method — BA locks the method before elicitation, (2) Gather Input — collect stakeholder perspectives (value, complexity, risk, dependencies), (3) Apply Method — use chosen method consistently, (4) Resolve Conflicts — reconcile disagreements with data, (5) Communicate Results — explain method, show results, get buy-in.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Lock the method before elicitation begins. The BA announces "We are using RICE for this backlog prioritization" and cannot switch mid-run even if results displease stakeholders.</statement>
        <rationale>Method-shopping (run RICE, switch to MoSCoW when results displease) destroys credibility. Locking the method first signals the decision is process-driven, not outcome-driven. Document why you picked this method (backlog size, stakeholder count, data availability, release vs backlog).</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Input gathering must separate elicitation into value-only (stakeholder opinion) and effort (engineering estimate). Stakeholders should NOT score effort; delivery owns that estimate. Value and effort are scored independently, then combined by the method.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing value and effort during elicitation produces scope inflation. Stakeholders overestimate effort, call high-effort items "low effort" to justify prioritization, or anchor engineering's estimate. Separating them forces explicit trade-off discussion.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="handling-disagreements">
      <p>When stakeholders conflict: (1) revisit criteria — remind everyone of the framework, (2) use data — bring metrics and evidence, (3) consider perspectives — each stakeholder sees different value, (4) find compromise — phase approach, conditions, (5) escalate — Product Owner or Sponsor decides and the BA documents the decision. The reconciliation process is as important as the method itself.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Elicit individual scores before group consensus. Compute mean and standard deviation. Reconcile only rows with σ (standard deviation) > threshold (0.8 on 1-5 scale, or 20% on RICE Reach). Lock the method before scoring begins.</statement>
        <rationale>Group scoring defaults to the loudest voice. Individual scoring then aggregation surfaces hidden disagreement (σ > 0.8 means the team fundamentally disagrees on relative importance). Reconciliation is targeted to the few high-disagreement items and documented with the rationale for the final decision.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Document the reconciliation outcome: "Finance scored this 4, Engineering scored 2. After discussion, agreed to 3 because [reason]: [date], [attendees]." This audit trail justifies the priority record to stakeholders who lost their item.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholders ask "Why is that feature lower priority than mine?" The reconciliation record answers: "This is why we collectively valued yours at X and theirs at Y, here's the conversation that led to that." Without the record, the priority looks arbitrary.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>HiPPO weighting — highest-paid voice anchors group sessions and reshapes consensus.</description>
        <reason>The senior person scores 5, others follow. Elicit individually first, compute mean and σ. Reconcile only the high-σ rows. When the SVP walks in and says "that's a 5", the team's individual scores vanish. Use async scoring (Airtable form, Notion DB, CSV upload) to prevent this.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <example type="good" title="Reconciliation documentation">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Priority Reconciliation Notes

**Feature:** API Webhooks

**Individual Scores (before reconciliation):**
- Product: 5 (massively important for integrations)
- Engineering: 2 (3 person-weeks, tech debt impact)
- Sales: 4 (two enterprise customers requesting)
- Support: 3 (reduces manual sync work 20%)

**Std Dev:** 1.16 (high disagreement, σ > threshold)

**Reconciliation Session:** 2024-04-15, 30 min, [attendees listed]

**Discussion:**
- Product: "Webhooks unlock the integration ecosystem; estimated 5% ARR upside from partners."
- Engineering: "Cost is not just build; ongoing maintenance, security audit, versioning. Tech debt for 6 months."
- Sales: "Two named deals ($50k each) are blocked without webhooks."
- Support: "Even one webhook setup removes 30 support tickets/quarter."

**Final Score:** 3.5 (weighted toward Product and Sales evidence)

**Rationale:** Two large deals unblock us; engineering cost is real but manageable if we timebox scope (webhooks v1 = Events only, no filtering). Ranked #7 in backlog.

**Decision Owner:** Product Manager (agreed)
        ]]></code>
        <note>Detailed reconciliation notes prevent the "why is my item not first?" conversation from becoming a data-free dispute.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="prioritization-in-agile">
      <p>Agile prioritization works at two levels: backlog (Product Owner stack-ranks items in priority order, re-prioritized each sprint) and release (MoSCoW or RICE to carve out the release scope, then stack-rank within categories).</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Backlog prioritization is ordinal (stack rank: #1, #2, #3…). Release prioritization is categorical (MoSCoW: Must, Should, Could) or scored (RICE: rank by score). Do not mix — "Must Have, rank 23" is meaningless.</statement>
        <rationale>The two artifacts serve different purposes: backlog answers "what do we work on next sprint?"; release answers "what scope commits do we make?" Using both on the same item creates confusion about whether the item is in or out.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Re-prioritization happens every sprint review (backlog) or every quarter (release). Do not set priorities at planning and forget; the world moves faster than quarterly plans.</statement>
        <rationale>Stale priorities are a common failure: scope is locked in January, market moves, and the team ships January's priorities in March with no adjustment. Re-prioritization triggers (sprint review, or when a new high-value item arrives) keep delivery aligned to current reality.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <p>Five mistakes derail prioritization: (1) Everything is Must — no real prioritization, (2) HiPPO effect — Highest Paid Person's Opinion dominates, (3) Ignoring effort — all focus on value, (4) No criteria — gut feeling decisions, (5) One-time exercise — not revisiting priorities.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>If more than 60% of effort is consumed by Must/High/Critical items, the prioritization is rejected and re-run with a forcing function (RICE or weighted scoring) that forces relative ranking.</statement>
        <rationale>Default group behavior assigns everything to the top category. A credible prioritization distributes across categories; flat distribution signals incomplete elicitation or that the team does not believe in the prioritization method.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Elicit individual scores before group consensus. Compute mean and standard deviation. Reconcile only rows with σ > threshold (0.8 on 1-5, or 20% on RICE Reach). Lock the method before scoring begins.</statement>
        <rationale>These three steps prevent HiPPO, method-shopping, and guessing. Individual scoring surfaces genuine disagreement; high-σ rows get discussion; method-locking prevents the stakeholder who dislikes RICE results from switching to MoSCoW.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="traceability-and-documentation">
      <p>Prioritization must link back to requirements. Every prioritized item needs a requirement ID, title, type (functional/non-functional/constraint), source, and acceptance criteria. Traceability ensures that when scope changes, the team knows which requirement docs to update and which stakeholders to notify.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Require `req_id` (e.g., REQ-001) for every item before prioritization. Free-text items ("Export to PDF") without IDs cannot be traced to requirements docs; when scope changes, no one knows which docs to update and which stakeholder committed to the definition.</statement>
        <rationale>Traceability is the difference between a defensible prioritization and a hand-wavy artifact. "Export to PDF" vs. "REQ-042: Users must export reports to PDF with chart/table support." The latter links to a requirement doc with acceptance criteria, estimate, owner, and stakeholder commitment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Update requirement frontmatter after prioritization: priority field, priority_method, priority_setter, priority_locked_at, and reconciliation notes. This becomes the audit trail for future scope discussions.</statement>
        <rationale>When a stakeholder asks three months later "Why isn't that feature in Q3?", the requirement doc shows the priority decision and the rationale. Without frontmatter, priorities look arbitrary.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Best practices ensure prioritization is defensible, repeatable, and tied to business outcomes. Lock the method before elicitation, measure outcomes against predictions, reconcile disagreements with data, and document all decisions with rationale.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Lock the method *before* elicitation. Switching methods mid-run (e.g., running MoSCoW, then switching to RICE because results displease) destroys BA credibility and creates the false record that justifies undelivered scope.</statement>
        <rationale>Method selection is a process choice, not a result-dependent choice. Document why you picked MoSCoW over RICE (bounded scope, clear Must/Should boundaries) and stick to it even if the results surprise stakeholders. Changing methods mid-run signals that the outcome mattered more than the process, which is the beginning of the false record problem.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Re-prioritize monthly or every quarter. Stale priorities are worse than no priorities — they commit the team to features the market no longer values. Set a calendar reminder or tie re-prioritization to sprint reviews and quarterly planning ceremonies.</statement>
        <rationale>Prioritization is not a one-time event; it is a standing process. Products evolve; features that were Must in Q1 may be Won't in Q3 as the market moves, competitors launch, or user research reveals different needs. Re-prioritization keeps delivery aligned to reality.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Validate RICE predictions quarterly: compare predicted Reach/Impact/Confidence against actual metrics (adoption, engagement, revenue) and adjust the model. If Reach predictions miss by >2x, flag it and retrain the scoring or use a simpler method.</statement>
        <rationale>RICE scores are only as good as the data feeding them. Without feedback, teams keep making the same estimation mistakes. Quarterly review of prediction accuracy calibrates confidence levels and surfaces when the method itself is not working.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>The BA owns the process; agents own the artifacts. Five phases drive multi-stakeholder prioritization: (1) Method selection — agent recommends method with rationale, (2) Normalize input set — agent ensures all items have req_id, type, status, (3) Elicit scores individually, compute aggregates and flags, (4) Apply method deterministically, (5) Publish report with sensitivity analysis and update requirement frontmatter.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Agents generate artifacts (scores, ranks, reports); the BA makes three decisions: lock the method, approve reconciliation results, and sign off on final scope. Do not automate the decision-maker role.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents are fast at mechanics (compute RICE, aggregate stakeholder scores, flag high-σ rows); humans are good at judgment (when to compromise, which stakeholder perspective matters most, escalation). The BA stays in the loop at method lock, reconciliation, and sign-off.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/moscow-prioritization-template.md" purpose="MoSCoW template with Must/Should/Could/Won't sections and distribution tracking."/>
      <template path="templates/rice-scoring-template.md" purpose="RICE scoring matrix with Reach/Impact/Confidence/Effort and final rank."/>
      <template path="templates/value-effort-matrix-template.md" purpose="Value-Effort quadrant analysis with quick-wins and major-projects tracks."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/standards-and-resources/babok/"/>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MoSCoW_method"/>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog/rice-framework"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
