<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="threads-basics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>smm-manager</domain>
    <summary>Meta Threads setup and content strategy. Text-first platform leveraging Instagram audience. Growth from conversational content, high cadence (7-10/day), reply velocity, not volume alone.</summary>
    <category>social-media</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>threads</tag>
      <tag>meta</tag>
      <tag>social-media</tag>
      <tag>content-strategy</tag>
      <tag>community</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Threads Basics</title>

    <summary>A setup and content strategy methodology for Meta Threads, a text-first social platform that leverages an existing Instagram audience. Growth is driven by conversational content (hot takes, questions, personal stories), high posting cadence (7-10 posts/day), and reply velocity — not just posting volume. The platform rewards authentic engagement; algorithm suppresses link-heavy posts and low-reply accounts.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Threads crossed 100M users rapidly, giving early adopters a significant reach advantage before competition densifies. Accounts that simply cross-post from X/Twitter underperform because Threads rewards shorter, more conversational formats. No official scheduling API exists as of 2026 — agents can draft content packs, but manual posting by the operator is required.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Standing up a brand or founder presence on Threads while leveraging an existing Instagram audience.</item>
        <item>Drafting daily content packs (5-12 posts) for a SMM operator who has defined voice guidelines.</item>
        <item>Auditing an account that cross-posts from X/Twitter verbatim and is underperforming.</item>
        <item>Hot-take and conversation-starter ideation for accounts where engagement bait is acceptable.</item>
        <item>Bootstrapping a new niche account that needs cadence and format scaffolding.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Target audience does not overlap with Instagram demographics (e.g., enterprise security buyers — use LinkedIn).</item>
        <item>Brand voice forbids hot takes, personal stories, or unmoderated conversation.</item>
        <item>Team has zero capacity for replies — Threads' algorithm rewards reply velocity; posting alone plateaus within weeks.</item>
        <item>Regulated industries (finance, healthcare) where every post needs compliance review incompatible with the required cadence.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="profile-optimization">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use the same username as Instagram; keep bio under 160 characters with a clear what/who/CTA structure.</statement>
        <rationale>Threads profile syncs from Instagram. Consistent username maximizes discoverability from the existing Instagram audience. Short bios with clear purpose outperform lengthy ones because Threads users scroll quickly.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Username: same as Instagram (auto-synced).</item>
        <item>Display name: may include keyword for searchability.</item>
        <item>Bio: 160 chars max, formula: [What you do] + [Who you help] + [CTA or personality].</item>
        <item>Link: one URL; update based on current campaign goal.</item>
        <item>Profile photo: same as Instagram (synced automatically).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="instagram-integration">
      <rule>
        <statement>Import followers from Instagram immediately after account creation to seed the initial audience.</statement>
        <rationale>Threads provides a built-in follower migration from Instagram. Not importing leaves the account starting from zero when an audience already exists on a connected platform.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="week-1-setup-checklist">
      <list>
        <item>Create Threads account via Instagram.</item>
        <item>Optimize profile (bio, link).</item>
        <item>Import followers from Instagram.</item>
        <item>Research successful accounts in niche.</item>
        <item>Plan first week of content (minimum 5 posts/day).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="content-pillars">
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag every draft with its content pillar; reject pillar-less drafts. Cap agent-generated posts at 50% of weekly volume.</statement>
        <rationale>Without pillar tags, agents drift toward whatever style won last week. The other 50% must come from the operator's lived context (replies, real-time reactions) because the algorithm rewards authentic conversation, not publishing volume.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Opinions: industry takes, hot takes (2-3/day).</item>
        <item>Value: tips, insights, learnings (1-2/day).</item>
        <item>Questions: engagement drivers (1/day).</item>
        <item>Personal: behind the scenes, stories (1/day).</item>
        <item>Curated: interesting finds, quotes (1/day).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="posting-cadence">
      <rule>
        <statement>Post minimum 3 times/day; optimal 7-10 times/day. Reply within the first hour of each post for algorithm boost.</statement>
        <rationale>Threads' algorithm rewards reply velocity, not just post volume. Accounts that post but do not reply plateau within weeks. Replies drive reach more than the post itself.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep agent-generated posts under 500 characters; validate length programmatically after generation.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs are unreliable at character-count limits. Over-length posts fail silently or look unprofessional on Threads' compact format. Include a hard length constraint in every prompt and check post-generation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cross-posting-anti-pattern">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Cross-posting X/Twitter threads verbatim to Threads.</description>
        <reason>Twitter irony, link references, and thread formatting do not translate. Threads rewards warmth and conversational register; verbatim X content reads as out-of-place and suppresses engagement. Force a register-shift rewrite step.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent auto-posts to Threads on a schedule.</description>
        <reason>No stable scheduling API exists as of 2026. Meta is aggressive about automation detection. Best practice: agent drafts and ranks 20 candidates, operator picks 7-10 and posts manually within prime windows.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent uses identical hook phrases across drafts ("Hot take:", "Honest question:").</description>
        <reason>Hook repetition reduces engagement. Enforce banned-bigram lists in the prompt to force variety across a content pack.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent includes engagement-bait phrases: "comment X for Y", "tag a friend", "follow for more".</description>
        <reason>These phrases are flagged by Meta and suppress reach. Explicitly prohibit them in every prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A Claude subagent can ideate the daily post pack from a content pillar mix, rewrite Twitter/X posts into native Threads voice, and draft reply scaffolds for the operator to send manually. The agent should NOT auto-post: there is no stable scheduling API, and Meta is aggressive about automation detection. Best division of labor — agent drafts and ranks 20 candidates, operator picks 7-10 and posts manually within the day's prime windows.</p>
      <p>Best practices: Cap agent-generated posts at 50% of weekly volume; the other 50% comes from operator's lived context (replies, real-time reactions). Keep one human-written reply per outbound post — replies drive the algorithm more than the post itself. Tag every draft with its content pillar; without tags, the agent drifts toward whatever style won last week. Rotate prime windows weekly (8-10 / 12-14 / 18-21) and let the agent A/B test cadence within those slots. Strip URLs from agent output unless explicitly allowed; Threads suppresses link-heavy posts. Maintain a "do not post" list (tickers, regulated claims, named competitors) and inject it into every prompt as a hard constraint.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-constraints">
      <p>No official scheduling API at the start of 2026; tools that "schedule" Threads use unofficial automation that breaks regularly. Algorithm rewards conversation, not posting volume — agents that only post (do not reply) plateau within weeks. Cross-posting from X verbatim is a known anti-pattern; agents must rewrite, not duplicate, which costs tokens. Engagement metrics in native insights are limited; attribution to revenue is near-zero for organic Threads. Trend-jacking has a 24-48h half-life; agents running on slow cadence (daily) miss the window. Expect steady platform iteration and API changes.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>Official API: Meta Threads API (Graph) with partial support (posting + insights for approved Meta apps; OAuth required, limited rollout). SaaS platforms: Buffer (native Threads scheduling via official integration), Hootsuite (native Threads support since 2024), Later (Threads scheduling, link-in-bio), Typefully (cross-posting X→Threads with rewrites), Metricool (Threads analytics + scheduling), Postiz (OSS scheduler with Threads support — operator hosts). CLI tools: instagrapi (Python, unofficial Instagram/Threads access — read only, breakage risk), threads-api (Node, community, read public posts; rate-limited and unstable), imagemagick/ffmpeg (prep optional 9:16 visuals), pandoc (convert markdown content packs into operator-friendly docs).</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/bio-templates.txt" purpose="Founder, expert, and creator bio formulas."/>
      <template path="templates/daily-posts.txt" purpose="Morning/afternoon/evening post templates and multi-post thread format."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-ideation.txt" purpose="Daily content pack ideation prompt with pillar tags and hook scoring."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developers.facebook.com/docs/threads"/>
      <link href="https://about.fb.com/news/tag/threads/"/>
      <link href="https://buffer.com/resources/threads/"/>
      <link href="https://blog.hootsuite.com/threads/"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/gitroomhq/postiz-app"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
