<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Data Modeling Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every data-modeling application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Produce conceptual, logical, and physical artefacts in that order. Conceptual: entity names + relationships only. Logical: attributes, primary/foreign keys, cardinality, 3NF. Physical: tables, exact data types, indexes, partitioning, engine-specific constraints.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Skipping logical produces tables that mirror screen layouts and break under the second feature.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every physical schema MUST list its top 10 access patterns and prove each one is index-backed via</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Indexes designed after queries arrive are 5-10x more expensive to add under load.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose Relational (PostgreSQL) for structured data with complex relationships, transactions, and ACID guarantees. Choose Document (MongoDB) for flexible schema, hierarchical data, and aggregate-oriented access. Choose Key-Value (Redis, DynamoDB) for extreme low-latency simple lookups. Choose Wide-Column (Cassandra, ScyllaDB) for high write throughput and predictable partition-key access. Choose Graph (Neo4j) for highly connected data with multi-hop traversals. Choose Time-Series (TimescaleDB, InfluxDB, ClickHouse) for timestamped data points and time-window aggregation. Choose Vector (pgvector, Qdrant, Weaviate) for similarity search on embeddings. Choose Search (Elasticsearch, Meilisearch) for full-text and faceted queries.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each engine optimises a specific access pattern; mismatched paradigm choice forces application-side workarounds that cost 20-30% of code volume.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default to PostgreSQL when in doubt. It covers relational, JSONB documents, full-text search, vector (pgvector), and time-series (TimescaleDB) within a single operational footprint.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Solo builders cannot afford to operate four engines; PostgreSQL collapses the surface area while staying fast enough for most workloads to 100M rows.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>1NF: atomic column values, no repeating groups. 2NF: 1NF + no partial dependencies on the primary key. 3NF: 2NF + no transitive dependencies (non-key column depends only on the primary key). BCNF: every determinant is a candidate key — apply only when 3NF still has anomalies.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">3NF eliminates duplication and update anomalies. Over-normalising past 3NF generates excessive joins without practical benefit; deliberate denormalisation past 3NF is a paradigm choice (e.g. wide-column, document) not a default.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Denormalise only when an</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Undocumented denormalisation rots silently — readers add it, writers forget the second copy, data drifts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Index every foreign key column and every column that appears in a WHERE/JOIN/ORDER BY of a top-10 access pattern. Composite indexes follow the equality-then-range column order. Use partial indexes for sparse predicates (e.g.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Foreign keys without indexes cause N+1 lookups and table-level locks during cascading deletes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plan partitioning before a table is expected to exceed 10M rows or 10 GB. Use range partitioning for time-series, hash for high-cardinality writes, list for small enumerated tenants.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Re-partitioning a populated table requires downtime or complex zero-downtime migration tooling; plan it once at design time.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-23 chunk-00 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
