<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Micro-MVP Cut Rubric Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that govern mechanical cutting of a feature to a day-sized slice. These prevent the most common solo-builder failure: "small" features that quietly grow to three days.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-six-axis-cut" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cut along six axes: data model, surface, permissions, persistence, tests, UI polish. For each axis, write the minimum slice + deferred items. Reject scoping that cuts only along 1-2 axes (insufficient discipline).</statement>
      <rationale source="solo-builder velocity studies">Cutting only along "surface" leaves data + permissions oversized. Six axes force a holistic minimum slice; the slice gets 5-10× smaller than a single-axis cut.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-day-sized-ceiling" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The output slice ships in ≤ 8 hours of focused work. Reject slices that exceed 8 hours OR cannot be split into a single coherent slice + deferred follow-ups.</statement>
      <rationale source="flow-state research">8 hours is the practical ceiling for a single coherent build session. Past this, context switches eat the day; flow breaks; "done today" slips to "done this week."</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-deferral-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every deferred item is recorded with axis + reason in the deferral_list. Reject silent deferrals ("we'll figure it out later"). Deferrals become explicit follow-up slices in the backlog.</statement>
      <rationale source="scope-creep audits">Silent deferrals re-enter as scope creep mid-build. Explicit deferrals make the next-day choice visible and reduce mid-build temptation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-smoke-only-tests" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>First slice ships with smoke tests only: one happy-path, one error-path. Reject demands for comprehensive test coverage in the first slice. Coverage expansion is a deferred slice.</statement>
      <rationale source="lean shipping practice">Comprehensive testing on the first slice doubles slice cost without proportional confidence gain. Smoke is sufficient to catch "did it boot at all?" — the actual user-validation happens next.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-raw-ui-ship" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>First slice ships with raw UI: default styles, no animations, no responsive polish. Polish is a deferred slice. Reject pre-launch designer review or polish hours billed to the first slice.</statement>
      <rationale source="user-validation theory">Polish before user validation is sunk cost if the slice misses. Raw UI gets the data; polish responds to real usage signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Six-axis cut for a notification feature">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Feature: "User can mute a project notification"

Cut:
  data model:    single boolean field `muted` on Project. Defer: per-channel toggles.
  surface:       one toggle on /projects/:id page. Defer: bulk mute, settings page.
  permissions:   owner-only. Defer: team-level mute, role-based mute.
  persistence:   simple DB update. (Already supported; nothing to defer.)
  tests:         smoke = "owner toggles, gets back muted=true". Defer: error paths, race tests.
  UI polish:     default checkbox label "Mute notifications". Defer: animated toggle, copy review.

Estimate: 4 hours. Ship today. Deferred items → next-slice candidates.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates all 5 rules — 6 axes, day-sized, explicit deferrals, smoke only, raw UI.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Hidden scope creep slice">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Feature: "User can mute a project notification"

Spec:
  Add muted field, build settings page with per-channel toggles, add
  team-level mute for admins, write 8 tests, animated toggle with
  dark-mode variant.

Estimate: 16 hours. Ships in 2.5 days due to context switches.
Deferred items: not documented.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1, r2, r3, r4, r5 violations — slice exceeds day, no axis discipline, no deferrals listed.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
