<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="risk-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Identify threats and opportunities, rate by probability and impact, assign owners with triggers, plan responses, monitor weekly. Every risk needs a named owner and explicit triggers.</summary>
    <category>uncertainty</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>risk-management</tag>
      <tag>probability</tag>
      <tag>impact</tag>
      <tag>emv</tag>
      <tag>contingency</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Risk Management</title>

    <summary>Identify threats and opportunities, rate them by probability and impact, assign owners with observable triggers, plan responses, and monitor weekly. The rule: every risk must have a named owner (a person, not "the team") and explicit triggers — observable signals that convert an abstract risk into an actionable event. "Accept" is not a free pass; it requires a contingency budget line equal to the risk's EMV.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Surprises become crises because risks were identified but not tracked. EMV (Probability × Impact in dollars) provides a relative ranking and seeds contingency reserves — it does not imply precision. A risk that materializes becomes an Issue and leaves the register; double-tracking inflates the register and hides what is actually in flight. Risk reviews must be short (15 min) and frequent (weekly), not 2-hour quarterly exercises.</p>
      <p>Probability × Impact scores are subjective; team optimism systematically under-rates probability of own work failing. Black-swan / unknown-unknown risks are by definition not in the register; rely on resilience design, not prediction. "Accept" is the most-abused response: it lets teams skip planning while pretending to manage the risk. Registers go stale within weeks if not actively reviewed; a 6-month-old register is worse than none (false confidence). EMV math implies precision the inputs don't have; use it for relative ranking only.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Project initiation: build initial risk register before charter sign-off</item>
        <item>Stage-gate reviews: refresh probability/impact and trigger statuses</item>
        <item>Pre-launch (T-2 weeks): focused launch-risk pass with rollback plans</item>
        <item>After incidents: feed lessons back as new risks for similar projects</item>
        <item>High-uncertainty domains: new technology, new vendor, regulatory change</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Trivial internal task (1 person, under 1 week, no external dependency) — overhead exceeds value</item>
        <item>Pure agile teams with strong incremental delivery — short cycles already de-risk; use a "top 5" sticky list</item>
        <item>Crisis already in progress — switch to incident response; add lessons to register afterward</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="risk-types">
      <list>
        <item>Threat — negative risk; probability × impact = potential loss</item>
        <item>Opportunity — positive risk; probability × impact = potential gain; use Exploit/Enhance/Share/Accept strategies</item>
        <item>Known risk — identified and plannable; goes in the register with a response</item>
        <item>Unknown-unknown — cannot predict; rely on resilience design, not prevention</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Track opportunities, not just threats; use symmetric response strategies (Exploit/Enhance/Share/Accept).</statement>
        <rationale>Risk registers that list only threats miss half the picture. Opportunities require active responses to capture; an unmanaged opportunity is a threat of lost value.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="four-step-process">
      <list>
        <item>Step 1 — Identify: brainstorm from charter + WBS + lessons learned + risk categories (technical, external, organizational, project); each risk needs a quoted source from inputs</item>
        <item>Step 2 — Analyze: qualitative P×I matrix for all; quantitative EMV = P_numeric × impact_USD for risks that will feed contingency reserves</item>
        <item>Step 3 — Plan Responses: assign a named owner and observable triggers; select response strategy; fund Accept responses with contingency</item>
        <item>Step 4 — Monitor: weekly 15-minute review; compare register vs current status reports; convert materialized risks to Issues and remove from register</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every risk must have a named owner (a person, not "the team") and explicit observable triggers.</statement>
        <rationale>Risks without owners are ignored. Triggers convert abstract risks into actionable events — without them, the risk stays abstract until it is already a crisis.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="response-strategies">
      <p>Threat strategies:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Avoid — eliminate the risk source (e.g., remove unproven technology from scope)</item>
        <item>Transfer — shift to third party via insurance, fixed-price contract, or warranty</item>
        <item>Mitigate — reduce probability or impact (e.g., cross-train backup, add automated tests)</item>
        <item>Accept — acknowledge and provision contingency equal to EMV; never accept without a budget line</item>
      </list>
      <p>Opportunity strategies:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Exploit — ensure the opportunity materializes (e.g., assign dedicated resource)</item>
        <item>Enhance — increase probability or impact (e.g., early market seeding)</item>
        <item>Share — partner with another party to maximize capture</item>
        <item>Accept — take it if it comes without special action</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Set contingency reserve = sum(EMV) of all Accepted threats; management reserve sits on top for unknown-unknowns.</statement>
        <rationale>Accepting a risk without provisioning a contingency budget is hoping, not managing. EMV-based reserves give the sponsor a defensible number for the risk budget line.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="register-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Stale risk register never reviewed after creation.</description>
        <reason>A 6-month-old register is worse than none because it creates false confidence. Risks have resolved, new risks have emerged, and the register now misleads rather than informs. Weekly 15-minute reviews are mandatory.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using "Accept" response without a contingency budget line.</description>
        <reason>"Accept" is the most-abused response: it lets teams skip planning while pretending to manage the risk. Accepting without provisioning a reserve is hoping. Every Accept must map to a specific contingency amount equal to its EMV.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Double-tracking materialized risks as both a Risk and an Issue.</description>
        <reason>When a risk materializes, convert it to an Issue and remove it from the register. Keeping it in both places inflates the risk count and confuses status reporting.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Setting risk reviews as 2-hour quarterly events instead of 15-minute weekly sessions.</description>
        <reason>Quarterly reviews find risks that have already become crises. Weekly 15-minute reviews catch drift while corrective action is still affordable.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Require each agent-identified risk to cite a specific quoted source from inputs; reject generic risks without evidence.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs generate generic risks ("scope creep", "team turnover") without grounding in project specifics. Requiring a source quote forces actual analysis of the charter, WBS, and vendor list.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Probability ratings cluster around "Medium" — too safe; require justification per rating ("M because vendor missed last 2 SLAs in Q1")</item>
        <item>Numerical EMV implies false precision; always print confidence interval or skip dollar values in agent output if inputs lack dollar-denominated impact estimates</item>
        <item>Agent may merge distinct risks into one (loses owner clarity) or over-split one into many (inflates register); constrain via target count (8-15 risks for a 6-month project)</item>
        <item>Auto-closing risks based on absence of mention in status reports is wrong — no-mention is not evidence of resolution; require an explicit "closed by [person] on [date]" field</item>
        <item>Do not let an agent tag a risk as Accept without a budget/contingency line item — it must propose a specific dollar amount or token-effort equivalent</item>
        <item>Pair risk identification with Change Control: any approved change request triggers a risk re-rating pass</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A subagent can scaffold the initial register from charter, scope, WBS, similar past projects' lessons, and a prompt list of risk categories. Use a 2-pass model: first pass enumerates, second pass deduplicates and rates. Keep numerical scoring deterministic via a script — let the LLM produce candidates, the script computes Score and EMV. Human-in-loop required for risk responses (Avoid/Transfer/Mitigate/Accept) because they imply budget and decisions. Schedule weekly automated re-scan of register vs new comms logs to surface drift.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-pm-agent (drafts register, runs weekly review), faion-business-analyst (derives requirement-driven risks: assumptions made → risks), faion-improver (pulls lessons-learned from done projects and seeds new risks), faion-sdd-executor-agent (links risks to specific SDD tasks via risk_id field).</p>
      <p>Prompt pattern: Input charter.md, wbs.md, prior_lessons.md, vendor_list.md; Output risks.yaml (id, title, category{technical|external|org|project}, probability{L,M,H}, impact{L,M,H}, type{threat|opportunity}, trigger, owner_role, response_strategy, response_plan, status). Rules: each risk has a quoted source from input; no invented vendors.</p>
      <p>Weekly audit: compare current register against last 7 days of status_reports. Flag: closed risks still listed; new issues mentioned twice but not in register; stale risks (no update in 30 days).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Track opportunities, not just threats — Exploit/Enhance/Share/Accept symmetric to threat strategies.</item>
        <item>Every risk has an Owner who is a person, not a role like "the team".</item>
        <item>Define explicit Triggers (observable signals) so risks become actionable, not abstract.</item>
        <item>Reserve contingency = sum(EMV) of accepted risks; management reserve sits on top for unknown-unknowns.</item>
        <item>Convert a risk that materialises into an Issue and remove it from the register (don't double-track).</item>
        <item>Risk reviews are short (15 min) but frequent (weekly) — not 2-hour quarterly drills.</item>
        <item>Pair with Change Control: any change request triggers a risk re-rating pass.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools: yq (filter risks by score, owner); jq (process JSON exports from Jira/Risk modules); python -m statistics / numpy (Monte Carlo for schedule risk (PERT)); pandoc (render register to DOCX for steering committee).</p>
      <p>Services and apps: Jira (Risk Register plugin, agent-friendly via REST API — use a Risk issue type with custom P/I fields); Atlassian Confluence (agent-friendly via REST API, common register host); Smartsheet (agent-friendly via REST + automations, triggers when status changes); Riskonnect (agent-friendly API, enterprise risk); ServiceNow GRC (agent-friendly Table API, for regulated industries); LogicManager (agent-friendly API, mid-market GRC); OpenRisk (FAIR, agent-friendly via Python lib pyfair, quantitative risk in dollar terms); Notion / Airtable (agent-friendly via REST API, lightweight registers for solo/small projects).</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/risk-register.md" purpose="Risk register table: ID, category, P, I, score, response, owner, trigger, status"/>
      <template path="templates/risk-response-plan.md" purpose="Individual risk response plan with prevention steps and fallback actions"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/risk-score.py" purpose="Compute Score and EMV from risks.yaml using deterministic P×I matrix"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.fairinstitute.org"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/mikefarah/yq"/>
      <link href="https://stedolan.github.io/jq"/>
      <link href="https://pandoc.org"/>
      <ref slug="pm-agile"/>
      <ref slug="pm-traditional"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
