<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="FinOps INFORM Phase — Cost Visibility Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules including a `skip-this-methodology` rule. Each pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="mandatory-tag-set" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All taggable resources MUST carry the mandatory tag set: `team`, `product`, `environment`, `cost-center`, `owner`. Untagged resources trigger a daily compliance report.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps INFORM phase">Without these five tags chargeback is impossible; every other FinOps practice depends on this.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="tag-policy-as-code" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tag policy MUST be declared as code (OPA, AWS Config, Azure Policy) and enforced at provisioning time. Manual tagging post-hoc is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Policy as code discipline">Manual tagging decays; preventive enforcement catches violations before they become spend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="dashboard-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A persistent cost dashboard MUST exist with at minimum: total spend, spend by team, spend by environment, spend by service. Refresh ≤24h.</statement>
      <rationale source="Dashboards as the org's shared truth">Verbal cost discussions diverge — a shared dashboard is the only stable artefact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="baseline-kpis-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>KPI baselines MUST be published: $/active-user, $/revenue, $/MAU (or domain equivalent). Without baselines, ROI of subsequent optimization is unmeasurable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Unit economics">Saving 20% on spend means nothing if revenue dropped 30%; unit metrics anchor the conversation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="coverage-gates" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tag coverage ≥80% is a hard gate for proceeding to OPTIMIZE phase; &lt;80% = stay in INFORM and fix tagging first.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sequencing discipline">Optimizing on noisy data produces wrong decisions; INFORM gates protect downstream work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip when (a) tag coverage ≥95% AND dashboards exist AND chargeback live; OR (b) single-team single-product environment where attribution overhead exceeds value.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scope guard">If INFORM is already done, time is better spent on OPTIMIZE; below-threshold orgs don't need the ceremony.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
