<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="immersive-design-principles Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for immersive-design-principles. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Name the immersion level explicitly before designing any spatial experience. Never conflate passthrough and fully immersive — their comfort, interaction, and accessibility constraints are different.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents conflate VR (occluded) and AR (passthrough); design decisions for one cause harm when applied to the other.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Place UI elements and interactive controls in the near zone (0.5-2 m), main content and interactive objects in the mid zone (2-10 m), and scenery in the far zone (10 m and beyond).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Objects placed outside their appropriate depth zone cause eye strain (too near) or interaction failure (too far); depth zones match natural human vergence and accommodation ranges in XR.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never head-lock UI elements. Use world-locked or body-locked panels at 1.5-3 m, eye level.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Head-locked UI follows every head movement and causes immediate nausea; world-locked UI stays stable as the user looks around.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Implement realistic motion physics: gravity, momentum, inertia, collision feedback, and synchronized haptics. Couple every visual transition with an audio and haptic cue.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Visual transitions without audio or haptic cues cause vestibular surprise — the brain expects multimodal confirmation of environment changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prefer user-initiated transitions over automatic ones; use gradual fade in/out (not instant) with audio cues and visual mode indicators.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sudden mode changes without user agency are a primary source of disorientation and loss of presence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Respond to physical space: adjust content to room size, warn about obstacles, reposition UI for comfort, and adapt to lighting conditions when in passthrough or blended modes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ignoring physical context in blended and passthrough modes creates collision risk and UI overlap with physical objects.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default every new XR experience to the highest-comfort settings; let users opt into lower comfort, never the opposite.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A 5-10% nausea-prone subgroup will fail experiences that test fine on the rest; conservative defaults protect the most sensitive users without restricting others.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always offer at least two locomotion methods (teleport plus smooth, or teleport plus seated). Pin teleport-as-default; smooth is opt-in with vignette on.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Smooth locomotion without teleport excludes motion-sensitive users and wheelchair users; agents recommend smooth as the "modern" default and must be explicitly corrected.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Minimum 90 FPS per eye for VR; 60 FPS minimum for AR. Maximum 20 ms head-tracking latency and 50 ms controller latency. Drop visual fidelity before dropping below the FPS floor.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dropping below the performance floor causes simulator sickness regardless of all other design decisions; frame rate is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use human-scale for familiar objects (doors 2 m, tables 70-75 cm, chairs 45 cm). When scaling differently, make it obvious with a size reference (human for scale) and gradual transition.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unexpected scale breaks depth perception and comfortable interaction; scale ambiguity is disorienting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep the floor/ground plane visible at all times with consistent appearance; maintain a stable horizon. These are the two primary grounding cues that reduce nausea.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Loss of ground plane causes floating feeling and disorientation; an unstable horizon is the single fastest driver of vestibular mismatch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Implement a guardian/chaperone system: visual boundary when approaching walls, haptic warning, audio alert option, pause on boundary crossing, easy re-centering.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Physical collisions with real-world objects are a safety hazard; guardian systems are the standard mitigation across all major XR platforms.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Add visual captions in 3D space for all audio-cued events; captions must be size- and position-adjustable.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Spatial-audio captions are commonly omitted; require a captions story for every voiced or audio-cued event in design review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Seated mode must be fully functional: every interaction reachable while seated, all content viewable without standing or walking. Wheelchair-user parity is a hard requirement, not an afterthought.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Seated mode is the most commonly omitted accessibility feature in room-scale VR design; agents skip it unless explicitly checked.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat WAI XAUR (W3C XR Accessibility User Requirements) as the requirements floor, not a nice-to-have. It covers disability cases that vendor design guidelines miss.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Platform-vendor guidelines (Meta, Apple, Valve) are consensus documents that lag novel interaction patterns; XAUR is the authoritative accessibility requirements source for XR.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
