<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-immersion-levels" title="Immersion Level Selection and Spatial Design Rules">
  <summary>Four immersion levels and their appropriate use cases, depth and layering rules, motion physics, and transition guidelines.</summary>

  <section title="Immersion level taxonomy">
    <p>Four levels, each with distinct design constraints: Passthrough (real world plus overlays; AR navigation, information overlay); Blended (mixed real and virtual; MR workspace with virtual monitors, productivity, collaboration); Fully Immersive (complete virtual environment; VR game, training simulation); Portal (windows into virtual space; VR meeting room view with easy exit).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Name the immersion level explicitly before designing any spatial experience. Never conflate passthrough and fully immersive — their comfort, interaction, and accessibility constraints are different.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents conflate VR (occluded) and AR (passthrough); design decisions for one cause harm when applied to the other.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Spatial depth zones">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place UI elements and interactive controls in the near zone (0.5-2 m), main content and interactive objects in the mid zone (2-10 m), and scenery in the far zone (10 m and beyond).</statement>
      <rationale>Objects placed outside their appropriate depth zone cause eye strain (too near) or interaction failure (too far); depth zones match natural human vergence and accommodation ranges in XR.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never head-lock UI elements. Use world-locked or body-locked panels at 1.5-3 m, eye level.</statement>
      <rationale>Head-locked UI follows every head movement and causes immediate nausea; world-locked UI stays stable as the user looks around.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Motion and transitions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement realistic motion physics: gravity, momentum, inertia, collision feedback, and synchronized haptics. Couple every visual transition with an audio and haptic cue.</statement>
      <rationale>Visual transitions without audio or haptic cues cause vestibular surprise — the brain expects multimodal confirmation of environment changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer user-initiated transitions over automatic ones; use gradual fade in/out (not instant) with audio cues and visual mode indicators.</statement>
      <rationale>Sudden mode changes without user agency are a primary source of disorientation and loss of presence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Respond to physical space: adjust content to room size, warn about obstacles, reposition UI for comfort, and adapt to lighting conditions when in passthrough or blended modes.</statement>
      <rationale>Ignoring physical context in blended and passthrough modes creates collision risk and UI overlap with physical objects.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
