<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-comfort-and-safety" title="Motion Comfort, Safety, Performance, and Comfort Settings">
  <summary>Motion sickness causes and mitigations, guardian system requirements, scale conventions, and performance floors for XR experiences.</summary>

  <section title="Motion sickness mitigations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default every new XR experience to the highest-comfort settings; let users opt into lower comfort, never the opposite.</statement>
      <rationale>A 5-10% nausea-prone subgroup will fail experiences that test fine on the rest; conservative defaults protect the most sensitive users without restricting others.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always offer at least two locomotion methods (teleport plus smooth, or teleport plus seated). Pin teleport-as-default; smooth is opt-in with vignette on.</statement>
      <rationale>Smooth locomotion without teleport excludes motion-sensitive users and wheelchair users; agents recommend smooth as the "modern" default and must be explicitly corrected.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Motion sickness: fixed reference points (cockpit, dashboard, ground plane), vignetting during movement, teleportation instead of smooth movement.</item>
      <item>Disorientation: consistent horizon, north indicator, stable floor and ground plane always visible.</item>
      <item>Eye strain: proper convergence distance, focal point guidance, correct depth of field.</item>
      <item>Arm fatigue: supported positions, alternative inputs, rest prompts at intervals.</item>
      <item>Simulator sickness: maintain 90+ FPS and under 20 ms latency; reduce scene complexity before dropping frame rate.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Performance floors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Minimum 90 FPS per eye for VR; 60 FPS minimum for AR. Maximum 20 ms head-tracking latency and 50 ms controller latency. Drop visual fidelity before dropping below the FPS floor.</statement>
      <rationale>Dropping below the performance floor causes simulator sickness regardless of all other design decisions; frame rate is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/comfort-settings.json">Default comfort-settings schema covering locomotion, visual, audio, and interaction</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Scale and grounding">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use human-scale for familiar objects (doors 2 m, tables 70-75 cm, chairs 45 cm). When scaling differently, make it obvious with a size reference (human for scale) and gradual transition.</statement>
      <rationale>Unexpected scale breaks depth perception and comfortable interaction; scale ambiguity is disorienting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the floor/ground plane visible at all times with consistent appearance; maintain a stable horizon. These are the two primary grounding cues that reduce nausea.</statement>
      <rationale>Loss of ground plane causes floating feeling and disorientation; an unstable horizon is the single fastest driver of vestibular mismatch.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Guardian and play space">
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement a guardian/chaperone system: visual boundary when approaching walls, haptic warning, audio alert option, pause on boundary crossing, easy re-centering.</statement>
      <rationale>Physical collisions with real-world objects are a safety hazard; guardian systems are the standard mitigation across all major XR platforms.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
