<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-accessibility" title="XR Accessibility Coverage per Disability Category">
  <summary>Vision, hearing, mobility, and cognitive accessibility requirements for immersive experiences, grounded in WAI XAUR.</summary>

  <section title="WAI XAUR as the floor">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat WAI XAUR (W3C XR Accessibility User Requirements) as the requirements floor, not a nice-to-have. It covers disability cases that vendor design guidelines miss.</statement>
      <rationale>Platform-vendor guidelines (Meta, Apple, Valve) are consensus documents that lag novel interaction patterns; XAUR is the authoritative accessibility requirements source for XR.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Vision">
    <list>
      <item>High contrast mode with toggle.</item>
      <item>Large text options; minimum readable size is larger in XR than on screen — test at the actual viewing distance.</item>
      <item>Audio descriptions for all informative visual elements.</item>
      <item>Haptic feedback as alternative to visual-only signals.</item>
      <item>Voice navigation for all interactions.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Hearing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add visual captions in 3D space for all audio-cued events; captions must be size- and position-adjustable.</statement>
      <rationale>Spatial-audio captions are commonly omitted; require a captions story for every voiced or audio-cued event in design review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Haptic feedback synchronized with sound events.</item>
      <item>Visual indicators (directional flash) for audio alerts from off-screen sources.</item>
      <item>Per-source volume controls.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Mobility">
    <rule>
      <statement>Seated mode must be fully functional: every interaction reachable while seated, all content viewable without standing or walking. Wheelchair-user parity is a hard requirement, not an afterthought.</statement>
      <rationale>Seated mode is the most commonly omitted accessibility feature in room-scale VR design; agents skip it unless explicitly checked.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Teleportation for all movement (not just as comfort option).</item>
      <item>Voice commands for all actions.</item>
      <item>Controller-free options where platform supports hand tracking.</item>
      <item>Adjustable height settings to accommodate different physical heights and seated postures.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Cognitive">
    <list>
      <item>Simplified UI mode with reduced information density.</item>
      <item>Clear, step-by-step instructions; no assumed prior XR experience.</item>
      <item>Pauseable experiences with no time pressure during paused state.</item>
      <item>Difficulty adjustment where applicable.</item>
      <item>Memory aids: hints, reminders, progress indicators.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
