<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cloud Cost Tagging Policy Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>≥5 testable rules grounding the finops-devops-cost-tagging methodology, each paired with rationale and source reference.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="required-tag-set" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enforce a required tag set — env, owner, cost-center, application, terraform — on every resource that can be tagged.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Five mandatory tags cover environment, accountability, billing, app grouping and provenance with zero overlap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="tag-normalisation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Normalise tag values: lowercase, kebab-case, no whitespace, no synonyms (production ≠ prod ≠ Prod).</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Cloud bills aggregate by exact string match; synonyms shatter the cost report into unusable shards.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="untagged-quarantine" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarantine resources missing required tags within 24h via SCP / org policy denying further write actions until tags are applied.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Tagging slippage compounds — only an enforcement gate stops the long tail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="inheritance-not-duplication" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Inherit tags from parent resources where the platform supports it (auto-scaling group → instance, Kubernetes namespace → cost label) instead of stamping each child manually.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Manual stamping drifts; inheritance keeps lineage intact through autoscaling and re-creation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="chargeback-export-ready" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Publish a chargeback-ready monthly export keyed on (env, cost-center, application) and reconcile against the finance ledger before issue-day.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Without a reconciled export, FinOps loses credibility with finance and tagging discipline erodes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, do NOT run this methodology — return early with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree's negative branch must terminate cleanly without partial output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold AND scope is explicit, run the methodology end-to-end and produce the canonical artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree positive-branch terminus; aliases the apply-end-to-end verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
