<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="visibility-of-system-status Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for visibility-of-system-status as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Progress bars for indeterminate-length operations are misleading; they can only be accurate for operations with known total work units.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Showing a progress bar stuck at 50% for an unknown-duration operation frustrates users who cannot estimate completion time.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Over-notification: showing a success toast for every auto-save event creates notification fatigue and users stop noticing actual errors.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Auto-save confirmation should appear only after a pause in editing and dismiss after 2 seconds maximum; excessive notifications train users to ignore them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Skeleton screens require designing the exact expected layout in advance; they break when the content structure differs from expectations.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Skeleton screens work well for predictable layouts like article lists but mislead users on complex dynamic content where actual layout differs from skeleton.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>ARIA live regions for screen readers require careful implementation — aria-live="assertive" for errors, aria-live="polite" for non-critical updates; mixing them causes accessibility regressions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Screen reader users rely on live regions to hear status changes; incorrect politeness levels make updates either intrusive or invisible.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Offline/online status detection via navigator.onLine is unreliable; it detects network adapter state, not actual internet connectivity.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A user can appear online to the browser but unable to reach the internet; status indicators must actually test connectivity with real API calls.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
