<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="ux" count="186" version="3.0" generated="2026-05-23">
  <description>L2 index of methodologies in the ux domain. The retriever reads this after picking ux from L1 domains.xml. Entries list slug + tier + summary; open the leaf AGENTS.md / content/*.xml for full payload.</description>
  <methodology slug="CLAUDE-methodologies" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/CLAUDE-methodologies">
    <summary>Playbook step that selects which UX-methodology bundle Claude should load given the design task at hand (heuristic eval, generative UI, plugin choice, spatial, VUI).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="a11y-annotation-pattern-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/a11y-annotation-pattern-library">
    <summary>Produces an archetype-keyed library of a11y annotations + a dev-handoff doc resolving each annotation to role/name/state/keyboard/focus.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="a11y-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/a11y-basics">
    <summary>Entry-level accessibility layer for web products: WCAG POUR principles, conformance levels, four evaluation types, and a 5-minute pre-PR quick-check protocol.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="a11y-screen-status-tracker" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/a11y-screen-status-tracker">
    <summary>Per-screen accessibility status tracker (pass / partial / fail) with owner + last-tested + remediation plan for every named screen.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="a11y-testing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/a11y-testing">
    <summary>End-to-end accessibility testing process combining automated scan, manual keyboard pass, AT testing, and disabled-user feedback into a single audit report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ab-testing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ab-testing">
    <summary>Run a pre-registered controlled experiment (control vs variant) on a live population with a primary metric, guardrails, and pre-calculated sample size to decide ship/hold on evidence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="accessibility-evaluation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/accessibility-evaluation">
    <summary>Five-stage WCAG 2.1/2.2 AA audit report: automated scan, triage, keyboard, screen reader, structured findings with W3C-technique citations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="accessibility-first-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/accessibility-first-design">
    <summary>Design-phase methodology preventing 70-80% of WCAG 2.2 AA violations via token-grounded color/contrast, semantic-first components, and a11y handoff annotations baked into the design system.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="accessibility-first-design-a11y" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/accessibility-first-design-a11y">
    <summary>Spec for designing UI components with accessibility as a structural constraint, not a post-build patch — keyboard, SR, contrast, motion baked in.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ada-title-ii-compliance-2026" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ada-title-ii-compliance-2026">
    <summary>Conformance report for US state/local government digital services on the WCAG 2.1 AA target under DOJ's April-2024 final rule (Apr 2026 / Apr 2027 deadlines by population).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="adobe-firefly-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/adobe-firefly-integration">
    <summary>Produces an Adobe Firefly + Creative Cloud integration with structured prompt rules and brand-compliance auditing, scoped to the UX/UI designer's CC pipeline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="adobe-firefly-integration-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/adobe-firefly-integration-ui-design">
    <summary>Produces a Firefly Services REST client that batch-generates commercial-safe images, applies Generative Fill to placeholder regions, and audits prompts for brand compliance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="aesthetic-minimalist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/aesthetic-minimalist">
    <summary>Apply Nielsen Heuristic</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-accessibility-automation-2026" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-accessibility-automation-2026">
    <summary>Produces a 2026 accessibility automation config wiring AI-powered scanning (axe-core + Lighthouse + AI triage) into CI, with automated WCAG 2.2 AA reporting and a human-required-for-AT testing gate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-accessibility-automation-2026-a11y" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-accessibility-automation-2026-a11y">
    <summary>Produces a full continuous-a11y pipeline (axe-playwright + AI ranking + VPAT 2.5 draft + alt-text + caption) with a human accessibility lead gating every AI artifact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-assisted-accessibility" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-assisted-accessibility">
    <summary>Produces a WCAG 2.2 AA conformance report combining AI-enhanced automated scanning (axe-core, Lighthouse) for 60–70 % coverage with structured AT + human testing plan for the remainder.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-assisted-accessibility-a11y" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-assisted-accessibility-a11y">
    <summary>Produces a two-agent a11y workflow (Haiku scans + filters + ranks, Sonnet generates code fixes) with mandatory human expert validation before any dev ticket lands.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-assisted-persona-building" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-assisted-persona-building">
    <summary>Produces a validated persona report from analytics + interviews + surveys via two-pass clustering (Sonnet broad cluster → Haiku detail refine) with quote grounding + human validation gate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-design-assistant-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-design-assistant-patterns">
    <summary>Produces a decision record for AI assistants embedded in UX/UI design tools — sidebar (long tasks) vs modal (single-shot) vs inline (micro-suggestions) — with trigger rules and fallback states.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-design-assistant-patterns-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-design-assistant-patterns-ui-design">
    <summary>Produces a decision record selecting one of four AI-assistant patterns (sidebar / modal / inline / review-mode) for a design-tool integration and locks the pattern for the product.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-enhanced-design-systems" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-enhanced-design-systems">
    <summary>Produces a UX/UI design-system automation config (auto-docs + token scan + Figma-to-code diff + variant generator) that requires a solid token foundation and consistent naming.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-enhanced-design-systems-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-enhanced-design-systems-ui-design">
    <summary>Produces a design-system automation config (component-doc generator + token-violation scanner + variant generator) that amplifies a mature DS — only when tokens and naming are already systematic.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-generated-layout-review-checklist" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-generated-layout-review-checklist">
    <summary>Ten-point checklist for reviewing AI-generated mockups (v0, Galileo, Figma Make) before they enter a design system or ship to engineering.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-interview-analysis" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-interview-analysis">
    <summary>Produces a cross-interview themes report from raw audio/video transcripts using AI transcription + per-interview coding + cross-interview synthesis with quote-grounded themes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-persona-building" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-persona-building">
    <summary>Produces a lightweight single-pass persona report (Sonnet + Haiku) for early exploration when full clustering is overkill, with explicit not-validated labelling.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-plugin-ecosystem" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-plugin-ecosystem">
    <summary>Decision record that catalogues which Figma AI plugins fit which design task and where the agent/plugin boundary lies (no headless plugin API).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-plugin-ecosystem-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-plugin-ecosystem-ui-design">
    <summary>Produces a Figma REST API client that performs the work usually attempted via UI plugins — contrast audits, style extraction, bulk renames — without a designer at the keyboard.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-spatial-computing" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-spatial-computing">
    <summary>Spec for UX in spatial computing surfaces (Vision Pro, Meta Quest, AR overlays) where AI is the primary interaction modality — gaze, gesture, voice fused with multimodal models.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-spatial-computing-a11y" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ai-spatial-computing-a11y">
    <summary>Produces an XR accessibility spec with three-tier input fallback (gaze→voice→controller), on-device latency budget, and W3C XAUR gap analysis for AR/VR/MR products.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="anti-pattern-rationale-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/anti-pattern-rationale-template">
    <summary>Records every UX anti-pattern discovery as a versioned artefact with named owner, evidence, and re-occurrence triggers so the same anti-pattern is not re-litigated in the next sprint.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ar-design-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ar-design-patterns">
    <summary>Produces an AR interaction spec covering placement, occlusion-aware UI, gesture grammar, lighting estimation, and reset-on-track-loss for handheld + headset AR apps.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ar-design-patterns-a11y" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ar-design-patterns-a11y">
    <summary>Accessible AR (augmented-reality) design patterns: anchor stability, environment-aware contrast, dwell vs gaze input, audio cues, motion budgets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="audience-segmentation" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/audience-segmentation">
    <summary>6-step audience-segmentation report: 2-3 dimensions, 2-5 mutually-exclusive segments, six-criterion attractiveness score, single primary target selection with rationale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="breaking-change-deprecation-policy" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/breaking-change-deprecation-policy">
    <summary>Codified deprecation policy for design-system breaking changes: pins timeline (deprecation window, removal date), opt-in flags, and migration guidance per component so consumer teams never improvise.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="card-sorting" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/card-sorting">
    <summary>Run open, closed, or hybrid card-sorting sessions with target users to discover how they group content, then synthesise into an evidence-based taxonomy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="card-sorting-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/card-sorting-ux-research">
    <summary>Ask 15-20+ users to organise 30-60 content cards into groups and name them; produce a similarity-matrix-backed IA spec artefact identifying high-confidence groupings and ambiguous items before navigation is locked in.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cog-walk-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/cog-walk-basics">
    <summary>Learnability inspection: per-step answers to the four cognitive-walkthrough questions (intent, action visibility, action-effect link, progress feedback), emitted as a structured findings report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cog-walk-process" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/cog-walk-process">
    <summary>End-to-end cognitive-walkthrough process: prerequisites assembly, 2-4 evaluators, per-step evaluation forms for all four questions, issue documentation, prioritized synthesis report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cognitive-inclusion-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/cognitive-inclusion-design">
    <summary>Produces a cognitive-inclusion spec covering chunking, predictability, progress indicators, focus mode, dyslexia font, reduced motion, and extended time limits for users with ADHD, autism, dyslexia, dyscalculia, anxiety, low literacy, and aging cognition.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cognitive-inclusion-design-a11y" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/cognitive-inclusion-design-a11y">
    <summary>Design spec for cognitive accessibility: plain language, predictable navigation, error tolerance, recoverable actions, time-extension defaults.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cognitive-walkthrough" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/cognitive-walkthrough">
    <summary>Produces a cognitive-walkthrough report stepping through a known-correct action sequence and answering 4 questions per step about learnability.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitive-analysis" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/competitive-analysis">
    <summary>Benchmark direct and adjacent competitors on selected UX dimensions using a repeatable rubric so positioning decisions and design choices reference comparable evidence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="competitive-analysis-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/competitive-analysis-ux-research">
    <summary>Examine 3-5 direct + 2-3 indirect + 1-2 aspirational competitors against pre-defined UX criteria; produce a feature matrix, per-competitor profile, and Must/Should/Could/Avoid recommendation set.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="consistency-standards" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/consistency-standards">
    <summary>Audit and enforce internal and external consistency — terminology, components, gestures, and platform conventions — so users do not have to relearn the same idea twice.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="consistency-standards-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/consistency-standards-ux-research">
    <summary>Apply Nielsen Heuristic #4 across five layers (internal, external, visual, functional, verbal) via a design system and consistency audits; produce an audit spec artefact counting distinct variations per UI element and recommending consolidation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="content-audit" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/content-audit">
    <summary>Inventory every page or asset against quality, ownership, freshness, and performance criteria to produce a remove / update / keep action list per item.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="content-audit-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/content-audit-basics">
    <summary>Systematic content inventory and quality scoring: per-URL inventory row, rubric-scored quality, owner assignment, kept/update/delete decision emitted as an audit report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="content-audit-process" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/content-audit-process">
    <summary>Six-step inventory and evaluation of every content asset: crawl/inventory, classify by type, score by multiple criteria, assign action (Keep / Update / Consolidate / Rewrite / Remove / Review), prioritise, output an action plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contextual-inquiry" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/contextual-inquiry">
    <summary>Produces a contextual-inquiry report from semi-structured interviews conducted in the user's environment while they perform actual work, with master-apprentice notes + interpretation session.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contextual-inquiry-ux-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/contextual-inquiry-ux-research">
    <summary>Field research method: semi-structured master/apprentice interviews in the user's environment, observation-row schema, behaviour tagging, synthesized findings report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="core-vui-design-principles" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/core-vui-design-principles">
    <summary>Produces a VUI principle spec covering simplicity (short single-idea responses), natural conversation (follow-up awareness, turn-taking), and context awareness (memory of prior turns) for all voice runtimes from Alexa Skills to LLM Realtime agents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="critical-issue-triage-protocol" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/critical-issue-triage-protocol">
    <summary>Turns post-session UX triage from a gut-feel argument into a 30-minute deterministic protocol: severity × frequency × context modifier yields a same-day-fix / sprint / backlog / discard decision per finding.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cross-platform-token-distribution" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/cross-platform-token-distribution">
    <summary>Produces a Style-Dictionary-driven token distribution pipeline emitting CSS, iOS Swift, Android XML, and Tailwind config from a single W3C DTCG source.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-critique" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-critique">
    <summary>Run a structured design critique session that ties feedback to design goals and user evidence so designers leave with concrete next actions, not opinions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-critique-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-critique-ux-research">
    <summary>Structured conversation analysing a design against defined goals and principles; produces an actionable feedback spec artefact where every comment is specific, principle-grounded, and converted into a tracked decision.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-decision-log-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-decision-log-template">
    <summary>Captures every design decision (Figma comment thread, Slack ping, standup verbal) as a single-row artefact with context, decision, alternatives, and owner so the same decision is not re-litigated next week.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-qa-during-build" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-qa-during-build">
    <summary>Sprint-cadence design-QA checklist that catches design drift between handoff and ship: token usage audit, spec-deviation log, fix-tickets ledger, sign-off gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-review-facilitation-script" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-review-facilitation-script">
    <summary>Pinned 45-minute design-review script that opens with the review-ask, runs structured rounds of feedback (clarify → critique → suggest), and closes with a triaged action list per reviewer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-system-changelog-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-system-changelog-template">
    <summary>Structured changelog template for design-system releases (what / why / impact / migration / risk) that consumer teams can parse and act on without chasing the maintainer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-system-drift-dashboard" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-system-drift-dashboard">
    <summary>Produces a quantitative drift report tracking token adoption, hardcoded values, and v1→v2 migration ROI across every consumer repo on a weekly cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-system-governance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-system-governance">
    <summary>Operating model for a design system: contribution rules, RFC process, breaking-change comms, deprecation policy, and ownership map — the artefact that keeps v1→v2 migrations from forking the product surface.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-system-impact-queue" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-system-impact-queue">
    <summary>Standing queue that captures design-system implications surfaced during reviews / drifts / RFCs and triages them on a fixed cadence so they never bleed into ad-hoc component churn.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-system-success-factors" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-system-success-factors">
    <summary>Produces a governance + adoption health report for a design system covering ownership, documentation freshness, contribution model, adoption metrics, and component coverage.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-to-dev-handoff" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-to-dev-handoff">
    <summary>Process for handing off a finished design to engineering with a complete spec, walkthrough video, and acceptance criteria so engineering can ship without follow-up questions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-tokens-fundamentals" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-tokens-fundamentals">
    <summary>Produces a three-tier (primitive → semantic → component) W3C DTCG token spec with accessibility-baked color pairs, motion variants, and logical spacing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="design-tokens-fundamentals-ui-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/design-tokens-fundamentals-ui-design">
    <summary>Three-tier design-token architecture (global → semantic → component) with named-by-intent semantics, single source of truth, and CI-enforced semantic-references-global rule so brand changes propagate in one commit.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="diary-studies" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/diary-studies">
    <summary>Produces a diary-study report from longitudinal self-recorded entries over days/weeks with daily-and-event-triggered prompts + reminder cadence + analysis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="diary-study-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/diary-study-basics">
    <summary>Longitudinal self-report study spec: participant recruitment, entry templates (daily + event-triggered), reminder schedule, drop-off threshold, exit interview hook.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="diary-study-execution" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/diary-study-execution">
    <summary>Operational + analytical phase of a running diary study: compliance monitor, low-quality entry detector, drop-off remediation, codebook-driven coding, temporal-pattern synthesis report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="edge-case-checklist" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/edge-case-checklist">
    <summary>Closed checklist of 10 edge cases (long text, RTL, slow network, no-data, error, offline, dark mode, small screen, a11y screen reader, time zone) applied to every shipped component so the production-bug surface drops by an order of magnitude.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="enterprise-xr-applications" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/enterprise-xr-applications">
    <summary>Produces an enterprise-XR application spec covering training simulations, remote assistance, digital twins, 3D analytics, distributed collaboration — with comfort, IT integration, security, and ROI gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-handling-in-vui" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/error-handling-in-vui">
    <summary>Produces a VUI error-recovery spec implementing a three-rung re-prompt ladder (brief re-ask → constructive re-ask with examples → escalation to visual/DTMF/human).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-prevention" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/error-prevention">
    <summary>Design constraints, confirmations, defaults, and forgiving formats so dangerous actions never occur or surface as a question before they commit.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-prevention-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/error-prevention-ux-research">
    <summary>Eliminate error-prone conditions before they occur using six strategies (constraints, defaults, suggestions, validation, confirmation, affordances); produce an audit spec artefact mapping each error class in the product to a prevention strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-recovery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/error-recovery">
    <summary>Write error messages and recovery flows that name the problem in plain language, point at the offending input, and offer a concrete next action.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="error-recovery-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/error-recovery-ux-research">
    <summary>Produce plain-language error messages with three components — what happened, why, how to fix it — applied to every error surface in the product; emit an error-message spec artefact covering every error class.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feature-discovery" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/feature-discovery">
    <summary>Six-step process for identifying, validating, and prioritizing product features: four-source collection → Kano → opportunity score → effort → RICE → validate before build.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="figma-ai-ecosystem" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/figma-ai-ecosystem">
    <summary>Report mapping Figma's first-party AI surfaces (Make, AI tools, code-connect, dev mode) plus the third-party plugin layer, with capability + risk per surface.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="figma-ai-ecosystem-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/figma-ai-ecosystem-ui-design">
    <summary>Produces a decision record drawing the agent / human boundary across Figma's AI surfaces (Make, Draw, Sites, Image Tools) — REST + Webhooks for agents, UI-only for designers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="figma-comment-triage-protocol" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/figma-comment-triage-protocol">
    <summary>30-minute daily Figma comment sweep that categorises every open comment into FIX / DECIDE / ANSWER / IGNORE with a named owner so comments do not silt up the canvas.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026">
    <summary>Decision record comparing Figma vs Adobe (XD/Firefly/Creative Cloud) for a design org in 2026 — feature parity, AI integration, total cost, lock-in risk.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/figma-vs-adobe-strategy-2026-ui-design">
    <summary>Produces a scored toolchain decision record selecting Figma, Adobe CC, or the Figma+Firefly hybrid for a product team, revisited every 6 months.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="flexibility-efficiency" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/flexibility-efficiency">
    <summary>Layer accelerators — keyboard shortcuts, saved views, command palettes, batch operations — over the default path so novices and experts both move quickly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="flexibility-efficiency-a11y" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/flexibility-efficiency-a11y">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="focus-groups" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/focus-groups">
    <summary>Produces a focus-group findings report from &gt;=3 groups of 6-10 participants × 60-90 minutes per segment, with written-first exercises + late concept reveal + theme stability check.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="focus-groups-ux-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/focus-groups-ux-research">
    <summary>Moderated 6-10 person focus-group report: screener, discussion guide, moderator playbook, session notes, post-process coding into themes with quoted evidence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="generative-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/generative-ui-design">
    <summary>Spec for UIs whose layout / components are produced at request time by an LLM (v0-style runtime UI generation) — input model, safety guardrails, fallback layout, eval gate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="generative-ui-design-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/generative-ui-design-ui-design">
    <summary>Produces an ideation-phase UI spec from a feature brief by generating 5–10 layout variants (v0, Claude Artifacts, Galileo, Uizard, Relume) and selecting one for hand-off, with explicit not-production-ready labelling.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="handoff-spec-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/handoff-spec-template">
    <summary>Single Markdown artefact that closes design→engineering handoff loss: states, tokens, motion, accessibility, edge cases, and code map are all named in one file with token references and pixel-accurate measurements.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="help-documentation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/help-documentation">
    <summary>Design contextual, searchable, task-oriented help — tooltips, inline guides, knowledge base — so users solve their own problems without leaving the flow.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="help-documentation-a11y" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/help-documentation-a11y">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="heuristic-eval-severity-rubric" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/heuristic-eval-severity-rubric">
    <summary>Calibrated 0..4 severity scale for Nielsen-style heuristic evaluation with anchored examples per level so two evaluators rate the same violation within ±1 of each other.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="heuristic-evaluation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/heuristic-evaluation">
    <summary>Have three to five evaluators independently score a UI against the ten Nielsen heuristics with severity ratings, then synthesise a deduplicated prioritised issue list.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="heuristic-evaluation-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/heuristic-evaluation-ux-research">
    <summary>3-5 expert evaluators independently audit a product against Nielsen's 10 usability heuristics; reconcile findings into a single severity-rated report identifying 60-75% of usability problems without user testing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ia-framework" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ia-framework">
    <summary>Structure shared information environments by designing organization schemes, taxonomies, navigation, and search so users find content without learning internal org charts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ia-templates" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/ia-templates">
    <summary>Produce the four canonical IA artefacts — sitemap, taxonomy document, navigation specification, page inventory — using shared templates so every project starts from the same skeleton.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="immersive-design-principles" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/immersive-design-principles">
    <summary>Produces an immersive (AR/VR/MR/XR) experience spec balancing presence + comfort with concrete budgets for FOV usage, locomotion, session length, vestibular safety, and accessibility.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="immersive-design-principles-a11y" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/immersive-design-principles-a11y">
    <summary>Five immersive design principles (comfort, locomotion safety, sensory budgets, agency, retreat-option) that gate VR / AR / MR experience design.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="information-architecture" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/information-architecture">
    <summary>Translate IA framework decisions into a sitemap, taxonomy, and navigation spec that the design team can build against without re-deriving the structure.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="insight-to-design-ticket" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/insight-to-design-ticket">
    <summary>Translates a research insight into a properly-scoped design ticket with hypothesis, success metric, design constraints, and a draft acceptance criteria so the design sprint starts with no ambiguity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="jobs-to-be-done" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/jobs-to-be-done">
    <summary>Produces a job-statement artefact (functional + emotional + social dimensions, forces of progress, 8-stage job map) revealing why customers hire the product.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="journey-mapping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/journey-mapping">
    <summary>Generate a current-state customer journey map (stage × row matrix with persona, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points, opportunities) grounded in cited research evidence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="journey-mapping-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/journey-mapping-ux-research">
    <summary>Map the end-to-end customer journey across stages, touchpoints, actions, emotions, and pain points so cross-functional teams can spot friction no single team owns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-powered-conversational-ai" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/llm-powered-conversational-ai">
    <summary>Spec for text-or-voice conversational UI backed by an LLM — turn structure, tool surfaces, fallback policy, refusal model, conversational a11y.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-powered-conversational-ai-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/llm-powered-conversational-ai-ui-design">
    <summary>Produces a conversational-AI design spec for an LLM-core voice/text interface (ASR → LLM → TTS) replacing rule-based intent-slot NLU, with latency budget, safety filters, fallback escalation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="match-real-world" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/match-real-world">
    <summary>Audit UI copy and icons against users' mental model (Nielsen Heuristic #2) and produce a substitutions report — jargon and system-centric strings replaced with the user's vocabulary, consistently across the product.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="match-real-world-a11y" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/match-real-world-a11y">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mobile-ux" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/mobile-ux">
    <summary>Produce a mobile UX audit report covering touch targets, thumb-zone placement, navigation pattern, input types, Core Web Vitals, and platform conformance against hard thresholds (44pt/48dp, LCP&lt;2.5s, CLS&lt;0.1).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mobile-ux-basics" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/mobile-ux-basics">
    <summary>Mobile-first design spec: touch-target sizing, thumb-zone placement, navigation patterns, form optimization, performance budgets and platform-specific (iOS vs Android) conventions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mobile-ux-patterns" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/mobile-ux-patterns">
    <summary>Apply touch-target, gesture, navigation, and feedback patterns proven on mobile so flows respect thumb reach, network variance, and platform conventions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="motion-and-micro-interaction-system" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/motion-and-micro-interaction-system">
    <summary>Tokenised motion system (durations, easings, choreography rules, prefers-reduced-motion, perceived-perf budget) sitting alongside the design-system colour and typography token sets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="motion-and-microinteraction-spec" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/motion-and-microinteraction-spec">
    <summary>Per-component motion spec (duration, easing, choreography, prefers-reduced-motion fallback, perceived-perf impact) emitted alongside the visual spec so dev cannot improvise timing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-platform-design-parity" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/multi-platform-design-parity">
    <summary>Parity matrix spec that maps tokens, gestures, density tiers, and platform-native conventions across web / mobile-web / iOS / Android / desktop / TV / wearable so a single decision propagates to every surface.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multimodal-vui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/multimodal-vui-design">
    <summary>Spec for voice-first UI that also exposes visual / haptic affordances — modality matrix, fallback ladder, recognition error model, persona voice constraints.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multimodal-vui-design-ui-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/multimodal-vui-design-ui-design">
    <summary>Produces a voice + visual interaction spec for smart displays with four interaction patterns and a three-tier fallback hierarchy (voice → touch → keyboard) plus state-sync verification.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="opportunity-solution-trees" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/opportunity-solution-trees">
    <summary>Visual discovery framework linking one outcome to a hierarchy of customer opportunities, candidate solutions and experiments, emitted as an OST spec the team can iterate on.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pain-point-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/pain-point-research">
    <summary>Five-step process producing a ranked pain log: define scope, mine four source tiers (complaints, questions, forums, job boards), categorise, score with Pain Intensity Matrix (frequency × severity × reach × spend × alternatives), extract root causes via 5 Whys.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="pattern-bank-tagging-schema" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/pattern-bank-tagging-schema">
    <summary>Closed-vocabulary tagging schema for the inspiration / patterns bank so future retrieval is deterministic and AI agents can pre-filter by surface, intent, and severity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="persona-building" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/persona-building">
    <summary>5-step persona-building report grounded in &gt;=10 interview transcripts: cluster goals/frustrations/behaviours, define at most 1 primary + 1 negative persona, validate against cohort behaviour.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="personas" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/personas">
    <summary>Produces 3-5 research-based personas (≥6 interviews, goal/behaviour clusters, verbatim-quote evidence, scenarios + JTBD pairing) for design-decision grounding.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="personas-ux-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/personas-ux-research">
    <summary>Research-based persona report distilling goals, behaviours, frustrations and context from observed data into 3-5 named archetypes referenceable in design reviews.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="problem-validation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/problem-validation">
    <summary>Validate a problem against an evidence hierarchy (paid &gt; committed &gt; engaged &gt; stated &gt; anecdote), apply Mom Test rewrites to avoid leading questions, output a PROCEED / PIVOT / KILL decision with a scored evidence log and a pre-declared kill threshold.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="problem-validation-2026" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/problem-validation-2026">
    <summary>2026 variant of problem validation: 5-step interview opener (Vision → Framing → Weakness → Pedestal → Ask), commitment signal taxonomy (Time / Reputation / Money), Mom Test replacement question table, validation as a recurring weekly loop during discovery.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prototype-iteration-log-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/prototype-iteration-log-template">
    <summary>Pinned per-flow iteration log with fixed shape (problem → hypothesis → variant → evidence → outcome → next) so prototype work stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prototyping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/prototyping">
    <summary>Produce a prototype plan tying a chosen fidelity (paper / clickable / high-fi / code) to stated learning objectives, plus a usability test script with 3-5 scenario-based tasks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prototyping-ui-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/prototyping-ui-design">
    <summary>Build the smallest interactive prototype that can falsify a single hypothesis in 1-3 hours, then use evidence-collection to decide kept / rolled-back / shipped-with-changes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="recognition-over-recall" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/recognition-over-recall">
    <summary>Audit a UI surface against Nielsen Heuristic</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="recognition-over-recall-a11y" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/recognition-over-recall-a11y">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="regulatory-compliance-2026" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/regulatory-compliance-2026">
    <summary>Produces an accessibility compliance report mapping product surfaces to ADA Title II + EAA + AODA + Section 508 obligations, with WCAG 2.1/2.2 AA conformance evidence and remediation backlog.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="regulatory-compliance-2026-a11y" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/regulatory-compliance-2026-a11y">
    <summary>Cross-regime accessibility compliance map (ADA Title II, EU EAA, EN 301 549, Section 508, AODA) producing a per-region conformance plan + VPAT-ACR.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="scope-creep-park-list-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/scope-creep-park-list-template">
    <summary>One-page format used live in stakeholder design walkthroughs to capture 'wouldn't it be cool if' ideas without committing to them, with explicit owner, date, and revisit gate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="screen-reader-test-script-templates" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/screen-reader-test-script-templates">
    <summary>Per-flow screen-reader test script (NVDA / VoiceOver / TalkBack) with expected announcements, gestures, and pass/fail criteria.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="semantic-tokens-and-modes" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/semantic-tokens-and-modes">
    <summary>Produces a three-layer design-token configuration (reference / system / component) with mode coverage across light/dark/HC/brand and a Style Dictionary build pipeline emitting platform tokens.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-accessibility" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/spatial-accessibility">
    <summary>Produces a spatial-accessibility report mapping every AR/VR/MR interaction to ≥2 input modalities, seated-mode parity, comfort options, and a non-spatial fallback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-accessibility-a11y" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/spatial-accessibility-a11y">
    <summary>Accessibility rules for XR (VR/AR/MR) spatial UI: reach zones, height variability, occlusion, spatial audio, seated alternates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-computing-overview" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/spatial-computing-overview">
    <summary>Produces a platform-selection recommendation comparing 2026 XR/AR/VR/MR platforms (visionOS, Quest, PSVR2, HoloLens, Android XR, WebXR) against use-case, install base, and SDK constraints.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-design-tools" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/spatial-design-tools">
    <summary>Produces a phase-gated tool-selection config for spatial (AR/VR/MR) workflows: concept in Figma + ShapesXR, prototype in Unity or Unreal, production in engine; with asset-pipeline standards (USD/USDZ for visionOS, glTF for Quest/Web) and polygon + file-size budgets set at concept stage.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-interaction-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/spatial-interaction-patterns">
    <summary>Produces an interaction-pattern specification for spatial (AR/VR/MR) apps: state machines for direct-manipulation, ray-cast selection, gaze+dwell, voice, and gesture — with primary + fallback modality per interaction.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-ui-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/spatial-ui-patterns">
    <summary>Produces a pattern-taxonomy spec for 3D user interfaces in AR/VR/MR: panel-type assignment (world-locked / head-locked / body-locked / hand-attached), comfort distance ≥1 m, FoV occupancy ≤40°, touch targets ≥60×60 pt at 1 m.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-ux-fundamentals" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/spatial-ux-fundamentals">
    <summary>Produces a spatial-spec mapping every panel and control to one of three field zones — near (0.3-1.0 m), mid (1.0-3.0 m), far (3.0 m+) — with anchoring, occlusion, and sight-line annotations enforced via lint.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="spatial-ux-fundamentals-ui-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/spatial-ux-fundamentals-ui-design">
    <summary>Designing for spatial (XR / Vision Pro / Quest) starts with three primitives — comfort zones, spatial affordances, and depth hierarchy — that prevent user fatigue and disorientation in the first 10 minutes of use.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-walkthrough-script" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/stakeholder-walkthrough-script">
    <summary>60-minute stakeholder design walkthrough opens with a single decision-ask, presents options not artefacts, parks off-scope, and closes with a signed decision line — short-circuits the demo-mode pretty-pictures trap.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="success-metrics-definition" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/success-metrics-definition">
    <summary>Before sprint planning or launch, define one North Star Metric and 3-5 Primary KPIs via AARRR (Acquisition / Activation / Retention / Revenue / Referral) with quantified baseline + target, exact measurement definitions, and vanity-vs-actionable classification.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="survey-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/survey-design">
    <summary>6-step survey-design spec: single research objective, question type selection, neutral phrasing audit, ordered flow (screener-&gt;demographics), 5-10 person pilot, pre-registered analysis plan.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="surveys" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/surveys">
    <summary>Produces a quantitative-survey instrument (NPS/CSAT/SUS/SEQ + custom items) with sampling plan, channel mix, fielding window, and analysis plan — validated for question-construction antipatterns before fielding.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="surveys-ux-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/surveys-ux-research">
    <summary>Standardized-survey report: question-bank instance, sample plan, fielding log, metric computations (NPS / SUS / CSAT) with cohort breakdowns and verbatim evidence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="synthetic-users" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/synthetic-users">
    <summary>Produces a directional feedback report from AI-generated research participants during ideation, with a mandatory human-validation gate before any product decision.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tailwind-design-tokens" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/tailwind-design-tokens">
    <summary>Generate a tailwind.config.js + tokens.css + Style Dictionary config that bridges semantic design tokens to Tailwind utilities via CSS custom properties, with safelist coverage and RGB-channel opacity support.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tailwind-design-tokens-ui-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/tailwind-design-tokens-ui-design">
    <summary>Bridges Tailwind config to a governed design-token layer so Tailwind utilities resolve to semantic tokens (color.feedback.error → bg-error-500) instead of magic numbers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="testing-with-assistive-technology" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/testing-with-assistive-technology">
    <summary>Produces an AT-testing config: three tiers — automated scan in CI (every PR), manual screen-reader and keyboard sweep (every release), assistive-user session (quarterly) — with bug-report format (WCAG SC + repro + ARIA APG pattern + scope).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="testing-with-assistive-technology-a11y" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/testing-with-assistive-technology-a11y">
    <summary>Operational guide for AT testing rigs (screen readers, switch devices, voice-control, magnifiers) — environment setup, test matrix, finding capture.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="token-organization" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/token-organization">
    <summary>Produces a design-token configuration with three-tier hierarchy (primitives / semantic / component) and a `{category}.{property}.{variant}.{state}` naming convention that makes tokens self-documenting and prevents bloat.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tree-testing" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/tree-testing">
    <summary>Produces a tree-testing study config that validates a site's information architecture with task-based navigation through a text-only hierarchy — separating IA validation from visual/interaction design.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tree-testing-ux-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/tree-testing-ux-research">
    <summary>Findability evaluation report: text-only IA tree, scenario tasks, per-task success/directness scores, problem-area annotations and IA-revision recommendations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="usability-test-session-tracker-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/usability-test-session-tracker-template">
    <summary>Produces a per-session usability-test tracker artefact that normalises task success/failure logging across many moderation sessions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="usability-testing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/usability-testing">
    <summary>Produce a usability-test artefact (plan + session script + findings report) with scenario-based tasks, success criteria, and four-level severity ratings tied to participant-blocked counts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="usability-testing-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/usability-testing-ux-research">
    <summary>Run moderated or unmoderated usability sessions with five-plus representative users on prioritised tasks to surface friction with severity ratings and recommended fixes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="use-case-mapping" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/use-case-mapping">
    <summary>Document specific ways users interact with the product to achieve goals: enumerate use cases, name actor + goal + trigger + flow + alternate flows + edge cases, produce a use-case spec artefact downstream design and QA read.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-control-freedom" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/user-control-freedom">
    <summary>Produce a User Control Audit — per-action table covering undo, cancel, exit, recovery — flagging missing emergency exits and confirmation-overuse with severity and fix direction (Nielsen Heuristic</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-control-freedom-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/user-control-freedom-ux-research">
    <summary>Audit and design undo, cancel, redo, exit, and recovery mechanisms so users can escape unwanted states without confirmation fatigue or data loss.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-interviews" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/user-interviews">
    <summary>Produce a user-interview artefact (research-question deck + interview guide + per-session notes + insight statements) with verbatim quote citations and a sanitised-transcript log.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-interviews-ux-research" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/user-interviews-ux-research">
    <summary>Plan, recruit, conduct, and synthesise one-to-one semi-structured interviews with target users to surface jobs-to-be-done, mental models, and unmet needs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-research-at-scale" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/user-research-at-scale">
    <summary>Operating-model spec for AI-augmented research: automated transcription, agent-driven tagging/clustering, 10% human verification sample, repository as single source of truth.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="user-validation-methods" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/user-validation-methods">
    <summary>Router methodology covering four validation lenses (JTBD, Persona, Problem Validation, Pain Mining); produces a routing decision artefact that selects the correct sub-methodology per research question and pins the rationale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="validation-methods" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/validation-methods">
    <summary>Reference combining three pre-PMF validation lenses (Problem Validation, Pain Mining, Niche Viability Scoring) into one artefact; produces a triangulated discovery decision per opportunity covering whether the problem is real, painful, and in a market worth serving.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="value-proposition-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/value-proposition-design">
    <summary>Design a value proposition using the Strategyzer Canvas: map customer jobs / pains / gains against products &amp; services / pain relievers / gain creators, score fit, and emit a positioning statement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="visibility-of-system-status" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/visibility-of-system-status">
    <summary>Produce a Status Audit report (Nielsen Heuristic</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="visibility-of-system-status-a11y" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/visibility-of-system-status-a11y">
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-ui" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/voice-ui">
    <summary>Produces a voice-UI specification authoring sample dialogues first, then defining intents/slots, prompts, and a 3-tier error-recovery ladder (rephrase → examples → fallback) before any NLU training begins.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-ui-basics" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/voice-ui-basics">
    <summary>Designing a VUI starts with three primitives — intents (closed set of user goals), prompts (system speech), and error-handling (recovery paths) — so conversation flows do not loop or strand the user.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vpat-acr-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vpat-acr-template">
    <summary>Generates a VPAT 2.5 Accessibility Conformance Report with per-criterion status, evaluation method, and remarks suitable for procurement and ADA documentation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vr-design-patterns" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vr-design-patterns">
    <summary>Produces a VR-design pattern spec: visible ground plane + stable horizon, teleport-first locomotion for novices, world-anchored UI, accessibility fallbacks (seated mode, subtitles, one-handed control) — to ship a comfortable, inclusive VR app.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vr-design-patterns-a11y" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vr-design-patterns-a11y">
    <summary>Five canonical VR design patterns (snap-turn default, vignette, locomotion choice, hand-presence options, retreat affordance) emitted as a record.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-accessibility-inclusivity" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vui-accessibility-inclusivity">
    <summary>Produces a VUI inclusivity report measuring WER (word-error-rate) fairness across demographic slices (accent, age, gender), enforcing reading-grade-8 prompts, visual transcript alternative, and motor/visual fallbacks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-accessibility-inclusivity-a11y" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vui-accessibility-inclusivity-a11y">
    <summary>Accessibility + inclusivity spec for voice user interfaces: accent + dialect coverage, text alternates, confirmation cues, command discoverability.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-conversation-design" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vui-conversation-design">
    <summary>Produces a multi-turn voice-dialog spec modelled as a state machine with explicit intents/entities/prompts, ≤12-word prompts, cap of 3 reprompts, and separate voice + screen scripts validated in realistic noise conditions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-conversation-design-ux-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vui-conversation-design-ux-research">
    <summary>Intent-based VUI dialog-flow spec: intents, slots, prompt classes (open/directed/option/confirmation), happy paths and all repair branches (no-match / no-input / max-retry / escape-to-human).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-iot-integration" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vui-iot-integration">
    <summary>Produces a smart-home voice-control spec with cohesive intent design, multi-device synchronization, explicit feedback for partial failures, undo support, and noise-robust testing for grouped scenes and routines.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-market-context" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vui-market-context">
    <summary>Produces a voice-platform decision record comparing the five major voice platforms (Alexa, Google Assistant, Siri, Bixby, custom LLM) on developer access, install base, distribution, and Matter / Home Assistant openness as of 2026.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-market-context-ux-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vui-market-context-ux-research">
    <summary>Generates a one-page voice market brief with sourced adoption stats + platform comparison weighted by target geo.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-privacy-security" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vui-privacy-security">
    <summary>Produces a voice privacy + security spec enforcing transparency-before-capture, visual + audio trust indicators, step-up authentication for sensitive actions, and PII redaction at transcript boundaries — across GDPR / HIPAA / CCPA / BIPA.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-testing-best-practices" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vui-testing-best-practices">
    <summary>Produces a four-layer VUI test plan — unit (intent accuracy), integration (dialog flow completion), user (≥5 moderated real users), stress (noise + accents + interruptions) — with subgroup accuracy buckets and deterministic LLM-voice seeds for regression.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vui-testing-best-practices-ux-research" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/vui-testing-best-practices-ux-research">
    <summary>Produces a two-tier VUI test report (deterministic + LLM-judge) keyed to feature × locale × noise with per-tier accuracy metrics.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="wcag-22-compliance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/wcag-22-compliance">
    <summary>Delta methodology covering the 9 new WCAG 2.2 success criteria (focus not obscured, dragging movements, target size 24×24, redundant entry, accessible authentication, etc.).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="wireframing" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/wireframing">
    <summary>Produce a wireframe document (layout description + annotation table + state checklist + open questions) covering ≥3 layout variants per key screen and ALL states (default, empty, loading, error, success, permission-gated) without visual styling.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="wireframing-ui-design" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ux/wireframing-ui-design">
    <summary>Builds the lowest-fidelity-that-still-answers-the-question wireframe in 30-60 minutes: information hierarchy, layout grid, primary actions, and content slots — explicitly stripped of visual polish to keep stakeholder feedback on structure not aesthetics.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
