<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="ux" count="93">
  <methodology>
    <slug>a11y-basics</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>The entry-level accessibility layer for web products: WCAG POUR principles, A/AA/AAA conformance levels, four evaluation types, five-minute quick-check protocol, and pre-commit gate criteria.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/a11y-basics</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>a11y-screen-status-tracker</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for a11y screen status tracker that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/a11y-screen-status-tracker</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>a11y-testing</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Five-step accessibility testing process combining automated scanning (axe, WAVE, Lighthouse, Pa11y), manual keyboard testing, screen reader verification, cognitive accessibility checks, and prioritized issue documentation.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/a11y-testing</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ab-testing</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Design decisions based on opinions create debates without resolution.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/ab-testing</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>accessibility-first-design</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Methodology for embedding accessibility requirements at the design stage — color contrast ratios, semantic structure, touch target sizing, motion controls, and focus management — before a single line of code is written.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/accessibility-first-design</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ada-title-ii-compliance-2026</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Compliance methodology for US state and local government entities required to meet WCAG 2.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/ada-title-ii-compliance-2026</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ai-accessibility-automation-2026</slug>
    <tier>geek</tier>
    <summary>Full continuous accessibility automation pipeline for products with frequent deployments: axe-playwright scans every deploy, AI ranks and de-duplicates violations, code fixes are suggested per issue, VPAT 2.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/accessibility-specialist/ai-accessibility-automation-2026</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ai-assisted-accessibility</slug>
    <tier>geek</tier>
    <summary>AI accelerates WCAG auditing by automating scan execution, false-positive filtering, fix suggestion generation, and bulk alt text creation — reducing audit time by 60–75%.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/accessibility-specialist/ai-assisted-accessibility</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ai-assisted-persona-building</slug>
    <tier>geek</tier>
    <summary>Synthesize data-backed user personas from multi-source inputs (analytics CSVs, interview transcripts, survey exports) using a two-pass agent pipeline: a Sonnet subagent clusters behavioral patterns and produces draft persona JSON, then a validation agent checks each persona for JTBD consistency and flags fabricated fields.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/user-researcher/ai-assisted-persona-building</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ai-interview-analysis</slug>
    <tier>geek</tier>
    <summary>Use AI to automate transcript processing and cross-interview theme extraction.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/user-researcher/ai-interview-analysis</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ai-persona-building</slug>
    <tier>geek</tier>
    <summary>Lightweight single-pass persona generation: a Sonnet subagent receives a structured description of a user type with known data points and a JTBD statement, and produces a persona card.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/user-researcher/ai-persona-building</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ai-spatial-computing</slug>
    <tier>geek</tier>
    <summary>AI enables spatial interfaces (AR/VR/MR) to adapt contextually — recognizing environments, predicting gestures, routing voice commands, and powering gaze-based accessibility.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/accessibility-specialist/ai-spatial-computing</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>anti-pattern-rationale-template</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Anti Pattern Rationale Template: codified design / UX practice that turns the recurring 'role-ux-ui-designer/Inspiration + patterns capture (30min/week)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/anti-pattern-rationale-template</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ar-design-patterns</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Design patterns for augmented reality experiences on iOS (ARKit/RealityKit), Android (ARCore), WebAR (8th Wall, model-viewer), and social AR (Snap Lens Studio).</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/ar-design-patterns</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>audience-segmentation</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A structured process to divide a potential market into distinct, mutually exclusive groups using two to three differentiating dimensions (demographic, behavioural, psychographic, or needs-based), score each segment against six weighted attractiveness criteria, and select at most one primary target for pre-traction products.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/user-researcher/audience-segmentation</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>breaking-change-deprecation-policy</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Breaking Change Deprecation Policy: codified design / UX practice that turns the recurring 'role-ux-ui-designer/Design-system component update (single component)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/breaking-change-deprecation-policy</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>card-sorting</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Navigation categories that make sense internally often fail users because they mirror org charts or product taxonomies rather than user mental models.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/card-sorting</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>cog-walk-basics</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A usability inspection method where evaluators step through a task from a first-time user's perspective, answering four questions per step: (1) Will the user try to achieve the right effect? (2) Will they notice the correct action? (3) Will they associate the action with the desired effect? (4) Will they see that progress is being made? Designed specifically to expose learnability failures before user testing.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/cog-walk-basics</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>cog-walk-process</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>The full structured process for running a cognitive walkthrough: defining prerequisites (persona, task, correct action sequence, interface), assembling 2-4 evaluators, completing per-step evaluation forms for all four questions, documenting issues with concrete fixes, and synthesizing findings into a prioritized summary report.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/cog-walk-process</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>cognitive-inclusion-design</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Design patterns for cognitive accessibility: ADHD, autism, dyslexia, anxiety, learning disabilities (15-20% of population).</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/cognitive-inclusion-design</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>competitive-analysis</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Without competitive analysis, design teams reinvent solved problems, miss user expectations set by other products in the market, and cannot answer stakeholder questions like "what do competitors do?" Analyzing direct competitors surfaces the baseline users already expect; analyzing indirect competitors reveals alternative approaches; analyzing aspirational examples (best-in-class UX from adjacent industries) reveals what "best practice" looks like.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/competitive-analysis</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>consistency-standards</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Nielsen's Usability Heuristic #4: users should not have to wonder whether different words, situations, or actions mean the same thing.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/consistency-standards</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>content-audit-basics</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A content audit is a systematic inventory and quality review of all content on a site or application.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/content-audit-basics</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>content-audit-process</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>A structured 6-step process for systematically inventorying and evaluating all content assets, assigning each item an action (Keep/Update/Consolidate/Rewrite/Remove/Review), and producing a prioritized report.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/content-audit-process</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>contextual-inquiry</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Contextual inquiry is a semi-structured field research method conducted in the user's actual work environment while tasks unfold.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/contextual-inquiry</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>critical-issue-triage-protocol</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>A decision rule for when a UX research finding is a same-day-fix vs a backlog item — severity scoring, frequency thresholds, and a 30-minute triage protocol that prevents both overreaction and silent neglect.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/critical-issue-triage-protocol</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>design-critique</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Design critique is a structured conversation about a design where participants analyze work against defined goals and principles, providing specific, actionable feedback to improve the design.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/design-critique</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>design-decision-log-template</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Canonical decision-log format for design decisions made in Figma comments, Slack threads, and standups — prevents re-litigation, accelerates onboarding, and gives later AI handoffs a citable source.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/design-decision-log-template</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>design-qa-during-build</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Design Qa During Build delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Zero-to-one product design: brief to dev handoff (8 weeks)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: After handoff, design drift creeps in during sprint. No methodology cover</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/design-qa-during-build</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>design-system-changelog-template</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Design System Changelog Template delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Design-system component update (single component)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Consumer teams ignore vague 'updated' notes; a structured changelog (wha</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/design-system-changelog-template</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>design-system-drift-dashboard</slug>
    <tier>geek</tier>
    <summary>Design System Drift Dashboard delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Design system v1 to v2 migration (12 weeks)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Quantitative tracking of adoption + drift over time is missing; needed to make mi</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/design-system-drift-dashboard</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>design-system-governance</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Contribution rules, RFC process, breaking-change communication, and deprecation policy for design systems — the operating model that keeps v1→v2 migrations from forking the product surface.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/design-system-governance</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>design-system-impact-queue</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A standing queue that captures design-system implications surfaced during design reviews and component updates, so they get triaged on a cadence instead of bleeding into ad-hoc component drift.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/design-system-impact-queue</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>diary-study-basics</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A longitudinal research method where participants self-record behaviors, thoughts, and contexts in the moment or shortly after, over days or weeks.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/diary-study-basics</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>diary-study-execution</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>The operational and analytical phase of a running diary study: monitoring participant compliance, detecting low-quality entries, managing drop-off, coding entries against a fixed codebook, computing temporal patterns, and synthesizing findings into a structured report.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/diary-study-execution</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>error-prevention</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Eliminate error-prone conditions before they occur using six strategies: constraints, defaults, suggestions, validation, confirmation, and affordances.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/error-prevention</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>error-recovery</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Plain language error messages with three components: what happened, why, how to fix it.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/error-recovery</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>feature-discovery</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Six-step process for identifying, validating, and prioritizing product features: collect from four sources, categorize with Kano model, score opportunity, estimate effort, prioritize with RICE, then validate top candidates before engineering commitment.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/user-researcher/feature-discovery</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>figma-comment-triage-protocol</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Figma Comment Triage Protocol delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Daily Figma sync + comment triage (30min)' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Designers waste daily hours on uncategorized Figma comments; no faion methodology c</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/figma-comment-triage-protocol</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>flexibility-efficiency</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #7: design for both novice and expert users simultaneously by providing accelerators (keyboard shortcuts, bulk operations, templates) that novices can ignore but experts use daily, plus progressive disclosure and multiple paths for the same goal.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/accessibility-specialist/flexibility-efficiency</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>focus-groups</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A focus group is a moderated discussion with 6-10 participants who share characteristics relevant to the research.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/focus-groups</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>handoff-spec-template</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Handoff Spec Template — testable methodology for design, research, accessibility, severity. User pain explicitly named 'handoff loss'; no faion methodology defines the structured spec format (states / tokens / motion / a11y / edge cases / code map).</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/handoff-spec-template</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>help-documentation</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Users who cannot find answers give up, generating support costs and reducing adoption.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/accessibility-specialist/help-documentation</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>heuristic-eval-severity-rubric</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Heuristic Eval Severity Rubric — testable methodology for design, research, accessibility, severity. Nielsen's heuristics methodology lacks a 0–4 severity rubric with calibrated examples; without it, ratings drift between designers.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/heuristic-eval-severity-rubric</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>heuristic-evaluation</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Apply Nielsen's 10 heuristics: expert evaluators find 60-75% of problems without user testing.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/heuristic-evaluation</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ia-framework</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Information architecture (IA) is the structural design of shared information environments.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/ia-framework</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>ia-templates</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>When producing IA deliverables for a new product, site redesign, or content migration, templates accelerate the output from research insights to structured documentation.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/ia-templates</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>immersive-design-principles</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A framework for XR/AR/VR/MR experience design covering immersion-level selection (passthrough, blended, fully immersive, portal), motion-comfort mitigations (vignette, snap turn, teleport, grounding), comfort settings completeness, spatial layout rules, and WAI XAUR accessibility coverage.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/immersive-design-principles</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>jobs-to-be-done</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Framework for understanding why customers hire products.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/user-researcher/jobs-to-be-done</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>journey-mapping</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>A customer journey map is a visualization of the complete end-to-end experience a specific persona has with a product or service across all stages, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points, and opportunities.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/journey-mapping</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>match-real-world</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Users encounter unfamiliar jargon and technical terms.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/accessibility-specialist/match-real-world</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>mobile-ux-basics</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A mobile-first design methodology covering touch target sizing, thumb-zone placement, navigation patterns, form optimization, performance budgets, and platform conventions (iOS vs Android).</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/mobile-ux-basics</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>mobile-ux-patterns</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Mobile-specific UI patterns for navigation (tab bars, hamburger menus), forms (progressive disclosure, inline validation), interactions (pull-to-refresh, swipe actions, long-press), loading states (skeleton screens), empty states, error recovery, and onboarding.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/mobile-ux-patterns</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>motion-and-micro-interaction-system</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Motion tokens (durations, easings), prefers-reduced-motion, perceived performance, choreography between components — the motion methodology corpus has zero of.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/motion-and-micro-interaction-system</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>motion-and-microinteraction-spec</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Motion And Microinteraction Spec: codified ux practice that turns the recurring 'role-ux-ui-designer/Zero-to-one product design: brief to dev handoff (8 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/motion-and-microinteraction-spec</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>multi-platform-design-parity</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Web, mobile-web, native iOS/Android, desktop, TV, wearable — token mapping, gesture vs pointer, density tiers across platforms unified.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/multi-platform-design-parity</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>opportunity-solution-trees</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A visual discovery framework that links one product outcome to a hierarchy of customer opportunities, candidate solutions, and experiments.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/user-researcher/opportunity-solution-trees</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>pain-point-research</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Systematic 5-step process for discovering and prioritizing user pain points: define scope, mine four source tiers (complaints, questions, forums, job boards), categorize by type, score with the Pain Intensity Matrix (frequency × severity × reach × spend × alternatives), then extract root causes via 5 Whys.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/user-researcher/pain-point-research</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>pattern-bank-tagging-schema</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Pattern Bank Tagging Schema: codified ux practice that turns the recurring 'role-ux-ui-designer/Inspiration + patterns capture (30min/week)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/pattern-bank-tagging-schema</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>persona-building</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A five-step process for creating semi-fictional customer archetypes grounded in real interview data: gather data from at least 10 interviews, cluster utterances by goals/frustrations/behaviours, define at most one primary and one negative persona, validate against real cohort behaviour, and refresh quarterly.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/user-researcher/persona-building</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>personas</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Personas are research-based fictional characters representing key user types.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/personas</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>problem-validation</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Before committing engineering resources to a solution, collect evidence across a validation hierarchy (paid &gt; committed &gt; engaged &gt; stated &gt; anecdote), apply Mom Test question rewrites to avoid leading/hypothetical framing, and output a PROCEED / PIVOT / KILL decision with a scored evidence log.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/user-researcher/problem-validation</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>problem-validation-2026</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>A focused variant of the problem-validation methodology adding a 5-step interview opener (Vision → Framing → Weakness → Pedestal → Ask), a commitment signal taxonomy (Time / Reputation / Money), a Mom Test replacement question table, and the 2026 principle that validation is a recurring weekly loop during discovery, not a one-time gate.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/user-researcher/problem-validation-2026</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>prototype-iteration-log-template</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Prototype Iteration Log Template — pinned template for the UX/UI designer: fixed shape + named owner + evidence anchors + outcome review, so prototype iteration on one flow (1–3hr) stops being folklore and starts being a reviewable operating tool.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/prototype-iteration-log-template</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>recognition-over-recall</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Users must remember information from one part of the interface to use in another.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/accessibility-specialist/recognition-over-recall</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>regulatory-compliance-2026</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Regional accessibility law matrix for 2026: ADA Title II (US government, April 2026 deadline), European Accessibility Act (EU e-commerce + banking, June 2025/2030), Section 508, AODA (Canada), and equivalent frameworks in the UK, Australia, and Asia-Pacific.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/regulatory-compliance-2026</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>scope-creep-park-list-template</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Scope-Creep Park-List Template: a one-page format used live in stakeholder design walkthroughs to capture "wouldn't it be cool if" ideas without committing to them.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/scope-creep-park-list-template</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>screen-reader-test-script-templates</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Reusable VoiceOver / NVDA / TalkBack test scripts per UI component archetype — form, modal, table, navigation, autocomplete, video player, toast — that turn the abstract testing-with-assistive-technology methodology into copy-pasteable steps for every audit.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/screen-reader-test-script-templates</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>spatial-accessibility</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Accessibility methodology for spatial/XR interfaces (Apple Vision Pro, Meta Quest, HoloLens, WebXR) addressing motor limitations, visual and hearing impairment, cognitive load, and motion sensitivity.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/spatial-accessibility</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>stakeholder-walkthrough-script</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>One-hour stakeholder design walkthrough script that opens with problem + decision-ask, presents options not artefacts, and closes with a signed decision line — short-circuits the demo-mode "pretty pictures" trap.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/stakeholder-walkthrough-script</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>success-metrics-definition</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Before sprint planning or launch, define a North Star Metric and 3-5 Primary KPIs using the AARRR framework (Acquisition, Activation, Retention, Revenue, Referral).</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/user-researcher/success-metrics-definition</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>survey-design</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>A six-step process for designing surveys that produce valid quantitative data: define a single research objective, choose question types, write neutral non-hypothetical questions, structure the flow (screener → easy → core → demographics → open-end), pilot with 5-10 people, and pre-register the analysis plan before fielding.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/user-researcher/survey-design</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>surveys</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Structured data collection from many users through standardized questions that quantify attitudes, preferences, and experiences.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/surveys</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>synthetic-users</slug>
    <tier>geek</tier>
    <summary>Methodology for using AI-generated research participants to produce directional feedback during early ideation — covering persona simulation, interview analysis, and the mandatory gate of validating key findings with at least 3 real users before any product decision.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ux/user-researcher/synthetic-users</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>testing-with-assistive-technology</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Manual testing with real screen readers, keyboard-only navigation, and mobile AT to catch the 50-70% of accessibility issues that automated tools miss.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/testing-with-assistive-technology</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>tree-testing</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Tree testing evaluates the findability of topics in a website's hierarchy by having participants navigate a text-only version of the site structure (no design, no content) to locate answers to scenario tasks.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/tree-testing</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>usability-test-session-tracker-template</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Usability Test Session Tracker Template: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-ux-ui-designer/Usability-test moderation (single session)'.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/usability-test-session-tracker-template</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>usability-testing</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>A structured method for observing real users attempt predefined tasks with a product.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/usability-testing</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>use-case-mapping</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Use case mapping is documenting specific ways users interact with your product to achieve goals.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/user-researcher/use-case-mapping</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>user-control-freedom</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Usability Heuristic #3: Users often perform actions by mistake.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/user-control-freedom</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>user-interviews</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>User interviews are one-on-one conversations with users or potential users to understand their needs, behaviors, motivations, and pain points.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/ux-researcher/user-interviews</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>user-research-at-scale</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>An operating model for running research in parallel with product velocity using AI-augmented pipelines: automated transcription, agent-driven tagging and clustering, human verification on a sampled 10%, and a repository as the single source of truth.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/user-researcher/user-research-at-scale</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>user-validation-methods</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>A router methodology that covers four validation lenses in a single entry point: JTBD (why users hire products), Persona Building (who users are), Problem Validation (does this problem exist and matter), and Pain Point Mining (where users express frustration publicly).</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/user-researcher/user-validation-methods</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>validation-methods</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>A reference combining three validation lenses: Problem Validation (evidence hierarchy + 5-step process + PROCEED/PIVOT/KILL decision), Pain Point Mining (tiered source strategy + Pain Intensity Matrix scoring), and Niche Viability Scoring (5-criteria weighted model: market size 25%, competition 20%, barriers 20%, profitability 20%, your fit 15%).</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/user-researcher/validation-methods</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>value-proposition-design</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>Products fail because they don't clearly articulate why someone should buy.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/user-researcher/value-proposition-design</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>visibility-of-system-status</slug>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <summary>The design must always keep users informed about what is going on through appropriate feedback within a reasonable amount of time.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/solo/ux/accessibility-specialist/visibility-of-system-status</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>vpat-acr-template</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Vpat Acr Template: produces a versioned, owner-signed artefact that closes the gap 'role-ux-ui-designer/Accessibility audit and remediation program (6 weeks)'.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/vpat-acr-template</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>vr-design-patterns</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Design patterns for fully-immersive 6DoF VR covering environment anchoring (ground plane, horizon, stable reference objects), locomotion menu (teleport default + smooth opt-in), UI placement (world-locked or body-locked, 1.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/vr-design-patterns</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>vui-accessibility-inclusivity</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Methodology for designing voice user interfaces that work equitably across accents, dialects, speech impediments, age groups, and languages.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/vui-accessibility-inclusivity</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>vui-conversation-design</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>VUI conversation design structures intent-based dialog flows for voice interfaces: defining intents, slots, prompt classes (open, directed, option, confirmation), happy paths, and all repair branches (no-match, no-input, max-retry, escape-to-human).</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/vui-conversation-design</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>vui-market-context</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Voice market context: adoption stats and platform comparison for strategic decision-making.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/vui-market-context</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>vui-testing-best-practices</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>VUI testing across three accuracy tiers with deterministic assertions and LLM-judge scoring.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/ux-researcher/vui-testing-best-practices</path>
  </methodology>
  <methodology>
    <slug>wcag-22-compliance</slug>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <summary>Delta methodology for upgrading from WCAG 2.</summary>
    <path>skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ux/accessibility-specialist/wcag-22-compliance</path>
  </methodology>
</index>
