<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Python Code Quality — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every python-code-quality application must obey.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-ruff-single-tool" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Ruff as the single lint + format tool. Remove black, isort, flake8, autoflake, pyupgrade from dev dependencies.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">Ruff implements all five tools' rules in one Rust binary, 10–100x faster, with one config; coexistence creates conflicting opinions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-mypy-strict-at-boundary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run mypy or pyright in strict mode. Allow per-module override only for vendored or legacy code, never as the global default.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">Strict catches Optional misuse, implicit Any, untyped defs — the cheapest layer of defect detection. Global relaxation hides bugs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-coverage-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Configure pytest-cov with a hard --cov-fail-under threshold (≥80% branches for new code).</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">A threshold turns coverage into a gate, not a vanity number. Without it, coverage drifts down silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-bandit-on-commit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run bandit (or ruff's S rules) on every commit. Block high-severity findings.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">SQL injection, hardcoded creds, weak hashes are easier to catch at commit time than in security review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-precommit-canonical-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Make pre-commit the single canonical gate. CI re-runs the same hooks to prevent --no-verify bypass.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">Same checks locally and in CI → no merge-time surprises. Bypassing locally fails CI.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-sync-target-version" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set requires-python, ruff target-version, mypy python_version, and pyproject.toml [tool.ruff.target-version] all to the same Python version.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network">Mismatched target versions produce false positives (e.g., 3.12 syntax flagged because ruff targets 3.10).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
