<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Handoff Spec Template Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Handoff Spec Template. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-eight-state-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every interactive component lists all 8 states (default, hover, active, focus, disabled, loading, error, empty); absent states are rejected unless explicitly marked N/A with a one-line reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-system maturity audits">Missing states are the #1 source of handoff loss; explicit N/A keeps the matrix complete.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-token-references-not-raw" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All colors, spacing, typography, and motion values reference design tokens by name (e.g. color.primary.500, spacing.md); raw hex / px values are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-tokens fundamentals">Raw values break dark-mode + theming and create drift between spec and code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-motion-duration-and-easing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every motion spec names duration in ms and an easing curve (CSS keyword or cubic-bezier). &apos;Smooth&apos; / &apos;fast&apos; alone are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Material motion guidelines">Vague motion descriptions force engineers to guess; concrete values produce deterministic feel.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-a11y-focus-and-contrast" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every spec carries focus-order annotation + computed contrast ratios on every text/background pair; contrast ratios below WCAG AA threshold (4.5:1 body, 3:1 large) are flagged for designer review.</statement>
      <rationale source="WCAG 2.2 AA">Missing a11y annotations push the work to eng or get skipped entirely; computed ratios force the designer to fix in design, not patch in code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-edge-cases-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every spec names at least 3 edge cases (long text overflow, RTL, slow-network, no-data, error) with the visual treatment for each; specs without edge cases are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Defensive-design practice">Edge cases drive most production bugs; naming them in the spec moves the conversation upstream.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-handoff-spec-template.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
