<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="API-First Development Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding API-First Development. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-contract-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>OpenAPI 3.1 YAML is committed before any handler code; if the spec changes mid-feature, regenerate stubs and re-run contract tests in the same PR.</statement>
      <rationale source="FIRST.org API design literature + OpenAPI spec v3.1.0">Code-first APIs drift from documentation within weeks; locking the contract as the first commit prevents the drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-operationid-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every operation carries a camelCase operationId; blank or duplicate operationIds are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="openapi-generator-cli docs">SDK generators and Prism routers key on operationId; blanks produce conflicting function names that break generated clients.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-oas-3-1-nullables" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Nullable fields use type: [&apos;string&apos;, &apos;null&apos;]; nullable: true (OAS 3.0 syntax) is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenAPI 3.1.0 spec change log">OAS 3.1 aligns with JSON Schema 2020-12; the 3.0 nullable: true pattern produces incorrect validation in 3.1-aware tools.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-shared-error-schema" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All 4xx/5xx responses reference a single #/components/responses/Error; per-endpoint ad-hoc error shapes are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — error-shape inconsistency audit">Consumers cannot write a single error handler when each endpoint returns a different error shape.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-mock-before-backend" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prism mock server is deployed and shared with the consumer team before backend implementation begins.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stoplight Prism docs">Mock-first lets frontend agents start immediately; without it the spec is written but never exercised.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-ci-lint-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spectral lint passes as a pre-merge CI gate; lint errors that break mock-server routing block the PR.</statement>
      <rationale source="Spectral CI integration guide">Without a CI gate, lint regressions ship and the spec degrades into documentation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md &quot;Applies If&quot; do not all hold, OR any &quot;Skip If&quot; disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-api-first-development.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
