<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="focus-groups">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Moderated discussion with 6-10 participants exploring attitudes, reactions to concepts, and shared vocabulary. Minimum 2-3 groups per segment; findings are qualitative and directional.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>focus-groups</tag>
      <tag>qualitative-research</tag>
      <tag>group-dynamics</tag>
      <tag>concept-testing</tag>
      <tag>language-discovery</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>group</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Focus Groups: Structure, Moderation, and Analysis</title>

    <summary>A focus group is a moderated discussion with 6-10 participants who share characteristics relevant to the research. The group explores attitudes, reactions to concepts, and language around a topic. Run a minimum of 2-3 groups per segment; findings are qualitative and directional, not statistically generalizable. Focus groups surface group dynamics, shared vocabulary, and cross-segment contrasts that individual interviews spread across too many sessions to achieve quickly.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Focus groups surface group dynamics, shared vocabulary, and cross-segment contrasts that individual interviews spread across too many sessions to achieve quickly. Running 3-4 homogeneous-but-diverse groups (current users, competitor users, non-users) in parallel reveals segment-specific objections and the language people actually use — inputs that feed copy, positioning, and concept prioritization.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Early concept exploration: diverse reactions to multiple positioning angles before committing to one direction.</item>
        <item>Language and terminology discovery: harvest vocabulary users actually use for copy and search synonyms.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder buy-in: leadership needs to "watch users" to believe research findings.</item>
        <item>Cross-segment comparison: 3-4 groups reveal segment-unique objections and shared concerns.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Usability testing — group dynamics suppress individual struggle; use moderated 1:1 sessions.</item>
        <item>Sensitive topics (health, finances, conflict) — participants self-censor in groups.</item>
        <item>Behavior measurement — groups capture stated behavior, not actual behavior.</item>
        <item>Final go/no-go decisions — groupthink and dominant voices distort signal.</item>
        <item>Quantitative claims — N=8 per group is not statistically generalizable.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="method-choice">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use focus groups for attitude exploration, concept reactions, language discovery, and cross-segment comparison. Do not use them for usability testing, sensitive topics, individual behavior measurement, or final go/no-go decisions.</statement>
        <rationale>Group dynamics are a feature for attitude exploration (diverse reactions surface quickly) and a bug for usability testing (participants suppress struggle when observed by peers). The method matches some research goals and actively harms others.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run minimum 2-3 groups per segment. Never report a finding from a single group.</statement>
        <rationale>A single group finding is anecdote, not pattern. Group composition, moderator dynamics, and random participant selection create too much session-level noise for any single group to be representative.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="group-composition">
      <rule>
        <statement>6-10 participants per group. Homogeneous enough for comfort (common frame of reference), diverse enough for variety (different perspectives). Run 2-4 groups total.</statement>
        <rationale>Below 6: insufficient dynamic diversity. Above 10: moderator cannot manage all voices; quieter participants get lost. Homogeneity enables candor; diversity enables range.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Screen aggressively for professional respondents (people who cycle across studies). Use live screener calls or short video tasks to verify participation quality.</statement>
        <rationale>Professional respondents give polished, rehearsed answers that do not represent real users. They are common on large panel platforms and inflate perceived consensus.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="discussion-guide-structure">
      <p>Standard 90-min structure: Opening 5 min (introductions, ground rules) → Warm-up 10 min (easy questions) → Core topics 40-60 min (3 topics maximum) → Concept reaction 15 min (if showing stimuli) → Wrap-up 5 min (summary, final thoughts).</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Show concepts and stimuli only after the warm-up and initial topic exploration. Introducing stimuli too early biases the discussion toward reacting to your framing rather than expressing independent attitudes.</statement>
        <rationale>Pre-stimulus exploration captures the user's unprompted mental model. Introducing stimuli first anchors all subsequent discussion to the product frame, suppressing organic vocabulary and unprompted concerns.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/discussion-guide.md">Full 90-min discussion guide template with opening script, ground rules, topic sections, concept-reaction block.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="moderation-techniques">
      <rule>
        <statement>Capture written first-impressions (silent post-it round) before group discussion to break anchoring on the first speaker's view. Then open the floor.</statement>
        <rationale>The first speaker's view anchors the whole group. Written capture before discussion preserves independent assessments that would otherwise be lost to social conformity.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/session-notes.md">Note-taking template: participant table, group dynamics, concept reactions, moderator observations.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="post-session-pipeline">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use speaker diarization on all focus group recordings. Without speaker labels, transcript analysis cannot identify dominant-participant skew or per-segment quote attribution.</statement>
        <rationale>Dominant participants can drive 40-60% of transcript volume. Without diarization, LLM theme extraction weights their views as group consensus. Diarization allows per-speaker filtering before analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a dissent prompt pass explicitly after the consensus pass: "What disagreement existed within this group?" LLMs are biased toward consensus narratives and collapse nuanced dissent into a single theme without explicit prompting.</statement>
        <rationale>Consensus-biased synthesis misses the finding that often matters most: the minority view, the segment-specific objection, the latent concern. Dissent prompting is the structural counter to this bias.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/postprocess.sh">Shell pipeline: ffmpeg audio extract → WhisperX diarize → Claude theme extraction.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="cross-group-comparison">
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag transcripts with both speaker ID and segment label before analysis. Filter synthesis prompts by segment to surface cross-group contrasts: shared themes, segment-unique themes, and contradictions.</statement>
        <rationale>Untagged cross-group analysis merges distinct segment signals and produces a false "global user" view. Segment filtering preserves the core value of running multiple groups.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Count unique speakers per theme, not utterance count, to assess theme strength. Polite agreement ("yeah, that's right") is not endorsement.</statement>
        <rationale>High utterance count from a single speaker inflates theme strength artificially. Unique-speaker count is the correct denominator: consensus = most participants expressed the theme independently.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="reporting">
      <p>Report structure per finding: theme name → what we heard (summary) → representative verbatim quote with speaker type → implication for design or strategy.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Report per-group findings before cross-group synthesis. Never aggregate groups before documenting group-level patterns.</statement>
        <rationale>Early aggregation destroys segment signals. Cross-group synthesis must build on documented per-group patterns, not replace them.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="dominant-participant-risk">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Dominant participant drives the transcript and LLM analysis treats their views as group consensus.</description>
        <reason>Without diarization and speaker-filtered analysis, a participant generating 50% of transcript volume gets 50% weight in theme extraction. Always diarize and compute unique-speaker-count per theme before any consensus claims.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Online groups analyzed without adjusting for the ~30% nonverbal signal loss versus in-person sessions.</description>
        <reason>Zoom groups flatten energy, disagreement, and hesitation. Online findings should be framed as stated attitudes only, not as a proxy for in-person dynamics. Use smaller groups (4-6) and more structured activities to compensate.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="llm-analysis-failures">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM theme extraction over-clusters nuanced disagreement into a single theme without explicit dissent prompting.</description>
        <reason>LLMs trained on consensus-seeking corpora produce consensus-seeking summaries. Force dissent extraction with a separate pass: "What disagreements or tensions existed?" before merging with the consensus pass.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-generated themes form neat categories without an unclassified bucket.</description>
        <reason>Every real focus group transcript contains messy, boundary-spanning material that resists clean categorization. Forcing 100% classification loses the material that often drives the most interesting insights. Always include a "messy/unclassified" bucket.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM-generated discussion guides over-rely on closed-ended probing questions.</description>
        <reason>Agents produce grammatically correct but logically leading questions by default. Human researchers must rewrite at least 30% of probes for genuine openness before the guide is used.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agents operate around the human moderator, not as moderators. Pre-session: a research agent drafts the discussion guide from objectives, generates probing follow-ups, and screens recruits. Post-session: a transcription agent (Whisper + diarization) produces speaker-labeled transcripts; a synthesis agent extracts themes per segment with verbatim quotes; a comparison agent maps cross-group agreement/disagreement. A human signs off each theme before it lands in the report.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>`faion-ux-researcher-agent` — drafts guide, designs probes, performs cross-group synthesis.</item>
        <item>`faion-content-marketer` — extracts user-language vocabulary for copy reuse.</item>
        <item>`faion-product-manager` — converts findings into prioritized opportunity statements.</item>
        <item>`faion-market-researcher` (from `pro/research/market-researcher`) — segments + recruitment screener logic.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="theme-extraction-prompt-pattern">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Transcript (speaker-labeled): {transcript}
Segment: {segment_name}
Extract 3-7 themes. For each: theme name, supporting quotes (with speaker ID), strength of consensus (unanimous/majority/split/minority). Flag any dominance pattern where one speaker drives a theme alone.]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="cross-group-comparison-prompt-pattern">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Themes from Group A ({segment}): {themes_a}
Themes from Group B ({segment}): {themes_b}
Identify: (1) shared themes, (2) segment-unique themes, (3) contradictions. Cite quote IDs.]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>Tools and services for focus group execution and analysis:</p>
      <list>
        <item>OpenAI Whisper / `whisper-cli`: Transcribe recordings locally. Install: `pip install openai-whisper`.</item>
        <item>`pyannote.audio`: Speaker diarization (who said what). Install: `pip install pyannote.audio`.</item>
        <item>WhisperX: Whisper + diarization combined. Install: `pip install whisperx`.</item>
        <item>`ffmpeg`: Extract audio from Zoom recordings. Distro package.</item>
        <item>`yt-dlp`: Download recordings from links if needed. Install: `pip install yt-dlp`.</item>
        <item>Anthropic SDK: Theme extraction with prompt caching across long transcripts. Install: `pip install anthropic`.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="saas-platforms">
      <p>Services and apps for online focus groups and recruitment:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Zoom (SaaS, Partial): REST API for cloud recordings. Cheapest for online groups; export MP4+VTT.</item>
        <item>UserTesting Live Conversations (SaaS, Partial): API for sessions. Built-in note-taking, recruit panel.</item>
        <item>Discuss.io (SaaS, Yes): REST API. Purpose-built for online focus groups.</item>
        <item>Recollective (SaaS, Yes): API. Asynchronous + live group hybrid.</item>
        <item>dscout (Live) (SaaS, Yes): API. Diary + live group combo.</item>
        <item>Respondent.io (SaaS, Yes): API. High-quality recruitment, niche segments.</item>
        <item>User Interviews (SaaS, Yes): API. Recruitment panel, screener builder.</item>
        <item>Otter.ai / Fireflies (SaaS, Partial): Cloud transcription; check data residency before sending sensitive PII.</item>
        <item>Dovetail (SaaS, Yes): API. Tagging + theming workspace; agent-writable via API.</item>
        <item>EnjoyHQ / Marvin (SaaS, Yes): Research repository; agent can post quotes/themes.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Run a minimum of 2 groups per segment; never report a finding from a single session.</item>
        <item>Brief the moderator separately from the agents — moderators need context-flexibility, not scripted prompts. Agents prepare the guide; humans run the room.</item>
        <item>Capture written first-impressions (silent post-it round) before group discussion to break anchoring on the first speaker's view.</item>
        <item>Tag transcripts with both speaker ID and segment label; filter analysis prompts by segment to surface cross-group contrasts.</item>
        <item>Run a "dissent prompt" pass explicitly: "What disagreement existed within this group?" — counters LLM bias toward consensus narratives.</item>
        <item>Compensate participants well ($75-150/90 min in US baseline; higher for B2B/specialist). Lowballing screens for low-quality respondents.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Whisper without diarization assigns all speech to one speaker → quote attribution becomes unreliable. Always run diarization for groups.</item>
        <item>Long transcripts (&gt;50k tokens) require chunked summarization; without overlap windows, themes spanning chunk boundaries get lost. Use a 10-15% overlap.</item>
        <item>LLMs treat polite agreement ("yeah, that's right") as endorsement. Calibrate by counting unique speakers per theme, not utterance count.</item>
        <item>Auto-generated themes invent neat categories; force the model to also output a "messy/unclassified" bucket and review it manually.</item>
        <item>Privacy: never upload raw recordings to a third-party LLM endpoint without explicit consent in the participant agreement. Default to local Whisper for sensitive segments.</item>
        <item>Recruitment fraud (bots/repeats) is now common via global panels. Verify with a live screener call or short video task before slotting into a group.</item>
        <item>LLM-generated discussion guides over-rely on closed-ended phrasing. Always have the human researcher rewrite at least 30% of probes for openness.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/discussion-guide.md" purpose="Full 90-min discussion guide template with opening script, ground rules, topic sections, concept-reaction block."/>
      <template path="templates/session-notes.md" purpose="Note-taking template: participant table, group dynamics, concept reactions, moderator observations."/>
      <template path="templates/postprocess.sh" purpose="Shell pipeline: ffmpeg audio extract → WhisperX diarize → Claude theme extraction."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/focus-groups/"/>
      <link href="https://www.userinterviews.com/ux-research-field-guide-chapter/focus-groups"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/m-bain/whisperX"/>
      <ref slug="user-interviews"/>
      <ref slug="qualitative-analysis"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
