<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="methodologies-summary">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>A routing index for all 33 methodologies in the pro/product/product-manager/ skill, mapping tasks to slugs in a Quick Selection Guide.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>routing</tag>
      <tag>product-manager</tag>
      <tag>methodology-index</tag>
      <tag>quick-reference</tag>
      <tag>task-triage</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Methodologies Summary (Product Manager)</title>
    <summary>A routing index for all 33 methodologies in the pro/product/product-manager/ skill. Not a methodology itself — it answers "which methodology do I need?" for a given PM task, mapping tasks to slugs in a Quick Selection Guide. Read this first when entering product-manager scope without a specific methodology pinned; then load the chosen methodology's own AGENTS.md.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>With 33 methodologies spanning MVP scoping, feature prioritization, roadmaps, discovery, business models, and operations, an agent entering the skill cold has no cheap way to pick the right methodology without a router. This summary provides a one-read decision tree that narrows the search to a single slug before any heavy content is loaded.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Cold start: agent has a PM task and no methodology is pre-selected.</item>
        <item>Task triage: deciding between RICE vs. MoSCoW, MVP vs. MLP, roadmap vs. OKR, lifecycle vs. feedback management.</item>
        <item>Onboarding a new PM or agent to the skill — first read to orient.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Methodology already chosen — skip summary, go straight to that folder's AGENTS.md.</item>
        <item>Cross-skill work (BA, PM-agile, project-manager) — use the respective skill's own router.</item>
        <item>Execution or templates — look in the chosen methodology's own files, never here.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="core-18-methodologies">
      <section name="mvp-and-mlp">
        <list>
          <item>mvp-scoping: Teams build too much before validation. Output: core problem, minimum features, 4-week constraint.</item>
          <item>mlp-planning: MVP works but users do not love it. Output: WOW moments, delight features, MLP phases.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="feature-prioritization">
        <list>
          <item>feature-prioritization-rice: Too many features, limited resources. Formula: RICE = (Reach x Impact x Confidence) / Effort.</item>
          <item>feature-prioritization-moscow: Stakeholders disagree on priorities. Buckets: Must/Should/Could/Won't (60%/20%/10%/0%).</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="planning-and-roadmaps">
        <list>
          <item>roadmap-design: No clear development direction. Output: Now-Next-Later with milestones and 20% buffer.</item>
          <item>user-story-mapping: Features lack user context. Structure: Activities to Tasks to Releases.</item>
          <item>release-planning: Unclear work for upcoming sprint. Output: Sprint goal, capacity, velocity.</item>
          <item>product-launch: No clear release timeline. Output: Release goal, effort, sprints plus 20% buffer.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="goals-and-metrics">
        <list>
          <item>okr-setting: Goals are vague or unmeasurable. Framework: Objective plus 3-5 Key Results plus Initiatives.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="discovery-and-validation">
        <list>
          <item>problem-validation: Building solutions for non-problems. Output: 5+ interviews, competitor analysis, search volume.</item>
          <item>product-discovery: Root cause not understood. Method: Five Whys (5 levels deep).</item>
          <item>jobs-to-be-done: Features do not match user needs. Format: When [situation], I want [motivation], So I can [outcome].</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="business-models">
        <list>
          <item>business-model-research: Business model not structured. Framework: Lean Canvas (9 blocks).</item>
          <item>value-proposition-design: Product-market fit unclear. Framework: Customer segment plus Value map.</item>
          <item>niche-evaluation: Too many opportunities. Output: Weighted scoring (market size, competition, fit, monetization).</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="operations">
        <list>
          <item>backlog-management: Backlog items unclear or oversized. Principles: DEEP, Definition of Ready.</item>
          <item>stakeholder-management: Features disconnected from goals. Chain: Goal to Actor to Impact to Deliverable.</item>
          <item>risk-assessment: Unknown risks in product decisions. Method: Impact x Uncertainty matrix, test high-risk first.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="extended-15-methodologies">
      <section name="discovery-and-research">
        <list>
          <item>continuous-discovery-habits: Building weekly customer touchpoint habits.</item>
          <item>feedback-management: Collecting, triaging, and acting on user feedback.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="product-development">
        <list>
          <item>minimum-product-frameworks: Choosing among MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC.</item>
          <item>mlp-planning: Evolving from MVP to Minimum Lovable Product via 4-layer audit.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="roadmaps-and-strategy">
        <list>
          <item>competitive-positioning: Market positioning against competitors.</item>
          <item>portfolio-strategy: Multi-product portfolio management.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="growth-and-scale">
        <list>
          <item>product-led-growth: PLG strategy and implementation.</item>
          <item>experimentation-at-scale: Scaling experiments to 100+ per year with statistical rigor.</item>
          <item>learning-speed-competitive-moat: Organizational learning velocity as competitive advantage.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="operations-and-lifecycle">
        <list>
          <item>product-lifecycle: Introduction, Growth, Maturity, Decline stage management.</item>
          <item>product-analytics: Analytics and measurement frameworks.</item>
          <item>technical-debt-management: Technical debt registration, scoring, and paydown strategy.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="quick-selection-guide">
      <list>
        <item>Define MVP: mvp-scoping.</item>
        <item>Add delight to MVP: mlp-planning.</item>
        <item>Choose right minimum product framework: minimum-product-frameworks.</item>
        <item>Choose next feature: feature-prioritization-rice OR feature-prioritization-moscow.</item>
        <item>Create roadmap: roadmap-design.</item>
        <item>Set team goals: okr-setting.</item>
        <item>Validate idea: problem-validation, jobs-to-be-done.</item>
        <item>Launch product: product-launch.</item>
        <item>Manage backlog: backlog-management.</item>
        <item>Build discovery habit: continuous-discovery-habits.</item>
        <item>Scale experiments: experimentation-at-scale.</item>
        <item>Act on user feedback: feedback-management.</item>
        <item>Assess product stage: product-lifecycle.</item>
        <item>Address technical debt: technical-debt-management.</item>
        <item>Build learning velocity moat: learning-speed-competitive-moat.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-role-routing-only">
      <p>Use this file as the first read when an agent enters product-manager scope without a specific methodology pinned. Flow:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[PM task arrives → Read methodologies-summary/AGENTS.md
              → Match task to row in "Quick Selection Guide"
              → Read knowledge/pro/product/product-manager/<picked>/AGENTS.md
              → Load that methodology's agent-integration.md (if present)
              → Execute]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>faion-pm-agent: owns mvp-scoping, product-discovery, business-model-research routes.</item>
        <item>faion-mvp-scope-analyzer-agent: invoked from mvp-scoping row.</item>
        <item>faion-mlp-agent: invoked from mlp-planning row.</item>
        <item>faion-market-researcher-agent: invoked from problem-validation, value-proposition-design, niche-evaluation rows.</item>
        <item>faion-persona-builder-agent: invoked from jobs-to-be-done row.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="prompt-pattern-router">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Task: <PM task>
Step 1: Read pro/product/product-manager/methodologies-summary/AGENTS.md
Step 2: Pick ONE row from Quick Selection Guide
Step 3: Read that methodology's AGENTS.md and apply
Return: methodology slug + chosen agent]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="limitations">
      <list>
        <item>README is hand-curated — drifts when methodologies are added/removed; verify the folder list against ls pro/product/product-manager/ before trusting it.</item>
        <item>"Quick Selection Guide" maps tasks to methodologies but not to agents; agent selection must be cross-referenced in each methodology's own agent-integration.md.</item>
        <item>No CLI tools, services, or scripts apply at this level — those belong to individual methodologies.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog/learning-velocity"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
