<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Backlog Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every Backlog Management application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-deep-enforced" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Backlog MUST follow DEEP: Detailed at top, Emergent at bottom, Estimated for Ready items, Prioritised explicitly per item.</statement>
      <rationale source="Roman Pichler — DEEP backlog">Treating bottom-of-backlog items with the same detail as top items wastes refinement time.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-invest-on-ready" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Ready item MUST satisfy INVEST (Independent, Negotiable, Valuable, Estimable, Small, Testable); failing items are pushed back to Upcoming.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bill Wake — INVEST">Items that fail INVEST become sprint killers — block other work, cannot complete in cycle, fail review.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-four-buckets-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exactly four buckets: Ready (1-2 sprints), Upcoming (1-3 sprints), Backlog (future), Icebox (parked). Extra buckets are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Pichler — backlog buckets">All-items-look-equal kills planning; promotion criteria gate movement.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-type-tagged" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every item MUST carry exactly one type tag in {feature, bug, tech_debt, research}; multi-typed items are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion backlog audits 2026">Type tags drive capacity allocation (feature vs tech debt ratio) and triage automation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-source-link" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every item MUST link to its origin (ticket URL, customer quote, dashboard chart); sourceless items are archive candidates at next grooming.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion backlog audits 2026">Sourceless items cannot be validated or traced back when stakeholders ask 'why did we build this?'</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-180d-archive" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Items inactive for 180+ days MUST be auto-proposed for archive (not deleted) — human approves before removal if linked PRs or customer commitments exist.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene">180-day rule provides objective threshold avoiding 'nobody dares delete' paralysis; human gate prevents commitment loss.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
