<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Backlog Principles: DEEP, INVEST, Bucket Definitions, and Item Quality">
  <summary>Core rules for a healthy backlog: structural principles, the four-bucket model, and the minimum quality bar for a Ready item.</summary>

  <section title="DEEP Principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply DEEP to every backlog: Detailed (top-of-backlog items have AC and estimates), Emergent (bottom items stay rough), Estimated (all Ready items are sized), Prioritized (every item has an explicit rank).</statement>
      <rationale>Treating bottom-of-backlog items with the same detail as top items wastes refinement time. DEEP matches detail investment to delivery probability.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="INVEST Principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every Ready item must satisfy INVEST: Independent (no hidden dependencies), Negotiable, Valuable (explicit user benefit), Estimable, Small (fits in one sprint), Testable (has Given/When/Then AC).</statement>
      <rationale>Items that fail INVEST become sprint killers — they block other work (not Independent), cannot be completed in one cycle (not Small), or fail review (not Testable).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ready item has no acceptance criteria, or AC is a restatement of the title.</description>
      <reason>Untestable AC makes sprint planning slow and definition-of-done review impossible.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Four-Bucket Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain exactly four buckets: Ready (next 1-2 sprints, fully refined), Upcoming (1-3 sprints, defined with some detail), Backlog (future, rough ideas), Icebox (parked, low probability). Enforce explicit promotion criteria between buckets.</statement>
      <rationale>Without defined buckets and promotion criteria, all items look equal and planning degrades to whoever speaks loudest.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap Ready at 2 sprints of team capacity (~8-25 items). Below 8 means insufficient pipeline; above 25 means refinement is being wasted on items that may never ship.</statement>
      <rationale>Ready items beyond 2-sprint capacity will be re-refined when they finally reach sprint planning, making the earlier work waste.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Item Quality">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag every item with exactly one type: feature, bug, tech_debt, or research. Mixed-type backlogs cannot be reasoned about or correctly prioritized.</statement>
      <rationale>Type tags are required for capacity allocation decisions (ratio of feature to tech debt), health metrics, and agent-based triage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Source-link every item to its origin (ticket URL, customer quote, dashboard chart). Items without a source are archive candidates at the next grooming.</statement>
      <rationale>Sourceless items cannot be validated or traced back when stakeholders ask "why did we build this?"</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Item: "Add autocomplete to product search — As a customer I want to see suggestions as I type so I find products faster. Given I type 2 characters, when I pause, then I see top 5 suggestions. Estimate: M. Source: support-ticket-4521."</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Item: "Better search — Search doesn't work well." No story, no AC, no source, no estimate.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-process.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/backlog-item.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
