<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Backlog Management Process: Capture, Groom, Prioritize, Refine, Cleanup">
  <summary>Five-step backlog management process with rules and antipatterns for each step.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Capture">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture from all sources (feature requests, bug reports, tech debt, research outcomes, stakeholder input, team ideas) quickly and without evaluation. Evaluate at grooming, not at intake.</statement>
      <rationale>Evaluation at intake creates a bottleneck and discourages submission. Capture quickly; triage in batch at the weekly grooming session.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Groom (Weekly)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a weekly grooming session (1-2 hours): review new items, refine top items, re-prioritize based on latest learning, archive stale items. Grooming skipped once starts a degradation loop.</statement>
      <rationale>A backlog that is not groomed weekly accumulates noise faster than signal. One missed session doubles the next session's load.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Prioritize">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply a documented prioritization method (RICE, MoSCoW, or stack ranking) and re-run it when: new information arrives, goals change, or sprint planning begins. Never leave priority implicit.</statement>
      <rationale>Implicit priority means the backlog reverts to insertion order or loudest-voice order at sprint planning.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Refine">
    <rule>
      <statement>For top-of-backlog items: break into stories no larger than one sprint, add Given/When/Then acceptance criteria, estimate, and resolve all blockers. An item is Ready only when it meets all four criteria.</statement>
      <rationale>Items missing any of the four criteria will cause sprint planning delays or mid-sprint scope discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Acceptance criteria pasted verbatim from feature requests or support tickets.</description>
      <reason>Customer-sourced AC is typically ambiguous prose, not testable Given/When/Then statements. Unreviewed AC causes failed sprint review.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Cleanup">
    <rule>
      <statement>Archive items with 180+ days of inactivity (unless priority is P1). Merge items with title similarity above 0.85 after human review. Delete confirmed duplicates. Target: stale ratio below 10%.</statement>
      <rationale>Stale items degrade signal-to-noise and make backlog size metrics meaningless. The 180-day rule provides an objective threshold that avoids "nobody dares delete" paralysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat auto-archive as a proposed status, not direct deletion. Archive proposal requires human approval before any item with linked PRs or customer commitments is removed.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-archive of items with external commitments creates support and trust issues. Human approval on the archive list is the safety gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-principles.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/health-check.md"/>
    <link path="templates/grooming-agenda.md"/>
    <link path="templates/validate-backlog.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
