<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-design-process" title="Survey Design Process and Question Writing Rules">
  <summary>Six-step survey design process with question type selection, bias patterns, structure rules, and length guidelines.</summary>

  <section title="Role of surveys">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run 10 or more customer interviews before designing a survey. Surveys quantify hypotheses shaped by qualitative research; they do not discover new problems.</statement>
      <rationale>Surveys without a qualitative foundation ask the wrong questions with high statistical precision and produce confidently wrong answers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-register the analysis plan and segment cuts before fielding — define which comparisons you will make and at what N threshold per segment. Surveys without pre-registration become fishing expeditions.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc analysis finds patterns by chance; pre-registration forces honesty about what the survey is designed to answer.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Question writing rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write neutral, non-hypothetical questions. Ask about past behaviour ("how often have you used...") not predictions ("would you use...").</statement>
      <rationale>Hypothetical questions systematically overpredict positive intent; past behaviour is a stronger predictor of future behaviour.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>One concept per question. Split double-barreled items into two separate questions.</statement>
      <rationale>Double-barreled items produce uninterpretable responses: agreeing could mean agreeing with either clause or both.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include "Prefer not to say" or "Don't know" as response options. Forcing a choice corrupts data more than a missing response.</statement>
      <rationale>Forced-choice on unknowable items produces random noise distributed across the scale that looks like signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Randomize answer order on multiple-choice questions (eliminates primacy/recency bias) but keep ordinal scales fixed in direction.</statement>
      <rationale>Primacy and recency effects are large on long option lists; ordinal scales must be consistent to preserve comparability across respondents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Leading question: "Do you like our product?"</description>
      <reason>Positive framing biases toward agreement; rewrite as "How would you rate your experience with [product]?" on a 1-5 scale.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hypothetical: "How often will you use this feature?"</description>
      <reason>Predicts nothing; rewrite as "How often have you used similar features in other tools?"</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Survey structure and length">
    <p>Recommended flow: screener (1-2 qualifying questions) → easy openers (2-3 to build momentum) → core questions (5-10 main research) → demographics (3-5 for segmentation) → one open-end ("anything else?").</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Target 5-7 minutes total length for standard research surveys; pilot with 5-10 people to verify timing and cut 25% of questions you thought were essential.</statement>
      <rationale>Every minute above 7 minutes reduces completion rate by roughly 5-10%; abandonment at the end biases the completed sample toward highly engaged users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Embed an attention check ("select 'agree' for this row") in any survey over 5 minutes; exclude respondents who fail.</statement>
      <rationale>Inattentive respondents produce random noise; they are detectable and removable without compromising sample integrity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Report margin of error explicitly per segment, not just overall N. Any segment with N below 30 gets descriptives only — no recommendations.</statement>
      <rationale>Small segments reported as actionable findings are statistical noise dressed as insight.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
