<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Survey Examples and Agentic Gotchas">
  <summary>Two worked survey examples (SaaS pricing, feature prioritisation) and agentic failure modes specific to LLM-assisted survey design.</summary>

  <section title="Worked examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Pricing survey for SaaS (n=150). Objective: determine acceptable price range for a new tier.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Screener: "Do you currently use project management software?" (Yes → continue, No → end)
Q1: "How much do you pay monthly for PM tools?" [open numeric]
Q2-Q5: Van Westendorp (too cheap, cheap, expensive, too expensive) [open numeric x4]
Q6: "Which features would you pay extra for?" [multi-select]
Q7: "What would make a $49/mo plan worth it?" [open text]

Results (n=150):
- Optimal price: $29-39/month (Van Westendorp OPP)
- Must-have features: integrations, mobile app
- Insight: 85% expect annual discount option
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Feature prioritisation (n=200). Objective: decide next quarter's roadmap.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Q1-Q3: MaxDiff (3 rounds, 4 features per round, balanced incomplete block design)
Q4: Satisfaction matrix (current features, 1-5 scale)
Q5: "What is the #1 thing you wish we would build?" [open text]

Results (n=200):
- Top priority: API access (38% best-of-set across MaxDiff rounds)
- Highest gap: Reporting (low satisfaction + high importance)
- Surprise: Mobile app less important than assumed
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM drafts a Likert 5 scale by default for every attitude question.</description>
      <reason>Use 7-point for nuanced attitude measurement where you need to detect small shifts; binary for behavioral self-report where ambiguity is the failure mode.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent summarises open-end responses with top-line themes and drops disconfirming quotes.</description>
      <reason>Require quote-with-respondent-ID grounding for every theme claim; disconfirming quotes are the most valuable signal in qualitative open-ends.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent generates MaxDiff with unbalanced item-to-set assignment.</description>
      <reason>MaxDiff requires balanced incomplete block design; unbalanced assignment produces biased utilities. Use Conjointly or Sawtooth, not agent-generated task lists.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent reports "NPS went up 3 points" without acknowledging the ±5-7 confidence interval.</description>
      <reason>Gate any NPS reporting through a stats checker tool; LLM-only NPS commentary is almost always underpowered and overconfident.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/survey-design-doc.md">Survey design document template</link>
    <link path="templates/question-bank.md">Question bank for pricing, satisfaction, feature priority</link>
    <link path="templates/vw-pricing.py">Van Westendorp price-sensitivity analysis script</link>
  </see-also>
</text>
