<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="survey-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for survey-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Leading question: "Do you like our product?"</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Positive framing biases toward agreement; rewrite as "How would you rate your experience with [product]?" on a 1-5 scale.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Hypothetical: "How often will you use this feature?"</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Predicts nothing; rewrite as "How often have you used similar features in other tools?"</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM drafts a Likert 5 scale by default for every attitude question.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use 7-point for nuanced attitude measurement where you need to detect small shifts; binary for behavioral self-report where ambiguity is the failure mode.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent summarises open-end responses with top-line themes and drops disconfirming quotes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require quote-with-respondent-ID grounding for every theme claim; disconfirming quotes are the most valuable signal in qualitative open-ends.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates MaxDiff with unbalanced item-to-set assignment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>MaxDiff requires balanced incomplete block design; unbalanced assignment produces biased utilities. Use Conjointly or Sawtooth, not agent-generated task lists.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent reports "NPS went up 3 points" without acknowledging the confidence interval.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Gate any NPS reporting through a stats checker tool; LLM-only NPS commentary is almost always underpowered and overconfident.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
