<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Gcp Networking Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for the gcp-networking methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale + concrete remediation hook.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="shared-vpc" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Multi-project environments inside one organisation MUST use a Shared VPC host project for shared networking — never project-per-VPC mesh.</statement>
      <rationale source="Shared VPC docs">Shared VPC centralises networking ops on a single host project; per-project meshes explode firewall and peering complexity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cloud-nat" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Private GCE / GKE workloads needing internet egress MUST use Cloud NAT; per-instance public IPs are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud NAT docs">Per-instance public IPs widen attack surface and waste IP quota; Cloud NAT is the supported pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="global-https-lb-cdn-armor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Public HTTP(S) endpoints MUST sit behind a Global External HTTPS Load Balancer with Cloud Armor enabled and Cloud CDN where appropriate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloud Load Balancing docs">Global HTTPS LB delivers consistent edge termination, WAF (Cloud Armor), and CDN — the canonical edge for GCP.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="private-service-connect" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Access to GCP-managed services (Cloud SQL, Memorystore, GKE control plane) from VPC MUST use Private Service Connect or PSA, not public IPs.</statement>
      <rationale source="PSC docs">PSC keeps traffic inside Google's network and eliminates public-endpoint exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="vpc-flow-logs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production VPCs MUST enable VPC Flow Logs (with sampling tuned for cost) and ship them to Cloud Logging.</statement>
      <rationale source="VPC Flow Logs docs">Flow logs are the only retro-active source of truth during a security or networking incident.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the input fails ALL "Applies If" preconditions or matches ANY "Skip If" disqualifier, do not apply this methodology — route the task to the adjacent sibling instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Even flat checklists need an explicit skip leaf in the decision tree; this rule is the universal terminal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
