<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Knowledge Sharing Ritual Set Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the Knowledge Sharing Ritual Set methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="artefact-per-ritual" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every ritual instance MUST produce at least one persisted artefact (notes, recording, ADR, action-items list); rituals that produce nothing are auto-cancelled after 2 misses.</statement>
      <rationale source="Knowledge-sharing audits (Faion 2026-Q1)">rituals without artefact decay into social meetings within 6 weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cadence-locked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cadence is fixed: weekly tech-talk 60min, biweekly demo 45min, monthly architecture review 90min, quarterly skip-level 45min/person; variations require an explicit ADR.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cadence-discipline practice (Atlassian Team Playbook)">drifting cadence kills the muscle memory; calendar-stable beats topic-stable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-presenter-rotation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each ritual has a named presenter on the calendar invite 7 days ahead; un-staffed slots are explicit holes flagged in the artefact, not silent no-shows.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene (PMBOK 7 Tailoring)">without a named presenter the ritual becomes ad-hoc and quality collapses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-level-anonymity-respected" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip-level notes MUST aggregate themes, never quote a named individual without consent; quotes require explicit opt-in.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — HR / psych-safety review">named quotes destroy the safety that makes skip-level useful.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="action-items-have-owner-and-due" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Action items emitted by any ritual MUST have (owner, due_date); un-assigned items are forbidden and surfaced as ritual debt.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion operational reviews">open-ended action items pile up and credibility of the ritual erodes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
