<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-components" title="Journey Map Components and Types">
  <summary>Eight required map components and four journey types, with rules for when each type applies.</summary>

  <section title="Eight Map Components">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every journey map must include all eight components: persona, stages, actions, touchpoints, thoughts, emotions, pain points, and opportunities.</statement>
      <rationale>Omitting emotions produces an action log, not a journey map. Omitting opportunities produces a complaint document, not a design input. All eight components are required for the map to drive action.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Persona: who is taking the journey (specific, research-based, not a generic archetype)</item>
      <item>Stages: major phases of the experience (Awareness, Research, Purchase, Delivery, Use, Support)</item>
      <item>Actions: what the user does at each stage</item>
      <item>Touchpoints: where interaction happens (web, email, app, phone, in-store)</item>
      <item>Thoughts: what the user is thinking and asking at each stage</item>
      <item>Emotions: how the user feels (use 1-5 scale or emotional arc diagram)</item>
      <item>Pain points: friction and frustrations at each stage</item>
      <item>Opportunities: specific improvement ideas tied to pain points</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Journey Types">
    <list>
      <item>Current state: documents how things are today — use to find problems and build stakeholder consensus on what to fix</item>
      <item>Future state: documents the ideal experience — use as a design target after current state problems are understood</item>
      <item>Day-in-the-life: broader context beyond the product — use to understand competing demands on user attention</item>
      <item>Service blueprint: includes backstage processes — use when operational failures drive user pain points</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Label future-state maps explicitly as design proposals, not research findings.</statement>
      <rationale>Future-state maps generated from team imagination (not research) create false consensus that a designed experience matches user needs. The distinction must be visible on the map itself.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Research Grounding">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every map cell must cite a research artifact (interview ID, support ticket ID, analytics event); "no data" is a valid and required value when evidence is absent.</statement>
      <rationale>Ungrounded cells are team assumptions masquerading as research findings. Requiring citations forces explicit identification of gaps, which then become research priorities rather than invention prompts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
