<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Journey Mapping Process">
  <summary>Seven-step mapping process from scope definition to visualization, with rules for research grounding and emotional arc.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1 — Define Scope">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map one persona and one journey per map; scope to a specific start and end point.</statement>
      <rationale>Combining two personas hides differences between their experiences, producing a map that represents neither accurately. A scope without defined endpoints produces maps with no clear beginning or resolution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Scope: Sarah (mid-market buyer persona), purchase journey from first product discovery to post-purchase unboxing. Start: first ad impression. End: product first use.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2 — Gather Research">
    <rule>
      <statement>Collect multi-source evidence before mapping: user interviews, observation, analytics, support tickets, surveys, and employee interviews from customer-facing roles.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-source maps are advocacy documents masquerading as research. Customer support staff see pain points daily that UX research misses — their input is mandatory, not optional.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3 — Identify Stages">
    <rule>
      <statement>Break the journey into 4-8 major stages; name stages from the user's perspective, not the company's process names.</statement>
      <rationale>Company process names (Lead, Opportunity, Closed) reflect internal pipeline stages, not user experience stages. User-perspective names (Discovering, Evaluating, Deciding) keep the map focused on user experience, not operations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Steps 4-5 — Map Actions, Touchpoints, Emotions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map emotions with grounding in research evidence; never invent emotional states from team assumptions.</statement>
      <rationale>Invented emotional arcs produce maps that validate team assumptions rather than challenge them. LLMs and teams both smooth emotional arcs — real journeys have sharp dips. Prompt explicitly for variance when using agents.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6 — Identify Pain Points and Opportunities">
    <rule>
      <statement>The emotional arc dip is the primary signal for where to invest redesign effort; prioritize pain points at the sharpest drops.</statement>
      <rationale>Sharp emotional dips represent the highest concentration of user frustration. These stages have the most to gain from improvement and the most risk from neglect.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every opportunity in the Opportunities column must link to a backlog item or hypothesis — a map without downstream action is waste.</statement>
      <rationale>Journey maps created without action commitments become deck artifacts. The opportunities column is only valuable if it generates work.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 7 — Maintain as Living Document">
    <rule>
      <statement>Attach a "last validated" date to every map; trigger a review when a major feature ships that affects the mapped journey.</statement>
      <rationale>Journey maps go stale quickly. A map from last quarter may contradict current analytics after a product change. Stale maps create false consensus about a user experience that no longer exists.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
