<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Journey Mapping Examples and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>E-commerce journey example, workshop format, stage metrics, and agentic synthesis workflow with gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="E-commerce Purchase Journey Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Stages: Discover → Research → Decide → Purchase → Receive → Use. Emotional arc: Curious (3) → Engaged (4) → Uncertain (2) → Anxious (2) → Impatient (2) → Excited or Disappointed (1-5). Sharpest drop: Purchase stage. Pain point: long checkout form, hidden fees revealed at last step. Opportunity: simplify checkout to single page, show total cost breakdown earlier. Evidence: P3 interview "I almost didn't finish because I didn't know what the final price was", Sentry error logs show 40% cart abandonment at payment page.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Workshop Format">
    <p>Duration: 2-4 hours. Participants: cross-functional team including customer support. Agenda: introduction and scope (15 min), review research (20 min), map stages (30 min), add actions and touchpoints (30 min), add emotions and thoughts (30 min), identify pain points (30 min), prioritize opportunities (30 min), next steps (15 min). Materials: large paper or whiteboard, sticky notes, markers, research summaries, persona reference.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Metrics by Journey Stage">
    <list>
      <item>Awareness: reach, impressions, brand search volume</item>
      <item>Consideration: engagement rate, time on site, content downloads</item>
      <item>Purchase: conversion rate, cart abandonment rate, checkout completion</item>
      <item>Onboarding: activation rate, time-to-first-value</item>
      <item>Usage: retention rate, feature adoption, session frequency</item>
      <item>Support: resolution time, CSAT, first-contact resolution rate</item>
      <item>Loyalty: NPS, repeat purchase rate, referral rate</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Agent synthesizes journey maps from structured research inputs: interview transcripts, support ticket exports, analytics funnel CSVs, NPS comments. Feed agent a corpus of evidence per stage. Agent outputs stage x row matrix. Agent identifies emotional arc and pain-point clusters from sentiment in source text. Human review mandatory before sharing with stakeholders — agent cannot validate whether emotional attributions match real user intent.</p>
    <reference path="templates/journey-map.md">Full journey map template: stage × row matrix</reference>
    <reference path="templates/stage-detail.md">Single stage deep-dive template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/funnel-to-stages.py">Python: convert funnel analytics CSV to stage summaries for agent ingestion</reference>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-map.txt">LLM prompt for synthesizing journey map from interview excerpts</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent hallucinate emotions when no sentiment evidence exists in the input corpus.</description>
      <reason>Always require "no data" as a valid cell value. Agents fill empty cells with plausible-sounding emotions that are invention, not research. Invented emotional arcs produce false consensus.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent smooths emotional arcs, producing a gentle curve rather than sharp dips.</description>
      <reason>Real journeys have sharp emotional drops at friction points. Prompt explicitly: "identify variance and sharp drops, not average sentiment." Smooth arcs hide the most actionable insights.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Future-state map labeled as current-state research.</description>
      <reason>Future-state maps generated by agents are design proposals, not research outputs. Label explicitly on the artifact: "Future State — Design Hypothesis (not validated with users)".</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
