<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ICP Fit Scorecard Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every per-customer ICP scoring run must enforce. Hard rules; designed to prevent vanity bands, no-action runs, and unevidenced scores.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-five-weighted-signals" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every customer scorecard scores exactly 5 signals with fixed weights summing to 100: pain_match (0-25), budget_fit (0-20), urgency (0-15), product_fit (0-25), accessibility (0-15). No bonus categories.</statement>
      <rationale source="ICP-research practice; B2B SaaS scorecard literature">Free-form additions inflate scores and let everyone clear the keep bar. Locked weights enforce a real distribution.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-band-thresholds-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Total score routes to a band: KEEP ≥70 (invest, founder-touch), NURTURE 40-69 (default flow, no extra invest), REMOVE &lt;40 (sunset offer or polite no within 30 days).</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-customer cost-modelling research">Without fixed thresholds, founders drift kept-list upward over time. Locked bands force action.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-evidence-per-signal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every signal score carries a 1-sentence evidence note citing a specific artefact (ticket id, transcript line, dashboard metric, contract clause). No unevidenced signals.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice for B2B scoring">LLMs cheerfully invent fit scores; evidence anchors make the scorecard falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-quarterly-re-score" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-score the full active book once per quarter. Compare against prior scorecard; flag &gt;15-point movers (positive or negative) for narrative review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer-lifecycle research; quarterly business review cadence">Annual scoring is too lagging; weekly is too noisy. Quarterly catches real signal shifts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-remove-action-executed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every REMOVE row triggers a defined action within 30 days: sunset email + refund offer + grace period, OR documented exception with reviewer name and reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-customer playbook practice">A scorecard without action is a vanity exercise; mandating action within 30 days converts scoring into outcome.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-histogram-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After scoring, publish the band histogram + median score in the founder's internal log (or build update). Shape of distribution is the actual ICP signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Distribution-thinking research">A single median hides the distribution; histogram shows where the long tail of REMOVEs lives and informs persona refinement.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies-If hold and no Skip-If trigger applies, walk the 6-step procedure end-to-end and run the validator before declaring the scorecard ready.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory run leaf">Decision-tree run leaf for canonical execution path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the Applies-If preconditions are not met OR any Skip-If disqualifier holds.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory skip leaf">Decision-tree skip leaf for non-applicable inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
