<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-confidence" title="Confidence Score and LLM Validation Pipeline">
  <summary>Confidence score formula, pre-phase check template, LLM validation pipeline, LLM-as-judge pattern, and CI/CD gate enforcement strategies.</summary>

  <section title="Confidence Score">
    <rule>
      <statement>Calculate confidence as a weighted sum of four objective factors; require artifact evidence (test output, coverage report) rather than agent self-assessment.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents treating confidence scores as checkboxes self-report inflated values. Requiring actual measurement artifacts (not just agent assertions) produces reliable scores.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Confidence = (Automated_Pass * 0.4) + (Coverage * 0.2) +
             (Risk_Mitigation * 0.2) + (Traceability * 0.2)

Factors:
  Automated_Pass  (40%): % of automated checks passing
  Coverage        (20%): % of requirements covered by tests
  Risk_Mitigation (20%): % of identified risks with mitigations
  Traceability    (20%): % of requirements traceable to implementation
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Pre-Phase Confidence Check Template">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Confidence Check: [Phase Name]

### Prerequisites Met
- [ ] Previous gate passed (artifact attached)
- [ ] Required artifacts exist
- [ ] Dependencies available
- [ ] Context understood

### Current Confidence: X%

### Proceed?
- [ ] YES (>= threshold)
- [ ] NO (< threshold) — Reason: [...]
      ]]></code>
      <note>Every phase transition requires an explicit confidence check. "Proceed?" is a binary decision, not a sliding scale.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM Validation Pipeline">
    <p>Standard flow for validating LLM-generated code:</p>
    <list>
      <item>LLM generates code</item>
      <item>L1 check: if fail, re-prompt with exact lint/type output; cap at 3 re-prompts</item>
      <item>L2 check: if fail, re-prompt with exact test failure output; cap at 3 re-prompts</item>
      <item>AI review: secondary model reviews for correctness and completeness</item>
      <item>Human spot-check: business logic, security implications</item>
      <item>Merge</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Check LLM output against L1 immediately after generation; do not accumulate multiple files before the first gate check.</statement>
      <rationale>Early feedback prevents context drift. An agent that writes 10 files before seeing L1 errors must revisit all 10; an agent that sees L1 errors after each file corrects patterns immediately.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM-as-Judge Pattern">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a different model from the one that generated the code for L4 correctness evaluation.</statement>
      <rationale>Generation model has systematic blind spots for its own output — it will approve its own logic errors. A secondary evaluator with fresh context catches what the generator cannot.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
LLM-as-judge prompt (L4):
You are an evaluator. Input: spec.md (AC-X list), test-plan.md, implementation diff.
Score 0-100 on:
- Correctness: implementation matches all AC? (40%)
- Completeness: all requirements addressed? (20%)
- Security: obvious vulnerabilities? (20%)
- Maintainability: readable, follows patterns? (20%)
Output: score, factor breakdown, issues blocking L4 approval.
Threshold: 80% minimum.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Gate Enforcement Strategies">
    <list>
      <item>Hard block (L1, L2): pipeline fails, no proceed — these gates are 100% automated and objective</item>
      <item>Soft block (L3, L4): warning, require human approval to proceed — human judgment can assess context</item>
      <item>Advisory: log issues, allow proceed — for non-critical informational checks only</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define gate pass criteria in constitution.md at project start, not per-feature under deadline pressure.</statement>
      <rationale>Negotiating thresholds under deadline pressure produces inconsistent standards and technical debt. Fixed, project-level standards prevent this.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/quality-gates.yml">GitHub Actions pipeline implementing L1-L4</reference>
  <reference path="templates/calculate-confidence.py">Python confidence score calculator</reference>
  <reference path="templates/run-gates.sh">Local L1-L2 gate runner script</reference>
</text>
