<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-hierarchy" title="Help Hierarchy and Content Patterns">
  <summary>Seven-level help hierarchy, contextual help patterns (inline hints, tooltips, tours), and content type matrix by use case.</summary>

  <section title="Help Hierarchy">
    <p>Prioritized from best to last resort:</p>
    <p>1. Interface design that needs no explanation (best — eliminate confusion at source).</p>
    <p>2. Inline help — field hints, placeholder text visible during interaction.</p>
    <p>3. Tooltips — on-hover explanation for icons and controls.</p>
    <p>4. Guided tours — onboarding walkthroughs for new users.</p>
    <p>5. FAQs — answers to common questions (5 max per page).</p>
    <p>6. Documentation — detailed task-focused articles with numbered steps.</p>
    <p>7. Human support (last resort — tickets, chat, email).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Fix the interface before adding help content; help that compensates for a broken design is a band-aid, not a solution.</statement>
      <rationale>Help content that explains a confusing flow treats the symptom; redesigning the flow eliminates the need. Documentation is more expensive to maintain than a clear UI.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Contextual Help Patterns">
    <p>Inline hints (always visible): label + hint text below field, placeholder text in inputs.</p>
    <p>Tooltips (on demand): [?] icon hover → brief explanation, [i] icon hover → feature context.</p>
    <p>Contextual panels: collapsible sidebar with page-specific help for complex features.</p>
    <p>Onboarding tours: step-by-step overlay anchored to specific UI elements with [Skip] and [Next] options.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Stripe dashboard: contextual tooltip on each metric explains what it measures and how to improve it. Help appears where the user is, not in a separate help center.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Help buried in footer with no contextual help anywhere in the app. Users who get stuck mid-task must navigate away to find answers, losing their context.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Types by Use Case">
    <p>
      Onboarding: welcome tour (first login), empty states (new sections), progress checklist (guide setup).
      In-context: tooltips (hover), inline hints (always visible), [?] icons (on demand).
      Reference: FAQs (quick answers), how-to articles (numbered steps), reference docs (complete detail).
      Support: search (self-service), chat (real-time help), email (complex issues).
    </p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Organize help content by user tasks (verbs), not product features (nouns).</statement>
      <rationale>Users search for what they want to accomplish ("how to reset password"), not what the feature is called internally ("Authentication Settings"). Task-based organization matches search intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/help-article.md">Help article structure template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/help-audit.md">Help coverage audit template</reference>
</text>
