<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Help and Documentation Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Authoring quality rules, measuring help effectiveness, common mistakes, and agent limitations for help content generation.</summary>

  <section title="Authoring Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Test search discoverability by typing the phrase a frustrated user would type, not the feature name.</statement>
      <rationale>Users search by task context ("why is my payment failing") not by feature name ("Payment Processing Module"); discoverability testing must use user-language queries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a "Last reviewed" date to every help article and schedule quarterly reviews in the project backlog.</statement>
      <rationale>Help content decays as the product changes; undated articles have no signal about staleness, and users lose trust when steps no longer match the UI.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep FAQs to five questions maximum per page; create separate detailed articles for depth.</statement>
      <rationale>Long FAQ pages become unscannable; five questions per page with links to detail articles maintains scannability while enabling depth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Link related articles bidirectionally; users reading "password reset" also need "two-factor authentication".</statement>
      <rationale>Single-article dead ends force users back to search; bidirectional links keep users in the help flow until their question is answered.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Measuring Help Effectiveness">
    <p>
      Help searches — what users are looking for (unmet needs signal).
      Search success rate — do users find answers? (gaps in coverage).
      Support tickets — questions that help should answer but does not.
      Feature adoption — does contextual help increase usage of complex features?
      Deflection rate — tickets created after reading an article = help failure.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Help content not maintained after feature changes.</description>
      <reason>Outdated screenshots and broken step sequences are worse than no documentation; they waste user time and erode trust.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Documentation written for experts, not users.</description>
      <reason>Jargon without explanation excludes the users who need help most; documentation must assume the minimum viable context.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No help exists at the point of confusion — only a footer link to a help center.</description>
      <reason>Users who encounter confusion mid-task need help in context, not after navigating away and losing their progress.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Usage Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every agent-generated step sequence must be verified against actual product flows before publishing.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs generate plausible-sounding but incorrect step sequences without product access; factual accuracy requires human verification against the live product.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Articles touching billing, security, or account deletion require legal/compliance review before publishing.</statement>
      <rationale>Incorrect information in these areas creates legal and reputational risk; human review is mandatory regardless of how accurate the agent output appears.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Instruct the agent to keep help articles under 500 words and audit length in a follow-up pass.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs over-enumerate steps; long articles are not read to completion and fail to answer the user's specific question quickly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/help_gap_finder.py">Python script to find features missing help coverage</reference>
</text>
