<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="clickup-setup">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>ClickUp workspace architecture: 4-level hierarchy, ClickApps configuration, custom status workflow, views, and automation rules for project management and time tracking.</summary>
    <category>pm</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>clickup</tag>
      <tag>project-management</tag>
      <tag>task-tracking</tag>
      <tag>team-coordination</tag>
      <tag>workflow-automation</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>ClickUp Setup</title>

    <summary>ClickUp workspace architecture: 4-level hierarchy (Workspace → Space → Folder → List), ClickApps configuration (Sprints, Time Tracking, Custom Fields, Priorities, Multiple Assignees), custom status workflow per space, views (List, Board, Gantt, Workload, Dashboard), and automation rules for status transitions and template application. Create custom fields at the highest applicable level (Workspace > Space > Folder) to avoid duplication.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>ClickUp combines task tracking, docs, goals, and time tracking in one tool, making it suited for cross-functional teams that would otherwise need multiple SaaS subscriptions. The workspace hierarchy separates permissions and workflows by team while sharing a single workspace. Automation rules reduce manual status management and enforce consistent task structure via templates.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Starting a new organization that needs PM, docs, and time tracking in one tool</item>
        <item>Migrating from a simpler tool (Trello, Asana) when the team has outgrown it</item>
        <item>Cross-functional team with different workflows per department (Engineering uses Sprints; Marketing uses a content calendar)</item>
        <item>OKR and goal tracking needed alongside task management</item>
        <item>Time tracking and billing required</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Team is already on GitHub and needs code-task traceability — GitHub Projects is a better fit</item>
        <item>Solo developer or very small team — ClickUp's hierarchy adds setup overhead that exceeds its value at this scale</item>
        <item>Team primarily needs kanban with minimal configuration — Trello is simpler and faster to adopt</item>
        <item>Technical team values keyboard-first, minimal-config workflows — Linear is a better fit</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="workspace-hierarchy">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Limit hierarchy depth to 4 levels: Workspace (organization) → Space (department/team) → Folder (project/initiative) → List (phase/workflow stage). Never create Folders inside Folders — it creates navigation complexity that cannot be displayed in most views.</statement>
        <rationale>Every hierarchy level adds a navigation click. Deeper hierarchies increase onboarding friction and create permission management complexity.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use Spaces to separate teams with different workflows and permission requirements. Spaces have independent status sets and ClickApp configurations — never share a Space between teams with incompatible workflows.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing teams in one Space forces a single status workflow on all of them. Separate Spaces allow Engineering to use Sprints while Marketing uses a content calendar without conflict.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Workspace hierarchy design:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Workspace — organization-wide configuration and permissions root</item>
        <item>Spaces — department/team level (Engineering, Product, Marketing, Support)</item>
        <item>Folders — project or initiative within a space</item>
        <item>Lists — workflow stages or phase container (Current Sprint, Backlog, Done)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="clickapps-configuration">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Enable these ClickApps at workspace level: Custom Fields, Priorities (Urgent/High/Normal/Low), Multiple Assignees. Enable Sprints and Time Tracking at Space level where applicable. Enabling Sprints workspace-wide forces sprint discipline on spaces that do not practice it (e.g., Support).</statement>
        <rationale>Workspace-level ClickApps apply to all Spaces. Space-level ClickApps are opt-in — enabling sprint management only where needed reduces noise elsewhere.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>ClickApp selection guide:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Workspace-level: Custom Fields, Priorities, Multiple Assignees, Templates</item>
        <item>Space-level (per team need): Sprints, Time Tracking, Milestones, Recurring Tasks</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="custom-fields">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Create custom fields at the highest applicable level: Workspace if used everywhere, Space if team-specific, Folder if project-specific. Never create the same field twice at different levels — use the inherited version.</statement>
        <rationale>Duplicate fields at multiple hierarchy levels create data inconsistency when filters aggregate across levels.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use dropdown type for Sprint and Component fields — not free text. This prevents typos, enables filtering, and allows automation rules to trigger on specific values.</statement>
        <rationale>Free-text sprint names like "Sprint1", "sprint 1", "Sprint 01" break filters and automation. Dropdowns enforce consistent values.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep the total number of visible custom fields per view to 8 or fewer. Archive custom fields that are not actively used.</statement>
        <rationale>Too many fields create cognitive load and slow down task entry. Fields not used in automation or reporting have no value in the main view.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="custom-field-strategy">
        <p>Custom field best practices:</p>
        <list>
          <item>Story Points — Workspace level, Dropdown (1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13)</item>
          <item>Component — Space level, Dropdown (list all product components)</item>
          <item>Affected Teams — Space level, Multiple Select</item>
          <item>Billing Code — Space level if multiple billing streams, Dropdown</item>
          <item>Customer — Space level for customer-facing work, Link to a Space list</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="custom-status-workflow">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define the status workflow at Space level, not List level. A consistent status set across all Lists in a Space enables cross-list filtering and automation. Typical development workflow: Backlog → Ready for Dev → In Development → Code Review → QA Testing → Complete / Won't Do.</statement>
        <rationale>Per-List status sets make cross-list "show all In Development tasks" queries impossible. Space-level statuses are queryable across all Folders and Lists.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Status workflow examples by team type:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Engineering: Backlog → Ready for Dev → In Development → Code Review → QA Testing → Complete / Won't Do</item>
        <item>Marketing: Idea → Planning → In Progress → In Review → Published / Archived</item>
        <item>Support: New → Assigned → In Progress → Waiting for Customer → Resolved / Won't Fix</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="automation-rules">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Start with 3-5 automation rules and add more only as specific manual friction points are identified. Document every automation rule in a team handbook — undocumented automations confuse new team members who observe unexpected behavior.</statement>
        <rationale>Automation bloat creates circular triggers and unexpected state changes. Each rule should solve a confirmed pain point, not a hypothetical one.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Test every automation rule on a test task before enabling it in production. Automation loops (rule A triggers rule B which triggers rule A) cause infinite task state changes. Check for circular dependencies before enabling.</statement>
        <rationale>ClickUp automation loops are not automatically detected. They cause task status thrashing and notification spam that is difficult to diagnose after the fact.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Starter Automation Rules">
        <note>Automation 1: when status changes to "In Development" → assign from custom field "Developer". Automation 2: when task created in List "Features" → apply task template "Feature Template". Automation 3: when due date arrives AND status not in ["Complete", "Won't Do"] → send email to assignee. These three cover the most common manual steps without creating circular dependencies.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Automation: when status changes to "In Development" → set status to "In Progress". Then: when status changes to "In Progress" → set status to "In Development".</description>
        <reason>Circular automation loop. Task will switch states indefinitely until manually stopped.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="views">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Create purpose-specific views rather than general-purpose catch-all views: List view for detailed task management (all fields visible), Board for kanban execution (grouped by status), Gantt for timeline planning (with dependencies), Workload for capacity planning, Dashboard for sprint metrics. Each view should answer a specific question.</statement>
        <rationale>General-purpose views become cluttered. Purpose-specific views load faster (fewer fields) and train team members on which view to use for each workflow step.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Add Workload view whenever Sprint ClickApp is enabled. Workload requires Time Estimates on tasks to show capacity — set time estimates as a required field when Sprints are active.</statement>
        <rationale>Capacity planning without time estimates is guesswork. Workload view is only useful when estimates are populated consistently.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>View types and their purposes:</p>
      <list>
        <item>List — detailed task editing, all fields visible, sort by priority/due date</item>
        <item>Board — kanban workflow, grouped by status, drag-and-drop status changes</item>
        <item>Gantt — timeline view with task dependencies, used for release planning</item>
        <item>Workload — capacity view showing team members and estimated hours per sprint</item>
        <item>Dashboard — sprint metrics, burndown, team capacity summary</item>
        <item>Calendar — due date view, deadlines at a glance</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="integrations">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For GitHub integration: enable branch naming convention "clickup-{task_id}-{task_name}" to create automatic task-to-PR links. Set auto status to "Complete" on PR merge. Store the integration webhook URL in .aidocs/memory/ — it changes when re-authenticated.</statement>
        <rationale>Branch name conventions enable ClickUp to detect linked PRs automatically without manual linking by developers.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For Slack integration: notify on status changes and comment additions, not on every field change. Over-notification causes recipients to mute the channel within days.</statement>
        <rationale>Signal-to-noise ratio is the primary failure mode of PM tool Slack integrations. Scope notifications to meaningful state changes only.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Recommended integrations and configuration:</p>
      <list>
        <item>GitHub — automatic PR linking, status on merge, branch naming convention</item>
        <item>Slack — status change notifications, daily/weekly summaries, not every field change</item>
        <item>n8n — complex automations beyond native ClickUp automation (cross-tool workflows)</item>
        <item>Toggl — time tracking integration for billable work estimation</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Guidelines for AI agents interacting with ClickUp:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Agent authentication — use personal ClickUp API tokens, store in environment variables (CLICKUP_TOKEN)</item>
        <item>Task creation — agents read Workspace/Space/Folder hierarchy once to cache IDs, then batch create tasks</item>
        <item>Custom field writes — agents must fetch field_id UUIDs first; never hallucinate field IDs</item>
        <item>Due dates — ClickUp API uses millisecond Unix timestamps, not ISO 8601; convert before API calls</item>
        <item>Template application — ClickUp API has no template application endpoint; agents must create tasks with inline content</item>
        <item>Status updates — agents respect Space-level status workflow; never invent ad-hoc statuses</item>
      </list>

      <note>Store team_id, space_ids, folder_ids, list_ids, and custom field_ids in `.aidocs/memory/` — agents reuse these IDs across sessions to avoid refetching and wasting API quota.</note>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://clickup.com/api/clickupreference/operation/GetAuthorizedTeams/"/>
      <link href="https://clickup.com/features"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/icapps/clickup-cli"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
