<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="pm-certification-alignment-2026 Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for pm-certification-alignment-2026. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not allocate study time proportional to domain weight. Allocate proportional to (weight x current gap): a candidate already strong in People should deprioritize it even though it is 33% of the exam.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Weight-proportional allocation optimizes for the exam's average candidate, not for the individual candidate's actual weaknesses. The maximum study ROI comes from closing the highest-weight gaps first.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every coverage claim against an exam theme must cite a verbatim anchor from the official ECO PDF or PMBOK section (e.g., "ECO p.12 / PMBOK 8 §3.4"). Reject any claim without an anchor.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents confidently fabricate PMBOK section references; a verbatim anchor forces verification against an indexed source and prevents teaching content that does not exist in the official material.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sustainability content in PMBOK 8 is thin; supplement with ISO 14001, GRI standards, and IFRS S1+S2 for substantive study material. Never use agent-generated ISO clause text without cross-referencing the actual standard.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents fabricate plausible-sounding ISO clauses; the real standards are the only authoritative source and must be the cross-reference for any sustainability claim.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Practical decision-making and tailoring questions resist memorization. Require scenario-based practice; rote-answer training agents perform poorly on these questions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">PMP tailoring questions require reasoning from situational context, not recall; agents trained on rote patterns produce generic answers ("use both predictive and agile") that fail on specific scenarios.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For the +18% Business Environment shift, prioritize these methodology areas first before re-doing People or Process content: benefits-realization, value-stream-management, change-control, pm-framework-focus-areas. Add sustainability framing (ISO 14001, GRI) to each.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The Business Environment domain grew from 8% to 26%; existing methodology libraries built on PMBOK 6/7 are structurally deficient here. Filling this gap delivers the highest exam-score improvement per study hour.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store the alignment matrix in git as CSV with columns: domain, task_id, enablers, themes, covered_by (methodology slugs), evidence_anchor. Empty covered_by = gap. Never claim coverage without an evidence_anchor.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A git-tracked matrix creates a diff history as the ECO changes; treating it as the system-of-record (and generating the wiki from it, not the reverse) prevents drift between documentation and actual coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-run the alignment mapping after each annual ECO refresh and after any PMBOK edition release. Wire coverage_gaps.py to CI; failures open an issue assigned to the curriculum owner.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">ECO changes are typically announced 6 months before effective date; a CI-triggered gap report provides automated early warning rather than a manual audit cycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
