<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="PM Certification Alignment 2026 Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding PM Certification Alignment 2026. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="eco-mapping-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each methodology MUST be tagged with primary ECO 2026 domain ∈ {People, Process, Business Environment} and theme.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI Examination Content Outline 2026">Untagged methodologies cannot inform candidate study plans; explicit tagging makes coverage measurable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="coverage-vs-weights" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Coverage analysis MUST compare methodology count per domain against ECO weight percentages (People 33%, Process 41%, Business Environment 26%).</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI ECO 2026">Coverage gaps correlate with exam-section underperformance; weight-vs-count comparison surfaces them.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="themes-five-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Theme tags MUST come from the five canonical 2026 exam themes; ad-hoc themes forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI ECO 2026 — Five themes section">Ad-hoc themes fragment the rubric; five-theme constraint preserves comparability across cohorts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="gap-action-with-due" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each coverage gap MUST trigger an action item with owner + due date (e.g. author missing methodology by Q3-2026).</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion content roadmap discipline">Gaps without actions persist for years; the rule forces backlog placement.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="study-plan-evidence-based" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Candidate study plan MUST cite the rubric output; ad-hoc study plans forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — exam-prep delivery audit">Ad-hoc study plans rely on instructor intuition; evidence-based plans tune time per ECO weight.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for PM Certification Alignment 2026 fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying PM Certification Alignment 2026 outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
