<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-domain-weights" title="2026 Domain Weights and Exam Themes">
  <summary>2026 PMP ECO domain weight deltas versus PMBOK 7, five exam themes, the anchor-citation requirement, and study-allocation rule.</summary>

  <section title="2026 Domain Weight Shifts">
    <p>Domain weights (PMBOK 7 → PMBOK 8): People 42% → 33% (-9%). Process 50% → 41% (-9%). Business Environment 8% → 26% (+18%). The +18% Business Environment shift is the most significant change in the PMP exam in a decade.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not allocate study time proportional to domain weight. Allocate proportional to (weight x current gap): a candidate already strong in People should deprioritize it even though it is 33% of the exam.</statement>
      <rationale>Weight-proportional allocation optimizes for the exam's average candidate, not for the individual candidate's actual weaknesses. The maximum study ROI comes from closing the highest-weight gaps first.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Five Exam Themes">
    <p>Value Delivery: outcomes over outputs, benefits realization, value stream thinking. Governance: oversight, decision frameworks, stage gates. Sustainability: environmental, social, economic impact (ISO 14001, GRI, IFRS S1+S2). Stakeholder Engagement: communications integrated with stakeholder analysis. Practical Decision-Making: tailoring, situational trade-offs, hybrid approach selection.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every coverage claim against an exam theme must cite a verbatim anchor from the official ECO PDF or PMBOK section (e.g., "ECO p.12 / PMBOK 8 §3.4"). Reject any claim without an anchor.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents confidently fabricate PMBOK section references; a verbatim anchor forces verification against an indexed source and prevents teaching content that does not exist in the official material.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Limitations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Sustainability content in PMBOK 8 is thin; supplement with ISO 14001, GRI standards, and IFRS S1+S2 for substantive study material. Never use agent-generated ISO clause text without cross-referencing the actual standard.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents fabricate plausible-sounding ISO clauses; the real standards are the only authoritative source and must be the cross-reference for any sustainability claim.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Practical decision-making and tailoring questions resist memorization. Require scenario-based practice; rote-answer training agents perform poorly on these questions.</statement>
      <rationale>PMP tailoring questions require reasoning from situational context, not recall; agents trained on rote patterns produce generic answers ("use both predictive and agile") that fail on specific scenarios.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
