<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Launch-Day Warroom Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every launch-day war room must enforce. These prevent the most common failure: coordination breakdown when traffic spikes.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-named-roles-with-backup" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every role (launch director, content captain, ops lead, support triage, exec stand-in) is named with primary + named backup. Reject launches with any role unfilled OR backup missing OR a single person holding two roles.</statement>
      <rationale source="launch postmortems">Empty or doubled roles produce the "everyone thought someone else was watching" failure. Backups handle the inevitable absence (sick day, network outage, parallel duty).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-dress-rehearsal-48h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a 60-minute dress rehearsal 48-72 hours before launch. Walk through hourly checkpoints, post test messages to launch channels, simulate one rollback scenario. Reject launches without a recorded dress rehearsal.</statement>
      <rationale source="incident response training literature">Rehearsals expose template errors and channel-permission bugs at near-zero cost. Teams that rehearse have 3-5× lower MTTR during launch incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-hourly-checkpoints" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Launch day runs on hourly checkpoints, each with explicit decisions: traffic_status, channel_post_status, support_queue_depth, error_rate, next_hour_action. Reject silent hours: every hour produces a logged update.</statement>
      <rationale source="war-room ops literature">Hourly cadence prevents drift and surfaces issues 6× faster than ad-hoc updates. Silence is the loudest failure signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-decision-rights-matrix" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every decision class (post tweet, halt email send, pause PH push, scale infra) has a named decider AND threshold. Reject ambiguous decision authority. Decisions over launch-stop authority belong to launch director with exec stand-in tiebreaker.</statement>
      <rationale source="agile decision-making research">Unambiguous decision rights cut deliberation latency by 50%+ during high-pressure windows. RACI matrices apply during launches too.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-rollback-playbook" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A rollback playbook covers: partial rollback (retract one channel), full rollback (pull PH listing + email retraction + status page update), exec-comms template. Rollback decision criteria documented (e.g., "error rate &gt; 5% sustained 30 min triggers partial"). Reject launches without rollback playbook.</statement>
      <rationale source="launch-rollback case studies">Launches that go sideways without rollback playbooks compound damage. Pre-defined rollback turns chaos into a known procedure.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="War-room runbook with named roles">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Launch: AcmeNext v2 — Product Hunt + email + Twitter
Window: 2026-05-22 07:00 PT - 19:00 PT

Roles:
  Launch director:   @jdoe       (backup: @asmith)
  Content captain:   @kchen      (backup: @rgomez)
  Ops lead:          @tparker    (backup: @sosborne)
  Support triage:    @ljohnson   (backup: @nyamada)
  Exec stand-in:     @mceo

Channels:
  #launch-control   — decisions, hourly updates (all leads + exec)
  #launch-content   — copy review, asset publishing (content + director)
  #launch-support   — incoming issues, customer responses (support)
  #launch-exec      — exec-only briefings on issues > sev3
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 + r3 + r4 in a launch-day setup.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Chaos by Slack thread">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
DM thread of 8 people. No named roles. PM is asking on Slack "who's
posting to PH at 7am?" Marketing lead asks "should we hold the email
send if signups slow?" — no answer. Engineer pushes hotfix without
notifying support, who get blindsided by panicked customers.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1, r3, r4 violations. Common shape of launches that fail on coordination.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
