<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-rules" title="Help and Documentation — Core Rules">
  <summary>Concrete rules for implementing Nielsen Heuristic #10: layered help hierarchy, contextual placement, task-focused content, and maintenance discipline.</summary>

  <section title="Help Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow the help hierarchy in order: interface design first (no help needed), then inline hints, tooltips, guided tours, FAQs, documentation, and human support as a last resort.</statement>
      <rationale>Each layer up the hierarchy adds friction and cost. If a tooltip can answer the question, a knowledge base article is overkill.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>If a UI element requires a tooltip to be understood, fix the UI first — help content cannot substitute for clear design.</statement>
      <rationale>Documentation that compensates for poor design grows unbounded and becomes impossible to maintain as the UI evolves.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Contextual Placement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place help at the point of confusion: inline hints below inputs, tooltips on ? icons, contextual sidebars on complex pages.</statement>
      <rationale>Help content found only in a separate help center requires users to leave their task context, increasing cognitive load and abandonment risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every empty state is help content — design empty states with action guidance, not just "No items found."</statement>
      <rationale>Empty states are the most frequent onboarding moment; they are the first help interaction most users encounter.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Content Quality">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write help content in user language (support ticket language), not product-team language — users search with their words, not yours.</statement>
      <rationale>Search success rate directly correlates with vocabulary alignment between help content and user mental models.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every how-to article must have a "Result" section describing what success looks like after completing all steps.</statement>
      <rationale>Users who complete steps but do not know if they succeeded will contact support anyway; a clear success description closes the loop.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep inline hints under 15 words; tooltips under 40 words; how-to articles structured with numbered steps and no more than 7 steps per section.</statement>
      <rationale>Users in an error state or onboarding context have limited attention; long help content is skipped.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Maintenance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write help content at the moment a feature ships — treat it as a definition of done, not a post-launch task.</statement>
      <rationale>Retroactive documentation is always incomplete; features ship faster than writers can reconstruct intent from memory.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Version-pin screenshots with the app version they were taken from; stale screenshots erode trust faster than missing ones.</statement>
      <rationale>A screenshot showing a UI that no longer exists actively misleads users and generates support tickets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track "zero-results help searches" weekly — each is an explicit content gap signal.</statement>
      <rationale>Search analytics reveal user intent vocabulary that no content strategy meeting can surface.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/help-content.md">How-to article structure template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/help-audit.md">Help audit table template</reference>
  <reference path="scripts/help-audit.sh">Script to check docs for broken links and stale content markers</reference>
</text>
