<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Help and Documentation — Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete good and bad examples of help and documentation implementation across real products.</summary>

  <section title="Good Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Notion: contextual ? icon on each feature, searchable help center, video tutorials, template gallery (learning by example). Help is accessible without leaving the product and organized by user task.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Stripe: comprehensive documentation with code examples in multiple languages, interactive API explorer, contextual tooltips in dashboard. Help is written at the developer's level of abstraction and tested against real API responses.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Slack: Slackbot answers questions in-context, keyboard shortcut guide (?/), getting started checklist for onboarding, searchable help center. Multiple help types serve different user states (first-time, returning, expert).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Help buried in footer: no contextual assistance in the product, users must search the entire site to find an answer.</description>
      <reason>Users in an error state or confusion moment will not navigate away from their current task to find help; they will abandon or contact support instead.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Outdated documentation: screenshots from an old version, features that no longer exist, broken links.</description>
      <reason>Stale screenshots actively mislead users; they follow steps that no longer match the UI and conclude the product is broken, not the documentation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Technical overload: documentation assumes expertise, no beginner content, jargon without explanation.</description>
      <reason>Help written for the product team's level of knowledge fails new users who lack that vocabulary; support ticket volume increases for questions that beginner documentation would answer.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Help Content Types by Phase">
    <p>Onboarding phase: welcome tours (first login), empty states (new sections with action guidance), progress checklist (guide setup completion).</p>
    <p>In-context phase: tooltips on hover (explain specific elements), inline hints always visible (guide input), ? icons on demand (detailed explanation).</p>
    <p>Reference phase: FAQs (quick answers to common questions), how-tos (step-by-step task guidance), reference docs (complete information).</p>
    <p>Support phase: search (self-service answer finding), chat (real-time human assistance), email (complex issue resolution).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Help Effectiveness Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Help searches: what users look for — reveals vocabulary gaps</item>
      <item>Search success rate: do users find answers? — reveals content gaps</item>
      <item>Zero-results searches: explicit content gap signal, track weekly</item>
      <item>Support tickets: questions that help should already answer</item>
      <item>Feature adoption rate: does contextual help increase usage?</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
