<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="help-documentation Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for help-documentation as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents generate plausible but inaccurate step-by-step instructions when they lack ground-truth product screenshots or current UI state</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without access to the live product, agents cannot verify that steps match actual UI elements or account for real state transitions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Generated documentation goes stale immediately after product changes — no self-updating mechanism without a pipeline</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Static documentation quickly diverges from reality; version-pinning screenshots and maintaining a content update schedule are manual processes.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Contextual help placement requires UI/UX judgment that agents cannot make from text descriptions alone</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents cannot visualize the layout; human designers must validate that help content appears in the right location without creating visual clutter.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents cannot verify that help content is accessible (screen reader, keyboard navigation) without running automated tools</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Accessibility must be tested with actual assistive technology; text descriptions alone cannot verify readability or usability for users with disabilities.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Help audit tables generated from requirement lists miss implicit user confusion patterns — support tickets are a better input</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Real users encounter edge cases and confusing state transitions that requirements documents do not capture.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents cannot verify that generated step-by-step instructions match the actual current UI</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always require a human QA pass against the live product before publishing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Generated FAQ answers are often correct in aggregate but wrong in specific edge cases</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Human review required before publishing; test with actual users if possible.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents producing onboarding tour copy do not know which UI elements exist or their current labels</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Provide a component inventory as input; require verification against the running product.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Direct publication of agent-generated documentation without editorial review</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Treat all agent output as first draft requiring editorial review before publishing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents will invent plausible troubleshooting steps that do not correspond to real error states</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require a list of actual error codes/states as input to the agent prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
