<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="comms" count="26">
  <methodology slug="active-listening" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/active-listening">
    <summary>A structured listening practice (RASA: Receive, Appreciate, Summarize, Ask) that ensures the speaker feels understood before the listener responds.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="brainstorming-ideation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/brainstorming-ideation">
    <summary>Brainstorming-ideation covers using brainstorming techniques as a generative input for automated pipelines — where the output is a scored shortlist, not a facilitated group session.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="brainstorming-techniques" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/brainstorming-techniques">
    <summary>Brainstorming techniques structure group ideation to maximize quantity and diversity of ideas while preventing dominant voices and premature evaluation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="business-storytelling" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/business-storytelling">
    <summary>Frameworks for structuring persuasive business communication so that audiences grasp the point immediately and remember it.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="conflict-resolution" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/conflict-resolution">
    <summary>Conflict resolution uses two complementary frameworks: Thomas-Kilmann's five modes (Competing, Collaborating, Compromising, Avoiding, Accommodating) to select the right strategy for a situation, and Marshall Rosenberg's Nonviolent Communication (NVC) four-step formula (Observation → Feeling → Need → Request) to structure the message.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contractor-audition-flow" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/contractor-audition-flow">
    <summary>Contractor Audition Flow: codified comms practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Build a bench of vetted subcontractors without becoming an agency-of-agencies' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="contractor-onboarding-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/contractor-onboarding-runbook">
    <summary>Contractor Onboarding Runbook: codified comms practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Hire and onboard a new contractor (3–5 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="difficult-conversations" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/difficult-conversations">
    <summary>The Crucial Conversations framework structures high-stakes conversations (high stakes + differing opinions + strong emotions) through seven sequential skills: Start with Heart → Learn to Look → Make it Safe → Master My Stories → STATE My Path → Explore Others' Paths → Move to Action.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="executive-stakeholder-demo-narrative-frame" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/executive-stakeholder-demo-narrative-frame">
    <summary>Executive Stakeholder Demo Narrative Frame delivers a concrete, testable methodology that turns the recurring task of 'Client demo prep + run' into an auditable artefact, addressing the gap: Business storytelling and selling-ideas exist at solo tier. Pro-tier outsource specialist</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="feedback" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/feedback">
    <summary>A set of structured models for delivering and receiving feedback that is specific, behavior-focused, and actionable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-inbound-reply-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/freelancer-inbound-reply-template">
    <summary>Freelancer Inbound Reply Template — testable methodology for scripts, written cadences, stakeholder updates. First-touch reply template for LinkedIn / email inbound that qualifies AND warms in 4 lines. Distinct from cold outbound; faion's growth-copywriting covers outbound but not inbound triage.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-payment-chase-script-library" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/freelancer-payment-chase-script-library">
    <summary>Freelancer Payment Chase Script Library — testable methodology for scripts, written cadences, stakeholder updates. Escalation ladder of payment-chase emails (polite → firm → legal-mention) tuned to preserve the relationship while collecting. Most existing comms methodologies are too generic for collections.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-rate-raise-letter-template" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/freelancer-rate-raise-letter-template">
    <summary>Freelancer Rate Raise Letter Template — testable methodology for scripts, written cadences, stakeholder updates. Battle-tested raise-announcement letter template for retainer clients with grace-period framing. difficult-conversations is too general.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-scope-change-script-library" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/freelancer-scope-change-script-library">
    <summary>Freelancer Scope Change Script Library — testable methodology for scripts, written cadences, stakeholder updates. 10-15 ready scripts for common 'just one more thing' situations (small ask vs. big ask vs. mission-creep vs. emergency). Faion has difficult-conversations but no domain-specific scripts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="freelancer-weekly-report-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/freelancer-weekly-report-template">
    <summary>Freelancer Weekly Report Template — testable methodology for scripts, written cadences, stakeholder updates. Outcome-first weekly report template optimized for non-technical clients. Faion's pm/communications-management is too process-heavy for a solo's 10-min Friday recap.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="graceful-offboard-script" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/graceful-offboard-script">
    <summary>Graceful Offboard Script — testable methodology for scripts, written cadences, stakeholder updates. Bad-fit offboarding is a strategic move for agencies; no methodology covers how to do it without damaging brand or referral pipeline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ideation-methods" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/ideation-methods">
    <summary>Structured frameworks for generating and developing ideas systematically: SCAMPER (apply 7 lenses to an existing product to generate variants), Mind Mapping (visual branching for exploring connections), and Starbursting (5W+H question generation before answering).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mom-test" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/mom-test">
    <summary>The Mom Test (Rob Fitzpatrick, 2013) is a customer discovery interview protocol with three rules: talk about their life not your idea; ask about past specifics not future hypotheticals; talk less than 20% of the time.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="negotiation" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/negotiation">
    <summary>A framework for interest-based negotiation that replaces positional bargaining with mutual-gain problem solving.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="paid-test-task-scoring-rubric" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/paid-test-task-scoring-rubric">
    <summary>Paid Test Task Scoring Rubric: codified comms practice that turns the recurring 'p5-micro-agency-founder/Hire and onboard a new contractor (3–5 weeks)' decision into a repeatable, auditable artefact.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="selling-ideas" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/selling-ideas">
    <summary>A persuasion framework for pitching technical or business ideas to different audiences.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="senior-promotion-case-template-outsource-shop" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/senior-promotion-case-template-outsource-shop">
    <summary>Promotion case template tailored to outsource shops (SoftServe/EPAM/Globant/Andela) — combines technical scope, revenue impact, and utilization on the same rubric.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-support-sla-template" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/solo-support-sla-template">
    <summary>Solo-SaaS support SLA tiers (free/paid/enterprise) with reply-time bands and canned-reply templates that protect founder calendar while signalling responsiveness.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="solo-testimonial-extraction-script" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/solo-testimonial-extraction-script">
    <summary>A 3-question testimonial elicitation script that produces a usable quote, a metric, and a use-case sentence in one customer reply — replacing "could you write us a testimonial?" with a high-yield interview pattern.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="stakeholder-communication" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/stakeholder-communication">
    <summary>Stakeholder communication selects a dialogue mode before any conversation: Interview (requirements gathering), Brainstorm (option generation), Clarification (resolving ambiguity), Validation (confirming understanding), or Socratic (probing assumptions).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="storytelling" tier="solo" path="skills/faion/knowledge/solo/comms/communicator/storytelling">
    <summary>People remember stories 22x better than facts alone.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
