<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Serverless Cold Start Optimization Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the serverless-cold-start-optimization methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale; the final rule is the skip-this-methodology gate referenced by the decision tree.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-measure-before-mitigating" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mitigation work MUST start from a measured baseline (cold + warm p50 / p95 / p99 at expected RPS). Cold-start fixes without baseline are speculative and often regress warm latency or cost.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Lambda performance whitepapers; cold-start postmortems.">Cold-start optimisation has knobs that hurt cost (PC) or warm latency (memory bloat); evidence-based picks avoid regressions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-pick-cheapest-mitigation-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mitigation MUST be tried cheapest first: bundle trim + import lazy-loading → memory bump → runtime swap (Node/Python &gt; Java) → SnapStart → provisioned concurrency → container migration. Skipping cheap options to apply PC by default wastes budget.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS pricing + Lambda perf studies.">Cheaper mitigations frequently close the gap; PC costs $0.0000041/GB-s × seconds; defaulting to PC mints unnecessary cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-runtime-cold-start-ranking" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When runtime is replaceable, prefer runtimes with shorter cold starts: Node.js / Python / Go &lt; Rust &lt; .NET &lt; Java (without SnapStart). Java + SnapStart approaches Node/Python class.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Lambda benchmark studies 2023-2025.">Runtime is the single biggest determinant of cold-start latency; switching can shave seconds.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-provisioned-concurrency-is-a-trade" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provisioned concurrency MUST be sized to expected RPS / concurrency, not as a 'set it and forget it' constant. Auto-scaling on PC MUST be configured to avoid cold spikes during traffic ramps.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Application Auto Scaling for Lambda PC.">Under-provisioned PC still cold-starts during spikes; over-provisioned PC pays for idle capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-measure-after-fix" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post-fix numbers MUST be measured at the same RPS as the baseline; the spec MUST document the % cold-start reduction AND any warm-latency / cost change.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal cold-start fix audits.">Without post-measurement, the mitigation cannot be defended or rolled back; regressions are common (warm latency up after memory bump).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When prerequisites hold (latency budget, baseline, runtime config, bundle data), apply r1 → r5 and emit the spec.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology design — gate rule.">Order encodes risk: measure first, cheap fix second, runtime third, PC sizing fourth, validate last.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do NOT use when (a) async non-user-facing function, (b) steady high-RPS, (c) SLO already met. Exit with note.</statement>
      <rationale source="Preconditions — skip gate.">Cold-start ceremony in these contexts wastes engineering capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
