<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agency-to-Agency Referral Program Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Agency-to-Agency Referral Program application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-give-before-take" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Send ≥3 qualified referrals to a peer BEFORE asking for any. Track in shared sheet so asymmetry is visible.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Cialdini, Influence ch.2 (reciprocity): unilateral giving builds debt; asking before giving signals neediness.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-economics-pick-one" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose ONE economics model per peer: flat 10-20% finder's fee, reciprocity-only, OR co-delivery with shared margin. Mixing models breaks trust.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Mixed models lead to opportunistic re-pricing per deal; explicit policy creates predictability.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-anti-poach-clause" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every referred engagement includes anti-poach: receiving agency will not solicit referrer's clients; referrer will not solicit receiving agency's team; ≥18 months.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Standard agency MSA practice; absence guarantees one bad incident kills the relationship permanently.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-quarterly-outreach-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Touch the roster ≥4×/year: one founder call (15-30 min), one shared-insight email, one shared content cross-post, one in-person event/dinner where feasible.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Referrals decay without contact; quarterly cadence is the floor for top-of-mind without spam.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-roster-pruning" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Once/year, drop peers who sent zero AND received zero (after ≥3 referrals sent). Replace with new candidates.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Time on roster is scarce; dead relationships compound and crowd out warm ones.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>