<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-messaging-and-sequences" title="Retargeting: Messaging by Segment, Sequences, Frequency, Exclusions">
  <summary>Segment-to-message mapping, sequential retargeting timeline, frequency caps by intent level, and exclusion windows to prevent targeting converters.</summary>

  <section title="Segment-to-Message Mapping">
    <rule>
      <statement>Match ad message to the segment's decision stage; do not show the same ad to all retargeting audiences.</statement>
      <rationale>A cart abandoner who is 10 minutes from converting needs urgency and a discount; showing them a brand awareness ad resets the conversation and loses the sale. Message relevance to intent stage is the primary lever that makes retargeting outperform cold traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Message progression from low to high intent — each message addresses the specific friction at that stage.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
All visitors (awareness):
"Still thinking about [solving problem]?
Here's why [Product] might be the answer. → Learn More"

Product viewers (consideration):
"[Product] helps [audience] achieve [outcome].
See how teams like yours use it. → Watch Demo"

Pricing viewers (high intent):
"Ready to get started?
Use code WELCOME for 20% off your first month. → Start Free Trial"

Cart abandoners (urgent):
"You left something behind!
Complete your order and get free shipping today. → Complete Order"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Sequential Retargeting">
    <p>Sequential retargeting shows different ads to the same person over a defined time window, telling a story across multiple touchpoints. This counters the diminishing returns of repeatedly showing the same ad.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Day 1-3: Reminder — what they viewed, product/feature in focus.</item>
      <item>Day 4-7: Benefits — what they are missing, value proposition reinforcement.</item>
      <item>Day 8-14: Social proof — testimonials, case studies, user numbers.</item>
      <item>Day 14+: Urgency — last chance, discount, expiring offer.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Frequency Caps">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set frequency caps: 3 per week for all-visitor segments, 5 per week for high-intent segments, up to 7 per week for cart abandoners in the first week only.</statement>
      <rationale>Frequency above 5 for warm audiences produces negative ad experiences (reported ads, hides, unfollows) and elevates CPM without increasing conversion probability. Cart abandoners tolerate slightly higher frequency in the first week before the intent window closes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Fatigue signals: CTR declining week-over-week, frequency above 5, negative feedback increasing. When fatigue appears: refresh creative (new hook/visual) rather than expanding audience — the issue is creative, not audience fit.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Exclusion Windows">
    <rule>
      <statement>Exclude purchasers for 30-90 days from acquisition campaigns; re-engage them with upsell messaging after the exclusion window.</statement>
      <rationale>Showing acquisition ads to recent purchasers generates negative sentiment (they just bought and are now being sold to again) and inflates conversion metrics with zero net-new customer value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running retargeting for only cart abandoners and ignoring the rest of the funnel.</description>
      <reason>Full-funnel retargeting captures the majority of non-converting visitors at every intent level. Cart abandoners represent less than 5% of traffic; building retargeting only for them ignores 95% of the recoverable opportunity.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-segmentation.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/retargeting-campaign-structure.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
