<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Error Prevention — Nielsen Heuristic #5 Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Error Prevention — Nielsen Heuristic #5 application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-six-strategies-considered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every error class MUST be evaluated against all six prevention strategies. Skipping strategies is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Picking the first strategy that fits produces shallow prevention; evaluating all six surfaces better matches.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-frequency-ranked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Errors MUST be ranked by frequency × cost. Unranked audits are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Without ranking the team fixes the easy errors; the expensive ones rot.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-destructive-confirmation-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Destructive actions MUST always be paired with confirmation OR be undoable. No-confirmation no-undo destructive actions are a hard fail.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Destructive actions without confirmation or undo are the most common trust-killer; this rule is non-negotiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-default-honesty" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Defaults MUST favour the user's most likely intent, not the business's preferred outcome (e.g., do not default-opt-in to marketing email).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Defaults are powerful; dark-pattern defaults erode trust and create regulatory exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-strategy-tested" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each implemented prevention MUST be tested (analytics, usability test, or A/B) to confirm error-rate reduction. Untested preventions are rejected as complete.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Implementation is not validation; the audit closes only when the error rate actually drops.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
