<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Error Prevention — Good and Bad Examples">
  <summary>Real product examples of effective error prevention and concrete anti-patterns to avoid.</summary>

  <section title="Good Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Gmail compose: detects "attached" in message body without an attachment and prompts "Did you mean to attach a file?" — catches the slip before send. Also warns about empty subject line. Offers Undo Send for 30 seconds. Three prevention strategies in one flow.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Google Forms: all required fields marked, field types constrain input (date picker, dropdown), validation runs before submission with inline errors. Users cannot submit invalid data.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Amazon checkout: address validation with suggestions catches typos in real time. Payment validation before order is placed. Shipping timeline shown clearly so users confirm they are ordering the right option.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Validation runs only on form submit, showing all errors at once at the top of the page after the user has completed the entire form.</description>
      <reason>Users must re-find each field and re-enter data, often losing unsaved work in other fields. Inline validation on blur prevents this entirely by catching errors one at a time as they occur.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Accepting an invalid email address at entry and failing later when the email confirmation message cannot be delivered.</description>
      <reason>The error surface is now disconnected from the input — users have no way to diagnose or fix the problem without returning to the form. Inline email validation (format check on blur) catches this at the source.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using placeholder text as the only format hint, which disappears when the user starts typing.</description>
      <reason>Users who type quickly and then look up cannot see the format they were supposed to follow. Format hints must persist below or beside the field, not inside it.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying a confirmation dialog to every navigation-away or form-close action, including cases where no data would be lost.</description>
      <reason>Unnecessary confirmations train users to click through without reading. When a genuinely important confirmation appears, it is dismissed with the same reflex — eliminating its protective value.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Measuring Prevention Effectiveness">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track form abandonment rate, validation error frequency, submission error frequency, and support tickets mentioning specific fields as prevention effectiveness metrics.</statement>
      <rationale>Without measurement, prevention improvements cannot be validated. A drop in validation errors after adding inline feedback is direct evidence of effectiveness.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
