<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Referral Ledger — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `referral-ledger` must enforce. The rules pin the discipline that turns a ledger from folklore into a reviewable, owned, version-controlled operating tool.</summary>

  <section title="Rules">
    <rule id="r1-append-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Entries are append-only. Corrections are added as new entries that reference the prior entry&apos;s id; rows are not edited in place.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-journal practice (Annie Duke); event-sourcing patterns">Editable history loses the decision trail. Append-only preserves what was believed at decision time, which is what audit and retro need.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-fixed-columns" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The ledger has a fixed column schema (id, ts, owner, hypothesis, evidence, outcome, next). Custom per-row columns are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Relational-data principles; observability-as-data practice">Heterogeneous schemas destroy aggregability. A fixed schema makes the ledger queryable across months.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-evidence-link" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every entry includes an evidence link (commit, ticket, dashboard, transcript). Entries without links are flagged at weekly review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Validated-learning practice (Lean Startup); engineering-experiment logging">Without evidence anchors entries become opinion. Evidence anchors are the difference between a learning artefact and a wishlist.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-named-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ledger is reviewed at a fixed cadence (weekly or monthly) by a named owner. The review produces a digest + next-action.</statement>
      <rationale source="OKR review practice; weekly business review (Bezos memo culture)">Ledgers that no one reads decay into write-only logs. The review cadence is what extracts the signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-retention-policy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ledger entries older than the published retention horizon (e.g. 24 months) are archived to cold storage but not deleted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Institutional-memory practice; backup-retention norms">Long-tail learning lives in old entries. Deletion erases institutional memory; archival preserves it cheaply.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
