<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-concepts" title="Use Case Modeling — Core Concepts">
  <summary>Use case components, actor types, relationship types, and quality checklist for enterprise UC modeling.</summary>

  <section title="Use Case Components">
    <rule>
      <statement>A use case must have all four structural elements: actor, use case goal, system boundary, and scenario paths.</statement>
      <rationale>Without all four, the UC is either a feature description (missing actor goal) or an org chart (missing system boundary).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Components by role:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Actor — who or what interacts with the system (human, system, or time trigger).</item>
      <item>Use Case — the specific goal the actor achieves through the system.</item>
      <item>System — the boundary of what is being built or analyzed.</item>
      <item>Scenario — a specific path through the use case (main, alternative, or exception).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Actor Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Actor type must be one of {human, system, time}. Job titles are not valid actor names.</statement>
      <rationale>Job titles collapse to org-chart labels and change; goal-bearing actors (Customer, PaymentGateway, NightlyBatch) survive system redesigns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Primary actors — initiate use cases to achieve their own goals.</item>
      <item>Secondary actors — support the system (databases, external services, schedulers).</item>
      <item>External systems — other systems that the UC interacts with to complete a goal.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Use Case Relationships">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use include for shared behavior that always executes; use extend for optional behavior that adds to a base UC at declared extension points.</statement>
      <rationale>The directionality of extend is consistently inverted — extension points belong to the base UC; the extending UC references them. Inverting this breaks traceability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Include — base UC always calls the included UC (e.g., Place Order includes Process Payment).</item>
      <item>Extend — extending UC optionally adds behavior at a declared extension point (e.g., Apply Coupon extends Place Order).</item>
      <item>Generalization — specialized UC inherits the structure of a parent UC (e.g., Pay with Credit Card generalizes Pay).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="UC Quality Checklist">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every UC must pass all nine quality gates before it is baselined.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing any gate — especially alternative flows and exception flows — produces happy-path-only specs that fail in production.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Use case name is Verb + Noun.</item>
      <item>Clear primary actor identified with type in {human, system, time}.</item>
      <item>Preconditions are verifiable (not aspirational).</item>
      <item>Main flow has 5-9 steps; each step = one actor action + one system response.</item>
      <item>At least one alternative flow documented.</item>
      <item>At least one exception flow documented.</item>
      <item>Postconditions defined for success and failure.</item>
      <item>Business rules cited by ID.</item>
      <item>Reviewed and signed off by stakeholders.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="UC Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Feature as use case — naming a UC "Display Screen" or "Show Report".</description>
      <reason>Features describe system behavior, not actor goals. UCs must be named from the actor's perspective: what does the actor achieve?</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>UI nouns in system response — "displays popup", "shows modal", "highlights button".</description>
      <reason>UI elements change across design iterations; UCs must use system-behavior verbs (validates, persists, emits, notifies) to remain stable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Main flow with more than 9 steps.</description>
      <reason>Oversized main flows bundle multiple actor goals. Split into separate UCs; each UC covers one goal.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Omitting exception flows — only happy path documented.</description>
      <reason>Exceptions are where systems fail and users abandon. A UC without exception flows cannot drive test coverage or error-handling design.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
