<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Use Case Modeling — Five-Step Process">
  <summary>Step-by-step process for producing a UC catalog: identify actors, identify UCs, create UC diagram, write UC specs, validate.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Identify Actors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the system boundary in writing before identifying actors. Every actor identification prompt must include that boundary paragraph verbatim.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a written boundary, actors expand to include every person who touches any related system, producing an unmanageable diagram.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Questions to identify actors:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Who will use this system?</item>
      <item>What external systems connect to this system?</item>
      <item>Who maintains the system or receives its outputs?</item>
      <item>What time-based or event-based triggers initiate system behavior?</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Identify Use Cases">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name every use case as Verb + Noun from the actor's perspective. Reject names that do not pass this test.</statement>
      <rationale>Verb + Noun names (Place Order, Generate Report, Manage User Account) encode the actor's goal; feature names (Order System, Report Module) encode the system's structure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>For each actor, ask:</p>
    <list>
      <item>What tasks does this actor perform with the system?</item>
      <item>What information does the actor need from the system?</item>
      <item>What does the actor create, update, or delete?</item>
      <item>What events trigger the actor's actions?</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap the UC count per release at approximately 30. UC sets larger than 30 collapse into documents nobody re-reads.</statement>
      <rationale>Useful UC count is bounded by stakeholder review capacity; beyond 30 per release, the diagram becomes an archive rather than a working tool.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Create UC Diagram">
    <p>The UC diagram visualizes actors and UCs within the system boundary. Relationships (include/extend/generalization) are added only after all UCs are drafted and reviewed.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the relationship pass (include/extend/generalization) last, using only Opus or equivalent, only after all UCs are drafted, and require a one-line rationale per edge.</statement>
      <rationale>Relationship inference is the highest-error part of UC modeling; drafters and reviewers both default to incorrect extend directionality. The relationship pass requires global view of the full UC set.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/uc-to-plantuml.sh">Script emitting a PlantUML UC diagram from a use-case-index.json</reference>
    <reference path="templates/uc-diagram.md">UC diagram template listing actors, UCs per actor, and relationships</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Write UC Specifications">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each UC spec must have all nine elements: name/ID, description, actors, preconditions, main flow (5-9 steps), alternative flows (at least 1), exception flows (at least 1), postconditions, business rules.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing elements — especially exception flows — produce specs that pass review and fail in production. Postconditions must be observable (DB row, message, file, audit log).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store UCs as markdown with YAML frontmatter containing id, name, primary_actor, status, version, regulation_anchors, and source. Persist under .aidocs/&lt;feature&gt;/use-cases/UC-NNN-&lt;slug&gt;.md.</statement>
      <rationale>Frontmatter feeds ReqIF export, the index script, and CI checks. Source citations prevent hallucinated requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/uc-spec.md">Full use case specification template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Validate Use Cases">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use an adversarially framed reviewer prompt (different model or adversarial system prompt) — not the same model that drafted the UC — to score each UC against the 9-item quality checklist.</statement>
      <rationale>Drafter and reviewer using the same model and prompt yields self-congratulatory reviews; adversarial framing surfaces gaps the drafter skipped.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Validation questions:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Are all actor goals covered by at least one UC?</item>
      <item>Is the main flow correct from the actor's perspective?</item>
      <item>Are alternative flows complete?</item>
      <item>Are exception flows handled with observable postconditions?</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
