<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Use Case Modeling — Examples">
  <summary>Place Order UC example with main/alternative/exception flows; common antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Example: Place Order">
    <example type="good">
      <note>UC-101: Place Order. Primary Actor: Customer (human). System: E-Commerce Platform.</note>
      <note>Preconditions: Customer is logged in; shopping cart has at least one item.</note>
      <note>Main Flow (5 steps): 1. Customer clicks Checkout — system displays order summary. 2. Customer confirms shipping address — system calculates shipping cost. 3. Customer selects payment method — system displays payment form. 4. Customer enters payment details — system validates payment. 5. Customer clicks Place Order — system creates order and sends confirmation email.</note>
      <note>Alternative Flow AF-1 (New Shipping Address): At step 2, customer enters a new address — system validates and saves — returns to step 2.</note>
      <note>Exception Flow EX-1 (Payment Declined): At step 4, payment validation fails — system displays error message — customer can retry or select different payment method.</note>
      <note>Postconditions (success): order created with status Confirmed; inventory reduced; confirmation email sent.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Feature as use case: "Display Product Screen" or "Show Report".</description>
      <reason>These describe system behavior, not actor goals. A use case must capture what the actor achieves, not what the system renders.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Missing secondary actors: e.g., no Payment Gateway actor on a payment UC.</description>
      <reason>External systems that participate in the interaction belong in the diagram; omitting them produces an incomplete system boundary.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No exception flows — only happy path documented.</description>
      <reason>Exceptions are where the system fails and users abandon. A UC without exception flows cannot drive error-handling design or negative test coverage.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>UI details in system response: "system highlights the Submit button" or "system shows a green popup".</description>
      <reason>UI elements change across design iterations; system responses must use behavior verbs (validates, persists, emits, notifies) to remain stable across redesigns.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Too abstract: "Use System" as a use case name.</description>
      <reason>UC names must encode a specific actor goal. Abstract names cannot drive test scaffolding or traceability.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>More than 9 steps in main flow without splitting.</description>
      <reason>Oversized main flows bundle multiple actor goals; they mislead estimation and test scaffolding. Trigger a split when step count exceeds 9.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
