<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Supabase RLS Audit Checklist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Supabase RLS Audit Checklist methodology. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-rls-enabled-every-public-table" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every table in the `public` schema MUST have RLS enabled (rls_enabled=true). Tables exempt MUST be explicitly listed in the audit with a documented reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="Supabase RLS docs + community incident reports">Default-off RLS is the leading cause of Supabase data leaks; default-on is the safe posture.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-policy-per-verb" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each table MUST declare policies for every USED verb (SELECT/INSERT/UPDATE/DELETE). Missing verb = no access; UNUSED verbs should be denied explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Postgres RLS docs">Permissive defaults bite during refactors; explicit policy-per-verb makes the access matrix auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-anon-cannot-read-other-tenant" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test fixture with ≥2 tenants MUST prove the `anon` role canNOT SELECT rows belonging to tenant_b when authenticated as tenant_a. Fixture-driven test is the binary check.</statement>
      <rationale source="Supabase community incident postmortems">Policies that look right but leak under join/subquery edge cases get caught only by fixtures.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>RlsAuditReport names a single owner. &apos;team&apos; / &apos;we&apos; / &apos;&apos; are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI">Plural ownership = no ownership.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-fixture-driven-tests" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit MUST execute the fixture-driven test in a real Postgres (CI or clone), capture pass/fail, and record the row counts. Untested policies are not audited.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal practice">Visual review of policies misses subtle bugs; running fixtures is proof.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md &quot;Applies If&quot; do not all hold, OR any &quot;Skip If&quot; disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent&apos;s context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-supabase-rls-audit-checklist.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
