<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Experiment Verdict Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that kill zombie experiments and convert every test into a routed decision + captured learning.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="five-verdict-vocabulary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every experiment ends with a verdict from exactly five values: ship-treatment, ship-control, inconclusive-iterate, inconclusive-stop, harmful-rollback. "We'll think about it" or any sixth state is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion experiment-ops audit; cf. Statsig + GrowthBook verdict taxonomies">Five verdicts cover every honest outcome; an open-ended sixth state accumulates zombie experiments.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="close-within-5-days" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Verdicts MUST be written within 5 business days of the experiment's pre-registered close date. Experiments missing the date are auto-stopped at the platform (variant assignment paused) until a verdict is written. "Running longer for more data" requires a NEW pre-registration with explicit power re-justification.</statement>
      <rationale source="Peeking-fallacy literature (Optimizely, 2014; Lai, 2019)">Running until accidentally significant ships false positives. Forced close + explicit re-justification is the only known cure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="secondary-metric-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Verdicts MUST explicitly address pre-registered secondary metrics. Treatment wins on primary but loses on ≥1 secondary becomes "inconclusive-iterate" or "harmful-rollback" by default; overriding to "ship-treatment" requires a named exec sign-off captured in the card.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-metric optimization disaster archive (cf. Microsoft Bing experiments)">Primary-only verdicts ship treatments that win on conversion but tank retention / refunds / NPS.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="captured-learning" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each verdict MUST record one `learning` line: a generalizable claim with `confidence` tag from {weak, moderate, strong}. The learning is added to the learnings database. Verdicts without a learning are bounced back to the owner.</statement>
      <rationale source="Learnings-database discipline; faion learnings-database-schema">Without captured learnings, experiments are a Brownian process — same hypotheses re-tested every 2 quarters.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="routed-action" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each verdict MUST route the next action to a named owner with a target date: ship-treatment → release owner; harmful-rollback → on-call; inconclusive-iterate → experiment owner with next pre-registration; inconclusive-stop → backlog owner who removes related items; ship-control → backlog owner. Cards without a routed action are not closed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion experiment-ops audit">"Verdict written" without a routed action is the politest form of zombie: closed but nothing happens.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## EXP-2026-Q2-031 — Pricing-page hero variant B

- hypothesis: shortening the hero copy increases primary CTA clicks for cold traffic
- arms: control (long copy) / B (short copy)
- primary: CTA CTR — B +6.2% (95% CI [+2.1%, +10.3%], p=0.004)
- secondary: signup conversion — B −1.8% (CI [−4.0%, +0.4%], NS); 7-day retention — flat
- verdict: ship-treatment with monitoring (CTA win clean, signup non-significant)
- learning: shorter hero copy on cold pricing traffic — moderate confidence; revisit when bottom-of-funnel data accrues.
- routed: release owner @marina; release ticket REL-1402, target 2026-05-23. Monitoring alert on signup CR.
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
EXP-2026-Q2-031: B looks better, let's keep it running another week to confirm.
]]></code>
      <note>No close, no verdict vocabulary, no secondary check, no learning, no routed action — classic zombie; the team will rediscover the hypothesis next quarter.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
