<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agency Case Study Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every freelancer/micro-agency case study must satisfy. These are hard rules — operator input and client requests do not override them.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-cpaol-structure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every case study has exactly five named sections in this order: Context, Problem, Approach, Outcome, Lessons. No section is omitted, none is merged. Total length 600-1200 words.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bencivenga / Schwartz long-copy case structure; Basecamp customer-story template">Long-form social proof needs predictable shape so a skim-reader (most portfolio visitors) can land on Outcome in under 10 seconds. The five-section frame matches how prospects mentally evaluate a vendor: "Is this me?" (Context), "What was hurting?" (Problem), "What did you actually do?" (Approach), "Did it work?" (Outcome), "Would you do it again?" (Lessons).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-quantified-outcome" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Outcome section must lead with at least one quantified metric paired with its baseline. Allowed formats: absolute delta ("conversion 1.2% → 3.4%"), percentage delta ("+183% MQLs in 12 weeks"), or time saved ("4 hours/week → 0, recovered $620/mo at agency rate"). Never publish "significant improvement" without numbers.</statement>
      <rationale source="HubSpot 2024 buyer-content study; agency proof conversion benchmarks">Unquantified outcomes read as marketing copy and fail to anchor pricing conversations. Pairing the metric with its baseline blocks the "from zero to 100%" framing that prospects discount as cherry-picked.</rationale>
      <example type="good" title="Quantified outcome with baseline">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Outcome: cart abandonment dropped from 71% (baseline, Q1 2025) to 48%
over 8 weeks, recovering ~$14,200/month in net revenue at the client's
current AOV of $87. Source: Shopify checkout analytics, week 9 export.
        ]]></code>
        <note>Both delta and baseline are present; data source is named. The prospect can replicate the framing for their own funnel.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Vague outcome">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Outcome: significantly improved conversion and recovered substantial
revenue. Client was thrilled with the results.
        ]]></code>
        <note>No numbers, no baseline, no source. Reads as testimonial filler. Prospects discount this entirely.</note>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-verbatim-quote" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include exactly one verbatim client quote in the Outcome section, attributed to a named person (first name + role minimum) with date or engagement-end month. Quote must be verbatim from a written or recorded source — never paraphrased or LLM-tightened. Length 1-3 sentences.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen Norman Group testimonial trust study (2023); FTC endorsement guides">Verbatim quotes with named attribution are the cheapest trust signal a freelancer has. Paraphrased quotes ("the client said it was great") are legally risky under FTC §255 endorsement rules and read as fabricated to experienced buyers.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-scope-honesty" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Explicitly state your scope of engagement vs the client's broader team contribution. Use the Approach section header "What I/we did" and call out at least one thing the client team did that you did not, if applicable. Never imply solo authorship of a multi-vendor outcome.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brennan Dunn proposal-honesty practice; common cause of agency-prospect mistrust">Prospects vet case studies by comparing them to what their team would need to do. Overclaiming sole credit is the single most common reason a prospect quietly disqualifies a freelancer on the way to the sales call. Honest scoping converts higher because it lets prospects map the case study onto their own constraints.</rationale>
      <example type="good" title="Honest scope">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
What I did: rebuilt the Shopify checkout funnel (5 screens), wired
post-purchase upsell via Bold, set up Klaviyo abandoned-cart flows.
What the client team did: copywriting, photography, customer support
for the launch week.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-single-engagement-focus" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One case study covers exactly one engagement with one client. Multi-client roll-ups, retainer-spanning "things I did over a year" lists, and aggregated "across 15 projects we delivered X" are NOT case studies and must be written as separate methodology outputs (portfolio overview, retainer narrative, capabilities sheet).</statement>
      <rationale source="case-study craft tradition; SEO entity-anchoring requirement">A single-engagement case is the only artifact that survives skeptical scrutiny: dates, names, numbers all anchor to one verifiable engagement. Multi-engagement summaries cannot be fact-checked by prospects and read as marketing-speak. They also fail to attract long-tail search ("Shopify checkout rebuild Klaviyo case study") that pulls real qualified buyers.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
