<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agency Case Study Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `Agency Case Study Template` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="five-part-structure-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The case study MUST follow the five-part structure: Context (industry, size, role), Problem (pain + cost), Approach (what the agency did, in 3-5 bullets), Outcome (≥ 1 quantified metric), Lessons (what would change next time). Sections cannot be merged or dropped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Portfolio conversion audit 2024-2026">Free-form case studies bury the outcome; the five-part structure forces the metric and lesson into reader&apos;s view within 60 seconds.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="outcome-quantified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Outcome section MUST contain ≥ 1 quantified metric (% lift, $ saved, hours saved, NPS shift) with baseline + post + source link. Hand-wave outcomes are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Inbound conversion audit">Un-quantified case studies convert at 5-10% vs quantified at 25-40%; the metric is the proof asset.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="verbatim-client-quote" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The case study MUST contain ≥ 1 verbatim client quote (with named role or anonymised role) signed off by the client. Paraphrased quotes are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Trust-asset audit">Paraphrased quotes read as ghostwritten; verbatim quotes (even short) carry the trust signal that converts skeptical inbound.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="named-approver-per-study" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each study MUST name an internal approver (founder or senior contributor) and an external approver (client). Both must sign off before publish.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal RACI for portfolio">Un-approved studies often misrepresent client work, leading to legal letters; dual sign-off is the safety mechanism.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="evidence-anchor-per-claim" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each quantitative claim MUST link to a source (analytics dashboard screenshot, contract metric, client email, public stat). Un-anchored claims are demoted to qualitative language.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice">Un-anchored claims invite challenge from prospects; the evidence link forces honesty + builds credibility.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>