<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-domains" title="PMBOK 8 Seven Performance Domains">
  <summary>The seven PMBOK 8 performance domains with definitions, key activities, and notable changes from PMBOK 6.</summary>

  <section title="Domain Map">
    <p>Seven domains replace the ten Knowledge Areas. Quality, Communications, and Procurement are absorbed — not removed — into the remaining domains. All domains operate concurrently; none is sequential to another.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Assign one accountable domain owner per domain on every project, even when one person holds multiple domains.</statement>
      <rationale>Domains with no named owner drift to green in status reports regardless of actual health; accountability produces honest reporting.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Governance">
    <p>Replaces Integration Management. Covers oversight, decision frameworks, and value realization tracking.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Establish project authority and decision rights</item>
      <item>Link project outcomes to portfolio value</item>
      <item>Manage change control and escalation paths</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Scope">
    <p>Enhanced definition over PMBOK 6 Scope Management. Requires explicit documented scope boundaries, not just a scope statement.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Define and baseline what is in scope and out of scope</item>
      <item>Control scope changes through the governance domain</item>
      <item>Validate deliverables against acceptance criteria</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Schedule">
    <p>Same focus as PMBOK 6 Time Management. Covers plan, sequence, estimate, and control timelines and dependencies.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Identify all activities and dependencies</item>
      <item>Develop schedule with critical path and resource constraints</item>
      <item>Monitor schedule performance and forecast completion</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Finance">
    <p>Replaces Cost Management. Broader financial lens including ROI, benefits realization, and financial risk.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Develop and baseline budget</item>
      <item>Track actual vs. planned expenditure (EVM optional)</item>
      <item>Forecast financial performance and report to sponsors</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Stakeholders">
    <p>Now absorbs Communications. Single domain for identifying, analyzing, engaging, and communicating with all stakeholders.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Build and maintain stakeholder register</item>
      <item>Develop engagement strategies per stakeholder segment</item>
      <item>Plan and execute communications — frequency, channel, tone</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating Communications as automatic once it is absorbed into Stakeholders.</description>
      <reason>Without an explicit comms plan, communications gets under-invested and stakeholder satisfaction drops regardless of delivery quality.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Resources">
    <p>Enhanced focus on both human and physical resources. Covers acquisition, development, and management.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Acquire team members and physical resources</item>
      <item>Develop team capability (see team-development methodology)</item>
      <item>Manage resource conflicts and availability</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Risk">
    <p>Same focus as PMBOK 6 Risk Management. Covers identify, analyze, respond to, and monitor uncertainties.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Identify risks and opportunities systematically</item>
      <item>Analyze probability and impact</item>
      <item>Implement responses and monitor risk register</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="New Emphases in PMBOK 8">
    <list>
      <item>Value Delivery over output delivery — outputs shipped vs. outcomes realized tracked separately</item>
      <item>Systems Thinking — understand project in broader organizational context</item>
      <item>Sustainability — environmental, social, and economic impact; requires measurable metrics</item>
      <item>Governance Integration — stronger portfolio/program/project linkage</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track value realization rate (outcomes realized / outputs shipped) alongside delivery metrics.</statement>
      <rationale>A 100% delivery rate with 30% value realization rate is the most common trap; domains must surface it explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
