<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-health-check" title="Domain Health Check and RAG Assessment">
  <summary>RAG status assessment procedure, domain-owner RACI pattern, cross-domain interaction chains, and agent gotchas for PMBOK 8 domain health checks.</summary>

  <section title="RAG Assessment Procedure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor every domain color rating with a quoted artifact (retro line, incident, missed milestone); ratings without evidence are not valid inputs.</statement>
      <rationale>Unanchored RAG ratings default to Green due to politeness bias; evidence quotes force the assessor to confront actual data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-score domain RAG monthly minimum AND on triggers: incident, scope change, leadership change.</statement>
      <rationale>The value of the framework is the trend line, not the snapshot; trigger-based re-scoring catches mid-cycle regressions that monthly cadence misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Green: domain performing as expected, no gaps requiring action</item>
      <item>Amber: domain has a documented gap with an active remediation plan</item>
      <item>Red: domain has a critical gap with no remediation plan, or remediation failing</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Domain-Owner RACI">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign one Accountable owner per domain; one person can hold multiple domains, but no domain can be unowned.</statement>
      <rationale>Domains with no named owner drift to Green in status reports regardless of actual health; accountability produces honest reporting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Governance → PM or PMO lead</item>
      <item>Scope → PM or Product Owner</item>
      <item>Schedule → PM</item>
      <item>Finance → Sponsor or Finance lead</item>
      <item>Stakeholders → PM (communications included)</item>
      <item>Resources → Line Manager or PM</item>
      <item>Risk → PM with risk register owner</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Cross-Domain Interaction Chains">
    <p>Domains are interdependent; a Red in one domain typically cascades to Amber or Red in others. Common chains:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Resources Red → Schedule Amber (capacity gap delays delivery)</item>
      <item>Stakeholders Red → Finance Amber (sponsor disengagement delays approvals)</item>
      <item>Governance Red → Scope Amber (unclear decision rights cause scope creep)</item>
      <item>Risk Red → all domains (unmitigated risk materializes everywhere simultaneously)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>When multiple domains are Red, identify which single domain improvement unblocks the most others; fix that first.</statement>
      <rationale>Parallel remediation across all Red domains spreads PM attention too thin and produces no completed fixes; sequenced priority maximizes recovery velocity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent rates every domain Green when not given calibration examples.</description>
      <reason>Politeness bias in LLM outputs; provide one explicit Red exemplar in the prompt to force calibration.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent conflates PMBOK 7 vocabulary (Performance Domains) with PMBOK 8 vocabulary (seven domains) in the same output.</description>
      <reason>PMBOK 7 has eight domains; PMBOK 8 has seven with different names. Pin the version in the system prompt to prevent cross-contamination.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Long corpora cause domain conflation — one agent inference for all domains simultaneously.</description>
      <reason>Chunk by domain (one inference per domain) for higher signal; combined inference loses domain-specific evidence in the noise.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/domains.yaml">Per-project domain status manifest with owner, evidence, and gap fields</reference>
</text>
