<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-concepts" title="Terraform Core Concepts">
  <summary>HCL building blocks, workflow, meta-arguments, lifecycle rules, and state management fundamentals.</summary>

  <section title="HCL Building Blocks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the standard 8-block structure: terraform, provider, resource, data, variable, output, locals, module — each with a distinct responsibility.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing responsibilities (e.g., embedding logic in resource blocks that belongs in locals) makes configurations hard to refactor and test.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always use pessimistic version constraints (~> major.minor) for providers; pin Terraform itself to >= 1.5.0 minimum.</statement>
      <rationale>Pessimistic constraints allow patch updates automatically while blocking breaking major changes. TF 1.5+ is required for import blocks.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Terraform Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow the four-step workflow in order: init → plan → apply → destroy (never skip plan before apply in automation).</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping plan in CI allows unexpected destroys or replacements to reach production without review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <note>Commands: terraform init (initialize + download providers), terraform plan (dry run), terraform apply (execute), terraform destroy (teardown).</note>
  </section>

  <section title="Meta-Arguments">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use for_each over count when resources need unique identifiers or will be addressed individually; use count only for identical, index-based resources.</statement>
      <rationale>count creates resources addressed by index; removing an item from the middle shifts indexes and causes unexpected replacements. for_each uses stable keys.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add explicit depends_on only when implicit dependency graphs are insufficient; avoid overuse as it disables parallel operations.</statement>
      <rationale>Terraform builds dependency graphs from references automatically. Explicit depends_on is a last resort that serializes operations unnecessarily.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Lifecycle Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set create_before_destroy on resources where downtime is unacceptable; set prevent_destroy on production databases and state backends.</statement>
      <rationale>Default destroy-then-create causes downtime. prevent_destroy adds a guardrail against accidental terraform destroy on critical data stores.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use precondition and postcondition blocks to validate assumptions before and after resource creation rather than relying on cloud API errors.</statement>
      <rationale>Conditions surface misconfigurations at plan time with clear error messages, before any resources are created or modified.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="State Management">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always configure a remote backend with locking; add *.tfstate* to .gitignore; commit .terraform.lock.hcl for provider version consistency.</statement>
      <rationale>Local state blocks team collaboration and has no locking. State files contain sensitive data and must never be committed to git.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
